<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:46:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>(œ) V1. B. hears it in Scotch Gaelic l<hi rend="italic">ao</hi>gh ; it may be produced by saying (uu) and suddenly opening the mouth, see (<hi rend="italic">œ</hi>'u).</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">œ</hi>'u) acute inchoant diphthong, art. 7 ix, or (uu), begun with the mouth open and without internal rounding, very common in south Lancashire and Cheshire.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(œ)</hi> V 9. B. makes it the “narrow ” form of (<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), and the regular form of <hi rend="smallcaps">ls </hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi>p<hi rend="italic">, </hi>c<hi rend="italic">o</hi>me ; Sw. occ. <hi rend="smallcaps">ls</hi> form.</p><p>(œ) V 22. B. hears it as the regular <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> sound of <hi rend="italic">er, ir, yr.</hi> Sw.</p><p>hears it in the first element of h<hi rend="italic">ow</hi> (hœ'<hi rend="italic">u</hi>), which E. finds dialectal.</p><p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">œ</hi>) a dialectal south-west English sound of (Ǝ) through which a sound of <hi rend="smallcaps">(a, ɔ)</hi> seems to run, and usually appreciated as the latter.</p><p>P.	(p ph prh, p<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>, ph<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">p</hi>).</p><p>(p)	S 3 <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, Cil3, E <hi rend="italic">p</hi>ee<hi rend="italic">p</hi>ing, perfectly mute, art. 8.</p><p>(ph) S 1 <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> C iii 12, Hungarian <hi rend="italic">f</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">mg </hi><hi rend="italic">φ,</hi> an (f) spoken by the lips only without the teeth, mouth in position for blowing to cool, flated form of (bh), which see.</p><p>(prh) Cv13, flated form of (brh), common with babies before they can speak.</p><p>(p<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>) Ci12, mute of (ph), the lips closed flat to form a complete stop, theoretical.</p><p>(ph<hi rend="subscript">1</hi>) S 2 <hi rend="italic">g</hi>, middle of lips in contact, flatus expelled from each corner of the mouth, theoretical.</p><p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">p</hi>)	Ci11, mute of (f), lower lip forming a complete stop with</p><p>upper teeth, theoretical.</p><p>Q.	(q qɟ qɟh qh qj).</p><p>(q)	S 8 <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> C x 3, <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> si<hi rend="italic">ng</hi>er, fi<hi rend="italic">n</hi>ger, (g) with nasal passages open, (qɟ) S 8 <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, C x 5, <hi rend="smallcaps">sn</hi> nasal of the palatal series, see (kɟ gɟ).</p><p>Bopp considers it to be <hi rend="smallcaps">f</hi> <hi rend="italic">gn,</hi> and Sw. hears it in <hi rend="smallcaps">f</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">it </hi><hi rend="italic">gn,</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">sp</hi> <hi rend="italic">ñ, </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">pr </hi><hi rend="italic">nh,</hi> in all of which LLB. and E. hear (nj)only.</p><p>(qɟh) S 4 <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> flated (qɟ), theoretical.</p><p>(qh) S 4 <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> C ix 3, flated (q). B. hears it before mutes, as sink (s<hi rend="italic">i</hi>qhk) ; E. does not, art. ll.</p><p>(qj) C x 4, palatalized (q), different from (qɟ).</p><p>R.	(r rh rsh, r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi> r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>h, ,r ,rh ,r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>, <hi rend="italic">r r</hi>h <hi rend="italic">rw, r</hi><hi rend="subscript">o</hi><hi rend="italic">,</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">r r</hi><hi rend="subscript">o</hi>, ɹ<hi rend="smallcaps">).</hi></p><p>(r)	C vi 8, <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> <hi rend="italic">r</hi>ing, tip of tongue far behind gums, flap weak in</p><p>England, strong in Scotland and Italy.</p><p>(rh) C v 8, flated form of (r).</p><p>(rsh) <hi rend="smallcaps">pl</hi> p<hi rend="italic">rz</hi>ez, tongue in position for (sh) with point flapped.</p><p>(r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>) S 5 c, C ii 8, imperfect (d), the tongue not quite in contact,</p><p>almost (zhj) ; imperfect (r), the flap being omitted, considered by B. aud Sw. as normal (r), a sign for flapping being added where a trill is used. Sv. makes <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> <hi rend="italic">r</hi> before a vowel regularly (,r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>). To E., a bom Londoner, (r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>) before a vowel is very difficult to utter.</p><p>(r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>h) S 1 <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, flated (r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>), theoretical.</p><p>(,r) C vi 9, <hi rend="smallcaps">sp</hi> <hi rend="italic">r</hi>ey, <hi rend="smallcaps">it</hi> <hi rend="italic">r</hi>è, fully trilled <hi rend="italic">r</hi> with the point of the tongue advanced to the gums.</p><p>(,rh) C v 9, flated (,r), occ. <hi rend="smallcaps">f</hi> nôt<hi rend="italic">re</hi>.</p><p>(,r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>) alveolar unflapped (,r), see (r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>), possibly the “soft” <hi rend="smallcaps">sp</hi> <hi rend="italic">r</hi> in ama<hi rend="italic">r</hi>, a<hi rend="italic">r</hi>ado, b<hi rend="italic">r</hi>eve.</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">r</hi>)	C vi 3, Parisian Pa<hi rend="italic">r</hi>is, uvular <hi rend="italic">r</hi>, art. 10 (3), resembling (grh). (<hi rend="italic">r</hi>h) C v 3, flated (<hi rend="italic">r</hi>), common as a <hi rend="smallcaps">g</hi> final <hi rend="italic">r</hi> in the pause, and then</p><p>greatly resembling a faint (krh).</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">rw</hi>) C vi 2, labialized uvular (<hi rend="italic">r</hi>), regular in Northumberland.</p><p>(r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi>) untrilled uvular (<hi rend="italic">r</hi>), heard faintly between vowels in North</p><p>umberland, in ve<hi rend="italic">r</hi>y, me<hi rend="italic">rr</hi>y (va<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi>, ma<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>r<hi rend="subscript">o</hi><hi rend="italic">i</hi>), almost (v’a<hi rend="italic">i</hi>, m’a<hi rend="italic">i</hi>), like <hi rend="smallcaps">it </hi>v<hi rend="italic">ai, </hi>m<hi rend="italic">ai</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(r)</hi>	C vi 7, reverted or cerebral <hi rend="italic">r</hi>, the underpart of the point of</p><p>the tongue brought near the palate, and, according to E.’s observations, allowed to flap, but constantly asserted to be unflapped, see <hi rend="smallcaps">(r</hi><hi rend="subscript">o</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">).</hi> Common in modern Indian, not in <hi rend="smallcaps">sn</hi>, and found in Norway and Sweden.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The characteristic of south of England dialectal speech, and parent of received E r and the vocal degeneration of r, art. 7 vii. By some considered as greatly retracted (r,).</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(r</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">o</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">)</hi>	C iv 7, unflapped variety of <hi rend="smallcaps">(r),</hi> supposed to prevail for <hi rend="smallcaps">(r),</hi></p><p>which see.</p><p>(ɹ) art. 7 vii, fully degenerated vocal <hi rend="smallcaps">(r),</hi> which may be followed permissively by a trilled or flapped (r), forming the murmur diphthongs.</p><p>S.	(s sh shj sj, ,s ,sh, <hi rend="italic">s</hi>, <hi rend="italic">s</hi>j).</p><p>(s)	S 1 <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> C iii 9, <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> seal, hissing, with a convex tongue forming</p><p>a central strait, the sides being held firmly by the palate and teeth, point tense and unruffled, with many unconscious varieties.</p><p>(sh)	S 1 <hi rend="italic">f, C</hi> iii 7, <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> ru<hi rend="italic">sh</hi>, tongue retracted in respect to (s), upper</p><p>surface rather hollowed than convex, see (çh, shj) and occ. lips projected, as <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> hu<hi rend="italic">sh</hi> (hǝsh<hi rend="superscript">5</hi>).</p><p>(shj) C iii 8, (sh) with convex tongue, tip somewhat depressed,</p><p>second element in (tɟ = tjshj), High <hi rend="smallcaps">g s</hi> initial before <hi rend="italic">p, t, </hi>as <hi rend="italic">s</hi>pielen, <hi rend="italic">s</hi>tehen, where (sh) is not admissible.</p><p>(sj) C iii 6, <hi rend="smallcaps">pl</hi> ko<hi rend="italic">s</hi>', palatalized (s), art. 12.</p><p>(,s) C iii 9, point of tongue advanced nearly to teeth. LLB. hears it in Tuscan sharp <hi rend="smallcaps">it </hi>lo zio, usually taken as (,t,sìo).</p><p>(,sh) advanced (shj), tongue convex and nearer the palate. LLB.</p><p>hears it in Tuscan pece (pè·sh<hi rend="italic">e</hi>), and considers it the only proper sound of <hi rend="smallcaps">it </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">c</hi> before <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> which is usually assumed to be (,t,sh) or (,tɟ) ; but an Englishman’s (tɟ) is quite intelligible.</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">s</hi>)	<hi rend="smallcaps">ar</hi>. (s<hi rend="italic">aa</hi>d), according to Lepsius a close emphatic <hi rend="italic">s</hi> or (.s<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>),</p><p>see (<hi rend="smallcaps">k</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">(d, t, z</hi>).</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">s</hi>j) Irish Gaelic ciste (,kj<hi rend="italic">is</hi>jte,) treasure, <hi rend="italic">s</hi> of the same series as (tj), which see. [Lecky, MS. communication.]</p><p>T.	(t tɟ th tj, ,t, th,, <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">t t</hi>ɟ, <hi rend="italic">t t</hi>j).</p><p>(t)	S 3 c, C i 8, <hi rend="smallcaps">e </hi><hi rend="italic">t</hi>oo<hi rend="italic">,</hi> tip of the tongue far behind the gums,</p><p>generated by reverted (τ), with which it is confused by Indians, who use their cerebral 3 5 for E (t, d).</p><p>(tɟ) <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> <hi rend="italic">ch</hi>est=(tjshj), art. 12, not to be confounded with (kɟ), which see.</p><p>(th) S 1 <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> C iii 10, <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> <hi rend="italic">th</hi>in, Icelandic p, <hi rend="smallcaps">mg </hi><hi rend="italic">θ, </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">ar</hi> ό, point of tongue against back of front teeth, hiss produced by flatus escaping between tongue and teeth, not necessarily between the interstices of the teeth, as Sw. says.</p><p>(tj) Ci6, Hungarian t<hi rend="italic">y,</hi> palatalized (t), art. 12, see (dj).</p><p>(,t) S 3 <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> C i 9, F <hi rend="italic">t</hi>as, usual Continental alveolar <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> with the</p><p>tongue against gums, <hi rend="smallcaps">sn</hi> 7τ, found in some midland and northern <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> dialects before <hi rend="italic">r</hi> or <hi rend="italic">--er,</hi> see (,d).</p><p>(th,) C iii 10, <hi rend="smallcaps">sp</hi> <hi rend="italic">z</hi> everywhere, and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> before <hi rend="italic">e, i, </hi>vo<hi rend="italic">z z</hi>opo, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>e<hi rend="italic">c</hi>éo <hi rend="italic">c</hi>into, lisped (s), tongue against gums, and hence a retracted (th), see (dh,). LLB. hears it in <hi rend="smallcaps">it</hi> vi<hi rend="italic">z</hi>io, where it is generally assumed to be (,t,s).</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">t</hi>) <hi rend="smallcaps">ar</hi> b (<hi rend="italic">t</hi>aad), which Lepsius describes as a close emphatic (.d<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>), see (<hi rend="smallcaps">k</hi>).</p><p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">t</hi>) C i 7, reverted or cerebral <hi rend="smallcaps">sn </hi><hi rend="italic">~ζ,</hi> with underpart of the point of the tongue against the palate, common in south-west <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> in connexion with <hi rend="smallcaps">(r),</hi> parent of received <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> (t).</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(t</hi>ɟ<hi rend="smallcaps">)</hi> consonantal diphthong=(<hi rend="smallcaps">t</hi>çh), heard in Wiltshire in connexion with <hi rend="smallcaps">(r),</hi> as (Ǝ<hi rend="smallcaps">rt</hi>ɟ) rich.</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">t</hi>)	Irish Gaelic “ broad ” post-aspirated mute, as in Irish Gaelic</p><p>al<hi rend="italic">t</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tá, tú.</hi> The place of the tip of the tongue is apparently unimportant, but it is generally assumed to be dental or interdental. The essential points are that the tongue is laterally expanded and slack, while the back is raised, leaving a hollow in the “ front. ” It is followed by a slow flated glide, while the position changes to that of the vowel, resembling a greatly predominating (th) mixed with (kh). The voice is not put on till the vowel position is reached. This is constantly used for (th) by Irish speakers of English. [Lecky, MS. communication.]</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">t</hi>j) Irish Gaelic “slender” form of post-aspirated mute, as in ail<hi rend="italic">t</hi>, of a knuckle ; the tongue is spreading and slack ; the part nearest to the palate is about an inch on the inner side of the tip, being more towards the back than in the position for (s), the “front” being also raised ; the tip is not turned up and its position is unimportant. The glide of the post-aspiration sounds like a predominating (jh) mixed with (s), being tighter at first and looser afterwards than the <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> (jh). [Lecky, MS. communication.]</p><p>U.	(u ŭa, <hi rend="italic">u u</hi>h <hi rend="italic">ú</hi>u<hi rend="smallcaps">, </hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">1</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">, u).</hi></p><p>(u)	V 3, T15, short <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> to unemphatic, <hi rend="smallcaps">f</hi> poule, replaced by (<hi rend="italic">u</hi>)</p><p>in <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> ; long <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> too. Some phonetists make the <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> long (uu) to be always (<hi rend="italic">ú</hi>u) or (<hi rend="italic">u</hi>w).</p><p>(ŭa)	art. 7 vi, where (ŭ) replaces (w), <hi rend="smallcaps">f</hi> <hi rend="italic">oi</hi>e (ŭa), <hi rend="italic">ou</hi>i (ŭi), in s<hi rend="italic">oi</hi>, d<hi rend="italic">oi</hi>gt,</p><p>&amp;c. LLB. considers that (s, ,d), &amp;c., are labialized, art. 12.</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">u</hi>)	V 4, T 14, <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> f<hi rend="italic">u</hi>ll, w<hi rend="italic">oo</hi>d, w<hi rend="italic">o</hi>man, c<hi rend="italic">ou</hi>ld, “wide ” form of (u). (uh) V 16. B. hears it in the “colloquial” use of <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> awf<hi rend="italic">u</hi>l, fiss<hi rend="italic">u</hi>re,</p><p>nat<hi rend="italic">u</hi>re, fort<hi rend="italic">u</hi>ne (which E. does not understand), but says also that it is (<hi rend="italic">u</hi>) with a raised tongue, and hence—(<hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="superscript">1</hi>). Sw. hears it in <hi rend="smallcaps">swd</hi> <hi rend="italic">u</hi>pp, Sv. and St. in Norwegian h<hi rend="italic">u</hi>ska.</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">ú</hi>u) art. 7 ix, grave inchoant diphthong, possibly Sw.’s (uw), common dialectally in Cumberland and Westmorland.</p><p>(<hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">1</hi>) midland <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> vowel replacing (ǝ, Ǝ). E. feels it to be near (<hi rend="italic">o</hi><hi rend="superscript">1</hi>), or to be a “thickened” (<hi rend="italic">u</hi>) ; Mr Hallam, to whom it is native, considers it to have the tongue intermediate to its position for (<hi rend="italic">o</hi>, u), and the closure of the lips equal to that for (<hi rend="italic">o</hi>), but made with flattened lips. In Yorkshire, Cumberland, and Westmorland it is replaced by (<hi rend="italic">u</hi>), with which most received speakers confound it.</p><p>(<hi rend="smallcaps">u</hi>) V 15. Sw. hears it long in Norwegian and <hi rend="smallcaps">swd</hi> bus, ut, and says it is not far from <hi rend="smallcaps">f</hi> l<hi rend="italic">u</hi>ne, but see (y). St.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> considers it intermediate between (u, y).</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@1</hi> Englische Philologie: <hi rend="italic">I. </hi>Die lebende Sprache, <hi rend="italic">p. 4.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@2</hi> Ibid.,<hi rend="italic"> p. 328.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>