<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:42:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Stuttgart, <hi rend="italic">Lit. Ver.</hi> (1839), <hi rend="italic">Bibliothek</hi> (1843, &amp;c.) ; <hi rend="italic">Württemb. Alterth. Ver.</hi> (1843). Vienna, <hi rend="italic">K. k. Orient. Akad.</hi> Weimar, <hi rend="italic">D. Shakespeare Ges.</hi> (1864), <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch</hi> (1865, &amp;c.). Wiesbaden, <hi rend="italic">Ver. f. Nass. Alterth.</hi> (1821), <hi rend="italic">Annalen</hi> (1830, &amp;c.). Würzburg, <hi rend="italic">Uist. Ver.</hi> (1830), <hi rend="italic">Archiv</hi> (1833). <hi rend="smallcaps">Switzerland:</hi> Basel, <hi rend="italic">Hist., u. Antiq. Ges. </hi>Bern <hi rend="italic">Schweiz. Hist. Ges.</hi> Freiburg, <hi rend="italic">Soc. d’Hist.</hi> Geneva, <hi rend="italic">Soc. d’Hist. et d'Arch. </hi>Lausanne, <hi rend="italic">Soc. d’Hist.</hi> Zurich, <hi rend="italic">Soc. d’Hist. ; Antiq. Ges. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Italy:</hi> Genoa, <hi rend="italic">Soc. di Storia Patria.</hi> Naples, <hi rend="italic">R. Accad. ; R. Accad. Ercolanese.</hi> Rome, <hi rend="italic">Accad. Rom. di Arch.</hi>;<hi rend="italic"> Soc. Rom. di Storia Patria</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Inst. di Corr. Arch. ; Brit. and Amer. Arch. Soc.’; K. Deutsch. Archäolog. Inst., Arch. Ztng.</hi> (1843-85) and <hi rend="italic">Jahrb.</hi> Turin, <hi rend="italic">Real Deputaz. di Stor. Patr. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Belgium</hi> : Antwerp, <hi rend="italic">Acad. d’Archéol.</hi> (1842), <hi rend="italic">Bull. </hi>(1865 &amp;c.). Bruges, <hi rend="italic">Soc. pour l'Hist. et les Antiq. de la Flandre</hi> (1839), <hi rend="italic">Publ. </hi>Brussels, <hi rend="italic">Soc. de l’Hist. de Belgique</hi> (1858), <hi rend="italic">Publ. ; Soc. Roy. de Numism.</hi> (1841), <hi rend="italic">Revue ; Soc. des Bibliophiles</hi> (1865). Ghent, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Roy. des Beaux-Arts et de la Litt.</hi> (1808), <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> (1844, &amp;c.); <hi rend="italic">Willems Fond</hi> (1851). Liége, <hi rend="italic">Inst. Archéol. </hi>(1852), <hi rend="italic">Bull.</hi> (1852, &amp;c.). Louvain, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Litt.</hi> (1839), <hi rend="italic">Mém.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Publ.</hi> Mons, <hi rend="italic">Cercle Archéol.</hi> (1856), <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> (1857, &amp;c.). Tournai, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Hist. et Litt.</hi> (1846), <hi rend="italic">Bull. </hi>(1849, &amp;c.). Verviers, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Arch.</hi> Ypres, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Hist.</hi> (1861). <hi rend="smallcaps">Holland:</hi> Leyden, <hi rend="italic">Acad. Lugduno-Batava.</hi> Luxembourg, <hi rend="italic">Inst. Archéol.</hi> (1846, reorganized in 1862), <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi> (1849, &amp;c.). Utrecht, <hi rend="italic">Hist. Genootschap. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Denmark:</hi> Copenhagen, <hi rend="italic">Island. Litt. Selskab ; K. Danske Selskab ; K. Nordisk Oldskrift Selskab.</hi> Reykjavik <hi rend="italic">(Iceland), Fornleifarfelag. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Norway:</hi> Christiania, <hi rend="italic">Norske Hist. Forening ; Norske Oldskrift Selskab. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Sweden: </hi><hi rend="italic">K. Vitterhets Hist. och Antiq. Akad. ; Svenska Akad. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Spain</hi> : Barcelona, <hi rend="italic">R. Acad. de Buenas Letras</hi> ; Madrid, <hi rend="italic">R. Acad. de Cienc. Mor. y Pol. ; R. Acad. Esp. Arq. ; R. Acad. de la Hist. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Greece</hi> : Athens, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Archéol. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Russia</hi> : Helsingfors, <hi rend="italic">Finska Litt. Sällskapet.</hi> Mitau, <hi rend="italic">Courland Soc. of Lit. and Art.</hi> Moscow, <hi rend="italic">Imp. Russ. Soc. of Hist. and Antiq. ; Archæolog. Soc.</hi> Narva, <hi rend="italic">Archæolog. Soc.</hi> Odessa, <hi rend="italic">Hist. and Antiq. Soc.</hi> Riga, <hi rend="italic">Lett. Lit. Ges. ; Hist. and Antiq. Soc.</hi> St Petersburg, <hi rend="italic">Russ. Hist. Soc. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Turkey:</hi> Constantinople,<hi rend="italic">,Soc. for Adv. of Turkish Lit. ; Hellenic Philolog. Soc. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Japan</hi> : Yokohama, <hi rend="italic">Asiatic Soc. of Japan, Trans.</hi> (1874, &amp;c.).</p><p>XVIII. <hi rend="smallcaps">Geography.</hi></p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Congrès International pour les Progrès des Sciences Géographiques</hi> first met in 1871. The <hi rend="italic">Royal Geographical Society of London,</hi> founded in 1830, had joined to it in the following year the <hi rend="italic">African Association</hi> (1788), the successor of the <hi rend="italic">Saturday Club</hi> ; the <hi rend="italic">Palestine Association</hi> (1805) became merged with it in 1834. It publishes <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> (1832, &amp;c.) and <hi rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> (1857, &amp;c.). The <hi rend="italic">Hakluyt Society</hi> (1846) has printed more than 70 vols. of rare voyages and travels. The <hi rend="italic">Alpine Club</hi> (1858). whose publications are <hi rend="italic">Peaks Passes, and Glaciers</hi> (1859-62) and <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> (1863, ,&amp;c.), and the <hi rend="italic">Palestine Exploration Fund</hi> (1865), publishing <hi rend="italic">Quarterly Statement</hi> (1869, &amp;c.) and <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> meet in London. The <hi rend="italic">Scottish Geographical Society</hi> (1884) has its centre at Edinburgh, and issues the <hi rend="italic">Scottish Geographical Magazine.</hi> Manchester has also a <hi rend="italic">Geographical Society. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Australia : </hi>Melbourne, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Soc.</hi> Sydney, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Inst. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Canada</hi> : Quebec, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Soc. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">India:</hi> Bombay, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Soc., Trans.</hi> (1836, &amp;c.).</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">United States</hi> : New York, <hi rend="italic">Amer. Geogr. (and Statist.) Soc., Bull.</hi> (1852, &amp;c.), <hi rend="italic">Journ.</hi> (1859, &amp;c.), and <hi rend="italic">Proc.</hi> (1862, &amp;c.) ; <hi rend="italic">Palestine Exploration Soc.</hi> (1870). <hi rend="smallcaps">France:</hi> Bordeaux, <hi rend="italic">Soc. de Géogr. Commerciale</hi> (1874), <hi rend="italic">Bull.</hi> Lyons, <hi rend="italic">Soc. de Géogr.</hi> (1873), <hi rend="italic">Bull.</hi> Marseilles, <hi rend="italic">Soc. de Géogr.</hi> (1876), <hi rend="italic">Bull.</hi> Paris, <hi rend="italic">Soc. de Géogr. </hi>(1821, reorganized in 1827), <hi rend="italic">Bull.</hi> (1822, &amp;c.). <hi rend="smallcaps">Germany</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Austria-Hungary : </hi><hi rend="italic">D. Geographentag</hi> (1881), <hi rend="italic">Verhandl. ; D. Alpen-Ver.</hi> (1869), <hi rend="italic">Ztschr. u. Jahrb.</hi> (1869, &amp;c.). Berlin, <hi rend="italic">Ges. f. Erdkunde</hi> (1828), <hi rend="italic">Ztschr.</hi> (1853, &amp;c.) and <hi rend="italic">Verhandl.</hi> (1873, &amp;c.); <hi rend="italic">Ges. zur Erforschung Aequat. Afrikas</hi> (1873), <hi rend="italic">Corr.-Blatt.; Afrik. Ges. </hi>(1878), <hi rend="italic">Mittheil.</hi> Bremen, <hi rend="italic">Geograph. Ges.</hi> (1877), <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Blätter.</hi> Carlsruhe, <hi rend="italic">Badische Geogr. Ges.</hi> (1880), <hi rend="italic">Verhandl.</hi> Cassel, <hi rend="italic">Ver. f. Erdk.</hi> (1882). Darmstadt, <hi rend="italic">Ver. f. Erdk. </hi>(1845)<hi rend="italic">, Notizblatt </hi>(1854<hi rend="italic">,</hi> &amp;c.). Dresden, <hi rend="italic">Ver. f. Erdk.</hi> (1863), <hi rend="italic">Jahresber. </hi>Frankfort, <hi rend="italic">Ver. f. Geogr. u. Statist.</hi> (1836), <hi rend="italic">Jahresber.</hi> Halle, <hi rend="italic">Ver. f. Erdk.</hi> (1873). Hamburg, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Ges.</hi> (1873), <hi rend="italic">Jahresber.</hi> Hanover, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Ges.</hi> (1878), <hi rend="italic">Jahresber. </hi>Jena, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Ges.</hi> (1880), <hi rend="italic">Mittheil.</hi> Leipsic, <hi rend="italic">Ver. f. Erdk.</hi> (1861), <hi rend="italic">Jahresber. </hi>Lübeck, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Ges.</hi> (1880). Munich, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Ges.</hi> (1869), <hi rend="italic">Jahresber.</hi> Pesth, <hi rend="italic">Hung. Geogr. Soc.</hi> (1873). Vienna, <hi rend="italic">K. k. Geogr. Ges., Mitth.</hi> (1857, &amp;c.); <hi rend="italic">Ver. der Geogr.</hi> Weimar, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Inst. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Switzerland: </hi><hi rend="italic">Bern, Inst. Geogr.; Schweiz. Alpen- Club.</hi> Geneva, Soc. <hi rend="italic">de Géogr., Mém. </hi>(1860, &amp;c.)<hi rend="italic">.</hi> Zurich, <hi rend="italic">Karten-Ver. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Italy: </hi>Rome, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Geogr. Ital., Bull.</hi> (1868, &amp;c.). Turin, <hi rend="italic">Circolo Geogr. Ital.</hi> (1868). <hi rend="smallcaps">Belgium</hi> : Antwerp, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Belge de Géogr.</hi> (1870), <hi rend="italic">Bull.</hi> Brussels, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Belge de Géogr. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Holland:</hi> Amsterdam, <hi rend="italic">Het Aardrijkskundig Genoot., Tijdschrift</hi> (1874, &amp;c.) ; <hi rend="italic">Landkundige Genootschap. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Denmark:</hi> Copenhagen, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Selskab. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Spain </hi>and <hi rend="smallcaps">Portugal</hi> : Lisbon, <hi rend="italic">Soc. de Geogr., Bol.</hi> (1876, &amp;c.). Madrid, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Geogr., Bol. </hi>(1876, &amp;c.). <hi rend="smallcaps">Russia</hi> : Irkutsk, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Soc., Bull.</hi> (1871, &amp;c.). St Petersburg, <hi rend="italic">Imp. Russ. Geogr. Soc., Mem.</hi> (1849, &amp;c.)and <hi rend="italic">Bull.</hi> (1865, &amp;c.). Tiflis, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Soc., Mem.</hi> (1852, &amp;c.). <hi rend="smallcaps">Egypt:</hi> Cairo, <hi rend="italic">Soc. Khédiviale de Géogr., Bull.</hi> (1876, &amp;c.). <hi rend="smallcaps">Japan:</hi> Tokio, <hi rend="italic">Geogr. Soc. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Central</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">South America</hi> : Buenos Ayres, <hi rend="italic">Inst. Geogr. Argent.</hi> Mexico, <hi rend="italic">Soc. de Geogr. ed Estad., Bol.</hi> (1861, &amp;c.). Rio Janeiro, <hi rend="italic">Roy. Geogr. Soc.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.</hi>—The <hi rend="italic">Catal. of Printed Books in the British Museum</hi> (1841), folio, <hi rend="italic">s.v.</hi> “Academies,” contains a list of all the publications of societies at that time in the museum. This has been re-arranged and greatly enlarged as <hi rend="italic">Academies </hi>(1885-86), 5 parts folio. See also <hi rend="italic">Annuaire des Soc. Sav. de la France et de l'Etranger</hi> (1846), 8vo; A. d’Héricourt, <hi rend="italic">Annuaire,</hi> 1863-66, 3 pts. 8vo; <hi rend="italic">Cat. of Periodicals in Bodleian Lib.,</hi> pt. iii. <hi rend="italic">Foreign,</hi> 1880, 8vo ; S. H. Scudder, <hi rend="italic">Cat. of Scientific Serials,</hi> 1633-1876, Camb. (U. S.),1879, 8vo,very complete ; P. E. Richter, <hi rend="italic">Periodica im Besitze des k. öff. Bibl. zu Dresden,</hi> 1880, 8vo ; <hi rend="italic">Cat. of Trans.,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">in Radcliffe Lib.,</hi> 1884, 8vo ; <hi rend="italic">List of Foreign Corr. of the Smithsonian Inst.</hi> 1886, 8vo. British societies are now well represented in the <hi rend="italic">Year Book of the Scientific and Lear ned Societies of Great Brit. and Ireland,</hi> 1884, &amp;c. See also Hume’s <hi rend="italic">Learned Societies and Printing Clubs of the U. K.,</hi> 1853, 8vo ; E. Mailly, <hi rend="italic">Inst. Sc. de la Grande Bret.,</hi> 1861-67, 6 pts. ; H. G. Bohn, <hi rend="italic">App. to Bibliographer’s Manual,</hi> 1864, 8vo ; <hi rend="italic">Engl. Catal. of Books,</hi> 1864-82, 3 vols. 8vo ; and “ Sc. Societies and Field Clubs,” in <hi rend="italic">Nature,</hi> v., viii. For France, see U. Robert, <hi rend="italic">Bibl. des Soc. Sav de la France,</hi> pt. i., 1878 ; F. Bouillier, <hi rend="italic">L’Institut et les Acad. de Province,</hi> 1879, 8vo ; <hi rend="italic">Bibliogr. des Travaux Hist. et Arch. publ. par les Soc. Sav. de la France,</hi> 1885, &amp;c., 4to (in prog.). For Germany and Austria-Hungary, see H. A. Stöhr, <hi rend="italic">Allg. Deutsches Vereinshandbuch,</hi> 1873, &amp;c., 8vo; J. Müller, <hi rend="italic">Die wiss. Vereine u. Ges. Deutschlands im 19ten Jahrh.,</hi> 1883, 4to (in prog.) ; J. Winckler, <hi rend="italic">Die period. Presse Oesterreichs,</hi> 1875, 8vo ; and P. A. F. Walther for German historical societies (1845). E. Huth, <hi rend="italic">Verzeichniss,</hi> Berlin, 1887, &amp;c. (in prog.), describes publications of societies relating to natural science. See also “ Les Congrès Scientifiques,” by Count de Marsy, in <hi rend="italic">Compte Rendu du Congrès Bibliogr.,</hi> 1879. For Belgium, see <hi rend="italic">Introd. à la Bibl. de la Belgique,</hi> 1875. For Italy, see G. Ottino, <hi rend="italic">La Stampa Periodica in Italia,</hi> 1875, 8vo. For Russia, consult C. Woldemar, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. d. russ. Gelehrten- und Schul-Anstalten,</hi> St Petersburg, 1865, 8vo, and Hawaii, <hi rend="italic">Die neuen russ. Nalurforschergesellschaften,</hi> Riga, 1872-74.	(H. R. T.).</p><p>SOCIETY ISLANDS. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Tahiti Archipelago. </hi>SOCINUS, the Latinized form of the Italian Soccini,</p><p>Sozini, or Sozzini.</p><p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Lelio Francesco Maria Sozini</hi> (1525-1562), theological inquirer, was born at Siena on 29th January 1525. His family descended from Sozzo, a banker at Percena,</p><p>whose second son, Mino Sozzi, settled as a notary at Siena in 1304. Mino Sozzi’s grandson, Sozzino (d. 1403), was the ancestor of a line of patrician jurists, of whom Mariano Sozzini, senior (1397-1467), was the first and the most famous. Lelio was the sixth son of Mariano Sozzini, junior (1482-1556), by his wife Camilla Salvetti. The family name is variously spelled (usually “ Soccini ” by modern writers) ; Lelio invariably uses the form “ Sozini,” Latinizing it “Sozinus” ; his nephew <hi rend="smallcaps">Fausto</hi> (see below) writes “ Sozzini ” and “ Socinus.” Sozini was educated as a jurist under his father’s eye at Bologna. According to Melanchthon, it was his desire to reach the <hi rend="italic">fontes juris</hi> which led him to Biblical studies and hence to the rejection of “ the idolatry of Rome.” Later on he acquired some knowledge of Hebrew and Arabic (he gave to Bibliander a manuscript of the Koran) as well as Greek, but he was never a laborious student. His father supplied him with means, and on coming of age he went to Venice, the headquarters of the evangelical movement in Italy. A tradition first published by Sand in 1678, and amplified by subsequent writers, makes Sozini the leading spirit in certain alleged theological conferences at Vicenza, about 1546, which are said to have forecast the main positions of the Unitarian heresy ; but the whole account, including the story of the flight of Sozini, must be rejected as mythical. At this period the standpoint of Sozini was that of evangelical Protestantism ; his mental temper presents a singular union of enthusiastic piety with a love for the subtleties of theological speculation. It was at Chiavenna in 1547 that he came under the influence of a gentle mystic, Camillo of Sicily, surnamed “ Renato,” whose teaching anticipated at many points that of the early Quakers. Pursuing his religious travels, Sozini visited Switzerland, France, England, and Holland, returning to Switzerland at the close of 1548. He had commendatory letters to the Swiss churches from Nicolas Meyer, envoy from Wittenberg to Italy ; but his family name was a sufficient passport, and wherever he went his personal charm won friends. We find him in 1549-50 at Geneva and Basel (with Sebastian Münster), but chiefly at Zurich, where he lodges with Pellican. He spends eleven months (July 1550 to June 1551) at Wittenberg, at first under Melanchthon’s roof, then with Johann Forster for the improvement of his Hebrew. From Wittenberg Sozini returned to Zurich (end of 1551) after visiting Prague, Vienna, and Cracow. Political events attracted him back to Italy in June 1552. Two visits to Siena (where freedom of speech was for the moment possible, owing to the shaking off of the Spanish yoke) brought him into fruitful contact with his young nephew Fausto. He was at Padua (not at Geneva, as is often said) at the date of Servetus’s execution (27th October 1553). Thence he made his way to Basel (January 1554), Geneva (April), and Zurich (May), where he took up his abode.</p><p>Calvin, as well as Melanchthon, received Sozini with open arms. Melanchthon (though a phrase in one of his letters has been strangely misinterpreted) never regarded him with theological suspicion. To Calvin’s keen glance Sozini’s over-speculative tendency and the genuineness of his religious nature were equally apparent. A passage often quoted from one of Calvin’s letters to Sozini (1st January 1552) has been construed as a breaking off of amicable intercourse ; but, while more than once uneasy apprehensions arose in Calvin’s mind, there was no breach of correspondence or of friendship. Of all the Reformers Bullinger was Sozini’s closest intimate, his warmest and wisest friend. Sozini’s theological difficulties turned upon the resurrection of the body, predestination, the ground of salvation (these were the points on which he corresponded with Calvin), the doctrinal basis of the original gospel (queries addressed to Bullinger), the nature of repentance</p></body></text></TEI>