<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:13:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="smallcaps">tonic, Enharmonic, Harmony, Interval,</hi> and Music.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">System,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany,</hi> page 430.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">System,</hi> in aſtronomy. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy.</hi></p><p>SYSTOLE, in anatomy, the contraction of the heart, whereby the blood is drawn off its ventricles into the arteries ; the oppoſite ſtate to which is called the <hi rend="italic">diastole,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">dilatation of the heart.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n⁰ 124.</p><p>SYSTYLE, in architecture, that manner of placing columns where the ſpace between the two ſhafts conſiſts of two diameters or four modules.</p><p>SYZYGY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Syzygia,</hi> in aſtronomy, a term equally uſed for the conjunction and oppoſition of a planet with the sun. The word is formed from the Greek συςυγια, which properly signifies <hi rend="italic">conjunctiο.</hi> On the phenomena and circumſtances of the syzygies a great part of the lunar theory depends. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy.</hi></p><p>Tor t, the 19th letter and 16th conſonant of our alphabet ; the found whereof is formed by a ſtrong expulsion of the breath through the mouth, upon a hidden drawing back of the tongue from the fore-part of the palate, with the lips at the ſame time open. The proper found of <hi rend="italic">t</hi> is expreſſed in moſt words beginning or ending with that letter ; as in <hi rend="italic">take, tell, hot, put. Ti</hi> before a vowel has the found of si<hi rend="italic">,</hi> or rather of S<hi rend="italic">hi,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">creation,</hi> except when <hi rend="italic">ſ </hi>precedes, as in <hi rend="italic">question ;</hi> and in derivatives from words ending in <hi rend="italic">ty,</hi> as, <hi rend="italic">mighty, mightier. Th</hi> has two sounds ; the one soft, as <hi rend="italic">thou, father ;</hi> the other hard, as <hi rend="italic">thing, think.</hi> The found is soft in theſe words, <hi rend="italic">then, thence,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">there,</hi> with their derivatives and compounds ; and in the words <hi rend="italic">that, this, thus, thy, they, though ;</hi> and in all words in which <hi rend="italic">th</hi> comes between two vowels, as, <hi rend="italic">whether, rather ;</hi> and between <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and a vowel, as <hi rend="italic">burthen.</hi></p><p>In abbreviations, amongst the Roman writers, T. ſtands for <hi rend="italic">Titus, Titius,</hi> &amp;c. ; Tab. for <hi rend="italic">Tabularius ;</hi> Tab. P. H. C. <hi rend="italic">Tabularius Provinciae Hispania Citerioris;</hi> Tar. <hi rend="italic">Tarquinius; </hi>Ti. <hi rend="italic">Tiberius ;</hi> Ti. F. <hi rend="italic">Tiberii filius ;</hi> Ti. L. <hi rend="italic">Tiberii libertus ; </hi>Ti. N. <hi rend="italic">Tiberii Nepos</hi> ; T. J. A. V. P. V. D. <hi rend="italic">tempore judicem arbitrumve postulat ut det ;</hi> T. Μ. P. <hi rend="italic">terminum poſuit ; </hi>T. Μ. E). D. <hi rend="italic">terminum dedicavit;</hi> Tr. <hi rend="italic">trans, tribunus ;</hi> Tr. Μ. or Mil. <hi rend="italic">tribunus militum;</hi> TR. PL·. DES. <hi rend="italic">tribunus plebis designatus</hi> ; TR. AER. <hi rend="italic">tribunus orarii ;</hi> TRV. CAP. <hi rend="italic">triumviri capitales</hi> ; T. P. or TRIB. POT. <hi rend="italic">tribunicia potestate ; </hi>Tul, H. <hi rend="italic">Tullus Hostilius.</hi></p><p>Amongſt the ancients, T. as a numeral, stood for <hi rend="italic">one hundred and ſixty</hi> ; and with a daſh at top, thus, T, it ſignified <hi rend="italic">one hundred and ſixty thousand.</hi> In muſic, T ſtands for tutti, “ all, or altogether.”</p><p>TABANUS, the <hi rend="smallcaps">breeze-fly:</hi> a genus of infects belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">diptera.</hi> The mouth is extended in a fleſhy proboſcis, terminated by two lips. The reſtrum is furniſhed with two pointed palpi placed on each side of the proboſcis, and parallel to it. Gmelin has enumerated 38 ſpecies ; of which three only are found in Great Britain, the bovinus, pluviatilis, and cœcutiens.</p><p>1.	The <hi rend="italic">bovinus,</hi> or great horſe fly, has a grey head ; the eyes almoſt of a black brown, occupying the greateſt part of it. The thorax is of a grey colour; the abdomen is yellowiſh, with a triangular white ſpot on the middle of every ring, which conſtitutes a longitudinal band of ſpots, the point of which is directed towards the thorax. The thighs are blackiſh, and the legs yellow. The wings are ſomewhat duſky, with brown veins of a deeper dye. This infect is the terror of horned cattle, horſes, &amp;c. Its mouth is armed with two ſharp hooks which penetrate their hide ; while with its proboſcis, which is shaped like a ſting, it sucks their blood, of which it is very greedy. The puncture of the tabanus is keen and painful. The insect is very common in damp woods and meadows, eſpecially during the great heats, when it is moſt troubleſome. The horned cattle are ſometimes ſo moleſted by their stings, that they go mad, run down  precipices, tear themſelves on the stumps of trees, stones, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">2.</hi>	The <hi rend="italic">pluviatilis</hi> is of an ashen grey colour ; its eyes are green, with brown ſtreaks. The thorax is brown, marked with about ſeven longitudinal grey lines ; the wings, which are brown and aſh-coloured, are dotted over with ſmall white ſpots, and have a black ſpot on the margin ; the legs are ſurrounded with brown and white rings alternately. This ſpecies is very common in meadows, and is about four lines in ſength.</p><p>3.	The <hi rend="italic">coecutiens</hi> has a brown head ; eyes green and brown, with black ſpots ; the thorax brown with black ſpots ; the abdomen above, yellow with triangular brown ſpots ; yellow legs, and white wings with black and brown ſpots. The length is four lines and a half.</p><p>TABARCA, a little iſland lying oppoſite to a ſmall town of that name, which divides the maritime coaſts of Tunis and Algiers, in Africa, two miles from the land, in poffeſſion of the noble family of the Lamellini of Genoa, who have here a governor and a garrison of 200 men to protect the coral fiſhery. N. Lat. 36. 50 E. Long. 9. 16.</p><p>TABASHEER, a Perſian word, ſignifying a hard ſubstance found in the cavities of the bamboo or Indian reed, and highly valued as a medicine in the Eaſt Indies. Though ſome account was given of the tabasheer by the Arabian phyſicians, no accurate knowledge of it was obtained till Dr Ruffel favoured the public with his obſervations on it.</p><p>According to this gentleman’s information, the. tabaſheer is produced from the female bamboo, which is diſtinguished from the male by the the largeneſs of its cavity. It is eaſy to diſcover, without opening them, what bamboos contain it, as they make a rattling noiſe when ſhaken. Dr Ruffel having examined a bamboo brought from Vellore, conſiſting of six joints, found no appearance of tabaſheer in two of them ; all the reſt contained ſome, but of various quality and quantity ; the whole amounting to about 27 grains. The beſt was of a bluiſh white reſembling ſmall fragments of ſhells, harder also than the reſt, but which might be eaſily crumbled between the fingers into a gritty powder ; and when applied to the tongue and palate, had a flight ſaline and teſtaceous taste; the weight not exceeding four grains. The colour of the reſt was cineritious, rough on the ſurface, and more friable; having ſome particles of a larger ſize intermixed, but light, ſpongy, and ſomewhat reſembling pumice ſtones ; which appearance, our author ſuppoſes, led the Arabians to think that fire was concerned in the production. The two middle joints were of a pure white colour within, and lined with a thin film. In theſe the tabaſheer was principally found. The other joints, particularly the two upper ones, were diſcoloured within ; and in ſome parts of the cavity was found a blackiſh ſubſtance in grains or in powder, adhering to the ſides, the film being there obliterated.</p></body></text></TEI>