<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:13:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>on one another, one Sandracottus, a native of India, had driven out the Macedonians, and made himſelf maſter of the whole country. He oppoſed Seleucus with an army of <hi rend="smallcaps">600,000</hi> men, and a prodigious number of elephants; which intimidated the Macedonian ſo much, that he offered to leave Sandracottus in quiet poſſeſſion of his dominions, provided he would furniſh him with 500 elephants. To this Sandracottus readily assented ; upon which Seleucus marched back into the west againſt Antigonus, and, in conjunction with Lyſimachus and Ptolemy, engaged and totally defeated and killed him at Ipſus. After this Seleucus marched into Upper Syria, which he reduced entirely, and built the city of Antioch on the Orontes. In the ſame country he built ſeveral other cities ; one of which he called <hi rend="italic">Seleucia,</hi> from his own name ; another <hi rend="italic">Apamea,</hi> from his wife Apama, the daughter of one Artabazus a Perſian; and a third <hi rend="italic">Laodicen,</hi> from his mother Laodice. He firſt entered into an alliance with Demetrius, and married Stratonice his daughter; but ſoon after aſſiſted Lyſimachus and Ptolemy to deprive him of the beſt part of his dominions. Thus Demetrius being reduced ſo low that he could give him no farther jealouſy, Seleucus betook himſelf to the building of another city, which he called likewiſe <hi rend="italic">Seleucia, </hi>and which ſtood on the place where the city of Bagdad now stands. Beſides theſe, he built a great many others ; 16 of which he called <hi rend="italic">Antioch,</hi> ſrorn the name of his brother Antiochus ; nine <hi rend="italic">Seleucia,</hi> from his own name ; three <hi rend="italic">Apamea, </hi>from Apama his firſt wife ; one <hi rend="italic">Stratonicea,</hi> from his ſecond wife Stratonice ; and six <hi rend="italic">Laodicea,</hi> from his mother Laodice.</p><p>In 284 Seleucus entered into a war with Lyſimachus, with whom he had hitherto lived in ſtrict amity. Out of 36 general officers left by Alexander the Great, they two only ſurvived, and both were upwards of 70 years old. Nevertheleſs they were both filled with the ambition and animoſity of young men. The two armies met at a place called <hi rend="italic">Curopedion</hi> in Phrygia, where an obſtinate engagement took place. Victory was long doubtful : but at laſt Lyſimachus was run through with a spear, and died on the ſpot; on which his troops betook themſelves to flight, and left Seleucus maſter of their baggage. This victory added to the poſſeſſions of Seleucus all thoſe provinces which had formerly been ſubject to Lyſimachus. The former exulted much in his good fortune ; being chiefly pleaſed that he was now the laſt of Alexander’s captains, and by this victory became, as he ſtyled it, <hi rend="italic">the conqueror of conquerors;</hi> and on this account he is generally called <hi rend="italic">Nicator,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">the conqueror.</hi> His triumph, however, on this occaſion, was but ſhort-lived ; for, ſeven months after, as he was marching towards Macedon to take posſession of that kingdom, he was treacherouſly murdered by Ptolemy Ceraunus, on whom he had conferred innumerable favours. Philetærus prince of Pergamus purchaſed his body at a great price from Ptolemy, and sent it to his ſon Antiochus ; who, with extraordinary pomp, burned it in Seleucia on the ſea coaſt, erecting on the place a magnificent chapel, which he called from Iris ſurname <hi rend="italic">Nicatorium.</hi></p><p>Seleucus was ſucceeded by his ſon Antiochus Soter, who held the empire 19 years. He reſigned to Antigonus Conatus all pretensions to the crown of Macedon ; and having engaged in a war with Eumenes king of Pergamus, he was defeated by him, and obliged to yield up part of his dominions. He died in 261 B. C. and was ſucceeded by his ſon Antiochus Theos ; who having engaged in a war with Ptolemy Philadelphus king of Egypt, the Parthians and Bactrians took an οppοrtunity to revolt, and could never afterwards be reduced. In 246 B. C. he was poiſoned by his wife Laodice, whom he had divorced for Berenice daughter to Ptolemy, with whom he made peace on the revolt of the Bactrians. On the death of Ptolemy, Antiochus divorced Berenice, and took back Laodice ; who, to ſecure herſelf againſt the effects of his fickle diſpoſition, poiſoned him, as we have juſt mentioned, and raised to the throne her own ſon, named <hi rend="italic">Seleucus Callinicus.</hi> Not thinking herſelf ſafe, however, as long as Berenice lived, Laodice began immediately to concert meaſures for putting both her and her ſon to death. Berenice attempted to ſave herſelf by retiring to Daphne, where ſhe ſhut herſelf up in an aſylum built by Seleucus Nicator. There ſhe was cloſely besieged by the ſons of Seleucus ; of which the cities of Aſia having intelligence, formed a confederacy in her favour. Her brother the king of Egypt alſo haſtened to her relief with a conſiderable army; but before either of theſe could come to her aſſiſtance, both ſhe and her ſon were barbarouſly murdered, with all the Egyptians who attended them.</p><p>Ptolemy, on hearing the melancholy news of his ſiſter’s death, determined to take the moſt ſevere vengeance on her murderers. Joining his forces to thoſe of the Aſiatics, he carried every thing before him. Having in the firſt place put an end to the life of Laodice, he made himſelf maſter of all Syria and Cilicia ; then paſſing the Euphrates, he ſubdued all the country as far as Babylon and the Tigris ; and had not the progreſs of his arms been interrupted by a ſedition which obliged him to return to Egypt, it is more than probable that he would have ſubdued the whole Syrian empire. As ſoon as he was returned, Seleucus attempted to revenge himſelf ; but his fleet being deſtroyed by a violent ſtorm, and his land-army defeated by Ptolemy, he concluded a truce for ten years. During all this time the Parthian prince had eſtabliſhed himſelf ſo firmly on the throne, that it was in vain to think of diſpoſtessing him. However, as ſoon as his other affairs would permit, Seleucus undertook an expedition againſt Arsaces the Parthian monarch ; by whom he was utterly defeated, taken prisoner, and carried into Parthia, where he died four years after. He was ſucceeded by his eldeſt ſon Seleucus Ceraunus, a weak prince, who was poiſoned by a conſpiracy of two of his officers, when he had reigned one year; after which his brother Antiochus, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Great,</hi> aſcended the throne in 225 B. C.</p><p>In the very beginning of his reign, two of his generals, Alexander and Molo, rebelled againſt him. The former had been appointed governor of Persia, and the latter of Media; but they, deſpiſing the king’s youth, refuſed to obey. The occaſion of this revolt is ſaid to have ſeen their dread of the cruelty of Hermias the king’s prime miniſter; and as they hoped to draw into their ſchemes Achæus governor of the provinces off Asia Minor, they doubted not of ſucceſs. In this, however, they failed; but this did rot diſcourage them from proceeding in their rebellion. Epigenes, the commander of the troops about the king’s perſon, adviſed him to march without delay againſt the rebels; but as Hermias reproached him with treachery and a deſign to betray the king into the hands of his enemies, Antiochus sent two of his generals into the eaſt, while he himſelf undertook an expedition againſt Ptolemy Philadelphus, with a view of recovering Coeleſyria. In this attempt, however, he was diſappointed ; and the generals whom he had sent into the eaſt were totally defeated, and their troops cut off : upon which he determined to lay aſide for the preſent his Syrian enterprise, and march in person againſt the rebels. This was again oppoſed by Hermias ; but as he found it impoſsible to alter the king’s mind, the treacherous miniſter found means to get Epigenes the author of this project executed, under pretence of holding a correspondence with Molo one of the rebel chiefs. Antiochus in the mean time pursued</p></body></text></TEI>