<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:13:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>had long halberts faſtened to their poles, and ſharp hooks to their axle-trees ; the former were about the height of a man’s head, and the latter almoſt ſwept the ground, and cut off the legs of all who ſtood in their way. But Eumenes undertook to render them uſeleſs, and even fatal, to the enemy. This brave prince, putting himſelf at the head of the bowmen and slingers, ordered them to charge, not in a body, but divided in platoons, and to aim only at the horſes in the chariots. Accordingly, as ſoon as the chariots moved, Eumenes advanced at the head of his men, who pouring on them from every quarter darts, ſtones, and javelins, and at the ſame time ſhouting as loud as they could, so frightened the horſes that they could no longer be kept in order, but ſcouring up and down, and turning againſt their own troops, fell on the Arabians who ſupported them, which occaſioned a great confuſion in that quarter. Thoſe in the Syrian army who were at a diſtance, hearing the noise and outcries, and not knowing the cauſe of them, were ſtruck with no ſmall terror. After this advantage, the Roman cavalry advanced, and fell on thoſe whom the chariots had put in diſorder. The Syrians being already intimidated, after a faint reſiſtance gave way ; and the Romans made a great ſlaughter of their men and horſes, both being borne down with the weight of their heavy armour. Eumenes charged the left-wing, in which Seleucus commanded, with ſuch vigour, that he put it to flight ; and the fugitives flying to the phalanx for protection, put that body likewiſe in diſorder ; which Domitius obſerving, advanced againſt it at the head of his legionaries, but could not break it till he ordered his men to attack the elephants ; which, as before obſerved, were placed in the ſpaces between the companies. The Romans had learned, in their wars with Pyrrhus and Hannibal, not to fear thoſe monſters which were once ſo terrible to them.	They attacked them, therefore, with great reſolution ; and driving them againſt the phalanx, put that body into diſorder, by means of thoſe very animals which had been poſted there for its defence.</p><p>But in the mean time advice was brought that the left wing of the Romans was in great danger. Antiochus, who had obſerved that the flanks of the left wing were quite open and uncovered, the four ſquadrons which covered it having joined the reſt of the cavalry to fall upon the enemy’s left wing, had charged it at the head of all his auxiliaries, not only in front but in flank. The Roman infantry, seeing themſelves in imminent danger of being ſurrounded and hemmed in on all ſides, fled in great diſorder to their camp, which was guarded by 2000 men under the command of a legionary tribune called <hi rend="italic">Æmilius.</hi> This man feeing the Romans flying towards him, marched out at the head of all his troops to meet them ; and after having bitterly reproached them for their cowardice and ignominious flight, ordered his men to draw their ſwords, and cut in pieces ſuch as ſhould advance one ſtep farther, or refuſe to face about againſt the enemy. This order, given ſo ſeaſonably, and put in execution without mercy againſt ſome, had the deſired effect. Thoſe who were flying firſt halted ; and</p><p>then,	being both reinforced and encouraged by Æmilius, returned under his conduct to wipe off the diſhonour of their flight. At the ſame time Attalus the brother of Eumenes, having left the right wing on his receiving advice that the left was in danger, arrived very ſeaſonably with 200 horſe. Antiochus obſerving that the troops which had fled were returning to the battle, and that the enemy's  right wing was ready to fall upon him, turned his horſe about and fled. This ſerved in a manner as a ſignal for the reſt of the troops, for the whole Syrian army immediately turned their backs. Eumenes alone pursued them at the head of the cavalry, and made a moſt dreadful havock of the fugitives. The Romans walking over heaps of dead bodies, eſpecially where the phalanx ſtood, marched up to the Syrian camp, attacked, and plundered it. The riches they found in it are not to be deſcribed : but the taking of it cost the Romans a new battle, which proved more fatal to the Syrians than that in the field ; for the Romans having, in ſpite of a moſt deſperate reſiſtance, forced the intrenchments, gave no quarter, but put all to the ſword without diſtinction. There fell this day in the battle, in the purſuit, and in the plunder of the camp, 50,000 foot and 4000 horſe ; 1500 were taken priſoners, and 15 elephants. In the conſular army there were but 300 foot killed and 25 horſe. Eumenes had only 15 of his men killed ; ſo that this victory, as we are told by the ancients, ſeemed a prodigy to all nations both of the eaſt and west.</p><p>Antiochus retired to Sardis with as many of his forces that had eſcaped the ſlaughter as he could draw together. From Sardis he ſoon marched to rejoin his ſon Seleucus, who had fled to Apamea. As for the conſul, he took advantage of the king’s defeat and flight, making himself master of all the neighbouring countries. Deputies haſtened to him from all parts ; the cities of Thyatira, Magnesia, Trallis, Magneſia in Caria, all Lydia, and Epheſus itſelf, though highly favoured by Antiochus, declared for the Romans. Polyxenidas, upon the news of the king’s defeat, left the port of Epheſus, and ſailed to Patara, where he landed with a very ſmall guard, and returned by land into Syria. The conſul took the road to Sardis, which opened its gates to him. As he stopped there, his brother Africanus, as ſoon as his health allowed him, came and joined him in that city, and congratulated him on the glory he had ſo lately acquired.</p><p>Antiochus finding his affairs in a bad ſituation both by ſea and land, and not daring to appear before the conſular army in the field, ſent Antipater his brother’s son, and Zeuxis, who had been governor of Lydia and Phrygia, to ſue for a peace. They were ordered to treat chiefly with the elder brother, of whoſe clemency and good nature Antiochus entertained a high opinion. Accordingly, on their arrival at Sardis, where the conſul then was with his brother, they addreſſed the latter, and were by him preſented to thc conſul. Their ſpeech was very ſubmiſſive, and ſuch as became a vanquiſhed people.</p><p>Hereupon a council was ſummoned, and after long debates the ambassadors were called in ; and Scipio Africanus being desired by the conſul to acquaint the deputies with the reſolutions of the aſſembly, is ſaid to have expresſed himſelf in the following terms : “ We are ſenſible that the victory which we have lately gained is owing to the gods, and therefore ſhall treat the vanquiſhed with moderation, demanding little more of them now than we did at our firſt entering into Aſia. Antiochus ſhall obtain a peace upon the following terms : That he give up his pretenſions to Europe, confine his dominions to Aſia beyond Mount Taurus ; and that he pay 15,000 Euboec talents for the expences of the war ; 500 down, 2500 when the ſenate and people ſhall confirm the articles, and 1000 more every year for 12 years together. We alſo inſiſt upon his ſatisfying king Eumenes, and his paying him the 400 talents he owes him, and what remains due for the corn which his father ſent to the king of Syria. It is likewiſe the pleaſure of the council that you deliver up to us Hannibal the Carthaginian, Thoas the AEtolian. Mnesilochus the Acarnanian, and Philo and Eubulus two Chalcidians; for theſe have been the authors of our divisions, the incendiaries who kindled the preſent war. Laſtly, the king of Syria, for a further proof of his sincerity, ſhall give us 20 ſuch hoſtages as we ſhall chooſe, of whom Antiochus his youngeſt ſon ſhall be one.”</p></body></text></TEI>