<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:06Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to gain him over: he therefore approached nearer to his country ; by which alſo he drew towards the armies of Weymar and Hesse. In his way he cut in pieces a body of 3000 Croats. General Konigſmark routed the Imperialiſts at Gera ; a second time at Scholen ; and a third time entirely defeated them near Leipſic. Bannier was very preſſing on the allies to join him ; and at laſt, in 1640, he was joined by the Weymar army under the dukes of Longueville and Gubrien, a body of Russians led by general Melander, and the troops of Lunenburgh commanded by general Klitzing. The army now amounted to 22 battalions of infantry and 22,000 horſe ; ſo that they were much more than a match for their enemies, had they been under the ſole direction of Bannier. But unanimity was wanting ; every one would be ſupreme in the command ; and Bannier, the beſt general of them all, had the leaſt influence. Inſtead of thoſe maſterly and deciſive ſtrokes by which the Swedes had hitherto diſtinguiſhed themſelves, the armies continued looking at one another, each ſuffering the rigours of famine. At laſt Bannier, reſolving to expoſe his troops no longer, ſet out for Thuringia, through Franconia, to ſeize an advantageous poſt on the Maine ; but as he advanced to the Sala, he found the Imperialiſts entrenched on the other side. Finding it impoſſible to force a passage, he took the road through Hesse, where his troops ſuffered greatly by famine. Here he propoſed to fight the enemy ; but the Landgrave and duke of Lunenburg refuſed their conſent. Upon this he threatened to leave them to the mercy of the confederates, and thus obliged them to be ſomewhat more pliant. None of thoſe brilliant ſuccesses, however, now attended the operations of the Proteſtant allies : the campaigns of 1640 and 1641 were ſpent in uſeleſs marches and countermarches ; ſerving only to bring the army into the greateſt dangers, from which they were as conſtantly relieved by the active and intrepid Bannier. At laſt this brave general, worn out with perpetual fatigues, died of a fever in the year 1641, leaving the Swediſh army in a worſe ſituation than ever.</p><p>The Imperialiſts were too well acquainted with the abilities of Bannier, not to take advantage of the opportunity offered by his death. A Swediſh detachment was cut in pieces at Quidlenberg. The Swediſh army, accuſtomed only to be obedient to Bannier, became mutinous, and Piccolomini reſolved to fall upon them with his whole force. But the four generals, Wrangel, Konigſmark, Wittemberg, and Pful, having convinced the ſoldiers of the neceſſity of defending themſelves, made ſuch excellent diſpositions, that the Imperialiſts durst not attack them. Piccolomini then detached part of his army to attack the Heſſians in their quarters ; but Wrangel and Konigſmark threw themſelves in their way, and defeated them with the loſs of 2000 mem This victory, however, did not retrieve the Swediſh affairs. Dissenſions and mutiny began again to take place in the army to ſuch a degree as threatened its diſſolution. In 1642 general Torenſton was ſent from Sweden, with a large ſum of money and a ſtrong reinforcement, to take upon him the ſupreme command. This general was inferior in abilities to none of his predecessors, and deſigned without loſs of time to come to an engagement ; but the Weymar army ſeparating from him, put an end to that deſign, and obliged him to remain for a considerable time inactive. He was also confined to his chamber for ſome time by a dangerous gout ; and thus a report of his death being ſpread, the Imperialiſts were encouraged to begin a long march through roads ſcarce passable, in hopes of ſurpriſing the Swediſh army without a general. Torſtenſon having intelligence of this, ſeized an advantageous poſt, which could not be forced; and thus obliged the enemy to retreat, after having ſuffered as much by their fatiguing march as if they had fought a bloody battle. Then joining general Stalhanch, who had been driven by the Imperialiſts out of Sileſia, he reduced the town of Great Glogau, with a number of other important places ; after which he laid siege to Schweidnitz. The duke of Saxe-Lawenburgh, at the head of all his cavalry, endeavoured to throw in ſuccours ; but was defeated with the loss of 3000 men. He himſelf was taken priſoner, and died of chagrin a few days after. In conſequence of this defeat Schweidnitz ſurrendered at diſcretion ; and Torſtenſon having ſent a detachment to inveſt the city of Neisse, proceeded with the reſt to drive the enemy entirely out of Sileſia. This he effectually performed ; obliging them to retire over barren mountains, almoſt famished for want of proviſions, and haraſſed by his light troops ; ſo that this lately formidable army was almoſt entirely ruined. With his victorious troops the Swediſh general then poured into Moravia ; where, in five days, he reduced the ſtrong town of Olmutz (which not long ago ſuſtained a ſiege of as many weeks by the late king of Pruſſia). Litta and Newſtadt ſhared the ſame fate ; after which, the Swedes, returning ſuddenly to Sileſia, made themſelves matters of Oppelein and Brieg, and laid ſiege to Breslau. Here the garriſon made ſuch an obſtinate defence, that the Imperialiſts had time to assemble under the conduct of the archduke Leopold, and come to their relief. As Torſtenſon was greatly inferior in number, he raised the ſiege ; but appeared ſo formidable in his retreat, that the enemy durſt neither attack him, nor attempt to prevent his encamping in a very advantageous ſituation. The Imperialiſts took this opportunity of laying ſiege to Glogau ; but after having loſt a great number of men, they were forced to abandon the enterpriſe on the junction of Wrangel with Torſtenſon ; by which means the Swedes were once more in a condition to face their enemies in the field.</p><p>Torſtenſon now projected an irruption into Bohemia, and putting his army into winter-quarters in that country ; but in this he was prevented by the vigilance of the enemy : however, he reduced the city of Zittau, where, for the firſt time, a cartel for priſoners was eſtabliſhed ; by which means the Swediſh army was conſiderably augmented. Thus diſappointed in his deſigns on Bohemia, Torſtenſon directed his courſe to Leipſic, which he intended to inveſt. The Imperial generals aſſembled their whole force, and ſet out to relieve that important place. The two armies ſoon came in sight of each other ; and a furious cannonading was the prelude to a general engagement. A ſingle bullet had almoſt proved fatal to the Swediſh cauſe. It carried away the furniture of Torſtenſon’s horſe, killed the count Palatine’s horſe, pierced general Rabenau through the body, took off the head of a celebrated counſellor named <hi rend="italic">Crabbe, </hi>and carried away the leg of a private ſoldier. The Swedes, as ſoon as the armies came up, behaved with their wonted reſolution, and after an obſtinate conflict obtained a complete victory ; 5000 of the enemy being killed on the fpot, 3000 wounded, and as many taken priſoners. This victory was followed by the immediate ſurrender of Leipſic ; and in all probability the Swedes would have finally triumphed over all their enemies, had not a rupture with Denmark enſued. Torſtenſon and Horn behaved with their uſual valour in Holſtein and Schonen, while general Konigſmark diſtinguiſhed himſelf in Germany ; but the ruin of the Weymar army, which was totally defeated with the loſs of one half its number at Dettingen by the Bavarians, proved a dreadful blow, from which the Swedes could ſcarce recover themſelves. Indeed, notwithſtanding the valour and ſucceſs of the Swedes, their affairs in Germany muſt have gone to wreck in the campaigns of 1643, had not the</p></body></text></TEI>