<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:27Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>at a particular ſum, the preſent single payment paid on admission is found by
                ſubtracting the value of the annual payment during the joint lives from the whole
                preſent value of the annuity in one payment. Suppoſe, for inſtance, the annual
                payments to be fixed at five guineas, the annuity to be 30 l. the rate of intereſt
                four <hi rend="italic">per cent,</hi> and the joint lives each 40; the value of the
                annuity in one preſent ſingle payment is 101. 11. The value of five guineas or 5.25
                    <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> is (5.25 multiplied by 9.82 the value of the
                joint lives) 51.55 ; which, subtracted from 101.11. gives 1.49.5, the anſwer.</p>
            <p>If a ſociety takes in all the marriages among perſons of a particular profession
                within a given diſtrict, and ſubjects them for perpetuity to a certain equal and
                common tax or annual payments, in order to provide life annuities for all the widows
                that ſhall result from theſe marriages ; ſince, at the commencement of ſuch an
                eſtablishment, all the oldeſt, as well as the youngeſt, marriages are to be intitled
                equally to the propoſed benefit, a much greater number of annuitants will come
                immediately upon it than would come upon any similar eſtabliſhment which limited
                itſelf in the admission of members to perſons not exceeding a given age. This will
                check that accumulation of money which ſhould take place at firſt, in order to
                produce an income equal to the diſburſements at the time when the number of
                annuitants comes to a <hi rend="italic">maximum</hi> ; and therefore will be a
                particular burden upon the eſtabliſhment in its infancy. For this ſome compenſation
                muſt be provided ; and the equitable method of providing it is, by levying fines at
                the beginning of the eſtabliſhment on every member exceeding a given age,
                proportioned to the number of years which he has lived beyond that age. But if ſuch
                fines cannot be levied, and if every payment muſt be equal and common, whatever
                diſparity there may be in the value of the expectations of different members, the
                fines muſt be reduced to one common one, anſwering as nearly as poſſible to the
                diſadvantage, and payable by every member at the time when the eſtabliſhment begins.
                After this, the eſtabliſhment will be the ſame with one that takes upon it all at
                the time they marry; and the tax or annual payment of every member adequate to its
                ſupport will be the annual payment during marriage due from perſons who marry at the
                mean age at which, upon an average, all marriages may be conſidered as commencing.
                The fines to be paid at firſt are, for every particular member, the same with the
                difference between the value of the expectation to him at his preſent age, and what
                would have been its value to him had the ſcheme begun at the time he married. Or,
                they are, for the whole body of members, the difference between the value of the
                common expectation, to perſons at the mean age of all married perſons taken together
                as they exiſt in the world, and to perſons at that age which is to be deemed their
                mean age when they marry.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe we wiſh to know the preſent value of an annuity to be enjoyed by one life,
                for what may happen to remain of it beyond another life, after a given term ; that
                is, provided both lives continue from the preſent time to the end of a given term of
                years ; the method of calculating is this : Find the value of the annuity for two
                lives, greater by the given term of years than the given lives ; diſcount this value
                for the given term; and then multiply by the probability, that the two given lives
                ſhall both continue the given term ; and the product will be the anſwer. Thus, let
                the two lives be each the term ſeven years, the annuity l. 10, intereſt Four <hi
                    rend="italic">per cent.</hi> The given lives, increaſed by ſeven years, become
                each 57. The value of two joint lives, each 37, is (by Table II.) 10.25. The value
                of a ſingle life at 37 is (by the table under the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Annuity)</hi> 13.67. The former ſubtracted from the latter is 3.42, or the
                value of an annuity for the life of a perſon 317 years of age, after another of the
                ſame age, as has been ſhown above. 3.42 dd- counted for ſeven years (that is,
                multiplied by 0.76 the value of 11. due at the end of ſeven years) is 2.6. The
                probability that a ſingle life at 30 ſhall continue ſeven years is <hi
                    rend="superscript">49</hi>∕<hi rend="subscript">56</hi>
                <hi rend="smallcaps">@@(b).</hi> The probability, therefore, that two ſuch lives ſhall
                continue ſeven years, is 2401∕3136, or in decimals 0.765 ; and 2.6 multiplied by
                0.765 is 1.989, the number of years purchaſe which ought to be given for an annuity
                to be enjoyed by a life now 30 years of age, after a life of the same age, provided
                both continue ſeven years. The annuity then being 10 l<hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi>
                its preſent value is 1.19.89.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the value is required of an annuity to be enjoyed for what may happen to
                remain of one life after another, provided the life in expectation continues a given
                time. I. Find the preſent value of the annuity for the remainder of the life in
                expectation after the given time, which is done in this manner : Multiply the
                preſent value of the life at the given time by the preſent value of 1 l. to be
                received at that time, and multiply the product again by the probability that the
                life in expectation will continue ſo long. Let the given time which the life in
                expectation is to continue be 15 years, and let the perſon then be arrived at 50
                years of age. A life at fifty, according to Μ. de Moivre’s valuation of lives, and
                reckoning intereſt at <hi rend="italic">four per cent.</hi> is worth 11.34 years
                purchaſe. The preſent value of 1 l. to be received at the end of 15 years, is
                0.5553, and the probability that a life at 35 will continue 15 years is <hi
                    rend="superscript">146</hi>∕<hi rend="subscript">490</hi>. Theſe three values
                multiplied into one another give L.4.44 for the preſent value ot the life in
                expectation. 2. Find the value of the reverſion, provided both lives continue the
                given time, by the rule given in parag. 5th. 3. Add theſe values together, and the
                ſum will be the anſwer in a ſingle preſent payment. We ſhall now illuſtrate this
                rule by an example.</p>
            <p>An annuity of 10 l. for the life of a person now 30, is to commence at the end of 11
                years, if another perſon now 40 ſhould be then dead ; or, if this ſhould not happen
                at the end of any year beyond 11 years in which the former ſhall happen to survive
                the latter : What is the preſent value of ſuch an annuity, reckoning intereſt at
                four <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi> and taking the probabilities of life as they
                are in Dr Hailey’s table, given in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Mortality
                ?</hi></p>
            <p>The value of 10l. <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> for the remainder of the life of
                a perſon now 30, after 11 years is L. 69.43. The probability that a perſon 40 years
                of age ſhall live 11 years, is, by Dr Halley's table, <hi rend="superscript"
                    >335</hi>∕<hi rend="subscript">445</hi>. The probability, therefore, that he
                will die in 11 years, is ſubtracted from unity @@(C), or which multiplied by
                1.69.43, gives 1. 17.16.—The value of the reverſion, provided both live 11 years, is
                17 l. and this value added to the former, makes l. 34.16. the value required in a
                ſingle preſent paymcnt ; which payment divided by 1. 11.43, the value of two joint
                lives, aged 30 and 40, with unity added, gives 3 l. ; or the value required in
                annual payments during the joint lives, the firſt payment to be made
                immediately.</p>
            <p>@@@(b) The probability that a given life shall continue any number of years, or reach
                a given age, is (as is well known) the fraction, whose numerator is the number of
                the living in any table of observations opposite to the given age, and denominator,
                the number opposite to the present age of the given life.</p>
            <p>@@@(c) For the difference between unity and the fraction expressing the probability
                thta an event will happen, gives the probability that it will not happen.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
