<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>multitude. The czar, however, had thrown every poſſible obſtruction in the way of his antagoniſt. Thirty thousand men were poſted in a defile on the road, to oppoſe his paſſage ; and this corps was ſuſtained by a body of 20,000 others, poſted ſome leagues nearer Narva. The czar himſelf had ſet out to hasten the march of a reinforcement of 40,000 men, with whom he intended to attack the Swedes in flank and rear. But the celerity and valour of the Swedes baffled every endeavour. With 4000 foot and an equal number of horſe the king ſet out, leaving the reſt of the army to follow him at their leiſure. With theſe he attacked and defeated the Russian armies one after another, puſhing his way to the czar’s camp, which he gave immediate orders for attacking. This camp was fortified by lines of circumvallation and contravallation, by redoubts, by 150 pieces of braſs cannon placed in front ; and was defended by an army of 80,000 men : yet ſo violent was the attack of the Swedes, that in three hours the entrenchments were carried ; the king with 4000 men that compoſed the wing he commanded in perſon, purſued a flying army of 50,000 to the river Narva. The bridge broke down by the weight of the fugitives, and the river was inſtantly covered with their bodies. Great numbers returned in deſpair to their camp, where they defended themſelves for a while ; but at laſt the generals Gallowin and Frederowitz, who commanded them, ſurrendered. Thirty thouſand were killed in the intrenchments and in the purſuit, or drowned in the river ; 20,000 ſurrendered at diſcretion, and were diſmissed unarmed ; while the reſt were totally diſperſed. An hundred and fifty pieces of fine cannon, 28 mortars, 151 pair of colours, 20 ſtandards, and all the baggage of the enemy, were taken. Among the priſoners were the duke de Croy, the prince of Georgia, and ſeven other generals. Charles behaved with the greateſt generoſity to the conquered. Being informed that the tradeſmen of Narva had refuſed credit to the officers whom he detained priſoners, he ſent 1000 ducats to the duke of Croy, and to every other officer a proportionable ſum.</p><p>Peter was advancing with 40,000 men to ſurround the Swedes, when he received intelligence of the dreadful defeat at Narva. He was greatly chagrined ; but, comforting himſelf with the hopes that the Swedes would in time teach the Russians to beat them, he returned to his own dominions, where he applied himſelf with the utmoſt diligence to the raising of another army. He evacuated all the provinces which he had invaded, and for a time abandoned all his great projects, thus leaving Charles at liberty to proſecute the war againſt Poland.</p><p>As Auguſtus had expected an attack, he endeavoured to draw the czar into a cloſer alliance with him. The two monarchs had an interview at Birſen, where it was agreed that Auguſtus ſhould lend the czar 50,000 German ſoldiers, to be paid by Muſcovy ; that the czar ſhould ſend an equal number of his troops to be trained up to the art of war in Poland ; and that he ſhould pay the king three millions of rix-dollars in the ſpace of two years. Of this treaty Charles had notice, and by means of his miniſter count Piper entirely fruſtrated the ſcheme.</p><p>In 1701, as early as the ſeaſon permitted, Charles, having received a reinforcement from Sweden, took the field, and appeared ſuddenly on the banks of the Duna, along which the Saxon army was poſted to receive him. The king of Poland at that time being ſick, the army was commanded by Ferdinand duke of Courland, mariſchal Stenau, and general Paykel, all officers of valour and experience. They had fortified certain iſlands in the mouth of the river, and taken every other precaution againſt an attack ; the ſoldiers were hardy, well diſciplined, and nearly equal to the Swedes in number ; yet Charles, having passed the river in boats with high sides, to ſcreen the men from the fire of the enemy, attacked them with ſuch fury, that they were entirely defeated, with the loſs of 2500 killed on the ſpot, and 1500 taken priſoners. All the Saxon baggage, 56 pieces of cannon, five pair of colours, and six ſtandards, fell into the hands of the Swedes.</p><p>This victory was followed by the ſurrrender of all the towns and fortresses in the duchy of Courland. The king then passed into Lithuania, where every town opened its gates to him. At Birſen, an army of 20,000 Russians retired with the utmoſt precipitation on the news of his approach. Here Charles, perceiving that the kingdom of Poland was greatly diſaffected to Auguſtus, began to project the ſcheme of dethroning him by means of his own ſubjects. This ſcheme he executed with more policy than he ever ſhowed on any other occaſion. The manner of putting it in execution was concerted between Radziewischi, cardinal primate of Poland, and count Piper. Intrigues and cabals were held at the houſe of the treacherous eccleſiaſtic, while he was publiſhing circular letters to keep the people in their duty to the king. The diet being filled with Swediſh partions, became tumultuous, and broke up in confusion. The affairs of the kingdom then fell into the hands of the ſenate; but here the Swediſh party was as ſtrong as in the diet. It was agreed that they ſhould ſend an embassy to Charles ; that the poſpolite ſhould mount, and be ready againſt all events ; but the chief regulations reſpected the king’s authority, which it was determined at any rate to retrench. Auguſtus, reſolving rather to receive laws from the victorious Charles than from his own ſubjects, ſent an embassy to him, committing the management of the whole to the counteſs of Konigsrnark, a native of Sweden, and a lady famous for her wit and beauty. But the king refuſed to ſee her; on which ſhe returned, chagrined and diſappointed, to Warſaw. The ambassadors of the ſenate inſtantly obtained an audience ; and were assured by Charles, that he took arms againſt the Saxons in defence of the liberties of the Poles, whom he ſhould always regard as his beſt friends. Conferences were appointed to be held at Kinſchin ; but Charles ſoon after altered his mind, and told the ambaſſadors he would hold them at Warſaw.</p><p>Auguſtus, in the mean time, finding his ſcheme of peace fruſtrated, had recourſe to the ſenate ; but met with ſuch a rough anſwer from them, that he determined once more to apply to Charles. To him therefore he ſent his chamberlain ; but a passport being forgot, the ambaffador was arreſted. Charles continued his march to Warſaw, which ſurrendered on the firſt ſummons ; but the citadel held out for ſome days. Auguſtus, finding at laſt that no dependence was to be had on the Poles, determined to truſt his fortune wholly to the Saxon army and the nobility of the palatinate of Cracow, who offered to ſupport him to the utmoſt of their power. The Saxon army was now advanced to the frontiers, and Auguſtus immediately put himſelf at the head of it. Being joined by the nobility of Cracow, he found his forces to amount to 30,000 men, all brave and well- diſciplined. With theſe he marched in queſt of his enemy; who did not decline the combat, though he had with him only 12,000 men. Though the Saxons were ſtrongly poſted, having their front covered by a morals, besides being fortified with palliſadoes and chevaux de frise, they were attacked with irreſiſtible impetuosity, and entirely defeated, with the loſs of 4000 killed, 2000 made priſoners, and all their baggage and cannon. This victory was followed by the loſs of Cracow : after which Charles ſet out in purſuit of the flying army, with a deſign of preventing them from re- assembling ; but his horſe falling under him, he had the miſ-</p></body></text></TEI>