<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>French under Condé and Turenne made a moſt powerful diverſion, and performed ſuch exploits as immortalized the names of theſe two generals.</p><p>In 1645, the war againſt Denmark was puſhed with ſuch vigour, that a peace, very honourable and advantageous for Sweden, was concluded ; and thus Torſtenſon was again at liberty to act againſt the Imperialiſts. He now took meaſures for carrying the war into the heart of the Auſtrian dominions. Hatfield assembled a conſiderable army to oppoſe the Swedes ; and the emperor came in perſon to Prague to animate his troops. The two armies came in sight at Jancowitz, and both prepared for an engagement. The valour of the Swedes once more prevailed; and they totally defeated their enemies. Four thouſand of the Imperialiſts were killed on the ſpot, among whom were general Hatfield and a great number of officers ; and near 5000 were taken prisoners. No great advantages, however, were derived from this victory. Some towns indeed were reduced ; but at laſt Torſtenson was obliged to retire into Moravia, where he put his army into winter-quarters ; and in the beginning of the year 1646 reſigned the command to Wrangel.</p><p>The new general conducted the Swediſh affairs with great ability and ſucceſs ; till at laſt the Imperialiſts, finding themſelves finally unable to drive the Swedes out of Germany, concluded a peace with them in 1648. This was the memorable treaty of Weſtphalia, by which the Germanic conſtitution was settled upon its ancient principles, and thoſe implacable diſputes which had ſo long torn the empire were ended ; the duchies of Bremen and Verden, all the Upper and part of Lower Pomerania, the city of Wiſmar and the iſle of Rugen, were aſſigned to Sweden, and a gratification of five millions of crowns was given to the army.</p><p>Sweden now enjoyed ſome years oſ repoſe. Charles Guſtavus, count Palatine, having gained the favour of Chriſtina, was appointed generaliſſimo of the forces, and heir-apparent to the crown. A marriage was propoſed between them ; but the queen would never liſten to this or any other propoſal of the kind. In 1650, the ceremony of the queen’s coronation was performed ; but in four years thereafter, ſhe reſigned the crown in favour of Guſtavus. (See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Christina).</hi></p><p>The new king found himſelf involved in conſiderable difficulties on his acceſſion to the throne. The treaſury was quite exhauſted ; great part of the revenue was appointed for the ſupport of Chriſtina’s houſehold ; the people were oppressed with taxes ; and the nation having been diſarmed for ſeveral years, began to loſe its reputation among foreigners. To remedy theſe evils, Charles propoſed to reſume all the crown lands which had been alienated by grants to favourites during the late reign ; to repeal a duty which had been laid upon salt ; to put the kingdom in a poſture oſ defence ; and to enter upon a war with ſome neighbouring ſtate. Under a pretence, therefore, that Caſimir king of Poland had queſtioned his title to the throne, he began to make preparations for invading that kingdom. Several embaſſies were ſent from Poland to Stockholm ; but ſome point of ceremony always diſappointed them of an audience of the king ; ſo that they were obliged to return without their errand. As ſoon as matters were in readinels, General Wittemberg made an irruption into Poland from the side of Pomerania. The Poles oppoſed him with an army of 15,000 men ; but inſtead of fighting, they began to negotiate, and in a ſhort time entirely diſperſed themſelves. Charles himſelf ſoon followed with a powerful army, and purſued his march without obſtruction, all the cities throwing open their gates to him as he approached, and offering to ſupply him with necessaries. As he advanced to Cracow, Caſſimir reſolved to make one effort to save his capital. His army amounted only to 10,000 men ; and theſe were unfortunately ſuch as had never stood fire. After a feeble reſiſtance, they fled with precipitation, having loſt 1000 men killed and taken priſoners. A few days after this Charles deſeated the Poles a ſecond time, about eight leagues from Cracow ; upon which Caſimir fled with his family to Oppelen in Sileſia. The capital was then inverted ; and though defended with the utmoſt valour by Stephen Czarneſki, was in a ſhort time obliged to capitulate. Thus in leſs than three months Charles apparently became maſter of Poland ; but it ſoon became evident that the Poles had no intention of abandoning their former ſovereign.</p><p>In 1656 a war took place with the elector of Brandenburg. While Charles was employed in the conqueſt of Poland, that prince had invaded the Royal and Ducal Prusſia, and reduced the moſt conſiderable towns with little oppoſition. The king of Sweden took umbrage at his progreſs ; and having marched againſt him, deſeated his forces in ſeveral slight encounters, and obliged him to own that he was a vasſal of Sweden. Theſe rapid conqueſts alarmed all Europe ; and the different powers ſought for means of driving the Swedes out of Poland, which they had ſo unexpectedly and unjuſtly ſeized. The Poles were no ſooner aſſured that they ſhould be aſſiſted, than they everywhere revolted and massacred the Swedes. Caſimir returned from Sileſia ; and thoſe very troops and generals who had before ſubmitted to Charles without oppoſition, now ranged themſelves under the banners of his antagoniſt. Charles immediately marched from Pruſſia to chaſtiſe the inſolence of the Poles, and totally defeated a body of 12,000 men under the command of Czarneſki. This did not hinder all the Poles incorporated with his troops to deſert ; which conſiderably reduced his army ; and the campaign being performed in the depth of winter, he was at laſt obliged to retreat to Pruſſia. In his march he was haraſſed by the Poles ; and a body of 4000 Swedes was ſurpriſed and defeated by them at Warka. This loſs, however, was ſoon after recompenſed by a complete victory gained by Adolphus the king’s brother and General Wrangel over Czarneſki. In the mean time the king was taking meaſures for laying ſiege to Dantzic ; but was prevented by the Dutch, who threatened to oppoſe him, unleſs a proper regard was paid to their intereſt. Charles accordingly granted them advantageous terms ; and afterwards gained over the elector of Brandenburg, by ceding to him the ſovereignty of Pruſſia, that he might be at liberty to turn his whole ſtrength againſt Poland.</p><p>By the treaty just concluded with the elector, the latter was to aſſiſt Charles in his war with Poland ; but the elector had ſo procraſtinated matters, that the Poles, having obtained aſſiſtance from the Tartars, had reduced the city of Warſaw. The two princes, however, now marched in concert againſt their enemies, who were encamped in a ſtrong ſituation in the neighbourhood of the city above-mentioned, their camp being fronted by the Viſtula. The Poles were driven from their entrenchments with prodigious slaughter, and a vaſt number taken priſoners. The Poles and Tartars then laboured to break the alliance ; with which view they entered Ducal Pruſſia, and defeated the electoral army, taking prince Radzivil and other perſons of diſtinction priſoners. The Swedes ſoon had their revenge. General Steinbock attacked the ſame Poliſh army at Philippowa, and overthrew it with ſuch ſlaughter as obliged the Poles for that ſeaſon to quit the field. A more formidable enemy than the Poles now began to make them appearance. The Russians invaded the provinces oſ Carelia, Ingermania, and</p></body></text></TEI>