<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>he had repaired ſome time ſince for a nobleman of the name of Ankarſtrom, a captain in the army ; and the cutler who had made the dagger referred at once to the ſame perſon.</p><p>The king languiſhed from the 17th to the 29th of March. At firſt the reports of his medical attendants were favourable ; but on the 28th a mortification was found to have taken place, which terminated his exiſtence in a few hours. On opening his body, a ſquare piece of lead and two ruſty nails were found unextracted within the ribs.</p><p>During his illneſs, and particularly after he was made acquainted with the certainty of his approaching disſolution, Guſtavus continued to diſplay that unſhaken courage which he had manifeſted on every occaſion during his life. A few hours before his deceaſe he made ſome alterations in the arrangement of public affairs. He had before, by his will, appointed a council of regency ; but convinced, by recent experience, how little he could depend on the attachment of his nobles, and being alſo aware of the neceſſity of a ſtrong government in difficult times, he appointed his brother, the duke of Sudermania, ſole regent, till his ſon, who was then about fourteen, ſhall have attained the age of eighteen years. His laſt words were a declaration of pardon to the conspirators againſt his life. The actual murderer alone was excepted ; and he was excepted only at the ſtrong inſtance of the regent, and thoſe who ſurrounded his majeſty in his dying moments. Immediately on the death of the king, the young prince was proclaimed by the title of Guſtavus IV.</p><p>Ankarſtrom was no ſooner apprehended, than he confessed with an air of triumph, that he was the perſon “ who had endeavoured to liberate his country from a monſter and a tyrant ” Suſpicions at the ſame time fell on the counts Horn and Ribbing, baron Pechlin, baron Ehrenſvard, baron Hartſmandorf, Von Engerſtrom the royal ſecretary, and others ; and theſe ſuſpicions were confirmed by the confeſſion of Ankarſtrom. After a very fair and ample trial, this man was condemned to be publicly and ſeverely whipped on three ſucceſſive days, his right hand and his head to be cut off, and his body impaled ; which ſentence he suffered not till the 17th of May, long after the death of the king. —His property was given to his children, who, however, were compelled to change their name.</p><p>The counts Horn and Ribbing were condemned to loſe their right hands, and to be decapitated. Col. Liljehorn and lieutenant Ehrenjwerd were alſo to be beheaded.— All theſe conſpirators were degraded from the rank of nobles, and their property declared to be confiscated. Major Hartmanſdorf was to forfeit his rank in the army, and to be imprisoned for one year. Engerſtrom was to ſuffer perpetual impriſonment, and baron Pechlin and ſecretary Lilleſtrahle to be impriſoned during pleaſure. Four others, accuſed of being concerned in the conſpiracy, were pardoned, and ſome were acquitted.</p><p>The kingdom of Sweden, in its preſent ſtate, is divided into the following provinces: 1. Sweden Proper. <hi rend="italic">2.</hi> Gothland. 3. Finland. 4. Swediſh Lapland. And, 5. The Swediſh iſlands. Great abatements muſt be made for the lakes and unimproved parts of Sweden, which are ſo extenſive that the habitable part is confined to narrow bounds.</p><p>The face of Sweden is pretty ſimilar to thoſe of its neighbouring countries ; only it has the advantage of navigable rivers.</p><p>The ſame may be ſaid with regard to its climate, ſoil, &amp;c. Summer burſts from winter ; and vegetation is more ſpeedy than in ſouthern climates. Stoves and warm furs mitigate the cold of winter, which is ſo intenſe, that the noſes and extremities of the inhabitants are ſometimes mortified. The Swedes, ſince the days of Charles XII. have been at incredible pains to correct the native barrenneſs of their country, by erecting colleges of agriculture, and in ſome places with great ſucceſs. The ſoil is much the ſame with that of Denmark and ſome parts of Norway, generally very bad, but in ſome valleys ſurprisingly fertile. The Swedes, till of late years, had not induſtry ſufficient to remedy the one, nor improve the other. The peaſants now follow the agriculture of France and England ; and ſome late accounts ſay, that they rear almoſt as much grain as maintains the natives. Gothland produces wheat, rye, barley, oats, pease, and beans ; and in caſe of deficiency, the people are ſupplied from Livonia and the Baltic provinces. In ſummer, the fields are verdant, and covered with flowers ; and produce ſtrawberries, raſpberries, currants, and other ſmall fruits, The common people know, as yet, little of the cultivation of apricots, peaches, nectarines, pine-apples, and the like high-flavoured fruits ; but melons are brought to great perfection in dry seasons.</p><p>Sweden produces cryſtals, amethyſts, topazes, porphyry, lapis lazuli, agate, cornelian, marble, and other fossils. The chief wealth of the country, however, arises from her mines of ſilver, copper, lead, and iron. The laſt-mentioned metal employs no fewer than 450 forges, hammeringmills, and ſmehing-houſes. A kind of a gold mine has likewiſe been diſcovered in Sweden ; but ſo inconſiderable, that from the year 1741 to 1747, it produced only 2398 gold ducats, each valued at 9s. 4d. ſterling. The firſt gallery of one ſilver mine is 100 fathoms below the ſurface of the earth ; the roof is ſupported by prodigious oaken beams, and from thence the miners deſcend about 40 fathoms to the loweſt vein. This mine is ſaid to produce 20,000 crowns a-year. The product of the copper mines is uncertain ; but the whole is loaded with vaſt taxes and reductions to the government, which has no other reſources for the exigences of ſtate. Thoſe ſubterraneous manſions are aſtoniſhingly ſpacious, and at the ſame time commodious for their inhabitants, ſo that they ſeem to form a hidden world. The water-falls in Sweden afford excellent conveniency for turning mills for forges ; and for ſome years the exports of iron from Sweden brought in 300,000 l. ſterling. Dr Buſching thinks that they conſtituted two-thirds of the national revenue. It muſt, however, be obſerved, that the extortions of the Swediſh government, and the importation of American bar-iron into Europe, and ſome other cauſes, have greatly diminiſhed this manufacture in Sweden ; ſo that the Swedes very soon muſt apply themſelves to other branches of trade and improvements, eſpecially in agriculture.</p><p>The animals differ little from thoſe of Norway and Denmark, only the Swediſh horſe are known to be more ſerviceable in war than the German. The fiſhes found in the rivers and lakes oſ Sweden are the ſame with thoſe in other northern countries, and taken in such quantities, that their pikes (particularly) are ſalted and pickled for exportation. The train-oil of the ſeals, taken in the gulph of Finland, is a conſiderable article of exportation.</p><p>There is a great diverſity of characters among the people of Sweden ; and what is peculiarly remarkable among them, they have been known to have different characters in different ages. At preſent, their peaſants ſeem to be a heavy plodding race of men, ſtrong and hardy ; but without any other ambition than that of ſubſiſting themſelves and their families as well as they can : they are honeſt, ſimple, and hoſpitable ; and the mercantile claſſes are much of the ſame caſt ; but great application and perseverance is diſcovered among them all. One could form no idea that the modern Swedes are the deſcendants of those who, under Guſtavus Adolphus and Charles XII. carried terror in their</p></body></text></TEI>