<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>according to the number of farms it contains; every farm of 60 l. or 70 l. <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi> is charged with a foot-ſoldier, furniſhing him with diet, lodging, and ordinary clothes, and about 20s. a-year in money ; or else a little wooden houſe is built him by the farmer, who allows him hay and paſturage for a cow, and ploughs and ſows land enough to ſupply him with bread. When embodied, they are ſubject to military law, but otherwiſe to the civil law of the country. It may therefore literally be laid, that every Swediſh soldier has a property in the country he defends. This national army is thought to amount to above 50,000 men. Sweden formerly could have fitted out 40 ſhips of the line.</p><p>SWEDENBORG (Emanuel), was born at Stockholm on the 29th of January 1689. His father was biſhop of Weſt-Cothia ; member of a ſociety for the propagation of the goſpel, formed on the plan of that of England ; and preſident of the Swediſh church in Pennſylvania and London. To this laſt office he was appointed by Charles XII. who ſeems to have had a great regard for the biſhop, and to have continued that regard to his ſon.</p><p>Of the courſe of young Swedenborg’s education we have procured no account ; but from the character of the father, it may be ſuppoſed to have been pious ; and by his appearing with reputation as an author, when but 20 years of age, it is proved to have been succesful.∙ His firſt work was publiſhed in 1709 ; and the year following he sent into the world a collection of pieces on different ſubjects, in Latin verſe, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Ludus Heliconius, live Carolina Miscellanea quae variis in locis cecinit.</hi> The ſame year he began his travels, firſt into England, and afterwards into Holland, France, and Germany ; and returning to Stockholm in 1714, he was two years afterwards appointed to the office of assessor in the Metallic College by Charles XII. who honoured him with frequent conversations, and bestowed upon him a large ſhare of his favour. At this period of his life Swedenborg devoted his attention principally to phyſic and mathematical ſtudies ; and in 1718 he accompanied the king to the liege of Frederickſhall, where he gave an eminent proof that he had not ſtudied in vain. Charles could not send his heavy artillery to Frederickſhall from the badneſs of the roads, which were then rendered much worſe than uſual by being deeply covered with ſnow. In this extremity Swedenborg brought the ſciences to the aid of valour. By the help of proper inſtruments he cut through the mountains, and raised the valleys which ſeparated Sweden from Norway, and then ſent to his master two galleys, five large boats, and a ſloop, loaded with battering pieces, to be employed in the siege. The length of this canal was about two miles and a half. The execution of this great work, however, did not occupy all his time. In 1716 he had begun to publiſh essays and obſervations on the mathematical and phyſical ſciences, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Daedalus Hyperboreus;</hi> and he found leisure during the siege to complete his intended collection, and alſo in the same year to publiſh an introduction to algebra, under the whimſical title of <hi rend="italic">The Art of the Rules.</hi></p><p>At the siege of Frederickſhall he lost his patron Charles; but found another in Ulrica Eleonora, the sister and ſuccesſor of that hero, by whom in 1719 he was ennobled, and took of courſe his ſeat among the ſenators of the equeſtrian order in the triennial aſſemblies of the ſtates. His promotion did not leſſen his ardour for the ſciences ; for he publiſhed in the ſame year <hi rend="italic">A Method to fix the Value of Money, and to determine the Swedish Meaſures in ſuch a way as to ſuppreſs all the Fractions and facilitate the Calculations.</hi> About the ſame time he gave the public a treatiſe on <hi rend="italic">the Position</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">and Courſe of the Planets ;</hi> with another on <hi rend="italic">the Height of the Tides, and Flux and Reflux of the Sea ;</hi> which, from information gathered in different parts of Sweden, appeared to have been greater formerly than when he wrote.</p><p>As Swedenborg continued, under the new ſovereign, to hold the office of aſſeſſor to the Metallic College, he thought it neceſſary, for the diſcharge of his duty, to make a ſecond journey into foreign countries, that he might himſelf examine their mines, particularly thoſe of Saxony and Harts. During theſe travels, which were undertaken for the improvement of the manufactures of his native country, he printed at Amſterdam@@, 1. <hi rend="italic">Prodromus principiorum Naturalium, five novorum tentaminum, Chemiam et Physicam experimentalem geometrice explicandi.</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">Nova observata &amp; inventa circa Ferrum &amp; Ignem, praecipue naturam Ignis Elementarum, una cum nova Camini inventione.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">Methodus nova inveniendi Longitudines locorum terrae marique ope Lunae.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Modus construendi receptacula navalia, vulgo en Suedois, Dockybynadder.</hi> 5. <hi rend="italic">Nova constructio aggeris aquotici.</hi> 6. <hi rend="italic">Modus explorandi virtutes Navigiorum.</hi> And at Leipſic and Hamburg, 7. <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea observata circa res naturales, praesertim Mineralia, Ignem, &amp; Montium stratae.</hi></p><p>This journey was made, and theſe tracts publiſhed, in the compaſs of a year and a half ; and perhaps there has not been another man, Linnæus excepted, who has done ſo much in ſo ſhort a time. After his return in 1722, Swedenborg divided his time ſo equally between the duties of his office and his private ſtudies, that in 1733 he finiſhed his grand work, entitled <hi rend="italic">Opera Philosophica &amp; Mineralia,</hi> and had it printed under his own direction in 1734, part at Dreſden and part at Leipſic ; in which year he alſo went to inspect the mines of Auſtria and Hungary. This work is divided into three volumes folio ; the title of the firſt is <hi rend="italic">Principia rerum Naturalium sive novorum tentaminum, Phaenomena Mundi elementares philosophice explicandi.</hi> The ſecond, <hi rend="italic">Regnum subterraneum sive Minerale de Ferro ;</hi> and the third, <hi rend="italic">Regnum subterrameum sive Minerale de Cupro, &amp; Orichalco ;</hi> all of them written with great ſtrength of judgment, and ornamented with plates, to facilitate the comprehenſion of the text.</p><p>In the year 1729 he was enrolled among the members of the Society of Sciences at Upſal, and was, probably about the ſame time, made a Fellow of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Stockholm ; nor were ſtrangers leſs willing than his own countrymen to acknowledge the greatneſs of his merit. Wolfius, with many other learned foreigners, were eager to court his correspondence. The Academy of St Petersburg ſent him, on the 17th of December 1734, diploma of aſſociation as a correspondent member ; and ſoon afterwards the editors of the <hi rend="italic">Acta Eruditorum</hi> at Leipſic found in his works a valuabſe ſupplement to their own collection.</p><p>By many persons the approbation of learned academies would have been highly valued ; but by Baron Swedenborg it was conſidered as of very little importance. “ Whatever of wordly honour and advantage may appear to be it the things before mentioned, I hold them (ſays he@@) but as matters of low eſtimation, when compared to the honour of that holy office to which the Lord himſelf hath called me, who was graciouſly pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf to me, his unworthy servant, in a personal appearance, in the year 1743, to open in me a sight of the spiritual world, and to enable me to converſe with ſpirits and angels ; and this privilege has continued with me to this day. From that time I began to print and publiſh various unknown <hi rend="italic">Arcana,</hi> which have been either ſeen by me or revealed to me, concerning heaven and hell, the ſtate of men after death, the true wor-</p><p>@@@[mu] European Magazine, 1787, July.</p><p>@@@[m] Short Account of the Honourable E. Swedenborg.</p></body></text></TEI>