<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the dogs to run near, and often ſtop to repel them. During the day, he commonly remains in his soil, which is in the moſt ſequeſtrated part of the woods. He comes out in the night in quest of food. In ſummer, when the grain is ripe, it is eaſy to ſurpriſe him among the cultivated fields, which he frequents every night. As ſoon as he is ſlain, the hunters cut off his teſticles, the odour of which is ſo ſtrong, that in a few hours it would infect the whole fleſh. The ſnout of an old boar is the only part that is eſteemed ; but every part of the caſtrated and young boar, not exceeding one year fed, makes delicate eating. The pork of the domeſtic boar is ſtill worſe than that of the wild boar ; and it can only be rendered fit for eating by caſtration and fattening. The ancients caſtrated the young boars which they could carry off from their mothers, and returned them to the woods, where they grew fat, and their pork was much better than that of domeſtic hogs. There are several varieties of the common hog.</p><p>2. The ae<hi rend="italic">thiopicus,</hi> or Ethiopian hog, with ſmall tuſks in the lower jaw, very large ones in the upper, in old boars bending towards the forehead in form of a ſemicircle : no fore teeth : noſe broad, depressed, and almoſt of a horny hardneſs : head very large and broad : beneath each eye a hollow, formed of looſe ſkin, very ſoft and wrinkled ; under theſe a great lobe or wattle, lying almoſt horizontal, broad, flat, and rounded at the end, placed ſo as to intercept the view of any thing below from the animal. Between theſe and the mouth on each side, there is a hard callous protuberance. The mouth is ſmall: ſkin duſky : briſtles diſposed in faſciculi, of about five each ; longeſt between the ears and on the beginning of the back, thinly diſperſed on the reſt of the back. Ears large and ſharp pointed, inside lined with long whitiſh hairs : tail ſlender and flat, not reaching lower than the thighs, and is covered with hairs diſpoſed in ſaſciculi. Body longer, and legs ſhorter, than in the common swine : its whole length 4 feet 9 inches ; height before. 2 feet 2 inches: but in a wild ſtate, it grows to an enormous ſize.—Theſe animals inhabit the hotteſt parts of Africa, from Senegal to Congo, alſo the iſland of Madagaſcar. We know little of their nature ; but they are repreſented as very fierce and ſwift, and that they will not breed with the domeſtic ſow.</p><p>3. The tajassu, pecary, or Mexican hog, with four cutting teeth above, and six below: two tuſks in each jaw ; thoſe in the upper jaw pointing down, and little apparent when the mouth is ſhut ; the others hid : length from noſe to the end of the rump about three feet : head not ſo taper as in common ſwine : ears ſhort and erect : body covered with briſtles, ſtronger than thoſe of the European kind, and more like thoſe of a hedge-hog ; they are duſky, ſurrounded with rings of white ; thoſe on the top of the neck and back are near five inches long, grow ſhorter on the sides; the belly almoſt naked ; from the ſhoulders to the breaſt is a band of white : no tail : on the lower part of the back is a gland, open at the top, diſcharging a fetid ichorous liquor; this has been by miſtake called a <hi rend="italic">navel.—</hi>Inhabits the hotteſt parts of South America, and ſome of the Antilles : lives in the foreſts on the mountains : not fond of mire or marſhy places : leſs fat than the common hog. Theſe animals go in great droves. They are very fierce, and will fight ſtoutly with the beaſts of prey : the jaguar, or American leopard, is their mortal enemy ; often the body of that animal is found with ſeveral of these hogs ſlain in combat. Dogs will scarce attack this animal : if wounded, it will turn on the hunters. They feed on fruits and roots ; alſo on toads and all manner of ſerpents, which they hold with their fore-feet, and ſkin with great dexterity. The fleſh is reckoned very good food ; but all writers agree that the dorſal gland muſt be cut out as ſoon as the animal is killed, or the fleſh will become ſo infected as not to be eatable. The Indian name oſ this ſpecies is <hi rend="italic">paquiras,</hi> from whence ſeems to be derived that of p<hi rend="italic">ecary.</hi> There are more varieties of this species, the <hi rend="italic">tajaſſu minor</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">patera.</hi></p><p>4. The <hi rend="italic">babyrussa,</hi> or Indian hog, with four cutting teeth in the upper, six in the lower jaw ; ten grinders to each jaw ; in the lower jaw two tuſks pointing towards the eyes, and ſtanding near eight inches out of their ſockets; from two ſockets on the outſide of the upper jaw two other teeth, twelve inches long, bending like horns, their ends almoſt touching the forehead: ears ſmall, erect, ſharp pointed : along the back are ſome weak briſtles ; on the reſt of the body only a sort of wool, ſuch as is on the lambs : the tail long, ends in a tuft, and is often twiſted : the body plump and ſquare. Inhabits Buero, a small iſle near Amboina : it is alſo found in Celebes, but neither on the continent of Aſia or Africa; what M. de Buffon takes for it is the Ethiopian boar. They are ſometimes kept tame in the Indian iſles : live in herds: have a very quick ſcent : feed on herbs and leaves of trees ; never ravage gardens like other ſwine : their fleſh well tasted. When purſued and driven to extremities, they ruſh into the ſea, ſwim very well, and even dive, and paſs thus front iſle to iſle. In the foreſts they often reſt their heads, by hooking their upper tuſks on ſome bough. The tuſks, from their form, are useleſs in fight.</p><p>SUSA, the ancient royal reſidence of the kings of Persia, built by Darius Hyſtaſpis, according to Pliny ; though he probably only reſtored it, being a very ancient city, founded by Tithonus father of Memnon. It was in compaſs 120 ſtadia, of an oblong quadrangular form, with a citadel called <hi rend="italic">Memnοneum.</hi> In ſcripture it is called <hi rend="italic">Suſan, </hi>the royal citadel, from the great number of lilies growing in that diſtrict (Athenaeus) ; situate on the river Uhlai, or Eulæus (Daniel) : and the Spaniards call at this day a lily <hi rend="italic">aſuſena</hi> (Pinedo). Suſa was the winter, as Ecbatana was the ſummer, reſidence of the kings of Persia, (Xenophon, Strabo, Plutarch). Here the kings kept their treaſure, (Herodotus.) Now called <hi rend="italic">Tuster.</hi></p><p>SUSPENSION, in Scots law. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Law,</hi> n⁰ clxxxv. 5, 6, and 7.</p><p>SUSSEX, a county of England, deriving its name from its ſituation in reſpect of the other Saxons, and called <hi rend="italic">Sussex, i. e.</hi> the country of the South Saxons, has Hampſhire on the west, the Britiſh channel on the south, Surry on the north, and Kent on the eaſt. Its length is 65 miles, its breadth 30, and its circumference 170. It is divided into 6 rapes, and theſe into 65 hundreds, in which are 342 pariſhes, of which 123 are vicarages, one city, 16 market-towns, 1,140,000 acres, and about 120,000 souls. It has few good ports, though it lies along the channel for 65 miles, which is its greateſt length, the coaſt being encumbered in many places with rocks ; and where it is more open, ſuch quantities of sand are thrown upon it by the ſouth-weſt winds, and the harbours ſo choaked up, that they will not admit vessels of any great draught or burden. The county is well watered by the rivers Arun, Adar, Ouſe, Rother, Lavant, Cuckmeer, Aſhburn, and Aften, by which it is well supplied with fiſh, as well as from the ſea. Hence different places of the county are famed for different sorts of fiſh, as the Arun for mullets, which enter it from the ſea in ſummer in shoals, and by feeding upon a particular kind of herb become extremely delicious : Chi- cheſter for lobſters, Selſey for cockles, Amberley for trout, Pulborough for eels, Rye for herrings, and the county in</p></body></text></TEI>