<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>liberal and enlightened patron of learning and ſcience, and laboured ſtrenuouſly to introduce into his kingdom the moſt valuable improvements in agriculture that had been made in foreign countries.</p><p>But while thus active in promoting the arts of peace, he was not inattentive to thoſe of war. The fleet, which he found decayed and feeble, he in a few years reſtored to a reſpectable footing, and, beſides changing the regulations of the navy, he raiſed a new corps of ſailors, and formed them to the ſervice by continual exerciſe. The army, which, as well as the navy, had been neglected during the ariſtocracy, was next to be reformed. The king began by giving cloaks, tents, and new arms to all the regiments. Afterwards, under the direction of Field Marſhal Count de Heſſenſtein, a new exerciſe was introduced, and ſeveral camps were formed, in which the ſoldiery were manoeuvred by the king himſelf. The ſale of military offices, which had been permitted for many years, was entirely ſuppreſſed ; and the king provided not only for the re-eſtabliſhment of discipline and good order in the army, but for the future welfare of the individuals which compoſed it. Theſe warlike preparations were neceſſary to a plan which he had formed for entirely aboliſhing the power of the ariſtocracy, and freeing Sweden from the factions which had long been formed in it by the court of St Peterſburgh. The change which he had introduced into the conſtitution was very inimical to the intrigues of that court ; and the Russian ambassador exerted himſelf openly to bring about a rupture between the king and the diſcontented nobles. Guſtavus ordered him to quit the kingdom in eight days, and immediately prepared for war with Ruſſia. To this apparently raſh enterpriſe he was incited by the Ottoman Porte, at that time unable to oppoſe the armies of the two empires ; and his own ambition, together with the internal ſtate of his kingdom, powerfully concurred to make him lend every aſſiſtance to his ancient ally. It is needleſs for us to enter into a detail of the particulars oſ that war, which, as well as the aſtoniſhing activity and military ſkill displayed by the Swediſh monarch, are freſh in the memory of all our readers. Suffice it to ſay, that neither Guſtavus Adolphus nor Charles XII. gave greater proofs of undaunted courage and military conduct in their long and bloody wars than were given by Guſtavus the III. from the end oſ the year 1787 to 1790, when peace was reſtored between the courts of St Peterſburgh and Stockholm. Had his army remained faithful, it ſeems in a high degree probable that he would have penetrated to the metropolis of the Russian empire in the firſt campaign ; and when he was deſerted by that army, and his councils distracted by new hoſtilities commenced againſt him by the Danes, the vigour and reſources of his mind never forſook him. When the court of Copenhagen was compelled, by the means of England and Pruſſia, to withdraw its troops from the territories of Sweden, the king attacked Ruſſia with ſuch vigour both by ſea and land, diſplayed ſuch addreſs in retrieving his affairs when apparently reduced to the laſt extremity, and renewed his attacks with ſuch pertinacious courage, that the empreſs lowered the haughtiness of her tone, and was glad to treat with Guſtavus as an equal and independent ſovereign.</p><p>The king of Sweden was now at liberty to cheriſh again the arts of peace, and to humble the haughty ſpirit of the nobles. For his attempting to deprive thole men of that power which they had for many years employed againſt their country, he has been held up to the world as a deſpot who trampled on the liberties of his ſubjects ; as a man without ſincerity or patriotiſm ; and, in one word, as a perjured tyrant, who overthrew the conſtitution which he had ſworn to maintain. That he was not troubled with a ſcrupulous</p><p>conſcience, when ſo artfully conducting the revolution of 1772, muſt be acknowleged ; nor can it be denied, that in his treaties with other powers he ſometimes endeavoured to overreach them : but if the neceſſities of ſtate could in any caſe be an apology for falſehood, they would ſufficiently apologize for the duplicity of Guſtavus. He was engaged in the arduous enterpriſe of freeing his ſubjects from an ariſtocratic tyranny ſupported by a foreign power the moſt formidable in the north ; he had been forced into a war with that power, and, as there is reaſon to believe, promiſed aſſiſtance which he never received ; and it cannot excite wonder nor great indignation, that, as ſoon as he could make an honourable peace, he embraced the opportunity without paying much regard to the intereſts of an alliance, which tamely looked on while he was ſtruggling with difficulties apparently unſurmountable. That the revolution which he effected in his own country was calculated to promote the general good of the people, is unqueſtionable ; and to gain ſuch an object he might ſurely reſtore the crown to its ancient ſplendor, without bringing upon his government the odious epithet of <hi rend="italic">deſpotiſm.</hi></p><p>The nobles, however, continued diſcontented, and a conſpiracy was planned againſt Guſtavus under his own roof. He had entered into the alliance that was formed againſt the revolutionary government of France ; and to raiſe an army which he was to lead in perſon to cooperate with the emperor and the king of Pruſſia, he was obliged to negotiate large loans, and to impoſe upon his ſubjects heavy taxes. The nobles took advantage of that circumstance to prejudice the minds of many of the people againſt the ſovereign who had laboured ſo long for their real good. On the 16th of March 1792, he received an anonymous letter, warning him of his immediate danger from a plot that was laid to take away his life, requeſting him to remain at home, and avoid balls for a year ; and assuring him that, if he ſhould go to the maſquerade for which he was preparing, he would be aſsaſſinated that very night. The king read the note with contempt, and at a late hour entered the ball room. Alter ſome time he ſat down in a box with the compte D’Eſſen, and observed that he was not deceived in his contempt for the letter, ſince had there been any deſign againſt his life, no time could be more favourable than that moment. He then mingled, without apprehenſion, among the crowd ; and juſt as he was preparing to retire in company with the Pruſſian ambaſſador, he was ſurrounded by ſeveral perſons in maſks, one of whom tired a piſtol at the back of the king, and lodged the contents in his body. A ſcene of dreadful confuſion immediately enſued. The conſpirators, amidſt the general tumult and alarm, had time to retire to other parts of the room ; but one of them had previouſly dropped his piſtols and a dagger cloſe by the wounded king. A general order was given to all the company to unmaſk, and the doors were immediately cloſed ; but no perſon appeared with any particular diſtinguiſhing marks of guilt. The king was immediately conveyed to his apartment ; and the surgeon, after extracting a ball and dome ſlugs, gave favourable hopes of his majeſty’s recovery.</p><p>Suſpicions immediately fell upon such of the nobles as had been notorious for their oppoſition to the meaſures of the court. The anonymous letter was traced up to colonel Liljehorn, major in the king’s guards, and he was immediately apprehended. But the moſt ſucceſsful clue that ſeemed to offer was in conſequence of the weapons which had fallen from the aſſaſſin. An order was iſſued, directing all the armourers, guriſmiths, and cutlets in Stockholm, to give every information in their power to the officers of juſtice concerning the weapons. A gunſmith who had repaired the piſtols readily recognized them to be the same which</p></body></text></TEI>