<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by the governor, the greateſt tokens of joy were ſhown all over the town. In the midſt of the tumult Charles went to bed. He had been booted for 16 days, and now his legs were swelled to ſuch a degree that it was necessary to cut his boots off. Having slept for ſome hours, he aroſe, reviewed his troops, and gave orders !or renewing the war with redoubled vigour.</p><p>Sweden was now in the greateſt diſtreſs. We have already mentioned, that on the news oſ the defeat at Pultowa, the Danes had invaded Schonen, but were defeated by General Steenboek. This victory, however, did not put an end to the war. On the contrary, the kings of Denmark and Poland, with the czar of Muſcovy, entered into ſtricter bonds of amity than ever. They dreaded the return of Charles to his own dominions, and apprehended that numberless victories would ſoon efface the remembrance oſ Pultowa. They determined, therefore, to make the beſt uſe of their time ; and perhaps Charles never took a more imprudent reſolution than obſtinately to remain ſo long in the Turkiſh dominions. The kings of Denmark and Poland invaded Pomerania ; but after laying ſiege in vain to Stralſund, Wismar, and other places, they were obliged to retire with disgrace into winter-quarters. In 1712, the king of Denmark invaded and reduced Bremen and Verden ; but the ſame year met with a terrible defeat from Steenboek,∙ with the loss of a vast number killed and wounded, and almoſt all them artillery taken. The following year, however, this general being purſued, and ſurrounded by the united forces of the Russians, Danes, and Saxons, was obliged to throw himſelf into the neutral town of Tommingen ; where he was beſieged, and obliged to surrender at diſcretion, with his whole army. The conſequence of this diſaſter was an invaſion of Finland by the czar; which province he totally reduced, after defeating the Swedes in ſeveral engagements. Indeed, the Swediſh forces were now ſo much reduced, that they were unable to cope with almoſt any enemy. The return of Charles, however, ſeemed to give new life to the whole nation. Though the number of inhabitants was viſibly diminished, the levies he had ordered were completed in a few weeks : but the bands left to cultivate the earth consiſted oſ the infirm, aged, and decrepid ; so that a famine was threatened in conſequence of the military rage which had ſeized all the youth of the kingdom.</p><p>The presence of Charles did not now produce thoſe conſequences which the allies had feared. The kingdom was too much reduced to be able to furniſh the necessary ſupplies of men and money; and though the king’s courage and military ſkill were not in the leaſt diminished, the efforts he made, inſtead of restoring Sweden to its ſplendour, lerved entirely to ruin it. In 1715, Pruſſia declared againſt him, on account of his demanding back the town of Stetin, which that monarch had ſeized. To complete his embarrassment, the elector of Hanover, George I. of Britain, al- ſo became his enemy. The forces of Denmark, Pruſſia, Saxony, and Hanover, joined to inveſt Wiſmar, while a body of 36,000 men formed the ſiege of Stralsund ; at the ſame time that the czar, with a fleet of 20 large ſhips of war, and 150 tranſports, carrying 30,000 men, threw every part of the Swediſh coaſt into the greateſt conſternation. The heroiſm of Charles could not prevail againſt io many enemies ; yet he was ſtill ſo dreadful, that the prince of Anhalt, with 12,000 brave troops, did not think himſelf a match for this furious enemy when at the head of only 2000, till he had entrenched his army behind a ditch, defended by chevaux de frize. It appeared, indeed, that his precaution was not unnecessary ; for in the night Charles with his men clambered up the ditch, and attacked the enemy in his usual manner. Numbers, however, at laſt prevailed ; and Charles was obliged to retire, after having ſeen his favourite Grothuſen, General Dardorff and During, the companions of his exile, killed by his ſide, he himſelf being wounded in the breaſt.</p><p>This raſh attempt was made in order to save Rugen, from whence the town of Stralſund was ſupplied with pro- visions. The place was well fortified, and garrisoned with 9000 men, with Charles himſelf at their head ; but nothing could reſiſt the efforts of the enemy. The houſes were laid in aſhes by the bombs ; the walls miserably ſhattered, and large breaches made in them by the cannon ; ſo that by the 1 7th of December it was propoſed to give the assault. The attack on the horn-work was deſperate : the enemy was twice reptulſed ; but at laſt, by dint of numbers, effected a lodgment. The next day Charles headed a ſally, in which he dealt terrible deſtruction among the beiiegers, but was at length overpowered and obliged to retreat into the town. At laſt his officers, apprehending that he muſt either fall into the hands of the enemy, or be buried in the ruins of the place, intreated him to retire. A retreat, however, was now almoſt as dangerous as to remain in the town, on account of the fleets of the enemy with which the ſea was covered ; and it is thought this very circumſtance induced the king to conſent to it. Setting out, therefore, in a ſmall boat with fails and oars, he palled all the enemy’s ſhips and batteries, and arrived ſafe at Yſtedt in Schonen.</p><p>To revenge himſelf for theſe losses, Charles invaded Norway with an army of 25,000 men. The Danes were every where defeated and purſued with that vigour for which the king of Sweden was so remarkable ; but ſtrong reinforcements arriving from Denmark, and proviſions failing, he was at laſt obliged to retire, and evacuate the country. Soon alter this the Swedes loſt Wiſmar ; but when every thing ſeemed to go to wreck, Baron Goertz the chief miniſter and favourite of Charles found means to ſet on foot a treaty with the czar of Moſcovy, by which the moſt formidable of all Charles’s enemies was taken off. The miniſter found means to work upon the inflexible and ſtubborn temper of Charles, by repreſenting to him that the cession of certain provinces to Peter would induce him to assiſt him in his projects of again dethroning Auguſtus, and of replacing James on the throne of Britain ; which laſt ſcheme he had projected out of revenge for the elector of Hanover having seized on the duchies of Bremen and Verden. In conſequence of the conferences between the czar and Goertz, the former engaged to lend into Poland an army of 80,000 men, in order to dethrone that prince whom he had so long defended. He engaged alio to furniſh ſhips for tranſporting 30,000 Swedes to Germany and 10,000 into Denmark. This treaty, however, was not fully ratified ; and the king’s death, which happened in 1718, put a final ſtop to all the great proſpects of Sweden.</p><p>The king had reſolved on the conqueſt of Norway before he dethroned Auguſtus ; and as no difficulties ever deterred him, he marched his army into that cold and barren country in the month of October, when the ground wascover- ed with froſt and snow. With 18,000 men he formed the ſiege of Frederickſhall, though the ſeverity of the froſt rendered it almoſt impoſſible to break ground. Charles, however,  reſolved to form trenches ; and his ſoldiers cheerfully obeyed, digging into the ground with the ſame labour as if they had been piercing a rock. On the 11th of December the king visited the trenches in the midſt of a terrible fire from the enemy, imagining that his men might be animated by his presence. He took his poſt in the moſt dangerous ſtation he could chooſe, ſtanding upon a gabion and leaning  with his arm over the parapet, while the enemy were firing chain ſhot at the very ſpot where he ſtood. He was in </p></body></text></TEI>