<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>effecting it. Having one day mounted his horſe, under pretence of hunting as uſual in the foreſt, when he got at a proper diſtance, he changed his dreſs to the habit of a peasant ; and quitting his horſe, he travelled for two days on foot through by-paths, and over mountains almoſt impaſſable, arriving on the third at Flenſburgh. Here no one was admitted without a paſſport ; and Guſtavus dreaded preſenting himſelf to the governor or the officer upon guard, for fear of being diſcovered. Happily for him, it chanced to be on that ſeaſon of the year when the merchants of Lower Saxony drove a conſiderable trade in cattle, which they purchaſe in Jutland. Guſtavus hired himſelf to one of theſe merchants ; and under favour of his diſguiſe eſcaped out of the Daniſh territories, and arrived at Lubec.</p><p>Banner was no ſooner acquainted with his eſcape, than he ſet out after him with the utmoſt diligence, found him at Lubec, and reproached him with great warmth as ungrateful and treacherous ; but he was ſoon appeaſed by the arguments urged by Guſtavus, and eſpecially by the promiſe he made of indemnifying him in the loſs of his ranſom. Upon this Banner returned, giving out that he could not find his priſoner. Chriſtian was enraged at his eſcape, apprehending that he might reverſe all his deſigns in Sweden ; and gave orders to Otho his general to make the stricteſt ſearch, and leave no means untried to arreſt him. Guſtavus applied to the regency for a ſhip to convey him to Sweden, where he hoped he ſhould be able to form a party againſt the Danes. He likewiſe endeavoured to draw the regency of Lubec into his meaſures ; and reaſoned with ſo much zeal and ability, that Nicholas Gemins, firſt conſul, was entirely gained ; but the regency could never be prevailed on to declare for a party without friends, arms, money, or credit. However, before his departure, the conſul gave him aſſurances, that if he could raiſe a force sufficient to make head againſt the enemy in the field, he might depend on the ſervices of the republic, and that the regency would immediately declare for him. Guſtavus deſired to be landed at Stockholm ; but the captain of the ſhip, either having ſecret orders to the contrary, or buſineſs elſewhere, ſteered a different courſe, and put him on ſhore near Calmar ; a city hitherto garriſoned by the troops of Chriſtina widow of the regent. In truth, the governor held this place for his own purpoſes, and only waited to make the beſt terms he could with the Danes. When Guſtavus arrived, he made himſelf known to him and the principal officers of the garriſon, who were moſtly Germans, and his fellow-soldiers in the late adminiſtrator's army. He flattered himſelf that his birth, his merit, and connections, would immediately procure him the command. But the mercenary band, ſeeing him without troops and without attendants, regarded him as a deſperate perſon devoted to deſtruction, refuſed to embrace his propoſals, and even threatened to kill or betray him, if he did not inſtantly quit the city.</p><p>Diſappointed in his expectations, Guſtavus departed with great expedition ; and his arrival being now publicly known, he was again forced to have recourſe to his peaſant’s diſguiſe to conceal him from the Daniſh emiſſaries diſperſed over the country to ſearch for him. In a waggon loaded with hay he paſſed through every quarter of the Daniſh army, and at laſt repaired to an old family caſtle in Sudermania. From hence he wrote to his friends, notifying his return to Sweden, and beſeeching them to aſſemble all their forces in order to break through the enemy’s army into Stockholm, at that time beſieged ; but they, too, refuſed to embark in ſo hazardous and deſperate an attempt.</p><p>Guſtavus next applied himſelf to the peaſants ; but they anſwered, that they enjoyed ſalt and herrings under the government of the king of Denmark ; and that any attempts to bring about a revolution would be attended with certain ruin, without the proſpect of bettering their condition ; for peaſants they were, and peaſants they ſhould remain, whoever was king. At length, after ſeveral vain attempts to throw himſelf into Stockholm, after that city was ſurrendered to the king, after the horrid maſſacre of the senates, and after running a thouſand dangers, and undergoing hardships and fatigues hardly to be ſupported by human nature, he formed the reſolution of trying the courage and affection of the Dalecarlians. While he was in the deepeſt obſcurity, and plunged in almoſt unſurmountable adverſity, he never relinquiſhed his deſigns nor his hopes. The news of the maſſacre had, however, very near sunk him into deſpondency, as thereby he lost all his friends, relations, and connections, and indeed almoſt every proſpect of ſafety to himſelf or deliverance to his country. It was this that inſpired the thought of going to Dalecarlia, where he might live with more ſecurity in the high mountains and thick woods of that country, if he ſhould fail in the attempt of exciting the inhabitants to revolt.</p><p>Attended by a peaſant, to whom he was known, he travelled in diſguiſe through Sudermania, Nericia, and Weſtermania, and, after a laborious and painful journey, arrived in the mountains of Dalecarlia. Scarce had he finished his journey, when he found himſelf deſerted by his companion and guide, who carried off with him all the money he provided for his ſubſiſtence. Thus forlorn, deſtitute, half ſtarved, he entered among the miners, and wrought like a ſlave under ground, without relinquiſhing his hopes of one day aſcending the throne of Sweden. His whole proſpect for the preſent was to live concealed, and gain a maintenance, until fortune ſhould effect ſomething in his favour : nor was it long before this happened. A woman in the mines perceived, under the habit of a peaſant, that the collar of his ſhirt was embroidered. This circumſtance excited curioſity ; and the graces of his perſon and converſation, which had ſomething in them to attract the notice of the meaneſt of the vulgar , afforded room for ſuſpicion that he was ſome perſon of quality in diſguiſe, forced by the tyranny of the government to ſeek ſhelter in theſe remote parts. The ſtory came to the ears of a neighbouring gentleman, who immediately went to the mines to offer his protection to the unfortunate ſtranger ; and was aſtoniſhed on recognizing the features of Guſtavus, whoſe acquaintance he had been at the university of Upſal. Touched with compassion at the deplorable ſituation of ſo diſtinguiſhed a nobleman, he could ſcarce refrain from tears; but however had preſence of mind enough not to make the diſcovery. At night he ſent for Guſtavus, made him an offer of his houſe, and gave him the ſtrongeſt aſſurances of his friendſhip and protection. He told him, he would meet with better accommodations, and as much ſecurity as in the mines; and that, ſhould he chance to be diſcovered, he would, with all his friends and vaſſals, take arms in his defence.</p><p>This offer was embraced by Guſtavus with joy, and he remained for ſome time at his friend’s house ; but finding it impoſſible to induce him to take part in his deſigns, he quitted him, and fled to one Peterſon, a gentleman whom he had formerly known in the ſervice. By him he was received with all the appearance of kindneſs ; and, on the very first propoſal made by Guſtavus, offered to raiſe his vaſſals. He even named the lords and peaſants whom he pretended to have engaged in his ſervice ; but in a very few days after, he went ſecretly to a Daniſh officer, and gave him information of what had paſſed. The officer immedi-</p></body></text></TEI>