<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>exacted of him. The king, looking at him ſternly, anſwered, " Think of what you are doing.” “ I do, replied Cederſtrom ; and what I think to day, I ſhall think tomorrow : and were I capable of breaking the oath by which I am already bound to the ſtates, I ſhould be likewise capable of breaking that your majeſty now requeſts me to take.”</p><p>The king then ordered Cederſtrom to deliver up his sword, and put him in arreſt.</p><p>His majeſty, however, apprehenſive of the impreſſion which the proper and reſolute conduct of Cederſtrom might make upon the minds oſ the other officers, shortly afterwards softened his tone of voice ; and again addreſſing himſelf to Cederſtrom, told him, that as a proof of the opinion he entertained of him, and the confidence he placed in him, he would return him his ſword without insisting upon his taking the oath, and would only deſire his attendance that day. Cederſtrom continued firm ; he anſwered, that his majeſty could place no confidence in him that day, and that he begged to be excuſed from the ſervice.</p><p>While the king was ſhut up with the officers, Senator Ralling, to whom the command of the troops in the town had been given two days before, came to the door of the guard room, and was told that he could not be admitted. The ſenator inſiſted upon being preſent at the diſtribution of the orders, and ſent to the king to deſire it ; but was anſwered, he muſt go to the ſenate, where his majeſty would ſpeak to him.</p><p>The officers then received their orders from the king ; the firſt of which was, that the two regiments of guards and of artillery ſhould be immediately assembled, and that a detachment of 36 grenadiers ſhould be posted at the door of the council-chamber to prevent any of the ſenators from coming out.</p><p>But before the orders could be carried into execution, it was necessary that the king ſhould addreſs himſelf to the ſoldiers ; men wholly unacquainted with his deſigns, and accuſtomed to pay obedience only to the orders of the ſenate, whom they had been taught to hold in the higheſt reverence.</p><p>As his majeſty, followed by the officers, was advancing from the guard room to the parade for this purpoſe, ſome of them more cautious, or perhaps more timid than the reſt, became, on a ſhort reflection, apprehenſive of the conſequences of the meaſure in which they were engaged : they began to expreſs their fears to the king, that unleſs ſome perſons of greater weight and influence than themſelves were to take a part in the ſame cauſe, he could hardly hope to ſucceed in his enterpriſe. The king stopped a while, and appeared to heſitate. A ſerjeant of the guards overheard their diſcourſe, and cried aloud,—“ It ſhall ſucceed—Long live Guſtavus !” His majeſty immediately ſaid, " Then I will venture ;”—and ſtepping forward to the ſoldiers, he addressed them in terms nearly ſimilar to thoſe he had made uſe of to the officers, and with the same ſucceſs. They anſwered him with loud acclamations : one voice only ſaid, No ; but it was not attended to.</p><p>In the mean time ſome of the king’s emissaries had ſpread a report about the town that the king was arreſted. This drew the populace to the palace in great numbers, where they arrived as his majeſty had concluded his harangue to the guards. They teſtified by reiterated ſhouts their joy at ſeeing him ſafe ; a joy which promiſed the happieſt concluſion to the buſineſs of the day.</p><p>The ſenators were now immediately ſecured. They had from the window of the council-chamber beheld what was going forward on the parade before the palace ; and, at a loſs to know the meaning of the ſhouts they heard, were coming down to inquire into the cauſe of them, when 30 grenadiers, with their bayonets fixed, informed them it was his majeſty’s pleaſure they ſhould continue where they were. They began to talk in a high tone, but were anſwered only by having the door ſhut and locked upon them.</p><p>The moment the ſecret committee heard that the ſenate was arreſted, they ſeparated of themſelves, each individual providing for his own ſafety. The king then mounting his horſe, followed by his officers with their ſwords drawn, a large body of ſoldiers, and numbers of the populace, went to the other quarters of the town where the ſoldiers he had ordered to be assembled were poſted. He found them all equally willing to ſupport his cause, and to take an oath of fidelity to him. As he paſſed through the ſtreets, he declared to the people, that he only meant to defend them, and ſave his country ; and that if they would not confide in him, he would lay down his ſceptre, and ſurrender up his kingdom. So much was the king beloved, that the people (ſome of whom even fell down upon their knees) with tears in their eyes implored his majeſty not to abandon them.</p><p>The king proceeded in his courſe, and in leſs than an hour made himſelf maſter of all the military force in Stockholm. In the mean time the heralds, by proclamation in the ſeveral quarters of the city, summoned an aſſembly of the States for the enſuing morning, and declared all members traitors to their country who ſhould not appear. Thither his majeſty repaired in all the pomp of royalty, ſurrounded by his guards, and holding in his hand the ſilver ſceptre of Guſtavus Adolphus. In a very forcible ſpeech, he lamented the unhappy ſtate to which the country was reduced by the conduct of a party ready to ſacrifice every thing to its ambition, and reproached the ſtates with adapting their actions to the views of foreign courts, from which they received the wages of persidy. “ If any one dare contradict this, let him rise and ſpeak.”—Conviction, or fear, kept the assembly silent, and the ſecretary read the new form of government, which the king ſubmitted to the approbation of the ſtates. It consisted of fiſty-ſeven articles ; of which the following five were the chief.</p><p>1. The king has the entire power of convoking and diſſolving the aſſembly of the ſtates as often as he thinks proper. 2. His majeſty alone has the command of the army, fleet, and finances, and the diſpoſal of all offices civil and military. 3. In caſe of an invaſion, or of any pressing neceſſity, the king may impoſe taxes, without waiting for the aſſembly of the ſtates. 4. The diet can deliberate upon no other ſubjects than thoſe propoſed by the king. 5. The king ſhall not carry on an offenſive war without the conſent of the ſtates. When all the articles were gone through, the king demanded if the ſtates approved of them, and was anſwered by a general acclamation. He then diſmiſſed all the ſenators from their employments, adding, that in a few days he would appoint others ; and concluded this extraordinary ſcene by drawing out of his pocket a ſmall book of pſalms, from which, after taking off the crown, he gave out Te Deum. All the members very devoutly added their voices to his, and the hall reſounded with thankſgivings, which it is to be feared never roſe to heaven, if ſincerity was neceſſary to their paſſport.</p><p>The power thus obtained the king employed for the good of his ſubjects. He took care that the law ſhould be adminiſtered with impartiality to the richeſt noble and the pooreſt peaſant, making a ſevere example of ſuch judges as were proved to have made juſtice venal. He gave particular attention and encouragement to commerce, was a</p></body></text></TEI>