<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:12:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>city. Here he was treated with the utmoſt hospitality : the Turks practiſed to its utmoſt extent their generous maxim of regarding as ſacred the perſons oſ unfortunate princes who had taken ſhelter in their dominions ; and perhaps regarded him, notwithſtanding his misfortunes, as an ally that might be uſeful to themſelves againſt the Russians. Every one, indeed, regarded him in his diſtreſs. The French king offered him a ſafe paſſage from the Levant to Marseilles, from whence he might eaſily return to his own dominions. But Charles was too obſtinate to receive advice. Puffed up with the notion of imitating Alexander the Great, he diſdained to return except at the head of a numerous army ; and he yet expected, by means of the Turks, to dethrone his adverſary the Czar. Negotiations for this purpoſe, indeed, were carried on in the Turkiſh divan ; and it was propoſed to escort Charles with a numerous army to the frontiers of Poland : but the revolution which took place there quickly put an end to all ſuch projects. Auguſtus thought himſelf no longer bound to obſerve the treaty which he had made, than Charles was at hand to force him to it. After the battle of Pultowa, therefore, he entered Poland, and took every meaſure, in concert with the Czar, for the recovery of his kingdom. Staniſlaus was not able to ſtand before ſuch enemies, but was obliged to leave his dominions and fly to Bender, in the diſguiſe of a Swediſh officer, in order to ſhare the fortune of Charles.—It was not in Poland alone that the Swediſh affairs began to suffer in conſequence of the defeat at Pultowa The Danes quickly invaded the province of Schonen with an army of 13,000 foot and 2500 horſe. Only 13,000 Swediſh forces remained to defend all the territories poſſessed by Charles in Germany ; and of theſe only a small part were allotted for the defence of Schonen. The regency of Sweden, however, exerted themſelves to the utmoſt to repel this ungenerous invaſion ; and having collected an army of 1 2,000 militia and 8000 regulars, diſpatched them under general Steenboek into Schonen. Some Saxon troops were incorporated in this army ; and among theſe a prodigious deſertion took place, which the general found it impoſſible to prevent ; and thus the Danes gained ſeveral advantages, and at laſt took Chriſtianſtadt. Their insolence on this ſucceſs was ſo great, that the Swedes demanded to be inſtantly led againſt them. Here the good fortune of Sweden ſeemed once more to revive. The Danes were driven from a very ſtrong ſituation, with the loſs of 8000 killed and taken priſoners, besides a vaſt number wounded. The king received the intelligence of this victory with the greateſt exultation ; and could not help exclaiming, “ My brave Swedes, ſhould it pleaſe God that I once more join you, we ſhall conquer them all !”</p><p>In the mean time, Charles, by means of his agents the count Poniatowſki and the Sieur Neugebar, uſed his utmoſt efforts to procure a rupture between the Porte and Russia. For a long time the money bellowed by Peter on the vizirs and janiſaries prevailed ; but at laſt, in 1711, the grand ſignior, influenced by his mother, who was ſtrongly in the intereſt of Charles, and had been wont to call him <hi rend="italic">her lion, </hi>determined to avenge his quarrel with Peter. He therefore gave orders to the vizir to fall upon the Ruſſians with an army of 200,000 men. The vizir promiled obedience ; but at the ſame time professed his ignorance in the art of war, and diſlike to the preſent expedition. The khan of Crim Tartary, who had been gained over by the reputation and presents of the king of Sweden, had orders to take the field with 40,000 of his men, and had the liberty of assembling his army at Bender, that Charles might see that the war was undertaken upon his account. The Czar, on theſe news, left the siege of Riga, where he had continued for some months; and with 24,000 men entered Moldavia, where he was joined by Cantemir a vaſſal of the Porte. The vizir marched against him with a prodigious army, and, through the negligence of the Czar, cooped him up in ſuch a manner that he could neither advance nor retreat. In this deſperate ſituation, he perceived that he was now in as bad a ſituation as Charles at Pultowa ; and gave orders for breaking through the enemy with fixed bayonets. The deſponding spiritless ſoldiers, however, were little dispoſed to execute theſe orders ; when Catharine, wise to the czar , without his knowledge, ſet on foot a treaty with the vizir; and having ſoon obtained his conſent, had the peace ſigned in six hours ; by which means, in all probability, the whole Russian army was saved.</p><p>The new treaty was moſt violently oppoſed by count Poniatowſki and the khan of Tartary. The former had made the king acquainted with the ſituation of both armies ; on which he inſtantly ſet out from Bender, filled with the hopes of fighting the Russians, and taking ample vengeance. Having ridden 50 leagues poſt, he arrived at the camp juſt as the czar was drawing off his half-famiſhed troops. He alighted at Poniatowſki’s tent ; and being informed of particulars, inſtantly flew in a rage to the vizir, whom he loaded with reproaches, and accuſed of treachery. Recollecting himſelf, however, he propoſed a method by which the fault might be remedied ; but finding his propoſal rejected, he posted back to Bender, after having by the groſseſt insults ſhowed his contempt of the vizir,</p><p>The violent behaviour of Charles did not promote his intereſt. The vizir perceived that his ſtay in Turkey might prove fatal to himſelf ; and therefore determined to get him out of the country as soon as poſſible, either by fair means or foul. Succeeding vizirs adopted the ſame plan ; and at laſt the grand ſignior himſelf wrote a letter to the king, in which he deſired him to depart by next winter, promiſing to ſupply him with a sufficient guard, with money, and every thing else necessary for his journey. Charles gave an evasive answer, and determined to procraſtinate his journey, as well to gratify his own ſtubborn temper, as becauſe he diſcovered a correspondence between Auguſtus and the khan of Tartary, the object of which, he had reason to believe, was to betray him to the Saxons. When he was therefore again pressed to fix the day of his departure, he replied, that he could not think of going before his debts were paid. Being aſked how much was necessary for this purpoſe, he replied, 1000 purſes @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> Twelve hundred purſes were inſtantly sent to the ſeraſquſer at Bender, with orders to deliver them to the king of Sweden, but not before he ſhould have begun his journey. By fair promises, however, Charles perſuaded him to part with the money ; after which, inſtead of letting out, he ſquandered away his treaſure in preſents and gratifications, and then demanded 1000 purſes more before he would ſet out. The ſerasquier was aſtoniſhed at this behaviour. He ſhed tears ; and, turning to the king, told him, that his head would be the forfeit of having obliged him with the money. The grand ſignior, on being acquainted with this ſhameful behaviour of Charles, flew into a rage, and called an extraordinary divan, where he himſelf spoke, a thing very unuſual for the Turkiſh monarchs. It was unanimously agreed that ſuch a trouble-</p><p>@@@(a) Each purse contained 30 sequins.</p></body></text></TEI>