<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of which was duke Charles his uncle. Remonſtrances, accompanied with threats, took place on both ſides ; and at an interview between the king and Charles, the diſpute would have ended in blows, had they not been parted by ſome of the nobility. This, however, made ſuch an impression upon Sigiſmund, that he was apparently reconciled to his brother, and promiſed to comply with the inclinations of the people in every reſpect, though without any inclination to perform what he had promiſed. The agreement, indeed, was ſcarce made, before Sigiſmund conceived the horrid deſign of murdering his uncle at the Italian comedy acted the night after his coronation. The duke, however, having notice of the plot, found means to avoid it. This enraged the king ſo much, that he reſolved to accompliſh his designs by force ; and therefore commanded a Poliſh army to march towards the frontiers of Sweden, where they committed all the ravages that could be expected from an enraged and cruel enemy. Complaints were made by the Proteſtant clergy to the ſenate : but no other reply was made them, than that they ſhould abſtain from theſe bitter invectives and reproaches, which had provoked the Catholics, until the king’s departure ; at which time they would be at more liberty.</p><p>In 1595 Sigiſmund ſet ſail for Dantzic, leaving the adminiſtration in the hands of duke Charles. The conſequence of this was, that the diſſenſions which had already taken place being continually increaſed by the obſtinacy of the king, duke Charles aſſumed the ſovereign power ; and in 1604 Sigiſmund was formally depoſed, and his uncle Charles IX. raised to the throne. He proved a wife and brave prince, reſtoring the tranquillity of the kingdom, and carrying on a war with vigour againſt Poland and Denmark. He died in 16l1, leaving the kingdom to his ſon, the celebrated Guſtavus Adolphus.</p><p>Though Charles IX. by his wife and vigorous conduct had in a great meaſure retrieved the affairs of Sweden, they were ſtill in a very diſagreeable ſituation. The finances of the kingdom were entirely drained by a series of wars and revolutions ; powerful armies were preparing in Denmark, Poland, and Ruſſia, while the Swediſh troops were not only inferior in number to their enemies, but the government was deſtitute of reſources for their payment.</p><p>Though the Swediſh law required that the prince ſhould have attained his 18th year before he was of age, yet ſuch ſtriking marks of the great qualities of Guſtavus appeared, that he was allowed by the ſtates to take upon him the adminiſtration even before this early period. His firſt act was to reſume all the crown-grants, that he might be the better able to carry on the wars in which he was unavoidably engaged ; and to fill all places, both civil and military, with perſons of merit. At the head of domeſtic and foreign affairs was placed chancellor Oxenſtiern, a person every way equal to the important truſt, and the chooſing of whom impresſed mankind with the higheſt opinion of the young monarch’s penetration and capacity.</p><p>Soon after his acceſſion, Guſtavus received an embaſſy from James I. of Britain, exhorting him to make peace with his neighbours. This was ſeconded by another from Holland. But as the king perceived that the Daniſh monarch intended to take every opportunity of cruſhing him, he reſolved to act with ſuch vigour, as might convince him that he was not eaſily to be overcome. Accordingly he broke into Denmark with three different armies at once ; and though the enemy’s ſuperiority at ſea gave them great advantages, and the number of the king’s enemies distracted his attention, he carried on the war with ſuch ſpirit, that in 1613 a peace was concluded upon good terms. This war</p><p>being finiſhed, the king applied himſelf to civil polity, and made ſome reformations in the laws of Sweden. In 1615, hoſtilities were commenced againſt Ruſſia, on account of the refuſal of that court to reſtore ſome money which had been formerly lent them. The king entered Ingria, took Kexholm by ſtorm, and was laying ſiege to Pleſcow, when, by the mediation of James I. peace was concluded, on condition of the Russians repaying the money, and yielding to Sweden ſome part of their territory. In this and the former war, notwithſtanding the ſhortneſs of their duration, Guſtavus learned the rudiments of the military art for which he ſoon became ſo famous. He is said, indeed, to have catched every opportunity of improvement with a quickneſs of underſtanding ſeemingly more than human. In one campaign, he not only learned, but improved, all the military maxims of La Gardie, a celebrated general, brought the Swediſh army in general to a more ſteady and regular diſcipline than had formerly been exerciſed, and formed and ſeaſoned an invincible body of Finlanders, who had afterwards a very conſiderable ſhare in the victories of the Swedes.</p><p>Peace was no ſooner concluded with Ruſſia, than Guſtavus was crowned with great ſolemnity at Upsal. Soon after this, Guſtavus ordered his general La Gardie to acquaint the Poliſh commander Codekowitz, that as the truce between the two kingdoms, which had been concluded for two years, was now expired, he deſired to be certainly informed whether he was to expect peace or war from his maſter. In the mean time, having borrowed money of the Dutch for the redemption of a town from Denmark, he had an interview on the frontiers with Chriſtian the king of that country. At this interview, the two monarchs conceived the utmost eſteem and friendſhip for each other ; and Guſtavus obtained a promiſe, that Chriſtian would not aſſiſt Sigiſmund in any deſigns he might have againſt Sweden. In the mean time, receiving no ſatisfactory answer from Poland, Guſtavus began to prepare for war. Sigiſmund entered into a negotiation, and made ſome pretended conceſſions, with a view to ſeize Guſtavus by treachery ; but the latter having intimation of his deſign, the whole negotiation was changed into reproaches and threats on the part of Guſtavus.</p><p>Immediately after this, Guſtavus made a tour in diſguiſe through Germany, and married Eleonora the daughter of the elector of Brandenburg. He then reſolved to enter heartily into a war with Poland ; and with this view ſet ſail for Riga with a great fleet, which carried 20,000 men. The place was well fortified, and defended by a body of veterans enthuſiaſtically attached to Sigiſmund. A dreadful bombardment enſued ; the ſtreets were raked by the cannon, and the houſes laid in aſhes by the bombs ; the moat was filled up, one of the half-moons taken by ſtorm, and the ſtrong fortreſs of Dunamund was reduced. The cannon having now effected a breach in another part of the walls, Guſtavus reſolved to make a general aſſault. For this purpoſe a flying bridge over the moat was contrived by his majeſty ; for though the ditch was filled with faſcines and rubbiſh, it ſtill contained too much water to admit the pasſage of a large body of men. The ſoldiers, however, crowded on to the attack with ſo much impetuoſity, that the bridge gave way, and the attempt proved unſucceſsful. Next day the Swedes were repulſed in attempting to ſtorm another half-moon ; and the king was obliged to proceed more ſlowly. By the middle of September, at which time the town had been inveſted for six weeks, two bridges were thrown over the river together with a ſtrong boom, while the Swedes had formed their mines under the ditch. The garriſon being now reduced to extremity, were obliged to</p></body></text></TEI>