<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:37Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>value in a single present payment of an annuity of L. 1 for the life of the wife after the husband ; that is, for the life of the widow. The annuity, therefore, being ſuppoſed L.20, its value in a single payment is 20 multiplied by 3.797, that is, L. 75.94. And this laſt value divided by 14.455 (that is, by the value of the joint lives increaſed by unity), gives 5.25, the value in annual payments beginning immediately, and to be continued during the joint lives of an annuity of <hi rend="smallcaps">L.20</hi> to a wife aged 24 for her life, after her husband aged 30.</p><p>SURYA, the orb of the sun perſonified and adored by a ſect oſ Hindoos as a god. He ſeems to be the same divinity with the Phœbus of Greece and Rome ; and the ſect: who pay him particular adoration are called <hi rend="italic">Sauras.</hi> Their poets and painters deſcribe his car as drawn by ſeven green horses, preceded by Arun, or the <hi rend="italic">Dawn,</hi> who acts as his charioteer, and followed by thouſands of genii worſhipping him and modulating his praiſes. He has a multitude of names, and among them twelve epithets or titles, which denote his diſtinct powers in each of the twelve months ; and he is believed to have deſcended frequently from his car in a human ſhape, and to have left a race on earth, who are equally renowned in the Indian ſtories with the Heliadai of Greece : it is very ſingular, that his two ſons called <hi rend="italic">Afwinau </hi>or <hi rend="italic">Aſwinicurnarau,</hi> in the dual, ſhould be conſidered as twin brothers, and painted like Caſtor and Pollux; but they have each the character of Æsculapius among the gods, and are believed to have been born oſ a nymph, who, in the form of a mare, was impregnated with ſunbeams.</p><p>SUS, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Hog,</hi> in zoology, a genus of quadrupeds belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">mammalia</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">belluae.</hi> There are four cutting teeth in the upper jaw, whoſe points converge; and, for the moſt part, six in the lower jaw, which ſtand forwards : There are two tuſks in each jaw, thoſe in the upper jaw being ſhort, while thoſe of the under jaw are long, and extend out of the mouth. The ſnout is prominent, moveable, and has the appearance of having been cut off, or truncated. The feet are armed with divided or cloven hoofs. There are six ſpecies; the ſcrofa, æthiopicus, tajassu, babyruſſa, porcus, and africanus. The moſt remarkable are,</p><p>I. The <hi rend="italic">ſcrofa,</hi> or common hog, having the body covered with briſtles ; two large teeth above and below. In a wild ſtate, of a dark brinded colour, and beneath the briſtles is a ſoft ſhort hair ; the ears ſhort, and a little rounded. <hi rend="smallcaps">Tame: </hi>the ears long, ſharp-pointed, and ſtouching ; the colour generally white, ſometimes mixed with other colours. In a tame ſtate it is univerſal ; except in the frigid zones, and in Kamtſchatka, where the cold is very ſevere. Since its introduction into America by the Europeans, it abounds to excels in the hot and temperate parts. It is found wild in moſt parts of Europe. In the foreſts of South America there are vast droves, which derive their origin from the European kind relapſed into a ſtate of nature ; and are what Mr Bancroft, in his Hiſtory of Guiana, deſcribes as a particular ſpecies by the name of <hi rend="italic">Warree.</hi> They cannot bear exceſſive cold ; inhabit wooded countries ; and are very ſwift. In America they are uſeful by clearing the country of rattle-ſnakes, which they devour without danger.</p><p>Of all quadrupeds, the hog is the moſt rude and brutal. The imperfections of his form ſeem to have an influence on his nature and diſpoſitions. All his habits are groſs ; all his appetites are impure ; all his ſenſations are confined to a furious luſt, and a brutal gluttony. He devours indiſcriminately every thing that comes in his way, even his own progeny the moment after their birth. This voraciouſneſs ſeems to proceed from the perpetual cravings of his ſtomach, which is of an immoderate ſize ; and the groſſneſs of his appetities, it is probable, ariſes from the bluntness of his ſenses of taſte and of feeling. The rudeneſs of the hair, the hardneſs of the ſkin, and the thickneſs of the fat, render theſe animals leſs ſensible to blows. Mice have been known to lodge upon a hog’s back, and to eat his ſkin and fat, without his ſhowing any marks of ſensibility. The other ſenſes oſ the hog are very good. It is well known to the hunters that the wild boar hears and ſmells at a great diſtance ; for, in order to ſurpriſe him, they are obliged to watch him in ſilence during the night, and to place themſelves oppoſite to the wind, that he may not perceive the ſmell, which never fails to make him turn back.</p><p>But the hog, though the moſt impure and filthy of all quadrupeds, is yet uſeful by the very ſordidness of its manners ; this alone devouring what is the refuſe of all others, and contributing not only to remove what would be a nuiſance to the human race, but alſo converting the moſt nauſeous offals into the richeſt nutriment : for this reaſon its ſtomach is capacious, and its gluttony exceſſive : not that its palate is inſensible to the difference of eatables ; for where it finds variety, it will reject the worſt with as diſtinguiſhing a taſte as other quadrupeds.</p><p>The parts of this animal are finely adapted to its way of life. As its method of feeding is by turning up the earth with its noſe for roots of different kinds, ſo nature has given it a more prone form than other animals ; a ſtrong brawny neck; eyes ſmall, and placed high in the head ; a long ſnout, noſe callous and tough, and a quick ſenſe of ſmelling to trace out its food. Its inteſtines have a ſtrong reſemblance to thoſe of the human ſpecies. The external form of its body is very unwieldly ; yet, by the ſtrength of its tendons, the wild boar (which is only a variety of the common kind) is enabled to fly from the hunters with amazing agility : the back-toe on the feet of this animal prevents its slipping while it deſcends declivities, and muſt be of ſingular uſe when purſued. Yet, notwithſtanding its powers of motion, it is by nature ſtupid, inactive, and drowſy ; much inclined to increaſe in fat, which is diſpoſed in a different manner from that of other animals, and forms a regular coat over the whole body. It is reſtleſs at a change of weather, and in certain high winds is ſo agitated as to run violently, ſcreaming horribly at the ſame time : it is fond of wallowing in the dirt, either to cool its ſurfeited body, or to deſtroy the lice, ticks, and other infects with which it is infeſted. Its diſeaſes generally ariſe from foul feeding and intemperance ; measles, impoſthumes, and ſcrophulous complaints, are reckoned among them. Theſe are beſt prevented by keeping the animals, as the ancients ſtrongly recommended, very clean in their ſties ; allowing them air, exercise, and a ſufficiency of water. Linnæus obſerves, that its fleſh is wholeſome food for athletic conſtitutions, or thoſe that uſe much exerciſe ; but bad for ſuch as lead a ſedentary life : it is, however, of moſt univerſal uſe ; and furniſhes numberleſs materials for epicuriſm.</p><p>The boar, or male of theſe creatures, is choſen with great care, when intended for the propagation of his ſpecies ; and is thus employed from the age of two to five years, and then either ſold or fatted. The males not allotted to this uſe are caſtrated, ſometimes at the age of six weeks, and ſometimes when they are six months old ; and then fed to a great ſize either for ſale or for the uſe of the family. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sows </hi>are kept for breed generally from one year old to ſeven, and are then ſpayed and fatted. They have commonly more greaſe on their inteſtines than hogs, theſe being fatteſt on their backs.</p><p>As to the age of theſe animals, it is ſaid that the life of the wild boar may be extended to twenty-five or thirty years.</p></body></text></TEI>