<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:13:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to believe that he would receive a vaſt reinforcement in Ætolia : but when he came to make the experiment, he ſoon found his miſtake ; all the troops he could raiſe there amounted to no more than 4000 men. With this force, ſo exceedingly inadequate to the purpoſe, he was obliged to oppoſe the Roman army, who were advancing in conjunction with the Macedonians, and had already made ſurpriſing progress. Antiochus ſeized the Straits of Thermopylae; but was driven from them by the Romans, the king himſelf being the firſt that fled. Almoſt his whole army was deſtroyed in the battle or in the purſuit, and Antiochus returned with disgrace into Aſia.</p><p>Soon after his return, Antiochus equipped a fleet of 200 ſail ; on which he immediately embarked for the Thracian Cherſoneſus, now Crim Tartary, where he fortified the cities of Lyſirhachia, Seſtus, and Abydos, with others in that neighbourhood, to prevent the Romans from croſſing the Helleſpont. In the mean time Polyxenidas the Syrian admiral ſent intelligence to the king that the Roman fleet had appeared off Delos; upon which he deſired him to ſeek them out and engage them at all events. He did ſo, and was defeated with the loſs of 40 ſhips taken or sunk in the engagement. This was ſoon after revenged by the deſtruction of the Rhodian fleet by the artifice of Polyxenidas ; but in the end the king’s affairs went everywhere to wreck. Having laid siege to the city of Pergamus, he was obliged to raiſe it with loſs ; the Phoenician fleet commanded by Hannibal was defeated by the Rhodians ; and ſoon after the Syrian fleet under Polyxenidas was utterly defeated by the Romans. Antiochus was ſo much diſheartened by theſe repeated defeats, that he appeared like one infatuated. Inſtead of fortifying more ſtrongly thoſe cities which lay on the frontiers of his kingdom, he entirely deſerted them: and thus Lyſimachia and Abydos, the two keys to Aſia, fell into the hands of the Romans without the leaſt reſiſtance.</p><p>The arrival of the Romans in Aſia ſtruck Antiochus with ſuch terror, that he inſtantly ſued for peace. The terms he offered were indeed very advantageous, but by no means agreeable to the expectations of the Romans. They therefore gave him this final anſwer : 1. That ſince he had drawn upon himſelf the war; he ſhould defray the whole expence of it ; 2. That he ſhould reſtore liberty in general to all the Greek cities in Aſia; and, 3. That to prevent future hostilities, he ſhould relinquiſh all Asia on this side Mount Taurus. Theſe terms, however, ſtill appeared to him ſo intolerable, that he reſolved to continue the war ; and determined alſo to take the moſt imprudent method of carrying it on, namely, by hazarding all on the event of a general engagement. The king encamped near Magneſia, and ſtrongly fortified his camp. The Romans inſulted him in his trenches, and propoſed to attack his fortifications if he continued to decline an engagement. At laſt the king, thinking it would be ſhameful for him longer to refuſe an engagement, being at the head of an army far more numerous than that of the enemy, in a friend’s country, and in the midſt of his allies, resolved at all events to accept the challenge, and accordingly prepared for a decisive battle.</p><p>The Roman army cosiſted of four legions, partly Romans and partly Latins, each legion at this time containing 5500 men, and of 7000 auxiliaries ſent by the kings of Pergamus and Macedon; but of theſe 2000 were ordered to guard the camp during the action. The Romans were polled in the centre, and the Latins in the two wings, the left of which extended to the river. On the side of the right wing, to cover and ſupport it, the conſul potted the auxiliary troops of Eumenes, a ſmall body of horſe, and ſome Trallians and Cretans lightly armed. Sixteen elephants which the Romans had were placed behind the army by way of corps-de-reserve, the conſul not thinking it proper to oppoſe them to thoſe of the enemy, which were far more numerous, being in all 52, and besides excelled the Roman elephants in ſtrength, height, and courage, the former being brought from India and the latter from Africa. As for the Syrian army, all the nations of the eaſt ſeemed to be affembſed to ſupport the cauſe of Antiochus. But the main ſtrength of it confiſted in 16,000 toot, armed after the Macedonian manner, who compoſed the phalanx. This body faced every way, was armed with long pikes, and taught to fight in cloſe order, as the ſoldiers of Alexander the Great had formerly been. Antiochus did not draw up his phalanx as uſual, but divided it into 10 companies ſeparated from each other, placing, in the ſpaces between each of the companies, an elephant loaded with a tower full of armed men. On the right of the phalanx was drawn up in a line part of the cavalry, viz. 1500 Aſiatic Gauls, 3000 horſe armed cap-a-pee, and 1000 more, the flower of the Median cavalry. At ſome diſtance from theſe followed the cavalry of the king’s houſehold richly clothed, and wearing bucklers plated over with ſilver. In the ſame line 1200 Scythians on horſeback, armed with bows and arrows, made a great figure, being all choſen men, and of an extraordinary size. The light-armed troops, to the number of 3000, partly Trallians and partly Cretans, with 10,000 Myſian archers and 4000 men more, partly Cyrtoeans armed with slings, partly Persians armed with bows, and partly Arabians mounted on dromedaries, cloſed the right wing, which was led on by thc king in perſon, ſurrounded by a body of Syrians and Lydians well mounted, but not heavily armed. The left wing was commanded by Seleucus and Antipater; the former the king’s ſon, and the latter his nephew, and diſpoſed thus: Cloſe to the phalanx were poſted 1500 Galatians and 2000 Cappadocians, which king Ariarathes had ſent to the aſſiſtance of his father-in-law. Next to theſe were placed 2700 auxiliaries ſent from different countries ; theſe were followed by 3000 cuiraſſiers well mounted; and, laſtly, in the flank of this wing marched 2000 horſe lightly armed. At ſome diſtance were placed ſeveral ſmall bodies of light-armed troops both foot and horſe; among which were 2500 Galatian horſe, ſome Tarentines, Cretans, Carians, Cilicians, &amp;c. The phalanx, which was in the centre, was commanded by three officers of diſtinction, viz. Minio, Zeuxis, and Philip. A vaſt number of chariots, armed with hooks and ſcythes, were drawn up before the firſt line, as were likewiſe a great many elephants carrying towers with ſeveral floors, all filled with slingers and archers ; beſides many camels, animals then unknown to the Roman troops, mounted by Arabians armed with ſwords six feet long, that the riders might from their backs reach the enemy. The Romans had never ſeen a more numerous army, nor one more finely adorned; nevertheleſs they never ſhowed ſo great a contempt for an army as for this which they were now going to attack.</p><p>On the day of the battle the weather proved very favourable to the Romans ; for a thick fog rising in the morning, the day was almoſt turned into night, ſo that the Syrian commanders could not have all the corps under their command in view, on account of their great uxtent, nor lend them proper orders in time; whereas the fog was not thick enough to prevent the Roman generals from ſeeing their ſeveral bodies at the greateſt diſtance, as they took up but little ground. Beſides, the damp which was occasioned by the fog ſlackened the ſtrings of the enemy’s bows, ſo that the Aliatics who uſed them could ſhoot their darts and arrows but faintly. The whole dependence of Antiochus in the firſt attack was on his armed chariots, which were to cut their way into the Roman army. For this purpoſe they</p></body></text></TEI>