<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:11:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in their rights and privileges.—Indeed he had not been long ſeated on the throne before he incurred the displeaſure of that body ; for having large arrears due to the army, with ſeveral other incumbrances, Guſtavus found it neceſſary to raiſe large contributions on the clergy. On this he was accuſed of avarice and hereſy before the pope’s nuncio. Guſtavus took the proper methods for defending himſelf againſt theſe accuſations; and in a ſhort time after ſhowed a great partiality for the doctrines of Luther, which by this time had been preached and received by many people in Sweden. This embroiled him more than ever with the eccleſiaſtics ; and it ſoon appeared, that either Guſtavus muſt reſign his throne, or the clergy ſome part of the power they had aſſumed. Matters were driven to extremities by the king’s allowing the ſcriptures to be translated into the Swediſh language. In 1526, the king, finding them entering into a combination againſt the reformiſts, went to Upſal, and publicly declared his reſolution of reducing the number of oppreſſive and idle monks and prieſts, who, under pretence of religion, fattened on the ſpoils of the induſtrious people. At laſt, taking advantage of the war between the pope and Charles V. of Spain, he declared himſelf to be of the reformed religion, and eſtabliſhed it throughout his dominions ; and at the ſame time, to humble the arrogance of the eccleſiaſtics, he gave the ſenators die precedency of them, and in many other reſpects degraded them from the dignities they formerly enjoyed. For ſome time the ſtates heſitated at ſupporting the king in his work of reformation ; inſomuch, that at laſt he threatened to reſign the kingdom, which, he ſaid, was doomed to perpetual ſlavery either to its temporal or ſpiritual tyrants. On this the ſtates came into his measures, and retrenched the privileges of the eccleſiaſtics in the manner he propoſed. Several diſturbances, however, enſued. An impoſtor, who pretended to be of the family of Sture the former regent, having claimed the throne, the Dalecarlians revolted in his favour ; but on the approach of a powerful army ſent by Guſtavus, they ſubmitted to his terms. Soon after, Lutheran profeſſors were eſtabliſhed in every dioceſe ; upon which a new rebellion enſued. At the head of this was Thure Johanſon, who had married the king’s ſiſter. Several of the nobility joined him ; and the king of Denmark alſo acceded to their cauſe, thinking, by means of theſe diſturbances, to reunite the three kingdoms of Sweden, Denmark, and Norway, as they had formerly been. But Gustavus prevailed, and the rebels were obliged to take refuge in Denmark. A freſh accident, however, had like to have embroiled matters worſe than before. The ſubſidy granted to the regency of Lubec was ſtill due ; and for the payment of <hi rend="italic">it</hi> the ſtates granted to the king all the uſeleſs bells of the churches and monaſteries. The people were ſhocked at the ſacrilege ; and the Dalecarlians again betook themſelves to arms. Intimidated, however, by the courage and vigorous conduct of the king, they again ſubmitted, and were taken into favour. But tranquillity was not yet reſtored. Chriſtian having eſtabliſhed a powerful intereſt in Norway, once more made an attempt to recover his kingdoms, and was joined by the Dalecarlians ; but being defeated; by the Swediſh forces, he was forced to return to Norway, where, being obliged to capitulate with the Daniſh generals, he was kept priſoner all his life.</p><p>In 1542, Guſtavus having happily extricated himſelf out of all his troubles, prevailed on the ſtates to make the crown hereditary in his family ; after which he applied himſelf to the encouragement of learning and commerce. A treaty was ſet on foot for a marriage between his eldeſt son Eric and Elizabeth queen of England. The prince’s brother, duke John, went over to England, and resided for ſome</p><p>time at the court of London with great ſplendour. He returned, full of expectations of ſucceſs ; but bringing with him no sort of proofs in writing, his father ſoon perceived that he had been the dupe of Elizabeth’s ſuperior policy. However, at laſt he allowed Prince Eric to go in perſon to England; but before he could embark, the death of Guſtavus made him lay aside all thoughts of the voyage and marriage.</p><p>Guſtavus Vaſa died in 1560, and was ſucceeded by his ſon Eric XIV. The new king was a man poſſessed of all the exterior ornaments which give an air of dignity to the perſon; but he had neither the prudence nor the penetration of his father. He created the firſt nobility that were ever known in Sweden ; which he had no ſooner done than he quarrelled with them, by paſſing ſome acts which they thought derogatory to their honour and dignity. The whole courſe of his reign was diſturbed by wars with Denmark, and diſputes with his own ſubjects. In the former he was unfortunate, and towards the latter he behaved with the greateſt cruelty. At laſt, by the torments of his own conſcience, it is ſaid, he run mad. He afterwards recovered his ſenſes, but was thereupon dethroned by his brothers ; of whom Duke John, who had been hitherto kept priſoner by Eric, ſucceeded him in the kingdom.</p><p>This revolution took place in the year 1568, but with no great advantage to Sweden. Diſputes about religion between the king and his brothers, and wars with Muſcovy, threw matters into the utmoſt confusion. At laſt prince Sigiſmund, the king’s ſon, was choſen king of Poland, which proved the ſource of much trouble to the kingdom. He was elected on the following conditions, viz. That there ſhould be a perpetual peace between the ſtates of Poland and Sweden ; that, on the death of his father, prince Sigiſmund ſhould ſucceed to the throne of Sweden ; that, on urgent occaſions, he might, with the conſent of the ſtates, return to Sweden; that he ſhould maintain, at his own expence, a fleet for the ſervice of Poland ; that he ſhould cancel a debt which had been long due from the crown of Poland to Sweden ; that, with the conſent of the ſtates, he ſhould build five fortresses on the frontiers of Poland ; that he ſhould have liberty to introduce foreign ſoldiers into the kingdom, provided he maintained them at his own expence ; that he ſhould not make uſe of Swediſh counſellors in Poland ; that he ſhould have his body-guard entirely of Poles and Lithuanians ; and that he ſhould annex to Poland that part of Livonia now ſubject to Sweden. In 1590 king John died ; and as Sigiſmund was at a diſtance, every thing fell into the utmoſt confuſion : the treaſury was plundered, and the wardrobe quite ſpoiled, before even duke Charles could come to Stockholm to take the adminiſtration into his hands until king Siſgiſmund ſhould return. This, however, was far from being the greateſt diſaſter which befel the nation at this time. It was known that the king had embraced the Popish religion, and it was with good reaſon ſuſpected that he would attempt to reſtore it upon his arrival in Sweden. Sigiſmund alſo was obliged, on leaving Poland, to promiſe that he would stay no longer in Sweden than was neceſſary to regulate his affairs. Theſe circumſtances ſerved to alienate the minds of the Swedes from their ſovereign even before they ſaw him ; and the univerſal diſſatisfaction was increaſed, by seeing him attended, on his arrival in Sweden in 1593, by Malaſpina the pope’s nuncio, to whom he made a present of 30,000 ducats to defray the expences of his journey to Sweden.</p><p>What the people had foreſeen was too well verified : the king refuſed to confirm the Proteſtants in their religious privileges, and ſhowed such partiality on all occaſions to the Papiſts, that a party was formed againſt him ; at the head</p></body></text></TEI>