<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0252.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0246-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEGOVIA</label>,
an ancient city of Spain, of great power in the time of the Cæſars, is built upon two hills near the banks of the Arayda in Old Caſtile. W. Long. 3. 48. N. Lat. 41.0. It is ſtill a biſhop’s ſee, and is diſtinguiſhed for ſome venerable remains of antiquity. In the year 1525 the city contained 5000 families, but now they do not ſurpaſs 2000, a ſcanty population for 25 pariſhes; yet, beſides 21 churches and a cathedral, there are 21 convents.</p><p>The firſt object in Segovia that attracts the eye is the aqueduct, which the singular ſituation of the citv renders neceſſary. As it is built upon two hills, and the valley by which they are ſeparated, and extends conſiderably in every direction, it was difficult for a part of the citizens to be ſupplied with water. The difficulty was removed, according to the opinion of the learned, in the reign of Trajan, by this aqueduct, which is one of the moſt aſtoniſhing and the beſt preſerved of the Roman works.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Swineburn's Travels through Spain.</p></note> In the opinion of Mr Swinburne, who ſurveyed it in 1776, and who ſeems to have given a very accurate account of the curioſities of Segovia, it is ſuperior in elegance of proportion to the Pont du Gard at Niſmes. It is ſo perfectly well preſerved, that it does not ſeem leaky in any part. From the firſt low arches to the reſervoir in the town, its length is 2400 Spaniſh feet; its greateſt height (in the Plaza del Azobejo at the foot of the walls) is 104; it is there compoſed of a double row of arches, built of large ſquare ſtones without mortar, and over them a hollow wall of coarſer materials for the channel of the water, covered with large oblong flags. Of the lower range of arcades, which are 15 feet wide by 65 high, there are 42. The upper arches are 119 in number, their height 27 Spaniſh feet, their breadth ſeventeen, the tranſverſal thickneſs, or depth of the piers, eight feet.</p><p><note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Travels in Spain by the Chev. Bourgeanne.</p></note> The cathedral is a mixture of the Gothic and Mooriſh architecture. The inſide is very ſpacious and of majeſtic ſimplicity. The windows are well diſpoſed, and the great altar has been lately decorated with the fineſt Grenadian marble. But it is to be regretted, that in this cathedral, as well as in moſt others of Spain, the choir is placed in the middle of the nave. The church is nearly upon the model of the great church of Salamanca, but it is not ſo highly finiſhed.</p><p>The alcazar, or ancient palace of the Moors, ſtands in one of the fineſt poſitions poſſible, on a rock riſing above the open country. A very pretty river waſhes the foot of the precipice, and the city lies admirably well on each ſide on the brow of the hill; the declivity is woody, and the banks charmingly rural; the ſnowy mountains and dark foreſts of Saint Ildefonzo compoſe an awful back-ground to the picture. Towards the town there is a large court before the great outward tower, which, as the priſon of Gil Blas, is ſo well deſcribed by Le Sage, that the ſubject requires no farther explanation. The reſt of the buildings form an antique palace, which has ſeldom been inhabited by any but priſoners ſince the reign of Ferdinand and Iſabella, who were much attached to this ſituation. There are ſome magnificent halls in it, with much gilding in the ceilings, in a ſemi-barbarous taſte. All the kings of Spain are ſeated in ſtate along the cornice of the great ſaloon; but it is doubtful whether they are like the princes whoſe names they bear; if that reſemblance, however, be wanting, they have no other merit to claim. The royal apartments are now occupied by a college of young gentlemen cadets, educated at the king’s expence in all the ſciences requiſite for forming an engineer. The grand-maſter of the ordnance reſides at Segovia, which is the head eſtabliſhment of the Spaniſh artillery.</p><p>The mint is below the alcazar, a large building, the moſt ancient place of coinage in the kingdom. The machines for melting, ſtamping, and milling the coin, are worked by water: but there is reaſon to believe<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0253.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0247"/>
that Seville has at preſent more buſiness, as being nearer the ſource of riches, the port of Cadiz, where the ingots of America are landed.</p><p>The unevenneſs of the crown of the hill gives a wild look to this city. Moſt of the ſtreets are crooked and dirty, the houſes wooden and very wretched; nor do the inhabitants appear much the richer for their cloth manufactory. Indeed, it is not in a very flouriſhing condition, but what cloth they make is very ſine.</p><p>The country about Segovia has the reputation of being the beſt for rearing the kind of ſheep that produces the beautiful Spaniſh wool; but as thoſe flocks wander over many other parts of the kingdom, Segovia ſeems to have no excluſive title to this reputation. Segovia (ſays Townſend, whoſe valuable travels will be read with much pleaſure) was once famous for its cloth made on the king’s account; but other nations have ſince become rivals in this branch, and the manufacture in this city has been gradually declining. When the king gave it up to a private company, he left about 3000 l in trade; but now he is no huger a partner in the buſineſs. In the year 1612 were made here 25,500 pieces of cloth, which conſumed 44,625 quintals of wool, employed 34,189 persons; but at preſent they make only about 4000 pieces. The principal imperfections of this cloth are, that the thread is not even, and that much greaſe remains in it when it is delivered to the dyer; in conſequence of which the colour is apt to fail. Yet, independently of imperfections, ſo many are the diſadvantages under which the manufacture labours, that foreigners can afford to pay 3 l. for the arroba of fine wool, for which the Spaniard gives no more than 20 ſhillings, and after all his charges can command the market even in the ports of Spain.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Segovia</hi> (New), a town of North America, in New Spain, and in the audience of Guatimala; ſeated on the river Yare, on the confines of the province of Honduras. W. Long. 84. 30. N. Lat 13. 25.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Segovia,</hi> a town of America, in Terra Firma, and in the province of Venezuela, ſeated on a river, near a very high mountain, where there are mines of gold. W. Long. 65. 30. N. Lat. 8. 20.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Segovia,</hi> a town of Aſia, in the iſland of Manila, and one of the largeſt of the Philippines, ſeated at the north end of the iſland, 240 miles north of Manila, and ſubject to Spain. E. Long. 120. 59. N. Lat. 18.</p><p>36. .</p></div></body></text></TEI>