<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0298.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0292-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SERGEANT</label>,
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Serjeant</hi> <hi rend="italic">at Law,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">of the Coif,</hi> is the higheſt degree taken at the common law, as that of Doctor is of the civil law ; and as these are ſuppoſed to be the moſt learned and experienced in the practice of the courts, there is one court appointed for them to plead in by themſelves, which is the common pleas, where the common law of England is moſt ſtrictly obſerved : but they are not reſtricted from pleading in any other court, where the judges, who cannot have that honour till they have taken the degree of ſerjeant at law, call them <hi rend="italic">brothers.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sergeant</hi> <hi rend="italic">at Arms,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Mace,</hi> an officer appointed to attend the perſon of the king ; to arreſt traitors, and inch perſons of quality as offend ; and to attend the lord high ſteward, when fitting in judgment on a traitor.</p><p>Of theſe, by ſtatute 13 Rich. IL cap. 6. there are not to be above 30 in the realm. There are now nine at court at L. 100 <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi> ſalary each ; they are called the <hi rend="italic">king’s ſergeants at arms,</hi> to diſtinguiſh them from others : they are created with great ceremony, the perſon kneeling before the king, his majeſty lays the mace on his right ſhoulder, and ſays, <hi rend="italic">Riſe up, ſergeant at arms, and eſquire for ever.</hi> They have, beſides, a patent for the office, which they hold for life.</p><p>They have their attendance in the preſence-chamber, where the band of gentlemen-penſioners wait ; and, receiving the king at the door, they carry the maces before him to the chapel door, whilſt the band of penſioners ſtand foremoſt, and make a lane for the king, as they alſo do when the king goes to the houſe of lords.</p><p>There are four other ſergeants at arms, created in the ſame manner ; one, who attends the lord chancellor ; a ſecond, the lord treaſurer ; a third, the ſpeaker of the houſe of commons ; and a fourth, the lord mayor of London on ſolemn occaſions.</p><p>They have a conſiderable ſhare of the fees of honour, and travelling charges allowed them when in waiting, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> five ſhillings per day when the court is within ten miles of London, and ten ſhillings when twenty miles from London. The places are in the lord chamberlain’s gift.</p><p>There are also ſergeants of the mace of an inferior kind, who attend the mayor or other head officer of a corporation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Common</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sergeant,</hi> an officer in the city of London, who attends the lord, mayor and court of aldermen on court days, and is in council with them on all occaſions, within and without the precincts or liberties of the city. He is to take care of orphans eſtates, either by taking account of them, or to ſign their indentures, before their paſſing the lord mayor and court of aldermen : and he was likewiſe to let and manage the orphans eſtates, according to his judgnaent to their beſt advantage. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Recorder.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sergeant,</hi> in war, is an uncommiſſioned officer in a company of foot or troop of dragoons, armed with an halbert, and appointed to see discipline obſerved, to teach the ſoldiers the exerciſe of their arms, to order, ſtraiten, and form their ranks, files, &amp;e. He receives the orders from the adjutant, which he communicates to his officers. Each company generally has two ſergeants.</p></div></body></text></TEI>