<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0335.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0329-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEXTON</label>,
a church-officer, thus called by corruption of the Latin <hi rend="italic">ſacrista,</hi> or Saxon segerst <hi rend="italic">one,</hi> which denotes the same. His office is to take care of the veſſels, veſtments, &amp;c. belonging to the church ; and to attend the miniſter, church-warden, &amp;c. at church. He is uſually choſen by the parſon only. Sextons, as well as parish-clerks, are regarded by the common law as perſons who have freehold in their offices ; and, therefore, though they may be puniſhed, yet they cannot be deprived, by eccleſiaſtical censures.</p><p>The office of ſexton in the pope’s chapel is appropriated to the order of the hermits of St Augustine. He is generally a biſhop, though ſometimes the pope only gives a biſhopric, <hi rend="italic">in partibus,</hi> to him on whom he confers the poſt. He takes the title of <hi rend="italic">Preβa oſ the Pope's Sacristy,</hi> and has the keeping the veſſels of gold and ſilver, the relics, &amp;c. When the pope says mass, the ſexton always taſtes the bread and wine firſt. If it be in private he fays mass, his holineſs, of two wafers, gives him one to eat ; and, if in public, the cardinal, who aſſiſts the pope in quality of deacon, of three wafers, gives him two to eat. When the pope is desperately sick, he adminiſters to him the ſacrament of extreme unction, &amp;c. and enters the conclave in quality of firſt conclaviſt.</p><p>The office of a ſexton in Sweden is ſomewhat Angular. During M. Outhier’s ſtay at Stockholm in 1736 he viſited the church of St Clara, and during divine ſervice he obſerved a ſexton going about with a long rod, waking thoſe perſons who had fallen aſleep.</p></div></body></text></TEI>