<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0296.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0290-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SE RAPIAS</label>,
in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the order of diandria, and to the claſs of gynandria ; and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 7th order, <hi rend="italic">Orck=hidae.</hi> The nectarium is egg-ſhaped and gibbous, with an egg-ſhaped lip. The species, according to Linnseus, are ten. 1. Latifolia; 2. Longifolia ; 3. Grandiflora, or enſifolia ; 4. Lancifolia ; 5. Rubra; 6. Lingua ; 7. Cordigera ; 8. Capensis ; 9. Erecta ; 10. Falcata. The three firſt are natives of Britain,</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">Latifolia,</hi> or broad-leaved helleborine, is distinguished by fibrous bulbs, by ovate ſtem-claſping leaves, and pendulous flowers. The ſtalk is erect, about a cubit high, and furniſhed with six or eight· nervous oval leaves ; the ſpike is about six inches long ; the three upper petals are of a green colour, and of an oval acute form ; the lateral ones are a little ſhorter, and of a white colour, with a little tinge of green. 2. The <hi rend="italic">Palustris</hi> or marſh helleborine, grows in rough boggy paſtures and marſhes, and flowers in July. It is diſtinguiſhed by fibrous bulbs, ſword-ſhaped ſeſſile leaves, pendulous flowers ; and the lip of the nectarium is obtuſe, somewhat ſerrated, and longer than the petals. The flowers grow to the number of <hi rend="italic">15</hi> or 20 in a looſe- ſpike. The three exterior petals are green mixed with red ; the lateral ones are white with a red bluſh ; and the nectarium is marked with red lines and yellow tuberculous ſpots. 3. The <hi rend="italic">Grandiflora,</hi> or white-flowered helleborine, grows in woods, and flowers in June. Its characteriſtics are, fibrous bulbs, ſword-ſhaped leaves, erect flowers; and the lip of the nectarium is obtuſe and ſhorter than the petals. The flowers are large and erect, and consiſting of ſix or eight in a thin ſpike ; the petals are all white, and connive together ; the lip of the nectarium is incloſed within the petals, is white and ſtreaked with three yellow prominent lines.</p></div></body></text></TEI>