<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0298.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0292-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SERIES</label>,
in general, denotes a continual ſucceſſion of things in the ſame order, and having the ſame relation or connection with each other : in this ſenſe we ſay, a ſeries of emperors, kings, biſhops, &amp;c.</p><p>In natural hiſtory, a ſeries is uſed for an order or ſubdiviſion of ſome claſs of natural bodies ; comprehending all ſuch as are diſtinguiſhed from the other bodies of that claſs, by certain characters which they poſſeſs in common, and which the rest of the bodies of that caſt have not.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Series,</hi> in arithmetic and algebra, a rank or number of terms in ſucceſſion, increaſing or diminiſhing in ſome certain ratio or proportion. There are ſeveral kinds of ſeries ; as <hi rend="italic">arithmetical, geometrical, infinite,</hi> &amp;c.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0299.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0293"/>
The two firſt of theſe are, however, more generally known or diſtinguiſhed by the names of arithmetical and geometrical progreſſion. Theſe ſerieſes have already been explained and illuſtrated in the article Algebra, particularly the two firſt : it therefore only remains, in this place, to add a little to what has already been done to the laſt of theſe ; namely,</p><p>INFINITE SERIES,</p><p>Is formed by dividing the numerator of a fraction by its denominator, that denominator being a compound quantity ; or by extracting the root of a ſurd.</p><p>An infinite ſeries is either <hi rend="italic">converging</hi> or <hi rend="italic">diverging.</hi></p><p>A converging ſeries is that in which the magnitude of the ſeveral terms gradually diminiſh ; and a diverging ſeries is that in which the ſucceſſive terms increaſe in magnitude.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">law of</hi> an infinite ſeries is the order in which the terms are obſerved to proceed. This law is often eaſily diſcovered from a few of the firſt terms of the ſeries ; and then the ſeries may be continued as far as may be thought neceſſary, without any farther diviſion, or evolution.</p><p>An infinite ſeries, as has already been obſerved, is obtained by diviſion or evolution ; but as that method is very tedious, various other methods have been propoſed for performing the ſame in a more eaſy manner ; as, by aſſuming a ſeries with unknown coefficients, by the binomial theorem, &amp;c.</p><p>I. <hi rend="italic">Of the Method of Series by Division and Evolution.</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Rule.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Let</hi> the diviſion or evolution of the given fraction, which is to be converted into an infinite ſeries, be performed as in Chapters I. and IV. of our article <hi rend="smallcaps">Algebra,</hi> and the required ſeries will be obtained.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Examples.</hi></p><p>From inſpection of the terms of this ſeries, it appears that each term is formed by multiplying the preceding term by <hi rend="italic">x ;</hi> and hence it may be continued as far as may be thought neceſſary without continuing the division.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0300.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0294"/>
In continuing the operation, thoſe terms may be neglected whoſe dimenſions exceed thoſe of the laſt term to which the root is to be continued.</p><p><hi rend="italic">II. Of the Method of Series by assuming a Series with unknown Coefficients.</hi></p><p>RULE. Aſſume a ſeries with unknown coefficients to repreſent that required. Let this ſeries be multiplied or involved, according to the nature of the queſtion ;and the quantities of the ſame dimenſion being put equal to each other, the coefficients will be determined; and hence the required ſeries will be known.</p><p>III. Oſ the Method of reducing a fractional Quantity into an infinite Series by the Binomial Theorem.</p><p>As this method has already been illuſtrated in the article Algebra, we ſhall therefore briefly state the theorem, and add a few examples.</p><p>Binomial Theorem.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0301.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0295"/>
In operations of this kind, the neareſt power to the given number, whether greater or leſs than it, is to be uſed, as by that means the ſeries will converge more quickly.</p><p>An infinite ſeries may be involved to any given power, or any proposed root of a given ſeries may be extracted by means of the following general theorem.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0302.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0296"/>
Now each term of the given series is to be compared above theorem ; and by ſubſtitution in the second, the with the correſpondent terms in the firſt part of the ſeveral terms of the required ſeries will be obtained.</p><p>Harmonic SERIES, a ſeries of terms formed in harmonical proportion. It has been already obſerved in the article Proportion, that if three numbers be in harmonical proportion, the firſt is to the third as the difference between the firſt and second is to the difference between the ſecond and third.</p><p>Again, let x be the fourth term, to find which in terms of a and b, we have</p><p>Whence the law of the ſeries is obvious, and it may be<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0303.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0297"/>
if, in a series of terms in harmonical proportion, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> be two affirmative quantities, and ſuch that <hi rend="italic">a&amp;lt;b ;</hi> then this series, which is poſitive at firſt, will become negative as ſoon as <hi rend="italic">n —</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">b</hi> exceeds <hi rend="italic">n—</hi> 1.a. But if <hi rend="italic">a&amp;gt;b</hi>, the series will converge, and although produced to infinity will not become negative.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> be equal to 2 and 1 respectively ; then this ſeries becomes 2/1 x 2/2 x 2/3 x 2/4, &amp;c. and ſince, if each term of an harmonical ſeries be divided by the ſame quantity, the ſeries will ſtill be harmonical. Therefore 1/1 x 1/2 x 1/3 x 1/4 x 1/5 &amp;c. is an harmonical ſeries: whence the denominators of this ſeries form a ſeries of numbers in arithmetical progreſſion ; and converſely, the reciprocals of an arithmetical progreſſion are in harmonical proportion.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Recurring SERIES</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ,</hi> a ſeries of which any term is formed by the addition of a certain number of preceding terms, multiplied or divided by any determinate numbers whether poſitive or negative. Thus 2. 3. 19. 101. 543. 2917. 15671, &amp;c. is a recurring ſeries, each term of which is formed by the addition of the two preceding terms, the firſt of which being previouſly multiplied by the constant quantity <hi rend="italic">2</hi> and the other by 5. Thus the third term 19 = 2 × 2 + 3 × 5; the fourth term 101 = 3 × 2 + 19 × 5, &amp;c.</p><p>The principal operation in a ſeries <hi rend="italic">of</hi> this nature is that of finding its film.—For this purpoſe, the two firſt and two laſt terms of the ſeries muſt be given, together with the confiant multipliers.</p><p>Let a, <hi rend="italic">b, c, d, e, f,</hi> &amp;c. be any number of terms of a ſeries formed according to the above law, each ſucceſſive term being equal to the ſum of the products of the two preceding terms, the firſt being multiplied by the given quantity m <hi rend="italic">,</hi> and the other by the given quantity <hi rend="italic">n.</hi> Hence we will have the following ſeries of equations c = ma + nb, d = mb + nc, e = mc + nd, f = md + ne <hi rend="italic">,</hi> &amp;c. Then adding theſe equations, we obtain c + d + e + f = m × a + b + c + n × b + c + d + e. Now the firſt member of this equation is the ſum of all the terms except the two firſt ; the quantity by which <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is multiplied in the ſecond member is the ſum of all the terms except the two laſt ; and that by which <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is multiplied is the ſum of all the terms except the firſt and laſt. Now let s = ſum of the ſeries ; then</p><p><hi rend="italic">Reversion of SERIES</hi> is the method of finding the value of the quantity whoſe ſeveral powers are involved in a ſeries, in terms of the quantity which is equ <hi rend="underline">al</hi> to the given ſeries.</p><p>In order to this, a ſeries muſt be affirmed, which being involved and ſubſtituted for the quantity equal to the ſeries, and its powers, neglecting thoſe terms whoſe powers exceed the higheſt power to which it is propoſed to extend the ſeries.</p><p>Let it be required to revert the ſeries ax + bx <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + cx <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> + dx <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> + ex <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi>, &amp;c. or, to find <hi rend="italic">x</hi> in an infinite ſeries expreſſed in the powers of <hi rend="italic">y.</hi></p><p>Subſtitute <hi rend="italic">y</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> n</hi> for <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> and the indices of the powers of y in the equation will be n, 2n, 3n, &amp;c. and 1, therefore n = 1; and the differences are 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 3. &amp;c. Hence, in this cafe, the ſeries to be aſſumed is Ay + By <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + Cy <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> + Dy <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi>, &amp;c. which being involved and ſubſtituted for the reſpective powers of <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> then we have<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0304.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0298"/>
<hi rend="italic">Summation of SERIES</hi> is the method of finding the sum of the terms of an infinite ſeries produced to infinity, or the ſum of any number of terms of ſuch a</p><p>Teries.</p><p>The value of any arithmetical ſeries, as 1 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 2 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.... n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, varies according as (n) the number of its terms varies ; and therefore, if it can be expressed in a general manner, it muſt be explicable by n and its powers with determinate coefficients ; and thoſe powers, in this caſe, muſt be rational, or ſuch whoſe indices are whole poſitive numbers ; becauſe the progreſsion, being a whole number, cannot admit of ſurd quantities. Laſtly, it will appear that the greateſt of the said indices cannot exceed the common index of the ſeries by more than unity : for, otherwiſe, when <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is taken indefinitely great, the higheſt power of n would be indefinitely greater than the ſum of all the reſt of the terms.</p><p>Thus the higheſt power of n, in an expreſſion exhibiting the value of 1 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 2 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.... n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, cannot be greater than n <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>; 1 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 2 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + 4 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.... n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, manifeſtly leſs than n <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, or n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +, &amp;c. continued to n terms ; but n <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi>, when <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is indefinitely great, is indefinitely greater than n <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>, or any other inferior power of n, and therefore cannot enter into the equation. This being premiſed, the method of inveſtigation may be as follows :<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0305.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0299"/>
To proceed farther would lead us far beyond the limits aſſigned for this article ; we muſt therefore refer thoſe who require more information on this ſubject to the following authors. Bertrand’s <hi rend="italic">Diveloppement,</hi> &amp;c. vol. I ; Dodson’s Mathematical Repoſitory, vol. I ; Emerſon’s Algebra ; Appendix to Graveſend’s Algebra; Hutton’s Paper on Cubic Equations and Infinite Series, in the Philoſophical Tranſactions for 1780, Maclaurin’s Fluxions; Malcolm’s Arithmetic ; Maſere’s Annuities ; and <hi rend="italic">Scriptores Logarithmici, &amp;c.</hi>; De Moivre’s Doctrine of Chances, and a Paper by the ſame author in the Philoſophical Tranſactions, n⁰ 240; Simpſon’s Algebra, Essays, Fluxions, and Miſcellanies ; Sterling’s <hi rend="italic">Summatio et Interpolatio Serierum ; Syntagma Mathesios, &amp;c.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>