<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0290.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0284-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEPTUAGINT</label>,
the name given to a Greek verſion of the books of the Old Teſtament, from its being ſuppoſed to be the work of ſeventy-two Jews, who are uſually called <hi rend="italic">the seventy interpreters,</hi> becauſe ſeventy is a round number.</p><p>The hiſtory of this verſion is expreſsly written by Arillæas, an officer of the guards to Ptolemy Philadelphus, the ſubſtance of whoſe account is as follows : Ptolemy having erected a fine library at Alexandria, which he took care to fill with the moſt curious and valuable books from all parts of the world, was informed that the Jews had one containing the laws of Moſes, and the hiſtory of that people ; and being deſirous of enriching his library with a Greek tranſlation of it, applied to the high-prieſt of the Jews ; and to engage him to comply with his requeſt, ſet at liberty all the Jews whom his father Ptolemy Soter had reduced to ſlavery. After ſuch a ſtep, he eaſily obtained what he deſired ; Eleazar the Jewiſh high-prieſt ſent back his ambaſſadors with an exact copy of the Moſaical law, written in letters of gold, and six elders of each tribe, in all ſeventy-two : who were received with marks of reſpect by the king, and then conducted into the iſle of Pharos, where they were lodged in a houſe prepared for their reception, and ſupplied with every thing neceſſary. They ſet about the tranſlation without loſs of time, and finiſhed it in ſeventy-two days: and the whole being read in the preſence of the king, he admired the profound wiſdom of the laws of Moſes ; and ſent back the deputies laden with preſents, for themſelves, the high- prieſt, and the temple.</p><p>Ariſtobulus, who was tutor to Ptolemy Phyſcon, Philo who lived in our Saviour’s time, and was contemporary with the apoſtles, and Joſephus, ſpeak of this tranſlation as made by 72 interpreters, by the care of Demetrius Phalereus in the reign of Ptolemy Philadelphus. All the Chriſtian writers, during the firſt 15 centuries of the Chriſtian era, have admitted this account of the Septuagint as an undoubted fact. But ſince the reformation, critics have boldly called it in queſtion, becauſe it was attended with circumſtances which they think inconſiſtent, or, at leaſt, improbable. Du Pin has aſked, why were 72 interpreters employed, ſince 12 would have been ſufficient ? Such an objection is trifling. We may as well aſk, why did king James I. employ 54 tranſlators in rendering the Bible into Engliſh, ſince Du Pin thinks 12 would have been ſufficient ?</p><p>1. Prideaux objects, that the Septuagint is not written in the Jewiſh, but in the Alexandrian, dialect ; and could not therefore be the work of natives of Paleſtine. But theſe dialects were probably at that time the ſame, for both Jews and Alexandrians had received the Greek language from the Macedonians about 50 years before.</p><p>2. Prideaux farther contends, that all the books of the Old Teſtament could not be tranſlated at the ſame time; for they exhibit great difference of ſtyle. To this it is</p><p>ſufficient to reply, that they were the work of 72 men, each of whom had ſeparate portions aſſigned them.</p><p>3. The Dean also urges, that Arillæas, Ariſtobulus, Philo, and Joſephus, all directly tell us, that the law was tranſlated without mentioning any of the other ſacred books. But nothing was more common among writers oſ the Jewiſh nation than to give this name to the Scriptures as a whole. In the New Teſtament law is uſed as ſynonymous with what we call the Old Teſtament. Beſides, it is expreſsly ſaid by Ariſtobulus, in a fragment quoted by Euſebius (<hi rend="italic">Preep. Evan.</hi> 1. I.),that the whole Sacred Scripture was rightly tranſlated through the means of Demetrius Phalereus, and by the command of Philadelphus. Joſephus indeed, says the learned Dean, aſſerts, in the preface to his Antiquities, that the Jewiſh interpreters did not tranſlate for Ptolemy the whole Scriptures, but the law only. Here the evidence is contradictory, and we have to determine, whether Ariſtobulus or Joſephus be moſt worthy of credit. We do not mean, however, to accuse either of forgery, but only to inquire which had the beſt opportunities of knowing the truth. Ariſtobulus was an Alexandrian Jew, tutor to an Egyptian king, and lived within 100 years after the tranſlation was made, and certainly had acceſs to ſee it in the royal library. Joſephus was a native of Paleſtine, and lived not until 300 years or more after the tranſlation was made, and many years after it was burnt along with the whole library of Alexandria in the wars of Julius Cæsar. Suppoſing the veracity of theſe two writers equal, as we have no proof of the contrary, which of them ought we to conſider as the beſt evidence? Ariſtobulus ſurely. Prideaux, indeed, ſeems doubtful whether there was ever ſuch a man; and Dr Hody ſuppoſes that the Commentaries on the five books of Moſes, which bear the name of Ariſtobulus, were a forgery of the ſecond century. To prove the exiſtence of any human being, who lived 2000 years before us, and did not perform ſuch works as no mere man ever performed, is a taſk which we are not dispoſed to undertake ; and we believe it would not be leſs difficult to prove that Philo and Joſephus exiſted, than that ſuch a perſon as Ariſtobulus did not exiſt. If the writings which have paſſed under his name were a forgery of the ſecond century, it is ſurprising that they ſhould have impoſed upon Clemens Alexandrinus, who lived in the ſame century, and was a man of abilities, learning, and well acquainted with the writings of the ancients. Euſebius, too, in his <hi rend="italic">Prœp. Evan.</hi> quotes the commentaries of Ariſtobulus. But, continues the learned Dean, “ Clemens Alexandrinus is the firſt author that mentions them. Now, had any ſuch commentaries exiſted in the time of Philo and Joſephus, they would ſurely have mentioned them. But is the circumſtance of its not being quoted by every ſucceeding author a ſufficient reaſon to diſprove the authenticity of any book ? Neither Philo nor Joſephus undertook to give a liſt of preceding authors, and it was by no means the uniform practice of theſe times always to name the authors from whom they derived their information.”</p><p>4. Prideaux farther contends, that the ſum which Ptolemy is ſaid to have given to the interpreters is too great to be credible. If his computation were juſt, it certainly would be ſo. He makes it L. 2,000,000<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0291.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0285"/>
Sterling, but other writers<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Blair's lectures on the Canon.</p></note> * reduce it to L. 85,42.l, and ſome to L. 56,947 ; neither of which is a ſum ſo very extraordinary in ſo great and magnificent a price as Philadelphus, who ſpent, according to a paſſage in Athenæus (lib. v.), no leſs than 10,000 talents on the furniture of one tent ; which is fix times more than what was ſpent in the whole of the embaſſy and tranſlation, which amounted only to 1552 talents.</p><p>5. Prideaux ſays, “ that what convicts the whole story of Ariſteas of falſity is, that he makes Demetrius Phalereus to be the chief actor in it, and a great favourite of the king ; whereas Philadelphus, as ſoon as his father was dead, call him into priſon, where he ſoon after died.”<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Stillingflett's Origines Sacrae.</p></note> But it may be replied, that Philadelphus reigned two years jointly with his father Lagus, and it is not ſaid by Hermippus that Demetrius was out of favour with Philadelphus during his father’s life. Now, if the Septuagint was tranſlated in the beginning of the reign of Philadelphus, as Euſebius and Jerome think, the difficulty will be removed. Demetrius might have been librarian during the reign of Philadelphus, and yet impriſoned on the death of Lagus. Indeed, as the cauſe of Philadelphus’s diſpleaſure was the advice which Demetrius gave to his father, to prefer the ſons of Arſinoe before the son of Berenice, he could ſcarcely ſhow it till his father’s death. The Septuagint tranſlation might therefore be begun while Philadelphus reigned jointly with his father, but not be finiſhed till after his father’s death.</p><p>6. Beſides the objections which have been conſidered, there is only one that deserves notice.<note anchored="false" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Prideaux's Connections, vol. iii. 1.</p></note> The ancient Chriſtians not only differ from one another concerning the time in which Ariſtobulus lived, but even contradict themſelves in different parts of their works. Sometimes they tell us, he dedicated his book to Ptolemy Philometer, at other times they ſay, it was addreſſed to Philadelphus and his father. Sometimes they make him the ſame perſon who is mentioned in 2 Maccabees, chap 1. and ſometimes one of the 72 interpreters 152 years before. It is difficult to explain how authors fall into ſuch inconſiſtencies, but it is probably occaſioned by their quoting from memory. This was certainly the practice of almoſt all the early Chriſtian writers, and ſometimes of the apoſtles themſelves. Miſtakes were therefore inevitable. Joſephus has varied in the circumſtances of the ſame event, in his antiquities and wars of the Jews, probably from the ſame cauſe ; but we do not hence conclude, that every circumſtance of such a relation is entirely false. In the account of the Marquis of Argyle’s death in the reign of Charles II. we have a very remarkable contradiction. Lord Clarendon relates, that he was condemned to be hanged, which was performed the same day : on the contrary, Burnet, Woodrow, Heath, Echard, concur in ſtating, that he was beheaded; and that he was condemned upon the Saturday and executed upon the Monday<note anchored="true" n="4" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Biograph. Britan.</p></note> *. Was any reader of Engliſh hiſtory ever sceptic enough to raiſe from hence a queſtion, whether the Marquis of Argyle was executed or not ? Yet this ought to be left in uncertainty according to the way of reaſoning in which the facts reſpecting the tranſlation of the Septuagint is attempted to be disproved.</p><p>Such are the objections which the learned and ingenious Prideaux has raised againſt the common account of the Septuagint tranſlation, and ſuch are the answers which may be given to them. We have choſen to ſupport that opinion which is ſanctioned by hiſtorical evidence, in preference to the conjectures of modern critics however ingenious; being perſuaded, that there are many things recorded in hiſtory, which, though perfectly true, yet, from our imperfect knowledge of the concomitant circumſtances, may, at a diſtant period, ſeem liable to objections. To thoſe who require positive evidence, it may be ſtated thus. Aristæas, Ariſtobulus, Philo, and Joſephus, aſſure us, that the law was tranſlated. Taking the law in the most reſtricted ſenſe, we have at leaſt ſufficient authority to assert, that the Pentateuch was rendered into Greek under Ptolemy Philadelphus. Ariſtobulus affirms, that the whole Scriptures were tranſlated by the 72. Joſephus confines their labours to the books of Moſes. He therefore who cannot determine to which of the two the greateſt reſpect is due, may ſuſpend his opinion. It is certain, however, that many of the other books were tranſlated before the age of our Saviour; for they are quoted both by him and his apoſtles : and, perhaps, by a minute examination of ancient authors, in the ſame way that Dr Lardner has examined the Chriſtian fathers to prove the antiquity of the New Teſtament, the preciſe period in which the whole books of the Septuagint were compoſed might, with conſiderable accuracy, be aſcertained.</p><p>For 400 years this tranſlation was in high eſtimation with the Jews. It was read in their ſynagogues in preference to the Hebrew ; not only in thoſe places where Greek was the common language, but in many ſynagogues of Jeruſalem and Judea. But when they ſaw that it was equally valued by the Chriſtians, they became jealous of it, and at length, in the ſecond century, Aquila, an apoſtate Chriſtian, attempted to ſubſtitute another Greek tranſlation in its place In this work he was careful to give the ancient prophecies concerning the Meſſiah a different turn from the Septuagint, that they might not be applicable to Chriſt. In the same deſign he was followed by Symmachus and Theodotion, who alſo, as St Jerome informs us, wrote out of hatred to Chriſtianity.</p><p>In the mean time, the Septuagint, from the ignorance, boldneſs, and careleſſneſs of tranſcribers, became full of errors. To correct theſe, Origen publiſhed a new edition in the beginning of the third century, in which he placed the tranſlations of Aquila, Symmachus, and Theodotion. This edition was called T <hi rend="italic">etrapla,</hi> the tranſlations being arranged oppoſite to one another in four columns. He alſo added one column, containing the Hebrew text in Hebrew letters, and another exhibiting it in Greek. In a ſecond edition he publiſhed two additional Greek verſions; one of which was found at Nicopolis, and the other at Jericho : this was called the <hi rend="italic">Hexapla.</hi> By comparing ſo many tranſlations, Origen endeavoured to form a correct copy of the Scriptures. Where they all agreed, he conſidered them right. The passages which he found in the LXX, but not in the Hebrew text, he marked with an obeliſk ; what he found in the Hebrew, but not in the LXX, he marked with an aſteriſk St Jerome ſays, that the additions which Origen made to the LXX, and marked with an aſteriſk, were taken from Theodotion. From this valuable work of Origen the verſion of the LXX was tranſcribed in a ſeparate volume, with the aſteriſks and<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0292.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0286"/>
obeliſks for the uſe of the churches ; and from this circumſtance the great work itſelf was neglected and loſt.</p><p>About the year 300 two new editions of the LXX were publiſhed; the one by Heſychius an Egyptianbiſhop, and the other by Lucian a preſbyter of Antioch. But as theſe authors did not mark with any note of diſtinction the alterations which they had made, their edition does not poſſeſs the advantages of Origen’s.</p><p>The beſt edition of the LXX is that of Dr Grabe, which was publiſhed in the beginning of the preſent century. He had acceſs to two MSS, nearly of equal antiquity, the one found in the Vatican library at Rome, the other in the Royal library at St James’s, which was preſented to Charles I. by Cyril, patriarch of Alexandria, and hence is commonly called the <hi rend="italic">Alexandrine MS.</hi> Anxious to diſcover which of theſe was according to the edition of Origen, Dr Grabe collected the fragments of the Hexapla, and found they agreed with the Alexandrian MS. but not with the Vatican where it differed with the other. Hence he concluded that the Alexandrine MS. was taken from the edition of Origen. By comparing the quotations from ſcripture in the works of Athanaſius and St Cyril (who were patriarchs of Alexandria at the time St Jerome ſays Heſychius’s edition of the LXX was there uſed) with the Vatican MS. he found they agreed ſo well that he juſtly inferred that that MS. was taken from the edition of Heſychius.</p><p>This version was in uſe to the time of our bleſſed Saviour, and is that out of which moſt of the citations in the New Teſtament, from the Old, are taken. It was alſo the ordinary and canonical tranſlation made uſe of by the Chriſtian church in the earlieſt ages ; and it ſtill ſubſiſts in the churches both of the eaſt and west.</p><p>Thoſe who deſire a more particular account of the Septuagint tranſlations may conſult Hody <hi rend="italic">de Bibliorum Textibus,</hi> Prideaux’s Connections, Owen’s Inquiry into the Septuagint Verſion, Blair’s Lectures on the Canon, and Michaelis’s lntroduction to the New Teſtament, laſt edition.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Septuagint</hi> <hi rend="italic">Chronology,</hi> the chronology which is formed from the dates and periods of time mentioned in the Septuagint tranſlation of the Old Teſtament. It reckons 1500 years more from the creation to Abraham than the Hebrew bible. Dr Kennicot, in the diſſertation prefixed to his Hebrew bible, has ſhown it to be very probable that the chronology of the Hebrew ſcriptures, ſince the period juſt mentioned, was corrupted by the Jews, between the years 175 and 200, and that the chronology of the Septuagint is more agreeable to truth. It is a fact, that during the ſecond and third centuries the Hebrew ſcriptures were almoſt entirely in the hands of the Jews, while the Septuagint was confined to the Chriſtians. The Jews had therefore a very favourable opportunity for this corruption. The following is the reaſon which is given by oriental writers : It being a very ancient tradition, that the Meſſiah was to come in the ſixth chiliad, becauſe he was to come in the laſt days (founded on a myſtical application of the six days creation), the contrivance was <hi rend="italic">to shorten the age of the world from about 5500 to</hi> 3760 ; <hi rend="italic">and thence to prove that Jeſus could not be the Meſſiah.</hi> Dr Kennicot adds, that ſome Hebrew copies having the larger chro</p><p>nology were extant till the time of Euſebius, and ſome till the year 700.</p></div></body></text></TEI>