<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0318.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0312-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SERRANUS</label>
(Joannes), or John de Serres, a learned French Proteſtant, was born about the middle of the ſixteenth century. He acquired the Greek and Latin languages at Lauſanne, and grew very fond of the philoſophy of Ariſtotle and Plato. On his return to France he ſtudied divinity. He began to diſtinguiſh himſelf in 1572 by his writings, but was obliged to forſake his country after the dreadful maſſacre of St Bartholomew. He became miniſter of Niſmes in 1582, but was never regarded as a very zealous Calviniſt : he has even been ſuſpected, though without reaſon, of having actually abjured the Proteſtant religion. He was one of the four clergymen whom Henry IV. conſulted about the Romiſh religion, and who returned for anſwer, <hi rend="italic">that Catholics might be ſaved.</hi> He wrote afterwards a treatiſe in order to reconcile the two communions, entitled <hi rend="italic">De fide Catholica, five de principiis religionis Christianœ, Communi omnium Chriſtianorum conſenſu, ſemper et ubique ratis.</hi> This work was diſliked by the Catholics, and received with ſuch indignation by the Calviniſts of Geneva, that many writers have affirmed that they poiſoned the author. It is certain at leaſt that he died at Geneva in 1598, at the age of 50. His principal works are, 1. A Latin tranſlation of Plato, publiſhed by Henry Stephens, which owes much of its reputation to the elegance of the Greek copy which accompanies it. 2. A Treatiſe on the Immortality of the Soul. 3 <hi rend="italic">De statu religionis et republicae in Francia.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Memoire de la me guerre civile et derniers troubles de France fous Charles IX. &amp;c. 5. Inventaire general de l'Histoire de France, illustre par la conference de l'Eglise et de l'Empire, idle.</hi> 6. <hi rend="italic">Recueil de chose memorable avenue en France sous Henri II François IL Charles IX. Henri III.</hi> Theſe three hiſtorical treatiſes have been juſtly accuſed of partiality and paſſion ; faults which it is next to impoſſible for a contemporary writer to avoid, eſpecially if he bore any part in the tranſactions which he deſcribes. His ſtyle is exceedingly incorrect and inelegant ; his miſtakes too and misſtatements of facts are very numerous.</p></div></body></text></TEI>