<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0240.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0234-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SECOND</label>,
in geometry, chronology, &amp;c. the 60th part of a prime or minute, whether of a degree or of an hour.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Second,</hi> in muſic, one of the muſical intervals; being only the difference between any found and the next neareſt found, whether above or below it.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Second</hi> <hi rend="italic">Major,</hi> in muſic. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Interval.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Second</hi> <hi rend="italic">Minor,</hi> in muſic. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Interval.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Second</hi> <hi rend="italic">Sight,</hi> in Erſe called <hi rend="italic">Taiſch,</hi> is a mode of feeing ſuperadded to that which nature generally her flows. This gift or faculty, which is neither voluntary<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0241.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0235"/>
nor constant, is in general rather troubleſome than agreeable to the poſſeſſors of it, who are chiefly found among the inhabitants of the Highlands of Scotland, thoſe of the Weſtern Iſſes, of the Iſle of Man, and of Ireland. It is an impreſſion made either by the mind upon the eye, or by the eye upon the mind, by which things diſtant or future are perceived, and ſeen as it they were preſent. A man on a journey far from home falls from his horſe; another, who is perhaps at work about the houſe, ſees him bleeding on the ground, commonly with a landſcape of the place where the accident befals him. Another ſeer, driving home his cattle, or wandering in idleneſs, or muſing in the ſunſhine, is ſuddenly ſurpriſed by the appearance of a bridal ceremony, or funeral proceſſion, and counts the mourners or attendants, of whom, if he knows them, he relates the names; if he knows them not, he can deſcribe the dreſſes. Things diſtant are ſeen at the inſtant when they happen.</p><p>Of things future, Johnſon ſays that he knows no rule pretended to for determining the time between the ſight and the event; but we are informed by Mr Groſe, that in general the time of accompliſhment bears ſome relation to the time of the day in which the impreſſions are received. Thus viſions ſeen early in the morning (which ſeldom happens) will be much ſooner accompliſhed than thoſe appearing at noon; and thoſe ſeen at noon will take place in a much ſhorter time than thoſe happening at night; ſometimes the accompliſhment of the laſt does not fall out within a year or more.</p><p>Theſe viſions are not confined to ſolemn or important events; nor is it true, as is commonly reported, that to the ſecond light nothing is preſentcd but phantoms of evil. The future viſit of a mountebank, or piper; a plentiſul draught of fiſh; the arrival of common travellers; or, if poſſible, ſtill more trifling matters than theſe, are foreſeen by the ſeers. A gentleman told Dr Johnſon, that when he had once gone far from his own iſland one of his labouring ſervants predicted his return, and deſcribed the livery of his attendant, which he had never worn at home; and which had been, without any previous deſign, occaſionally given him.</p><p>As many men eminent for ſcience and literature have admitted the reality of this apparently uſeleſs gift, we ſhall, without interpoſing our own opinion, give the reflections of two of the firſt characters of the age upon it, and leave our readers to form their own judgment. By Dr Beattie of Aberdeen it is thus accounted for.</p><p>The Highlands of Scotland are a pictureſque but a melancholy country. Long tracts of mountainous defert, covered with dark heath, and often obſcured by miſty weather; narrow valleys, thinly inhabited, and bounded by precipices reſounding with the fall of torrents; a ſoil ſo rugged, and a climate ſo dreary, as in many parts to admit neither the amuſements of paſturage nor the labours of agriculture; the mourntul daſhing of waves along the friths and lakes that interſect the country; the portentous noiſes which every change of the wind and every increaſed diminution of</p><p>the waters is apt to raiſe in a lonely region full, of echoes and rocks and caverns; the groteſque and ghaſtly appearance of ſuch a landſcape by the light of the moon: objects like theſe diffuſe a gloom over the fancy, which may be compatible enough with occaſional and ſocial merriment, but cannot fail to tincture the thoughts of a native in the hour of ſilence and ſolitude. If theſe people, notwithſtanding their reformation in religion, and more frequent intercourſe with ſtrangers, do ſtill retain many of their old ſuperſtitions, we need not doubt but in former times they muſt have been much more enſlaved to the horrors of imagination, when beſet with the bugbears of Popery and Paganiſm. Moſt of their ſuperſtitions are of a melancholy caſt. That of <hi rend="italic">ſecond ſight,</hi> by which ſome are ſtill ſuppoſed to be haunted, is conſidered by themſelves as a misfortune, on account of the many dreadful images it is laid to obtrude upon the fancy. It is ſaid that ſome of the Alpine regions do likewiſe lay claim to a fort of ſecond fight. Nor is it wonderful, that perſons of a lively imagination, immured in deep ſolitude, and ſurrounded with the ſtupendous ſcenery of clouds, precipices, and torrents, ſhould dream (even when they think themſelves awake) of thoſe few ſtriking ideas with which their lonely lives are diverſified: of corpſes, funeral proceſſions, and other ſubjects of terror; or of marriages, and the arrival of ſtrangers, and ſuch like matters of more agreeable curioſity.</p><p>Let it be obſerved alſo, that the ancient Highlanders of Scotland had hardly any other way of ſupporting themſelves than by hunting, fiſhing, or war; profeſſions that are continually expoſed to fatal accidents. And hence, no doubt, additional horrors would often haunt their ſolitude, and a deeper gloom overſhadow the imagination even of the hardieſt native.</p><p>A ſufficient evidence can hardly be found for the reality of the <hi rend="italic">ſecond sight,</hi> or at leaſt of what is commonly Underſtood by that term. A treatiſe on the ſubject was publiſhed in the year 1762, in which many tales were told of perſons whom the author believed to have been ſavoured, or haunted, with theſe illuminations; but moſt of the tales were trifling and ridiculous: and the whole work betrayed, on the part of the compiler, ſuch extreme credulity, as could not fail to prejudice many readers againſt his ſyſtem.</p><p>That any of theſe viſtonaries are apt to be ſwayed in their declarations by ſiniſter views, we will not ſay; but this may be ſaid with confidence, that none but ignorant people pretend to be gifted in this way. And in them it may be nothing more, perhaps, than ſhort fits of ſudden ſleep or drowſineſs, attended with lively dreams, and ariſing from ſome bodily diſorder, the effect of idleneſs, low ſpirits, or a gloomy imagination. For it is admitted, even by the moſt credulous Highlanders, that as knowledge and induſtry are propagated in their country, the ſecond ſight diſappears in proportion: and nobody ever laid claim to the faculty who was much employed in the intercourſe of ſocial life<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> This, however, is denied by Johnſon, who affirms that the Iſſanders of all degrees, whether of rank or underſtanding, univerſally admit it except the miniſters, who, according to him, reject it, in conſequenee of a ſyſtem, againſt conviction. He affirms, too, that in 1773 there was in the Hebrides a ſecond-ſighted gentleman, who complained of the terrors to wſhich he was expoſed.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi><pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0242.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0236"/>
Nor is it at all extraordinary, that one ſhould have the appearance of being awake, and ſhould even think one’s ſelf ſo, during thoſe fits of doſing; that they ſhould come on ſuddenly, and while one is engaged in ſome buſineſs. The ſame thing happens to perſons much fatigued, or long kept awake, who frequently fall aſleep for a moment, or for a long ſpace, while they are ſtanding, or walking, or riding on horſeback. Add but a lively dream to this ſlumber, and (which is the frequent effect of diſeaſe) take away the conſciouſneſs of having been aſleep, and a ſuperſtitious man may eaſily miſtake his dream for a waking viſion; which, however, is ſoon forgotten when no fubſequent occurrence recals it to his memory; but which, if it ſhall be thought to reſemble any future event, exalts the poor dreamer into a Highland prophet. This conceit makes him more recluſe and more melancholy than ever; and ſo feeds his diſeaſe, and multiplies his viſions: which, if they are not diſſipated by buſineſs or ſociety, may continue to haunt him as long as he lives; and which, in their progreſs through the neighbourhood, receive ſome new tinctures <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the marvellous from every mouth that promotes their circulation. As to the prophetical nature of this ſecond ſight, it cannot be admitted at all. That the Deity ſhould work a miracle in order to give intimation of the frivolous things that theſe tales are made up of, the arrival of a ſtranger, the nailing of a coffin, or the colour of a ſuit of clothes; and that theſe intimations ſhould be given for no end, and to thoſe perſons only who are idle and ſolitary, who ſpeak Gaelic, or who live among mountains and deferts—is like nothing in nature or providence that we are acquainted with; and muſt therefore, unleſs it were confirmed by ſatisfactory proof (which is not the caſe), be rejected as abſurd and incredible.</p><p>Theſe viſions, ſuch as they are, may reaſonably enough be aſcribed to a diſtempered fancy. And that in them, as well as in our ordinary dreams, certain appearances ſhould, on ſome rare occaſions, reſemble certain events, is to be expected from the laws of chance; and ſeems to have in it nothing more marvellous or ſupernatural, than that the parrot, who deals out his ſcurrilities at random, ſhould ſometimes happen to ſalute the paſſenger by his right appellation.</p><p>To the confidence of theſe objections Dr Johnſon replies, that by preſuming to determine what is fit, and what is beneficial, they preſuppofe more knowledge of the univerſal ſyſtem than man has attained; and therefore depend upon principles too complicated and extensive for our comprehenſion; and that there can be no ſecurity in the conſequence when the premiſes are not underſtood; that the ſecond ſight is only wonderful becauſe it is rare, for, conſidered in itſelf, it involves no more difficulty than dreams, or perhaps than the regular exerciſe of the cogitative faculty; that a general opinion of communicative impulſes, or viſionary repreſentations, has prevailed in all ages and all nations; that particular inſtances have been given with ſuch evidence, as neither Bacon nor Bayle has been able to reſiſt; that ſudden impreſſions, which the event has verified, have been felt by more than own or publiſh them; that the ſecond ſight of the Hebrides implies only the local frequency of a power, which is nowhere totally unknown; and that where we are unable to decide by antecedent reaſon, we muſt be content to yield to the force of teſtimony. By pretenſion to ſecond ſight, no profit was ever ſought <hi rend="italic">or</hi> gained. It is an involuntary affection, in which neither hope nor fear are known to have any part. Thoſe who profeſs to feel it do not boaſt of it as a privilege, nor are conſidered by others as advantageouſly diſtinguiſhed. They have no temptation to feign, and their hearers have no motive to encourage the impoſture.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Second</hi> <hi rend="italic">Terms</hi>, in algebra, thoſe where the unknown quantity has a degree of power leſs than it has in the term where it is raiſed to the higheſt. The art of throwing theſe ſecond terms out of an equation, that is, of forming a new equation where they have no place, is one of the moſt ingenious and uſeful inventions in all algebra.</p></div></body></text></TEI>