<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0289.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0283-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEPTARIÆ</label>,
in natural hiſtory, a large claſs of foſſils, commonly known by the names of <hi rend="italic">ludus Helmontii</hi> and wa <hi rend="italic">xen veins.</hi></p><p>They are defined to be foſſils not inflammable, nor soluble in water ; of a moderately firm texture and duſky hue, divided by ſeveral ſepta or thin partitions, and compoſed of a ſparry matter greatly debaſed by earth ; not giving fire with ſteel ; fermenting with acids, and in great part diſſolved by them ; and calcining in a moderate fire.</p><p>Of this claſs there are two diſtinct orders of bodies, and under thoſe six genera. The septariæ of the first order are thoſe which are uſually found in large maſſes, of a simple uniform conſtruction, but divided by large ſepta either into larger and more irregular portions, or into ſmaller and more equal ones, called <hi rend="italic">talc.</hi> The genera of this order are four. 1. Thoſe divided by ſepta of ſpar, called se <hi rend="italic">comiœ .</hi> 2. Thoſe divided by ſepta of earthy matter, <hi rend="italic">called gaiophragmia ;</hi> 3. Thoſe divided by ſepta of the matter of the pyrites, called <hi rend="italic">pyritercia</hi>: And, 4. Thoſe divided by ſepta of ſpar, with an admixture of cryſtal, called <hi rend="italic">diaugophragmia.</hi></p><p>Thoſe of the ſecond order are ſuch as are uſually found in ſmaller maſſes, of a cruſtated ſtructure, formed by various incruſtations round a central nucleus, and divided by very thin ſepta. Of this order are only two genera. 1. Thoſe with a ſhort roundiſh nucleus, inclosed within the body of the maſs ; and, 2. Thoſe with a long nucleus, ſtanding out beyond the ends of the maſs.</p></div></body></text></TEI>