<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0326.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0320-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SETACEOUS <hi rend="smallcaps">worm,</hi></label>
 in natural hiſtory, a name given by Dr Lifter to that long and Tender water- worm, which ſo much reſembles a horſe-hair, that, it has been ſuppoſed by the vulgar to be an animated hair of that creature. Theſe creatures, ſuppoſed to be living hairs,are a peculiar ſort of infects, which are bred and nouriſhed within the Todies of other infects, as the worms of the ichneumon flies are in the bodies of the caterpillars.</p><p>Aldrovand deſcribes the creature, and tells us it was unknown to the ancients ; but called <hi rend="italic">ſeta aquatica,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vermis setarius,</hi> by the moderns, either from its figure reſembling that of a hair, or from the ſupposition of its once having been the hair of some animal. We generally ſuppoſe it, in the imaginary ſtate of the hair, to have belonged to a horſe ; but the Germans ſay it was once the hair of a calf, and call it by a name signifying <hi rend="italic">vitulus aquaticus,</hi> or the “ water calf.”</p><p>Albertus, an author much reverenced by the common people, has declared that this animal is generated of a hair ; and adds, that any hair thrown into ſanding water, will, in a very little time, obtain life and motion. Other authors have diſſented from this opinion, and ſupposed them generated of the fibrous roots of water- plants ; and others, of the parts of graſshoppers fallen into the water. This laſt opinion is rejected by Al- drovand as the most improbable of all. Standing and foul waters are most plentifully ſtored with them ; but they are ſometimes found in the eleareſt and pureſt ſprings, and ſometimes out of the water, on the leaves of trees and plants, as on the fruit-trees in our gardens, and the elms in hedges. They are from three to five inches long, of the thickneſs of a large hair; and are<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0327.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0321"/>
brown upon the back, and white under the belly, and the tail is white on every part.</p></div></body></text></TEI>