<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0341.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0335-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHAMOIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Chamois,</hi></label>
 or <hi rend="smallcaps">Shammy,</hi> a kind of leather, either dreſſed in oil or tanned, much eſteemed for its ſoftneſs, pliancy, &amp;c. It is prepared from the ſkin of the chamois, or ſhamois, a kind of rupicapra, or wild goat, called alſo iford, inhabiting the mountains of Dauphiny, Savoy, Piedmont, and the Pyrenees. Belides the ſoftneſs and warmth of the leather, it has the faculty of bearing ſoap without damage ; which renders it very uſeful on many accounts,</p><p>In France, &amp;c. ſome wear the ſkin raw, without any preparation. Shammy leather is uſed for the purifying of mercury, which is done by paſſing it through the pores of this ſkin, which are very cloſe. The true chamois leather is counterfeited with common goat, kid, and even with ſheep ſkins, the practice of which makes a particular profeſſion, called by the French <hi rend="italic">chamoiſure.</hi> The laſt, though the leaſt eſteemed, is yet ſo popular, and ſuch vaſt quantities of it are prepared, eſpecially about Orleans, Marſeilles, and Tholouſe, that it may not be amiſs to give the method of preparation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Manner of ſhamoiſing, or oſ preparing ſheep, goat, or kid ſkins in oil, in imitation of ſhammy.—</hi> The ſkins, being waſhed, drained, and ſmeared over with quicklime on the fleſhy side, are folded in two lengthwiſe, the wool outwards, and laid on heaps, and ſo left to ferment eight days, or, if they had been left to dry after flaying, then fifteen days.</p><p>Then they are waſhed out, drained, and half dried ; laid on a wooden leg, or horſe, the wool ſtripped off with a round ſtaff for that purpoſe, and laid in a weak pit, the lime whereof had been uſed before, and has lost the greateſt part of its force.</p><p>After 24 hours they are taken out, and left to drain 24 more ; they are then put in another ſtronger pit. This done, they are taken out, drained, and put in again, by turns ; which begins to diſpoſe them to take oil ; and this practice they continue for six weeks in ſummer, or three months in winter : at the end whereof they are waſhed out, laid on the wooden log, and the ſurface of the ſkin on the wool side peeled off, to render them the ſoſter ; then made into parcels, ſteeped a night in the river, in winter more, ſtretched six or ſeven over one another on the wooden leg, and the knife paſſed ſtrongly on the flesh side, to take off any thing superfluous, and render the ſkin ſmooth. Then they are ſteeped, as before, in the river, and the same operation is repeated on the wool side ; they are then thrown into a tub of water, with bran in it, which is brewed among the ſkins till the greateſt part flicks to them, and then ſeparated into diſtinct tubs, till they ſwell, and rife of themſelves above the water. By this means the remains of the lime are cleared out ; they are then wrung out, hung up to dry on ropes, and ſent to the mill, with the quantity of oil neceſſary to ſcour them : the beſt oil is that of ſtock-fiſh. Here they are firſt thrown in<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0342.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0336"/>
bundles into the river for 12 hours, then laid in the mill-trough, and fulled without oil till they be well ſoftened ; then oiled with the hand, one by one, and thus formed into parcels of four ſkins each ; which are milled and dried on cords a ſecond time ; then a third ; and then oiled again, and dried. This proceſs is repeated as often as neceſſity requires ; when done, if there be any moiſture remaining, they are dried in a ſtove, and made up into parcels wrapped up in wool ; after ſome time they are opened to the air, but wrapped up again as before, till ſuch time as the oil ſeems to have loſt all its force, which it ordinarily does in 24 hours. The ſkins are then returned from the mill to the chamoiſer to be ſcoured : which is done by putting them in a lixivium of wood-aſhes, working and beating them in it with poles, and leaving them to ſteep till the ley hath had its effect ; then they are wrung out, ſteeped in another lixivium, wrung again ; and this is repeated till all the greaſe and oil be purged out. When this is done, they are half dried, and paſſed over a ſharpedged iron inſtrument, placed perpendicular in a block, which opens, softens, and makes them gentle. Laſtly, they are thoroughly dried, and paſſed over the ſame inſtrument again ; which finiſhes the preparation, and leaves them in form of shammy.</p><p>Kid and goat-ſkins are ſhamoiſed in the ſame manner as thoſe of sheep, excepting that the hair is taken off without the uſe of any lime ; and that when brought from the mill they undergo a particular preparation called <hi rend="italic">ramalling,</hi> the moſt delicate and difficult of all the others. It conſiſts in this, that, as ſoon as brought from the mill, they are ſteeped in a fit lixivium, taken out, ſtretched on a round wooden leg, and the hair is ſcraped off with the knife ; this makes them ſmooth, and in working to caſt a kind of fine knap. The difficulty is in ſcraping them evenly.</p></div></body></text></TEI>