<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0341-01" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0359.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>REGGIO DI CALABRIA</label>
a city of Italy, in the province of its own name, formerly Calabria Ulteriore Priina, is admirably situated on the Strait of Messina some miles farther south than the city of Messina on the other side. It is the terminus of the railway round the south-east coast from Bari; a scheme for a line along the west coast to Naples received legislative sanction in 1879. The luxuriant gardens and orchards of Reggio have been celebrated for centuries, and the climate is so warm that even the date-palm occasionally ripens its fruit. The old city was in great part destroyed by the earthquake of 1783, and it is now built on a regular plan, with broad streets running north and south and cross streets climbing the hill from the seaside. Besides the cathedral (rebuilt since the earthquake), the principal edifices are the chamber of commerce, the new comizio agrario, the castle on the height, the Renaissance Palazzo Musitano Guerrera, and the Gothic Villa Leo. Local manufactures are essences, scented waters, silks, and byssus gloves, caps, and shoes. Extensive improvements have since 1870 been made on the port of Reggio both by the municipality and the Government; in 1883 787 vessels (209,717 tons) entered and 713 (207,179) cleared. Oil, lemons, and similar fruits, essences, silk, and grain are the staple exports. The population of Reggio was, in 1881, 23,853 in the city, or including the various suburban villages—Sbarre (3622), Santa Catarina (1147), &amp;c.—35,437, and in the commune 39,296.</p><p>A colony, mainly of Chalciilians, partly of Messenians from the Peloponnesus, settled at Rhegium (Regium) in the 8th century B.c. About 494 b.c. Anaxilas, a member of the Messenian party, made</p><p>himself master both of Regium and Zanele (Messina). In 427 it joined the Athenians against Syracuse, but in 415 it remained neutral. An attack which it made on Dionysius of Syracuse in 399 was the beginning of a great struggle which in 387 resulted in its complete destruction and the dispersion of its inhabitants as slaves. Restored by the younger Dionysius under the name of Phcebias, the colony soon recovered its prosperity and resumed its original designation. In 280, when Pyrrhus invaded Italy, the Regines admitted within their walls a Roman garrison of Campanian troops; these mercenaries revolted, massacred the male citizens, and held possession of the city till in 270 they were besieged and destroyed by the Roman consul Genucius. Though one of the cities promised by the triumvirs to the veterans, Regium escaped through the favour of Octavius (hence Regium Julium). Alaric (410 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> Totila (549), and Robert Guiscard (1060) all occupied the city. It was at Reggio that Joseph Bonaparte received the title of king of the Two Sicilies. In 1860 the Bourbon garrison surrendered to the Garibaldians.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>