<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0264-04" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0282.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RAMBOUILLET</label>
chief town of an arrondissement in the department of Seine-et-Oise, France, 30 miles southwest of Paris on the line to Brest, is a small place of 5186 inhabitants, and derives its whole interest from the associations connected with the ancient chateau, which stands surrounded by a beautiful park of 2965 acres and a wide forest dating from the 14th century. A great machicolated tower and some apartments with good woodwork still remain. The gardens, partly in French, partly in English style, are picturesque, and have an avenue of Louisiana cypress unique in Europe. The park contains the national sheep-farm, where the first flock of merino sheep in France was raised last century. The school of sheep-farming is of recent foundation. Here, too, is the first military school erected for soldiers’ children.</p><p>Originally a royal domain, the lands of Rambouillet passed in the 14th century to the D’Angennes family, who held them for 300 years and built the château. Francis I. died there in 1547 ; and Charles IX. and Catherine de’ Medici found a refuge in the chateau in the wars of religion, as Henry III. did after them. The famous marquise de Rambouillet is separately noticed below. Created a duchy and peerage in favour of the duke of Toulouse, son of Louis XIV., Rambouillet was subsequently bought and embellished by Louis XVI., who erected a model farm, sheep establishment, and other buildings. The place was a hunting-seat of Napoleon I. and Charles X., and it was here that in 1830 the latter signed his abdication.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>