<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">The Russian Empire</hi></p>
            <p>The Russian empire stretches over a vast territory in E. Europe and N. Asia, with an
                area exceeding 8,660,000 sq. m., or one-sixth of the land surface of the globe (one
                twenty-third of its whole superficies). It is, however, but thinly peopled on the
                average, including only one-twelfth of the inhabitants of the earth. It is almost
                entirely confined to the cold and temperate zones. In Novaya Zemlya and the Taimyr
                peninsula, it projects within the Arctic Circle as far as 77° 6' and 77° 40' N.
                respectively; while its S. extremities reach 38° 50' in Armenia, 35° on the Afghan
                frontier, and 42° 30' on the coasts of the Pacific. To the W. it advances as far as
                20° 40' E. in Lapland, 17° in Poland, and 29° 42' on the Black Sea; and its E.
                limit—East Cape on the Bering Strait—is in 191° E.</p>
            <p>The White, Barents and Kara Seas of the Arctic bound it on the N., and the northern
                Pacific—that is, the Seas of Bering, Okhotsk and Japan—bounds it on the E. The
                Baltic, with the Gulfs of Bothnia and Finland, limits it on the N.W.; and two
                sinuous lines of land frontier separate it respectively from Sweden and Norway on
                the N.W. and from Prussia, Austria and Rumania on the W. On the S. and E. the
                frontier has changed frequently according to the expansion and contraction of the
                empire under the pressure of political exigency and expedience. The Black Sea is
                the principal demarcating feature on the S. of European Russia. On the W. side of
                that sea the S. frontier touches the Danube for some 120 m.; on the E. side of the
                same sea it zigzags from the Black Sea to the Caspian, utilizing the river
                Aras (Araxes) for part of the distance. As the Caspian is virtually a Russian sea,
                Persia may be said to form the next link in the S. boundary of the Russian empire,
                followed by Afghanistan. On the Pamirs Russia has since 1885 been conterminous
                with British India (Kashmir); but the boundary then swings away N. round Chinese
                Turkestan and the N. side of Mongolia, and, since 1904-5, it has skirted the N. of
                Manchuria, being separated from it by the river Amur. As thus traced, the boundary
                in Central Asia includes the two khanates of Bokhara and Khiva, which, though
                nominally protected states, are to all intents and purposes integral parts of the
                Russian empire. But it excludes Manchuria, with the Liao-tung peninsula and
                Port Arthur, upon which Russia only placed her grasp in 1898-99, a grasp which she
                was compelled by Japan to release after the war of 1904-5. The total length of the
                frontier line of the Russian empire by land is 2800 m. in Europe, and nearly 10,000
                m. in Asia, and by sea over 11,000 m. in Europe and</p>
            <p>between 19,000 and 20,000 m. in Asia.</p>
            <p>Russia has no oceanic possessions; her islands are all appendages of the mainland to
                which they belong. Such are Karlo, East Kvarken, the Aland archipelago, Dago, and
                Osel or Oesel in the Baltic Sea; Novaya</p>
            <p>Zemlya, with Kolguyev and Vaigach, in the Barents Sea; the Solovetski Islands in the
                White Sea; the New Siberian archipelago, Wrangel Land and Bear Islands, off the
                Siberian coast; the Commander Islands off Kamchatka; the Shan tar Islands and the N.
                of Sakhalin in the Sea of Okhotsk. The Aleutian archipelago was sold to the United
                States in 1867, together with Alaska, and in 1875 the Kurile Islands were ceded to
                Japan.</p>
            <p>If the border regions, that is, two narrow belts, on the N. and S., be left out of
                account, a striking uniformity of physical feature prevails throughout the whole
                vast extent of the Russian empire. High plateaus like that of Pamir (the “ Roof of
                the World ”) and Armenia, and lofty mountain chains like the snow-clad Caucasus, the
                Alai, the Tian-shan, the Sayan Mountains, exist only on the out</p>
            <p>skirts of the empire.</p>
            <p>Viewed broadly, the Russian empire may be said to occupy the territories to the N.W.
                of the great plateau formation of the old continent—the backbone of
                Asia—which stretches with decreasing altitude and width from the high tableland of
                Tibet and Pamir to the lower plateaus of Mongolia, and thence N.E. through the
                Vitim</p>
            <p>region to the farthest extremity of Asia. Thus it consists of the immense plains and
                flat lands which extend between the plateau formation and the Arctic Ocean,
                including the series of parallel chains and hilly spurs which skirt the
                former region on the N.W. And it is only to the E. of Lake Baikal that it climbs up
                on to the plateau, from which it descends again before it reaches the Pacific.</p>
            <p>This plateau formation—the oldest geological continent of Asia— being unfit for
                agriculture, and for the most part unsuited for permanent settlement, while its
                oceanic slopes have from the dawn of history been occupied by a relatively dense
                population, long prevented Slav colonization from reaching the.Pacific. The
                Russians chanced to cross it in the 17th century at its narrowest and most N. part,
                and thus struck the Pacific on the foggy and <hi rend="italic">froze n</hi>
                shores of the Sea of Okhotsk; but two centuries elapsed ere, after colonizing the
                depressions around Lake Baikal, they crossed over the plateau in a more genial zone
                and descended to the Pacific by the Amur. After that they spread rapidly S., up to
                the nearly uninhabited valley of the Usuri, to what is now the Gulf of Peter the
                Great. In the S.W. higher portions of the plateau formation the empire has
                only comparatively recently planted its foot on the Pamir, and it was only a few
                years earlier that it established itself firmly on the highlands of Armenia.</p>
            <p>A broad belt of hilly tracts—in every respect alpine in character, and displaying the
                same variety of climate and organic life as alpine tracts usually do—skirts the
                plateau formation throughout its entire length on the N. and N.W., forming an
                intermediate region between the plateau and the plains. .The Caucasus, the Elburz,
                the Kopet-dagh and Paropamisus, the intricate and imperfectly known network of
                mountains W. of the Pamir, the Tian-shan and the Ala-tau mountain regions,
                and farther N.E. the Altai, the still unnamed complex of the Minusinsk Mountains,
                the intricate mountain-chains of Sayan, with those of the Olekma, Vitim and Aldan
                all arranged <hi rend="italic">en échelon—</hi>the former from N.W. to S.E., and the
                others from S.W. to N.E.—all these belong to the same alpine belt that borders the
                plateau from end to end of the series.</p>
            <p>The flat lands which extend from the base of the Alpine foothills to the shores of
                the Arctic Ocean, assume the character either of dry deserts, as in the Aral-Caspian
                depression, or of low tablelands, as in central Russia and E. Siberia, of lacustrine
                regions in N.W. Russia and Finland, or of marshy prairies in W. Siberia, and of <hi
                    rend="italic">tundras</hi> in the far N. Throughout the whole of this vast area,
                their monotonous surfaces are diversified by only a few, and, for the most part,
                low, hilly tracts. Recently emerged, from the Post-Pliocene sea., or freed
                from their mantle of ice, they persistently maintain the self-same features over
                immense areas; and the few portions that rise above the general elevation have more
                the character of broad and gentle swellings than of mountain-chains. Of this class
                are the swampy plateaus of the Kola peninsula, sloping gently S. to the lacustrine
                region of Finland and N.W.. Russia; the Valdai tablelands, where all the great
                rivers of Russia take their rise ; the broad and gently sloping meridional belt of
                the Ural Mountains; and lastly the Taimyr, Tunguzka and Verkhoyansk ranges in
                Siberia, which, notwithstanding their sub-Arctic position, do not reach
                the snow-line. The picturesque Bureya Mountains above the Amur, the forest-clad
                Sikhota-ahn on the Pacific., and the volcanic chains of Kamchatka belong, however,
                to quite another orographical construction, being the border-ridges of the terraces
                by which the great plateau formation descends to the depths of the Pacific
                Ocean.</p>
            <p>It is.owing to these leading orographical features—divined by Carl Ritter, but only
                recently ascertained and established as fact by geographical research—that so many
                of the great rivers of the old continent are comprised within the limits of
                the.Russian empire. Taking their rise on the plateau formation, or in its outskirts,
                they flow first along lofty longitudinal valleys formerly filled with great lakes,
                next they cleave their way through the rocky barriers, and finally they enter the
                lowlands, where they become navigable, and, describing wide curves to avoid here
                ana there the minor plateaus and hilly tracts, they bring into water-communication
                with one another places thousands of miles apart. The double river-systems of the
                Volga and Kama, the Ob and Irtysh, the Angara and Yenisei,.the Lena and Vitim on the
                Arctic slope, and the Amur and Sungari on the Pacific slope, are instances. These
                were the obvious channels of Russian colonization.</p>
            <p>A broad depression—the Aral-Caspian desert—has arisen where the plateau formation
                reaches its greatest altitude, and at the same time suddenly changes its direction
                from N.W. to N.E. This desert is now filled to only, a small extent by the salt
                waters of the Caspian, Aral and Balkash inland seas; but it bears unmistakable
                traces of having been during Post-Pliocene times an immense inland basin. There the
                Volga, the Ural, the Syr-darya and the Amu-dap'a discharge their waters without
                reaching the ocean, but they bring life to the rapidly desiccating Transcaspian
                steppes, and link together the most remote parts of Russia.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Geology.—</hi>The most striking feature in the geology of Russia is
                its</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
