<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and Wrangdike hundred are mentioned in the middle of the 12th century, the latter formerly including the additional hundred of Little Casterton. The shire-court for Rutland was held at Oakham.</p><p>Rutland was originally included in the diocese of Lincoln, and in 1291 formed a rural deanery within the archdeaconry of Northampton; but on the erection of Peterborough to an episcopal see by Henry VIII. in 1541, the archdeaconry' of Northampton, with the deanery of Rutland, was transferred to that diocese. In 1879 the deanery of Rutland was subdivided into three portions, and in 1876 it was placed within the newly-founded archdeaconry of Oakham.</p><p>Among the most conspicuous of the Norman lords connected with this county was Walkelin de Ferrers, who founded Oakham Castle in the 12th century. The castle was subsequently bestowed by Richard II., together with the earldom of Rutland (see above), on Edward, son of Edmund, duke of York. Essendine (Essenden or Essingdon) was purchased in 1545 by Richard Cecil of Burleigh, and the title of baron of Essenden bestowed on his grandson is retained by the carls of Salisbury. Sir Everard Digby, one of the conspirators in the Gunpowder plot, belonged to the family of Digby, of Stoke Dry. Burley-on-the-hill was held by Henry Despenser, the warlike bishop of Norwich, in the reign of Richard II., and was purchased by George Villiers, duke of Buckingham, who entertained James I. there with Ben Jonson’s <hi rend="italic">Mask of the Gypsies.</hi></p><p>The battle of Stamford was fought at Horn, near Exton, in March 1470 between Edward IV. and the Lancastrians, when from the precipitate flight of the latter the engagement became known as Losecoat Field. On the outbreak of the Civil War Rutland displayed a strong puritanical and anti-royalist sentiment, and in 1642 the sheriff and a large number of the gentry and nobility of the county forwarded a petition to the House of Lords begging that the county might be placed in a state of defence, and that the votes of papists and prelates might be disallowed; and again, in 1648, a memorial addressed to Lord Fairfax protested against the design of the parliament to treat with Charles.</p><p>' Rutland has always been mainly an agricultural county. The Domesday Survey mentions numerous mills in Rutland, and a fishery at Ayston rendered 325 eels. In the 14th century the county exported wool. Stilton cheese has long been made in Leyfield Forest and the vale of Catmose, and limestone is dug in many parts of the county. The development of the economic resources of Rutland was helped in 1793 by the extension of the Melton Mowbray canal to Oakham.</p><p>Two members were returned to parliament for the county of Rutland from 1295 until under the Redistribution of Seats Act of 1885 the representation was reduced to one member.</p><p>The only old castle of which there are important remains is Oakham, dating from the time of Henry II. and remarkable for its Norman hall. Of Essendine Castle only the moat remains. The Bede-house at Liddington dates from the end of the 14th century. Hambleton Hall, now a farm-house, is a good specimen of Jacobean architecture. Many old houses of the 17th and 18th centuries are to be met with in the villages. An interesting feature of the ecclesiastical architecture of the county is the frequent continuation of the round-headed arch after the Early English style had become fully developed; as, for instance, in the Early English churches at Great Casterton, Stretton, Empingham, Clipsnam (Early English and Decorated), and St Peter’s, Preston, where the nave arcade is Norman on one side and Early English on the other, but yet retains round-headed arches on both sides. Tickencote church is a remarkable specimen of. late Norman work, with one of the finest chancel-arches extant in this style. Ketton church is transitional Norman, Early English, and early Decorated, the broach spire being of later date. St Mary’s., Greet ham, is a good example of Decorated, with fine tower and spire.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Victoria County History, Rutland",</hi>  James Wright, <hi rend="italic">Hi story and Antiquities of the County of Rutland</hi>  (London, 168^); T. Blore, <hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities of the County of Rutland,</hi>  vol. 1. pt. 2 (containing the East hundred and including the hundred of Casterton Parva; Stamford, 1811); C. G. Smith, <hi rend="italic">A Translation of that portion of Domesday Book which relates to Lincolnshire and Rutland</hi>  (London, 1870).</p><p>RUTLAND, a city and the county seat of Rutland county, Vermont, U.S.A., on Otter creek, about 67 m. S. by E. of</p><p>Burlington. Pop. (1900) 11,499, of whom 1533 were foreign-bom; (1910 census) 13,546. Area, SJ sq. m. It is served by the Delaware &amp; Hudson (being a terminus of one of its branches) and the Rutland (New York Central system) railways. It is pleasantly situated within sight of the Green Mountains. Among its public buildings and institutions are the United States Government Building, the State House of Correction, the Rutland Free Library (1886, with 17,500 volumes in 1908), the H. H. Baxter Memorial Library, a Memorial Hall, the County Court House, the City Hall, and the City Hospital. The famous Rutland marble is quarried in W. Rutland (pop. in 1910, 3427 and Proctor (pop. in 1910, 2871), which were parts of the township of Rutland until 1886. In 1905 the value of the city’s factory products was $2,522,856 (28-8% more than in 1900). The township of Rutland was granted by New Hampshire in 1761 to John Murray of Rutland, Massachusetts, and about the same time it was granted (as Fairfield) by New York. No settlement was made until 1770, and in 1772 the place was again granted by New York under the name of Socialborough. From 1784 to 1804 Rutland was one of the capitals of Vermont, and the Capitol, built in 1784, is the second oldest building in the state. The <hi rend="italic">Rutland Herald,</hi>  one of the oldest newspapers in Vermont still published, was established as a Federalist weekly in 1794*—a daily edition first appeared in 1861, and is now Republican. In 1847 the village of Rutland was incorporated, and in 1892 a portion of the township including the village was chartered as a city.</p><p>RUTLEDGE, JOHN (1739-1800), American jurist and politician, was born in Charleston, South Carolina, in 1739. • He studied law in London and began to practise in Charleston in 1761. He was a delegate to the Stamp Act Congress in 1765, and to the Continental Congress in 1774-77 and 1782-83; he was chairman of the committee which framed the state constitution of 1776, and the first “ president ” (governor) of South Carolina in 1776-78. Disapproving of certain changes in the constitution, he resigned in 1778, but was elected governor in the following year, and served until 1782. From 1784 to 1789 he was a member of the state court of chancery. In the Constitutional Convention of 1787 he urged that the president and the Federal judges should be chosen by the national legislature, and preferably by the Senate alone, and that the president should be chosen for a term of seven years, and should be ineligible to succeed himself. Rutledge championed the Constitution in the South Carolina convention by which that instrument was adopted on behalf of the state. He was associate justice of the United States Supreme Court in 1789-91, and chief justice of the supreme court of South Carolina in 1791-95. Nominated chief justice of the Supreme Court of the United States in 1795, he presided during the August term, but the Senate refused to confirm the nomination, apparently because of his opposition to the Jay Treaty. His mind failed late in 1795, and he died in Charleston on the 23rd of July 1800.</p><p>His brother, Edward Rutledge (1749-1800), a signer of the Declaration of Independence, was born in Charleston on the 23rd of November 1749. He studied law in his brother’s office, and in London in 1769-73, and began to practise in Charleston in 1773. He served in the Continental Congress in 1774-77, and was sent with John Adams and Benjamin Franklin to confer on terms of peace with Lord Howe on Staten Island in September 1776. As captain of artillery and later as lieutenant-colonel he served against the British in South Carolina in 1779-80, but he was captured near Charleston in 1780, and was imprisoned at St Augustine, Florida, for a year. He was a member of the state legislature from 1782 to 1798, and in 1791 drafted the act which abolished primogeniture in South Carolina. From 1798 until his death in Charleston, on the 23rd of January 1800, he was governor of South Carolina.</p><p>RUTLEY, FRANK (1842-1904), English geologist and petrog-rapher, was born at Dover on the 14th of May 1842. He was educated partly at Bonn, but his interest in geology was kindled at the Royal School of Mines, where he studied from 1862-64; he then joined the army, and served as lieutenant until 1867,</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>