<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>when he became an Assistant Geologist on the Geological Survey. Working then in the Lake district, he began to make a special study of rocks and rock-forming minerals, and soon qualified as acting petrographer on the Geological Survey. For several years he worked in this capacity at the Museum in Jermyn Street: he described the volcanic rocks of E. Somerset and the Bristol district in 1876, and wrote special memoirs on <hi rend="italic">The Eruptive Rocks of Brent Tor</hi>  (1878), and on <hi rend="italic">The Felsiiic Lavas of England and Wales</hi>  (1885). He was the author of an exceedingly useful little book on <hi rend="italic">Mineralogy</hi>  (1874; 12th cd., 1900); also of <hi rend="italic">The Study of Rocks</hi>  (1879; 2nd cd., 1881), <hi rend="italic">Rock-forming Minerals</hi>  (1888), and <hi rend="italic">Granites and Greenstones </hi>(1894); and of a number of petrographical papers, dealing with perlitic and sphcrulitic structures, with the rocks of the Malvern Hills, &amp;c. In 1882 he was appointed lecturer on Mineralogy in the Royal College of Science, and held this post until ill-health compelled him to retire in 1898. He died in London on the 16th of May 1904.</p><p>Obituary (by H. B. Woodward), with bibliography, in <hi rend="italic">GeoL Mag. </hi>(July 1904).</p><p>RUTUL1, a people of ancient Italy inhabiting Ardea and the district round it on the coast of Latium, at no great distance from Aricia, and just W. of the territory of the Volsci. They are ranked by the form of their name with the Siculi and Appuli (Apuli), probably also with the Itali, whose real Italic name would probably have been Vituli (see Italy). This suggests that they belong to a fairly early stratum of the Indo-European population of Italy. The same is suggested by the tradition adopted or moulded by Virgil, by which the leader of the people of the soil in their resistance to the settlement of Aeneas was the Rutulian prince Turnus, a name which, if any conjecture could be founded on it, might be held to point rather to Etruria than to any pure Italic source; he is represented as the <hi rend="italic">hospes</hi>  of the exiled Etruscan king Mezentius, and as taking up arms to defend him against his angry subjects. Pliny (iii. § 6) classes them, with the Siculi, among the primitive tribes that at one time or another inhabited part of Latium, and it is to be observed that they are not included in the thirty Latin communities who once took part in the Latin Festival on the Alban Mount (see further Siculi).    (R. S. C.)</p><p>RUVIGNY, HENRI DE MASSUE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquis de, afterwards Earl of Galway (1648-1720), was born at Paris on the 9th of April 1648, and was the son of the 1st Marquis de Ruvigny, a distinguished French diplomatist, and a relative of Rachel, the wife of Lord William Russell. He saw service under Turenne, who thought very highly of him. Probably on account of his English connexions he was selected in 1678 by Louis XIV. to carry out the secret negotiations for a compact with Charles II., a difficult mission which he executed with great skill. Succeeding his father as “ general of the Huguenots/’ he refused Louis’s offer, at the revocation of the Edict of Nantes, to retain him in that office, and in 1690, having gone into exile with his fellow Huguenots, he entered the service of William III. of England as a major-general, forfeiting thereby his French estates. In July 1691 he distinguished himself at the battle of Aughrim, and in 1692 he was for a time commander-in-chief in Ireland. In November of that year he was created Viscount Galway and Baron Portarlington, and received a large grant of forfeited estates in Ireland. In 1693 he fought at Neerwinden and was wounded, and in 1694, with the rank of lieutenant-general, he was sent to command a force in English pay which was to assist the duke of Savoy against the French, and at the same time to relieve the distressed Vaudois. But in 1695 the duke changed sides, the Italian peninsula was neutralized, and Galway’s force was withdrawn to the Netherlands. From 1697 to 1701, a critical period of Irish history, the Earl of Galway (he was advanced to that rank in 1697) was practically in control of Irish affairs as lord justice of Ireland. After some years spent in retirement, he was appointed in 1704 to command the allied forces in Portugal, a post which he sustained with honour and success until the battle of Almanza in 1707, in which Galway, in spite of care and skill on his own part, was decisively defeated. But he scraped together a fresh army, and, although infirm, was reappointed to his command by the home government. After taking part in one more campaign, and distinguishing himself by his personal bravery in action, he retired from active life. His last service was rendered in 1715, when he was sent as one of the lords justices to Ireland during the Jacobite insurrection. As most of his property in Ireland had been restored to its former owners, and all his French estates had long before been forfeited, parliament voted him pensions amounting to £1500 a year. He died unmarried on the 3rd of September 1720. The English peerage died with him, but not the French marquisate.@@</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>RUVO, a town and episcopal see of Apulia, Italy, in the province of Bari, 21m. W. of the city of that name by steam tramway, 853 ft. above sea-level. Pop. (1901) 25,245. The cathedral, a basilica with a very lofty nave (so high, indeed, that the gable of the façade is only slightly above the steep sloping roofs of the aisles, and the clerestory is very small), and with two aisles, has three apses, a square campanile and a rich façade with three portals. It belongs probably to the 13th century. The interior has a fine triforium; it contains some interesting frescoes of the 15th century, and is unique in Apulia in having a gallery supported by corbels round the nave (see A. Avena, <hi rend="italic">Monumenti dell’ Italia Méridionale,</hi>  Rome, 1902, 117). S. Giovanni Rotondo is an ancient circular baptistery with two large fonts. In the Palazzo Jatta is a famous and beautiful collection of vases and coins found in the Apulian tombs around the city; part of these, however, are now to be found in the museum at Naples. The Palazzo Spinola has an interesting Renaissance court. Ruvo occupies the site of the ancient Rubi, on the Via Trajana (see Appia, Via). Coins were issued by the city before it became Roman.    (T. As.)</p><p>RUWENZORI, more correctly Runsoro, said to be known also as Kokora, a mountain range in Central Africa, lying just north of the equator, and intersected near its eastern edge by 30° E. It has a length of about 65 m., with a maximum breadth of about 30 m., and its highest peaks rise above the limits of perpetual snow. The range as a whole, the major axis of which runs a little east of north, falls steeply on the west to the Central African rift-valley traversed by the Semliki, the western head-stream of the Nile, while on the east the fall is somewhat more gradual towards the highlands of western Uganda. The upper parts are separated by fairly low passes into six groups of snowy summits, lying a little to the west of the central line, rising in each case more than 15,000 ft. above the sea and reaching, in the culminating point of the western group (Mount Stanley), about 16,800 ft.</p><p>The origin of the range seems connected with that of the rift-valley on the west, both being due to vertical displacements of the earth’s crust. Ruwenzori has been formed by an upheaval <hi rend="italic">en masse</hi>  of a portion of the archaean floor of the continent, bounded east and west by lines of fracture, but resulting in a general dip from west to east. A further upheaval seems to have produced an ellipsoidal anticline, causing the strata to dip outwards at a generally high angle. Traces of volcanic action are almost non-existent. Composed in its outer parts of gneisses and mica-schists offering no great resistance to denudation, in its centre the range consists of much more refractory rocks (amphibolites, diorites, diabases, &amp;c.), to which fact, coupled with the existence of vertical fractures, the persistence and separation of the higher summits is probably due. The snow-clad area does not now extend more than ten miles in any direction, though there is abundant evidence that the glaciers were formerly far more extensive.</p><p>The upper region is almost entirely enveloped by day in thick cloud, which ^descends on the east to about 9000 ft., and lower still on the west. It sometimes lifts towards evening, giving a sight of the snowy peaks, but by 9 a.m. these have</p><p>@@@The later Viscounts Galway are descended from John Monckton (1695-1751), who was created viscount in 1727. His first wife’s mother, wife of the 2nd duke of Rutland, was a daughter of Lady William Russell, and thus a connexion of the Ruvignys.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>