<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>saturated by being laid in powdered sulphur maintained for some hours at about i io<hi rend="sup">6</hi> C. Sheets sulphured in this way can be made up into articles and joined together either by warming the parts to be united,, or.by means of indiarubber solution; after which the true vulcanization, or “ curing,” as it is termed, can be brought about in the usual way.</p><p>Another method of vulcanizing articles made from cut sheet rubber consists in exposing them to the action of chloride of sulphur. Either they are placed in a leaden cupboard into which the vapour is introduced, or they are dipped for a few seconds in a mixture of one part of chloride of sulphur and forty parts of carbon disulphide or purified light petroleum. Vulcanization takes place in this instance without the action of heat; but it is usual to subject the goods for a short time to a temperature of 40° C. after their removal from the solution, in order to drive off the liquid which has been absorbed, and to ensure a sufficient action of the chloride of sulphur. Treatment with a warm alkaline solution is afterwards advisable, in order to remove traces of hydrochloric acid generated during the process. Another very excellent method of vulcanizing cut sheet goods consists in placing them in a solution of the polysulphides of calcium at a temperature of 140° C. Rubber employed for the manufacture of cut sheets is often coloured by such pigments as vermilion, oxide of chromium, ultramarine, orpiment, antimony, lamp black, or oxide of zinc, incorporation being effected either by means of the masticator or by a pair of rollers heated internally by steam, and so geared as to move in contrary directions at unequal</p><p>speed (fig. 9). Most of the rubber now manufactured is not combined with sulphur when in the form of sheets, but is mechanically incorporated with about one-tenth of its weight of that substance by means of the mixing rollers—any required pigment or other matter, such as whiting or. barium sulphate, being added. The mixed rubber thus obtained is readily softened by heat, and can be very easily worked into any desired form or rolled into sheets by an apparatus known as the calendering machine. Vulcanization is then ensured by exposure for half an hour or more to a temperature of I35°-I5O° C., usually in closed iron vessels into which high-pressure steam is admitted (fig. 10). Tubes are generally made up around mandrels, and allowed throughout the curing to remain imbedded in pulverized French chalk, which affords a useful support for many articles . that tend to lose their shape during the process. Of late years a considerable amount of seamless tubing has been made, much in the.same way as lead piping, by forcing the mixed rubber through a die, and curing as above. The calendered sheets are generally cured between folds of wet cloth, the markings of which. . they retain; and hollow articles, such as playing balls or injection bottles, are vulcanized in iron or brass moulds, tinned inside and very slightly greased. Before it is put in, the article is roughly put together, and the expansion of the included air forces the rubber into contact with the internal surface of the mould, or a little carbonate of ammonia is enclosed. Belting intended for driving machinery is built up of canvas which has been thoroughly frictioned with the soft mixed rubber, and is cured by placing it in a kind of press kept by means of steam at a dry heat of about 140 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> C. Packing for the stuffing boxes of steam engines is similarly prepared from strips of rubber and frictioned canvas, as also are the so-called insertion sheets, in which layers of rubber alternate with.canvas or even wire gauze. Indiarubber stereotypes are now extensively made use of as hand stamps, and attempts nave been made to introduce them for press and machine printing. A plaster cast of the type is, when dry, saturated with shellac varnish and redried. Rubber mixed in the usual way with about 10% of sulphur is now softened by heat, forced into the mould, and retained there by pressure during the operation of curing, which is usually effected in an iron box heated over a gas burner to 140° C.</p><p>The ordinary macintosh or waterproof cloth is prepared by spreading on the textile fabric layer after layer of indiarubber paste or solution made with benzol or coal-naphtha. If cotton or linen is used, it is usual to incorporate sulphur with the paste, and to effect vulcanization by steam heat; but, when, silk or wool is employed, no sulphur is added to the paste, the»dried coating of rubber being merely brought into momentary contact with the mixture of chloride of sulphur and carbon disulphide already mentioned. Double texture goods are made by uniting the rubber surfaces of two pieces of the coated material. Air goods, such as cushions, beds, gas bags, and so forth, are made of textile fabrics which have been coated with mixed rubber either by the spreading process above described, or by means of heated rollers, the curing being then effected by steam heat. The manufacture of overshoes and fishing boots is an analogous process, only the canvas base is more thickly coated with a highly pigmented rubber of low quality. The articles are first fashioned by joining the soft material; they are then varnished, and afterwards cured in ovens heated to about 135° C. The fine vulcanized “ spread sheets ” are made by spreading layers of indiarubber solution, already charged with the requisite proportion of sulphur, on a textile base previously prepared with a mixture of paste, glue and treacle; Vulcanization is then effected by steam heat, and, the preparation on the cloth being softened by water, the sheet of rubber is readily removed. The required thickness of the spread sheet is very often secured by the rubber-faced surfaces of two cloths being united before curing. The threads used in making elastic webbing are usually cut from spread sheets. The manufacture of. springs, valves and washers does not require any very special notice, these articles being generally fashioned out of mixed rubber, and vulcanized either in moulds or in powdered French chalk. Rollers are made to adhere to their metal spindles by the intervention of a layer of ebonite, and after vulcanization they are turned. In order to make spongy or porous rubber, some material is incorporated which will give off gas or vapour at the vulcanizing temperature,—such as carbonate of ammonia, crystallized alum, and finely ground damp sawdust. Uncombincd sulphur is injurious, and often leads to the decay of vulcanized goods, but an excess of sulphur is generally required in order to ensure perfect vulcanization. Sometimes the excess is partially removed by boiling the finished goods with a solution of caustic soda, or some other solvent of sulphur. In other cases the injurious effects of free sulphur are obviated by using instead of it a metallic sulphide,— generally the orange sulphide of antimony; but, for the best results,' it. is necessary that this should contain from 20 to 30 % of uncombined sulphur.</p><p>It will thus be seen that for nearly all practical purposes, including tires, vulcanized rubber mixed with mineral matter is employed. Such articles contain varying proportions of rubber (12-60%), about 1-2 % of. combined sulphur, and from 25-70 % of mineral matter. Vulcanized rubber is also now largely used as an electrical insulator for the construction of cables, &amp;c.<hi rend="sub">(</hi> instead of gutta-percha.</p><p>When the vulcanization of rubber is carried too far, from the presence of a very large proportion of sulphur and an unduly long action of heat, the caoutchouc becomes hard., horn-like, ana often black. Rubber hardened by over-vulcanization is largely manufactured under the name of ebonite or vulcanite. It is usually made by incorporating about 40 % of sulphur with purified Borneo rubber by means of the usual mixing rollers, shaping the required articles out of the mass thus obtained, and heating for six, eight or ten hours to from 135® to 150°. Ebonite takes a fine polish, and is valuable to the electrician on account of its insulating properties, and to the chemist and photographer because vessels made of it are unaffected by most chemical reagents. A kind of vulcanite which contains a large proportion of vermilion or other mineral pigment is used, under the name of dental rubber, for making artificial gums and supports for artificial teeth.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Literature.—Henri Jumelle, </hi><hi rend="italic">Les Plantes à caoutchouc et à gutta</hi>  (Paris, 1903); Dr O. Warburg, <hi rend="italic">Les Plantes à caoutchouc et leur culture</hi>  (Paris, 1902; French translation by J. Vilbouchevitch); Herbert Wright, <hi rend="italic">Hevea brasiliensis or Para Rubber</hi>  (Colombo, 1908); <hi rend="italic">Rubber in the East: the official account of the Ceylon Rubber Exhibition, iqo6,</hi>  edited by J. C. Willis, M. Kelway Bamber and E. B. Denham (Colombo, 1906) ; Yves Henry, <hi rend="italic">Le Caoutchouc dans V Afrique occidentale française</hi>  (Paris, 1906); E. de Wildeman and L. Gentil, <hi rend="italic">Lianes caoutckoutifères de l'État Indépendant du Congo</hi>  (Brussels, 1904); C. O. Weber, <hi rend="italic">The Chemistry of Indiarubber</hi>  (London, 1902); Selected papers from the <hi rend="italic">Kew Bulletin,</hi>  iii. ” Rubber ” (London, 1906); <hi rend="italic">Kew Bulletin,</hi>  1906-9; <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the Imperial Institute,</hi></p><p>(W. R. D.)</p></body></text></TEI>