<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>crews increased 19½%, the number of men employed in the latter year being
                approximately 150,000.</p>
            <p>In i860 Russia possessed less than 1000 m. of railways; by 1885 this had increased to
                16,155 19., and by the middle of 1905 there were open for traffic over 40,500 m. of
                railway, of which 34,150 m. or 84*3 % were in European Russia and nearly</p>
            <p>6400 m. (15*7 %) in Asiatic Russia. Between 1895 and 1905 the building of railways
                proceeded at a rapid rate, the total length nearly doubling within the ten years,
                namely, from 22,600 to 40,500 m. The European railways cost on an average £10,465
                per mile to construct, and the Asiatic railways £5092 per mile.</p>
            <p>A considerable number of new railways, some of great strategic as well as commercial
                importance, were built during the last twenty years of the 19th century. At the same
                time the chief lines of railway which had been built by public companies with a
                state guarantee, and which represented a loss to the empire of £3,171,250 per annum,
                as well as a growing indebtedness, were bought by the state. On the whole, the state
                derives profit from its railways, although several of the later lines, while
                imperative for state purposes, must necessarily yield but a very small revenue, or
                be worked at a loss. The most important of the new railways is the Siberian, of
                which the first section, Chelyabinsk to Omsk, was opened in December 1895, and
                which, except for a short section round Lake Baikal, in 1901 was completed right
                through to Stryetensk, on the Shilka, the head of navigation on the Shilka and the
                Amur, 2710 m. from Chelyabinsk and 4076 miles from Moscow, via Samara
                and Chelyabinsk. The section round the S. end of Lake Baikal was completed in 1905.
                At the Pacific end of the Siberian railway a line connecting Vladivostok with
                Khabarovsk (479 m.) at the junction of the Amur and the Usuri, was first of all
                built, following the valley of the Usuri. But it was soon found that the cost of
                the section^required to complete the railway between Stryetensk and Khabarovsk,
                along the Shilka (246 m.) and the Amur (1160 m.), would be enormous, while neither
                the wild mountainous tracts of the lower Shilka and upper Amur, nor the marshy,
                often inundated region between Khabarovsk and the Little Khingan mountains, could
                ever be the seat of a numerous population. Consequently a company was formed by the
                Russian government in 1896 to construct, with the consent of the Chinese government,
                a railway from Vladivostok across Manchuria to Karymskaya near Chita in
                Transbaikalia. This runs for 222 m. on Russian territory and for 1080 m. on
                Manchurian territory, and from Kharbin sends off a branch to Dalny near Port Arthur
                on the Liao-tung peninsula. The first portion of the Manchurian railway, built by
                Russian engineers, with Chinese labour, was finished in 1902. At . the same
                time several secondary lines were built in connexion with the Siberian line.
                Chelyabinsk was linked by a transverse line with the middle Urals railway, which
                connects Perm, the head of navigation in the Volga basin, with Tyumen, the head of
                navigation on the Ob and Irtysh, passing through Ekaterinburg and other mining
                centres of the middle Urals. Tomsk is now connected with the main line by a short
                side branch. A railway has also been built to connect Perm with Kotlas, near the
                confluence of the Sukhona with the .Yug, at the head of the N. Dvina. This N.
                portion of the Russian railway system was further completed by the opening in 1906
                of a line from St Petersburg via Vologda to Vyatka, intersecting the
                Moscow-Arthangel line at Vologda.</p>
            <p>Another line of great strategic importance was built across the Transcaspian
                territory to Ferghana. Starting from Krasnovodsk, it runs S.E. to Merv (560 m.),
                with a branch line (194 m.) to Kushk, near Herat, then N.E. across the desert to
                Charjui, on the Amur river, Bokhara and the Russian fort Katta-kurgan, and then
                to Samarkand, Kokand and Andijan in Ferghana, 710 m. from Merv, with a branch to
                Tashkent (220 m.). This railway has become important for the export of raw cotton
                from Central Asia to Russia. In 1905 a second totally independent line was opened
                from Tashkent | down the Syr-darya to Kazalinsk, and thence to Orenburg.</p>
            <p>A third line of great importance is the junction line between the Transcaucasian
                railway—which runs from Batum and Poti to, Baku, via Tiflis, with a branch line to
                Kars—and the railway system of Russia proper. This junction has been effected not
                across the main Caucasus range, but at its E. extremity, that is, via the
                Caspian ports of Baku and Petrovsk, which are connected with Vladikavkaz (Beslan
                junction). The Black Sea j)ort of Novorossiysk, in W. Caucasia, having been
                connected with the Rostov-Vladikavkaz line, has consequently also been brought into
                touch with the Russian railways. The Volga is reached from central Russia by seven
                lines of railways, including one to Kazan, and three main lines radiate from the
                Volga E. (one to Siberia and two to the Ural river), while the upper Volga
                (Yaroslavl) is connected with Archangel by a line 523 m. long. A zone tariff was
                introduced on the Russian railways in 1894, and the cost of long journeys was
                considerably reduced; a journey of 623 m. can be made third class at a cost of only
                about 17 shillings, while for less than twice as much 1990 m. can be covered.</p>
            <p>Fish form an important article of national food. The numerous fasts of the national
                church prescribe a fish diet on many days in the year, and the continuous frost of
                winter is favourable to the transportation of fish for great distances. Along
                the</p>
            <p>Murman coast of the Arctic Ocean and in the White Sea, where many millions of
                herrings are caught annually by some 3000 persons, the yearly producers estimated at
                the value of £140,000. In the Baltic Sea, as well as in the lakes of its basin
                (Ladoga, Onega, llmefi, &amp;e.), the yearly value is estimated at £200,000. Of
                anchovies alone, 10,000,000 jars are prepared annually, while salted fish is, next
                after bread, the staple food of large masses of the population. The Black Sea
                fisheries, in which about 4000 men are engaged, yield fish valued at £300,000 per
                annum. The value of the fish has much increased owing to the introduction of cold
                storage; as a result of the employment of this method of packing, fish is now
                exported in a fresh state from the Black Sea to all parts of S.W. Russia, and
                even to Moscow. The annual yield of the Azov Sea fisheries, occupying 15,000 men, is
                valued at £600,000. In the Volga section of the Caspian Sea fish arc caught to the
                value of about £1,000,000 annually ; in the Ural section over 40,000 tons of fish
                and nearly 1500 tons of caviare are obtained. The total value of the Caspian
                fisheries is estimated at £3,000,000 per annum. Taking the Lake Aral and Siberian,
                river fisheries into account, it is estimated that altogether the fishing industries
                yield a revenue to the state of £330,000 annually.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> In
                addition from 13,000 to 60,000 seals and about 200 whales are killed annually off
                the Murman coast. Hunting is an occupation of considerable importance in N. and N.E.
                Russia, and along the shores of the Arctic Ocean.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Authorities.—The </hi><hi rend="italic">Russkiy Encyclopedic
                    heskiy Slovar,</hi> edited by Brockhaus and Efron, was begun in 1890, with the
                idea of giving a Russian version of Brockhaus’s <hi rend="italic">Conversations
                    Lexikon,</hi> but from the very first volumes it became a monumental
                encyclopaedia, and is, indeed, an inexhaustible source of information on
                everything Russian. A general popular description of Russia entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Rossiya, </hi>containing excellent geographical, geological and
                other descriptions of separate regions, and very well-chosen illustrations, was
                begun in 1899 under the editorship of V. P. Semenov. <hi rend="italic">La Russie a
                    la fin du xix* siècle,</hi> under the editorship of W. W. Kovalevsky,
                is especially worthy of notice. See also H. Norman, <hi rend="italic">All the
                    Russias </hi>(London, 1902) ; Sir D. Mackenzie Wallace, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Russia</hi> (2 vols., new ed., 1905, London); A. Leroy-Beaulieu, <hi
                    rend="italic">L'Empire des tsars</hi> (3 vols., 1882-88; Eng. trans., London,
                1803-96) ; A. Hettner, <hi rend="italic">Das europäische Russland</hi> (Leipzig,
                1905); R- Martin, <hi rend="italic">The Future of Russia</hi> (Eng. trans., London,
                1906) ; M. M. Kovalevsky, <hi rend="italic">Russian Political Institutions</hi>
                (Chicago, 1902), <hi rend="italic">Modern Customs and Ancient Laws of
                Russia </hi>(London, 1891), <hi rend="italic">Le Régime économique de la Russie</hi>
                (Paris, 1898), and <hi rend="italic">Die produktiven Kräfte Russlands</hi> (Paris,
                1896); A. M. B. Meakin, <hi rend="italic">Russia</hi> (London, 1906); G. von
                Schulze-Gävernitz, <hi rend="italic">Volks-wirtkschaftliche Studien aus
                    Russland</hi> (Leipzig, 1899) ; J. Maehat, <hi rend="italic">La Développement
                    économique de la Russie</hi> (Paris, 1902) ; <hi rend="italic">Industries of
                    Russia,</hi> by the Department of Trade and Manufactures (English by J. M.
                Crawford, 5 vols., St Petersburg, 1893); A. F. Rittieh, “ Die Ethnographie Russlands
                ” in <hi rend="italic">Petermanns Mitteilungen, </hi>Ergänzungsheft 54 (Gotha,
                1878); C. Joubert, <hi rend="italic">Russia as it really is</hi> (London,
                1904).    (P. A. K.; J. T. Be.)</p>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head><hi rend="smallcaps">History</hi></head>
                    <p>The history of Russia may be conveniently divided into four consecutive
                        periods: (1) the period of Independent Principalities; (2) the Mongol
                        Domination; (3) the Tsardom of Muscovy; and (4) the Modem Empire.</p>
                    <p>i. <hi rend="italic">A </hi><hi rend="italic">Conglomeration of Independent
                            Principalities.—</hi>The first period, like the early history of many
                        other countries, begins with a legend. Nestor, an old monkish chronicler of
                        Kiev, relates that in the middle of the 9th century the Slav and Finnish
                        tribes inhabiting the forest region around Lake Ilmen, between Lake Ladoga
                        and the upper waters of the Dnieper, paid tribute to military
                        adventurers from the land of Rüs, which is commonly supposed to have been a
                        part of Sweden. In the year 859 these tribes expelled the Northmen, but
                        finding that they quarrelled among themselves, they invited them, three
                        years later, to return. Our land, said the deputation sent to Rüs for this
                        purpose, is great and fertile, but there is no order in it; come and
                        reign and rule over us. Three brothers, princes of Rüs, called respectively
                        Rurik, Sineus and Truvor, accepted the invitation and founded a dynasty,
                        from which many of the Russian princes of the present day claim descent.</p>
                    <p>Who were those warlike men of Rus who are universally recognized as the
                        founders of the Russian Empire? This question has given rise to an enormous
                        amount of discussion among learned men, and some of the disputants have not
                        yet laid down their arms; but for impartial outsiders who have carefully
                        studied the evidence there can be little doubt that</p>
                    <p>@@@See<hi rend="italic">Researches into the State of Fisheries in Russia</hi>
                        (9 vols.), edited by Minister of Finance (1896, Russian); Kusnctzow's <hi
                            rend="italic">Fischerei und Thiererbeutung in den Gewässern
                            Russlands</hi> (1898).</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
