<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the vanquiſhed were to march, Theſe captains and generals he made priſoners of war, being reſerved to adorn his triumph. As ſor the plunder of the enemy’s camp, that he gave entirely up to hi$ own ſoldiers, without reſerving any part for himſelf, or permitting thoſe of the delivered army to have a ſhare. Thus, having re-ſe ued a Roman army from inevitable deſtruction, having defeated a powerful enemy, having taken and fortified their city, and, ſtill more, having refuſed any part oſ the ſpoil, he reſigned his dictatorſhip, after having enjoyed it but % days. The ſenate would have enriched him ; but he declined their proffers, chooſing to retire oκce more to his farm and his cottage, content with temperance and ſame.</p><p>But this repoſe from foreign invaſion did not leſſen the tumults of the city within. The clamours ſor the Agrarian law ſtill continued, and ſtill more fiercely, when Sicinius Dentatus, a plebeian, advanced in years, but of an admirable perſon and military deportment, came forward, to enumerate his hardſhips and his merits. This old ſoldier made no ſcruple of extolling the various merits of his youth ; but indeed his atchieve-ments ſupported oſtentation. He had ſerved his country in the wars 40 years; he had been an officer 30, firſt a centurion, and then a tribune : he had ſought 120 battles, in which, by the force of his ſingle arm, he had ſaved a multitude of lives : he had gained 14 civic, three mural, and eight golden crowns, btſides 83 chains, 60 bracelets, 18 gilt ſpears, and 23 horſe-trap-pings, whereof nine were for killing the enemy in ſingle combat : moreover, he had received 47 wounds, all before, and none behind. Theſe were his honours : yet, notwithſtanding all this, he had never received any ſhare of thoſe lands which were won from the enemy, but continued to drag on a life of poverty and contempt ; while others were poſſeſſed of thoſe very territories which his valour had won, without any merit to deſerve them, or ever having contributed to the conqueſt. A eaſe of ſo much hardſhip had a ſtrong effect upon the multitude ; they uuanimouſly demanded that the law might be paſſed, and that ſuch merit ſhould not go unrewarded. It was in vain that ſome of the ſenators roſe up to ſpeak againſt it ; their voices were drowned by the cries of the people. When reaſon, therefore, could no longer be heard, paſſion, as uſual, ſucceeded ; and the young patricians, running furiouſly into the throng, broke the balloting runs, and diſperſed the multitude that offered to oppoſe them. For this they were ſome time after fined by the tribunes ; but their reſolution, nevertheleſs, for the preſent, put off the Agrarian law.</p><p>The commonwealth of Rome had now for near 60 years been fluctuating between the contending orders that compoſed it, till at length, each ſide, as if weary, were willing to reſpire a while from the mutual exertions of their claims. The citizens, now, therefore, ef every rank, began to complain of the arbitrary de-eiſions of their magiſtrates, and wiſhed to be guided by a written body of laws, which being known might prevent wrongs as well as puniſh them. In this both the ſenate and the people concurred’, as hoping that ſuch laws would put an end to the commotions that fo long had haraſſed the ſtate. It was thereupon agreed,, that ambaſſadors ſhould be ſent to the Greek cities in Italy, and to Athens, to bring home ſuch laws ſrom</p><p>thence a3 by experience had been found moſt equî-table and uſeful. For thia purpoſe, three ſenators, Poſthumius, Sulpicius, and Manlius, were fixed upon, and galleys aſſigned to convoy them, agreeable to the majeſty of the Roman people. While they were upon this commiſſion abroad, a dreadful plague depopulated the city at home, and ſupplied the interval of their abſence with other anxiety than that of wiſhe-s for their return. In about a year the plague ceaſed, and the ambaſſadors returned, bringing home a body of law&gt;., collected ſrom the moſt civilized ſtates of Greece and Italy, which being afterwards formed into tçn tables, and two more being added, made that celebrated code called the <hi rend="italic">Laws of the Twelve Tables,</hi>  many fragments of which remain to this day.</p><p>The ambaſſadors were no ſooner returned, than the tribunes required that a body of men ſhould be choſen to digeſt their new laws into proper form, and to give weight to the execution of them. After long debates whether this choice ſhould not be partly made fiom the people as well as the patricians, it was at laſt agreed that 10 of the principal ſenators ſhould be elected, whoſe power, continuing for a year, ſhould be equal to that of kings and conſiſts, and that without any appeal. The peιfons choſen were Appius and Genutiu3, who had been elected conſuls for the en-ſuing year ; Poſthumius, Sulpicius, and M¾nlius, the three ambaſſadors ; Sextus and Romulus, former conſuls ; with Julius Veturius, and Horatius, ſenators of the firſt conſideration.</p><p>The decemviri beingnow inveſted with abſolute powgι&gt; agreed to take the reins of government by turns, and that each ſhould diſpenſe juſtice for a day.</p><p>Theſe magiſtrates, ſor the firſt year, wrought with extreme application : and their work being finiſhed, it was expected that they would be contented to give up their offices ; but having known the charms of power, they were now unwilling to reſign it : they therefore pretended that ſome laws were yet wanting to complete their deſign, and intreated the ſenate for a continuance of their offices ; to which that body aſ-ſented.</p><p>But they ſoon threw off the maſk of moderation ; and, regardleſs either ol the approbation of the ſenate or the people, reſolved to continue themſelves, againſt all order, in the decern virat∣e. A conduct ſo notorious produced diſcontents ; and theſe were as ſure to produce freſh acts of tyranny. The city wa3 become al* moſt a deſert, with reſpect to all who had any thing to· loſe ; and the decemvirs rapacity was then only diſcon-tinued, when they wanted freſh objects to ex-ereiſe it upon. In this ſtate of ſlavery, proſcription, and mutual diſtruſt, not one citizen was found to ſtrike for his country’s freedom ; theſe tyrants continued to rule without controul, being conſtantly guarded, not with-their lictors alone, but a numerous crowd of dependents, clients, and even patricians, whom their vices had confederated: round them.</p><p>In this gloomy ſituation of the ſtate, the Æqui and Volſei, thoſe conſtant enemies of the Romans, undertook their incurſions, reſolved to profit by the inteſtine diviſions of the people, and advanced within about io miles of Rome.</p><p>But the decemviri, being put in poſſeſſion of all the. military as weſt as of the civil power, divided their ar-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>