<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>neighbouring cities to have their ſtreets well ſwept and watered to defend him from the dull. However, all theſe mighty preparations ended in nothing. Inſtead of conquering Britain, he only gave refuge to one of its baniſhed prinςes ; and this he deſcribed in a letter to the ſenate, a∙3 taking poſſeſſion of the whole iſland. Inſtead of conquering Germany, he only led his army to the ſea ſhore in Batavia. There· diſpoſing his engines and warlike machines with great ſolemnity, and drawing up his men in order of battle,, he went on <hi rend="sup">ι</hi>  board his galley, with which coaſting along, he commanded his trumpets to ſound and the ſignal to be given as if for an engagement ; upon which, his men having had previous orders, immediately fell to gathering the ſhells that lay upon the ſhore into their helmets, terming them the<hi rend="italic">ſpoils of the conquered ocean worthy of the palace and the capitol.</hi>  After this doughty expedition, calling his army together as a general after victory, he - harangued them in a pompous manner, and highly extolled their atchievements ; and then diſtributing money among them, diſmiſſed them with orders to be joyful, and congratulated them upon their riches. But that ſuch exploits ſhould not paſs without a memorial, he cauſed a loſty tower to be erected by the ſea-ſide ; and ordered the galleys in which he had put to ſea to be conveyed to Rome in a great meaſure by land.</p><p>After numberleſs inſtances of ſolly and cruelty in this expedition, among which he had intentions of deſtroying the whole army that had formerly mutinied under his father Germanicus, he began to think of a triumph. The ſenate, who had long been the timid miniſters of his pride and cruelty, immediately ſet about conſulting how to ſatisfy his expectations. They conſidered that a triumph would, even to himſelſ, appear as a burleſque upon his expedition : they therefore decreed him only an ovation. Having come to this reſolution, they ſent him a deputation, informing him of the honours granted him, and the decree, which was drawn up in terms of the moſt extravagant adulation. However, their flattery was far from ſatisfying his pride. He conſidered their conduct rather as a diminution of his power, than an addition to his glory. He therefore ordered them, on pain of death, not to concern themſelves with his honours; and being met by their meſſengers on the way, who invited him to come and partake of the preparations which the ſenate had decreed, he informed them that he would came ; and then laying his hand upon his ſword, added, that he would bring that alſo with him. In this m inner, either quite omitting his triumph, or deferring it to another time, he entered the city with only an ovation ; while the ſenate paſſed the whole day in acclamations in his praiſe, and ſpeeches filled with the moſt exceſſive flattery. This conduct in ſome meaſure ſerved to reconcile him, and ſoon after their exceſſive zeal in his cauſe entirely gained his favour. For it happened that Protogenes, who was one of the moſt intimate and the moſt cruel of his favourites, coming into the houſe, was fawned upon by the whole body of the ſenate, and particularly by Proculus. Whereupon Protogenes with a fierce look, alked how one who was ſuch an enemy to the emperor could be ſuch a friend to him ? There needed no more to excite the ſenate againſt Proculus. They inſtantly ſeized upon him, and violently tore him</p><p>in pieces ; plainly ſhowitg by their conduct, that tyranny in a prince produces cruelty in thoſe whom lie governs.—It was after returning from this extravagant expedition, that he was waited upon by a deputation of the Jews of Alexandria, who came to deprecate his anger ſor not worſhipping his divinity as other nations had done. The emperor gave them a very ungracious reception, and would probably have deſtroyed their countrymen if he had not ſoon alter been cut off.</p><p>This affair of the ∖Jews remained undecided during h’s reign ; but it was at laſt ſettled by his ſucceſſor to their ſatisfaction. It was upon this occaſion that Philo made the following remarkable anſwer to his aſſociates, who w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ere terrified with apprehenſions of the emperor’s indignation ; “ Fear nothing (cried he to them), Caligula, by declaring againſt us, puts God on our ſide.”</p><p>The continuation of this horrid reign ſeemed to threaten univerſal calamity : however, it was but ſhort. There had already been ſeveral conſpiracies formed to deſtroy the tyrant, but without ſucceſs. That which at laſt ſucceeded in delivering the world of this monſter, was concerted under the influence of Caſſius Che-rea, tribune of the prætorian bands. This was a man of experienced courage, an ardent admirer of freedom, and conſequently an enemy to tyrants. Beſides the motives which he had in common with other men, he had received repeated inſults from Caligula, who took all occaſions of turning him into ridicule, and impeaching him of cowardice, merely becauſe he had an effeminate voice. Whenever Cherea came to demand the watch-word from the emperor, according to cuſtom, he always gave him either Venus, Adonis, or ſome ſuch, implying effeminacy and ſoftneſs. He therefore ſecretly imparted his deſigns to ſeveral ſenators and knights whom he knew to have received perſonal injuries from Caligula, or to be apprehenſive of thoſe to come. Among theſe was Valerius Aſiaticus, whoſe wife the emperor had debauched. Annius Vincianus, who was ſuſpected of having been in a former conſpiracy, was now deſirous of really engaging in the firſt deſign that offered Beſides theſe, were Clemens the preſect ; and Caliſtus, whoſe riches made him obnoxious to the: tyrant’s reſentment.</p><p>While theſe were deliberating upon the moſt certain and ſpeedy method of deſtroying the tyrant, an unexpected incident gave new’ ſtrength to the conſpiracy. Pompedius, a ſenator of diſtinction, having been accuſed before the errφeror, of having ſpoken of him with diſreſpect, the informer cited one Quintilia, an actreſs, to con ,rm his accuſation. Quintilia, however, was poſſeſſed of a degree of fortitude not eaſily found. She denied the fact with obſtinacy ; and being put to the torture at the informer’s requeſt, ſhe bore the ſevereſt torments of the rack with unſhaken conſtancy. But what is moſt remarkable of her reſolution is, that ſhe was acquainted with all the particulars of the conſpiracy ; and although Cherea was appointed to preſide at her torture ſhe revealed nothing : on the contrary, when ſhe was led to the rack, ſhe trod upon the toe of one of the conſpirators, intimating at once her knowledge of the confederacy, and her own reſolution not to divulge it. In this manner ſhe ſuffered until all her limbs were diſlocated ; and in that deplorable ſtate was preſented to the emperor, who ordered her a gratuity for what ſhe had ſuffered. Cherea could now no Ion-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>