<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in its courſe of exiſtence, it becomes grave and ſtately in its motions, loves peace and quiet ; and in majeſtic ſilence rolls on its mighty waters, till it is laid to reſt in the vaſt abyſs.</p><p>The philoſopher, the real lover of wiſdom, ſees much to admire in the economy and mechaniſm of running waters ; and there are few operations of nature which give him more opportunities of remarking the nice ad-juſtment of the moſt Ample means for attaining many purpoſes of moſt extenſive beneficence. All mankind ſeem to have felt this. The heart of man is ever open (unleſs perverted by the habits of ſelſiſh indulgence and arrogant ſelf∙conceit) to impreſſions of gratitude and love. He who aſcribes the religious principle (debated, though it be by the humbling abuſes of fu-perſtition) to the workings of fear alone, may betray the ſlaviſh meanneſs of his own mind, but gives a very unfair and a falſe picture of the hearts of his neighbours. Lucretius was but half a philoſopher when he penned his often-quoted apophthegm. Indeed his own invocations ſhow how much the animal was blended with the ſage.</p><p>We apprehend, that whoever will read with an ho-neſt and candid mind, unbiaſſed by licentious wiſhes, the accounts of the ancient ſuperſtitions, will acknowledge that the amiable emotions of the human ſoul have had their ſhare in creating the numerous divinities whoſe worſhip filled up their kalendars. The ſun and the hoſt of heaven have in all ages and nations been the objects of a ſincere worſhip. Next to them, the rivers ſeem to have attracted the grateful acknowledgments of the inhabitants of the adjacent countries. They have everywhere been conſidered as a ſort of tutelar divinities ; and each little diſtrict, every retired valley, had its river god, who was prefer* red to all others with a partial fondneſs. The expoſtu-lation of Naaman the Syrian, who was offended with the prophet for enjoining him to waſh in the river Jordan, was the natural effuſion of this attachment. “What ! (ſaid he), are not Abana and Pharphat, rivers of Da-maſcus, more excellent than all the waters of Judæa ? Might I not waſh in them and be clean ? So he went away wroth.”</p><p>In thoſe countries particularly, where the rural labours, and the hopes of the ſhepherd and the huſhand-man, were not ſo immediately connected with the approach and receſs of the ſun, and depended rather on what happened in a far diſtant country by the falls of periodical rains or the melting of collected ſnows, the Nile, the Ganges, the Indus, the river of Pegu, were the ſenſible agents of nature in procuring to the inhabitants of their fertile banks all their abundance, and they became the objects of grateful veneration. Their ſources were fought out with anxious care even by conquering princes; and when found, were univerſally worſhipped with the moſt affectionate devotion. Theſe remarkable rivers, ſo eminently and ſo palpably beneficent, preſerve to this day, anſidſt every change of habit, and every increaſe of civilization and improvement, the fond adoration of the inhabitants of thoſe fruitful countries through which they hold their ſtately courſe, and their waters are ſtill held ſacred. No progreſs of artificial refinement, not all the corruption of luxurious ſenfoality, has been able to eradicate this plant of native growth from the heart of man. The ſentiment is</p><p>congenial to his nature, and therefore it is universal} and we could almoſt appeal to the feelings of every reader, whether he does not perceive it in his own breaſt. Perhaps we may be miſtaken in our opinion in the caſe of the corrupted inhabitants of the populous and buſy cities, who are habituated to the fond contemplation of their own individual exertions as the ſources of all their hopes. Give the ſhoemaker but leather and a few tools, and he defies the powers of nature to disappoint him ; but the ſimpler inhabitants of the country, the moſt worthy and the moſt reſpectable part of every nation, after equal, perhaps greater exertion both of ſkill and of induſtry, are more accuſtomed to reſign themſelves to the great miniſters of Providence, and to look up to heaven for the “ early and the latter rains,” without which all their labours are fruitleſs.</p><p><hi rend="italic">........extrema per illos</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Numenque excedens terms veſtigia fecit.</hi></p><p>And among the huſhandmen and the ſhepherds of alt nations and ages, we find the ſame fond attachment to their ſprings and rivulets.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Fortunate ſenex, his inter flumina</hi><hi rend="italic">  nota</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"/><hi rend="italic">Et fontes ſacros friges captabis opacum,</hi></p><p>was the mournful ejaculation of poor Meliboeus. We hardly know a river of any note in our own country whoſe ſource is not looked on with ſome reſpect.</p><p>We repeat our affertion, that this worſhip was the offspring of affection and gratitude, and that it is giving a very unfair and falſe picture of the human mind to aſcribe theſe ſuperſtitions to the working of fear alone, Theſe would have repreſented the river-gods as ſeated on ruins, brandiſhing rooted-up trees, with angry looks, pouring out their ſweeping torrents. But no ſuch thing. The lively imagination of the Greeks felt, and expreſſed with an energy unknown to all other nations, every emotion of the human foul. They figured the Naiads as beautiful nymphs, patterns of gentleneſs and of elegance. They are repreſented as partially attached to the children of men; and their interference in human affairs Js always in acts of kind aſſiſtance and protection. They reſemble, in this reſpect, the rural deities of the northern nations, the fairies, but without their caprices and reſentments. And, if we attend to the deſcriptions and repreſentations of their River-Gods, beings armed with power, an attribute which ſlaviſh fear never fails to couple with cruelty and vengeance, we find the ſame expreſſion of affectionate truſt and confidence in their kind diſpoſitions. They are generally called by the reſpectable but endearing name of <hi rend="italic">father. “ Da Tyberi pater f</hi>  ſays Virgil. Mr Bruce ſays that the Nile at its ſource is called the <hi rend="italic">abay </hi>or “ father.”—We obſerve this word, or its radix,blended with many names of rivers of the eaſt ; and think it pro* bable that when our traveller got this name from the inhabitants of the neighbourhood, they applied to the ſtream what is meant to expreſs the tutelar or preſi-ding ſpirit. The river-gods are always repreſented as venerable old men, to indicate their being coeval with the world. But it is always a <hi rend="italic">cruda viridiſque feneftus, </hi>and they are never repreſented as oppreſſed with age and decrepitude. Their beards are long and flowing, their looks placid, their attitude eaſy, reclined on a bank, covered, as they are crowned, with never-fading ſedges and bulruſhes, and leaning on their urns, from which they pour out their plentiful and fertilizing ſtreams.—∙</p></body></text></TEI>