<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſuaded him ſrom it ; and on that occaſion, diſcloſing to him his birth, awakened in his breaſt ſentiments worthy of his extraction. He reſolved, at all adventures, to attempt the delivering of his mother and grandfather from oppreſſion. With this view he aſſembled the country people, over whom he had aſſumed a kind of ſovereignty, and engaged them to come to the city on an appointed day, and enter it by different gates, provided with arms, which they were to conceal. While Romulus was thus diſpoſing every thing for the execution of his deſign, Numitor made the ſame diſeovery to Remus concerning his parents, and the oppreſſions they groaned under ; which ſo fired him, that he was ready to embark in any enterpriſe. But Numitor took care to moderate the tranſports of his grandſon, and only deſired him to acquaint his brother with what he had heard fιom him, and to ſend him to his houſe. Romulus ſoon came, and was followed by Fauſtulus, who took with'him the trough or ſkiſſ in which the twins had been expoſed, to ſhow it to Numitor : but, as the ſhep-herd betrayed an air of concern and earneſtneſs in his looks, he was flopped at the gate of the city, led before Amulius, and examined concerning his burden. It was eaſily known by its make and inſcription, which was ſtill legible ; and therefore Fauſtulus owned what it was, and conſeſſed that the twins were living ; but, in order to gain time, pretended that they were feeding flocks in a remote deſert. In the mean time, the uſurper’s death being reſolved on, Remus undertook to raiſe the city, and Romulus to inveſt the king’s palace. The country people came at the time appointed, and formed themſelves into companies each conſiſting of ιoo men. They had no other enſigns but bundles of hay hanging upon long poles, which the Latins at that time called <hi rend="italic">manipuli</hi>  ; and hence came the name of <hi rend="italic">mαnipu∙ lares,</hi>  originally given to troops raiſed'in the country. With this tumultuous army Romulus beſet the avenues of the palace, forced the guard, and having killed the tyrant, after he had reigned 42 years, reſtored his grandfather Numitor to the throne.</p><p>Affairs being thus ſettled at Alba, the two brothers, by the advice of Numitor, undertook the founding of a new colony. The king beſtowed on them thoſe lands near the Tiber where they had been brought up, ſupplied them with all manner of inſtruments for breaking up ground, with ſlaves, and beaſts of burden, and granted full liberty to his ſubjects to join them. Hereupon moſt of the Trojans, of whom there ſtill remained 50 families in Auguſtus’s time, choſe to follow the fortune of Romulus and Remus, as did alſo the inhabitants of Pallantium and Saturnia, two ſmall towns. For the more ſpeedy carrying on of the work, it was thought proper to divide thoſe who were to be employed in the building of the city into two companies, one under the command of Romulus, the other of Remus ; but this diviſion, which was deſigned purely with a view to the public welfare, and that the two parties might work by way of emulation, gave birth to two factions, and produced a jealouſy between the two brothers, which broke out when they came to chooſe a place for the building of their new city ; for Remus was for the Aventine, and Romulus for the Palatine mount. Upon which, the matter being referred to their grandfather, he adviſed the contending parties to have recourſe to the gods, and to put an end to the diſpute by augury, to which he wa∙ himſelf greatly addicted. The day appointed for the ceremony being come, the brothers poſted themſelves each upon his hill ; and it was agreed, that whoever ſhould ſee the firſt flight, or the greateſt number, of vultures, ſhould gain his cauſe. After the two rival» had waited ſome time for the appearance of a favourable omen, Romulus, before any had appeared, ſent to acquaint his brother that he had ſeen ſome vultures ; but Remus, having actually ſeen ſix, while his brother’s meſſengers were yet on their way, haſtened, on their arrival, to mount Palatine, to examine the truth of what they had told him. He had no ſooner got thither, than by an unexpected good fortune twelve vultures appeared to Romulus. Theſe he immediately ſhowed to his brother ; and, tranſported with joy, deſired him to judge himſelf of the truth of what his meſſengers had told him. However, Remus diſcovered the deceit ; and, being told that Romulus had not ſeen the twelve vultures till after he had ſeen ſix, he inſiſted on the time of his ſeeing them, and the other on the number of birds he had ſeen. This widened the breach between the two brothers ; and, their parties being divided, while each man eſpouſed the cauſe of his leader, the diſpute grew ſo warm, that, ſrom words they came at length to blows. The ſhepherd Fauſtulus, who was equally dear to both the brothers, endeavouring to part the combatants, was by an unknown hand laid dead on the ſpot. Some writers tell us, that Remus likewiſe loſt his life in the fray ; but the greater number place his death later, and ſay that he was killed by one Fabius, for having, in dcriſion, leaped over the wall of the new city : but Livy ſays, the more common report was, that Remus ſell by the hand of his brother.</p><p>Romulus, being now head of the colony, by having got the better of his brother’s party in the late engagement, applied his thoughts wholly to the<hi rend="sup">z</hi> building of the city, which he propoſed to call after his own name. He choſe mount Palatine for its ſituation, and performed all thoſe ceremonies which the ſuperſtition of the Hetrurians had introduced. He firſt offered ſacrifices to the gods, and ordered all the people to do the ſame : and from that time decreed, that eagles ſhould be the auſpices of his new colony. After this, great fires were kindled before their tents, and all the people leaped through the flames to purify themſelves. When this ceremony was over, they dug a trench round the ſpot where the aſſemblies of the people were afterwards held, and threw into it the firſt-ſruits of whatever they were allowed to make uſe of for food : every man of the colony was ordered to eaſt into the ſame trench an handful of earth, brought either from his own or ſome neighbouring country. The trench they called<hi rend="italic">Mundus, </hi>that is, <hi rend="italic">the world,</hi>  and made it the centre round which the city was to be built. Then Romulus, yoking an ox and a cow to a plough, the coulter whereof was braſs, marked out, by a deep furrow, the whole compaſs of the city. Theſe two animals, the ſymbols of marriage, by which cities are peopled, were afterwards ſlain upon the altar. All the people followed the plough, throwing inwards the clod« of earth which the plough-ſhare ſometimes turned outwaιds. Wherever a gate was to be made, the plough was lifted up, and carried ; and hence came the Latin word <hi rend="italic">porta, <hi rend="sup">ti</hi>  v.</hi>  gate,” de-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>