<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>bay, ſorrel, or black colour, with grey or white ſpots interſperſed very thick. When this party-coloured</p><p>, coat is accompanied with a black head and black extremities, he is called a <hi rend="italic">roan horſe with a black-a-moor<hi rend="sup">,</hi>'s head:</hi>  and if the ſame mixture is predominant upon a deep ſorrel, he is called <hi rend="italic">claret roan.</hi></p><p>ROANOAK, an Hand of North America, near the coaſt of North Carolina. Here the Engliſh firſt attempted to ſettle in 1585, but were obliged to leave it for want of proviſions. E. Long. 75. o. N. Lat. 35∙ 40.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roanoak, a river of North America, which riſes in Virginia, runs through Carolina, and at length falls into the ſea, where it forms a long narrow bay called </hi><hi rend="italic">Λlbema<hi rend="sup">r</hi>le found.</hi></p><p>ROASTING, in metallurgic operations, ſigniſies the diſſipation of the volatile parts of an ore by heat. See Metallurgy, <hi rend="italic">pαſſim.</hi></p><p>ROB, in pharmacy, the juices of fruits purified and inſpiſſated till it is of the conſiſtence of honey.</p><p>ROBBERY, the <hi rend="italic">rapina</hi>  of the civilians, is the felonious and forcible taking, ſrom the perſon of another, of goods or money to any value, by violence or putting him in fear. 1. There muſt be a taking, otherwiſe it is no robbery. A mere attempt to rob was indeed held to be felony ſo late as Henry IVth’s time ; but afterwards it was taken to be only a miſdemeanour, and puniſhabie with fine and impriſonment ; till the ſtatute 7 Geo. II. c. 21. which makes it a felony (tranſportable for {'even years) unlawfully and malici-ouſly to aſſault another, with any offenſive weapon or inſtrument ;—or by menaces, or by other forcible or violent manner, to demand any money or goods ; — with a felonious intent to rob. If the thief, having once taken a purſe, returns it, ſtill it is a robbery : and ſo</p><p>it is whether the taking be ſtrictly from the perſon of another, or in his preſence only ; as where a robber by menaces and violence puts a man in fear, and drives away his lheep or his cattle before his face. 2. It is immaterial of what value the thing taken is: ä penny, as well as a pound thus forcibly extorted, makes a robbery. 3. Laſtly, the taking muſt be by force, or a previous putting in fear ; which makes the violation of the perſon more atrocious than privately ſtealing. For, according to the maxim of the civil law, “ <hi rend="italic">qui vi rapuit, fur improbior ejſe videtur.<hi rend="sup">f,</hi></hi>  This previous violence, or putting in fear, is the criterion that diſtinguiſh-cs robbery ſrom other larcenies. For if one privately ſteals ſixpence from the perſon of another, and afterwards keeps it by putting him in fear, this is no robbery, for the fear is ſubſequent : «either is it capital as privately ſtealing, being under the value of twelve-pence. Not that it is indeed neceſſary, though uſual, to lay in the indictment that the robbery was committed by <hi rend="italic">putting in feα<hi rend="sup">r</hi>  :</hi>  it is ſufficient, if laid to be done by <hi rend="italic">violence.</hi>  And when it is laid to be done by putting in ſear, this does not imply any great degree of terror <hi rend="sup">f</hi>∙or affright in the party robbed : it is enough that ſo much force or threatening, by word or geſture, be uſed, "as might create an apprehenſion of danger, or induce a man to part with his property without or againſt his confient. Thus, if a man be knocked down without previous warning, and ſtripped of his property while ſenſeleſs, though ſtrictly he cannot be ſaid to be<hi rend="italic">put in jeαr<hi rend="sub">y</hi>-</hi>  yet this is undoubtedly a robbery. Or, if a per</p><p>ſon with a ſword drawn begs an alms, and I give it him through miſtruſt and apprehenſion of violence, this is a felonious robbery. So if, under a pretence of ſale, a man forcibly extorts money ſrom another, neither ſhall this ſubterfuge avail him. But it is doubted, whether the forcing a higler, or other chapman, to ſell his wares, and giving him the full value of them, amounts to ſo heinous a crime as robbery.</p><p>This ſpecies of larceny is debarred of the benefit of clergy by ſtatute 23 Hen. VIII. c. 1. and other ſubſequent ſtatutes ; not indeed in general, but only when committed in a dwelling-houſe, or in or near the king’s highway. A robbery therefore in a diſtant field, or footpath, was not puniſhed with death ; but was open to the benefit of clergy, till the ſtatute 3 &amp; 4 W. and M. c. 9. which takes away clergy from both principals and acceſſories before the fact, in robbery, whereſoever committed. See Law, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> clxxxvi. 3°∙    .</p><p>ROBERT bruce, king of Scotland, in 1306 ; ä renowned general, and the deliverer of his country from a ſtate of vaſſalage to the Engliſh. See Scotland.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Robert, king of France, ſurnamed the Wiſe and the Pious, came to the crown in 996, aſtet the death of Hugh Capet his father. He was crowned at Orleans, the place of his nativity, and afterwards at Rheims, after the impriſonment of Charles of Lorraine. He married Bertha his couſin, daughter of Conrad king of Burgundy ; but the marriage was declared null by Gregory V. ; and the king, if we can give credit to cardinal Peter Damien, was excommunicated. This anathema made ſuch a noiſe in France, that all the king’s courteſans, and even his very domeſtics, went away from him. Only two continued with him ; who were ſo deeply impreſſed with a ſenſe of horror at whatever the king touched, that they purified it with fire : this ſcruple they carried ſo ſar, as to the very plates on which he was ſerved with his meat, and the veſſels out of which he drank. The ſame cardinal reports, that as a puniſh-ment for this pretended inceſt, the queen was delivered of a monſter, which had the head and neck of a duck He adds, that Robert was ſo ſtruck with aſtoniſhment at this ſpecies of prodigy, that he lived apart from the queen. He contracted a ſecond marriage with Confiance, daughter of λVilliam count of Arles and Provence ; but the arrogant diſpoſition of this princeſs would have totally overturned the kingdom, and thrown it into confuſion, had not the wiſdom of the king prevented her from intermeddling with the affairs of the ſtate. He carefully concealed from her whatever acts of liberality he ſhowed to any of his domeſtics. “ Take care (ſaid he to them) that the queen don’t perceive it.”— Henry duke of Burgundy, brother of Hugh Capet, dying in 1002, without lawful iſſue, leſt his dukedom to his nephew the king of France. Robert in-veiled his ſecond ſon Henry with this dukedom, who afterwards coming to the crown, reſigned it in favour of Robert his cadet. This duke Robert was chief ot the firſt royal branch of the dukes of Burgundy, who fiouriſhed till 1361. This dukedom was then re united to the crown by king John, who gave it to his fourth ſon Philip the Bold, chief of the ſecond houſe of Burgundy, wl√dι was terminated in the perſon of Charles the Raih, who was ſlain in ∣477. King Robert was ſo much tſteemed for his wiſdom and nrudence, that</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>