<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a miniſter of the goſpel, he was a ſaithful paſtor, and juſtly merited the eſteem and veneration of his flock. In a word, he may be pronounced to be one of the moſt perfect characters of the age ; and his name will be a laſting honour to the iſland that gave him birth. His converſation was cheerful, entertaining, and inſtruc-tive ; his manners affable, pleaſing, and endearing.</p><p>Dr Robertſon left three ſons and two daughters. The eldeſt ſon is procurator for the church of Scotland, and an advocate. The other two are officers in the army ; and one of them diſtinguiſhed himſelf under Lord Cornwallis in ſuch a manner as to command the warmeſt praiſe from that illuſtrious general.</p><p>ROB1GUS <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi>  ROBIGO, a Roman god and goddeſs, who joined in the preſervation of corn ſrom <hi rend="italic">blight.</hi>  Their feſtival was kept on the 25th of April. ROBIN <hi rend="smallcaps">hood.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Hood.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RoBiN Red-Βreaft.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Motacilla.</hi></p><p>ROBINIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">false acacia,</hi>  in botany: A genus of the decandria order, belonging to the diadelphia claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 3 2d order, <hi rend="italic">Papilionacea<hi rend="sup">,</hi>.</hi>  The calyx is quadriſid ; the legumen gibbous and elongated. There are nine ſpecies. The moſt remarkable are the caragnana and fe-rox, the leaves of the former of which are conjugated, and compoſed of a number of ſmall folioles, of an oval figure, and ranged by pairs on one common ſtock. The flowers are leguminous, and are cluſtered on a filament. Every flower conſiſts of a ſmall bell-ſhaped petal, cue into four ſegments at the edge, the upper part being rather the wideſt. The keel is ſmall, open, and rounded. The wings are large, oval, and a little raiſed. Within are 10 ſtamina united at the bafe, curved towards the top, and rounded at the ſummit. In the midſt of a ſheath, formed by the filaments of the ſtamina, the piſtil is perceivable, conſiſting of an oval germen, terminated by a kind of button. This germen becomes afterwards an oblong flattiſh curved pod, containing four or five ſe ds, of a ſize and ſhape irregular and unequal ; yet in both reſpects ſomewhat reſembling a lentil.</p><p>This tree grows naturally in the ſevere climates of Northern Aſia, in a ſandy ſoil mixed with black light earth. It is particularly found on the banks of great rivers, as the Oby, Jeniſia, &amp;c. It is very rarely met with in the inhabited parts of the country, becauſe cattle’are very fond of its leaves, and hogs of its roots ; and it is ſo hardy, that the ſevereſt winters do not affect it. Gmelin found it in the neighbourhood of To-bolik, buried under 15 feet of ſnow and ice, yet had it not ſuffered the leaſt damage. Its culture conſiſts in being planted or ſowed in a lightiſh ſandy ſoil, which muſt on no account have been lately manured. It thrives beſt near a river, or on the edge of a brook or ſpring4 but preſently dies if planted in a marſhy ſpot, where the water ſtagnates. If it is planted on a rich ſoil, well tilled, it will grow to the height of 20 feet, and in a very few years will be as big as a common birch tree.</p><p>In a very bad ſoil this tree degenerates, and becomes a mere ſhrub : the leaves grow hard, and their fine bright green colour is changed to a dull deep green. The Tonguſian Tartars, and the inhabitants of the northern parts of Siberia, are very fond of the fruit of this tree, it being almoſt the only ſort of pulſe they eat. M. Strahlemberg, author of a well-eſteemed deſcription</p><lb/><p>of Siberia, allures us that this fruit is tolerably pleaſant food, and very nouriſhing. Theſe peaſe are firſt infilled in boiling water, to take off a certain acrid taſte they have, and are afterwards dreſſed like common peaſe or Windſor beans ; and being ground into meal, pretty good cakes are made of them. The leaves and tender ſhoots of this tree make excellent fodder for ſeveral forts of cattle., 7 he roots, being ſweet and ſucculent, are very well adapted to fattening hogs ; and the fruit is greedily eaten by all ſorts of poultry. After ſeveral experiments ſomewhat ſimilar to the methods uſed with anil and indigo, a fine blue colour was procured from its leaves. The ſmaller kind of this tree ſeems ſtill. better adapted to anſwer this purpoſe. The ſtrik'ing elegance of its foliage, joined to the pleaſing yellow colour of its beautiful flowers, ſhould, one would imagine, bring it into requeſt for forming noſegays, or for ſpeed-ily making an elegant hedge.</p><p>Beſides the qualities above recited, it poſſeſſes the uncommon advantage of growing exceedingly quick, and of being eaſily tranſplanted. There are large plantations of it now in Sweden, Norway, Lapland, and Iceland. Linnæus aſſures us, that, after the <hi rend="italic">Pinus jol. quints,</hi>  erroneouſly called the <hi rend="italic">cedar tree of Siberia,</hi>  this tree, of all that are to be found in Siberia, is moſt worthy of cultivation.</p><p>2. The robinia ferox is a beautiful hardy ſhrub, and, on account of its robuſt ſtrong prickles, might be introduced into this country as a hedge plant, with much propriety. It reſiſts the ſevereſt cold of the climate of St Peterſhurgh, and perfects its ſeed in the garden of the empreſs there. It riſes to the height of fix or eight ſeet ; does not ſend out ſuckers from the root, nor ramble ſo much as to be -with difficulty kept within bounds. Its flowers are yellow, and the general colour of the plant a light pleaſing green. A figure of it is given in the <hi rend="italic">Flora Roſſlca</hi>  by Dr Pallas, who found it in the ſouthern diſtricts, and font the feeds to St Peterſhurgh, where it has proſpered in a ſituation where few plants can be made to live.</p><p>ROBINS (Benjamin), a moſt ingenious mathematician, was born at Bath in 1707. His parents were Quakers, and of low condition, conſequently neither able nor willing to have him much inſtructed in human learning. Nevertheleſs his own propenlity to ſcience procured him a recommendation to Dr Pemberton at London ; by whoſe aſſiſtance, while he attained the ſublimer parts of mathematical knowledge, he commenced teacher of the mathematics. But the buſineſs of teaching, which required confinement, not ſuiting his active diſpoſition, he gradually declined it, and engaged in buſineſs that required more exerciſe. Hence he tried many laborious experiments in gunnery, from the per-ſuaſion that the reſiſtance of the air has a much greater influence on ſwift projectiles than is generally imagined. Hence alſo he was-led to conſider the mechanic arts that depend on mathematical principles ; as the conſtruction of mills, the building of bridges, the draining of fens, the rendering of rivers navigable, and the making of harbours. Among other arts, fortification much engaged his attention ; and he met with opportunities pi perfecting himſelf by viewing the principal ſtrong places of Flanders, in ſome tours he made abroad with perſons of diſtinction.</p><p>Upon his return from one of theſe excurſions, he</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>