<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſtate of inactivity as his predeceſſor, until he received certain intelligence that the Veientes and Fidenates had .reſolved to deſtroy both Romans and Albans when they ſhould be weakened by a battle. Fuffetius then reſolved to come to an accommodation with the Romans ; and, having obtained a conference with Tullus, both ſeemed equally deſirous of avoiding the calamities of war. But, in order to eſtabliſh the peace on the moſt perfect foundation, Tullus propoſed that all, or at leaſt the chief families in Alba, ſhould remove to Rome ; or, in caſe they were unwilling to leave their native city, that one common council ſhould be eſtabliſhed to govern both cities, under the direction of one of the two ſovereigns. Fuffetius took aſide thoſe who attended him, to conſult with them about this piopoſal; but they, though willing to come to an accommodation with Rome, abſolutely refuſed to leave Alba. The only difficulty remaining, then, was to ſettle which city ſhould have the ſuperiority ; and, as this could not be determined by argument, Tullus propoſed to determine it by ſingle combat betwixt himſelf and Fuffetius. This propoſal, however, the Alban general thought proper to decline ; and it was at laſt agreed, that three champions ſhould be choſen out of each camp to decide the difference. This produced the famous combat between the Horatii and Curiatii, by which the ſovereignty was decided in favour of Rome. See Horatii.</p><p>Tullus now reſolved to call the Fidenates to an account for their treacherous behaviour during the war with Alba, and therefore cited them to appear before the ſenate ; but they, conſcious of their guilt, refuſed to appear, and took up arms in conjunction with the Veientes. Fuffetius, in obedience to the orders of Tullus, joined him with the Alban troops ; but the day before the battle, he acquainted the principal officers with his deſign, which was to ſtand neuter till fortune had declared ſor one ſide, and then to join with the conqueror. 'Γhis deſign being approved, Fuffetius, during the engagement, retired with his forces to a neighbouring eminence. Tullus perceived his treachery ; but diſſembling his uneaſineſs, told his men that Fuffetius had poſſeſſed himſelf of that hill by his order, and that he was from thence to ruſh down upon the enemy. The Veientes, in the mean time, who had expected that Fuffetius was to join them, were diſmayed, and the Romans obtained the victory. After the battle, Tullus returned privately to Rome in the night ; and having conſulted with the ſenate about the treachery of Fuffetius, returned to the camp by break of day. He then detached Horatius, who had conquered the three Curiatii, with a choſen body of horſe and foot, to demoliſh Alba, as had been concerted at</p><p>Rome. In the mean time, he commanded both the Roman and Alban troops to attend him unarmed, but gave private orders to the Romans to bring their ſwords concealed under their garments. When they were aſſembled, he laid open the treachery. of Fuffetius» and ordered him to be torn in pieces by horſes. His accomplices were all put to the ſword.;. and the inhabitants of Alba carried to Rome, where they were admitted to the privileges of citizens, andTυme of them even admitted to the ſenate.</p><p>Tullus now turned his arms againſt Fidenæ, which lie again reduced under the Roman yoke ; and took</p><p>Medulia, a ſtrong city of the Latins ; after which he waged a ſucceſsful war with the Sabines, whoſe union with the Romans ſeems to have ceaſed with the time of Numa. This was the laſt of his martial exploits ; after which we hear no more of him, but that he became extremely ſuperſtitious in his advanced years, giving ear to many fooliſh ſtories, as that it rained ſtones, that miraculous voices were heard from heaven, &amp;c. and for this he appointed nine days expiatory ſacrifices ; whenoe it became a cuſtom to appoint nine days to appeaſe the wrath of the gods as often as men were alarmed with prodigies. As to the manner of his death authors are not agreed. Some tell us that he was killed by lightning, together with his wife, children, and his whole family ; while others, are of opinion that he was murdered with his wife and children by Ancus Martius who ſucceeded him. He died after a reign of 33 years, leaving the city greatly increaſed, but the dominions much the ſame as they had been in the time of Romulus.</p><p>After a ſhort interregnum, Ancus Martius, the grandſon of Numa by his daughter Pompilia, and Marcus his relation, was unanimouſiy choſen by the people and ſenate. Though naturally inclined to war, he began his reign with attempting to reſtore the ceremonies of Numa, which had been neglected under Tullus Hoſtilius. He endeavoured alſo to draw the attention of his people to huſhandry and the peaceful arts ; adviſing them to lay aſide all ſorts of violence, and to return to their former employments. This gained him the affections of his ſubjects, but brought upon him the contempt of the neighbouring nations. The Latins, pretending that their treaty with Rome was expired, made inroads into the.Roman territories. Ancus, after uſing the ceremonies directed by Numa, took the field with an army conſiſting entirely of- new levied troops, and reduced the cities of Politorium, Tille-na, and Ficana, tranſplanting the inhabitants to Rome. A new colony of Latins repeopled Politorium ; but Ancus retook the place next year, and entirely demυ-liſhed it. Hc then laid ſiege to Medulia ; which, though it had been ruined by Tullus Hoſtilius, was now ſtronger than ever. It ſubmitted.after a ſiege ot four years, when Ancus found himſelf obliged to undertake a ſecond expedition againſt Ficana, which he had before reduced, as we have already related ; and it was not without the utmoſt difficulty that he reduced it a ſecond time. After this he defeated the Latins in a pitched battle ; vanquiſhed the Fidenates, Veientes, and Sabines ; and having taken in the hill Janiculum to he included within the walls, and built the port of Gſtia, he died in the 24th year of his reign.</p><p>Ancus Martius left two ſons behind him, one an infant, and the other about 15 years of age. Both of theſe he put under the tuition of Tarquin, the ſon of a rich merchant in Corinth,, who had fled from that city to ſecure his wealth ſrom Cypſelus tyrant of the place. He ſettled in Tarquinii, one of the principal cities in Hetruria ; but finding that he could not there attain to any of the principal polls in the city on account of his foreign extraction, he removed to Rome, where be had been gradually raiſed to the rank of patrician and ſenator. The death of Ancus Martins gave him an opportunity of afliιming the regal dignity, and ſetting aſide h.s pupils and in the beginning of his reign he</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>