<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Upon the departure of theſe troops, ſome of the Epirots, imagining that the camp was taken, began to loſe courage, and retire ; thoſe who were next to them followed their example, and in a ſhort time the whole army gave way. Pyrrhus having attempted ſeveral times in vain to rally his forces, returned to the charge with a ſmall number of his friends and the moſt courageous of his officers. With theſe he ſuſtained the fury of the victorious legions, and covered the retreat of his own men. But being, after a moſt gallant behaviour, dan-gerouſly wounded, he retired at laſt with his ſmall band in good order, leaving the Romans maſters of the field. As the ſun was near ſetting, the Romans, being extremely fatigued, and a great number of them wounded, the conſul Sulpicius, not thinking it adviſable to purſue the enemy, founded a retreat, repaſſed the ſtream, and brought his troops back to the camp. Sulpicius appeared in the field of battle the next day, with a deſign to bring the Epirots to a ſecond engagement ; but finding they had withdrawn in the night to Tarentum, he likewiſe retired, and put his troops into winter-quarters in Apulia.</p><p>Both armies continued quiet in their quarters during winter ; but early in the ſpring took the field anew.— The Romans were commanded this year by two men of great ſame, whom they had raiſed to the conſulate the ſecond time : theſe were the celebrated C. Fabri-cius and Æmilius Pappus ; who no ſooner arrived in Apulia, than they led their troops into the territory of Tarentum. Pyrrhus, who had received conſiderable reinforcements from Epirus, met them near the frontiers, and encamped at a ſmall diſtance from the Roman army. While the conſuls were waiting here for a favourable opportunity to give battle, a meſſenger from Nicias, the king’s phyſician, delivered a letter to Fabri-cius ; wherein the traitor offered to take off his maſter by poifon, provided the conſul would promiſe him a reward proportionable to the greatneſs of the ſervice. The virtuous Roman, being filled with horror at the bare propoſal of ſuch a crime, immediately communicated the affair to his colleague ; who readily joined with him in writing a letter to Pyrrhus, wherein they warned him, without diſcovering the criminal, to take care of himſelf, and be upon his guard againſt the treacherous deſigns of thoſe about him. Pyrrhus, out of a deep ſenſe of gratitude for ſo great a benefit, releaſed immediately, without ranſom, all the priſoners he had taken. But the Romans, diſdaining to accept either a ſavour from an enemy, or a recompenſe for not committing the blackeſt treachery, declared, that they would not receive their priſoners but by way of exchange ; and accordingly ſent to Pyrrhus an equal number of Samnite and Tarentine priſoners.</p><p>As the king of Epirus grew every day more weary oſa war which he feared would end in his diſgrace, he ſent Cyneas a ſecond time to Rome, to try whether he could, with his artful harangues, prevail upon the con-ſeript fathers to hearken to an accommodation, upon ſuch terras as were conſiſtent with his honour.. But the ambaſſador ſound the ſenators ſteady in their former reſolution, and determined not to enter into- a treaty with his maſter till he had left Italy, and withdrawn from thence all his forces. This gave the king great uneaſineſs ; for he· had already loſt moſt of his veteran troops and. beſt officers, and was ſenſible that he ſhould loſe the reſt if he ventured another engagement. While he was revolving theſe melancholy thoughts in his mind, ambaſſadors arrivçd at his camp from the Syra-cuſians, Agrigentines, and I√eontines, imploring the aſſiſtance of his arms to drive out the Carthaginians, and put an end to the troubles which threatened their respective ſtates with utter deſtruction. Pyrrhus, who wanted only ſome honourable pretence to leave Italy, laid hold of this ; and appointing Milo governor of Tarentum, with a ſtrong garriſon to keep the inhabitants in awe during his abſence, he ſet ſail ſor Sicily with 30,000 foot and 2500 horſe, on board a fleet of 200 ſhips. Here he was at firſt attended with great ſucceſs ; but the Sicilians, diſguſted at the reſolution he had taken of paſſing over into Africa, and much more at the enormous exactions and extortions of his miniſters and courtiers, had ſubmitted partly to the Carthaginians and partly to the Mamertines. When Carthage heard of this change, new troops were raiſed all over Africa, and a numerous army ſent into Sicily to recover the cities which Pyrrhus had taken. As the Sicilians daily deſerted from him in crowds, he was no way in a condition, with his Epirots alone, to withſtand ſo powerful an enemy ; and therefore, when deputies came to him from the Tarentines, Samnites, Bruttians, and Lucanians, repreſenting to him the loſſes they had ſuſtained ſince his departure, and remonſtrating, that, without his aſſiſtance, they muſt fall a ſacriſice to the Romans, he laid hold of that opportunity to abandon the iſland, and return to Italy. His fleet was attacked by that of Carthage ; and his army, after their landing, by the Mamertines. But Pyrrhus having, by his heroic bravery, eſeaped all danger, marched along the ſea-ſhore, in order to reach Tarentum that way. As he paſſed through the country of the Locrians, who had not long before maſſacred the troops he had left there, he not only exerciſed all ſorts of cruelty on the inhabitants, but plundered the temple of Proſerpine to ſupply the wants of his army. The immenſe riches which he found there, were, by his order, ſent to Tarentum by ſea ; but the ſhips that carried them being daſhed againſt the rocks by a tempeſt, and the mariners all loſt, this proud prince was convinced, ſays Livy, that the gods were not imaginary beings, and cauſed all the treaſure, which the ſea had thrown upon the ſhore, to be carefully gathered up, and replaced in the temple : nay, to appeaſe the wrath of the angry goddeſs, he put all thoſe to death who had adviſed him to plunder her temple. However, ſuperſtition made the ancients aſeribe to this act of impiety all the misfortunes, which , after» wards befel that unhappy prince.</p><p>Pyrrhus at length arrived at Tarentum ; but of the army he had carried into Sicily, he brought back into Italy only 2000 horſe and not· quite 20,000 foot. He therefore reinforced them w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ith the beſt troops he could raiſe in the countries of'the Samnites, Lucanians, and Bruttians ; and hearing that the two new conſuls, Cu-rius Dentatus and Cornelius. Lentulus, had divided their forces, the one invading Lucania and the other Samnium, he likewiſe divided his army into two bodies, marching, with the choice of his Epirots againſt Dentatus, in hopes of ſurpriſing him in his camp near Be-neventum. But the conſul having notice, of his approach, went out of his intrenchments with a ſtrong detachment of legionaries to meet him ; repulſed his</p></body></text></TEI>