<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Antium was laid aſide, and Camillus commanded to haſten to the relief of the allied cities, with the troops which Servilius had kept in readineſs at Rome in caſe of an emergency. Camillus immediately ſet out for the new war; and, upon his arrival before Sutrium, found that important place not only beſieged, but almoſt taken, the Hetrurians having made themſelves maſters of ſome of the gates, and gained poſſeſſion of all the avenues leading to the city. However, the inhabitants no ſooner heard that Camillus was come to their relief, but they recovered their courage, and, by barricadoes made in the ſtreets, prevented the enemy from making themſelves maſters of the whole city. Camillus in the mean time having divided his army into two bodies, ordered Valerius to march round the walls, as if he deſigned to ſcale them, while he with the other undertook to charge the Hetrurians in the rear, force his way into the city, and ſhut up the enemy between the beſieged and his troops. The Romans no ſooner appeared but the Hetrurians betook themſelves to a diſorderly flight through a gate which was not inveſted, Camillus’s troops made a dreadful ſlaughter of them within the city, while Valerius put great numbers of them to the ſword without the walls. From reconquering Sutrium, Camillus haſtened to the relief of Nepet. But that city being better affected to the Hetrurians than to the Romans, had voluntarily ſubmitted to the former. Wherefore Camillus, having inveſted it with his whole army, look it by aſſault, put all the Hetrurian ſoldiers without diſtinction to the ſword, and condemned the authors of the revolt to die by the axes of the lictors. Thus ended Camillus’s military tribuneſhip, in which he acquired no leſs reputation than he had done in the moſt glorious of his dictatorſhips.</p><p>In the following magiſtracy of ſix military tribunes, a dangerous ſedition is ſaid to have taken place through the ambition of Marcus Manlius, who had ſaved the capitol from the Gauls in the manner already related. Though this man had pride enough to deſpiſe all the other great men in Rome, yet he envied Camillus, and took every opportunity of magnifying his own exploits beyond thoſe of the dictator. But not finding ſuch a favourable reception from the nobility as he deſired, he concerted meaſures with the tribunes of the people, and ſtrove to gain the affections of the multitude. Not content with renewing the propoſal for the diſtribution of conquered lands, he alſo made himſelf an advocate for inſolvent debtors, of whom there was now a great number, as moſt of the lower claſs had been obliged to borrow money in order to rebuild their houſes. The ſenate, alarmed at this oppoſition, created A. Cornelius Coſſus dictator, for which the war with the Volſci afforded them a fair pretence. Manlius, however, ſtill continued to inflame the people againſt the patricians. Beſides the moſt unbounded perſonal generoſity, he held aſſemblies at his own houſe (in the citadel), where he confidently gave out that the ſenators, not content with</p><lb/><p>being the poſſeſſors of thoſe lands which ought to have been equally divided among all the citizens, had concealed, with an intent to appropriate it to their own uſe, all the gold which was to have been paid to the Gauls, and which would alone be ſufficient to diſcharge the debts of all the poor plebeians; and he moreover promiſed to ſhow in due time where this treaſure was concealed. For this aſſertion he was brought before the dictator; who commanded him to diſcover where the pretended treaſure was, or to confeſs openly before the whole aſſembly that he had ſlandered the ſenate. — Manlius replied, that the dictator himſelf, and the principal perſons in the ſenate, could only give the proper intelligence of this treaſure, as they had been the moſt active in ſecuring it. Upon this he was committed to priſon; but the people made ſuch diſturbance, that the ſenate were ſoon after fain to releaſe him. By this he was emboldened to continue his former practices; till at laſt the ſenate gave an order to the military tribunes to</p><p>take care that the commonwealth ſuffered no detriment from the pernicious projects of Marcus Manlius, and even gave them authority to aſſaſſinate him, if they found it neceſſary ſo to do. At laſt, however, he was publicly accuſed of aſpiring to be king; however, the people, it is ſaid, were ſo ſtruck with gratitude, on account of his having delivered the capitol from the Gauls, that they could not reſolve to condemn him. But the military tribunes, who, it ſeems, were bent on his deſtruction, having appointed the aſſembly to be held without the city, there obtained their wiſh. Manlius was thrown headlong from the capitol itſelf: it was thenceforth decreed that no patrician ſhould dwell in the capitol or citadel; and the Manlian family reſolved that no member of it ſhould ever afterwards bear the prænomen of <hi rend="italic">Marcus.</hi>  No ſooner was Manlius dead, however, than the people lamented his fate; and becauſe a plague broke out ſoon after, they imputed it to the anger of the gods on account of the deſtruction of the hero who had ſaved the ſtate @@(a).</p><p>The Romans, having now triumphed over the Sabines, the Etrurians, the Latins, the Hernici, the Æqui, and the Volſcians, began to look ſor greater conqueſts. They accordingly turned their arms againſt the Samnites, a people about 100 miles eaſt from the city, deſcended from the Sabines, and inhabiting a large tract of ſouthern Italy, which at this day makes a conſiderable part of the kingdom of Naples. Valerius Corvus and Cornelius were the two conſuls, to whoſe care it firſt fell to manage this dreadful contention between the rival ſtates.</p><p>Valerius was one of the greateſt commanders of his time; he was ſurnamed Corvus, from a ſtrange cir-cumſtance of being aſſiſted by a crow in a ſingle combat, in which he fought and killed a Gaul of a gigantic ſtature. To his colleague’s care it was conſigned to lead an army to Samnium, the enemy’s capital; while Corvus was ſent to relieve Capua, the capital of the</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) The above accounts are exactly conformable to what is to be found in the beſt Latin hiſtorians; nevertheleſs they are far from being reckoned univerſally authentic. Mr Hooke, in his annotations on the death of M. Manlius, has given very ſtrong reaſons againſt believing either that Camillus reſcued the gold from the Gauls, </hi>or that Manlius was condemned. See <hi rend="italic">Hooke's Roman Hiſtory,</hi>  Vol. II. p. 326, <hi rend="italic">et ſeq.</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>