<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>their ladders and ſend them tumbling down headlong into the ditches, where they were overwhelmed with ftones, or diſpatched with darts and other miſſile weapons. The baſtion of England proves the ſcene of the greateſt ſlaughter and bloodſhed; and the grand-maſter makes that his poſt of honour, and, by his preſence and example, inſpires his men with freſh vigour and bravery, whilſt the continual thunder of his artillery makes ſuch horrid work among the aſſailants as chills all their courage, and forces them to give way: the lieutenant-general, who commands the attack, leads them back with freſh vigour, and mounts the breach at the head of all; immediately after comes a cannonball from the Spaniſh baſtion, which overturns him dead into the ditch. This diſaſter, inſtead of fear and dread, fills them with a furious deſire of revenging his death: but all their obſtinacy cannot make the Rhodians go one ſtep back, whilſt the prieſts, monks, young men and old, and even women of every rank and age, aſſiſt them with an uncommon ardour and firmneſs; ſome in overwhelming the enemy with ſtones; others in deſtroying them with melted lead, ſulphur, and other combuſtibles; and a third ſort in ſupplying the combatants with bread, wine, and other refreſh-ments. </p><p>The aſſault was no leſs deſperate and bloody on the baſtion of Spain, where the knights, who guarded it, not expecting to be ſo ſoon attacked, and aſhamed to ſtand idle, were aſſiſting the baſtion of Italy; which gave the Turks an opportunity to mount the breach, and penetrate as far as their intrenchments, where they planted no leſs than 30 of their ſtandards on them. The grand-maſter was quickly appriſed of it, and ordered the baſtion of Auvergne to play againſt them; which was done with ſuch diligence, and ſuch continual fire, whilſt the Rhodians enter the baſtion by the help of their caſemates, and, ſword in hand, fall upon them with equal fury, that the Turks, alike beſet by the fire of the artillery and the arms of the Rhodian knights, were forced to abandon the place with a con-ſiderable loſs. The aga with great bravery rallies them afreſh, and brings them back, by which time the grand-maſter likewiſe appeared. The fight was renewed with greater fierceneſs; and ſuch ſlaughter was made on both ſides, that the grand-maſter was obliged to draw 200 men out of St Nicholas tower to his aſſiſtance: theſc were commanded by ſome Roman knights, who led them on with ſuch ſpeed and bravery, that their very</p><p>appearance on the baſtion made the janiſſaries draw back; which Solyman obſerving from his eminence, cauſed a retreat to be ſounded, to conceal the diſgrace of their flight. In theſe attacks there fell about 15, 000 of his belt troops, beſides ſeveral officers of diſtinction. The loſs of the beſieged -was no leſs conſiderable, if we judge from the ſmall number of their forces; but the greateſt of all to them was that of tome of their braveſt and moſt diſtinguiſhed knights and commanders, many of whom were killed, and ſcarce<hi rend="sup">,</hi> any eſcaped unwounded. But the moſt dreadful fate of all had like to have fallen on the favourite vizier Muſtapha, who had pro-poſed this general aſſault: the ill ſucceſs of which had ſo enraged the proud ſultan, that he condemned him to be ſhot with arrows at the head of his army; which dreadful ſentence was juſt ready to be executed, when the oldbaſhaw, by his intreaties, obtained a ſuſpenſion of it, in hopes that, when his fury was abated, he ſhould alſo obtain his pardon.</p><p>Solyman, however, was ſo diſcouraged by his ill ſuc-ceſſes, that he was on the point of raiſing the ſiege, and would have actually done fo, had he not been diverted from it by the advice which he received from an Albanian deſerter, ſome ſay by a letter from the traitor d'Amarald, that the far greater part of the knights were either killed or wounded, and thoſe that remained altogether incapable of ſuſtaining a freſh aſſault. This having determined him to try his fortune once more, the command of his forces was turned over to the baſhaw Achmed; and, to ſhow that he deſigned not to ſtir till he was maſter of the place, he ordered a houſe to be built on the adjacent mount Philermo for his winter-quarters. Achmed marched directly againſt the baſtion of Spain, which had ſuffered the moſt; where, before he could open the trenches, his men fell thick and threefold by the conſtant fire both of ſmall and great guns from the baſtion of Auvergne. He loſt ſtill a much greater number in rearing a rampart of earth to cover the attack, and give him an opportunity of ſapping the wall; and, as ſoon as he ſaw a large piece fall, ordered his men to mount the breach. They were no ſooner come to the top, than they found a new work and entrenchments which Martinengo had reared; and there they were welcomed with ſuch a briſk fire from the artillery, that they were glad to recover their trenches with the utmoſt precipitation, after having loſt the much greater part of their men. The attack was renewed, and a reciprocal fire continued with great obſtinacy, till a muſket-ſhot deprived that indefatigable engineer of one of his eyes, and the order of his aſſiduous ſervices for ſome time. The grand-maſter, having ordered him to be carried to his palace, took his place, and kept it till he was quite cured, which was not till 34 days after; and continued all the time in the intrenchments with his handful of knights, ſcarcely allowing himſelf reſt night or day, and ever ready to expoſe himſelf to the greateſt dangers, with an ardour more becoming a junior officer than an old worn-out ſovereign; which made his knights more laviſh of their own lives than their paucity and preſent circum-ſtances could well admit of.</p><p>Soon after this, the treaſon of D’Amarald was discovered, and he was condemned to death and executed; but by this time the city was reduced to the laſt extremity. The pope, emperor, and other crowned heads, had been long and often importuned by the grand-maſter for ſpeedy aſſiſtance, without ſucceſs; and, as an addition to all the other diſaſters, thoſe ſuc-cours which were ſent to him from France and England periſhed at ſea. The new ſupply which he had ſent for of proviſions from Candia had the ſame ill fate; ſo that the winds, ſeas, and every thing, ſeemed combined to bring on the deſtruction of that city and order. The only reſource which could be thought of, under ſo diſmal a ſituation, was, to ſend for the few remaining knights and forces which were left to guard the other iſlands, to come to the defence of their capital, in hopes that, if they could ſave this, the others might in time be recovered, in caſe the Turks ſhould ſeize upon them.</p><p>On the other hand, Solyman, grown impatient at the ſmall ground his general had gained, gave him expreſs orders to renew the attack with all imaginable ſpeed</p></body></text></TEI>