<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Theſe ſix ſorts are hardy plants, and will thrive in the open air here. The firſt and fourth ſorts are not quite ſo hardy as the others, ſo muſt have a better fi-tuation, ptherwiſe their branches will be injured by ſe-vere froſt in the winter. They arc eaſily propagated by ſeeds, which if ſown in autumn the plants will come up the following ſpring ; but if they are ſown in ſpring, they will not come up till the next ſpring ; they may be either ſown in pots, or the full ground. If they are ſown in pots in autumn, the pots ſhould be placed under a common frame in winter, where the ſeeds may be protected from hard froſt ; and in the ſpring, if the pots are plunged into a very moderate hot-bed, the plants will ſoon riſe, and have thereby more time to get ſtrength before winter. When the plants come up, they muſt be gradually hardened to bear the open air, into which they ſhould be removed as ſoon as the weather is favourable, placing them where they may have the morning ſun ; in the ſummer, they muſt be kept clean from weeds, and in dry weather watered. Toward autumn it will be proper to ſtint their growth by keeping them dry, that the extremity of their ſhoots may harden ; for if they are replete with moiſture, the early froſts in autumn will pinch them, which will cauſe their ſhoots to decay almoſt to the bottom if the plants are not ſcreened from them. If the pots are put under a common frame in autumn, it will ſecure the plants from injury : for while they are young and the ſhoots ſoft, they will be in danger of ſuffering, if the winter proves very ſevere ; but in mild weather they muſt always enjoy the open air, therefore ſhould never be covered but in froſt. The ſpring following, juſt before the plants begin to ſhoot, they ſhould be ſhaken out of the pots, and carefully ſeparated, ſo as not to tear the roots ; and tranſplanted into a nurſery, in rows three feet aſunder, and one foot diſtance in the rows. In this nurſery they may Hand two years to get·ſtrength, and then may be tranſplanted where they are to remain.</p><p>7. Beſides theſe, Linnæus has included in this genus the toxicodendron or poiſon-tree, under the name of <hi rend="italic">rhus vernix</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">poiſon-aſh.</hi>  This grows naturally in Virginia, Penſylvania, New .England, Carolina, and Japan, riſing with a ſtrong woody ſtalk to the height of 20 feet and upwards ; though in this country it is ſeldom ſeen above 12, by reaſon of the plants being extremely tender. The bark is brown, inclining to grey ; the branches are garniſhed with winged leaves compoſed of three or four pair of lobes terminated by an odd one. The lobes vary greatly in their ſhape, but for the moſt part they are oval and ſpear-ſhaped. The footſtalks become of a bright purple towards the latter part of ſummer, and in autumn all the leaves are of a beautiful purple before they fall off.</p><p>All the ſpecies of ſumach abound with an acrid milky juice, which is reckoned poiſonous; but this property is moſt remarkable in the vernix. The moſt diſtinct account of it is to be found in Proſeſſor Kalm’s Travels in North America. “ An inciſion (ſays he) being made into the tree, a whitiſh yellow juice, which lias a nauſeous ſmell, comes out between the bark and the wood. This tree is not known for its good qualities, but greatly ſo for the effect of its poiſon ; which, tho’ it is noxious to ſome people, yet does not in the leaſt affect others. And therefore one perſon can handle the tree as he pleaſes, cut it, peel off its bark, rub it or</p><lb/><p>the wood upon his hands, ſmell at it, ſpread the juice upon his ſkin, and make more experiments, with no in. convenience to himſelf : another perſon, on the contrary, dares not meddle with the tree while its wood is freſh ; nor can he venture to touch a hand which has handled it, nor even to expoſe himſelf to the ſtnoke of a fire which is made with this wood, without ſoon feel, ing its bad effects ; for the face, the hands, and frequently the whole body, ſwclls exceſſively, and is af* fected with a very acute pain. Sometimes bladders or bliſters ariſe in great plenty, and make the fiεk perſon look as if he was infected by a leprofy. In ſome people the external thin ſhin, or cuticle, peels off in a <hi rend="italic">fενι </hi>days, as is the caſe when a perſen has ſcalded or burnt any part of his body. Nay, the nature of ſome perſons will not even allow them to approach the place where the tree grows, or to expoſe themſelves to the wind when it carries the effluvia or exhalations of this tree with it, without letting them feel the inconvenience of the ſwelling which I have juſt now deſcribed. Their eyes are ſometimes ſhut up for one, or two, or more days together, by the ſwelling. 1 know two brothers, one of whom could without danger handle this tree in what manner he pleaſed, whereas the other could not come near it without ſwelling. A perſon ſometimes does not know that he has touched this poiſonous plant, or that he has been near it, before his face and hands ſhow it by their ſwelling. I have known old people who were more afraid of this tree than of a viper ; and I was acquainted w<hi rend="sub">j</hi>ith a perſon who, merely by the noxious exhalations of it, was ſwelled to ſuch a degree, that he was as ſtiff as a log of wood, and could only be turned about in ſheets.</p><p>“ I have tried experiments of every kind with the poifon-tree on myſelf. I have ſpread its juice upon my hands, cut and broke its branches, peeled off its bark, and rubbed my hands with it, ſmelt at it, carried pieces' of it in my bare hands, and repeated all this frequently, without feeling the baneful effects ſo commonly annexed to it ; but I, however, once cxperienced, that the' poiſon of the ſumach was not entirely without effect upon me. Oil a hot day in ſummer, as I was in ſome degree of peiſpiration, I cut a branch of the tree, anſh carried it in my hand for about half an hour together, and ſmelt at it now and then. I felt nq effects from it in the evening. But next morning I awoke with a-violent itching of my eye-lids and the parts thereabouts; and this was ſo painful, that I could hardly keep my hands from it. It ceaſed after I had waſhed my eyes for a while with very cold water. But my eye-lids were very ſtiff all that day. At night the itching returned ; and in the morning when I awoke, I felt it as ill as the morning before, and I uſed the ſame remedy againſt it. However, it continued almoſt for a whole week together ; and my eyes were very red, and my eye-lids were with difficulty moved during all that time. My pain ceaſed entirely afterwards. About the fame time I had ſpread the juice of the tree very thick upon my hand. Three days after, they occaſtoned bliſters, which ſoon went off without affecting me much. I have not experienced any thing more of the effects of this plant, nor had I any deſire ſo to do. However, I found that it could not exert its power upon me when-I was not perſpiring.</p><p>I have never heard that the poiſon of this ſumach</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>