<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>took care to ſtrengthen his party in the ſenate by adding another hundred to that body. Theſe were called <hi rend="italic">ſenator es miηorum gentium,</hi>  becauſe they were choſen out of the plebeians ; however, they had the ſame authority in the ſenate as the others, and their children were called <hi rend="italic">patridaηs.</hi></p><p>Tarquin was not inferior to any of his predeceſſors either in his inclination or abilities to carry on a war. As ſoon as he aſcended the throne, he recommenced hoſtilities with the Latins ; from whom he took the cities of Apiolas, Cruſtuminum, Nomentum, and Collatia. The inhabitants of Apiolse were ſold for Haves ; but thoſe of Cruſtuminum and Nomentum, who had ſubmitted after their revolt, were treated with great clemency. The inhabitants of Collatia were diſarmed, and obliged to pay a large ſum of money ; the ſovereignty of it, in the mean time, being given to Egerius, the ſon of Arunx, Tarquin’s brother; ſrom whence he took the name of <hi rend="italic">Collatinus,</hi>  which he tranſmitted to his poſterity. Corniculum, another city of Latium, was taken by ſtorm, and reduced to aſhes. This progreſs having greatly alarmed the Latins, ſeveiwl of them joined their forces in order to oppoſe ſuch a formidable enemy ; but being defeated in a bloody battle near Fi-denæ, they were obliged to enter into an alliance with Rome ; upon which the Latins having held a national conference, entered into a league with the Hetrurians, and again took the field with a very numerous army. But Tarquin, having defeated the confederate armies in two very bloody battles, obliged the Latin cities to ſubmit to a kind of dependence on Rome ; and, having entered the city in triumph, built the circus maximus with the ſpoils which he had taken from the enemy.</p><p>The war with the Latins was ſcarce ended, when another commenced with Hetruria. This was accounted the moſt powerful nation in Italy, and was at that time divided into 12 tribes or lucomonies. Theſe appointed a national aſſembly, in which it was decreed that the whole force of Hetruria ſhould be employed againſt Tarquin ; and if any city preſumed only to ſtand neuter, it ſhould be for ever cut off from the national alliance. Thus a great army was raiſed, with which they ravaged the Roman territory, and took Fidenæ by the treachery of ſome of its inhabitants. Tarquin, not being in a condition to oppoſe them at firſt, was obliged to ſubmit to jthe loſs occaſioned by their ravages for a whole year ; after which he took the field with all the forces he could raiſe. The Roman army was divided into two bodies, one under the king himſelf, the other commanded by his nephew Collatinus. The latter, having divided his forces in order to plunder the country, was defeated ; but Tarquin, in two engagements, vanquiſhed the army which oppoſed him. He then marched againſt Fidenæ, where he gained a third battle ; after which he took the city. Such of the citizens as were ſuſpected to have been concerned in betraying ſt to the enemy were whipped to death ; the reſt were ſent into baniſhment, and their ∙ lands divided by lot among the Roman ſoldiers. Tarquin now haſtened to oppoſe the new army of the Hetrurians before their forces could be properly collected ; and having come up with them at Ereturn, a place about jo miles from Rome, defeated them with great ſlaughter, ſor which victory he was decreed a</p><p>triumph by the ſenate 5 while the enemy, dlſlteartened by ſo many misfortunes, were glad to ſue for peace ; which Tarquin readily granted, upon the ſole condition of their owning his ſuperiorſty over them. In compliance with this, the Hetrurians ſent him all the, enſigns of royalty which were in uſe among them, viz. a crown of gold, a throne of ivory, a ſceptre with an eagle on the top of it, a tunic embroidered with gold, and adorned with figures of palm branches, together with a purple robe enriched with flowers of ſeveral colours. Tarquin, however, would not wear theſe magnificent ornaments till ſuch time as the ſenate and people had conſented to it by an expreſs law. He then applied the regalia to the decoration of his triumph, and never afterwards laid them aſide. In this triumph he appeared in a gilt chariot, drawn by four horſes, clothed in a purple robe, and a tunic embroidered with gold, a crown on his head, and a ſceptre in his hand, attended by 12 liétors with their axes and faſees.</p><p>Tarquin, having now obtained ſome reſpite from war, applied himſelf to the beautifying and ornamenting the city. He built the walls of Rome with hewn ſtone, and erected thoſe famous common ſewers which have deſervedly been accounted one of the wonders of the world. Rome at this time contained four hills within its compaſt, viz. the Palatinus, Tarpeius, Qui-rinalis, and Cœlius. In the valleys between theſe hills, the rain-water and ſprings uniting, formed great pools which laid under water the ſtreets and public places. The mud likewiſe made the way impaſſable, infected the air, and rendered the city unhealthy. Tarquin undertook to free the city from this nuiſance, by conveying off theſe waters by ſubterraneous channels into the Tiber. In doing this, it was neceſſary to cut thro* hills and rocks a channel large enough for a navigable ſtream, and covered with arches ſtrong enough to bear the weight of houſes, which were frequently built upon them, and ſtood as firm as on the moſt ſolid foundations. All theſe arches were made of hard ſtone, and neither trouble nor expence were ſpared to make the work durable. Their height and bιeadth were ſo conſiderable, that a cart loaded with hay could eaſily paſs through them under ground. The expence of con-ſtructing theſe ſewers was never ſo thoroughly underſtood as when it became neceſſary to repair them ; for then the cenſors gave no leſs than 1000 talents to the perſen appointed for this purpoſe.</p><p>Beſides theſe great works, Tarquin adorned the forum, ſurrounding it with galleries in which were ſhops for tradeſmen, and building temples in it for the youth of both ſexes, and halls ſor the adminiſtration of public juſtice. He next engaged in a war with the Sabines, on pretence that they had aſſiſted the Hetrurians. Both armies took the field, and came to an engagement on the confines of Sabinia, without any conſiderable advantage on either ſide ; neither was any thing-of conſequence done during the whole campaign. Tarquin then, conſidering with himſelf that the Roman forces were very deficient in cavalry, reſolved to add ſome new bodies of knights to thoſe already inſtituted by Romulus. But this project met with great oppoſition from the ſuperſtitious augurs, as the original diviſion of horſe into three bodies had been determined by auguries ; and Actius Nævius, the chief of</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>