<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſeat of the empire. The people were inclined to favour the project, Veii offering them a place fortified by art and nature, good houſes ready built, a wholeſome air, and a fruitful territory. On the other hand, they had no materials for rebuilding a whole city, were quite exhauſted by misfortunes, and even their ſlrength was greatly diminiſhed. This gave them a reluctance to ſo great an undertaking, and emboldened the tribunes to utter ſeditious harangues againſt Camillus, as a man too ambitious of being the reſtorer of Rome. They even inſinuated that the name of Romulus, which had been given him, threatened the republic with a new king. But the ſenate took the part of Camillus, and, being deſirous to ſee Rome rebuilt, continued him, contrary to cuſtom, a full year in the office of dictator; during which time he made it his whole buſineſs to ſup-preſs the ſtrong inclination of the people to remove to Veii. Having aſſembled the curiæ, he expoſtulated with them upon the matter; and, by arguments drawn from prudence, religion, and glory, prevailed upon them to lay aſide ail thoughts of leaving Rome. As it was neceſſary to have the reſolution of the people confirmed by the ſenate, the dictator reported it to the conſcript fathers, leaving every one at full liberty to vote as he pleaſed. While L. Lucretius, who was to give his opinion the firſt, was beginning to ſpeak, it happened that a centurion, who with his company had been upon guard, and was then marching by the ſenate-houſe, cried out aloud, “ Plant your colours, enſign; this is the beſt place to, ſtay in. ” Theſe words were conſider-ed as dictated by the gods themſelves; and Lucretius, taking occaſion from them to urge the neceſſity of ſtaying at Rome, “ An happy omen, (cried he); I adore the gods who gave it. ” The whole ſenate applauded, his words; and a decree was paſſed without oppoſition for rebuilding the city.</p><p>Though the tribunes of the people were defeated by Camillus in this point, they reſolved to exerciſe their authority againſt another patrician, who had indeed deſerved puniſhment. This was Q. Fabius, who had violated the law of nations, and thereby provoked the Gauls, and occaſioned the burning of Rome- His crime being notorious, he was ſummoned by C. Martius Rutilus before the aſſembly of the people, to anſwer for his conduct in his embaſſy. The criminal had reaſon to fear the ſevereſt puniſhment: but his relations gave out that he died, ſuddenly; which generally happened when the accuſed perſon had courage enough to prevent his condemnation, and the ſhame of a public puniſhment. On the other hand, the republic gave an houſe ſituated on the Capitol to M. Manlius, as a monument of his valour, and of the gratitude of his follow-citizens. Camillus cloſed this year by laying down his dictatorſhip: whereupon an interregnum enſued, during which he governed the ſtate alternately with P. Cornelius Scipio and it fell to his lot to preſide at the election of new magiſtrates, when L. Valerius Poplicola, L. Virginius Tricoſtus, P. Cornelius Coſſus, A. Manlius Capitolinus, L. Æmilius Mamercinus, and L. Poſthumius Albinus, were choſen. The firſt care of theſe new magiſtrates was to collect all the ancient monuments of the religion and civil laws of Rome which could be found among the ruins of the demoliſhed city. The laws of the twelve tables, and ſome of the laws of the kings, had been written on braſs, and</p><p>fixed up in the forum and the treaties made with ſeveral nations had been engraved on pillars erected in the temples. Pains were therefore taken to gather up the ruins of theſe precious monuments; and what could not be found was ſupplied by memory. The ponti-hees, on their part, took care to re-eſtabliſh the religious ceremonies, and made alſo a liſt of lucky and unlucky days.     </p><p>And now the governors of the republic applied themſelves wholly to rebuild the city; Plutarch tells us, that as the workmen were digging among the ruins of the temple of Mars, they found Romulus’s augural ſtaff untouched by the flames; and that this was looked upon as a prodigy, from whence the Romans inferred that their city would continue for ever. The expence of building private houles was partly defrayed out of the public treaſure. The ædiles had the direction of the works; but they had ſo little taſte for order or beauty, that the city, when rebuilt, was even leſs regular than in the time of Romulus. And though in Auguſtus’s time, when Rome became the capital of the known world, the temples, palaces, and private houſes, were built in a, more magnificent manner than before; yet even then theſe new decorations did not rectify the faults of the plan upon, which the city had been built after its firſt demolition.</p><p>Rome was ſcarce reſtored, when her citizens were alarmed by the news that all her neighbours were combining to her deſtruction. The Æqui, the Volſci, the Hetrurians, and even her old friends the Latins and the Hernici, entered into an alliance againſt her, in hopes of opprefling her before, ſhe had recovered her ſtrength. The republic, under this terror, nominated Camillus dictator a third time. This great commander, having appointed Servilius to be his general of horſe, ſummoned the citizens to take arms, without excepting, even the old men. He divided the new levies into three bodies. The firſt, under the command of A-Manlius, he ordered to encamp under the walls of Rome; the ſecond he ſent into the neighbourhood of Veii; and marched himſelf at the head of the third, to relieve the tribunes, who were cloſely beſieged in their camp by the united forces of the Volſci and Latins. Finding the enemy encamped near Lanuvium, on the declivity of the hill Marcius, he poſted himſelf behind it, and, by lighting, fires, gave the diſtreſſed Romans notice of his arrival. The Volſci and Latins, when they underſtood that Camillus was at the head of an army newly arrived, were ſo terrified, that they ſhut themſelves up in their camp, which they fortified with great trees cut down in haſte. The dictator, obſerving that this barrier was of green wood, and that every morning there aroſe a great wind, which blew full upon the enemy’s camp, formed the deſign of taking it by fire. With this view he ordered one part of his army to go by break of day with fire-brands to the windward ſide of the camp, and the other to make a briſk attack on the oppoſite ſide. By this means the enemy were entirely defeated, and their camp taken. Camillus then commanded his men to extinguiſh the</p><p>flames, in order to ſave the booty, with which he rewarded his army. He then left his ſon in the camp, to guard the priſoners; and, entering the country of the Æqui, made himſelf maſter of their capital city Bola. From thence he marched againſt the Volſci;</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>