<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and having the ſame degree of poliſh or roughneſs; and if this tube be inclined in ſuch a manner that the axis of its extremity may coincide with the axis of AB in the point C—we affirm that the velocity will be the ſame in both pipes, and that they will have the ſame expence; for the moving force in the ſloping pipe EC is compoſed of the whole weight of the column DE and the relative weight of the column EC; but this relative weight, by which alone it deſcends along the inclined pipe EC, is preciſely equal to the weight of a vertical column EA of the ſame diameter. Everything therefore is equal in the two pipes, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>  the lengths, the diameters, the moving forces, and the reſiſtances; therefore the velocities and diſcharges will alſo be equal.</p><p>This is not only the caſe on the whole, but alſo in every part of it. The relative weight of any part of it EK is preciſely in equilibrio with the reſiſtances along that part of the pipe; for it has the ſame proportion to the whole relative weight that the reſiſtance lias to the whole reſiſtance. Therefore (<hi rend="italic">and this is the moſt important circumſtance, and the balls of the whole theory )</hi>  the pipe EC may be cut ſhorter, or may be lengthened to infinity, without making any change in the velocity or expence, ſo long as the propelling head DE remains the ſame.</p><p>Leaving the whole head DA as it is, if we lengthen the horizontal pipe AB to G, it is evident that we increaſe the reſiſtance without any addition of force to overcome it. The velocity muſt therefore be diminiſh-ed; and it will now be a velocity which is produced by a ſmaller head than DE: therefore if we were to put in a pipe of equal length at E, terminating in the horizontal line AG, the water will not run equally in both pipes. In order that it may, we muſt diſcover the diminiſhed velocity with which the water now actually runs along AG, and we muſt make a head DI capable of impreſſing this velocity at the entry of the pipe, and then inſert at I a pipe IH of the ſame length with AG. The expence and velocity of both pipes will now be the ſame @@(a).</p><p>What, has now been ſaid of a horizontal pipe AB would have been equally true of any inclined pipe AB, A'B (fig. 8. ) Drawing the horizontal line CB, we ſee that DC is the whole head or propelling preſſure for either pipe AB or A'B; and if DE is the head neceſſary for the actual velocity, EC is the head neceſſary for balancing the reſiſtances; and the pipe EF of the ſame length with AB, and terminating in the ſame horizontal line, will have the ſame velocity; and its inclination being thus determined, it will have the ſame velocity and expence whatever be its length.</p><p>Thus we ſee that the motion in any pipe, horizontal or ſloping, may be referred to or ſubſtituted for the motion in another inclined pipe, whoſe head of water, above the place of entry, is that productive of the actual velocity of the water in the pipe. Now, in this caſe, the accelerating force is equal to the reſiſtance: we may therefore conſider this laſt pipe as a river, of which the bed and the ſlope are uniform or conſtant, and the current in a ſtate of permanency; and we now may clearly draw this important concluſion, that pipes and open ſtreams, when in a ſtate of permanency, perfectly reſemble each other in the circumſtances which are the immediate cauſes of this permanency. The equilibrium between the accelerating force obtains not only in general, but takes place through the whole length of the pipe or ſtream, and is predicable of every individual tranſverſe ſection of either. To make this more palpably evident if poſſible, let us conſider a ſloping cylindrical pipe, the current of which is in a ſtate of permanency. We can conceive it as conſiſting of two half cylinders, an upper and a lower. Theſe are running together at an equal pace; and the filaments of each immediately contiguous to the ſeparating plane and to each other, are not rubbing on each other, nor affecting each others motions in the ſmalleſt degree. It is true that the upper half is preſſing on the lower, but in a direction perpendicular to the motion, and therefore not affecting the velocity; and we ſhall ſee preſently, that although the lower ſide of the pipe bears ſomewhat more preſſure than the other, the reſiſtances are not changed. ( Indeed this odds of preſſure is accompanied with a difference of motion, which need not be conſidered at preſent; and we may ſuppoſe the pipe ſo ſmall or ſo far below the ſurface, that this ſhall be in-ſenſible). Now let us ſuppoſe, that in an inſtant the upper half cylinder is annihilated: We then have an open ſtream; and every circumſtance of accelerating force and of reſiſtance remains preciſely as it was. The motion muſt therefore continue as it did; and in this ſtate the only accelerating force is the ſlope of the ſurface. The demonſtration therefore is complete.</p><p>From theſe obſervations and reaſonings we draw a general and important concluſion, “ That the ſame pipe will be ſuſceptible of different velocities, which it will preſerve uniform to any diſtance, according as it has different inclinations; and each inclination of a pipe of given diameter has a certain velocity peculiar to itſelf, which will be maintained uniform to any diſtance</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) We recommend it to the reader to make this diſtribution or allotment of the different portions of the preſſure very familiar to his mind. It is of the moſt extenſive influence in every queſtion of hydraulics, and will on every occaſion give him diſtinct conceptions of the internal procedure. Obvious as the thought ſeems to be, it has eſcaped the attention of all the writers on the ſubject. Lecchi, in his </hi><hi rend="italic">Hydraulics</hi>  publiſhed in 1766, aſcribes ſomething like it to Daniel Bernoulli; but Bernoulli, in the paſſage quoted, only ſpeaks of the partition of preſſure in the inſtant of opening an orifice. Part of it, ſays he, is employed in accelerating the quieſcent water, and producing the velocity of efflux, and the remainder produces the preſſure (now diminiſhed) on the ſides of the veſſel. Bernoulli, Boſſut, and all the good writers, make this diſtribution in expreſs terms in their explanation of the motion of water through ſucceſſive orifices; and it is ſurpriſing that no one before the Chevalier de Buat ſaw that the reſiſtance ariſing from friction required a ſimilar partition of the preſſure; but though we ſhould call this good fortune, we muſt aſcribe to his great ſagacity and juſtneſs of conception the beautiful uſe that he has made of it: "<hi rend="italic">ſ</hi><hi rend="italic">uum cuique. </hi>"</p></body></text></TEI>