<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the mercy of Louis XIII.. At the beginning of the firſt ſiege, the number of inhabitants in the city amounted to 72,000 ; in the ſecond they diminiſhed to 28,000 ; and they were, when Mr Wraxal was there, between 17 and 18,000, of which ſcarce 2000 were Huguenots. The houſes of this city are fine, and ſupported with piazzas, under which perſons may walk in all weathers ; and the ſtreets in general are as ſtraight as a line. There ate ſeveral handſome churches, and other ſtructures, beſides a remarkable pump in the ſquare of Dauphiny, which throws out the water through ſeveral pipes. There are no remains of the old fortifications, except on the ſide of the harbour, where there are bulwarks and ſtrong towers to defend the entrance. The new fortifications are in the manner of Vauban. Before Canada was ceded to England·, and New Orleans to Spain, the trade of Rochelle was very lucrative. It revived about the year 1773, and, beſide that to the coaſt of Guinea and the Eaſt Indies, the inhabitants carried on a conſiderable trade in wines, brandy, fait, paper, linen cloth, and ſerge. It is ſeated on the ocean, in W. Long. 1. it. N. Lat. 46. 10.</p><p>ROCHESTER, a city of Kent, in England, is ſituated on the Medway, ſeven miles and a half north of Maidſtone, and 30 from London. It appears to have been one of the Roman ſtations, from the bricks in the walls, as well as the Roman coins that have been found about it. It has three pariſh churches built with ſtone and flints, beſides the cathedral, which is but a mean ſtructure. This little city, which was made a biſhop’s ſee by king Ethelbert, anno 604, has met with many misfortunes. In 676, it was ſacked by Eldred king of Mercia; in 839 and 885, beſieged by the L)anes, but reſcued by king Alfred. About 1 co years after, it was beſieged by king Ethelred, and forced to pay L. 100. Anno 999 it was taken and plundered by the Danes. Anno 1088 it was beſieged and taken by William Rufus. In king John’s time it was taken from the Barons, after three month’s ſiege ; and the very next year, viz. 1 256, its caſtle, founded by William the Conqueror, was ſtormed and taken by ſeveral .of the Barons, under the French king’s ſon. In the ιct"gn of Henry III. it was beſieged by Simon Mont-ford, who burnt its then wooden bridge and tower, and ſpoiled the church and priory, and then marched off. This city has alſo been ſeveral times deſtroyed by fire, viz. in 1130, on June 3. in 1137, and in 1177; after which it is ſaid to have continued deſolate till 1225, when it was repaired, ditched, and walled round. In the Saxon heptarchy there were three mints in Rocheſ-ter, two ſor the king and one for the biſhop. In 1281, its old wooden bridge was carried off by the ice, in a ſudden thaw after a froſt which had made the Medway paſſable on foot. Another was built in the reign of Richard II. but pulled down again, on the rumour oſ an invaſion from France. It was afterwards reſtored, but ſo often ſubject to expenſive repairs, by reaſon of the rapid courſe of the river under it, as well as the great breadth and depth of it, that in the reign of Edward III. it was reſolved to build a new bridge of ſtone ; and the ſame was begun, and in a manner completed, at the expence of Sir John Cobham and Sir Robert Knolles, Edward III.’s generals, out of the ſpoils they bad taken in <hi rend="sub">ι</hi>France. It has 21 arches. The town is ‘governed by a mayor, recorder, 12 aldeιmen, 12</p><lb/><p>common ∙councirmen, a town-clerk, three ſerjeants at mace, and a water-bailiff. To its cathedral belong a dean and fix prebendaries. Gundulph’s tower ſtands on the north ſide of the cathedral, and is ſuppoſed to have been built by the biſhop, as a place of fecurity for the treaſures and archives of that church and ſee. Some ſuppoſe it to have been intended for a bell tower, and others for an eccleſiaſtical priſon ; but whatever might be its deſtination, its machicolations, its loop-hole windows, and the thickneſs of its walls, ſhows ſtrength and defence were conſidered as neceſſary. This tower was 60 ſeet high, but ſome part has lately fallen down ; the walls are fix feet thick, and contain within them an area of 20 feet ſquare : it was divided into five floors or ſtories of unequal height, and had a communication with the upper part of the church, by means of an arch or bridge, the ſteps of which are ſtill viſible. It is ſuppoſed to have been erected after the cathedral was built. For the maintenance of its bridge, certain lands are tied down by parliament, to which it has ſent members from the firſt. The town-houſe, built in the year 1687, ſor the courts, aſſizes, and ſeſ-ſions, and the charity-ſchool, are two of the beſt public buildings here.—A mathematical ſchool was founded here, and an alms-houſe for lodging fix poor travellers every night, and allowing them 4 d. in the morning when they depart, except perſons contagiouſiy diſeaſed, rogues, and proctors. In the ſummer here are always fix or eight lodgers, who are admitted by tickets from the mayor. The Roman Watling-ſtreet runs through this town from Shooters-Hill to Dover. The mayor and citizens hold what is called an admiralty-court 01ice a-year for regulating the oyſter-ſiſhery in the creeks and branches of the Medway that are within their juriſdic-tion, and for proſecuting the cable-hangers, as they are called, who dredge and fiſh ſor oyſters without being free, by having fen<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ed ſeven years apprenticeſhip to a fiſherman who is free of the ſiſhery. Every licenſed dredger pays 6s. 8d. a-year to the ſupport of the courts, and the ſiſhery is now in a flouriſhing way. Part of the caſtle is kept in repair, and is uſed as a magazine, where a party of ſoldiers do conſtant duty. The bridge was repaired in 1744, and palliſadoed with new iron rails. Ro∙ cheſter contains about 700 houſes, and 2000 inhabitants. It conſiſts of only one principal ſtreet, which is wide, and paved with flints. The houſes are generally well built with brick, and inhabited by tradeſmen and innkeepers. It has alſo four narrow ſtreets ; but no fort of manufactory is carried on here. Stroud is at the weft end of this place, and Chatham at the eaſt. It is 27 miles north-weſt by well of Canterbury, and 30 ſouth-eaſt by eaſt of London. Long. o. 36. E, Lat, 51. 23. N-</p><p>RocHtsτER (earl of). See Wilmot.</p><p>ROCK, a large maſs or block of hard ſtone rooted</p><p>in the ground. See Mountain, Petrifaction, and Stone.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rock, in ornithology, a ſpecies of Vulture.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rock Baſons</hi></hi>  are cavities or artificial baſons of diffe</p><p>rent ſizes, from ſix feet to a few inches diameter, cut in the ſurface <hi rend="italic">of</hi>  the rocks for the purpoſe, as is ſuppoſed, of collecting the dew and rain pure as it de-ſcended ſrom the heavens, for the uſe of ablutions and purifications, preſcribed in the druidieal religion; theſe, eſpecially the dew, being deemed the pureſt of all</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>