<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>This commander gave no anſwer to his requeſts, but ſtill continued his march towards Rome. Being arrived before the walls of thé city, the forces of Vitellius were reſolved upon defending it to the utmoſt extremity. It was attacked on three ſides with the utmoſt fury ; while the army within, ſally ing upon the beſiegers, defended it with equal obſtinacy. The battle laſted a whole day, till at laſt the beſieged were driven into the city, and a dreadful ſtaughter made of them in all the ſtreets, which they vainly attempted to defend. In the mean time, the citizens ſtood by, looking on as 'both ſides fought ; and, as if they had been in a theatre, clapped their hands ; at one time encouraging one party, and again the other. As either turned their backs, the citizens would then fall upon them in their places of refuge, and ſo kill and plunder them without mercy. But what was ſtill more remarkable, during theſe dreadful ſlaughters both within and without the city, the people would not be prevented from celebrating one of their riotous feaſts, called the <hi rend="italic">Saturnalia ;</hi>  ſo that at one time might have been ſeen a ſtrange mixture of mirth and miſery, of cruelty and lewdneſs ; in one place, buryings and ſlaughters ; in another, drunkenneſs and feaſting ; in a word, all the horrors of a civil war, and all the licentiouſneſs of the moſt abandoned ſecurity !</p><p>During this complicated ſcene of miſery, Vitellius retired privately to his wife’s houſe, upon mount Aventine, deſigning that night to fly to the army commanded by his brother at Tarracina. But, quite incapable, through fear, of forming any reſolution, he changed his mind, and returned again to his palace, now void and deſolate ; all his ſlaves forſaking him in his diſtreſs, and purpoſely avoiding his preſence. There, after wandering for ſome time quite diſconſolate, and fearing the face of every creature he met, he hid himſelf in an obſcure corner, from whence he was ſoon taken by a party of the conquering ſoldiers. Still, however, wailing to add a few hours more to his miſerable life, he begged to be kept in priſon till the arrival of •Ve.ſpaſian at Rome, pretending that he had ſecrets of importance to diſcover. But his intreaties were vain : the ſoldiers binding his hands behind him, and throwing an halter round his neck, led him along, half naked, into the public forum, upbraiding him, as they proceeded, with all thoſe bitter reproaches their malice could ſuggeſt, or his own cruelties deſerve. They jallb tied his hair backwards, as was uſual with the moſt infamous malefactors, and held the point of a ſword under his chin, to prevent his hiding his face from the public. Some caſt dirt and filth upon him as he paſſed, others ſtruck him with their hands ; ſome ridiculed the defects of his perſon, his red fiery face, and the e-mormous greatneſs of his belly. At length, being come to the place of puniſhment, they killed him with many blows ; and then dragging the dead body through the ſtreets with an hook, they threw it, with all poſſible ignominy, into the river Tiber. Such was the miſerable</p><p>end of this emperor, in the 57th year of his age, after a ſhort reign of eight months and five days.</p><p>Vitellius being dead, the conquering army purſued their enemies throughout the city, while neither houſes nor temples afforded refuge to the fugitives. The ſtieets and public places were all ſtrewed with dead, each man lying ſlain where it was his misfortune to be</p><lb/><p>overtaken by his unmerciful purſuers. But not only the enemy ſuffered in this manner, but many of the citizens, who were obnoxious to the ſoldiers, were dragged from their houſes, and killed without any form of trial. The heat of their reſentment being ſomewhat abated, they next began to ſeek for plunder ; and under pretence of ſearching ſor the enemy, left no place without marks of their rage or rapacity. Beſides the ſoldiers, the lower rabble joined in theſe deteſtable outrages ; ſome ſlaves came and diſcovered the riches of their maſters ; ſome were detected by their neareſt friends ; the whole city was filled with outcry and lamentation ; inſomuch, that the former ravages of Otho and Vitellius were now conſidered as flight evils in compariſon.</p><p>At length, however, upon the arrival of Mutianus, general to Veſpaſian, theſe ſlaughters ceaſed, and the ſtate began to wear the appearance of former tranquillity. Veſpaſian was declared emperor by the unanimous conſent both of the ſenate and the army ; and dignified with all thoſe titles, which now followed rather the power than the merit of thoſe who were appointed to govern. Meſſengers were diſpatched to him into Egypt, deſiring his return, and teſtifying the utmoſt deſire for his government. However, the winter being dangerous for failing, he deferred his voyage to a more convenient ſeaſon. Perhaps, alſo, the diſſenſions in other parts of the empire retarded his return to Rome ; for one Claudius Civilis, in Lower Germany, excited his countrymen to revolt, and deſtroyed the Roman garriſons, which were placed in different parts of that province. But, to give his rebellion an air of juſtice, he cauſed his army to ſwear allegiance to Veſpaſian, until he found himſelf in a condition to throw off the maik. When he thought himſelf ſufficiently powerſul, he diſclaimed all ſubmiſſion to the Roman government ; and having overcome one or two of the lieutenants of the empire, and being joined by ſuch of the Romans as refuſed obedience to the new emperor, he boldly advanced to give Cerealis, Veſpaſi-an’s general, battle. In the beginning of this engagement, he ſeemed ſucceſsful, breaking the Roman legions, and putting their cavalry to flight. But at length Cerealis by his conduct turned the fate of the day, and not only routed the enemy, but took and deſtroyed their camp. This engagement, however, was not deciſive ; ſeveral others enſued with doubtful ſucceſs. An accommodation at length took place. Civilis obtained peace for his countιymen, and pardon for himſelf ; for the Roman empire was, at this time, ſo torn by its own diviſions, that the barbarous nations around made incurſions with impunity, and were ſure of obtaining peace whenever they thought proper to demand it.</p><p>During the time of theſe commotions in Germany, the Sarmatians, a barbarous nation in the north-eaſt of the empire, ſuddenly paſſed the river Iſer, and marched into the Roman dominions with ſuch celerity and fury, as to deſtroy ſeveral garriſons, and an army under the command of Eonteius Agrippa. However, they were driven back by Rubrius Gallus, Veſpaſian’s lieutenant, into their native ſoreſts; where ſeveral -attempts were made to confine them by garriſons and forts, placed along the confines of their country. But theſe hardy nations, having once found the way into the empire,</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>