<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ture, long narrow flexible pieces of timber, nailed upon the outſade of the ribs, from the item to the ftern-∙ poſt, ſo as to envelope the ſhip lengthwiſe, and appear on her ſide and bottom like the meridians on the ſur-face of the globe. The ribands being judiciouſly arranged with regard to their height and diſtance from each other, and forming regular ſweeps about the ſhip’s body, will compoſe a kind of frame, whoſe interior ſur-face will determine the curve of all the intermediate or filling-timbers which are ſtationed between the principal ones. As the figure of the ſhip’s bottom approaches to that of a conoid, and the ribands have a limited breadth, it is apparent that they cannot be applied to this convex ſurface without forming a double curve, which will be partly vertical and partly horizontal ; ſo that the vertical curve will increaſe by approaching the ſtem, and ſtill more by drawing near the iiern-poſt. It is alſo evident, that by deviating from the middle line of the ſhip’s length, as they approach the extreme breadth at the midſhip-frame, the ribands will alſo form an horizontal curve. The loweſt of theſe, which is termined upon the ſtem and ſtern-poſt, at the height of the riſing-line of the floor, and anſwers to the upper part of the floor-timber upon the midſhip-frame, is called the <hi rend="italic">floor-riband.</hi>  That which coincides with the wing-tranſom, at the height of the lower-deck upon the midſhip-frame, is termed the <hi rend="italic">breadth riband ; </hi>all the reſt, which are placed between theſe two, are called <hi rend="italic">intermediate ribands.</hi>  See Ship-building.</p><p>RIBES, the Currant and Gooseberry-bush: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the pen-tandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 36th order, <hi rend="italic">Pomaceœ.</hi>  There are five petals, and ſtamina inſerted into the calyx ; the ſtyle is bifid ; the berry polyſpermous, inferior.</p><p>The currant and the gooſeberry were long conſider-ed each as a ſeparate genus ; <hi rend="italic">ribes</hi>  the currant, and <hi rend="italic">groſſularia</hi>  the gooſeberry ; but they are now joined together, the groſſularia being made a ſpecies of <hi rend="italic">riles ; </hi>all the currant kinds having inermous or thornleſs branches, and racemous cluſters of flowers and fruit ; and the gooſeberry have ſpinous branches, and flowers and fruit for the molt part ſingly.</p><p>There are three ſpecies of the currant-tree, two of which, and their varieties, merit culture for their fruit; the other as a plant of variety or obſervation : all of which are inermous or unarmed, having no thorns on the branches.</p><p>I. Rubrum, common red-currant tree, &amp;c. hath a ſhrubby ſtem, dividing low into many branches, forming a buſhy head, five or fix feet high or more, without thorns ; broad trilobate leaves, and ſmooth pendulous cluſters of plane greeniſh flowers, ſucceeded by ſmall cluſters of berries. It grows naturally in woods and the hedges in moſt parts ol Europe, and compriſes all ſorts of red and white currants ; as, common ſmall red currant—large bunched red currant—Champaigne pale-red currant—common ſmall white currant—large white Hutch currant—yellow blotched-leaved currant—ſil-ver ſtriped leaved—gold ſtriped leaved.—gooſeberry-leaved. All theſe ſorts are varieties of one ſpecies, <hi rend="italic">tabes rubrum,</hi>  or common red currant ; it being the parent from which all the others were firſt obtained from the ſeed, and improved by culture. They all flower in the ſpring, and the fruit ripens in June and</p><lb/><p>July ; and by having the trees in different ſituations and modes of training, ſuch as plantations of ſtandards in the open quarters for the general ſupply, others trained againſt walls or pales of different aſpect, the fruit may be continued ripe in good perfection from about the middle of June until November, provided the later crops are defended with mats or nets from the birds.</p><p>2.    The nigrum, or black currant tree, hath a ſhrubby ſtem, dividing low into many branches, forming a buſhy head five or fix feet high ; broad trilobate leaves of a rank odour, and having racemous cluſters of oblong greeniſh flowers, ſucceeded by thin cluſters of black berries. The fruit of this ſpecies being of a ſtrong flavour, and ſomewhat phyſical teliſh, is not generally liked; it, however, is accounted very wholeſome: there is alſo made of it a ſyrup of high eſtimation for fore throats and quinſies ; hence the fruit is often called<hi rend="italic">ſquinancy berries.</hi>  There is a variety called the <hi rend="italic">Pennſylvanian black currant,</hi>  having ſmaller ſhoots and leaves, not ſtrong ſcented, and ſmall fruit but of little value ; ſo the ſhrub is eſteemed only for variety and ſhrubberies. The mode of bearing of all the varieties of currants is both in the old and young wood all along the ſides of the branches and ſhoots, often upon a ſort of ſmall ſprigs and ſnags, producing the fruit in numerous long pendulous cluſters.</p><p>3.    The groſſularia, or common gooſeberry buſh, riſes with a low ſhrubby ſtem, dividing low into a very branchy buſhy head, armed with ſpines ; trilobate ſmalliſh leaves, having hairy ciliated footltalks ; and ſmall green-iſh flowers, ſucceeded by hairy berries.’ It conflits of many varieties, of different ſizes and colours.</p><p>4.    The reclinatum, or reclinated broad-leaved gooſe-berrybuſh, riſes with a low ſhrubby ſtem, and reclinated ſomewhat prickly branches, trilobate broadiſh leaves, and ſmall greeniſh flowers, having the pedunculi fur-niſhed with triphyllous bractea.</p><p>5.    The oxyacanthoides, or oxyacantha-leaved gooſeberry, hath a ſhrubby ſtem, and branches armed on all ſides with ſpines, and largiſh trilobate hawthorn leaves.</p><p>6.    The uva criſpa, or ſmooth gooſeberry, hath a ſhrubby ſtem, and branches armed with ſpines ; trilobate leaves ; pedicles having monophyllous bractea ; and ſmooth fruit.</p><p>7.    Thecynoſhati, or prickly-fruited gooſeberry buſh, hath a ſhrubby ſtem and branches, armed with ſpines, moſtly at the axillas, and prickly fruit in cluſters.</p><p>All the above ſeven ſpecies of ribes, both currants· and gooſeberry kinds, and their reſpective varieties, are very hardy ſhrubs, that proſper almoit anywhere, both in open and ſhady ſituations, and in any common ſoil ; bearing plentifully in any expoſure, though in open funny ſituations they produce the largeſt and faireſt fruit, ripening to a richer vinous flavour ; but it is eligible to plant them in different ſituations and aſpects, in order to have the fruit as early and late as poſſible.</p><p>They are commonly planted in the kitchen-garden,-moſtly as dwarf ſtandards, in the open quarters, for the general ſupply ; being diſpoſed ſometimes in continued plantations in rows, eight or ten feet by ſix aſunder, where great quantities of the fruit are required for market or other large ſupplies ; and are· ſometimes diſpoſed in ſingle ranges round the outward</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>