<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Corvinus governor of Syria, he marched into the province of Aſia, properly ſo called, and there took up his winter·quarters. He ſpent the whole winter in ſettling the affairs of the ſeveral provinces of Aſia Minor and the adjacent iſlands ; and early in the ſpring paſſed into Greece, whence he ſet out for Rome, which he entered in the month Sextilis, afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Augufl, </hi>in three triumphs, which were celebrated ſor three days together.</p><p>And now Octavianus was at the height of his wiſhes, ſole ſovereign, ſole maſter, of the whole Roman empire. But, on the other hand, the many dangers which attend an uſurped powder, appearing to him in a ſtronger light than ever, filled his mind with a thouſand perplexing thoughts. The natural aversion of the Romans to a kingly government, their love of liberty, and the ides of March, when his father Julius was murdered in full ſenate by thoſe very men whom he thought the moſt devoted to his perſon, made him ſear there might ariſe another Brutus, who, to reſtore liberty to his country, might aſſaſſinate him on his very throne. This he knew had happened to Julius Cæſar; whereas Sylla, after having laid down the authority he had uſurped, died peaceably in his bed in the midſt of his enemies. The paſſion of ſear outweighed in his ſoul the charms of a diadem, and inclined him to follow the example of Sylla. He was indeed very unwilling to part with his authority ; but ſear began to get the better of his ambition. However, before he came to any reſolution, he thought it adviſable to conſult his two moſt intimate and truſty friends, Agrippa ând Mæcenas ; the former no leſs famous for his probity than his valour ; and the latter a man of great penetration, and generally eſteemed the moſt reſined politician of his age. Agrippa enlarged on the" many and almoſt inevitable dangers which attend monarchy, inſupportable to a free people, and to men educated in a commonwealth. He did not forget the examples of'Sylla and Cæſar; and cloſed his ſpeech with exhorting Octavianus to convince the world, by reſtoring liberty to his country, that the only motive for his taking up arms was to revenge his father’s death.</p><p>Mæcenas, on the other hand, remonſtrated to him, that he had done too much to go back ; that, after ſo much bloodſhed, there could be no ſafety for him but on the throne ; that, if he diveſted himſelf of the ſovereign power, he would be immediately proſecuted by the children and friends of the many illuſtrious perſons whom the misfortunes of the times had forced him to ſacriſice to his ſafety ; that it was abſolutely neceſſary for the welfare and tranquillity of the republic, that the ſovereign power ſhould be lodged in one perſon, not divided among many, &amp;c. Octavianus thanked them both for their friendly advice, but ſhowed himſelf inclined to follow the opinion of Mæcenas ; whereupon that able miniſter gave him many wiſe inſtructions and rules of government, which are related at length by Dio Caſſius, and will ever be looked upon as a maſterpiece in politics. Among other things he told him, That he could not fail of being ſucceſsful in all his undertakings, happy in his lifetimc, and famous in hiſtory after his death, if he never deviated from this rule ; to wit, To govern ethers as he would wiſh to be governed himſelf, had he been born to obey and not to command. He added,</p><p>That if, in taking upon him the ſovereign power, he dreaded the name of king, a name ſo odious in a commonwealth, he might content himſelf with the title of <hi rend="italic">Caſar</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Imperator,</hi>  and under that name, which was well known to the Romans, enjoy all the authority of a king.</p><p>This advice Octavianus followed, and from that time laid aſide all thoughts of abdicating the ſovereign power; but, to deceive the people into a belief that they ſtill enjoyed their ancient government, he continued the old magiſtrates, with the ſame name, pomp, and ornaments, but with juſt as much power as hc thought fit to leave them. They were to have no military power, but only their old juriſdiction of deciding finally all cauſes, except ſuch as were capital ; and though ſome of theſe laſt were left to the governor of Rome, yet the chief he reſerved for himſelf. He paid great court to the people : the very name that covered his uſurpation was a compliment to them ; for he affected to call it the power of the tribuneſhip, though he acted as abſolutely by it as if he had called it the dictatorial power. He likewiſe won the hearts of the populace by cheapneſs of proviſions and plentiful markets ; he frequently entertained them with ſhows and ſports; and by theſe means-kept them in good-humour, and made them forget uſurpation, ſlavery, and every public evil ; people in eaſe and plenty being under no temptation of inquiring into the title of their prince, or reſenting acts of power which they do not immediately feel.</p><p>As for the ſenate, he filled it with his own creatures, raiſing the number of the conſcript fathers to iooo. He ſupplied ſeveral poor ſenators with money out of the treaſury to diſcharge the public offices, and on all occaſions affected an high regard for that venerable body ; but at the ſame time diveſted them of all power, and reduced them to mere cyphers. To prevent them from raiſing new’ diſturbances in the diſtant provinces, he iſſued an edict, forbidding any ſenator to travel out of Italy without leave, except ſuch as had lands in Sicily, or Narbonne Gaul, which at that time comprehended Languedoc, Provence, and Dauphiny. To theſe provinces, which were near Italy, and in a perfect ſtate of tranquillity, they had full liberty to retire when they pleaſed, and live there upon their eſtates. Before he ended his ſixth conſulſhip, he took a cenſus of the people, which was 41 years after the laſt ; and in this the number of the men fit to bear arms amounted to 463,000, the greateſt that had ever been found before. He likewiſe celebrated the games which had been decreed by the ſenate for his victory at Actium ; and it was ordered, that they ſhould be celebrated every fifth year, four colleges of prieſts being appointed to take care of them ; to wit, the pontifices, the augurs, the ſeptemvirs, and quindecimvirs. The more to gain the affections of the people, he annulled, by one edict, the many ſevere and unjuſt laws which had been enacted during the triumvirate. He raiſed many public buildings, repaired the old ones, and added many ſtately ornaments to the city, which at this time was, if we may give credit to ſome ancient writers, about 50 miles in compaſs, and contained near four millions of fouls, reckoning men, women, children, and ſlaves. He attended buſineſs, reformed abuſes, ſhowed great regard for the Roman name, procured public abundance, pleaſure, and jollity,</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>