<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed ſacrifices to the god, and conſecrated the place of their retreat, they returned to Rome, led by their new magiſtrates and the deputies of the ſenate.</p><p>Thus the Roman conſtitution, which had originally been monarchic, and from thence had paſſed into an ariſtocracy, began now to verge towards a democracy. The tribunes immediately after their election obtained permiſſion from the ſenate to elect two perſons as their miniſters or aſſiſtants, who ſhould eaſe them a little in the great multiplicity of their affairs. Theſe were called <hi rend="italic">plebeian tedilei ;</hi>  and afterw<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ards came to have the in-ſpection of the public baths, aqueducts, with many other offices originally belonging to the conſuls, after which they were called ſimply<hi rend="italic">tdiles.</hi></p><p>All oppoſition to the making of regular levies being now at an end, the conſul Cominius led an army againſt the Volſci. He defeated them in battle, and took from them Longula and Poluſca ; after which he beſieged Corioli, a city ſtrongly fortified, and which might be called their capital. He carried this place, and gained a victory over the Antiates, the ſame day ; but Caius Marcius, an eminent patrician, had all the glory of both actions. The troops detached by the conſul to ſcale the walls of Corioli being repulſed in their firſt aſſault, Marcius rallied the runaways, led them on afreſh to the charge, drove back the enemy within their walls, and, entering the city with them, made himſelf maſter of it. This exploit atchieved, he with all expedition put himſelf iιr the foremoſt ranks of the conſul’s main army, that was juſt going to engage with the Antiates, who were come to the relief of the place ; and there he behaved with equal bravery, and had equal ſucceſs.</p><p>The next day the conſul, having erected his tribunal before his tent, called the ſoldiers together. His whole ſpeech to them was little more than a panegyric upon Marcius. He put a crown upon his head ; aſſigned him a tenth part of all the ſpoil ; and, in the name of the republic, made him a preſent of a fine horſe with ſtately furniture, giving him leave at the ſame time to chooſe out any ten of the priſoners for himſelf ; and laſtly, he allotted him as much money as he could carry away. Of all theſe offers Marcius accepted only the horſe, and one captive of the ten, an old friend of his family, that he might give him his liberty. To add to the glory of the brave warrior, the conſul beſtowed on him the ſurname of <hi rend="italic">Coriolanus,</hi>  transferring thereby from himſelf to Marcius all the honour of the conqueſt of Corioli. Cominius, at his return to Rome, diffland∙ ed his army ; and war was ſucceeded by works of religion, public games, and treaties of peace. A cenſus and a luſtrum cloſed the events of this memorable con-fulſhip. There appeared to be in Rome at this time no more than 110,000 men fit to bear arms; a number by many thouſands leſs than at the laſt enrollment. Donbt-leſs great numbers had run away to avoid being ſlaves</p><p>to their creditors.</p><p>Under the following adminiſtration of T. Geganius and P. Minucius, Rome was terribly afflicted by a famine, occaſioned chiefly by the neglect of ploughing and ſowing during the late troubles ; for the ſedition had happened after the autumnal equinox, about ſow-ing-time, and the accommodation was not made till juſt before the winter ſolſtice. The ſenate diſpatched agents into Hetruria, Campania, the country of the</p><lb/><p>Volſci, and even into Sicily, to buy corn. Thoſe who embarked for Sicily met with a tempeſt which retarded their arrival at Syracuſe ; where they were conſtrained to paſs the winter. At Cumæ, the tyrant Ariſtodemus ſeized the money brought by the commiſſaries ; and they themſelves with difficulty ſaved their lives by flight. The Volſei, far from being diſpoſed to ſuc-cour the Romans, would have marched againſt them, if a ſudden and moſt deſtructive peſtilence had not defeated their purpoſe. In Hetruria alone the Roman commiſſaries met with ſucceſs. They ſent a conſiderable quantity of grain ſrom thence to Rome in barks : but this was in a ſhort time conſumed, and the miſery became exceſſive : the people were reduced to eat any thing they could get ; and nature in ſo great extremity loathed nothing.</p><p>During this diſtreſe a deputation came from Velitræ a Volſcian city, where the Romans had formerly planted a colony, repreſenting that nine parts in ten of its inhabitants had been ſwept away by a plague, and praying the Romans to ſend a new colony to re-people it. The conſcript fathers without much heſitation granted the requeſt, preſſed the departure of the colony, and without delay named three leaders to conduct it.</p><p>The people at firſt were very well pleaſed with the propoſal, as it gave them a proſpect of relief in their hunger : but when they reflected on the terrible havoc the plague had made among the old inhabitants of Velitræ, they began to ſear that the place might be ſtill infected ; and this apprehenſion became ſo univerſal, that not one of them would conſent to go thither. Nevertheleſs the ſenate at length publiſhed a decree that all the citizens ſhould draw lots ; and that thoſe to whoſe lot it ſell to be of the colony ſhould inſtantly march for Velitræ, or ſuffer the ſevereſt puniſhments for their diſobedience : ſear and hunger made the people comply ; and the fathers, a few days after, ſent away a ſecond colony to Norba, a conſiderable city of Latium. But the patricians were diſappointed as to the benefit they expected from theſe meaſures. The plebeians who remained in Rome being more and more preſſed by hunger and want, grew daily more angry with the ſe-nate. At firſſ they aſſembled in ſmall companies to vent their wrath in abuſive complaints ; and at length, in one great body, ruffled all together into the forum, calling out upon their tribunes for ſuccour.</p><p>The tribunes made it their buſineſs to heighten the general diſcontent. Having convened the people, Spu-rius Icilius, chief of the college of tribunes, inveighed moſt bitterly againſt the ſenate ; and when he had end? ed his harangue, exhorted others to ſpeak freely their thoughts ; particularly, and by name, calling upon Brutus and Sicinius, the ringleaders of the former ſedition, and now ædiles. Theſe men, far from attempting to extinguiſh the fire, added freſh fuel to it : And the more to inflame the ſpirits of the multitude, they enumerated all the paſt inſults which the people had ſuffer-ed from the nobles. Brutus concluded his harangue with loudly threatening, that if the plebeians would follow his advice, he would ſoon oblige thoſe men who had cauſed the preſent calamity to find a remedy for it ; after which the aſſembly was diſmiſſed.</p><p>The next day, the conſuls, greatly alarmed at this commotion, and apprehending from the menaces of Brutus ſome very miſehievous event, thought it advi-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>