<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ROE, the ſeed or ſpawn of ſiſh. That of the male fiſhes is uſually diſtinguiſhed by the name of <hi rend="italic">ſoft roe, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">milt ;</hi>  and that of the female, <hi rend="italic">hard roe, or ſpawn. </hi>So inconceivably numerous are theſe ovula or ſmall eggs, that M. Petit found 342,144 of them in a carp of 18 inches ; but M. Lieuwenhoek found in a carp no more than 211,629. This laſt gentleman obſerves, that there are four times this number in a cod ; and that a common one contains 9,344,000 eggs.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roe, in zoology. See Cervus.</hi></p><p>ROELLA, in botany : A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 29th order, <hi rend="italic">Campanace&lt;ε.</hi>  The corolla is funnel-ſhaped, with its bottom ſhut up by ſtaminiferous valvules ; the ſtigma is bifid ; the capſule bilocular, and cylindrical inferior.</p><p>ROGA, in antiquity, a preſent which the emperors made to the ſenators, magiſtrates, and even to the people ; and the popes and patriarchs to their clergy. Theſe rogæ were diſtributed by the emperors on the firſt day of the year, on their birth-day, or on the <hi rend="italic">na-talis dies</hi>  of the cities ; and by the popes and patriarchs in paſſion-week. Roga is alſo uſed for the common pay of the ſoldiers.</p><p>ROGATION (rogatio), in the Roman juriſprudence, a demand made by the conſuls or tribunes of the Roman people, when a law was propoſed to be paſſed. <hi rend="italic">Rogatio</hi>  is alſo uſed for the decree itſelf made in conſequence of the people’s giving their aſſent to this demand ; to diſtinguiſh it from a <hi rend="italic">ſenatus conſultum,</hi>  or decree of the ſenate.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RoGΛ<hi rend="sup">c</hi>τiθN-ld<hi rend="sup">r</hi>eek,</hi>  the week immediately ſucceeding Whitſunday ; ſo called from the three feaſts therein, viz. on Monday, Tueſday, and Wedntſday.</p><p>ROGER de Hoveden, a learned man of the 13th century, was born in Yorkſhire, moſt probably at the town of that name, now called <hi rend="italic">Ho&lt;ιvden,</hi>  ſome time in the reign of Henry I. After he had received the firſt parts of education in his native country, he ſtudied the civil and canon law, which were then become the moſt faſhionable and lucrative branches of learning. He became domeſtic chaplain to Henry II. who employed him to tranfa&lt;ct ſeveral eccleſiaſtical affairs ; in which he acquitted himſelf with honour. But his moſt meritorious work was, his Annals of England, from A. D. 731, when Bede’s Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory ends, to A. D. 1202. This work, which is one of the moſt voluminous of our ancient hiſtories, is more valuable for the ſincerity with which it is written, and the great variety of facts which it contains, than for the beauty of its ſtyle, or the regularity of its arrangement.</p><p>ROGUE, in law, an idle ſturdy beggar ; who by ancient ſtatutes is for the firſt offence called a <hi rend="italic">rogue of the firſt degree,</hi>  and puniſhed by whipping, and boring through the griſtle of the right ear with a hot iron ; and for the ſecond offence, is termed a <hi rend="italic">rogue of the ſecond degree,</hi>  and, if above 18 years of age, ordered to be executed as a felon.</p><p>ROHAN (Peter de), Chevalier de Gié, and mar-ſhal of France, better known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Marſhal de Gié,</hi>  was the ſon of Louis de Rohan, the firſt of the name, lord of Guémené and Montauban, and deſeended of one of the moſt ancient and moſt illuſtrious families of the kingdom. The family of Rohan, be-foι e the Revolution, held the rank of prince in France</p><lb/><p>in conſequence of deriving its origin from the firſt ſovereigns of Brittany, and clearly admitted by the dukes of Brittany themſelves in the ſtates general of that province held in ι 088. The houſe of Rohan had ſtill another advantage, which was common to it with very few families, even the moſt diſtinguiſhed among the princes, namely, that inſtead of having been aggrandi-ſed by the wealth procured from alliances, it had held in itſelf for ſeven centuries the largeſt poſſeſſions of any family in the kingdom.</p><p>One of the moſt diſtinguiſhed branches of this family was Peter, the ſubject of the preſent article. Louis XI. rewarded his bravery with the ſtaff of marſhal of France in 1473. He was one of the four lords who governed the kingdom during the indiſpoſition of that prince at Chinon in 1484. Two years afterwards he oppo- , ſed the attacks of the archduke of Auſtria upon Picardy. He commanded the van-guard at the battle of Fornoue in i495y and ſignalized himſelf much in that engagement. His bravery procured him the countenance and confidence of Louis XII. who appointed him his prime counſellor, and general of the army in Italy ; but theſe advantages he loſt, by incurring the diſpleaſure of Anne of Brittany the queen.</p><p>The marſhal had flopped ſome of her equipage on the road to Nantz ; for which that vindictive princeſs prevailed on her huſhand to enter into a proceſs againſt him before the parliament of Toulouſe, at that time the moſt rigorous and ſevere in the kingdom. He was on the 15tl1 of February 1506 found guilty, baniſhed ſrom the court, and deprived of the privileges and emoluments of his office for five years. The expence of this proſecution amounted to more than 31,000 livres, and it did no honour either to the king or the queen. If indeed it be true, that the queen was never ſo much delighted as with the humiliation of her enemies, ſhe had good reaſon to be ſatisfied here. John of Authon, who hath entered into a pretty full detail of this affair, reports that Gié, being removed to the <hi rend="italic">Chateau de Dreux,</hi>  became an object of ridicule to the witneſſes who had ſworn againſt him. He wore a long white beard, and, quite full of the thoughts of his diſgrace, took it on one occaſion in his hands and covered his face with it. An ape, belonging to Alain d’Albret, count of Dreux, jumped from a bed where his maſter was re-poſing himſelf, and attacked the beard of Gié, who, with ſome difficulty, extricated himſelf. This ſeene not only occaſioned much laughter to the whole company who were preſent, but likewiſe became inſtantly the ſubject of the farces and mummeries which were then acting in France. Even the ſchool-boys made a repreſentation of it, where, alluding to the name of the queen, they ſaid, that there was a marſhal who wiſhed to ſhoe an aſs <hi rend="italic">fun aηe},</hi>  but that he received ſuch a blow with the foot, as threw him over the wall into the garden. Mateſehal de Gié died at Paris, the 22d A-pril ί ς 1 3, perfectly diſguſted with courts and grandeur.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rohan (Henry duke of), peer of France, and prince of Leon, was born at the Chateau de Blein in Brittany in 1579. Henry IV. under whoſe eyes he gave diſtinguiſhed prooſs of his bravery at the ſiege of A-miens, when only 16 years of age, loved him with as much affection as if he had been his own ſon. After the death of Henry, he became chief of the Calviniſts</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>