<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>So ſharp-fighted is pride in biemiſhes, and ſo willing to be gratified, that it takes up with the very flighteſt improprieties: filch as a blunder by a foreigner in ſpeaking our language, eſpecially if the blunder can bear a ſenſe that reflects on the ſpeaker:</p><p><hi rend="italic">Quickly.</hi>  The young man is an honeſt man.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Caius.</hi>  What ſhall de honeſt man do in my cloſet ? dere is no honeſt man dat ſhall come in my cloſet</p><p><hi rend="italic">Merry Wives of Windfor.</hi></p><p>Love ſpeeches are finely ridiculed in the following ρa∩'age,</p><p>Quoth he, My faith as adamantine,</p><p>As chains of deſtiny, I’ll maintain ;</p><p>True as Apollo ever ſpoke,</p><p>Or oracle from heart of oak ;</p><p>And if you’ll give my flame but vent,</p><p>Now in cloſe hugger-mugger pent,</p><p>And ſhine upon me but benignly,</p><p>With that one and that other pigſney,</p><p>The ſun and day ſhall ſooner part Than love, or you, ſhake off my heart ;</p><p>The fun, that ſhall no more diſpenſe His own, but your bright influence :</p><p>I’ll carve your name on barks of trees,</p><p>With true love-knots and flouriſhes ;</p><p>That ſhall infuſe eternal ſpring,</p><p>And everlaſting flouriſhing :</p><p>Drink every letter on’t in ſtum,</p><p>And make it briſh champaign become.</p><p>Where’er you tread, your foot ſhall ſet The primroſe and the violet ;</p><p>AH ſpices, perfumes, and ſweet powders,</p><p>Shall borrow from your breath their odours ; Nature her charter ſhall renew And take all lives of things from you j The world depend upon your eye,</p><p>And, when you frown upon it, die.</p><p>Only our loves ſhall ſtill ſurvive,</p><p>New-worlds and natures to out-live ;</p><p>And, like to herald’s moons, remain All creſcents, without change or wane.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Hudιbras, part</hi>  2. <hi rend="italic">canto</hi>  I.</p><p>Thoſe who have a talent for ridicule, which is ſeldom united with a taſte for delicate and refined beauties, are quick-ſighted in improprieties ; and theſe they eagerly graſp, in order to gratiſy their favourite propen-ſity. Perfons galled are provoked to maintain that ridicule is improper for grave ſubjects. Subjects really grave are by no means fit for ridicule ; but then it is urged againſt them, that, when called in queſtion whether a certain ſubject be really grave, ridicule is the only means of determining the controverſy. Hence a celebrated queſtion, Whether ridicule be or be not a teſt of truth ?</p><p>On one ſide, it is obſerved, that the objects of ridicule are falſehood, incongruity, impropriety, or turpitude of certain kinds : but as the object of every excited paſſion muſt be examined by reaſon, before we can determine whether it be proper or improper ; ſo ridicule muſt, apparently at leaſt, eſtabliſh the truth of the improprieties deſigned to excite the paſſion of contempt. Hence it comes in to the aid of argument and reaſon, when its impreſſions on the imagination are conſiſtent with the nature of things; but when it ſtrikes the fancy</p><p>and affections with fictitious images, it becomes the in-ſtrument of deceit. But however ridicule may impreſs the idea of apparent turpitude or falſehood in the imagination, yet ſtill reaſon remains the ſupreme judge ; and thus ridicule can never be the final teſt or touch-ſtone of truth and falſehood.</p><p>On the other ſide, it is contended that ridicule is not a ſubject of reaſoning, but of ſenſe or taſte ; (ſee and compare the articles Risible and Congrui-ty. Stating the queſtion, then, in more accurate terms, Whether the ſenſe of ridicule be the proper teſt for diſtinguiſhing ridiculous objects from what are not ſo ? they proceed thus : No perſon doubts that our fenſe of beauty is the true teſt of what is beautiful; and our ſenſe of grandeur, of what is great or ſublime. Is it more doubtful whether our ſenſe of ridicule be the true teſt of what is ridiculous ? It is not only the true teſt, but indeed the only teſt ; for this ſubject comes not, more than beauty or grandeur, under the province of reaſon. If any ſubject, by the influence of faſhion or cuſtom, have acquired a degree of vene* ration to which naturally it is not entitled, what are the proper means for wiping off the artificial colouring, and diſplaying the ſubject in its true light ? A man of true taſte fees the ſubject without diſguiſe ; but if he heſitate, let him apply the teſt of ridicule, which ſeparates it from its artificial connections, and expoſes it naked with all its native improprieties.—But it is urged, that the graveſt and moſt ſerious matters may be ſet in a ridiculous light. Hardly ſo; for where an object is neither rifible nor improper, it lies not open in any quarter to an attack from ridicule.</p><p>RIDING, in general, ſignifies the being carried along on any vehicle.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Riding on horſeback. See Horsemanship.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Riding, in medicine. During this exerciſe all the viſcera are ſhaken, and preſſed againſt each other ; at the ſame time the pure air acts with a greater force on the lungs. Weakly perſons, or thoſe whoſe ſtomachs are infirm, ſhould, however, be cautious of riding before their meals are ſomewhat digeſted.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Riding, in naval affairs, is the ſtate of a ſhip’s being retained in a particular ſtation, by means of one or more cables with their anchors, which are for this purpoſe ſunk into the bottom of the ſea, &amp;c. in order to prevent the veſſel from being driven at the mercy of the wind or current.—A rope is ſaid to </hi><hi rend="italic">ride,</hi>  when one of the turns by which it is wound about the capſtern or windlaſs lies over another, ſo as to interrupt the operation of heaving.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Riding Athwart,</hi></hi>  the pofition of a ſhip which lies acroſs the direction of the wind and tide, when the former is ſo ſtrong as to prevent her from falling into the current of the latter.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Riding between the Wind and Tide,</hi></hi>  the ſituation of a veſſel at anchor, when the wind and tide act upon her in direct oppoſition, in ſuch a manner as to deſtroy the effort of each other upon her hull ; ſo that ſhe is in a manner balanced between their reciprocal force, and rides without the leaſt ſtrain on her cables. When a ſhip does not labour heavily, or feel a great ſtrain when anchored in an open road or bay, ſhe is ſaid to ride eaſy. Gn the contrary, when ſhe pitches violently into the ſea, ſo as to ſtrain her cables, malls, or hull, it is called <hi rend="italic">riding hard,</hi>  and the veſſel is termed a <hi rend="italic">bad</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>