<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>paſſed with wood; and through the wood are walks, which open beyond it upon thoſe romantic ſcenes which ſurround the park, and which are the glory of Pers-ſield. The Wye runs immediately below the wood: the river is of a dirty colour; but the ſhape of its courſe is very various, winding firſt in the form of a horſe-ſhoe, then proceeding in a large ſweep to the town of Chepſtowe, and afterwards to the Severn. The banks are high hills; in different places ſteep, bulging out, or hollow on the ſides; rounded, flattened, or irregular at top; and covered with wood, or broken by rocks. They are ſometimes ſeen in front; ſome-times in perſpective; falling back for the paſſage, or cloſing behind the bend of the river; appearing to meet, riſing above, or ſhooting out beyond one another. The wood which incloſes the lawn crowns an extenſive range of theſe hills, which overlook all thoſe on the oppoſite ſhore, with the country which appears above or between them; and winding themſelves as the river winds, their ſides, all rich and beautiful, are alternately exhibited; and the point of view in one ſpot becomes an object to the next.</p><p>In many places the principal feature is a continued rock, in length a quarter of a mile, perpendicular, high, and placed upon a height. To reſemble mins is common to rocks : but no ruin of any lingle ſtructilre was ever equal to this enormous pile ; it ſeems to be the remains of a city ; and other ſmaller heaps ſcattered about it appear to be fainter traces of the former extent, and ſtrengthen the ſimilitude. It ſtretches along the brow which terminates the foreſt of Dean ; the face of it is compoſed of immenſe blocks of ſtone, but not rugged; the top is bare and uneven, but not craggy; and from the foot of it, a declivity, covered with thicket, ſlopes gently towards the Wye, but in one part is abruptly broken off by a ledge of rocks, of a different hue, and in a different direction. From the grotto it ſeems to riſe immediately over a thick wood, which extends down a hill below the point of view, acroſs the valley through which the Wye flows, and up the oppoſite banks, hides the river, and continues without interruption to the bottom of the rock-: from another ſeat it is ſeen by itſelf without even its baſe ; it faces another, with all its appendages about it ; and ſometimes the fight of it is partially intercepted by trees, beyond which, at a diſtance, its long line continues on through all the openings between them.</p><p>Another capital object is the caſtle of Chepſtowe, a noble ruin of great extent; advanced to the very edge of a perpendicular rock, and ſo immediately rivetted into it, that from the top of the battlements down to the river ſeems but one precipice : the fame ivy which overſpreads the face of the one, twines and cluſters amongſthe fragments of the other ; many towers, much of the walls, and large remains of the chapel, are (landing. Cloſe to it is a moſt romantic wooden bridge, very 7ιncient, very groteſque, at an extraordinary height above the river, and ſeeming to abut againſt the ruins at one end, and ſome rocky hills at the other. The caſtle is ſo near to the alcove at Persfield, that little circumſtances in it may be diſcerned ; from other ſpots more diſtant, even from the lawn, and from a ſhrubbery on the ſide of the lawn, it is diſtinctly viſible,'and always beautiful, whether it is ſeen alone, or with the bridge, with the town, with more or with leſs of</p><p>the rich meadows which lie along the banks of the Wye, to its junction three miles off with the Severn. A long ſweep of that river alſo, its red cliffs, and the fine riſing country in the counties of Somerſet and Glou∙ ceſter, generally terminate the proſpect.</p><p>Moſt of the hills about Persfield are full of rocks ; ſome are intermixed with hanging woods, aηd either advance a little before them, or retire· within them, and are backed, or overhung, or ſeparated by trees. In the walk to the cave, a long ſucceſſion of them is frequently ſeen in perſpective, all of a dark colour, and with wood in the intervals between them. In other parts the rocks are more wild and uncouth ; and ſometimes they Hand on the tops of the higheſt hills ; at other times down as low as the river ; they are home-objects in one ſpot, and appear only in the back-ground of another.    »</p><p>The woods concur with the rocks to render the ſcenes of Persfield romantic : the place everywhere abounds with them ; they covey the tops of the hills $ they hang on the ſteeps ; or they fill the depths of the valleys. In one place they front, in another they riſe above, in another they fink below the point of view∣ they are ſeen ſometimes retiring beyond each other, and darkening as they recede ; and ſometimes an opening between two is cloſed by a third at a diſtance beyond them. A point, called the <hi rend="italic">Lover's Leap,</hi>  commands a continued ſurface of the thickeſt foliage, which overſpreads a vaſt hollow immediately underneath. Below the Chineſe ſeat the courſe of the Wye is in the ſhape of a horfe-ſhoe : it is on one ſide incloſed by a ſemicircular hanging wood ; the direct ſteeps of a table-hill ſhut it in on the other ; and the great rock fills the interval between them : in the midſt of this rude ſcene lies the pe-ninſula formed by the river, a mile at the leaſt in length, and in the higheſt ſtate of cultivation : hear the iithmus the ground riſes conſiderably, and thence deſcends in a broken ſurface, till it flattens to the water’s edge at the other extremity. The whole is divided into cornfields and paſtures ; they are ſeparated by hedge-rows, coppices, and thickets ; open clumps and ſingle trees ſtand out in the meadows ; and houſes and other buildings, which belong to the farms, are ſcattered amongſt them : nature ſo cultivated, ſurrounded by nature ſo wild, compoſe a moſt lovely Iandſcape together.</p><p>The communications between theſe ſeveral points are generally by cloſe walks ; but the covert ends near the Chineſe ſeat ; and a path is afterwards conducted through the upper park to a ruſtic temple, which overlooks on one ſide ſome of the romantic views which have been deſcribed, and on the other the cultivated hills and valleys of Monmouthihire. To the rude and magnificent ſcenes of nature now ſucceeds a pleaſant, fertile, and beautiful country, divided into incloſures, not covered with woods, nor broken by rocks and precipices, but only varied by eaſy ſwells and gentle declivities. Yet the proſpect is not tame: the hills in it are high ; and it is bounded by a vaſt ſweep of the Severn, which is here viſible for many miles together, and receives in its courſe the Wye and the Avon.</p><p>From the temple a road leads to the Windcliff, an eminence much above the reſt, and commanding the whole in one view. The Wye runs at the foot of the hill ; the peninſula lies juſt below ; the deep boſom of</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>