<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>obeying, began to ſhow his diſpleaſure at being hi-' therto ſo ſubmiſſive. Nothing now therefore remained for the ſenate but to declare him an enemy to the ſtate, and to ſend Octavianus, with the army he had raiſed, to curb his inſolence. The latter was very ready to offer his army for this expedition, in order to revenge his own private injuries, before he undertook thoſe of the public. The two conſuls, Hirtius and Panſa, joined all their forces ; and thus combined, they marched at the head of a numerous army, againſt Antony, into</p><p>Ciſalpine Gaul. After one or two ineffectual conflicts, both armies came to a general engagement ; in which Antony was defeated, and compelled to fly to Lepidus, who commanded a body of forces in Further Gaul. This victory', however, which promiſed the ſenate ſo much ſucceſs, produced effects very different from their expectations. The two conſuls were mortally wounded ; but Panſa, previous to his death, called Octavianus to his bed-ſide, and adviſed him to join with Antony, telling him, that the ſenate only deſired to de-preſs both, by oppoſing them to each other. The advice of the dying conſul ſunk deep on his ſpirits ; ſo that from that time he only ſought a pretext to break with them. Their giving the command of a party of his army to Decimus Brutus, and their denying him a triumph ſoon after, ſerved to alienate his mind entirely from the ſenate, and made him reſolve to join Antony and Lepidus. He was willing, however, to try the ſenate thoroughly, before he came to an open rupture ; wherefore he ſent to demand the conſulſhip, which was refuſed him. He then thought himſelf obliged to keep no meaſures with that aſſembly, but privately ſent to ſound the inclinations of Antony and Lepidus, concerning a junction of forces, and found them as eager to aſſiſt as the ſenate was to oppoſe him. Antony was, in fact, the general of both armies, and Lepidus was only nominally ſo, his ſoldiers refuſing to obey him upon the approach of the former. Wherefore, upon being aſſured of the aſſiſtance of Octavianus upon their arrival in Italy, they ſoon croſſed the Alps with an army of 17 legions, breathing revenge againſt all wh∂<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  had oppoſed their deſigns.</p><p>The ſenate now began, too late, to perceive their error in diſobliging Octavianus ; and therefore gave him the conſulſhip which they had ſo lately refuſed, and, to prevent his joining with Antony, flattered him with new honours, giving him a power ſuperior to all law. The firſt uſe Octavianus made of his new authority was to procure a law ſor the condemnation of Brutus and Caſſius ; after which, he joined his forces with thoſe of Antony and Lepidus.</p><p>The meeting of theſe three uſurpers of their country’s freedom was near Mutina, upon a little iſland of the river Panarus. Their mutual ſuſpicions were the cauſe of their meeting in this place. Lepidus firſt entered, and, finding all things ſafe, made the ſignal for the other two to approach. Octavianus began the conference, by thanking Antony for his zeal in putting Decimus Brutus to death ; who, being abandoned by his army, was. taken as he was deſigning to eſcape into Macedonia, and beheaded by Antony’s command. Their conference laſted for three days ; and the reſult of it was, that the ſupreme authority ſhould be lodged in their hands, under the title of the <hi rend="italic">triumvirate,</hi>  for the ſpace of five years; that Antony ſhould have</p><p>Gaul ; Lepidus, Spain ; and Octavianus, Africa, and the Mediterranean iſlands. As for Italy, and the eaſtern provinces, they were to remain in common, until their general enemy was entirely ſubdued. But the laſt article of their union was a dreadful one. It was agreed that all their enemies ſhould be deſtroyed ; of which each preſented a liſt. In theſe were compriſed not only the enemies, but the friends of the triumvi-</p><p>-rate, ſince the partiſans of the one were often found among the oppoſers of the others. Thus Lepidus gave up his brother Paulus to the vengeance of his colleague ; Antony permitted the proſcription of his uncle Lucius ; and Octavianus delivered up the great Cicero.</p><p>The moſt ſacred rights of nature were violated ; 30« ſenators, and above 2000 knights, were included ia this terrible proſcription ; their fortunes were confiſ-cated, and their murderers enriched with the ſpoil. Rome ſoon felt the effects of this infernal union, and the horrid cruelties of Marius and Sylla were renewed.</p><p>As many as could eſcape the cruelty of the triumvirs, fled thither into Macedonia to Brutus, or found refuge with young Pompey, who was now in Sicily, and co» vered the Mediterranean with his numerous navy. Their cruelties were not aimed at the men alone ; but the ſofter ſex were in danger of being marked as objects either of avarice or reſentment. They made out ” a liſt of 1400 women of the beſt quality, and the richeſt in the city, who were ordered to give in an account of their fortunes, to be taxed in proportion. But this ſeemed ſo unpopular a meaſure, and was ſo firmly oppoſed by Hortenfia, who ſpoke againſt it, that, inſtead of 1400 women, they were content to tax only 400. However, they made up the deficiency, by extending the tax upon men ; near 100,000, as well citizens as ſtrangers, were compelled to furniſh ſupplies to the ſubverſion of their country’s freedom. At laſt, both the avarice and vengeance of the triumviri ſeemed fully ſatisfied, and they went into the ſenate to declare that the proſcription was at an end ; and thus having deluged th,e city with blood, Octavianus and Antony, leaving Lepidus to defend Rome in their abſence, marched with their army to oppoſe the conſpirators, who were now at the head of a formidable army in Aſia.</p><p>Brutus and Caſſius, the principal of theſe, upon the death of Cæſar, being compelled to quit Rome, went into Greece, where they perſuaded the Roman ſtudents at Athens to declare in the cauſe of freedom ; then parting, the former raiſed a powerful army in Macedonia and the adjacent countries, while the latter went into Syria, where he ſoon became maſter of 12 legions, and reduced his opponent Dolabella to ſuch ſtraits as to kill himſelf. Both armies ſoon after joining at Smyrna, the fight of ſuch a formidable force began to -revive the declining ſpirits of the party, and to re-unite the two generals ſtill more cloſely, between whom there had been ſome time before a flight miſunder. ſtanding. In ſhort, having quitted Italy like diſtreſs-ed exiles, without having one ſingle ſoldier or one town that owned their command, they now found themſelves at the head of a flouriſhing army, furniſhed -with all the neceſſaries for carrying on the war, and in a condition to ſuppprt a conteſt where the empire of the world depended on the event. This ſucceſs in raiſing levies was entirely owing to the juſtice, mœ</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>