<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that is, as the breadth and the ſquare of the depth directly and the length inverſely.</p><p>Now, to conſider firſt the ſtrain ariſing from the weight of the beam itſelf, it is evident that this weight increaſes in the ſame proportion with the depth, the breadth, and the length of the beam. Therefore its power of reſiſting this ſtrain muſt be as its depth directly, and the ſquare of its length inverſely. To conſider this in a more popular manner, it is plain that the increaſe of breadth makes no change in the power of reſiſting the actual ſtrain, becauſe the load and the abſolute ſtrength increaſe in the ſame proportion with the breadth. But by increaſing the depth, we increaſe the reſiſting ſection in the ſame proportion, and therefore the number of reſiſting fibres and the abfolute ſtrength: but we alſo increaſe the weight in the ſame proportion. This makes a compenſation, and the relative ſtrength is yet the ſame. But by increaſing the depth, we have not only increaſed the abſolute ſtrength, but alſo its mechanical energy : For the reſiſtance to fracture is the ſame as if the full ſtrength of each fibre was exerted at the point which we called the centre of effort ; and we ſhowed, that the diſtance of this from the underſide of the beam was a certain portion (a half, a third, a fourth, &amp;c.) of the whole depth of the beam. This diſtance is the arm of the lever by which the coheſion of the wood may be ſuppoſed to act. Therefore this arm of the lever, and conſequently the energy of the reſiſtance, increaſes in the proportion of the depth of the beam, and this remains uncompenſated by any increaſe of the ſtrain. On the whole, therefore, the power of the beam to ſuſtain its own weight increaſes in the proportion of its depth. But, on the other hand, the power of withſtanding a given ſtrain applied at its extremity, or to any aliquot part of its length, is diminiſhed as the length increaſes, or is inverſely as the length ; and the ſtrain ariſing from the weight of the beam alſo increaſes as the length. Therefore the power of reſiſting the ſtrain actually exerted on it by the weight of the beam is inverſely as the ſquare of the length. On the whole,'therefore, the power of a beam to carry its own weight, varies in the proportion of its depth directly and the ſquare of its length inverſely.</p><p>As this ſtrain is frequently a conſiderable part of the whole, it is proper to conſider it apart, and then to reckon only on what remains for the ſupport of any extraneous load.</p><p>In the next place, the power of a beam to carry any load which is uniformly diſſuſed over its length, muſt be inverſely as the ſquare of the length : for the power of withſtanding <hi rend="italic">any</hi>  ſtrain applied to an aliquot part of the length (which is the caſe here, becauſe the load may be conceived as accumulated at it3 centre of gravity, the middle point of the beam) is inverſely as the length ; and the <hi rend="italic">aitual</hi>  ſtrain is as the length, and therefore its momentum is as the ſquare of the length. Therefore the power of a beam to carry a weight uniformly diffuſed over it, is inverſely as the ſquare of the length. <hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi>  It is here underſtood, that the uniform load is of ſome determined quantity for every foot of the length, ſo that a beam of double length carries a double load.</p><p>We have hitherto ſuppoſed that the forces which tend to break a beam tranſverſely, are acting in a direction perpendicular to the beam. This is always the caſe in level floors loaded in any manner ; but in roofs, thte action of the load tending to break the rafters is oblique, becauſe gravity always acts in vertical lines. It may alſo frequently happen, that a beam is ſtrained by a force acting obliquely. This modification of the ſtrain is eaſily diſcuſſed. Suppoſe that the external force, which is meaſured by the weight W in fig. ι. acts in the direction A <hi rend="italic">w'</hi>  inſtead of AW. Draw C <hi rend="italic">a </hi>perpendicular to A w. Then the momentum of this external force is not to be meaſured by W × AC, but by W × <hi rend="italic">ά</hi>  C. The ſtrain therefore by which the fibres in the ſection of fracture DC are torn aſunder, is diminiſhed hr the proportion of CA to C 0, that is, in the proportion of radius to the fine of the angle CA&lt;i, which the beam makes with the direction of the external force.</p><p>To apply this to our purpoſe in the moſt familiar manner, let AB (fig. 3.) be an oblique rafter of a building, loaded with a weight W ſuſpended to any point C, and thereby occaſioning a ſtrain in ſome part D. We have already ſeen, that the immediate cauſe of the ſtrain on D is the reaction of the ſupport which is given to the point B. The rafter may at preſent be conſidered as a lever, ſupported at <hi rend="italic">A</hi>, and pulled down by the line CW. This occaſions a preſſure on B, and the ſupport acts in the oppoſite direction to the action of the lever, that is, in the direction B <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  perpendicular to BA. This tends to break the beam in every part. The preſſure exerted at B is , AE being a horizontal line. Therefore the ſtrain at D will be W×AE _ <hi rend="sub">ττ</hi></p><p>AB × BD. Had the beam been lying horizontally, the ſtrain at D, from the weight W ſuſpended at W, </p><p>C, would have been —× BD. It is therefore di miniſhed in the proportion of AC to AE, that is, in the proportion of radius to the coſine of the elevation, or in the proportion of the ſecant of elevation to the radius.</p><p>It is evident, that this law of diminution of the ſtrain is the ſame whether the ſtrain ariſes from a load on any part of the rafter, or from the weight of the rafter itſelf, or from any load uniformly diſſuſed over its length, provided only that theſe loads act in vertical lines.</p><p>We can now compare the ſtrength of roofs which have different elevations. Suppoſing the width of the building to be given, and that the weight of a ſquare yard of covering is alſo given. Then, becauſe the load on the rafter will increaſe in the ſame proportion with its length, the load on the flant∙fide BA of the roof will be to the load of a ſimilar covering on the half AF of the flat roof, of the ſame width, as AB to AF. But the tranſverſe action of any load on AB, by which it tends to break it, is to that of the ſame load on AF as AF to AB. The tranſverſe ſtrain therefore is the ſame on both, the increaſe of real load on AB being compenſated by the obliquity of its action. But the ſtrengths of beams to reſiſt equal ſtrains, applied to ſimilar points, or uniformly diffuſed over them, are inverſely as their lengths, becauſe the momentum or energy of the ſtrain is proportional to the length. There-</p></body></text></TEI>