<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rmers, whom Nero had taken from the oar and enliſted among the legions, went to meet Galba, three miles from the city, and with loud importunities demanded a confirmation of what his predeceſſor had done in their favour. Galba, who was rigidly attached to the ancient diſcipline, deferred their requeſt to another time. But they, conſidering this delay as equivalent to an abſolute denial, infilled in a very difreſpectful manner ; and ſome of them even had recourſe to arms : whereupon Galba ordered a body of horſe attending him to ride in among them, and thus killed 7000 of them ; but not content with this puniſhment, he afterwards ordered them to be decimated. Their inſolence demanded correction ; but ſuch extenſive puniſhments deviated into cruelty. His next ſtep to curb the inſolence of the ſoldiers, was his diſeharging the German cohort, which had been eſtabliſhed by the former emperors as a guard to their perſons. Thoſe he ſent home to their own country unrewarded, pretending they were diſaffected to his perſon. He ſeemed to have two other objects alſo in view ; namely, to puniſh thoſe vices which had come to an enormous height in the laſt reign, with the ſtricteſt ſeverity ; and to repleniſh the exchequer, which had been quite drained by the prodigality of his predeceſſors. But theſe attempts only brought on him the imputation of ſeverity and avarice ; for the ſtate was too much corrupted to admit of ſuch an immediate tranſition from vice to virtue. The people had long been maintained in ſloth and luxury by the prodigality of the former emperors, and could not think of being obliged to ſeek for new means of ſubfiftence, and to retrench their ſu-perfluities. They began, therefore, to ſatirize the old man, and turn the ſimplicity of his manners into ridicule. Among the marks of avarice recorded of him, he is ſaid to have groaned upon having an expenſive ſoup ſerved up to his table ; he is ſaid to have preſented to his ſteward, for his fidelity, a plate of beans ; a famous player upon the flute, named <hi rend="italic">Canus,</hi>  having greatly delighted him, it is reported, that he drew out his purſe, and gave him five-pence, telling him, that it was private and not public money. By ſuch ill-judged frugalities, at ſuch a time, Galba began to loſe his popularity ; and he, who before his acceſſion was eſteemed by all, being become emperor, √was conſidered with ridicule and contempt. But there*are ſome circumſtances alleged againſt him, leſs equivocal than thoſe trifling ones, already mentioned. Shortly after his coming to Rome, the people were preſented with a moſt grateful ſpectacle, which was that of Locuſta, Eli us, Policletus, Petro-nius, and Petinus, all the bloody miniſters of Nero’s cruelty, drawn in fetters through the city, and publicly executed. But Tigellinus, who had been more active than all the reſt, was not there. The crafty villain had taken care for his own ſafety, by the largeneſs of his bribes ; and though the people cried out for vengeance againſt him at the theatre and at the circus, yet the emperor granted him his life and pardon. Helotus the eunuch, alſo, who had been the inſtrument of poiſoning Claudius, eſcaped, and owed his ſafety to the proper application of his wealth. Thus, by the inequality of his conduct, he became deſpicable to his ſubjects. At one time ſhe wing himſelf ſevere, and frugal, at another remiſs and prodigal ; condemning ſorne illuſtrious perſons without any hearing, and pardoning others though guilty in ſhort, nothing was done but</p><p>by the mediation of his favourites ; all offices were venal, and all puniſhments redeemable by money.</p><p>Affairs were in this unſettled poſture at Rome, when the provinces were yet in a· worſe condition. The ſucceſs of the army in Spain in chooſing an emperor induced the legions in the other parts to wiſh for a ſimi-lar opportunity. Accordingly, many ſeditions were kindled, and ſeveral factions promoted in different parts of the empire, but particularly in Germany. There were then in that province two Roman armies ; the one which had lately attempted to make Rufus Virginius emperor, as has been already mentioned, and which was commanded by his lieutenant ; the other commanded by Vitellius, who long had an ambition to obtain the empire for himſelf. The former of theſe armies deſpiſing their preſent general, and conſidering themſelves as ſuſpected by the emperor for having been the laſt to acknowledge his title, reſolved now to be foremoſt in denying it. Accordingly, when they were ſummoned to take the oaths of homage and fidelity, they refuſed to acknowledge any other commands but thoſe of the ſenate. This- refuſal they backed by a meſſage of the prætorian bands, importing, that they were reſolved not to acquieſce in the election of an emperor created in Spain, and deſiring that the ſenate ſhould proceed to a new choice.</p><p>Galba being informed of this commotion, was ſenſible, that, beſides his age, he was leſs reſpected for want of an heir. He reſolved therefore to put what he had formerly deſigned in execution, and to adopt-ſome perſon whoſe virtues might deſerve ſuch advancement, and protect his declining age from danger. His favourites underſtanding his determination, inſtantly reſolved to give him an heir of their own chooſing ; ſo that there aroſe a great contention among them upon this occaſion. Otho made warm application for himſelf ; alleging the great ſervices he had done the emperor, as being the firſt man of note who came to his aſſiſtance when he had declared againſt Nero, However, Galba, being fully reſolved to conſult the public good alone, rejected his fuit ; and on a day appointed ordered Piſo Lucinianus to attend him. The character given by hiſtorians of Piſo is, that he was every way worthy of the honour deſigned him. He was noway related to Galba ; and had no other intereſt but merit to recommend him to his favour. Taking this youth therefore by the hand, in the preſence of his friends, he adopted him to ſucceed in the empire* giving him the moſt wholeſome leffons for guiding his future conduct. Pifo’s conduct ſhowed that he was highly deſerving this diſtinction : in all his deportment there appeared ſuch modeſty, firmneſs, and equality of mind, as beſpoke him rather capable of diſeharging, than ambitious of obtaining, his preſent dignity. But the army and the ſenate did not ſeem equally difιnte-reſted upon this occaſion ; they had been ſo long uſed to bribery and corruption, that they could now bear no emperor who was not in a capacity of ſatisfying their avarice. The adoption, therefore of Piſo was but coldly received ; for his virtues were no recommendation in a nation of univerſal depravity.</p><p>Otho now finding his hopes of adoption wholly fruſtrated, and ſtill further ſtimulated by the immenſe load of debt which he had contracted by his riotous way of living, reſolved upon obtaining the empire by force,</p></body></text></TEI>