<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>remark alſo formerly made on this caſe, that the ſquares of the diſcharges are nearly as the cubes of the height., or J yoo<hi rend="sup">2</hi> ; 4500T=6<hi rend="sup">j</hi> : 12,48<hi rend="sup">3</hi>.</p><p>And in making theſe firſt gueſſes we ſhall do it more exactly, by recollecting that a certain variation of the mean depth J requires a greater variation of the height, and the increment will be to the height nearly as half the height to the width, as may eaſily be ſeen. There-</p><p>0- 2 A</p><p>fore,if we add to 12<hi rend="sub">j</hi>4δ its th part, or its 24th part,</p><p>viz. 0,52, we have 13 for our firſt aſſumption, exceeding the truth only an inch and a half. We mention theſe circumſtances, that thoſe who are diſpoſed to apply theſe doctrines to the ſolution of practical caſes may be at no loſs when one occurs of which the regular ſolution requires an intricate analyſis.</p><p>It is evident that the inverſe of the foregoing problems will ſhow the effects of enlarging the ſection of a river, that is, will ſhow how much its ſurface will be ſunk by any propoſed enlargement of its bed. It is therefore needleſs to propoſe ſuch problems in this place. Common ſenſe directs us to make theſe enlargements in thoſe parts of the river where their effect will be greateſt, that is, where it is ſhalloweſt when its breadth greatly exceeds its depth, or where it is narrowcſt (if its depth exceed the breadth, which is a very rare caſe), or in general, where the ſlope is the lmallcſt for a ſhort run.</p><p>The ſame general principles direct us in the method of embankments, for the prevention of floods, by enabling us to aſeertain the heights neceſſary to be given to our banks, This will evidently depend, not only on the additional quantity of water which experience tells us a river br ings down during its freſhes, but alſo on thediſtance at which we place the banks from the natural banks of the river. This is a point where miſtaken economy frequently defeats its own purpoſe. If we raiſe our embankment at ſome diſtance ſrom the natural banks of the river, not only will a ſmaller height ſuf-ſice, and conſequently a ſmaller baſe, which will make 3 ſaving in the duplicate proportion of the height ; but our works will be ſo much the more durable nearly, if not exactly, in- the ſame proportion. For by thus enlarging the additional bed which we give to the ſwol-len river, we diminiſh its velocity almoſt in the ſame proportion that we enlarge its channel, and thus diminiſh its power of ruining our works. Except, therefore, in the caſe of a river whoſe freſhes are loaded with fine fand to, deſtroy the turf, it is always proper to place the embankment at a conſiderable diſtance from the natural banks. Placing them at half the breadth of the ſtream from its natural banks, will nearly double its channel ; and, except in the caſe now mentioned, the ſpace thus detached from our fields will afford excellent paſture.</p><p>The limits of ſuch a work as ours will not permit us to enter into any detail on the methpd of embankment. It would require a volume to give inſtructions as to the manner of founding, raiſing, and ſecuring the dykes which muſt be raiſed, and a thoufand circumſtances which muſt be attended to. But a few general obſervations may be made, which naturally occur while we are conſidering the manner in which a river works in fettling or altering its channel.</p><p>It muſt be remarked, in the firſt place, &lt;hat the river will riſe higher when embanked than it does while it was allowed to ſpread ; and it is by no means eaſy to conclude to what height it will riſe from the greateſt height to which it has been obſerved to riſe in its floods. When at liberty to expand over a wide valley ; then it could only riſe till it overflowed with a thickneſs or depth of water ſufficient to produce a motion backwards into the valley quick enough to take off the water as. faſt as it was 4upplied ; and we imagine that a foot or two would ſuffice in moſt caſes. The beſt way for a prudent engineer will be to obſerve the utmoſt riſe remembered by the neighbours in ſome gorge, where the river cannot ſpread out. Meaſure the increaſed ſection in this place, and at the ſame time recollect, that the water increaſes in a much greater proportion than the ſection ; becauſe an increaſe of the hydraulic mean depth produces an. increaſe of velocity in the duplicate proportion of the depth nearly. But as this augmentation of velocity will obtain alſo Between the embankments, it will be ſufficiently exact to ſuppoſe that the ſection muſt be increaſed here nearly in the ſame proportion as at the gorge already mentioned. Neglecting this method of information, and regulating the height of our embankment by the greateſt ſwell that has been obſerved in the plain, will aſſuredly make them too low, and render them totally uſeleſs.</p><p>A line of embankment ſhould always be carried ou by a ſtrict concert of the proprietors of both banks through its whole extent. A greedy proprietor, by advancing his own embankment beyond that of his neighbours, not only expoſes himſelf to rifle by the working of the waters on the angles which this will produce, but expoſes his neighbours alſo to danger, by narrowing the ſection, and thereby raiſing the ſurface and increaſing the velocity, and by turning the ſtream athwart, and cauſing it to ſhoot againſt the oppoſite bank. The whole ſhould be as much as poſſible in a line; and the general effect ſhould be to make the courſe of the ſtream ſtraighter than it was before. All bends ſhould be made more gentle, by keeping the embankment further from the river in all convex lines of the natural bank, and bringing it nearer where the bank is concave. This will greatly diminiſh the action of the waters on the bankment, and inſure their duration. The ſame maxim muſt be followed in fencing any brook which diſcharges itſelf into the river. The bends given at its mouth to the two lines of embankment ſhould be made leſs acute than thoſe of the natural brook, although, by this means, two points of land are left out. And the opportunity ſhould be embraced of making the direction of this tranſverſe brook more Hoping thao before, that is, leſs athwart the direction of the river.</p><p>It is of great conſequence to cover the outfide of the dyke with very compact turf cloſely united. If it admit water, the interior part of the wall, which is always more porous, becomes drenched in water, and this water acts with its ſtatical preſſure, tending to burſt the bank on the land-ſide, and will quickly ſhift it from its ſeat. The utmoſt care ſhould therefore be taken to make it and keep it perfectly tight. It ſhould be a continued fine turf, and every bare ſpot ſhould be carefully covered with freſh fod ; and rat holes muſt be carefully cloſed up.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>