<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Conſtantine and Licinius thus remaining undiſputed poſſeſſors and partners in the empire, all things promiſed a peaceable continuance of friendſhip and power. However, it was ſoon found, that the fame ambition that aimed after a part, would be content with nothing leſs than the whole. Ragan writers aſeribe the ruptuιe between theſe two potentates to Conſtantine ; while the Chriſtians, on the other hand, impute it wholly to Licinius. Both, perhaps, might have concurred : lor Licinius is convicted of having perſecuted Chriſtianity, which was ſo highly favoured by his rival ; and Conſtantine is known to have been the firſt to begin the preparations far an open rupture. Both ſides exerted all their power to make oppoſition ; and at the head of very formidable armies, came to an engagement near Cybalis, in Pannonia. Conſtantine, previous to the battle, in the midſt of his Chriſtian biſhops, begged the aſſiſtance of Heaven ; while Licinius, with equal zeal, called upon the pagan prieſts, to intercede with the gods in his favour. Conſtantine, after an obſtinate reſiſtance from the enemy, became victorious ; took their camp ; and, after ſome time, compelled Licinius to ſue ſor a truce, which was agreed upon. But this was of no long continuance; ſor loon after, the war breaking out afreſh, and the rivals coming once more to a general engagement, it proved deciſive. Licinius was entirely defeated, and purſued by Conſtantine into Nicomedia, where he ſurrendered himſelf up to the victor ; having firſt obtained an oath that his life ſhould be ſpared, and that he ſhould be permitted to paſs the remainder of his days in retirement. This, however, Conſtantine ſhortly after broke ; ſor either fearing his deſigns, or finding him actually engaged in freſh conſpiracies, he commanded him to be put to death, together with Martian his general, who ſome time before had been created Cæſar.</p><p>Conſtantine being now ſole monarch of the empire, without a rival to divide his power, or any perſon ſrom whoſe claims he could have the leaſt apprehenſions, reſolved to eſtabliſh Chriſtianity on ſo ſure a baſis, that no new regulations ſhould ſhake it. He commanded that in all the provinces of the empire the orders of the biſhops ſhould be exactly obeyed ; a privilege of which, in ſucceeding times, theſe fathers made but a very indifferent uſe. He called alſo a general council of theſe, to meet at Nicea, in order to repreſs  the hereſies that had already crept into the church, particularly that of Arius. To this place repaired about 3 (8 biſhops, beſides a multitude of preſhyters and deacons, together with the emperor himſelf ; who all, to about 17, concurred in condemning the tenets of Arius ; who, with his aſſociates, was baniſhed into a remote part of the empire.</p><p>Having thus reſtored univerſal tranquillity to. the empire, he was not able to ward off the calamities of a more domeſtic nature. As the hiſtories of that period are entirely at variance with each other, it is not eaſy to. tell the motives which induced him to put his wife Fauſta and his ſon Criſpus to death. The moſt plauſible account is this : Fauſta the empreſs, who was a woman of great beauty, but of extravagant deſires, had long, though ſecretly, loved Criſpus, Conſtantine’s ſon by a former wiſe. She had tried every art to inſpire this youth with a mutual paſſion; but, finding her more diſtant efforts ineffectual, had even the conſidence to make him an open conſeſſion of her deſires. This pro</p><lb/><p>duced an explanation, which was fatal to both. Crif-pus received her addreſſes with deteſtation ; and ſhe, to be revenged, accuſed him to the emperor. Conſtantine, fired at once with jealoufy and rage, ordered him to die without a hearing ; nor did his innocence appear till it was too late for redreſs. The only reparation therefore that remained, was the putting Fauſta, the wicked inſtrument of his former cruelty, to death ; which was accordingly executed upon her, together with ſome others who had been accomplices in her falſehood and treachery.</p><p>But the private misfortunes of a few were not to be weighed againſt evils of a more general nature, which the Roman empire ſhortly after experienced. Theſe aroſe from a meaſure which this emperor conceived and executed, of transferring the ſeat of the empire from Rome to Byzantium, or <hi rend="italic">Con</hi><hi rend="italic">ſt</hi><hi rend="italic">antinople,</hi>  as it was afterwards called. Whatever might have been the reaſons which induced him to this undertaking ; whether it was becauſe he was offended at ſome affronts he received at Rome, or that he ſuppoſed Conſtantinople more in the centre of the empire, or that he thought the eaſtern parts more required his preſence, experience has ſhown that they were weak and groundleſs. The empire had long before been in the moſt declining ſtate ; but this in a great meaſure gave precipitation to its downfall. After this it never reſumed its former ſplendor, but languiſhed.</p><p>His firſt deſign was to build a city which he might make the capital of the world ; and for this purpoſes he made choice of a ſituation at Chalcedon in Aſia Minor ; but we are told, that in laying out the ground-plan, an eagle caught up the line and flew with it over to Byzantium, a city which lay upon the oppoſite ſide of the Boſphorus. Here, therefore, it was thought expedient to ſix the ſeat of the empire and indeed nature ſeems to have formed it with all the conveniences and all the beauties rvhich might induce power to make&lt;it the ſeat of reſidence. It was ſituated on a plain that roſe gently from the water ; it commanded that ſtrait which unites the Mediterranean with the Euxine ſea, and was furniſhed with all the advantages which the moſt indulgent climate could beſtow. This city,, therefore, he beautified with the moſt magniſicent edifices ;. he divided it into 14 regions ; built a capitol, an amphitheatre, many churches, and other public works ; and having thus rendered it equal to the magnificence of his idea, he dedicated it in a very ſolemn manner to the God of martyrs ; in about two years after, repairing thither with his.whole court.</p><p>This removal produced no immediate alteration in the government of the empire ; the inhabitants of Rome, tho’ with reluctance, ſubmitted to the change ; nor was there for two or three years any diſturbance in the ſtate, until at length the Goths, finding that the Romans had withdrawn all their garriſons along the Danube, renewed their inroads, and. ravaged the country with unheard-of cruelty. Conſtantine, however,, ſoon repreſſed their incurſions,- and ſo ſtraitened them, that near 100,000 of their number periſhed by cold and hunger. Theſe and ſome other inſurrections being happily ſuppreſſed, the government of the empire was divided as follows. Conſtantine, the emperor’s, eldeſt ſon, commanded in Gaul and the weſtern provinces ; Conſtantius governed Africa and Illyricum ; and</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>