<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The projectors of the plan were Severua and Celer; two bold and enterpriſing men, who ſoon after put the emperor upon a ſtill more expenſive and arduous undertaking, namely, that of cutting a canal through hard rocks and ſteep mountains, from the lake Avernus tσ the mouth of the Tiber, ι6□  miles in length, and of ſuch breadth that two galleys of five ranks of oars might eaſily paſs abreaſt. His view in this was to open a communication between Rome and Campania, free from the troubles and dangers of the ſea ; for, this very year, a great number of veſſels laden with corn were ſhip-wrecked at Miſenum, the pilots chooſing rather to venture out in a violent ſtorm, than not to arrive at the time they were expected by Nero. For the executing of this great undertaking, the emperor ordered the priſoners from all parts to be tranſported into Italy ; and ſuch as were convicted, whatever their ’Crimes were, to be condemned only to his works. Nero, who undertook nothing with more ardour and readineſs than what was deemed impoſſible, expended incredible ſums in this raſh undertaking, and exerted all his might to cut through the mountains adjoining to the lake Avernus ; but, not being able to remove by art the obſtacles of nature, he was in the end obliged to drop the enterpriſe.</p><p>The ground that was not taken up by the foundations of Nero’s own palace, he aſſigned for houſes, which were not placed, as after the burning of the city by the Gauls, at random, and without order ; but the ſtreets were laid out regularly, ſpacious and ſtraight ; the edifices reſtrained to a certain height, perhaps of 70 feet, according to the plan of Auguſtus ; the courts were widened ; and to all the great houſes which ſtood by themſelves, and were called <hi rend="italic">ifles,</hi>  large porticoes were added, which Nero engaged to raiſe at his own expence, and to deliver to each proprietor the ſquares about them clear from all rubbiſh. He likewiſe promiſed rewards according to every man’s rank and ſub-ſtance ; and fixed a day for the performance of his promiſe, on condition that againſt that day their ſeveral houſes and palaces were finiſhed. He moreover made the following wiſe regulations to obviate ſuch a dreadful calamity for the future ; to wit, That the new buildings ſhould be raiſed to a certain height without timber ; that they ſhould be arched with ſtone from the quarries of Gabii and Alba, which were proof againſt fire ; that over the common ſprings, which were diverted by private men for their own uſes, overſeeers ſhould be placed to prevent that abuſe ; that every citizen ſhould have ready in his houſe ſome machine proper to extinguiſh the fire ; that no wall ſhould be common to two houſes, but every houſe be incloſed within its own peculiar walls, &amp;c. Thus the city in a ſhort time roſe out of its aſhes with new luſtre, and more beautiful than ever. However, ſome believed, that the ancient form was more conducing to health, the rays of the ſun being hardly felt on account of the narrowneſs of the ſtreets, and the height of the buildings, whereas now there was no ſhelter againſt the ſcorching heat. We are told, that Nero deſigned to extend the walls to Oſtia, and to bring from thence by a canal the ſea into the city.</p><p>The emperor uſed every art to throw the odium of this conflagration upon the Chriſtians, who were at that time gaining ground in Rome, Nothing could</p><lb/><p>be more dreadful than the perſecution raiſed againſt them upon this falſe accuſation, of which an account is given under the article <hi rend="italic">EccLfiaſlical HιsτoBr.</hi>  Hitherto, ho v-ever, the citizens of Rome ſeemed comparatively exempted from his cruelties, which chiefly fell upon ſtrangers and his neareſt connections ; but a conſpiracy formed againſt him by Pifσ, a man of great power and integrity, which was prematurely diſcovered, opened a new train of ſuſpicions that deſtroyed many of the principal families in Rome. This conſpiracy, in which ſeveral of the chief men of the city were concerned, was firſt diſcovered by the indiſcreet zeal of a woman named <hi rend="italic">Epicharis,</hi>  who, by ſome means now unknown, had been let into the plot, which ſhe revealed to Voluſius, a tribune, in order to prevail upon him to be an accomplice. Voluſius, inſtead of coming into her deſign, went and diſcovered what he had learned to Nero, who immedi-ately put Epicharis in priſon. Soon after, a freedman belonging to Scænius, one of the accomplices, made a farther diſeovery. The conſpirators were examined apart ; and as their teſtimonies differed, they were put to the torture. Natalis was the firſt who made a con-feſſion of his own guilt and that of many others. Scae-nius gave a liſt of the conſpirators ſtill more ample. Lucan, the poet, was amongſt the number ; and he, like the reſt, in order to ſave himſelf, ſtill farther enlarged the catalogue, naming, among others, Attilia, his own mother. Epicharis was now, therefore, again called upon and put to the torture ; but her fortitude was -proof againſt all the tyrant’s cruelty ; neither ſcourging nor burning, nor all the malicious methods uſed by the executioners, could extort the ſmalleſt conſeſſion. She was therefore remanded to priſon, with orders to have her tortures renewed the day following. In the meantime, ſhe found an opportunity of ſti angling herſelf with her handkerchief, by hanging it againſt the back of her chair. On the diſeoveries already made, Piſo, Lateranus, Fennius Rufus, Subrius Flavius; Sulpicius Aſper, Veſtinus the conſul, and numberleſs others, were all executed without mercy. But the two moſt remarkable perſonages who fell on this occaſion were Seneca the philoſopher, and Lucan the poet, who was his nephew. It is not certainly known whether Seneca was really concerned in this conſpiracy or not.—-This-great man had for ſome time perceived the outrageous conduct of his pupil ; and, finding himſelf incapable of controuling his ſavage diſpoſition, had retired from court into ſolitude and privacy. However, his retreat did not now protect him ; for Nero, either having real teſtimony againſt him, or elſe hating him' for his virtues, ſent a tribune to inform him that he was ſuſpected as an accomplice, and ſoon after ſent him an order to put himſelf to death, with which he complied.</p><p>In this manner was the whole city filled with ſlaLighter, and frightful inſtances of treachery. No maſter was ſecure from the vengeance of his ſlaves, nor even parents from the baſer attempts of their children. Not· only throughout Rome, ſhut the whole country round, bodies of ſoldiers were ſeen in purſuit of the ſuſpected and the guilty. Whole crowds of wretches loaded with chains were led every day to the gates of the palace, to wait their ſentence from the tyrant’s own lips. He airways j&gt;refided at the torture in perſen, attended by Ti-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>