<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Mr Buat therefore examined this by experiment, but found, that even with re ſpect to a pipe or channel which was uniform throughout, this was not true. We could give at once the final formula which he found to expreſs the velocity in every caſe whatever ; but this would be too empirical. The chief ſteps of his very ſa-gacious inveſtigation are inſtructive. We ſhall therefore mention them briefly, at leaſt as far as they tend to give us any collateral information ; and let it always be noted, that the inſtruction which they convey is not abſtract ſpeculation, but experimental truths, which muſt ever remain as an addition to our ltock of knowledge, although Mr Buat’s deductions from them ſhould prove falſe.</p><p>He found, in the firſt place, that in the fame channel the product of V and √7 increaſed as √ <hi rend="sub">i</hi> increaſed ; that is, the velocities increaſed faſter than the ſquare roots of the ſlope, or the reſiſtances did not increaſe as fall as the ſquares of the velocities. We beg leave to refer our readers to what we ſaid on the reſiſt-ance of pipes to the motion of fluids through them, in the article Pneumatics, when ſpeaking of bellows. They will there ſee very<hi rend="sup">7</hi> valid reaſons (we apprehend) for thinking that the reſiſtances muſt increaſe more Hourly than the ſquares of the velocities.</p><p>It being found, then, that V √ <hi rend="sub">s</hi> is not equal to a conſtant quantity<hi rend="italic">,</hi>  it becomes neceſſary to inve-ftigate ſome quantity depending on √<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="sub">ιf</hi>, or, as it is called, ſome function of 5/ <hi rend="sub">j</hi>, which ſhall render <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub">m</hi>  g</hi><hi rend="sup">a</hi>  conſtant quantity. Let X be this function of , ſo that we ſhall always have VX equal to the conſtant quantity<hi rend="italic">»ſ mg,</hi>  or 2f-2<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-∕ equal to the ac-</p><p>Λ.</p><p>tual velocity V of a pipe or channel which is in train.</p><p>Mr Buat, after many trials and reflections, the chief of which will be mentioned by and by, found a value of X which correſponded with a vaſt variety of Hopes and velocities, from motions almoſt imperceptible, in a bed nearly horizontal, to the greateſt velocities which could be produced by gravity alone in a vertical pipe; and when he compared them together, he found a very diſcernible relation between the reſiſtances and the magnitude of the ſection : that is, that in two channel# which had the ſame ſlope, and the ſame propelling force, the velocity was greateſt in the channel which had the greateſt ſection relative to its border. This may reaſonably be expected. The reſiſtances' ariſe from the mutual action of the water and this border. The water immediately contiguous to it is retarded, and this retards the next, and ſo on. It is to be expected, therefore, that if the border, and the velocity, and the ſlope, be the ſame, the diminution of this velocity will be ſo much the leſs as it is to be ſhared among a greater number of particles ; that is, as the area of the ſection is greater in proportion to the extent of its border. The diminution of the general or medium velocity muſt be leſs· in a cylindrical pipe than in a ſquar-e one of the ſame area, becauſe the border of its ſection is leſs.</p><p>It appears evident, that the reſiſtance of each particle is in the direct proportion of the whole reſiſtance, and the inverſe proportion of the number of particles which receive equal lhares of-it. It-is therefore directly as the</p><lb/><p>border, and inverſely as the ſection. Therefore in the V* . '</p><p>expreſſion — which we have given for the reſiſtance,</p><p>the quantity <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  cannot be conſtant, except in the ſame channel ; and in different channels it muſt vary along with the relation of the ſection to its border, becauſe the reſiſtances diminiſh in proportion as this relation increaſes.</p><p>Without attempting to diſcover this relation by theoretical examination of the particular motions of the various filaments, Mr Buat endeavoured to diſcover it by a compariſon of experiments. But this required ſome manner of ſtating this proportion between the augmentation of the ſection and the augmentation of its border.</p><p>His ſtatement is this : He reduces every ſection to a rectangular parallelogram of the ſame area, and having its baſe equal to the border unfolded into a ſtraight line. The product of this baſe by the height of the rectangle will be equal to the area of the lection. I herefore this height will be a repreſentative of this variable ratio of the ſection to its border (We do not mean that there is any ratio between a ſurface and a line : but the ratio of fection to ſection is different from that of border to border ; and it is the ratio of theſe ratios which is thus expreſſed by the height of this rectangle). If S be the ſection, and B the border, is evidently a line equal to the height of this rectangle. Every ſection being in this manner reduced to a rectangle, the perpendicular height of it may be called the hydraulic mean depth of the ſection, and may be expreſſed by the ſymbol <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  (Buat calls it the mean radius), If the channel be a cylindrical pipe, or an open half cylinder, it is evident that <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is half the radius. If the ſection is a rectangle, wlioſe width is <hi rend="italic">ιυ,</hi>  and height<hi rend="italic">  h, </hi>the mean depth is , &amp;c. In general, if <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  re-prefent the proportion of the breadth of a rectangular canal to its depth, that is, if y be made = -v , we ſhall</p><p><hi rend="italic">, <hi rend="sup">w</hi> , <hi rend="sup">t</hi>l<hi rend="sup">h</hi></hi></p><p>have <hi rend="italic">d —</hi>  —:—, or <hi rend="italic">d ~---—.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">q</hi>  + 2’    <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  4- 2</p><p>Now, ſince the reſiſtancee muſt augment as the proportion of the border to the ſection augments, <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  in the ſor-</p><p>V ’ <hi rend="italic">g    _</hi></p><p>mulas — ≈≈ — and V<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">λ∕s —    mg,</hi></hi>  muſt follow the</p><p><hi rend="italic">rn 5    <hi rend="sup">θ</hi></hi></p><p>proportions of <hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  and the quantity √w <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  muſt be proportional to √<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi>  for different channels, and </p><p><hi rend="italic">Vd</hi></p><p>ſhould be a conſtant quantity in every caſe. -</p><p>Our author was aware, however, of a very ſpecious objection to the cloſe dependence of the reſiſtance on the extent of the border ;, and that it might be ſaid that a double border did not occaſion a double refill-ance, unleſs the preſſure on all the parts was the ſame. For it may be naturally (and it is generally) ſuppoſed, that the reſiſtance will be greater when the preſſure is greater. The friction or reſiſtance analogous to friction may therefore bè greater on an inch of the bottom than on an inch of the ſides ; but Mr. D’Alembert and many others have demonſtrated, that the paths of the filaments will be. the ſame whatever be the preſſures:</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>