<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the navigation of rivers already kept up by weirs, which gave a partial and interrupted navigation, it was uſual to avoid the great expence of the ſecond dam and gate, by making the lock altogether detached from the river, within land, and having its baſon parallel to the river, and communicating by one end with the river above the weir, and by the other end with the river below the weir, and having a flood-gate at each end.— This was a moſt ingenious thought ; and it was a prodigious improvement, free from all the inconveniences of currents, ice, &amp;c. &amp;c. It was called a <hi rend="italic">Schluſſel,</hi>  or lock, with conſiderable propriety ; and this was the origin of the word <hi rend="italic">flume,</hi>  and of our application of its tranſlation <hi rend="italic">lock.</hi>  This practice being once introduced, it was not long before engineers found that a complete ſeparation of the navigation ſrom the bed of the river was not only the moſt perfect method for obtaining a ſure, eaſy, and uninterrupted navigation, but that it was in general the moſt ceconomical in its firſt conſtruction, and ſubject to no rifle of deterioration by the action of the current, which was here entirely removed. Locked canals, therefore, have almoſt entirely ſupplant-ed all attempts to improve the natural beds of rivers ; and this is hardly ever attempted except in the flat countries, where they can hardly he ſaid to differ from horizontal canals. We therefore cloſe with theſe obſervations this article, and reſerve what is yet to be ſaid on the conſtruction of canals and locks for the article <hi rend="italic">WATER-Works .</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">We beg leave, however, to detain the reader for </hi>a few moments. He cannot but have obſerved our anxiety to render this diſſertation worthy of his notice, by making it practically uſeful. We have on every occaſion appealed, from all theoretical deductions, however ſpecious and well ſupported, to fact and obſervation of thoſe ſpontaneous phenomena of nature which are continually paſſing in review before us in the motion of running waters. Reſting in this manner our whole doctrines on experiment, on the obſervation of what really happens, and what happens in a way which we cannot or do not fully explain, theſe ſpontaneous operations of nature came inſenſibly to acquire a particular value in our imagination. It has alſo happened in the courſe of our reflections on theſe ſub-jects, that theſe phenomena have frequently preſented themſelves to our view in groups, not leſs remarkable for the extent and the importance of their conſequences than for the ſimplicity, and frequently the ſeeming in-ſignificancy, nay frivolity, of the means employed. Our fancy has therefore been ſometimes warmed with the view of a ſomething ; an</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ens agit ans mo lern, et magno ſe corpore miſcens.</hi></p><p>This Iras ſometimes made us expreſs ourſelves in a way that is ſuſceptible of miſinterpretation, and may even lead into a miſtake of our meaning.</p><p>We therefore find ourſelves obliged to declare, that by the term Nature, which we have ſo frequently uſed <hi rend="italic">con amore,</hi>  we do not mean that indeſcribable idol which the ſelf-conceit and vanity of our neighbours in France have ſet up of late, and oſtentatiouſly ſtand on tiptoe to worſhip. This <hi rend="italic">ens rationis,</hi>  this creature of the imagination, has long been the object of cool contemplation in the cloſet of the philoſopher, and has ſhared his attention with many other play-things of his ever-working fancy. But ſhe has now become the ob</p><p>ject of a fincere 3nd fond idolatry, being held forth by her zealous high-prieſts to the reſined vanity of man as a ſort of mirror, in which he may behold his own che-riſhed features, and admire a beauty of his own com-poſition, painted with the moſt delicate glow of humanity, and decked out with every ornament with which the courtly fancies of a Voltaire, a Diderot, a Mirabeau, could contrive, to ſmooth over or to hide all traçes of created imperfection. We leave this idol to the worſhip of her intoxicated and unfortunate votaries. The ſolemn farce in the church of Notre Dame at Paris was an adoration every way worthy of the Divinity ; and our horror in reading the deſcription of the ceremonial was not without ſome allay of pleaſure, when we ſaw among her moſt active prieſts an artiſt, whom we had ſeen a few years before the <hi rend="italic">rnackiηifte de l<hi rend="sup">,</hi>opera </hi>at St Peteιiburgh, and grand-maſter of the lodge <hi rend="italic">des Moujſes.</hi>  We hope to be forgiven the pun, when we ſay that the ancient fabric which was that day profaned by the <hi rend="italic">abomination of deſolation,</hi>  was then in reality the <hi rend="italic">temple de Notre Dame.</hi>  Mr Brigonzi was, by his pro-ſeſſion, a fit ſucceſſor in the prieſthood to thoſe <hi rend="italic">ſages de lα France</hi>  (ſuch was the appellation that they gave each other), whom we have juſt now named ; and his <hi rend="italic">Lours de Theatre,</hi>  for which we have frequently admired his talents, were a very proper accompaniment to the fi-neffe and ruſe of theſe <hi rend="italic">ſoi-diflant</hi>  philoſophers, who, under the maik of the moſt reſined humanity, habitually practiſed arts of diſhoneſty which would have ruined the character of the meaneſt pedlar. No one will think that we expreſs ourſelves too ſtrongly who reflects on the many inſamous tricks played by Voltaire to his bookſellers. No one will think the charge too harſh, when he learns that Diderot, after having pretended to the poſſeſſion of an immenſe library, and ſold it to the empreſs of Ruſſia for an enormous ſum, had to ranſack the warehouſes of the bookſellers of Paris and throughout all Germany, in order to fill his ſhelves. As for Mirabeau, he ſurpaſſes eulogy.</p><p>Moſt aſſiduous were thoſe apoſtles in ſpreading this fanaticiſm, of which they enjoyed the courtly profits : and we imagine that the employment was as agreeable as it was lucrative ; for we cannot ſuppoſe that Le Kain had more enjoyment, when faſci-nating his Pariſian audience in the character of Voltaire’s Mahomet, than its author felt in the ſide-box, when grinning to himſelf, and conſcious what a fordid and envious wretch he was, he found himſelf crowned by the firſt actreſs, and worſhipped by the audience as the apoſtle of philanthropy and univerſal benevolence.</p><p>Such was the worſhip, ſſuch were the prieſts, of this Gallic idol; and, like their predeceſſors the Druids, they have made human ſacrifices a cuſtomary oblation at the ſhrine. We wonder at theſe things, and are ſurpriſed that any thing which can even be nicknamed <hi rend="italic">ρhilofi-phy</hi>  can produce ſuch effects. But the taſlc of this apoſtleſhip was as eaſy as it was agreeable. It was not the work of a day ; it was the completion of a ſtudied corruption of principles, which is now above a century old. We may ſay that it began under the clever but infamous Dubois; who from being the valet de chambre of an infirm biſhop, became cardinal, and ſovereign of the Gallic church, and almoſt of the ſtate. When objected to by the bigotted Louis XIV. (on a preſenta-tion for preferment) as a Janſeniſt, “ <hi rend="italic">Oh qui ηon,<hi rend="sup">,</hi>* </hi>ſaid the duke of Orleans, “ <hi rend="italic">Oh, Sire, qui non, il η<hi rend="sup">,</hi>efl</hi></p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>