<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pieces of wood, decreaſing gradually in length, ſo as to produce a ſucceſſion of tones and ſemitones in the diatonic ſeries, which had keys, and was played on as a ſpinet ; the hint of which, he ſays, was taken from an inſtrument in uſe among the Turks, conſiſting of 12 wooden cylinders, of different lengths, ſtrung together, which being ſuſpended and ſtruck with a ſtick, having a ball at the end, produced muſic. Hawkins’s Hilt. Muſi vol. ii. p. 449.</p><p>RIGOR, in medicine, a convulſive ſhuddtring from ſevere cold, an ague fit, or other diſorder.</p><p>RIMINI, an ancient, populous, and handſome town of Italy, in Romagna, which is part of the territory of the church, with a biſhop’s ſee, an old caſtle, and a ſtrong tower ; as alſo many remains of antiquity, and very fine buildings. It is famous for a council in 1359, conſiſting of 400 biſhops, who were all Arians except 20. It is ſeated in a fertile plain, at the mouth of the river Marecchia, on the gulph of Venice. E. Long. 12. 39. N. Lat. 44. <hi rend="italic">6.</hi></p><p>RIND, the ſkin of any fruit that may be cut off or pared. Rind is alſo uſed for the inner bark of trees,. or that whitiſh ſoft ſubſtance which adheres immediately to the wood. See Plant.</p><p>RING, an ornament of gold and ſilver, of a circular figure, and uſually worn on the finger.</p><p>The epiſcopal ring (which makes a part of the pontifical apparatus, and is eſteemed a pledge of the ſpiritual marriage betw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>een the biſhop and his church) is of very ancient {landing. The fourth council of Toledo, held in 633, appoints, that a biſhop condemned by one council, and found afterwards innocent by a lecond, ſhall be reſtored, by giving him the ring, ſtaff, &amp;c. From biſhops, the cuſtom of the ring has paſſed to cardinals, who are to pay a very great ſum<hi rend="italic">pro jure annuli car din ιlitd.</hi></p><p>RINGS. The antiquity of rings is known from Scripture and profane authors. Judah left his ring or ſignet w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ith Tamar (Gen. xxxviii. 18). When Pharaoh committed the government of all Egypt to Joſeph, he took his ring from his finger, and gave it to Joſeph (Gen. xli. 42). After the victory that the jſraelites obtained over the Midianites, they offered to the Lord the rings, the bracelets, and the golden necklaces, and the ear-rings, that they had taken from the enemy (Numb, xxxi. 50). The Iſraelitiſh women wore rings not only on their fingers, but alſo in their noſtrils and their ears. St James diſtinguiſhes a man of wealth and dignity by the ring of gold that he wore on his finger (James ii. 2). At the return of the prodigal ſon, his father orders him to be dreſſed in a new fuit of clothes, and to have a ring put upon his finger (Luke xv. 22). When the Lord threatened King Jeconiah with the utmoſt effects of his auger, he tells him, that though he wore the ſignet or ring upon his finger, yet he ſhould be torn off (Jer. xxii. 24 )</p><p>The ring was uſed chiefly to<hi rend="sup">,</hi>fεal with; and the Scripture generally puts it in the hands of princes and great perſons ; as the king of Egypt, Joſeph, Ahaz, Jezebel, King Ahaſuerus, his favourite Haman, Mordecai, who ſucceeded Haman in his dignity, King Darius ( 1 Kings xxi. 8. ; Eſther iii. Ίο, &amp;c. ; Dan. vi. 17). The patents and orders of theſe princes were ſealed with their rings or ſignets ; and it was this that ſecured to them their authority and reſpect. Sec the article Seal.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R iNG∙Bone.</hi>  See Farr jer γ, Sect, xxxi.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">NG-0uſel,</hi>  in ornithology, a ſpecies of T URDUS.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">R1O-GRAnde, a river of Africa, which runs from eaſt to weſt through Negroland, and falls into the Atlantic ocean, in 11 degrees of latitude. Some take it to be a branch of the Higer, of which there is not the leaſt proof.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Rιo-Grande,</hi>  a river of South America, in Braſil, which has its ſource in an unknown country : it croſſes the captainſhip of Rio-Grande, and falls into the ſea at Natal los Reyes.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rio-Janeiro,</hi>  a river of South America, which riſes in the mountains weſt of Braſil, and running eaſt through that country, falls into the Atlantic Ocean, in S. Lat 23. 30. The province of Janeiro is one of the richelt in Braſil ; and produces gold, ſilver, diamonds, and other precious ſtones.</p><p>RIOM, a town of France, in Auvergne ; ſeated on a hill, in ſo agreeable a country, that it is called the <hi rend="italic">garden of Auvergne</hi>  E. Long. 3. 12. N. Lat. 43. 51.</p><p>RIOT, in law. The riotous aſſembling of 12 perſons, or more, and not diſperfing upon proclamation, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as ſir ſt made high treaſon by ſtatute 3' &amp; 4 Edw∖ VI. c. 5. when the king was a minor, and a change of religion to be effected.: but that ſtatute was repealed by ſtatute I Mar. c. 1. among the other treaſens created ſince the 25 Edw, III. ; though the prohibition was in ſubſtance re-enacted, with an inferior degree of puniſh-ment, by ſtatute 1 Mar. ſt. 2. c. 12. which made the ſame offence a ſingle felony. Theſe ſtatutes ſpecified and particularized the nature of the riots they were meant to ſuppreſs ; as, for example, ſuch as were ſet on foot with intention to offer violence to the privy-council, or to change the laws of the kingdom, or for certain other ſpecific purpeſes ; in which caſes, if the perſons were commanded by proclamation to diſperſe, and they did not, it was by the ſtatute of Mary made ſelony, but within the benefit of clergy ; and alſo the act indemnified the peace-officers and their affiliants, if they killed any of the mob in endeavouring to ſuppreſs ſuch riot. This was thought a neceſſary ſecurity in that ſanguinary reign, when popery was intended to be re-eſtabliſhed, which was like to produce great diicontents : but at firſt it was made only ſor a year, and w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as afterwards continued for that queen’s life. And, by ſtatute 1 Eliz. c. 16. when a reformation in religion was to be once more attempted, it w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as revived and continued during her life alſo ; and then expired. From the acceſſion of James I. to the death of Queen Anne, it was never once thought expedient to ιevive it ; but, in the firſt year of George I. it was judged neceſſary, in order to ſupport the execution of the act of ſettlement, to renew it, and at one ſtroke to make it perpetual, with large additions. For, whereas the former acts expreſsly defined and ſpecified what ſhould be accounted a riot, the ſtatute 1 Geo. I. c. 5. enacts, generally, that if any 12 perſons are unlawfully aſſembled to the diſtutbance of the peace, and any one juſtice of the peace, ſheriff, under ſheriff, or mayor of a town, ſhall think proper to command them by proclamation to diſperſe, if they contemn his orders and continue together for one hour afterw<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ards, ſuch contempt ſhall be felony without benefit of clergy. And farther, if the reading of the proclamation be by force oppoſed, or the reader be in any manner wilfully</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>