<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>his light ſhrivelled grain will go much farther in ſeed than the plump grain would do. I ſaw the experiment made on wheat which was ſo ſhrivelled that it was thought ſcarcely worth giving to fowls, and yet produced heavy large ears.”</p><p>RIPHŒAN mountains, are a chain of high mountains in Ruſſia, to the north-eaſt of the river Oby, where there are ſaid to be the fineſt fables of the whole empire.</p><p>RIPHATH, or Rip hat, ſecond ſon of Gomer, and grandſon of Japhet (Gen. x. 3. run <hi rend="italic">Riphatſ</hi>  In moſt copies he is called <hi rend="italic">Diρhath</hi>  in the Chronicles (1 Chr. i. 6. γ<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">-</hi>&gt;b*t</hi><hi rend="italic">Diρhαf).</hi>  The reſemblance of the two Hebrew letters Ί <hi rend="italic">Reſh</hi>  and π <hi rend="italic">Daleth</hi>  is ſo much, that they are very often confounded. But, to the credit of the tranſlators of our Engliſh verſion be it ſaid, that in this inſtance, as well as in many others, they have reſtored the original reading, and rendered it Ri-phath. The learned are not agreed about the country that was peopled by the deſcendants of Riphath. The Chaldee and Arabic take it for France ; Euſebius for the country of the Sauromatæ ; the Chronicon Alex-andrinum for that of the Garamantæ ; Joſephus for Pa-phlagonia. Mela aſſures us, that anciently the people of this province were called <hi rend="italic">Riphatœi,</hi>  or R<hi rend="sup">,</hi>.phaces ;</p><p>and in Bithynia, bordering upon Paphlagonia, may be found the river Rhebeus, a people called <hi rend="italic">Rhebantes,</hi>  and a canton of the ſame name. Theſe reaſons have prevailed with Bochart to believe, that Riphath peopled Paphlagonia. Others think he peopled the Montes Riphei ; and this opinion ſeems the moſt reaſonable to us, becauſe the other ſons of Gomer peopled the northern countries towards Scythia, and beyond the Eux-ine ſea.</p><p>RISIBLE, any thing capable of exciting laughter.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ludicrous</hi>  is a general term, ſignifying, as may appear ſrom its derivation, what is playſome, ſportive, or jocular. <hi rend="italic">Ludicrous</hi>  therefore ſeems the genus, of which <hi rend="italic">riſible</hi>  is a ſpecies, limited as above to what makes us laugh.</p><p>However eaſy it may be, concerning any particular object, to ſay whether it be riſible or not, it ſeems difficult, if at all practicable, to eſtabliſh any general character, by which objects of that kind may be diſtin-guiſhed from others. Nor is that a ſingular caſe ; for, upon a review, we find the ſame difficulty in moſt of the articles already handled. There is nothing more eaſy, viewing a particular object, than to pronounce that it is beautiful or ugly, grand or little : but were we to attempt general rules for ranging objects under different claſſes according to theſe qualities, we ſhould be much gravelled. A ſeparate cauſe increaſes the difficulty of diſtinguiſhing riſible objects by a general character : all· men are not equally affected by riſible objects, nor the fame man at all times ; for in high ſpi-rits a thing will make him laugh outright, which will ſcarce provoke a ſmile in a grave mood. Riſible objects, However, are circumſcribed within certain limits. No object is riſible but what appears flight, little, or trivial ; for we laugh at nothing that is of importance to our own intereſt or to that of others. A real diſtreſs raiſes pity, and · therefore cannot be riſible ; but a flight or imaginary diſtreſs, which moves not pity, is riſible. The adventure of the fulling-mills in Don Quixote, is extremely riſible ; ſo is the ſcene where Sancho, in a dark night, tumbling into a pit, and at</p><p>taching himſelf to the ſide by hand and foot, hangs there in terrible diſmay till the morning, when he dif-covers himſelf to be within a foot of the bottom. A noſe remarkably long or ſhort, is riſible ; but to want it altogether, ſo ſar from provoking laughter, raiſss horror in the ſpectator. With reſpect to works both of nature and of art, none of them are riſible but what are out of rule ; ſome remarkable defect or exceſs, a very long viſage, for example, or a very ſhort one. Hence nothing juſt, proper, decent, beautiful, proportioned, or grand, is riſible.</p><p>Even from this flight ſketch it will be readily conjectured, that the emotion raiſed by a riſible object is of a nature ſo ſingular, as ſcarce to find place while the mind is occupied with any other paſſion or emotion ; and the conjecture is verified by experience ; for we ſcarce ever find that emotion blended with any other. ' One emotion we muſt except ; and that is, contempt raiſed by certain improprieties : every improper act inſpires us with ſome degree of contempt for the author ; and if an improper act be at the ſame time riſible to provoke laughter, of which blunders and abſurdities are noted inſtances, the two emotions of contempt and of laughter unite intimately in the mind, and produce externally what is termed a <hi rend="italic">laugh of derifiοn</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">of ſcorn.</hi>  Hence objects that cauſe laughter may be diſtinguiſhed into two kinds : they are either <hi rend="italic">rifible</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ridiculous.</hi>  A riſible object is mirthful only ; a ridiculous object is both mirthful and contemptible. The firſt raiſes an emotion of laughter that is altogether pleaſant : the pleaſant emotion of laughter raiſed by the other, is blended with the painful emotion of contempt ; and the mixed emotion is termed <hi rend="italic">the emotion of ridicule. .</hi>  The pain a ridiculous object gives me, is reſented and puniſhed by a laugh of deriſion. A riſible object, on the other hand, gives me no pain; it is altogether pleaſant by a certain ſort of titillation, which is expreſſed externally by mirthful laughter. See Ridicule.</p><p>Riſible objects are ſo common, and ſo well underſtood, that it is unneceſſary to confirme paper or time upon them. Take the few following examples :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Falſtaff.</hi>  I do remember him at Clement’s inn, like a man made after flipper of a cheeſe-paring. When· he was naked, he was for all the world like a forked radiſh, with a head fantaſtically carved upon it with a knife.    <hi rend="italic">Second part, Henry</hi>  IV. <hi rend="italic">aft.</hi>  3. <hi rend="italic">ſc.</hi>  5.</p><p>The foregoing is of diſproportion. The following examples are of flight or imaginary misfortunes.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Falſtaff.</hi>  Go fetch me a quart of ſack, put a toaſt in’t. Have I liv’d tσ be carried in a baſket, like a bar-row of butcher’s offal, and to be thrown into the Thames ! Well, if I be ſerved ſuch another trick, I’ll have my brains ta’en out and butter’d, and give them to a dog for a new-year’s gift. The rogues flighted me into the river with as little remorſe as they would have drown’d a bitch’s blind puppies, fifteen i'th'litter ; and you may know by my ſize that I have a kind of alacrity in finking ; if the bottom were as deep as hell, I ſhould down. I had been drown’d, but that the ſhore was ſhelvy and ſhallow ; a death that I abhor : for the water ſwells a man ; and what a thing ſhould I have been when I had been ſwell’d ? I ſhould have been a mountain of mummy.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Merry Wives of Wiηdfor<hi rend="sub">i</hi> aft fſe- iζ.</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>