<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>known, and his pride ſoon appeared ιipon hiâ coming to the throne ; having been heard to declare, that he had given the empire to his father ànd brother, and now received it again as his due.</p><p>The begirtnirtg of his reign wàs univerſally acceptable to the people, as he appeared equally remarkable far his clemency, liberality, and juſtice. He carried his abhorrence of cruelty ſo far, as at one time to forbid the ſacriſicing of exert. His liberality was ſuch, •that he would not accept of the legacies that were left ſhim by ſuch as had children of their own. His juſtice was ſuch, that he would fit whole days and reverſe the partial ſentertces of the ordinary judges. He appeared very carefrtl artd liberal in repairing the libraries which had been burnt, and recovering copies of ſuch books as had been loſt, ſending on purpoſe to Alexandria to tranſcribe them. But he ſoon began to ſhow the natural deformity of his mind. Inſtead of cultivating literature, as his father and brother had done, he neglected ail kinds of ſtudy, addicting himſelf wholly to the meaner purfuits,-particularly archery and gaming. No emperor before him entertained the people with ſuch various and expenſive ſhows. During theſe diverſions he diſtributed great rewards ; ſitting as preſident himſelf, adorned with a purple robe and crown, with the prieſts of Jupiter and the college of Flavian prieſts about him. The meanneſs of his occupations in ſolitude were a juſt contraſt to his exhibitions in public oſtentation. He uſually ſpent his hours of retirement in catching flies, and flicking them through with a bodkin ; ſo that one of his ſervants being aſked if the emperor was alone, he anſwered, that he had not ſo much as a fly to bear him company. His vices ſeemed every day to increaſe with the duration of his reign ; and as he thus became more odious to his people, all their murmurs only ſerved to add ſtrength to his ſuſpicions, and malice to his cruelty. His ungrateful treatment of Agricola ſeemed</p><p>the firſt ſymptom of his natural malevolence. Domitian . was always particularly fond of obtaining a military reputation, and therefore jealous of it in others. He had marched ſome time before into Gaul, upon a pretended expedition againſt the Catti, a people of Germany ; and, without ever ſeeing the enemy, reſolved to have the honour of a triumph upon his return to Rome. For that purpoſe he purchaſed a number of ſlaves, whom he dreſſed in German habits ; and at the head of this miſerable proceſſion entered the city, amidſt the apparent acclamations and concealed contempt of all his ſubjects. The ſucceſſes, therefore, of Agricola in Britain affected him with an extreme degree of envy. This admirable general, who is ſcarce mentioned by any writer except Tacitus, purſued the advantages which he had already obtained. He routed the Caledonians ; overcame Galgacus, the Britiſh chief, at the head of</p><p>30,000 men ; and afterwards ſending out a fleet to ſcour the coaſt,firſt diſcovered Great Britain tobe an iſland*. He likewiſe diſcovered and ſubdued the Orkneys, and thus reduced the whole into a civilized province of the Roman empire. When the account of theſe ſucceſſes was brought to Domitian, he received it with a ſeeming pleaſure, but real uneaſineſs. He thought Agri-cola’s -riling reputation a reproach upon his own inactivity ; and, inſtead of attempting to emulate, he reſolved to ſuppreſs the merit of his ſervices. He ordered him, therefore, the external marks of his -approbation, and</p><p>took care that triumphant ornaments, ſtatues, and other honours, ſhould be decreed him ; but at the ſame time he removed him from his command, under a pretence of appointing him to the government of Syria. By theſe means, Agricola ſurrendered up his government to Sa-luſtius Lucullus, but ſoon found that Syria was other* wiſe diſpoſed of. Upon his return to Rome, which was privately and by night, he was coolly received by the emperor ; and dying ſome time after in retirement, it was ſuppoſed by ſome that his end was haſtened by Domitian’s direction.</p><p>Domitian ſoon after found the want of ſo experienced a commander in the many irruptions of the barbarous nations that ſurrounded the empire. The Sarmatians in Europe, joined with thoſe in Aſia, made a formidable invaſion ; at once deſtroying a whole legion, and a general of the Romans. The Dacians, under the conduct of Decebalus their king, made an irruption, and overthrew the Romans in ſeveral engagements. Loſſes were followed by loſſes, ſo that every ſeaſon became memorable for ſome remarkable overthrow. At laſt, however, the ſtate making a vigorous exertion of its internal power, the barbarians were repelled, partly by force and partly by the aſſiſtance of money, which only ſerved to enable them to make future invaſions to greater advantage. But in whatever manner the enemy might have been repelled, Domitian was reſolved not to loſe the honour of a triumph. He returned in great ſplendor to Rome ; and not contented with thus triumphing twice without a victory, he reſolved to take the ſurname of <hi rend="italic">Germanicus,</hi>  for his conqueſt over a people with whom he never contended.</p><p>In proportion as the ridicule increaſed againſt him, his pride ſeemed every day to demand greater homage. He would permit his ſtatues to be made only of gold and ſilver ; aſſumed to himſelf divine honours ; and ordered that all men ſhould treat him with the ſame a□-pellations which they gave to the divinity. His cruelty was not behind his arrogance ; he cauſed numbers of the moſt illuſtrious ſenators and others to. be put to death upon the moſt trifling pretences. Saluſtius Lucullus, his lieutenant in Britain, was deſtroyed only for-having given his own name to a new ſort of lances of his own invention. Junius Ruſticus died for publiſhing-a book, in which he commended Thraſea and Priſcus, two philoſophers who oppoſed Veſpaſian’e coming to the throne.</p><p>Such cruelties as theſe, that ſeem almoſt without a motive, may naturally be ſuppoſed to have produced rebellion. Lucius Antonius, governor in Upper Germany, knowing how much the emperor was deteſted at home, affιιmed the enſigns of imperial dignity. As he was at the head of a formidable army, Ins ſucceſe remained long doubtful ; but a ſudden overflowing of the Rhine dividing his army, he was ſet upon at that juncture by Normandus, the emperor’s general, and totally routed. The news of this victory, we are told, was brought to Rome by ſupernatund means, on the ſame day that the ſhatfle was ſought. Domitian’s ſeverity was greatly increaſed by this ſucceſs, of ſhort duration. In order to diſcover thoſe who were accomplices with· the adverſe party, he invented new tortures, ſometimes cutting off the hands, at other times thruſting fire into the privities, of the people whom he ſuſpected of being ſhis enemies. During- theſe cruelties, he aggravated</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>