<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>did in an Indian canoe, we cannot ſuppoſe that he had much leiſure or conveniency for calculations, and therefore are not ſurpriſed that he did not ſee that even this circumſtance was of little avail in ſo ſmall or ſhallow a body of water. He carefully noted, however, the times of high and low water as he paſſed along. When arrived at Para, he found not only that the high water was later and later as we are farther from the mouth, but he found that at one and the ſame inſtant there were ſeveral points oſhigh water between Para and the confluence of the Madeira, with points of low water intervening. This concluſion was eaſily drawn from his own obſervations, although he could not fee at one in-ſlant the high waters in different places. He had only to compute the time of high water at a particular ſpot, on the day he obſerved it at another ; allowing, as uſual, for the moon’s change of poſition. The reſult of his obſervations therefore was, that the ſurface of the river was not an inclined plane whoſe ſlope was leſ-ſened by the tide of flood at the mouth of the river, but that it was a waving line, and that the propagation of the tide up the river was nothing different from the propagation of any other wave. We may conceive it clearly, though imperfectly, in this way. Let the place be noted where the tide happens 12 hours later than at the mouth of the river. It is evident that there is alſo a tide at the very mouth at ⅝he ſame inſtant; and, ſince the ocean tide had withdrawn itſelf during the time that the former tide had proceeded ſo far up the river, and the tide of ebb is ſucceſſively felt above as well as the tide of flood, there muſt be a low water between theſe two high waters.</p><p>Newton had pointed out this curious ſact, and obſerved that the tide at London-Bridge, which is 43 feet above the ſea, is not the ſame with that at Graveſ-end, but the preceding tide (See <hi rend="italic">Phil. Tranſ 6q.) </hi>This will be more particularly infilled on in another place.</p><p>Not far from the head of the Maragnon, the Cordilleras fend off a branch to the north-eaſt, which reaches and ranges along the ſhore of the Mexican Gulf, and the Rio Grande de Sta Martha occupies the angle betweeen the ridges.</p><p>Another ridge ranges with interruptions along the eaſt coaſt of Terra Firma, ſo that the whole waters of this country are collected into the Oroonoko. In like manner the north and eaſt of Braſil are hemmed in by mountainous ridges, through which there is no conſiderable paſſage ; and the ground ſloping backwards, all The waters of this immenſe track are collected from both ſides by many conſiderable rivers into the great river Paraguay, or Rio de la Plata, which runs down the middle of this country for more than 1400 miles, and falls into the ſea through a vaſt mouth in latitude 35°'</p><p>Thus the whole of South America ſeems as if it had been formerly ſurrounded by a mound, and been a great baſon. The ground in the middle, where the Parama, the Madeira, and the Plata, take their riſe, is an immenſe marſh, uninhabitable for its exhalations, and quite impervious in its preſent ſtate.</p><p>The manner in which the continent of North America is watered, or rather drained, has alſo ſome peculiarities. By looking at the map, one will obſerve firſt of all a general diviſion of the whole of the beſt known part into two, by the valleys in which the beds of the river St Laurence and Miſſiſſippi are ſituated. The head of this is occupied by a ſingular ſeries of freſh water ſeas or lakes, viz. the lake Superior and Michigan, which empty themſelves into lake Huron by two cata-<hi rend="sup">,</hi>racts. This again runs into lake Erie by the river Detroiî, and the Erie pours its waters into the Ontario by the famous fall of Niagara, and from the On* tario proceeds the great river St Laurence.</p><p>The ground to the ſouth-weſt of the lakes Superior and Erie is ſomewhat lower, and the middle of the valley is occupied by the Miſſiſſippi and the Miſſoure, which receive on both ſides a number of ſmaller ſtreams, and having joined, proceed to the ſouth, under the name Miſſiſſippi. In latitude 37, this river receives into its bed the Ohio, a river of equal magnitude, and the Cherokee river, which drains all the country lying at the back of the United States, ſeparated from them by the ranges of the Apalachian mountains. The Miſſiſſippi is now one of the chief rivers on the globe, and proceeds due ſouth, till it falls into the Mexican bay through ſeveral ſhifting mouths, which greatly reſemble thoſe of the Danube and the Nile, having run above 1200 miles.</p><p>The elevated country between this bed of the Miſſiſſippi and St Laurence and the Atlantic ocean is drained on the eaſt ſide by a great number of rivers, ſome of which are very conſiderable, and of long courſe ; becauſe inſtead of being nearly at right angles to the coaſt, as in other countries, they are in a great meaſure parallel to it. This is more remarkably the caſe with Hudſon’s river, the Delaware, Patomacſk, Rapahanoc, &amp;c. Indeed the whole of North America ſeems to conſiſt of ribs or beams laid nearly parallel to each other from north to ſouth, and the rivers occupy the interſtices. All thoſe which empty themſelves into the bay of Mexico are parallel and almoſt perfectly ſtraight, unlike what are ſeen in other parts of the world. The weſtermoſt of them all, the North River, as it is named by the Spaniards, is nearly as long as the Miſſiſſippi.</p><p>We are very little informed as yet of the diſtribution of rivers on the north-weſt coaſt of America, or the courſe of thoſe which run into Hudſon’s and Baffin’s bay.</p><p>The Maragnon is undoubtedly the greateſt river in the world, both as to length of run and the vaſt body of water which it rolls along. The other great rivers ſucceed nearly in the following order.</p><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Maragnon,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Amur,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Senegal,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Oroonoko.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Nile,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Ganges,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>St Laurence,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Euphrates,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Hoangho,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Danube,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Rio de la Plata,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Don,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Yeniſey,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Indus,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Miſſiſſippi,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Dnieper,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Volga,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Duina,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Oby,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>&amp;c.</p></cell></row></table><p>We have been much aſſiſted in this account of the courſe of rivers, and their diſtribution over the globe, by a beautiful planiſphere or map of the world publiſhed by Mr Bode aſtronomer royal at Berlin. The rangea of mountains are there laid down with philoſophical diſ-cermaent and preciſion ; and we recommend it to the</p></body></text></TEI>