<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in France ; and was equally formidable ſor his genius as his ſword. In defence of the civil and religious rights of hiε party, he maintained three warθ againſt Louis XIII. The firſt, which terminated to the advantage of the Proteſtants, broke out when that prince wiſhed to eſtabliſh the Romiſh religion in Le Bearn : the ſecond, becauſe of the ſiege which Cardinal De Richlieu cauſed to be laid to Rochelle : and the third, when that place was beſieged a ſecond time. The conſequences of this war are ſufficiently known : Rochelle ſurrendered : and the duke de Rohan perceiving, that after the taking of this place, the majority of his party were endeavouring to make up matters with the court, ſucceeded in procuring for them a general peace in 1629, upon very honourable and advantageous terms. The only ſacriſice of importance which the Huguenots were obliged to make, was their fortifications ; which put it out of their power to renew the war. Some factious perſons, diſſatisſied with ſeeing their fortreſſes fall into their enemies hands, were ready to accuſe their general of having ſold them. This great man, undeſerving of ſuch odious ingratitude, preſented his breaſt to theſe enraged malcontents, and ſaid, “ Strike, ſtrike ! I wiſh to die by your hands, after I have hazarded my life in your ſervice.” The peace of 1629 having extinguiſh-ed the flame of civil war, the duke de Rohan, no longer of uſe to his party, and become diſagreeable at court, retired to Venice. There is a very particular anecdote of him, extracted from the Memoirs of the ducheſs of Rohan, Margaret of Bethune, daughter of the famous Sully. Whilſt the duke de Rohan was at Venice, a propoſal was made to him ſrom the Porte, that ſor 2co,ooo crowns, and an annual tribute of 20,000, the Grand Signior would give him the iſland of Cyprus, and fully inveſt him with the dignity and prerogatives of king. The duke was warmly inclined to comply with this propoſal, and to ſettle in the iſland the Proteſtant families of France and Germany. He negociated this buſineſs at the Porte by means of the intervention of the patriarch Cyril, with whom he had much correſpondence ; but different circumſtances, and in particular the death of the patriarch, occurred to break off the treaty. The republic of Venice choſe Rohan for their commander in chief againſt the Impe-rialiſls ; but Louis XΠL took him from the Venetians, and ſent him ambaſtador into Swiſſerland, and into the Griſons. He wiſhed to aſſiſt theſe people in bringing back La Valteline under their obedience, the revolt of which the Spaniards and Imperialiſts encouraged. Rohan, being declared general of the Griſons, after many victories, drove the German and Spaniſh troops entirely from La Valteline in 1633. He defeated the Spaniards again in 1636 at the banks of the lake of Come. France, not thinking it proper to withdraw her troops, the Griſons roſe up in arms, and the duke de Rohan, not ſatisfied with the conduct of the court, , entered into a ſpecial treaty with them the 28th March 1637. This hero, fearing the reſentment of cardinal de Richlieu, retired to Geneva, with a view to join his friend the duke of Saxe-Weimar, who wiſhed him to undertake the command of his army, then ready to engage the Imperialiſts near Rhinfield. Although he declined this honour, yet he took the command of the regiment of Naffau, with which he threw the enemy into confuſion ; but was himſelf wounded; February 28. l683<hi rend="sub">j</hi>,</p><lb/><p>and died of his wounds the 13th of April following, at the age of 59. He was interred May 27th, in the church of St Pierre in Geneva, where there is a magnificent monument of marble erected to his memory, having on it the moſt illuſtrious actions of his life. The duke de Rohan was one of the greateſt generals of his time, equal to the princes of Orange, and capable, like them, of ſettling a commonwealth ; but more zealous than they for religion, or at leaſt appearing to be ſo. He was vigilant and indefatigable, not allowing himſelf any pleaſures which might take off his attention from his neceſſary employments, and well qualified for being the head of a party ; a poſt very difficult to retain, and in which he had to fear equally from his enemies and his friends. It is in this light that Voltaire has viewed this illuſtrious character, when he compoſed' the following verſe :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Avec tous les talens le Ciel ſ avait ſait naître :</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Il agit en Heros ; en Sage il écrivit.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Il fut mime grand homme en combattant ſon Maître, Et plus grand lorſqu’il le ſervit.</hi></p><p>His military virtues were much heightened by the ſweetneſs of his diſpoſition, his affable and courteous manners, and by a generoſity which had few examples. Neither ambition, pride, nor a view of gain, could ever be traced in his character. He was wont to ſay, that “ true glory and a zeal for the public good never dwelt where ſelf-intereſt reigned.” Rohan had always a particular regard for Henry the Fourth : “ Truly (ſaid he, ſometimes after the death of that prince) when I think of him, my heart is ready to break. A wound received in his preſence w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ould have afforded me more ſatisſaction than now to gain a battle. I would have valued an encomium from him in this art, of which he was the greateſt maſter of his time, more than than the united praiſes of all the commanders now living.” He wrote ſeveral intereſting performances : 1. The Intereſts of Princes, printed at Cologne in 1666, in I2mo: in which work he fully examines- the public intereſts of all the princes of Europe. 2. The Perfect General, or an abridgement of the wars from Casſar’s Commentaries, in 12mo. In this he makes it appear, that a knowledgeof the tactics of the ancients might be of much uſe to the moderns. 3. A Treatiſe on the Corruption of the ancient Militia. 4. A Treatiſe on the Government of the Thirteen∙ Provinces. 5. Memoirs; the beſt edition of which is in 2 vols I2mo. . fiey contain the hiſtory of France from 1610. to 1C29.    6. A</p><p>Collection of ſome Political Diſcourſes on State Affairs, from 1612 to 1629, 8vo, Paris, 1644, 1693, 1755 5 with the Memoirs and Letters of Henry Duke de Ro</p><p>han relative to the war of La Valteline, 3 vols 12mo&gt; Geneva, x 757. This was the firſt edition which appeared of theſe curious memoirs : We owe it to the great attention and diligence of M. le Baron de Zurlauben, who publiſhed them from different authentic manuſeripts. He likewiſe ornamented this edition with geographical, hiſtorical, and genealogical notes, and a preface, which contains an abridged, but highly intereſting life, of the duke de Rohan, author of the memoirs. The abbé Pérau has alſo written a life of him, which occupies the 2 iff and 22d volumes of the Hiſtory of the Illuſtrious Men of France. Some want of ſpirit might be excuſed in the detail of wars finiſhed upwards of 14q&gt;</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>