<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pride. Rollin ſpoke pretty well; but he had a greater readineſs of writing than ſpeakingt; and much more ſa-tisfaction might be derived from his works than from his ∙co∙nveι ſation. His name became famous throughout Europe ; ſeveral princes ſought the honour of his friendſhip. The duke of Cumberland and the prince-royal of Pruſſia (afterwards king) were among the lift of his admirers. This monarch honoured him with ſeveral letters ; in one of which he pays him the following compliment, “ Men of your character are fit companions for kings.” As to the literary merit of this author, it was, we ſuſpect, too much extolled in his own time, and has been too much undervalued in ours.</p><p>ROLLING, the motion by which a ſhip rocks from ſide to ſide like a cradle, occaſioned by the agitation of the waves.</p><p>Rolling, therefore, is a ſort of revolution about an imaginary axis paſſing through the centre of gravity of a ſhip : ſo that the nearer the centre of gravity is to the keel, the more violent will be the rolling motion ; becauſe the centre about which the vibrations are made is placed ſo low in the bottom, that the reſiſtance made by the keel to the volume of water which it diſplaces in rolling, bears very little proportion to the force of the vibration above the centre of gravity, tlre radius of which extends as high as the maſt-heads.</p><p>But if the centre of gravity is placed higher above -the keel, the radius of vibration will not only be diminiſhed, but an additional force to oppoſe the motion of rolling will be. communicated to that part of the ſhip’s bottom which is below the centre of gravity.</p><p>So far as relates to the effect of rolling, when produced by the quality or ſtowage of the ballaſt, and to the manner by which it may be prevented, viz. a change of the quantity or diſpoſition of the ballaſt, we ſliall endeavo-ur to explain under the article Trim. It may, however, be neceſſary to remark, that the conſtruction of the ſhip’s bottom may alſo contribute to ſtiminiſh this movement conſiderably.</p><p>Many fatal diſaſters have happened to ſhips ariſing ſrom a violent rolling ; as the loſs of the maſts, looſen-ing of the cannon, and ſtraining violently on the decks and ſides, ſo as to weaken the ſhip to a great degree. See Pitching.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RoLLiNG-Preſs.</hi>  See <hi rend="italic">Rolling- </hi><hi rend="italic">PRESS.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RoLLiNG-Tackle,</hi>  a pulley or purchaſe faſtened to that part of a ſail-yard which is to the windward of the mail, in order to confine the yard cloſe dow<hi rend="sup">,</hi>n to the leeward when tlre ſail is furled.</p><p>It is uſed to prevent the yard from having a great friction againſt the maſt in a high ſea, which would be equally pernicious to both.</p><p>ROLLO, the conqueror of Normandy, was a Norwegian duke, baniſhed from his country by Harold Harfagre, who conquered Norway in 870, on account -of the piracies he exerciſed. He firſt retired with his fleet among the iſlands of the Hebrides to the north-weſt of Scotland, whither the flower of the Norwegian nöbility had fled for refuge «ver ſince Harold had become maſter of the whole kingdom. He was there received with open arms by thoſe warriors, who, eager for conq,ueft and revenge, waited only for a chief to undertake ſome glorious enterpriſe. Rollo ſetting himſelf at their head, and ſeeing his power formidable, ſailed towards England, which had been long as it were a field open on all ſides ito the violence of the northern nations. But the great Alfred had ſome years before eſtabliſhed ſuch order in his part of the iſland, that Rollo, after ſeveral fruitleſs attempts, de-ſpaired of forming there ſuch a ſettlement as ſhould make him amends for the loſs of his own country. He pretended, therefore, to have had a ſupematural dream, which promiſed him a glorious fortune in France, and which ſerved at leaſt to ſupport the ardour of his followers. The weakntſs of die government in that; kingdom, and the confuſion in which it was involved, were ſtill moιe perſuaſive reaſons to inſure them of ſucceſs. Having therefore failed up the Seine to Rouen, he immediately took that capital of the province, then called <hi rend="italic">Neu/lria,</hi>  and making it his magazine of arms, he advanced up to Paris, to which he laid ſiege in form. This war at length ended in the entire cefiiαn of Neuſtria, which Charles the Simple was obliged to give up to Rollo and his Normans in order to purchaſe a peace. Rollo received it in perpetuity to himſelf and his poſterity, as a feudal duchy dependant on the crown of France. A deſcription of the interview between Charles and this new duke gives us a curious picture of the manners of theſe Normans (as they were called by foreigners) ; for the latter would not take the oath of fealty to his ſovereign lord any other way than by placing his hands within thoſe of the king ; and abſolutely refiiſed to kiſs his feet, as cuſtom then required. It was with great difficulty he was prevailed on to let one of his warriors perform this ceremony in his ſtead ; but the officer to whom Rollo deputed, this ſervice, ſuddenl.y raiſed the king’s foot ſo high, that he overturned him on his back ; a piece of rudeneſs which was only laughed at; to ſuch a degree were the Normans feared, and Charles deſpiſed.</p><p>Soon after* Rollo was perſuaded to embrace Chriſti-anity, and hc was baptized with much ceremony by the archbiſhop of Rouen in the cathedral of that city. As foθH as he ſaw himſelf in full poſſeſſion of Normandy, he exhibited ſuch virtues as rendered the province happy, and deſerved to make his former outrages forgotten. Religious, wiſe, and liberal, this captain of pirates became, after Alfred, the greateſt and moſt humane prince of his time-    '    <hi rend="sub">;</hi></p><p>ROMAN, in general, ſomething belonging to the city of Rome. See Rome.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">King of the ROMANS, in modern hiſtory, is a prince elected to be ſucceſſor to the reigning emperor of Germany.</hi></p><p>ROMANCE, in matters of literature, a fabulous relation of certain adventures deſigned for the entertainment and inſtruction of the readers, and differing from the <hi rend="italic">novel,</hi>as it always exhibits actions great, dangerous, and generally extravagant. Many authors of the firſt name have written on the ancient <hi rend="italic">romance.</hi>  It has exerciſed the pen of Hurd, of Warburtcn, and of fomé ladies, who have not thought it any derogation to the ſenſibility of their ſex to unite antiquarian reſearch with the cultivation of the <hi rend="italic">belles lettres.</hi>  We have not, however, ſeen anywhere ſo conciſe, jtiſt, and elegant an account of the origin and progreſs of <hi rend="italic">romances</hi>  as in H’lſraeli’s Curioſities of Literature. “ Romance (ſays this writer) has been elegantly defined the offspring of fiction and love. Men of learning have amuſed themſelves with tracing the epoeha of romances. In thia</p></body></text></TEI>