<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>all-fours, and took a ſhort repoſe upon a wretched pallet, that had been prepared for his reception. Being preſſed by hunger, he demanded ſomewhat to eat : they brought him a piece of brown bread, which he refuſed; but he, drank a little water. During this interval, the ſenate finding the prætorian guards had taken part with Galba, declared him emperor, and condemned Nero to die <hi rend="italic">more majorum ;</hi>  that is, “ according to the rigour of the ancient laws,” Theſe dreadful tidings were quickly brought by one of Phaon’s ſlaves from the city, while Nero yet continued lingering between his hopes and his fears. When he was told of the reſolution of the ſenate againſt him, he aſhed the meſſenger what he meant by being puniſhed “ according to the rigour of the ancient laws ?” To this he was anſwered, that the criminal was to be ſtripped naked, his head was to be fixed in a pillory, and in that poſture he was to be ſcourged to death. Nero was ſo terrified at this, that he ſeized two poniards which he had brought with him, and examining their points, returned them to their ſheaths, ſaying, that the fatal moment was not yet arrived. However, he had little time to ſpare ; for the ſoldiers who had been ſent in purſuit of him were juſt then approaching the houſe : wherefore hearing the ſound of the horſe’s feet, he ſet a dagger to his throat, with which, by the aſſiſtance of Epaphroditus, his freedman and ſecretary, he gave himſelf a mortal wound. He was dot quite dead when one of the centurions entering the room, and pretending he came to his relief, attempted to ſtop the blood with his cloak. But Nero, regarding him with a ſtern countenance, ſaid, “ It is now too late. Is this your fidelity?”—∙ Upon which, with his eyes fixed, and frightfully ſtaring, he expired, in the 32d year of his age, and the 14th of his reign.</p><p>Galba was.72 years old when he was' declared emperor, and was then in Spain with his legions. However, he ſoon ſound that his being raiſed to the throne was but an inlet to ne*<hi rend="sup">,</hi> disquietudes. His firſt embarraſſment aroſe from a diſorder in his own army ; for upon his approaching the camp, one of the wings of horſe repenting of their choice, prepared to revolt, and he found it no eaſy matter to reconcile them to their duty, h e alſo narrowly eſcaped aſſaſſination from ſome ſlaves, who were preſented to him by one of Nero’s freedmen with that intent. The death of Vindex alſo ſerved to add not a little to his diſquietudes ; ſo that, upon his very entrance into the empire, he had ſome thoughts of putting an end to his own liſe. But hearing from Rome that Nero was dead, and the empire transferred to him, he immediately aſſumed the title and enſigns of command. In his journey towards Rome he was met by Rufus Virginius, who, finding the ſenate had decreed him the government, came to yield him obedience. This general had more than once refuſed the empire himſelf, which was offered him by his ſoldiers ; alleging, that the ſenate alone had the diſpoſal of it, and from them only he would accept the honour.</p><p>Galba having been brought to the empire by means of his army, was at the ſame time willing to ſuppreſs their power to commit any future diſturbance. His firſt approach to Rome was attended with one of thoſe rigorous ſtrokes of juſtice which ought rather to be denominated <hi rend="italic">cruelty</hi>  than any thing elſe. A body of ma-</p><lb/><p>dens, with a reſolution of flying into Egypt. He accordingly diſpatched the freedmen, in which he had the moſt confidence, to prepare a fleet at Oſtia ; and in the meanwhile founded, in perſon, the tribunes and centurions of the guard, to know if they were willing to ſhare his fortunes. But they all excuſed themſelves, under divers pretexts. One of them had the boldneſs to anſwer him by part of a line from Virgil : <hi rend="italic">Ulque αdeone miſerum eft mori ?</hi>  “ Is death then ſuch a misfortune ?” Thus deſtitute of every reſource, all the expedients that cowardice, revenge, or terror could produce, took place in his mind by turns. He at one time reſolved to take refuge among the Parthians ; at another, to deliver himſelf up to the mercy of the inſurgents : one while, he determined to mount the roſtrum, to aik pardon for what was paſt, and to conclude with promiſes of amendment for the future. With theſe gloomy deliberations he went to bed ; but waking about midnight, he was ſurpriſed to find his guards had left him. The prætorian ſoldiers, in fact, having been corrupted by their commander, had retired to their camp, and proclaimed Galba emperor. Nero immediately ſent for his friends to deliberate upon his preſent exigence ; but his friends alſo forſeok him. He went in perſon from houſe to houſe ; but all the doors were ſhut againſt him, and none were found to anſwer his inquiries. While he was purſuing this inquiry, his very domeſtics followed the general defection ; and having plundered his apartment, eſeaped different ways. Being now reduced to deſperation, he defιred that one of his favourite gladiators might come and diſpatch him : but even in this requeſt there was none found to obey. “ Alas! (cried he) have I neither friend nor enemy ?” And then running deſperately forth, he ſeemed reſolved to plunge headlong into the Tiber. But juſt then his courage beginning to fail him, he made a ſudden ſtop, as if willing to recollect his reaſon ; and aſked for ſome ſecret place, where he might re-aſſume his courage, and meet death with becoming fortitude. In this diſtreſs, Phaon, one of his freedmen, offered him his country-houſe, at about four miles diſtant, where he might for ſome time remain concealed. Nero accepted his offer ; and, half-dreſſed as he was, with his head covered, and hiding his face with an handkerchief, he mounted on horſeback, attended by four of his domeſtics, of whom the wretched Sporus was one. His journey, though quite ſhort, was crowded with adventures. Round him he heard nothing but confuſed noiſes from the camp, and the cries of the ſoldiers, imprecating a thouſand evils upon his head. A paffenger, meeting him on the way, cried, *<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  There go men in purſuit of Nero.” Another alked him, if there was any news of Nero in the city ? His horſe taking fright at a dead body that lay near the road, he dropped his handkerchief ; and a ſoldier that was near, addreſſed him by name. He now therefore quitted his horſe, and forſaking the highway, entered a thicket that led towards the back part of Phaon’s houſe, through which he crept, making the beſt of his way among the reeds and brambles, with which the place was overgrown. When he was arrived at the back part of the houſe, while he was waiting till there ſhould be a breach made in the wall, he took up ſome water in the hollow of his hands from a pool to drink ; ſaying, " To this liquor is Nero reduced.” When the hole Was made large enough to admit him, he crept in upon</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>