<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">qu'athee. ”</hi>  He was at the utmoſt pains to bring into the court every man of eminent talents in gay literature, and of licentious principles in religion and morals, whom he employed in corrupting the minds of the young courtiers, and giving them favourable impreſſions of the indulgence which they might expect from him when he ſhould have the ſole direction of affairs. This ſyſtem was moſt aſſiduouſly purſued during that moſt licentious</p><p>and diſſolute adminiſtration of the regent Orleans, who was himſelf a ſpecimen of elegant ſenſuality not to be matched in the annals of the world. Long before the preſent day, all thinking men in France ſaw the mummery of the church, and groaned under its oppreſſion; and having no other notions of religion but what they were accuſtomed to from their cradle, no wonder that they diſcarded the principle along with thoſe deteſtable acceſſories. The nation, therefore, being greedy of flattery, buoyed up by a ſelf-conceit, in which even the ancient Greeks have not ſurpaſſed them, and having been thus ſtudiouſly corrupted, and long immerſed in a luxurious and refined ſenſuality, of which we in this nation have not yet acquired an adequate idea, was fully prepared for feeling all the effects of this fanaticiſm of NATURALISM.</p><p>But this idolatry we abhor. It ſhocks our reaſon; and, although it may at firſt ſeem to flatter our thought-leſs vanity, it really debaſes our nature, by taking ſrom us our intellectual kindred to the mind of perfect wiſ-dom. Who would not feel pleaſure in being the relation of a Bacon, of a Newton, or would thank the man who detected the falſe pedigree? It puts an end to our fond hopes, that the day will come when we ſhall ſurpaſs in underſtanding, in worth, and in felicity, the wiſeſt, the belt, and the moſt fortunate of our ſpecies.</p><p>We cannot but lament the appearances, however faint, of this ſanaticiſm among ourſelves. We cannot but obſerve, that ſome of the hired directors of public opinion in matters of taſte and ſcience have of late ſhow-ed a wonderful tenderneſs for the bold and licentious opinions in religion, morals, and politics, which are daily pouring in upon us from the preſſes of Paris. Perhaps they may be incited to this conduct by the ſucceſs of their brother journaliſts in that profligate metropolis; and may hope to be one day, like them, the directors of the public councils and the ſovereigns of the nation. We truſt, however, that the better part of the reflecting natives of Britain will not allow themſelves to be ſneered out of their higheſt boaſt and their ſweeteſt comforts; namely, that they are not the chance fragments of a fatal chaos, but the beautiful productions</p><lb/><p>of a wonderful Artiſt, and the darling objects of his care: and we aſſure ourſelves that ten thouſands of our countrymen are ready to rally under the banners of true religion and found philoſophy, and to follow the ſteps of a Clarke, a Butler, a Newton, and a Boyle, who ſo eminently diſtinguiſhed themſelves in the cauſe of Nature’s God.</p><p>By nature, then, we mean that admirable ſyſtem of general laws, by which the adored Author and Governor of the univerſe has thought fit to connect the various parts of this wonderful and goodly frame of things, and to regulate all their operations.</p><p>We are not afraid of continually appealing to the laws of nature: and as we have already obſerved in the article Philosophy, we conſider theſe general laws as the moſt magnificent diſplays of Infinite Wiſ-dom, and the contemplation of them as the moſt cheering employment of our underſtandings.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Igneus eſt illis vigor et c</hi><hi rend="italic">æ</hi><hi rend="italic">leſtis origo Seminibus.</hi></p><p>At the fame time we deſpiſe the cold-hearted philoſo-pher who Hops ſhort here, and is ſatisfied (perhaps inwardly pleaſed) that he has completely accounted for every thing by the laws of unchanging nature; and we<hi rend="italic"> </hi>ſuſpect that this philoſopher would analyſe with the ſame frigid ingenuity, and explain by irreſiſtible,<hi rend="italic"> </hi>the tender attachment of her whoſe breaſt he ſucked, and who by many anxious and ſleepleſs nights preſerved alive the puling infant. But let us rather liſten to the words of him who was the moſt ſagacious obſerver and the moſt faithful interpreter of nature’s laws, our iſtuſtri-ous countryman Sir Iſaac Newton. He ſays,</p><p>“Elegantiſſima hæcce rerumcompages non niſi conſilio et <hi rend="italic">dominio</hi>  entis ſapientiſſimi et potentiſſimi oriri potuit, Omnia, ſimili conſtructa conſilio, ſuberunt <hi rend="italic">unius</hi>  domi-nio. Hic omnia regit, non ut <hi rend="italic">anima mundi,</hi>  ſed ut uni-verſorum dominus. Propter dominium ſuum dominus deus, nuncupatur. Deus ad ſervientes ref-picit, et <hi rend="italic">deitas</hi>  eſt dominatio dei, non in corpus proprium, uti ſentiunt quibus deus eſt natura feu anima mun-di, ſed in ſervos. Deus ſummus eſt ens eternum, infinitum, abſolute perfectum. Ens utcunque perfectum, at ſine dominio, non eſt dominus deus.</p><p>“ Hunc cognoſcimus, ſolummodo per proprietates ejus et attributa. Attribuuntur ut ex phenomenis dignoſcuntur. Phenomena ſunt ſapientiſſimæ et opti-mæ rerum flructuræ, atque cauſæ finales. —Hunc admi-ramur ob perfectiones; hunc veneramur et colimus ob dominium” @@(b).</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b) Our readers will probably be pleaſed with the following liſt of authors who have treated profeſſedly of the motions of rivers: Guglielmini </hi><hi rend="italic">De Fluviis et Caſtellis Aquarurn —Danubius Illuſtratus;</hi>  Grandi <hi rend="italic">De Caſtellis;</hi>  Zendrini <hi rend="italic">De Motu Aquarurn;</hi>  Friſius <hi rend="italic">de Fluviis;</hi>  Lecchi <hi rend="italic">Idroſtatica i Idraulica;</hi>  Michelotti <hi rend="italic">Sperrinze I-drauliche;</hi>  Belidor’s <hi rend="italic">Architecture Hydraulique;</hi>  Boſſut <hi rend="italic">Hydrodynamique;</hi>  Buat <hi rend="italic">Hydraulique;</hi>  Silberſchlag <hi rend="italic">Theorie des Fleuves; Lettres de</hi>  M. L’Epinaſſe <hi rend="italic">au P. Friſi touchant ſa Theorie des Fleuves; Tableau des principales Rivieres du Monde, par</hi>  Genetté; Stevins <hi rend="italic">ſur les Ecluſes; Traité des Ecluſes, par</hi>  Boulard, <hi rend="italic">qui a remporté le Prix de l' Acad. de Lyons;</hi>  Bleiſwyck <hi rend="italic">Diſſertatio de Aggeribus;</hi>  Boſſut <hi rend="italic">et</hi>  Viallet <hi rend="italic">ſur la Conſtruction des Digues;</hi>  Stevin <hi rend="italic">Hydroſtatica;</hi>  Tielman van der Horit <hi rend="italic">Theatrurn Machinarum Univerſale;</hi>  De la Lande <hi rend="italic">ſur les Canaux de Navigation;</hi>  Racolta di Autori <hi rend="italic">chi Trattano del Mοtο dell' Acque,</hi>  3 tom. 4to, Firenza 1723. —This moſt valuable collection contains the writings of Archimedes, Albizi, Galileo, Caſtelli, Michelini, Borelli, Montanari, Viviani, Caſſini, Guglielmini, Grandi, Manfredi, Picard, and Narduci; and an account of the numberleſs works which have been carried on in the embankment of the Po.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>