<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>it decreaſes in the different filaments, from the axis or moſt rapid filament to the border ; and the connection of this with the mean velocity, which is expreſſed by our formula. 3√, Having acquired ſome diſtinct notions of this, we ſhall be able to ſee the manner in which undiſturbed nature works in forming the beds of our rivers, the ſorms which ſhe affects, and which we muſt imitate in all their local modifications, if we would ſecure that permanency which is the evident aim of all her operations. We ſhall here learn the mutual action of the current and its bed, and the circumſtances which enſure the ſtability of both. Theſe we may call the <hi rend="italic">regimen</hi>  or the <hi rend="italic">confirmation</hi>  of the ſtream, and may ſay that it is <hi rend="italic">in regimen,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">in confirmation.</hi>  This has a relation, not to the dimenſioris and the ſtope alone, or to the accelerating force and the reſiſtance ariſing from mere inertia ; it reſpects immediately the tenacity of the bed, and is different from <hi rend="italic">the train.</hi></p><p>4<hi rend="italic">th,</hi>  Theſe pieces of information will explain the deviation of rivers from the rectilineal courſe ; the reſiſtance occaſioned by theſe deviations ; and the circumſtan-ees on which the regimen of a winding ſtream depends.</p><p>ÿ I. <hi rend="italic">Of the Forms of the Channel.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The numerator of the fraction which expreſſes the velocity of a river in train has √7 for one of its factors. 'Γhat form, thereſore, is moſt favourable to the motion which gives the greateſt value to what we have called the hydraulic mean depth </hi><hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  This is the prerogative of the ſemicircle, and here <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is equal to half the radius ; and all other figures of the ſame area are the more favourable, as they approach nearer to a ſemicircle.- This is the form, therefore, of all conduit pipes, and ſhould be taken for aqueducts which are built of maſonry. Eaſe and accuracy of execution, however, have made engineers prefer a rectangular form ; but neither of theſe will do for a channel formed out of the ground. W e ſhall ſoon ſee that the ſemicircle is incompatible with a regimen ; and, if we proceed through the regular polygons, we ſhall find that the half hexagon is the only one which has any pretentions to a regimen ; yet experience ſhows us, that even its banks are too ſteep for almoſt any foil. A dry earthen bank, not bound together by graſs roots, will hardly ſtand with a ſlope of 45 degrees; and a canal which conveys running waters will not ſtand with this ſlope. Banks whoſe baſe is to their height as 4 to 3 will ſtand very well in moiſt foils, and this is a ſlope very uſually given. This form is even affected in the ſpontaneous operations of nature, in the channels which ſhe digs for the rills and rivulets in the higher and ſteeper grounds.</p><p>This form has ſome mathematical and mechanical properties which intitle it to ſome further notice. Let ABEC (fig. ιι.) be ſuch a trapezium, and AHGC the rectangle of equal width and depth. Biſect HB and EG by the verticals FD and KI, and draw the verticals <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  B, <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  E. Becauſe AH : HB= 3 :4, we have AB = 5, andBD=2, and FD 3, and BDſt-DF= BA. From theſe premiſſes it follows, that the trapezium ABEC has the ſame area with the rectangle; for HB being biſected in D, the triangles ACF, BCD are equal. Alſo the border ABEC, which is touched by the paſſing ſtream, is equal to FDIK. Therefore the mean depth, which is the quotient of the area divided by the border, is the ſame in both j and this 14the</p><p>caſe, whatever is the width BE at the bottom, or even though there be no rectangle ſuch as <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  BEe interpoſed between the ſlant ſides.</p><p>Of all rectangles, that whoſe breadth is twice the height, or which is half of a ſquare, gives the greateſt mean depth. If, therefore, FK be double of&lt;FD, the trapezium ABEC, which has the ſame area, will have the largeſt mean depth of any ſuch trapezium, and will be the belt form of a channel for conveying running waters. In this caſe, we have AC = 10, AH=</p><p>3, and BE~2. Or we may ſay that the bell form is a trapezium, whoſe bottom width is -∣- of the depth, and whoſe extreme width is ∙<hi rend="sup">i</hi><hi rend="sub">j</hi>-. This form approaches very near to that which the torrents in the hills naturally dig for themſelves in uniform ground, where their action is not checked by ſtones which they lay bare, or which they depoſit in their courſe. This ſhows us, and it will be fully confirmed by and by, that the channel of a river is not a fortuitous thing, but has a relation to the conſiſtency of the foil and velocity of the ſtream.</p><p>A rectangle, whoſe breadth is y of the depth of water, will therefore have the ſame mean depth with a. triangle whoſe ſurſace width is ∣ of its vertical depth ; for this is the dimenſions when the rectangle <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  BEe is taken away.</p><p>Let A be the area of the ſection of any channel, <hi rend="italic">τυ </hi>its width (when rectangular), and <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  its depth of water» Then what we have called its mean depth, or <hi rend="italic">d<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  will ſhe</p><p>———~l<hi rend="sup">iυ</hi>A, Or if <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  expreſſes the ratio of the</p><p>W+2Ä w+2i    <hi rend="sup">r</hi></p><p>width to the depth of a rectangular bed ; that is, if</p><p>w</p><p><hi rend="italic">q~~r,</hi>  we have <hi rend="sup">a ver</hi>y ſimple and ready expreſſion for</p><p>the mean depth, either from the width or depth. For</p><p><hi rend="italic">, <hi rend="sup">r</hi>zυ    , qh</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">d —-</hi>  , or <hi rend="italic">d = ——∙</hi></p><p>7+2    <hi rend="italic">q+2</hi></p><p>Therefore, if the depth were infinite, and the width</p><p>finite, we ſhould have <hi rend="italic">d-~∙,</hi>  or if the width be infi-2</p><p>nite, and the depth finite, we have <hi rend="italic">d ~h.</hi>  And theſe are the limits of the values of <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  ; and therefore, in rivers whoſe width is always great in compariſon of the depth, we may without much error take their real depth for their hydraulic mean depth. Hence we derive a rule of eaſy recollection, and which will at ail times give us a very near eſtimate of the velocity and expence of a running ſtream, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>  that <hi rend="italic">the velocities are nearly as the ſqaare roots of the depths.</hi>  We find this confirmed by many experiments of Michelotti.</p><p>Alſo, when we are allowed to ſuppoſe this ratio of the velocities and depths, that is, in a rectangular canal of great breadth and ſmall depth, we ſhall have the quantities diſcharged nearly in the proportion of the cubes of the velocities. For the quantity diſcharged <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is as., the velocity and area jointly, that is, as the height and velocity jointly, becauſe when the width is the ſame the area is as the height. Therefore, we have <hi rend="italic">d == h v.-</hi>But, by the above remark, <hi rend="italic">h = v<hi rend="sup">i</hi>.</hi>  Therefore, <hi rend="italic">d == v<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi>  ; and this is confirmed by the experiments of Boſſut, vol. ii. 236. Alſo, becauſe <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is as <hi rend="italic">v h<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  when <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  is conſtant, and by the above remark -(allowable when <hi rend="italic">&lt;ιυ</hi>  is very great in proportion to <hi rend="italic">h} v</hi>  is as √<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  we have <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">h </hi>∖<hi rend="italic">∕ h<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  or Z&gt;∣, or the ſquares of the diſcharges</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>