<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The Romans now congratulated themſelves on their happy deliverance ſrom tyranny. However, as Tarquin had by his policy procured himſelf many friends abroad, theſe now became enemies to the Roman name; and, by the defection of their allies, the Roman dominions were left in much the ſame ſtate as they had been in the time of Romulus. The territory of Rome had always been confined to a very narrow’ compaſs. Though almoſt conſtantly victorious in war for 243 years, they had not yet gained land enough to ſupply their city with proviſions. The main ſtrength of the ſtate lay in the number of the citizens of Rome ; which the cuſtom of tranſplanting the inhabitants of the conquered cities thither had ſo prodigiouſly increaſed, that it put the Romans in a condition of uſurping the authority over other nations, the moſt inconſiderable of which had an extent of territory far exceeding theirs. By frequent depredations and incurſions they ſo haraſſed the petty ſtates of Latium and Hetruria, that many of them were conſtrained to enter into treaties with Rome, by which they obliged themſelves to furniſh her with auxiliaries whenever ſhe ſhould be pleaſed to invade and pillage the lands of her other neighbours. Submiſſions of this kind the Romans called <hi rend="italic">making alliances</hi>  with them, and theſe uſeful alliances ſupplied the want of a larger territory ; but now, upon the change of her government, all the allies of Rome forſeok her at once, and either ſtood neuter, or eſpouſed the cauſe of the baniſhed king; ſo that ſhe was now obliged to maintain her liberties as ſhe beſt might.</p><p>The new conſuls in the mean time took the moſt effectual methods they could for ſecuring the liberties of the republic. The army which had been employed in the ſiege of Ardea marched home under the conduct of Herminius and Horatius, who concluded a truce with the Ardeates for 15 years. The conſuls then again aſtembled the people by centuries, and had the 'decree of Tarquin’s baniſhment confirmed ; a <hi rend="italic">rex ſacrorum</hi>  was elected to preſide at the ſacrifices, and many of the laws of Servius Tullius were revived, to the great joy of the people, who were thus reſtored to their ancient right of voting in all important affairs. Tarquin, however, reſolved not to part with his kingdom on ſuch eaſy terms. Having wandered ſrom city to city in order to move compaſſion, he at length made Tarquinii the ſeat of his reſidence ; where he engaged the inhabitants to ſend an embaſſy to Rome, with a modeſt, ſubmiſſive letter from himſelf, directed to the</p><p>Roman people. The ambaſſadors repreſented in ſuch ſtrong terms to the ſenate how reaſonable it was to let the king be heard before he w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as condemned, and the danger which threatened the ſtate from the neighbouring powers if that common juſtice were refuſed, that the conſiſts inclined to bring theſe agents before the people, and to leave the deciſion thereof to the curiae ; but Valerius, who had been very active in the revolution, ſtrenuouſly oppoſed this, and by his influence in the ſenate got it prevented. As that illuſtrious body had been greatly thinned by the murders committed by Tarquin, new members were elected from among the knights, and the ancient number of 300 again completed. The old ſenators had been called<hi rend="italic">patres</hi>  or “ fathers ;” and as the names of the new oneswere now written on the ſame roll, the whole body received the name of <hi rend="italic">patres conſcriptt.</hi></p><p>The old king was not to be foiled by a ſingle at</p><lb/><p>tempt. He prevailed on the inhabitants of Tarquinii to ſend a ſecond embaſſy to Rome, under pretence of demanding the eſtates of the exiles, but with private inſtructions to get the conſuls aſſaſſinated. The reſtoration of the eſtates of the exiles was oppoſed by Brutus, but Collatinus was for complying with it ; whereupon Brutus accuſed his colleague of treachery, and of a deſign to bring back the tyrant. The matter was then referred to the people, where it was carried by one vote in favour of the Tarquins. But whilſt the people were employed in loading carriages with the effects of the exiles, and in felling what could not be carried off, the ambaſſadors found means to draw ſome of the neareſt relations of the conſuls into a plot with them. Theſe were three young noblemen of the Aquilian family (the ſons of Collatinus’s ſiſter), and two of the Vitëllii (whoſe ſiſter Brutus had married) ; and theſe laſt engaged Titus and Tiberius, the two ſons of Brutus, in the ſame conſpiracy. They all bound themſelves by ſolemn oaths, with the dreadful ceremony of drinking the blood of a murdered man and touching his entrails. They met at the houſe of the Aquilii, where they wrote letters to Tarquin and gave them to the ambaf~ ſadors. But though they uſed all imaginable precaution, their proceedings were overheard by one Vindi-cius a ſlave, who immediately communicated the whole to Valerius ; upon which all the criminals were apprehended. Brutus ſtood judge over his own ſons ; and, notwithſtanding the interceſſion of the whole aſſembly, and the tears and lamentations of his children, commanded them to be beheaded-; nor would he depart till he ſaw the execution of the ſentence. Having performed this piece of heroic barbarity, he quitted the tribunal, and left Collatinus to perform the reſt. Collatinus, however, being inclined to ſpare his nephews, allowed them a day to clear themſelves ; and cauſed Vindicius, the only witneſs againſt them, to be delivered up to his maſters. This rouſed the indignation of the people in general, eſpecially of Valerius, who had promiſed to protect the witneſs, and therefore he refuſed to deliver him up to the lictors. The multitude called aloud for Brutus to return ; which when he had done, he told them that he had executed his two ſons in conſequence of his own paternal authority over them, but that it belonged to the people to determine the fate of the reſt. Accordingly, by a decree of the curiæ, all the delinquents ſuffered as traitors except the ambaſſadors, who were ſpared out of reſpect to their character. The ſlave Vindicius had his liberty granted</p><p>him; and was preſented with 25,00? aies of braſs, in value about L.,8o : 14 : 7 of our money. The decree for reſtoring the eſtates of the exiled Tarquins was annulled, their palaces were deſtroyed, and their lands divided among the indigent people. The public only 1 etained a piece of ground, near the Campus Martius? which the king had uſurped. This they conſecrated: to Mars, and it afterwards became a common field where the Roman youth exerciſed themſelves in running and wreſtling. But after this conſecration, the ſuperſtitious Romans ſcrupled to uſe the corn which they found there ready reaped to their hands : ſo that&gt;, with ſome trees, it was thrown into the Tiber ; and. the water being low, it flopped in the middle of the river, and began to form a fine iſland named afterward» <hi rend="italic">Inſula Sacra.</hi></p><p>The behaviour of Brutus towards his two ſons ſtruck.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>