<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ROCHEFOUCAULT (Francis earl oſ), deſcend-ed of an illuſtrious family, next in dignity to that of the ſovereigns, was chamberlain to king Charles VIII. and Louis XII. His character at court was admired as obliging, generous, upright, and fincere. In 1494 he ſtood godfather to Francis I. who, when he came to the throne, continued to pay great reſpect to that ſpi-ritual relation. He made him his chamberlain in ordinary, and erected, in 1515, the barony of Rochefoucault into an earldom; and, in his writ of erection, obſerves, that he did this in memory of the great, honourable, highly uſeful, and commendable ſervices which the ſaid Francis had done to his predeceſſors, to the crown of France, and to himſelf. The earl of Rochefoucault died in 1517, leaving behind him an illuſtrious memory, and a character univerſally reſpected. Since his time all the eldeſt ſons of that family have taken the name of Francis.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rochefoucault (Francis duke de la), prince of Marſillac, governor of Poitou, was born in 1603.</hi></p><p>-—He was the ſon of Francis, the firſt duke of Rocheſoucault, and was diſtinguiſhed equally by his courage and his wit. Theſe ſhining qualities endeared him to all the nobility at court, who were ambitious of decorating themſelves at once with the laurels of Mars and of Apollo. He wrote two excellent works ; the one a book of Maxims, which M. de Voltaire ſays has contributed more than any thing elſe to form the taſte of the French nation ; and the other, Memoirs of the Regency of Queen Anne of Auſtria. It was partly at the inſtigation of the beautiful ducheſs de Longueville, to whom he had been long attached, that the duke de Rochefoucault engaged in the civil wars, in which he ſignalized himſelf particularly at the battle of &gt;St Antoine. Beholding one day a portrait of this lady, he wrote underneath it theſe two lines from the tragedy of Alcyonée:</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pour mériter ſon cœur, pour plaire à ſes beaux yeux, <hi rend="sup">ii</hi> fiaifait la guerre aux rois, je l’aurais fait aux deux.” </hi>Which may be thus rendered in Engliſh :</p><p><hi rend="sup">ii</hi> To gain her heart, and pleafe her ſparkling eyes,</p><p><hi rend="sup">4</hi>* I’ve war’dwith kings, and would have brav’dthe ſkies.”</p><p>It is reported, that after his rupture with Madame Longueville, he parodied the above verſes thus :</p><p><hi rend="italic">« Pour ce cœur inconſtant, qu<hi rend="sup">,</hi>enfin je connais mieux,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">“ fie fiais la guerre aux rois, ſen ai perdu les yeux.”</hi></p><p>After the civil wars were ended, he thought of nothing but enjoying the calm pleaſures of friendſhip and literature. His houſe became the rendezvous of every perſon of genius in Paris and Verſailles. Racine, Boileau, Savigne, and La Fayette, found in his converſation charms which they ſought for in vain elſewhere. He was not, however, with all his elegance and genius, a member of the French Academy. The neceſſity of making a public ſpeech the day of his reception was the only cauſe that he did not claim admittance. This nobleman, with all the courage he had diſplayed upon various critical occaſions, and with his ſuperiorſty of birth and underſtanding over the common run of men, did not think himſelf capable of facing an audience, to utter only four lines in public, without being out of countenance. He died at Paris in 168υ<hi rend="sub">i</hi>  aged 68&gt;</p><p>leaving behind him a character which has been variouſly drawn by thoſe who during his life were proud of his friendſhip. That he was well acquainted with human nature is certain; and his merit in that reſpect was fully admitted by Swift, who was himſelf not eaſily impoſed upon by the artificial diſguiſes of the hypocrite.</p><p>ROCHELLE, a celebrated city of France, capital of the territory of Aunis, with a very commodious and ſale harbour, which, though it does not admit veſſels of any conſiderable burden, is yet well calculated for trade. <hi rend="sup">il</hi> It may be divided (ſays Mr Wraxal) into three parts ; the baſon, which is the innermoſt of theſe, is only a quarter of a mile in circumference ; and at the entrance are two very noble Gothic towers, called the Tower de St Nicholas, and the Tour de la Chaîne. They are now in a ſtate of decay, but were anciently deſigned to protect the town and harbour. Without theſe towers is the Avant Port, extending more than a league, and bounded by two points of land to the north and ſouth. Beyond all is the road where the largeſt ſhips uſually anchor, protected from the ſouth-weſt winds by the iſlands of Re, Oleron, and Aix.” The celebrated mound erected by Richlieu extends from ſide to ſide acroſs the whole harbour, nearly an Engliſh mile in length, and when the ſea retires is ſtill vilible. “ I walked out upon it (ſays Mr Wraxal) above 300 feet. Its breadth is at this time more than 150 ſeet, and it. widens continually towards the baſe. No effort of art or power can poſſibly impreſs the mind with ſo vaſt and lublime an idea of the genius of Richlieu, as does this bulwark againſt the ſea. While I ſtood upon it, in the middle of the port, between the waves which rolled on either ſide, and contemplated its extent and ſtrength, I was almoſt inclined to ſuppoſe this aſtoniſhing work to be ſuperior to human power, and the production rather of a deity than of a mortal. A ſmall opening of about 200 ſeet was left by Pompey Targon, the architect who conſtructed it, to give entrance to veſſels, and ſhut up by chains fixed acroſs it. A tower was likewiſe erect-ed at each end, no remains of which are now to be ſeen. Neither the duke'of Buckingham, nor the earl of Lindſey, who were ſucceſſively ſent from England to the aid of the beſieged by Charles the Firſt, dared to attack this formidable barrier : they retired, and left Rochelle to its fate. In all probability, a thouſand years, aided by ſtorms and all the fury of the ſea, will make little or no impreſſion on this mound, which is deſigned to endure as long as the fame of the Cardinal, its author.”</p><p>Before the revolution, Rochelle was a biſhop’s ſee, and contained a college of humanities, an academy, a ſchool for medicine, anatomy, and botany, and a mint. It cannot lay claim to any remote antiquity, being merely a little collection of houſes on the ſhore, inhabited by fiſhermen, when William IX. laſt count of Poictou, rendered himſelf maſter of it in 1139. From this Prince it deſeended to his only daughter Eleanor, afterwards queen of Henry II. of England ; and her charter incorporating the town is ſtill preſerved in the • regiſters of the city. In the year 1540, Rochelle was the grand aſylum of the Proteſtants ; and the maſſacre at Paris was ſoon followed by the ſiege of Rochelle, which began in November 1572, and was raiſed in June 1573; but in 1628, after a moſt obſtinate reſiſtance, ∣uιd a ſiege of 13 months, it ſurrendered to</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>