<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tues. The great qualities of liis trind were accompanied with all the advantages of perſon. His body was majeſtic and vigorous ; he was at that middle time of life which is happily tempered with the warmth of youth and the caution of age, being 42 years old. To theſe qualities were added, a modeſty that ſeemed peculiar to himſelf alone ; ſo that mankind found a pleaſure in praiſing thoſe accompliſhments of which the pofleiΓor ſeemed no way conſcious. Upon the whole, Trajan is diſtinguiſhed as the greateſt and the beſt emperor of Rome. Others might have equalled him in war, and ſome might have been his rivals in clemency and goodneſs ; but he ſeems the only prince who. united theſe talents in the greateſt perfection, and who appears equally to engage our admiration and our regard. Upon being informed of the death of Nerva, he prepared to return to Rome, whither he was invited by the united intreaties of the ſtate. He therefore began his march with a diſcipline that was for a long time unknown in the armies of the empire. The countries through which he paſſed were neither ravaged nor taxed, and he entered the city, not in a triumphant manner, though he had deſerved it often, but on foot, attended by the civil officers of the ſtate, and followed by his ſoldiers, who marched ſilently forward with modeſty and reſpect. It •would be tedious and unneceſſary to enter into a detail of this good monarch’s labours for the ſtate. Hisapplication to buſineſs, his moderation to his enemies, his modeſty in exaltation, his liberality to the deſerving,and hisfrugality in his own expences ; theſe have all been the ſubject of panegyric among his contemporaries, and they continue to be the admiration of poſterity. Upon giving the prefect of the pretorian band the ſword, according to cuſtom, he made uſe of this remarkable expreſſion,</p><p>Take this ſword, and uſe it, if I have merit, for me ; if otherwiſe, againſt me.” After which he added, That he who gave laws was the firſt who was bound to obſerve them. His failings were his love of women, which, however, never hurried him beyond the bounds of decency ; and his immoderate paſſion for war, to which he had been bred up from his childhood. The firſt war he was engaged in after his coming to the throne was with the Dacians, who, during the reign of Domitian, had committed numberleſs ravages upon rhe provinces of the empire. He therefore raiſed a powerful army, and with great expedition marched into thoſe barbarous countries, where he was vigorouſly oppoſed by Decebalus, the Dacian king, who ſor a long time withſtood his boldeſt efforts ; but was at laſt entirely reduced, and his kingdom made a Roman province, See Dacia. At his return to Rome, he entered the city in triumph ; and the rejoicings for his victories laſted for the ſpace of 120 days.</p><p>Having thus given peace and proſperity to the empire, Trajan continued his reign, loved, honoured, and almoſt adored, by his ſubjects. He adorned the city with public buildings ; he freed it from ſuch men as lived by their vices ; he entertained perſons of merit with the utmoſt familiarity ; and ſo little feared his enemies, that he could ſearcely be induced to ſuppoſe that he had any.</p><p>It had been happy for this great prince’s memory', if he had ſhown equal clemency to all his ſubjects; but, about the ninth year of his reign, he was perfuadcd to</p><lb/><p>look upon the Chriſtians with a ſuſpictous eye. The extreme veneration which he profeſſed for the religion of the empire, ſet him ſedulouſly to oppoſe every innovation, and the progreſs of Chriſtianity ſeemed to alarm him. A law had for ſome time before beed paſſed, in which all Heteriæ, or ſocieties diſſenting from the eſtabliſhed religion, were conſidered as illegal, being reputed nurſeries of impoſture and ſedition. Under the fonction of this law, the Chriſtians were perſecuted in all parts of the empire. Great numbers of them were put to death, as well by popular tumults as by edicts and judicial proceedings. However, the perſecution ceaſed after ſome time ; for the emperor having advice from Pliny, the pro-conſul in Bithynia, of the innocence and ſimplicity of the Chriſtians, and of their inoffenlive and moral way of living, he ſuſpended their puniſhments. But a total ſtop was put to them upon Tiberianus the governor of Paleſtine’s ſending him word, That he was wearied out with executing the laws againſt the. Galileans, who crouded to execution in ſuch multitudes; that he was at a loſs how to proceed. Upon this iιu formation, the emperor gave orders, that the Chriſtians ſhould not be ſought after ; but if any offered themſelves, that they ſhould ſuffer. In this manner the rage of perſecution ceaſed, and the emperor found leiſure to., turn the force of his arms againſt the Armenians and Parthians, who now began to throw off all ſubmiſſion to Rome.</p><p>While he was employed in theſe wars, there was a dreadful inſurrection of the Jews in all parts of the empire. This wretched people, ſtill infatuated, and ever expecting ſome ſignal deliverer, took the advantage of Trajan’s abſence in the eaſt to maſſacre all the Greeks and Romans whom they got into their power, without reluctance or mercy. This rebellion firſt began in Cy-rene, a Roman province in Africa ; from thence the flame extended to Egypt, and next to the iſland of Cyprus. Theſe places they in a manner diſpeopled with ungovernable fury. Their barbarities were ſuch, that they eat the fleſh of their enemies, wore their ſkins, fowed them aſunder, caſt them to wild beaſts, made them kill each other, and ſtudied new torments by which to deſtroy them. However, theſe cruelties were of no long duration: the governors of the reſpective provinces making head againſt their tumultuous fury, ſoon treated them with a retaliation of cruelty, and put them to death, not as human beings, but as outrageous peſt3 to ſociety. As the Jews had practiſed their cruelties in Cyprus particularly, a law was publicly enacted, by which it was made capital for any Jew to ſet foot on the iſland.</p><p>During theſe bloody tranſactions, Trajan was proſecuting his ſucceſſes in the eaſt. His firſt march was into Armenia, the king of which country had diſclaimed all alliance with Rome, and received the enſigns of royalty and dominion from the monarch of Parthia. How» ever, upon the news of Trajan’s expedition, his fears were ſo great, that he abandoned his country to the invaders ; while the greateſt part of his governors and nobility came ſubmiſſively to the emperor, acknowledging themſelves his ſubjects, and making him the moſt coſtly preſents. Having in this manner taken poſſeſſion of the whole country, and gotten the king into his power, he marched into the dominions of the</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>