<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the war in Africa being completed, Cæſar returned in triumph to Rome ; and, as if he had abridged all his former triumphs only to increaſe the ſplendor of this, the citizens were aſtoniſhed at the magnificence of the proceſſion, and the number of the countries he had fub-dued. It laſted four days : the firſt was for Gaul, the ſecond for Egypt, the third for his victories in Aſia, and the fourth for that over Juba in Africa. To every one of his ſoldiers he gave a ſum equivalent to about 1501. of our money, double that ſum to the centurions, and four times as much to the ſuperior officers. The citizens alſo ſhared his bounty ; to every one of whom he diſtributed 10 buſhels of corn, 10 pounds of oil, and a ſum of money equal to about two pounds Sterling of ours. He, after this, entertained the people at about 20,000 tables, treated them with the combat of gladiators, and filled Rome with a concourir of ſpectators from every part of Italy.</p><p>The people now ſeemed eager only to find out new modes of homage and unuſual methods of adulation for their great enſlaver. He was created, by a new title, <hi rend="italic">Magιfler Morum,</hi>  or Maſter of the Morals of the People ; he received the title of <hi rend="italic">Emperor, Father of his country ;</hi>  his perſon was declared ſacred ; and, in ſhort, up.on him alone were devolved for life all the<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  great dignities of the ſtate. It muſt be owned, however, that no ſovereign could make a better uſe of his power. He immediately began his empire by f eprefling vice and encouraging virtue. He communicated the power of judicature to the ſenators and the knights alone, and by many ſumptuary laws reſtrained the ſcandalous luxuries of the rich. He propoſed rewards to all ſuch as had many children 5 and took the moſt prudent methods of repeopling the city, that had been exhauſted in the late -commotions ; and beſides his other works, he greatly reformed the kalendar.    ∙</p><p>Having thus reſtored proſperity once more to Rome, he again found himſelf under a neceſſity of going into Spain, to oppoſe an army which had been raiſed there under the two ſons of Pompey and Labienus his former general. He proceeded in this expedition with his uſual celerity, and arrived in Spain before the enemy thought him yet departed from Rome. Cneius and Sextus, Pompey’s ſons, profiting by their unhappy father’s example, reſolved as much as poſſible to protract the war ; ſo that the firſt operations of the two armies were ſpent in ſieges and fruitleſs attempts to ſurpriſe each other. At length Cæſar, after taking many cities from the enemy, and purſuing young Pompey with unwearied perſeverance, compelled him to come to a battle upon the plains of Munda.</p><p>After a moſt obſtinate engagement, Cæſar gained a complete victory (ſee Munda) ; and having now ſubdued all his enemies, he returned to Rome for the laſt time to receive new dignities and honours, and to enjoy an accumulation of all the great offices of the ſtate. Still, however, he pretended to a moderation in the enjoyment of his power ; he left the conſuls to be named by the people ; but as he poſſeſſed all the authority of the office, it from this time began to fink into contempt. He enlarged the number of ſenators alſo ; but as he had previouſly deſtroyed their power, their new honours were but empty titles. He took care to pardon all who had been in arms againſt him, but not till he had deprived them of the power</p><lb/><p>of reſiſtance. He even ſet up once more the ſtatues of Pompey ; which, however, as Cicero obſerved, he only did to ſecure his own. The reſt of this extraordinary man’s life was employed for the advantage of the ſtate. He adorned the city with magnificent buildings ; he rebuilt Carthage and Corinth, ſending colonies to both cities ; he undertook to level ſeveral mountains in Italy, to drain the Pontine marſhes near Rome, and deſigned to cut through the Iſthmus oſPeloponne-ſus. - Thus he formed mighty projects and deſigns beyond the limits of the longeſt life ; but the greateſt of all was his intended expedition againſt the Parthians, by which he deſigned to revenge the death of Craſſus ; then to paſs through Hyrcania, and enter Scythia along the banks of the Caſpian ſea ; from thence to open himſelf a way through the immeaſurable ſoreſts of Germany into Gaul, and ſo return to Rome. Theſe were the aims of ambition : but the jealouſy of a few individuals put an end to them all.</p><p>The ſenate, with an adulation which marked the degeneracy of the times, continued to load Cæſar with freſh honours, and he continued with equal vanity to receive them. They called one of the months of the year after his name ; they Ramped money with his image ; they ordered his ſtatue to be ſet up in all the cities of the empire ; they inſtituted public ſacrifices on his birth-day ; and talked, even in his life-time, of enrolling him in the number of their gods. Antony, at one of their public feſtivals, fooliſhly ventured to offer him a diadem ; but he put it back again, re-fuſtng it ſeveral times, and receiving at every refuſal loud acclamations from the people. One day, when the ſenate ordered him ſome particular honours, he neglected to riſe ſrom his ſeat ; and from that moment is ſaid to have been marked for deſtruction. It began to be rumoured that he intended to make himſelf king ; for though in fact he already was ſo, the people, who had an utter averſton to the name, could not bear his affirming the title. Whether he really deſigned to aſſume that empty honour muſt now for ever remain a ſecret ; but certain it is, that the unſuſpecting openneſs of his conduct marked ſomething like a conſidence in the innocence of his intentions. When informed by thoſe about him of the jealouſies of many perſons who envied his power, he was heard to ſay, That he had rather die once by treaſon, than to live continually in the apprehenſion of it : and to convince the world how little he had to apprehend from his enemies, he diſhanded his company of Spaniſh guards, which facilitated the enterpriſe againſt his liſe.</p><p>A deep-laid conſpiracy was formed againſt him, compoſed of no leſs than 60 ſenators. At the head of this conſpiracy was Brutus, whoſe life Cæſar had ſpared after the battle of Pharſalia, and Caſſius, who had been pardoned ſoon after, both prætors for the preſent year. Brutus made it his chief glory to have been deſeended from that Brutus who firſt gave liberty to Rome ; and from a deſire of following his example, broke all the ties of private friendſhip, and entered into a conſpiracy which was to deſtroy his benefactor. Caſſius, on the other hand, was impetuous and proud, and hated Cæſar’s perſon ſtill more than his cauſe. He had often ſought an opportunity of gratifying his revenge by aſſaſſination, which took riſe rather from private than public motives.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>