<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ced the Pannom’ans, who had attempted to ſhake off the yoke after the death of Agrippa. Druſus performed great exploits in Germany ; but while he was conſidering whether he ſhould penetrate further into theſe northern countries, he was ſeized with a violent fever, which carried him off in a few days. He was ſucceeded in his command by Tiberius, who is reported to have done great things, but certainly made no permanent conqueſts in Germany. However, he w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as honoured with a triumph, and had the tribunitial power for five years conferred upon him; which was no ſooner done, than, to the great ſurpriſe of Auguſtus and the whole city, he deſired leave to quit Rome and retire to Rhodes. Various reaſens have been aſſigned for this extraordinary reſolution : ſome are of opinion that it was in order to avoid being an eye-witneſs of the debaucheries of his wiſe Julia, who ſet no bounds to her lewdneſs ; though others imagine that he was offended at the honours which Auguſtus had conferred on his grandchildren, eſpecially at his ſtyling them <hi rend="italic">princes of the Roman youth ;</hi>  which left him no hopes of enjoying the ſovereign power. However, Auguſtus poſitiveiy refuſed to comply with his requeſt, and ſes mother Livia uſed her utmoſt endeavours to diſſuade him from his reſolution : but Tiberius continued obſtinate ; and finding all other means ineffectual, at laſt ſhut himſelf up in his houſe, where he abſtained four whole days from nouriſhment. Auguſtus, perceiving that he could not get the better of his obſtinate and inflexible temper, at laſt complied with his requeſt. Tiberius ſoon 'grew weary of his retirement, and, giving out that he had left Rome only to avoid giving umbrage to the emperor’s two grandchildren, deſired leave to return ; but Auguſtus was ſo much diſpleaſed with his having obſtinately inſiſted on leaving Rome, that he obliged him to remain at Rhodes ſor ſeven years longer. His mother,, with much ado got him declared the emperor’s lieutenant in thoſe parts ; but Tiberius, dreading the reſentment of his father-in-law’, continued to act as a private perſon during the whole time of his ſtay there..</p><p>A profound peace now reigned throughout the whole empire ; and in conſequence of this the temple of Janus 'was ſhut, which had never before happened ſince the time of Numa Pompilius. During this pacific interval, the Saviour of mankind was born in Judaea, as is recorded in the ſacred hiſtory, 748 years after the foundation of Rome by Romulus. Three years after, Tiberius returned to the city, by permiſſion of Auguſtus, who yet would not allow him to bear any public office ; but in a ſhort time, Lucius Cæſar, one of the emperor’s grandchildren, died, not without ſuſpicions of his being poiſoned by Livia. Tiberius ſhow-ed ſuch great concern for his death, that the affection of Auguſtus for him returned ; and it is ſaid that he w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ould at that time have adopted Tiberius, had it not been for giving umbrage to his other grandſon Caius Cæſar. This obſtacle, however, was ſoon after removed ; Caius being taken off alſo, not without great ſuſpicions of Livia, as well as in the former caſe. Auguſtus w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as exceedingly concerned at his death,, and immediately adopted Tiberius as his ſon; but adopted alſo Agrippa Poſthumius, the third ſon of the famous Agrippa ; and obliged Tiberius to adopt Germanicus the ſon of his brother Druſus, though he had a ſon of his own named<hi rend="italic">Drujus ;</hi>  which was a great mortification to hint, As to Agrippa, however, who might have been an occafιon of jealouſy, Tiberius was ſoon freed from him, by his diſgrace and baniſhment, which very ſoon took place, but on what account is not known.</p><p>The northern nations now began to turn formidable : and though it is pretended that Tiberius was always ſucceſsful againſt them, yet about this time they gave the Romans a moſt terrible overthrow ; three legions and fix cohorts, under Quintilius Varus, being almoſt entirely cut in pieces. Auguſtus ſet nσ bounds to his grief on this fatal occaſion. For ſome months he let his hair and beard grow, frequently tearing his garments, knocking his head againſt the wall, and crying out like a diffracted perſon, “ Reſtore the legions, Varus!” Tiberius, however, was ſoon after ſent into Germany ; and for his exploits there he was honoured with.a triumph. Auguſtus now took him. for his colleague in the ſovereignty ; after which he ſent Germanicus againſt the northern barbarians, and Tiberius into Illyricum. This was the laſt of his public acts ; for having accompanied Tiberius for part of his journey, he died at Nola in Campania, in the 76th year of his age, and 56th of his reign. Livia was ſuſpected ef having haſtened his death by giving him. poiſoned figs. . Her reaſon for this was, that ſhe feared a reconciliation between him and his grandſon Agrippa whom he had baniſhed, as we have already related. Some months before, the emperor had paid a viſit to Agrippa, unknown to Livia, Tiberius, or any other perſon, excepting one Fabius Maximus.. This man, on his return home, diſcovered the ſecret to his wife, and ſhe to the empreſs. Auguſtus then perceiving that Fabius had betrayed him, was ſo provoked, that he baniſhed him from his preſence for ever ; upon which the unfortunate Fabius, unable to ſurvive his diſgrace, laid violent hands on himſelſe</p><p>Tiberius, who ſucceeded to the empire, reſolved to ſecure himſelf on the throne by the murder of Agrippa; whom accordingly he cauſed to be put to death by a military tribune. Though this might have been a ſuf-ficient evidence of what the Romans had to expect, the death of Auguſtus was no ſooner known, than the conſuls, ſenators, and knights, to uſe the expreſſion of Tacitus, ran headlong into ſlavery. The two conſuls firſt took an oath of fidelity to the emperor, and then adminiſtered it to the ſenate, the people, and the ſoldiery. Tiberius behaved in a dark myſterious manner, taking care to rule with an abſolute ſway, but at the ſame time ſeeming to heſitate whether he ſhould accept the ſovereign power or not ; inſomuch that one of the ſenators took the liberty to tell him, that other men<hi rend="sup">v</hi>were flow in performing what they had promiſed, but he was flow in promiſing what he had already per-formed. At laſt, however, his modeſty was overcome, and he declared his acceptance of the ſovereignty in the following words: “ Laccept the empire, and will hold it, till ſuch time as you, conſcript fathers, in your great prudence, ſhall think proper to give repoſe to my old age.”</p><p>Tiberius had ſcarce taken poſſeſſion of the throne, when news were brought him that the armies in Pan-nonia and Germany had mutinied. In Pannonia, three legions having been allowed ſome days of relaxation from their uſual duties, either to mourn for the death of χ∖uguſtus, or to rejoice for the acceſſion of Tiberius, grew turbulent and ſeditious. The Pannonian muti-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>