<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>given, we may make √∕—<hi rend="smallcaps">LλΛ + i,6=√B,</hi>  and the Z , ,    , . Λ *97(√7-O,i)</p><p>formula of mean velocity will give V=--</p><p>⅛—0,3 <hi rend="italic">(Vd —</hi>o,ι ), which we may expreſs thus : V= (√7-<hi rend="smallcaps">°&gt;</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">∣</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">)(λ⅛-</hi>0.3)&gt; which gives-—---=≈</p><p>v⅛-~<hi rend="sup">0</hi>∙<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p>_    V    _</p><p><hi rend="italic">Vd</hi>  —ο,ί ) ; and finally, ∙~---4-0,ι≈√<hi rend="italic">d.</hi></p><p>—Æ—0.2 √B.    <hi rend="sup">5</hi></p><p>Having thu3 obtained what we called the mean depth, we may ſuppoſe the ſection rectangular. This</p><p>*y</p><p>gives <hi rend="italic">d-----</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi>  Thus we have two equations, S=xy</p><p><hi rend="italic">. <hi rend="sup">χ</hi> Y</hi>Und <hi rend="italic">d =</hi>  —r --—.</p><p>* + ij__</p><p>From which we obtain x±=    ∕1 +</p><p>g</p><p>And having the breadth <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  and area S, we -have y —</p><p>And then we may change this for the trapezium often mentioned.</p><p>Theſe are the chief problems on this part of the ſubject, and they enable us to adjuſt the ſlope and channel of a river which receives any number of ſucceſſive permanent additions by the influx of other ſtreams. This laſt informs us of the rife which a new ſupply will pro* duce, becauſe the additional ſupply will require additional dimenſions of the channel ; and as this is not ſup-poſed to "increaſe in breadth, the addition will be in depth. The queſtion may be propoſed in the following problem.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. III. Given the ſlope j, the depth and the baſe of a rectangular bed (or a trapezium), and conſequently the diſcharge D, to find how much the ſection will riſe, if the diſcharge be augmented by a given quantity.</hi></p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  be the height after the augmentation, and <hi rend="italic">&lt;tυ</hi>  the width for the rectangular bed. We have in any uni-</p><p>&gt;- <hi rend="sup">V</hi> «7.    ..</p><p>form current <hi rend="italic">Yd ~~ſſq— —</hi>Raiſingthistoaſquarc,</p><p>√B^~<hi rend="sup">-</hi>~°’<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">.    .    ∙, <hi rend="sup">σz</hi>' k&gt;</hi>  D</p><p>and putting for <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  and V their values ~f⅛j<hi rend="sub">j</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ſſſjy</hi>  and</p><p>297    .    w <hi rend="italic">h</hi></p><p>snaking “g — 0,3 = K, the equation becomes</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">∕ d</hi>  v</p><p>*∖-ürfK + °<hi rend="sup">, 1</hi> ∕    Raiſing the ſecond member to</p><p>à ſquare, and reducing, we obtain a cubic equation, to be ſolved in the uſual manner.</p><p>But the ſolution would be extremely complicated. We may obtain a very expeditious and exact approximation ſrom this conſideration, that a ſmall change in one of the dimenſions of the ſection will produce a much greater change in the ſection and the diſcharge than in the mean depth <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  Having therefore augmented the unknown dimcnſioti, which is here the height, make uſe of this to form a new mean depth, and then the new equation <hi rend="italic">Vd~~r-,</hi>  ——— ff-o,ι will</p><lb/><p>give us another value of A, which will rarely exceed the truth by √<hi rend="sub">5</hi>∙. This ſerves (by the ſame proceſs) for finding another, which will commonly be ſufficiently exact. We ſhall illuſtrate this by an example.</p><p>Let there be a river whoſe channel is a rectangle 150 feet wide and fix feet deep, and which diſcharges 1500 cubic feet of water per ſecond, having a velocity of 2σ inches, and ſlope of ττ⅜773-, or about √⅛∙ of an inch in 100 fathoms. How much will it riſe if it receives an addition which triples its diſcharge ? and what will be its velocity ?</p><p>If the velocity remained the ſame, its depth would be tripled ; but we know by the general formula that its velocity will be greatly increaſed, and therefore its depth will not be tripled. Suppoſe it to be doubled, and to become 12 feet. This will give <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  ≈ 10,34483, or 124,r38 inches; then the equation , or <hi rend="italic">h=, </hi>and<hi rend="italic"/>in which we have √B= r07,8, D = 45oo ; <hi rend="italic">Vd —</hi>o,l = 11,0417, will give /&gt;=13,276; whereas it ſhould have been 12. This ſhows that our calculated value of <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  was too ſmall. Let us therefore increaſe the depth by 0,9, or make it_i2,9, and repeat the calculation. This will give us √<hi rend="italic">d</hi>—0,1 = 11,3927, and <hi rend="italic">h=</hi>  12,867, inſtead of 13,276. Therefore augmenting our data 0,9 changes our anſwer 0,409. If we ſuppoſe theſe ſmall changes to retain their proportions, we may conclude that if 12 be augmented by the quantity x×0,9, the quantity 13,276 will diminiſh by the quantity x×0,409. Therefore, that the eſtimated value of <hi rend="italic">h </hi>may agree with the one which reſults from the calculation, we muſt have 12+x×0,9= 13,276—xXo,409. <hi rend="sub">rτl</hi>.</p><p>This will give <hi rend="italic">x=</hi>  , and χ×o,9~0,8773Î</p><p>and A= 12,8773. If <hi rend="sup">we</hi> repeat the calculation with this value of<hi rend="italic">l&gt;,</hi>  we ſhall find no change.</p><p>This value of <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  gives &lt;/=131,8836 inches. If wc now compute the new velocity by dividing the new diſcharge 4500 by the new area 150× 12,87 73, <hi rend="sup">we</hi>  ſhall find it to be 27,95 inches, in place of 20» the former velocity.</p><p>We might have made a pretty exact firſt aſſumption, by recollecting what Was formerly obſerved, that when the breadth is very great in proportion to the depth, the mean depth differs irtſenſibly from the real depth, or rather follows nearly the ſame proportions, and that the velocities are proportional to the ſquare roots of the depths. Call the firſt diſcharge <hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  the height <hi rend="italic">h, </hi>and velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi>  and let D, H, and V, expieſs theſe</p><p>things m their augmented ſtate. We have u&gt;= —, and &lt;zυ <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p><p>XT    <hi rend="sup">D</hi> i    <hi rend="sup">D</hi>    <hi rend="italic">d<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="sup">V</hi> - ^H<hi rend="sup">,and v</hi> '<hi rend="sup">V</hi> = Λ <hi rend="sup">:</hi> ^<hi rend="sup">, and 7,</hi>*<hi rend="sup">i vi</hi>=*Z^ <hi rend="sup">i </hi>D<hi rend="sup">l</hi></p><p>pp∙ But by this remark <hi rend="italic">v' : N<hi rend="sup">1</hi>=k</hi>  ί H. Therefore</p><p><hi rend="italic">, <hi rend="sub">tr</hi> d*</hi>  D<hi rend="sup">l</hi>  ,ΠP Hz?</p><p>0 : Γi — <hi rend="sub">j</hi> i H*<hi rend="sup">,</hi>    ,aιτd Z<hi rend="sup">3</hi> D<hi rend="sup">l</hi> ≈ H⅝∕<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="sub">t</hi></p><p>and J’ : D* = <hi rend="italic">h<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  :</hi>  H' (a uſeful theorem) and H<hi rend="sup">3</hi>ss</p><p>, <hi rend="sub">γ</hi>y<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">3</hi>  ∕A <hi rend="sup">i</hi>IP∣ <hi rend="sub">o </hi></hi>∙^Γ-, and H = <hi rend="italic">J</hi>  1= 12,48.</p><p>Or we might have made the ſame aſſumption by the</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>