<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>permanency in an uniform ſoil neceſſarily ſuppoſes. Reaſoning after the ſame manner for all the portions <hi rend="italic">c d<hi rend="sub">i</hi>  b c, a b, s a,</hi>  we ſee that the regimen will be ſucceſſively eſtabliſhed in them, and that the ſlope neceſſary for this purpoſe will be greater as we approach the river head. The vertical ſection or profile of the courſe of the river <hi rend="italic">sabedeſ</hi>  will therefore reſemble the line SABCDEF which is ſhetehed below, having its different parts variouſly inclined to the horizontal line HF.</p><p>Such is the proceſs of nature to be obſerved in every river on the ſurface of the globe. It long appeared a kind of puzzle to the theoriſts ; and it was this obſer-vation of the increaſing, or at leaſt this continued velocity with ſmaller ſlope, as the rivers increaſed by the addition of their tributary ſtreams, which cauſed Gu-glielmini to have recourſe to his new principle, the energy of deep waters. We have now ſeen in what this energy conſiſts. It is only a greater quantity of motion remaining in the middle of a great ſtream of water after a quantity has been retarded by the ſides and bottom ; and we ſee clearly, that ſince the addition of a new and perhaps an equal ſtream does not occupy a ∙ bed of double ſurface, the proportion of the retardations to tire remaining motion muſt continually diminiſh as a river increaſes by the addition of new ſtreams. If therefore the ſlope were not diminiſhed, the regimen would be deſtroyed, and the river would dig up its channel. We have a full confirmation of this in the many works which have been executed on the Po, which runs with rapidity through a rich and yielding ſoil. About the year' 16oo, the waters of the Panaro, a very conſiderable river, were added to the Po Grande ; and although it brings along with it in its freſhes a vaſt quantity of fand and mud, it has'greatly deepened the whole Tronco di Venezia from the confluence to the ſea. This point was clearly aſcertained by Manfredi about the 1720, when the inhabitants of the valleys adjacent were alarmed by the project of bringing in the waters, of the Rheno, which then ran through the Ferrareſe. Their fears were overcome, and the Pυ Grande continues to deepen its channel every day with a prodigious advantage to the navigations ; and there are ſeveral ex-tenlive marſhes which now drain off by it, after having been for ages under water : and it is to be particularly remarked, that the Rheno is the fouleſt river in its freſhes of any in that country. We inſert this remark, becauſe it may be of great practical utility, as pointing out a method of preſerving and even improving tire depth of rivers or drains in flat countries, which is not obvious, and rather appears improper : but it is ſtrictly conformable to a true theory, and to the operations of nature, which never fails to adjuſt every thing ſo as to bring about an equilibrium. Whatever the declivity of the country may have been originally, the regimen begins to be ſettled at the mouths of the rivers, and the Hopes are diminiſhed in ſucceſſion as we recede from the coaſt. The original ſlopcs inland may have been much greater; but they will (when buſy nature has completed her work) be left ſomewhat, and only ſo much greater, that the velocity may be the ſame notwithſtaiid-ing the diminution of the ſection and mean depth.</p><p>Freſhes will diſturb this methodical progreſs relative only to the ſucceſſive permanent additions ; but their effects chiefly accelerate the deepening of the bed, and</p><p>the diminution of the ſlope, by augmenting the velocity during their continuance. But when the regimen of the permanent additions is once eſtabliſhed, the freſhes tend chiefly to widen the bed, without greatly deepening it : for the aquatic plants, which have been growing and thriving during the peaceable ſtate of the river, are now laid along, but not ſwept away, by the freſhes and protect the bottom from their attacks ; and the ſtones and gravel, which muſt hâve been left bare in a courſe of years, working on the ſoil, will alſo collect in the bottom, and greatly augment its power of reſiſtance ; and even if the floods ſhould have deepened the bottom ſome ſmall matter, ſome mud will be depoſited as the velocity of the freſhes diminiſhes, and this will remain till the next flood.</p><p>We have ſuppoſedthe ſoil uniform through the wholc courſe : This ſeldom happens ; therefore the circum-ſtances which inſure permanency, or the regimen of a river, may be very different in its different parts and in different rivers. We may ſay in general, that the farther that the regimen has advanced up the ſtream in any river, the more ſlowly will it convey its waters to the ſea.</p><p>There are ſome general circumſtances in the motion of rivers which it will be proper to take notice of juſt now, that they may not interrupt our more minute examination of their mechaniſm, and their explanations will then occur of themſelves as corollaries of the proposions which we ſhall endeavour to demonſtrate.</p><p>In a valley of ſmall width the river always occupies the loweſt part of it ; and it is obſerved, that this is ſeldom in the middle of the valley, and is neareſt to that ſide on which the ſlope from the higher grounds is ſteepeſt/ and this without regard to the line of its courſe. The river generally adheres to the ſteepeſt hills, whether they advance into the plaiu or retire ſrom it. This general feature may be obſerved over the whole globe. It is divided into copartments by great ranges of moιiu-tains ; and it may be obſerved, that the great rivers hold their courſe not very far from them, and that their chief feeders come ſrom the other ſide. In every copàrtment there is a ſwell of the low<hi rend="sup">r</hi> country at a diſtance from the bounding ridge of mountains ; and on the ſummit of this ſwell the principal feeders of the great river have their ſources.</p><p>The name <hi rend="italic">valley</hi>  is given with leſs propriety to theſe immenſe regions, and is more applicable to tracks of champaign land which the eye can take in at one view. Even here we may obſerve a reſemblance. It is not always in the very loweſt part of this valley that the river has its bed ; although the waters of the river flow in a channel below its immediate banks, theſe banks are frequently higher than the grounds at the foot of the hills. This is very diſtinctly ſeen in Lower Egypt, by means of the canals which are carried backward from the Nile for accelerating its fertilizing inundations; When the caliſhes are opened to admit the waters, it is always obſerved that the diſtricts moſt remote are the firſt covered, and it is ſeveral days before the immediately adjoining fields partake of the bleſſing. This is a conſequence of that general operation of nature by which the valleys are formed. The river in its floods is loaded with mud, which it retains as long as it rolls rapidly along its limited bed, tumbling its w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>aters over and over, and taking up in every ſpot as much as</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>