<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the bed, the viſcidity of the fluid, and its adheſion to the ſides. Here are neceſſarily combined a number of circumſtances which muſt be gradually detached that we may ſee the effect of each, viz. the extent of the bed, its perimeter, and its ſlope. By examining the effects produced by variations of each of theſe ſe-parately, we diſcover what ſhare each has in the general effect; and having thus analyſed the complicated phenomenon, we ſhall be able to combine thoſe its elements, and frame a formula which ſhall comprehend every circumſtance, from the greateſt velocity to the extinction of all motion, and from the extent of a river to the narrow dimenſions of a quill. We ſhall compare this formula with a ſeries of experiments in all this variety of circumſtances, partly made by Mr Buat, and partly collected from other authors; and we ſhall leave the reader to judge of the agreement.</p><p>Confident that this agreement will be found moſt ſa-tisfactory, we ſhall then proceed to conſider very curſorily the chief varieties which nature or art may introduce into theſe beds, the different velocities of the ſame ſtream, the intenſity of the reſiſtance produced by the inertia of the materials of the channel, and the force of the current by which it continually acts on this channel, tending to change either its dimenſions or its form. We ſhall endeavour to trace the origin of theſe great rivers which ſpread like the branches of a vigorous tree, and occupy the ſurſace even of a vaſt continent. We ſhall follow them in their courſe, unfold all their windings, ſtudy their train, and regimen, and point out the law of its ſtability; and we ſhall in-veſtigate the cauſes of their deviations and wanderings.</p><p>The ſtudy of theſe natural laws pleaſes the mind: but it anſwers a ſtill greater purpoſe; it enables us to aſſiſt nature, and to haſten her operations, which our wants and our impatience often find too ſlow. It enables us to command the elements, and to force them to adminiſter to our wants and our pleaſures.</p><p>We ſhall therefore, in the next place, apply the knowledge which we may acquire to the ſolution of the moſt important hydraulic queſtions which occur in the practice of the civil engineer.</p><p>We ſhall conſider the effects produced by a permanent addition to any river or ſtream by the union of another, and the oppoſite effect produced by any draught or offset, ſhowing the elevation or depreſſion produced up the ſtream, and the change made in the depth and velocity below the addition or offset.</p><p>We ſhall pay a ſimilar attention to the temporary ſwells produced by freſhes.</p><p>We ſhall aſcertain the effects of ſtraightening the courſe of a ſtream, which, by inereaſing its ſlope, muſt increaſe its velocity, and therefore ſink the waters above the place where the curvature was removed, and diminiſh the tendency to overflow, while the ſame immediate conſequence muſt expoſe the places farther down to the riſk of floods from which they would otherwiſe have been free.</p><p>The effects of dams or weirs, and of bars, muſt then be conſidered; the gorge or ſwell which they produce up the ſtream muſt be determined for every diſtance from the weir or bar. This will ſurniſh us with rules for rendering navigable or floatable ſuch waters as have too little depth or too great ſlope. And it will appear</p><p>that immenſe advantages may be thus derived, with a moderate expence, even from trifling brooks, if we will relinquiſh all prejudices, and not imagine that ſuch conveyance is impoſſible, becauſe it cannot be carried on by ſuch boats and ſmall craft as we have been accuſtom-ed to look at.</p><p>The effects of canals of derivation, the rules or ma-xims of draining, and the general maxims of embankment, come in the next place; and our diſcuſſions will conclude with remarks on the moſt proper forms for the entry to canals, locks, docks, harbours, and mouths of rivers, the beſt ſhape for the ſtarlings of bridges and of boats for inland navigations, and ſuch like ſub-ordinate but intereſting particulars, which will be ſug-geſted by the general thread of diſcuſſion.</p><p>It is conſidered, as phyſically demonſtrated (ſee Hydrostatics and Hydraulics), that water iſſuing from a ſmall orifice in the bottom or ſide of a very large veſſel, almoſt inſtantly acquires and maintains the velocity which a heavy body would acquire by falling to the orifice from the horizontal ſurface of the ſtagnant water. This we ſhall call its Natural Velocity. Therefore if we multiply the area of the orifice by this velocity, the product will be the bulk or quantity of the water which is diſcharged. This we may call the Natural Expence of water, or the Natural. Discharge.</p><p>Let O repreſent the area or ſection of the orifice ex-preſſed in ſome known meaſure, and <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  its depth under the ſurface. Let <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  expreſs the velocity acquired by a heavy body during a ſecond by falling. Let V be the medium velocity of the water's motion, Q the quantity of water diſcharged during a ſecond, and N the natural expence.</p><p>We know that V is equal to<hi rend="italic">.</hi>  Therefore.</p><p>If theſe dimenſions be all taken in Engliſh feet, have very nearly equal to 8; and therefore V =, and N=O. 8√<hi rend="italic">h</hi></p><p>But in our preſent buſineſs it is much more convenient to meaſure every thing by inches. Therefore ſince a body acquires the velocity of 32 feet 2 inches in a ſecond, we have 2<hi rend="italic">g </hi>= 64 feet 4 inches or 772 inches, and =27, 78 inches nearly 27 inches.</p><p>Therefore V=, = 27, 78√<hi rend="italic">h</hi>, and N=0. = O. 27, 78√<hi rend="italic">h</hi>.</p><p>But it is alſo well known, that if we were to calculate the expence or diſchage for every orifice by this ſimple rule, we ſhould in every inſtance find it much greater than nature really gives us.</p><p>When water iſſues through a hole in a thin plate, the lateral columns, preſſing into the hole from all ſides, cauſe the iſſuing filaments to converge to the axis off the jet, and contract its dimenſions at a little diſtance from the hole. And it is in this place of greateſt contraction that the water acquires that velocity which we obſerve in our experiments, and which we aſſume as equal to that acquired by falling from the ſurface. Therefore, that our computed diſcharge may beſt agree with obſervation, it muſt be calculated on the ſuppo-lition that the orifice is diminiſhed to the ſize of this ſmalleſt ſection. But the contraction is ſubject to variations, and the dimenſions of this ſmalleſt ſection</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>