<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>or inventors of abominable recreations, from Rome ; attempted to reſtore the ancient manner of electing magiſtrates by the ſuffrages of the people ; and gave them a free juriſdiction, without any appeal to himſelf. Although the will of Tiberius was annulled by the ſenate, and that of Livia ſuppreſſed by Tiberius, yet he cauſed all their legacies to be punctually paid; and in order to make Gemellus amends for miffing the crown, he cauſed him to be elected Princeps Juventutis, or principal of the youth. He reſtored ſome kings to their dominions who had been unjuſtly uilpoſſefſed by Tiberius, and gave them the arrears of their revenues. And, that he might appear an encourager of every virtue, he ordered a female ſlave a large ſum of money for enduring the moſt exquiſite torments without diſcovering the ſecrets of her maſter. So many conceſſions, and ſuch apparent virtue, coiιld not fail of receiving juſt applauſe. A ſhield of gold, bearing his image, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as decreed to be carried annually to the Capitol, attended by the ſenate and the ſons of the nobility ſinging in praiſe of the emperor’s virtues. It was likewiſe ordained, that the day on which he was appointed to the empire ſhould be called <hi rend="italic">Publia ;</hi>  implying, that when he came to govern, the city received a new foundation.</p><p>In leſs than eight months all this ſhew of moderation and clemency vaniſhed ; while furious paſſions, un-exampled avarice, and capricious cruelty, began to take their turn in his mind. As moſt of the cruelties of Tiberius aroſe from ſuſpicion, ſo moſt of thoſe committed by Caligula took riſe from prodigality. Some indeed aſſert, that a diſorder which happened ſoon after his acceſſion to the empire, entirely diſcompoſed his underſtanding. However this may be, madneſs itſelf could ſcarce dictate cruelties more extravagant, or in-conſiſtencies more ridiculous, than are imputed to him ; ſome of them appear almoſt beyond belief, as they ſeem entirely without any motive to incite ſuch barbarities.</p><p>The firſt object of his cruelty was a perſon named <hi rend="italic">Ρυlitus,</hi>  who had devoted himſelf to death, in caſe the emperor, who was then ſick, ſhould recover. When Caligula’s health was re-eſtabliſhed, he was informed of the zeal of Politus, and/ actually compelled him to complete his vow. This ridiculous devotee was therefore led round the city, by children, adorned with chaplets, and then put to death, being thrown headlong from the ramparts. Another, named <hi rend="italic">Secundus<hi rend="sub">i </hi></hi>had vowed to fight in the amphitheatre upon the ſame occaſion. To this he was alſo compelled, the emperor himſelf chooſing to be a ſpectator of the combat. However, he was more fortunate than the former, being ſo ſucceſsful as to kill his adverſary, by which he obtained a releaſe from his vow. Gemellus was the next who ſuffered from the tyrant’s inhumanity. The pretence againſſ him was, that he had wiſhed the emperor might not recover, and that he had taken a counter-poiſon to ſecure him from any ſecret attempts againſt his life. Caligula ordered him to kill himſelf; but as the unfortunate youth was ignorant of the manner of doing it, the emperor’s meſſengers ſoon inſtructed him in the fatal leſſon. Silenus, the emperor’s father-in-law, was the next that was put to death upon flight ſuſpicions·; and Gercinus, a ſenator of noted integrity, refuſing to witneſs falſely againſt him, ſhared his fate. After theſe followed a crowd of victims to the emperor’s avarice or ſuſpicion. The pretext againſt them was their enmity to his family ; and in proof of his accuſations he produced thoſe very memorials which but a while before he pretended to have burnt. Among the number of thoſe who were ſacriſiced to his jealouſy, was Macro, the late favourite of Tiberius, and the perſon to whom Caligula owed his empire. He was accuſed of many crimes, ſome of which were common to the emperor as well as to him, and his death brought on the ruin of his whole family.</p><p>Theſe cruelties, however, only ſeemed the firſt fruits of a mind naturally timid and ſul'picious: his vanity and profuſion ſoon gave riſe to others which were more atrocious, as they ſprung from leſs powerful motives. His pride firſt began by aſſuming to himſelf the title of <hi rend="italic">ruler, </hi>which was uſually granted only to kings. He would alſo have taken the crown and diadem, had he not been adviſed that he was already ſuperior to all the monarchs of the world. Not long afttr, he aſſumed divine honours, and gave himſelf the names of ſuch divinities as he thought moſt agreeable to his nature. For this purpoſe he cauſed the heads of the ſtatues of Jupiter and ſome other gods to be ſtruck off, and his own to be put in their places. He frequently ſeated himſelf between Caſtor and Pollux, and ordered all who came to their temple to worſhip, ſhould pay their adorations only to him ; nay, at laſt he altered their temple to the form of a portico, which he joined to his palace, that the very gods, as he ſaid, might ſerve him in the quality of porters.</p><p>He was not leſs notorious for the depravation of hi» appetites than for his ridiculous preſumptions. Neither perſon, place, nor ſex, were obſtacles to the indulgence of his unnatural lulls. There was ſcarce a lady of any quality in Rome that eſeaped his lewdneſs;. and, indeed, ſuch was the degeneracy of the times, that there were few ladies who did not think this diſgrace an honour. He committed inceſt with his three fitters, and at public feaſts they lay with their heads upon his boſom by turns. Of theſe he proſtituted Livia and A-grippina to his vile companions, and then baniſhed them as adnltereſſes and conſpirators againſt his perſen. As for Druſilla, he took her from her huſhand Longinus, and kept her as his wife. Her he loved ſo affectionately, that, being ſick, he appointed her as heireſs of his empire and fortune ; and ſhe happening to die before him, he made her a goddeſs. Nor did her example when living, appear more dangerous to the people than her divinity when dead. To mourn for her death was a crime, as ſhe was become a goddeſs ; and to rejoice for her divinity was capital, becauſe ſhe was dead. Nay, even ſilence itſelf was an unpardonable inſenſibili-ty, either of the emperor’s loſs or his fitter’s advancement. Thus he made his ſiſter ſubſervient to his profit, as before he had done to his pleaſure ; raiſing vaſt ſums of money by granting pardons to ſome, and by conſiſeating the goods of others. As to his marriages, whether he contracted them with greater levity, or diſſolved them with greater injuſtice, is not eaſy to determine. Being preſent at the nuptials of Livia Oreſtilla with Piſo, as ſoon as the ſolemnity was over, he commanded her to be brought to him as his own wiſe, and then diſmiſſed her in a few days. He ſoon after baniſhed her upon ſuſpicion of cohabiting with her huſ-band after ſhe was parted ſrom him. He was enamoured of Lollia Paulina, upon a bare relation of her grand?</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>