<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>has been mortal, but the pain ceaſes after a few days duration. The natives formerly made their flutes of this tree, becauſe it has a great deal of pith. Some people aſſured me, that a perſon ſuffering from its noi-ſome exhalations, would eaſily recover by ſpreading a mixture of the wood burnt to charcoal, and hog’s lard, upon the ſwelled parts. Some aſſerted, that they had really tried this remedy. In ſome places this tree is rooted out, on purpoſe that its poiſon may not affect the workmen.”</p><p>The natives are ſaid to diſtinguiſh this tree in the dark by its extreme coldneſs to the touch. The juice of ſome kinds of ſumach, when expoſed to the heat of the ſun, becomes ſo thick and clammy, that it is uſed for bird-lime, and the inſpiſſated juice of the poiſon-aſh is ſaid to be the fine varniſh of Japan. A cataplaſm made with the freſh juice of the poiſon-aſh, applied to the feet, is ſaid by Hughes, in his Natural Hiſtory of Barbadoes, to kill the vermin called by the Weft Indians <hi rend="italic">chigers.</hi>  Very good vinegar is made from an in-fuſion of the fruit of an American ſumach, which for that reaſon is called the <hi rend="italic">vinegar-tree.</hi>  The reſin called <hi rend="italic">gum copal</hi>  is from the rhus copallinum. See Copal.</p><p>RHYME, Rhime, <hi rend="italic">Ryme,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Rime,</hi>  in poetry, the ſimilar found or cadence and termination of two words which end two verſes, &amp;c. Or rhyme is a ſimilitude of ſound between the laſt ſyllable or ſyllables of a verſe, ſucceeding either immediately or at a diſtance of two or three lines, See Poetry, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  177, &amp;c.</p><p>RHYMER (Thomas the), was a native of the pa-riſh of Earlſtown, in the county of Berwick. His real name and title was Sir Thomas Lermont. He lived at the weſt end of Earlſtown, where part of his houſe is ſtill ſtanding, called <hi rend="italic">Rhymer’s Tower ;</hi>  and there is a ſtone built in the fore wall of the church with this in-ſcription on it,</p><p>Auld Rhymer’s race lies in this place.</p><p>He lived in the 13th century, and was contemporary with one of the earls of March, who lived in the ſame place.</p><p>RHYTHM, in muſic, the variety in the movement, as to the quickneſs or ſlowneſs, length or ſhortneſs, of the notes. Or it may be defined more generally, the proportion which the parts of the motion have to each other.</p><p>RIAL, or Ryal, a Spaniſh coin. See Money-<hi rend="italic">Table.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rial, or </hi><hi rend="italic">Royal,</hi>  is alſo the name of a piece of gold anciently current among us for 10 s.</p><p>RIBAN, or Ribban, in heraldry, the eighth part of a bend. See Heraldry, p. 447.</p><p>RIBAND, or Ribbon, a narrow ſort of ſilk, chiefly uſed for head-ornaments, badges of chivalry, &amp;c.</p><p>In order to give our readers an idea of the manner in which this curious and valuable branch of manufactures is managed, a view of the ribbon-weaver at I1I3 loom is repreſented in Plate CCCCXXXV. where, I. Is the frame of the loom. 2. The caſtle, containing 48 pulleys. 3. The branches, on which the pulleys turn. 4. The tires, or the riding-cords, which run on the pulleys, and pull up the high-liſſes. 5. The liſt-ſticks, to which the high-liſſes are tied. 6. The high-liſſes, or lifts, are a number of long threads, with platines, or plate-leads, at the bottom ; and ringlets, or loops, about their middle, through which the cords or crols-threads of the ground-harneſs ride. 7. The plate-leads, or platines, are flat pieces of lead, of about ſix inches long, and three or four inches broad at the top, but round at the bottom ; ſome uſe black ſlates inſtead of them : their uſe is to pull down thoſe liſſes which the workman had railed by the treddle, after his foot is taken off. 8. The branches or cords of the ground har-neſs, which go thro’ the loops in the middle of the high-liſſes : on the well-ordering of theſe- cords chiefly depends the art of ribbon-weaving, becauſe it is by means of this contrivance that the weaver draws in the thread or ſilk that makes the flower, and rejects or excludes the reſt. 9. The batton : this is the wooden frame that holds the reed or ſhuttle, and beats or cloſes the work : where, obſerve, that the ribbon-weaver does not beat his work ; but as ſoon as the ſhuttle is paſſed, and his hand is taken away, the batton is forced, by a ſpring from the top, to beat the work cloſe. 10. The ſhuttle, or reed. 11. The ſpring of the batton, by which it is made to cloſe the work. 12. The long-harneſs are the front-reeds, by which the figure is raiſed. 13. The linguas are the long pieces of round or ſquare lead, tied to the end of each thread of the long-harneſs to keep them tight. 14. The broad piece of wood, about a foot ſquare, leaning ſomewhat forward, intended to eaſe the weaver as he ſtoops to his ſhuttle ; it is fixed in the middle of the breaſt-beam. Some weavers, inſtead of this, have a contrivance of a cord or rope that is faſtened to the front-frame, and comes acroſs his breaſt ; this is called a <hi rend="italic">ſlopfall.</hi>  15. The feat-bench ; this leans forward very much. 16. The foot-ſtep to the treddles. 17. The breaſt-beam, being a croſs-bar that paſſes from one of the ſtandards to the other, fo as to front the workman’s breaſt : to this breaſt-bar is fixed a roll, upon which the ribbon paſſes in its way to be rolled upon the roller, that turns a little below. 18. The clamps, or pieces of wood, in which the broaches that confine the treddles reſt. 19. The treddles are long narrow pieces of wood, to the ends of which the cords that move the liſſes are faſtened. 20. The treddle-cords are only diſtinguiſhed from the riding-cords by a board full of holes, which divide them, in order to prevent the</p><p>plate-leads, which are tied to the high-liſſes, from pulling them too high when the workman’s foot is off the treddle : which flop is made by a knot in the treddle-cord, too big to be forced through that hole in the board. 21. The lames are two pieces of thin narrow boards, only uſed in plain works, and then to ſupply the place of the long-harneſs. 22. The knee-roll, by which the weaver rolls up his ribbon as he ſees proper, or by bit and bit as it is finiſhed. 23. The back-rolls, on which the warp is rolled. It is to be ob-ſerved, that there is always as many rolls as colours in the work to be wove. 24. The damps, which ſup-port the rollers. 25. The returning-flicks, or, as others call them, the <hi rend="italic">returns,</hi>  or the <hi rend="italic">tumblers,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">pulleys,</hi>  to which the tiers are tied, to clear the courſe of cords through the high-liſſes. 26. The catch-board for the tumblers. 27. The tire-board. 28. The buttons for the knee-rolls and treddle board, deſcribed in number 20.</p><p>Ribbons of all ſorts are prohibited from being imported.</p><p>RIBANDS (from <hi rend="italic">rib</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">brief),</hi>  in naval architec-</p></body></text></TEI>