<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>it was foggctted to them, 'that what could not be effected by the interceſſion öf the ſenate or the adjuration of the prieſts, might b⅞ brought about by the tears of his wife, or the commands of his mother. This deputation ſeemed to be reliſhed by all ; and even the ſenate itſelf gave it the fonction öf their authority. Vettnfia, the mother of Coriolanus, at firſt made ſome hesitation to undertake ſo pious a work : however, ſhe at laſt undertook the embaſſy, ând ſet forward from the city, accompanied by many of the principal matrons of Rome, with Vol<hi rend="sup">,</hi>umnia his wiſe, and his two children. Coriolanus, who at â diſtance diſcovered this mournful train of females, was reſolved to give them à denial, and called his officers round him to be witneſs of his reſolution ; but, 'when told that his mother and his wiſe were among the number, he inſtantly came down from his tribunal to meet and embrace them. At firſt, the womens tears and embraces took away the power of words ; and the rough ſoldier himſelf, hard as he was, could not refrain from ſharing in their diſtreſs. Coriolanus now ſeemed much agitated by contending paſſions ; while his mother, who ſaw him moved, ſeconded her words by the moſt perſuaſive eloquence, her tears ; his wife and children hung round him, intreating for protection and pity ; while the fair tram, her comp¾-nio'ns, added their lamentations, and deplored their own and their country’s diſtreſs. Coriolanus for a moment wa's filent, feeling the ſtrong conflict between honour and inclination : at length, as if routed from his dream, he flew to take up his mother, who had fallen at his feet, crying out, " O my mother, thou haft ſaved Rome, but loſt thy ſon.” He accordingly gave orders to draw off the army, pretending to the officers that the city was too ſtrong to be taken. Tullus, who had long envied ſhis glory, was not remiſs in aggravating the lenity of ſhis conduct to his countrymen. Upon their return, Coriolanus was ſlain in an inſurrection of the people, arid afterwards honourably buried, With late and ineffectual repentance.</p><p>The year following, the two conſuls of the former year, Manlius and Fabius, were cited by the tribunes to appear before the people. The Agrarian law, which had been propoſed ſome time before, for equally dividing the lands of the commonwealth among the people, was the object invariably purſued, and they were accuſed of having made unjuſtifiable delays inputting it off.</p><p>It ſeems the Agrarian law was a grant the ſenate could not think of giving up to the people. The conſuls, therefore, made many delays and excuſes, till at length they were once more obliged to have recourſe to a dictator ; and they fixed upon Quintus Cincinna-tιιs, a man who had for ſome time given up all views of ambition, and retired to his little farm, where the deputies of the ſenate found him holding the plough, and dreſſed in the mean attire of a labouring huſhandman. Fie appeared but little elevated with the addreſſes of Λ,∙eιemon.y and the pompous habits they Brought him ; and, upon declaring to him the ſenate’s pleaſure, he teſtified rather a concern that his aid ſhould be w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>atιted. However, he departed for the city, where both parties were ſtrongly enſlamed againſt each other : but he was reſolved to ſide with neither; only, by a ſtri’ct attention lo the intereſts off his country, inſtead of gaming the confidence of faction, to Obtain lire tſteem of all.</p><p>Thus, by threats and well-timed ſubmiſſion, he pre· vailed upon the tribunes to put off their law for a time, and carried himſelf ſo as to be a terror to the multitude whenever they reſuſed to enliſt ; and their greateſt encourager whenever their ſubmiſſion deſerved it. Thus, having reſtored that tranquillity to the people which he ſo much loved himſelf, he again gave up the lplen-d<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ors of ambition, to enjoy it with a greater reliſh in his little farm.</p><p>Cincinnatυs w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as not long retired from his office when a freſh exigence of the ſtate once more required his aſſiſtance* The Æqui and the Volſei, who, though ſtill worſted, ſtill were for renewing the war, made new inroads into the territories of Rome. Miιmtius, one of the conſuls who ſucceeded Cincinnatus, was ſent to oppoſe them ; but being naturally timid·, and rather more afraid of being conquered than défiions of victory, his army wηs driven into a defile between two mountains, from which, except through the enemy, there was no cgreſs. This, however, the Æqui had the precaution to fortify ; by which the Roman army was ſo hemmed in on every ſide, that nothing remained but ſubmiſſion to the enemy, famine, or immediate death. Some knights, v.ſho found means of getting away privately through the enemy’s camp, were the firſt that brought the account of this diſaſter to Rome. Nothing could exceed the conſternation of all ranks of people when informed of it. The ſenate at firſt thought of the other conſul ; but not having ſufficient experience of his abilities, they unaninouſly turned their eyes upon Cincin-natus, and reſolved to make him dictator. Cincinuatus, the only perſon on Wſhom Rome could now place her whole dependence, was found, as before, by the meſſengers of the ſenate, labouring in his little field with cheerful induſtry. He was at firſt aſtoniſhed at the enſigns of unbounded power with which the deputies* came to inveſt him ; but ſtill more at the approach or the principal of the ſenate, who came out to meet him. A dignity ſo unlooked for, however-, had no effect upon the ſimplicitv or the integrity of his manners : and being how poſſeſſed of abſolute powder, and called upon to nominate his maſter of the horſe, he choſe a poor man named<hi rend="italic">Tarquitius, </hi>one who, like himſelf, deſpiſed riches when they led to diſhonour. Upon entering the city, the dictator pυ'. on a ſerene look, and intreated all thoſe who were able to bear arms to repair before fun-ſet to the Campus Martius (the place where the levies were made) with neceſſary arms, and proviſions for five days. He put himſelf at the head öf theſe ; and, marching all night with great expedition, he arrived before day within fight of the enemy. Upon his approach, he ordered his ſoldiers to raiſe a loud ſhout, to apprize the conſul's army of the relief that w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as at hand. The Æqui w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>tre not a little amazed when they ſaw themſelves between two enemies ; but ſtill more when they perceived Cincinnatus making the ſtrongeſt entrenchments -beyond them, to prevent their eſcape, and inclofιiιg them as they bad incloſed the conſul. To prevent this, a furious combat enfiιed ; but the Æqui, being attacked on both ſides, and unable<hi rend="italic">to </hi>refill or fly, begged a ceſſation of arms. They offered the dictator his own terms : he gave them their lives ; but obliged them, in token of ſervitude, to paſs under the yoke, which was two ſpears ſet upright-, and another acroſs, in the form of a gallows beneath which</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>