<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>quent ’ inundations, by which it often does great damage. A ſmall part of the city is ſeparated ſrom the other by the river, and is therefore called <hi rend="italic">Traveftere, </hi>or beyond the Tiber. There are ſeveral bridges over the river, a great number of towers on the walls, and 20 gates. The remains of Rome’s ancient grandeur conſiſt of ſtatues, coloffuſes, temples, palaces, theatres, naumachias, triumphal arches, circuſes, columns, obeliſhs, fountains, aqueducts, mauſoleums, thermae or hot-baths, and other ſtructures. Of modern buildings, the ſplendid churches and palaces are the moſt remarkable. Mr Addiſon ſays, it is almoſt impoſſible for a man to form in his imagination ſuch beautiful and glorious ſcenes as are to be met with in ſeveral of the Roman churches and chapels. This gentleman tells us alſo, that no part of the antiquities of Rome pleaſed him ſo much as the ancient ſtatues, of which there is ſtill an incredible variety. Next to the ſtatues, he ſays, there is nothing more lurpriſing than the amazing variety of ancient pillars of ſo many kinds of marble. Rome is ſaid to be well paved ; but not well lighted, nor kept very clean, Two-thirds of the houſes are the property of the churches, convents, and alms houſes. Proteſtants are not obliged to kneel at the elevation of the hoſt, or at meeting the euchariſt in the ſtreets ; and they may have ſteſh-meat always at the inns, even during Lent. Here are many academies for promoting arts and ſciences, beſides the univerſity. The carnival here is only during the eight days before Lent, and there are no ſuch ſcenes of riot as at Venice : proſtitutes, however, are publicly tolerated. To maintain good order, there is a body of 300 Sbirri, or Halberdeers, under their barigella, or colonel. There is little or no trade carried on in Rome, but a vaſt deal of money is ſpent by travellers and other ſtrangers. The principal modern ſtructures are the church of St Peter, and the other churches ; the aqueducts and fountains ; the Vatican, and the other palaces ; the Campidolio, where the Roman ſenate re-fides, &amp;c.    1 he principal remains of antiquity are the</p><p>pila miliaria of fine marble ; the equeſtrian braſs ſtatue of Marcus Aurelius Antoninus ; the marble monument of the emperor Alexander Severus ; marble buſts of the emperors and their conforts ; three brick arches of the temple of Peace, built by the emperor Veſpaſian ; the triumphal arch of Septimus Severus and of Gallienus ; the circus of Antoninus Caracalla ; ſome parts of the cloaca-maxima ; the columna Antonina, repreſenting the principal actions of Marcus Aurelius ; the columna Trajani, or Trajan’s pillar ; ſome fragments of the curia, or palace of Antoninus Pius, and of Nerva’s forum ; the mauſolseum of Auguſtus, in the Strada Pontifici ; the remains of the emperor Severus’s tomb without St John’s gate ; the pyramid of Caius Ceſtus near St Paul’s gate ; the porphy ry coffin of St Helen, and the original ſtatue of Conſtantine the Great, in the church of St John of Lateran: a font of oriental granite, in the chapel of St Giovanni in fonte, ſajd to have been erected by Conſtantine the Great ; an Egyptian obeliſlc near the church of St Maria Maggiore ; the ſtately remains of Dioclefian’s baths ; the celebrated Pantheon ; the obeliſks of Se-ſoſtris and Auguſtus by the Clementine college ; the church of St Paul fuori della Mura, ſaid to have been built by Conſtantine the Great ; the Farneſe Hercu.</p><lb/><p>les, in white marble, of a Coloſſian ſize and exquiſite workmänihip, in a court of the Farneſe palace, and an admirable group cut out of one block of marble, in another court of the ſame palace. Beſides theſe there are a great many more, which our bounds will not allow us to take any further notice of. Here is a great number of rich and well-regulated hoſpitals. Near the church of St Sebaſtiano alle Catacombe, are the moſt ſpacious of the catacombs, where the Chriſtians, who never burned their dead, and ſuch of the Pagan Romans as could not afford the expence of burning, were buried. Along the Via Appia, without St Sehaſtian’s gate, were the tombs of the principal families of Rome, which at preſent are uſed for cellars and ſtore-houſes by the gardeners and vine-dreſſers. <hi rend="sub">x</hi></p><p>ROMNEY, a town of Kent in England. It is one of the cinque-port towns, and is ſeated on a marſh of the ſame name, famous for feeding cattle ; but the air is very unhealthy. It was once a large and populous place, but the retiring of the ſea has reduced it very much.; however, it fends two members to parliament.</p><p>R0M0RENTIN, is a ſmall town ſituated on the river Saudre, in the territory of Blaſois in France, fa-ιwsus for its woollen manufacture. It is laid to be a very ancient place ; and the inhabitants pretend that Cæſar built a tower here, of which there are ſtill ſome conſiderable remains. They have a manufacture of ſerge and cloth, which is uſed for the clothing of the troops.</p><p>R0MPEE, or Rompu, in heraldry, is applied to ordinaries that are repreſented as broken ; and to chevrons, bends, or the like, whoſe upper points are cut off.</p><p>ROMULUS, the founder and firſt king of Rome. See Rome, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 14.</p><p>RONCIGLIONE, is a town of Italy, in the Ec-cleſiaſtic State, and Patrimony of St Peter, in E. Long. 13. N. Lat. 42. X2. It is a ſmall place, but had a pretty good trade, and was one of the richeſt in the province, while it belonged to the dukes of Parma, which was till 1649, when pope Innocent X. became maſter of it, and it has ever ſince continued in the poſſeſſion of his ſucceffors.</p><p>RONDELETIA, in botany : A genus of the mo-' nogynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking with thoſe of which the order is doubtlul. The corolla is funnel-ſhaped ; the capſule bilocular, inferior, and polyſper-mous, roundiſh and crowned.</p><p>R0NA, one of the Hebrides iſlands, is reckoned about 20 leagues diſtant ſrom the north-eaſt point of Neſs in Lewis—about a mile long, and half a mile broad. It has a hill in the weſt part, and is only viſible from Lewis in a fair ſummer’s day. There is a chapel in the iſland dedicated to St Ronan, fenced with a ſtone wall round it. This church the natives take care to keep very neat and clean, and ſweep it every day. There is an altar in it, on which there lies a big plank of wood about 10 feet long. Every foot has a hole in it, and in every hole is a ſtone, to which the natives aſeribe ſevetal virtues ; one of them is ſingular (as they ſay) for promoting ſpeedy delivery to a woman in travel. The inhabitants are extremely ignorant, and very ſuperſtitious. See <hi rend="italic">Mar tin’s Deſcription.</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>