<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>In the mean time Brutus, with a ſmall number of friends, paſſed over a rivulet, and, night coming on, ſat down under a rock which concealed him from the purſuit of the enemy. After taking breath for a little time, he ſent out one Statilius to give him ſome information of thoſe that remained; but he never returned, being killed by a party of the enemy’s horſe. Brutus judging very rightly of his fate, now reſolved to die likewiſe, and ſpoke to thoſe who ſtood round him to lend him their laſt ſad aſſiſtance. None of them, however, would render him ſo melancholy a piece of ſervice. At laſt one Strato, averting his head, preſented the ſword’s point to Brutus; who threw himſelf upon it, and immediately expired.</p><p>From the moment of Brutus’s death the triumviri began to act as ſovereigns, and to divide the Roman dominions between them, as theirs by right of conqueſt. However, though there were apparently three who thus participated all the power, yet, in fact, only two were actually poſſeſſed of it; ſince Lepidus was at firſt admitted merely to curb the mutual jealouſy of Antony and Octavianus, and was poſſeſſed neither of intereſt in the army nor authority among the people. Their firſt care was to puniſh thoſe whom they had formerly marked for vengeance. The head of Brutus was ſent to Rome to be thrown at the foot of Cæſar’s ſtatue. His aſhes, however, were ſent to his wife Porcia, Cato’s daughter, who afterwards killed herſelf by ſwallowing burning coals. It is obſerved, that of all thoſe who had a hand in the death of Cæſar, not one died a natural death.</p><p>The power of the triumviri being thus eſtabliſhed upon the ruins of the commonwealth, Antony went into Greece, and ſpent ſome time at Athens, converſing among the philoſophers, and aſſiſting at their diſputes in perſon. From thence he paſſed over into Aſia, where all the monarchs of the eaſt, who acknowledged the Roman power, came to pay him their obedience. In this manner he proceeded from kingdom to kingdom, attended by a crowd of ſovereigns, exacting contributions, diſtributing favours, and giving away crowns with capricious inſolence. He preſented the kingdom of Cappadocia to Syſenes, in prejudice of Ariarathes, only becauſe he found pleaſure in the beauty of Glaphyra, the mother of the former. He ſettled Herod in the kingdom of Judea, and ſupported him againſt every oppoſer. But among all the ſovereigns of the eaſt who ſhared his favours, none had ſo large a part as Cleo patra, the celebrated queen of Egypt.</p><p>It happened that Serapion, her governor in the iſland of Cyprus, had formerly furniſhed ſome ſuccours to the conſpirators; and it was thought proper that ſhe ſhould anſwer for his conduct on that occaſion. Accordingly, having received orders from Antony to come and clear herſelf of this imputation of infidelity, ſhe readily complied, equally conſcious of the goodneſs of her cauſe and the power of her beauty. She had already experienced the force of her charms upon Cæſar and Pompey’s eldeſt ſon; and the addition of a few years ſince that time had not impaired their luſtre. Antony was now in Tarſus, a city of Cilicia, when Cleopatra reſolved to attend his court in perſon. She ſailed down the river Cydnus, at the mouth of which the city ſtood, with the moſt ſumptuous pageantry. Her galley was covered with gold; the ſails were of purple, large, and floating in the wind. The oars of</p><p>ſilver kept tune to the ſound of flutes and cymbals. She herſelf lay reclined on a couch ſpangled with ſtars of gold, and with ſuch ornaments as poets and painters had uſually aſcribed to Venus. On each ſide were boys like Cupids, who fanned her by turns; while the moſt beautiful nymphs, dreſſed like Nereids and Graces, were placed at proper diſtances around her. Upon the banks of the river were kept burning the moſt exquiſite perfumes, while an infinite number of people gazed upon the fight. Antony was captivated with her beauty; and, leaving all his buſineſs to ſatisfy his paſſion, ſhortly after followed her into Egypt.</p><p>While he thus remained idle, Octavianus, who took upon him to lead back the veteran troops and ſettle them in Italy, was aſſiduouſly employed in providing for their ſubliſtence. He had promiſed them lands at home, as a recompenſe for their paſt ſervices; but they could not receive new grants, without turning out the former inhabitants. In conſequence of this, multitudes of women, with children in their arms, whoſe tender years and innocence excited univerſal compaſſion, daily filled the temples and the ſtreets with their diſtreſſes. Numbers of huſbandmen and ſhepherds came to deprecate the conqueror’s intention, or to obtain an habitation in ſome other part of the world. Amongſt this number was Virgil the poet, who in an humble manner begged permiſſion to retain his patrimonial farm: Virgil obtained his requeſt; but the reſt of his countrymen, of Mantua and Cremona, were turned out without mercy.</p><p>Italy and Rome now felt the moſt extreme miſeries; the inſolent ſoldiers plundered at will; while Sextus Pompey, being maſter of the ſea, cut off all foreign communication, and prevented the people’s receiving their uſual ſupplies of corn. To theſe miſchiefs were added the commencement of another civil war. Fulvia, the wife of Antony, who had been left behind him at Rome, had felt ſor ſome time all the rage of jealouſy, and reſolved to try every method of bringing back her huſhand from the arms of Cleopatra. She conſidered a breach with Octavianus as the only probable means of rouſing him from his lethargy; and accordingly, with the aſſiſtance of Lucius her brother-in-law, who was then conſul, and entirely devoted to her intereſt, ſhe began to ſow the ſeeds of diſſenſion. The pretext was, that Antony ſhould have a ſhare in the diſtribution of lands as well as Octavianus. This produced ſome negociations between them; Octavianus offered to make the veterans themſelves umpires in the diſpute. Lucius refuſed to acquieſce; and being at the head of more than ſix legions, moſtly compoſed of ſuch as had been diſ-poſſeſſed of their lands, he reſolved to compel Octavianus to accept of whatever terms he ſhould offer. Thus a new war was excited between Octavianus and Antony; or, at leaſt, the generals of the latter aſſumed the function of his name. Octavianus, however, proved victorious: Lucius was hemmed in between two armies, and conſtrained to retreat to Reruſia, a city of Etruria, where he was cloſely beſieged by the oppoſite party. He made many deſperate ſallies, and Fulvia did all in her power to relieve him, but without ſucceſs. He was at laſt, therefore, reduced to ſuch extremity by famine, that he came out in perſon and delivered himſelf up to the mercy of the conqueror. Octavianus received him very honourably, and generouſly pardoned him and all his followers. Thus having con-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>