<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to determine our defences, and obliges us to give them deeper and more solid foundations in such places. But any perfora accuftoιned to the uſe of the ſeale and com-paſſes will form to himſelf rules of practice equally ſure and more expeditious than Mr de Buat’s formulæ.</p><p>We proceed, therefore, to what is more to out purpoſe, the conſideration of the reſiſtance cauſed by an elbow, and the methods of providing a force capable of overcoming it, We have already taken notice of the ſalutary conſequences ariſihg from the rambling courſe of rivers, inaſmuc'h as it more effectually ſpreads them over the face of a country. It is no leſs beneficial by diminiſhing their velocity. This it does both by lengthening their courſe, which dimim’ſhes the declivity, and by the very reſiſtance which they meet with at every bend. We derive the chief advantages from •our rivers, when they no longer ſhoot their way from precipice to precipice, loaded with mud and fand, but peaceably roll along their clear waters, purified during their gentler courſe, and offer themſelves for all the purpoſes of paſturage, agriculture, and navigation. The more a river winds its way round the foot of the hills, the more is the reſiſtance of its bed multiplied ; the more obſtacles it meets with in its way ſrom its ſource 'to the ſea, the more moderate is its velocity ; and in-ftead of tearing up the very bowels of the earth, and «digging for itſelf a deep trough, along which it ſweeps rocks and rooted-np trees, it flows with majeſtic pace ’even with the ſurface of our cultivated grounds, which it embelliſhes and fertilizes.</p><p>We may with ſafety proceed on the ſirppoſition, that the force neceſſary for overcoming the reſiſtance ariſiwg ſrom a rebound is as the ſquare of "the velocity ; and it is reaſonable to ſuppoſe it proportional to the ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence, and this for the rea-fons given for adopting this meaſure of the general <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Resistance of Fluids.</hi></hi>  It cannot, however, claim a greater confidence here than in that application ; and it has been ſhown in that article with what uncertainty and limitations it muſt be received. We leave it to our readers to adopt either this or the ſimple ratio of the fines, and ſhall abide by the duplicate ratio with Mr Buat,becauſe fit appears by his experiments that this law is very exactly obſerved in tubes in inclinations not 'exceeding 4.0 ' ; whereas it is in theſe ſmall angles that the application to the general reſiſtance of fluids is moſt in 4ault. But the correction is very ſimple, if this value ſhall be found erroneous There can be little doubt that the force neceſſary for overcoming the reſiſtance will increaſe •as the number of rebounds.-—Therefore we may expreſs the</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">x</hi> j <hi rend="sup">i</hi> n</p><p>veſiſtance, in general, by the formula <hi rend="italic">r— —</hi>—; where <hi rend="italic">m</hi></p><p>r is the reſiſtance, V the mean velocity of the ſtream, » the fine of the angle of incidence, <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  the number of equal rebounds (that is, having equal angles of incidence), and m is a number to be determined by experiment. Mr de Buat made many experiments on the reſiſtance occaſioned by the bendings of pipes, none of which differed from the reſult of the above formula •above one part in twelve ; and he concludes, that the</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">1</hi> j<hi rend="sup">i</hi></p><p>reſiſtance to one bend may he eftimateu at —-</p><p>3000 ∙</p><p>*ſſhe experiment was in thig form : A pipe of j inch ^diameter, and 10 feet loςg, wu formed with to rebounds of 36<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  each.A head of water was applied to ιi, which gave the water a velocity of fix ſeet <hi rend="italic">per ſecond.</hi>  Another pipe of the ſame diameter and length, but without any bendings, was ſubjected to a preſſure of a head of water, which was increaſed till the velocity of efflux was alſo ſix ſeet <hi rend="italic">per</hi>  ſecond. The additional head of water was inches. Another of the ſame diameter and length, having one bend of 24.<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  34', and running 85 inches<hi rend="italic">per</hi>  ſecond, was compared with a ſtraight pipe having the ſame velocity, and the difference of tire heads of water was of an inch. A computation from theſe two experiments will give the</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">1</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">j<hi rend="sup">1</hi></hi></p><p>above reſult, or, in Engliſh meaſure, <hi rend="italic">r — --—</hi></p><p>3200</p><p>very nearly. It is probable that this meaſure of the reſiſtance is too great ; for the pipe was of uniform diameter even in the bends : whereas in a river properly formed, where the regimen is exact, the capacity of the ſectiiui of the bend is increaſed.</p><p>The application of this theory to inclined tubes and to open ſtreams is very obvious, and very legitimate and ſafe. Let AB (fig. 17.) be the whole height of the reſervoir A B I K, and B C the horizontal length of a pipe, containing any number of rebounds, equal or unequal, but all regular, that is, conſtructed according to the conditions formerly mentioned. The whole head of water ſhould be conceived as performing, or as divided into portions which perform, three different offices.—</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">5</hi></p><p>One portion, AD — ——, impels the water into thé</p><p>505</p><p>entry of the pipe with the velocity with which it really moves in it ; another portion EB is in equilibrio with the reſiſtances ariſing from the mere length of the pipé expanded into a ſtraight line ; and the third portion DE ſerves to overcome the reſiſtance of the bends. If, therefore, we draw the horizontal line B C, and, taking the pipe B C out of its place, put it in the poſition DH, with its mouth C in Η, ſo that DH is equal to BC, the water will have the ſame velocity in it that it had before. <hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi>  For greater ſimplicity of argument, we may ſuppoſe that when the pipe was inſerted at B, its bends lay all in a horizontal plane, and that when it is inſerted at D, the plane in which all its bends lie ſlopes only in the direction DH, and is perpendicular to the plane of the figure. We repeat it, the water will have the ſame velocity in the pipes B C and D H, and the reſiſtances will be overcome. If we now prolong the pipe D H towards L to any diſtance, repeating continually the ſame bendings in a ſeries of lengths, each equal to D H, the motion will be continued with the velocity correſponding to the preſſure of the column AD ; becauſe the declivity of the pipe is augmented in each length equal to DH, by a quantity preciſely "ſufficient for overcoming all the reſiſtances ift that length ; and the true ſlope in theſe caſes is B E-f-E D, divided by the expanded length of the pipe B C or DH.</p><p><hi rend="sup">,</hi>Jhe analogy which we were enabled to eſtabliſh between the uniform motion or the train of pipes and of open ſtreams, intitles us now to ſay, that when a river has bendings, which are regularly repeated at equal intervals, its ſlope is compounded of the ſlope which is neceſſary for overcoming the reſiſtance of a ſtraight channel of its whole expanded length, agreeably to</p></body></text></TEI>