<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with thickets. If the place be watered by a ſtream, the croſſings may be in a variety of pleaſing deſigns; and if a ſpring riſe, or only a well for common uſe be ſunk by the ſide of the way, a little covering over it maybe contrived which ſhall at the ſame time be ſimple and pretty.</p><p>There are few villages which may not eaſily be rendered agreeable. A ſmall alteration in a houſe will ſometimes occaſion a great difference in the appearance. By the help of a few trifling plantations, the objects which have a good effect may be ſhown to advantage, thoſe which have not may be concealed, and ſuch as are ſimilar be diſguiſed. And any form which offends the eye, whether of ground, of trees, or of buildings, may ſometimes be broken by the ſlighteſt circumſtances, by an advanced paling, or only by a bench. Variety and beauty, in ſuch a ſubject, are rather the effects of attention than expence.</p><p>But if the paſſage through the village cannot be pleaſant; if the buildings are all alike, or ſtand in unmeaning rows and ſimilar ſituations; if the place fur-niſhes no opportunities to contrail the forms of dwellings with thoſe of out-houſes; to introduce trees and thickets; to interpoſe fields and meadows; to mix farms with cottages; and to place the ſeveral objects in different poſitions: yet on the outſide even of ſuch a village there certainly is room for wood; and by that alone the whole may be grouped into a maſs, which ſhall be agreeable when ſkirted by a riding; and ſtill more ſo when ſeen from a diſtance. The ſeparate farms in the fields, alſo, by planting ſome trees about them, or perhaps only by managing thoſe already on the ſpot, may be made very intereſting objects; or if a new one is to be built, beauty may be conſulted in the form of the houſe, and the diſpoſition of its appurtenances. Sometimes a character not their own, as the ſemblance of a caſtle or an abbey, may be given to them; they will thereby acquire a degree of conſideration, which they cannot otherwiſe be entitled to: and objects to improve the views are ſo important to a riding, that buildings muſt ſometimes be erected for that purpoſe only: but they ſhould be ſuch as by an actual effect adorn or dignify the ſcene; not thoſe little ſlight deceptions which are too well known to ſucceed, and have no merit if they fail: for though a fallacy ſometimes contributes to ſupport a character, or ſuggeſts ideas to the imagination, yet in itſelf it may be no improvement of a ſcene; and a bit of turret, the tip of a ſpire, and the other ordinary ſubjects of theſe frivolous attempts, are ſo inſignificant as objects, that whether they are real or fictitious is almoſt a matter of indifference.</p><p>The ſame means by which the proſpects from a riding are improved, may be applied to thoſe from a garden; though they are not eſſential to its character, they are important to its beauty; and wherever they abound, the extent only of the range which commands them, determines whether they ſhall be ſeen from a riding or a garden. If they belong to the latter, that aſſumes in ſome degree the predominant properties of the former, and the two characters approach</p><lb/><p>very near to each other: but ſtill each has its peculiarities. Progreſs is a prevailing idea in a riding; and the pleaſantneſs of the way is, therefore, a principal conſideration: but particular ſpots are more attended to in a garden; and to them the communications ought to be ſubordinate; their direction muſt be generally accommodated, their beauties ſometimes ſacri-ficed to the ſituation and the character of the ſcenes they lead to; an advantageous approach to theſe muſt be preferred to an agreeable line for the walk; and the circumſtances which might otherwiſe become it are misplaced, if they anticipate the openings: it ſhould ſometimes be contraſted to them; be retired and dark if they are ſplendid or gay, and ſimple if they are richly adorned. At other times it may burſt unexpectedly out upon them; not on account of the ſurpriſe, which Can have its effect only once; but the impreſſions art ſtronger by being ſudden; and the contrail is enforced by the quickneſs of the tranſition.</p><p>In a riding, the ſcenes are only the amuſements of the way, through which it proceeds without ſtopping: in a garden they are principal; and the ſubordinatiori of the walk raiſes their importance. Every art, therefore, ſhould be exerted to make them ſeem parts of the place. Diſtant proſpects cannot be ſo; and the alienation does not offend us; we are familiarized to it; the extent forbids every thought of a cloſer connection; and if a continuation be preſerved between them and the points which command them, we are ſatisfied. But <hi rend="italic">home-views</hi>  ſuggeſt other ideas; they appear to be within our reach: they are not only beautiful in proſpect, and we can perceive that the ſpots are delightful; but we wiſh to examine, to inhabit, and to enjoy them. Every apparent impediment to that gratification is a diſappointment; and when the ſcenes begin beyond the opening, the conſequence of the place 13 lowered; nothing within it engages our notice: it is an exhibition only of beauties, the property of which does not belong to it; and that idea, though indifferent in a riding which is but a paſſage, is very diſadvantageous to ſuch a reſidence as a garden. To obviate ſuch an idea, the points of view ſhould be made important; the objects within be appendages to thoſe without; the ſeparations be removed or concealed; and large portions of the garden be annexed to the ſpots which are contiguous to it. The ideal boundary of the place is then carried beyond the ſcenes which are thus appropriated to it; and the wide circuit in which they lie, and the different poſitions in which they may be ſhown, afford a greater variety than can generally be found is any garden, the ſcenery of which is confined to the in-cloſure.</p><p>Persfield @@(a) is not a large place; the park contains about 300 acres; and the houſe ſtands in the midſt of it. On the ſide of the approach, the inequalities of the ground are gentle, and the plantations pretty; but nothing there is great. On the other ſide, a beautiful lawn falls precipitately every way into a deep vale which ſhelves down the middle; the declivities are diverſified with clumps and with groves; and a number of large trees ſtraggle along the bottom. This lawn is encom</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a) The ſeat of Mr Morris, near Chepſtowe, in Monmouthſhire.</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>