<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which may be rolled up by the hand into the form of a pipe.</p><p>In theſe ſchedules of parchment, all the pleadings, memorials, and acts of court, are entered and filed by the proper officer ; which being done, they become records of the court. Of theſe there are in the exchequer ſeveral kinds, as the great wardrobe roll, the cofferer’s roll, the ſubſidy-roll, &amp;c.</p><p>Roll is alſo uſed for a lift of the names of perſons of the ſame condition, or of thoſe who have entered into the ſame engagement. Thus a court-roll of a manor, is that in which the names, rents, and ſervices, of each tenant are copied and enrolled.</p><lb/><p>years ago ; yet the memoirs of the duke de Rohan ſtill afford conſiderable pleaſure in the peruſal. He tells his ſtory with humour, with ſufficient exactneſs, and in ſuch a ſtyle as procures the confidence of the reader.</p><p>ROHAULT (James), a celebrated Carteſian philoſopher, was the ſon of a merchant of Amiens, where he was born in 1620. He became well ſhilled in the mathematics, and taught them at Paris, where he became acquainted with M. Clerſelier, an advocate, who gave him his daughter in marriage. Rohault alſo taught philoſophy in the ſame city with uncommon applauſe. He there improved the arts, and gave excellent lectures to the artiſts and workmen. He died at Paris in 1675. <hi rend="sup">wι</hi>θte, in French, 1. A Treatiſe on Natural Philoſophy. 2. The Elements of the Mathematics. 3. A Treatiſe on Mechanics, which is very curious. 4. Philoſophical Converſations ; and other works. His Phyſics have been tranſlated into Latin, by Dr Samuel Clarke, with notes, in which the Carteſian errors are corrected upon the Newtonian ſyſtem.</p><p>ROLAND RA, in botany : A genus of the polyga-mia ſegregata order, belonging to the ſyngeneſia claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Cornpofitee.</hi>  The common calyx conſiſts of diſtinct <hi rend="italic">fioſculi,</hi>  between each of which are ſhort <hi rend="italic">ſquamee, </hi>the whole forming a round head. The partial calyx is bivalved. The corolla is ſmall and funnel-ſhaped, the tube ſmall as a thread, the <hi rend="italic">lαrini&lt;t</hi>  ſhort and acute. The ſtamina are five ; the ſtyle bifid. It has no other ſeed veſſel except the partial calyx, which contains a long three-ſided ſeed. Of this there is only one ſpecies, viz. the Argentea ; a native of the Weſt Indies, and found in copſes and waſte lands.</p><p>ROLL, in manufactories, ſomething wound and folded up in a cylindrical form.</p><p>Few fluffs are made up in rolls, except ſatins, gaw-ſes, and crapes ; which are apt to break, and take plaits not eaſy to be got out, if folded otherwiſe. Ribbons, laces, gallons, and paduas of all kinds, are alſo thus rolled.</p><p>A roll of tobacco, is tobacco in the leaf, twiſted on the mill, and wound twiſt over twill about a ſtick or roller. A great deal of tobacco is ſold in America in rolls of various weights ; and it is not till its arrival in England, Spain, France, and Holland, that it is cut.</p><p>A roll of parchment, properly denotes the quantity of 60 ſhins.</p><p>The ancients made all their books up in the form of rolls ; and in Cicero’s time the libraries conſiſted wholly of ſuch rolls.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roll, in law, ſigniſies a ſchedule or parchment</hi></p><lb/><p><hi rend="italic">Calves-head Roti,</hi>  a roll in the two temples, in which every bencher is taxed yearly at 2 s. every barri-ſter at ί s. 6 d. and every gentleman under the bar at I s. to the cook and other officers of the houſe, in conſideration of a dinner of calves·heads provided in E after-term.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Muſter-RoLt,</hi>  that in which are entered the ſoldiers of every troop, company, regiment, &amp;c. As ſoon as a ſoldier’s name is writtea down on the roll, it is death for him to deſert.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RoLLs∙Ojftce<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  is an office in Chancery-lane, London, appointed for the cuſtody of the rolls and records in chancery.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Maſter of the Rolls.</hi>  See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Master of the Rolls.</hi></hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Ruler-Roll,</hi>  a ſchedule of parchment frequently ſew-ed or added to ſome part of a roll or record.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rolls</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">  of Parliament,</hi>  are the manuſcript regiſters or rolls of the proceedings of our ancient parliaments, which before the invention of printing were all engroſs-ed on parchment, and proclaimed openly in every county. In theſe rolls are alſo contained a great many deciſions of difficult points of law, which were frequently in former times referred to the deciſion of that high court.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roll, or </hi><hi rend="italic">Roller,</hi>  is alſo a piece of wood, iron, braſs, &amp;c. of a cylindrical form, uſed in the conſtruction of ſeveral machines, and in ſeveral works and manufactures.</p><p>Thus in the glaſs manufacture they have a running-roll, which is a thick cylinder of caſt braſs, which ſerves to conduct the melted glaſs to the end of the table on which large looking-glaſſes, &amp;c. are caſt.</p><p>Founders alſo uſe a roll to work the fand which they uſe in making their moulds.</p><p>The preſſes called <hi rend="italic">calendars,</hi>  as ſerving to calendar fluffs withal, conſiſt, among other eſſential parts, of two rollers. It is alſo between the two rollers that the waves are given to ſilks, mohairs, and other fluffs proper to be tabbied.</p><p>Impreſſions from copper-plates are alſo taken by paſſing the plate and paper between two rollers. Sec <hi rend="italic">Rolling-preſs </hi><hi rend="italic">PRINTING.</hi></p><p>Rolls, in flatting-mills, &amp;c. are two iron inſtruments of a cylindrical form, which ſerve to draw or ſtretch out plates of gold, ſilver, and other metals.</p><p>Rolls, in ſugar-works, are two large iron barrels which ſerve to bruiſe the canes, and to expreſs the juice. Theſe are caſt hollow, and their cavities are filled up with wood, the cylinders of which are properly the rollers.</p><p>ROLLER, in ſurgery, a long and broad bandage, uſually of linen-cloth, rolled round any part of the body, to keep it in, or diſpoſe it to a ſtate of health.</p><p>ROLLI (Paul), was born at Rome in 1687. He was the ſon of an architect, and a pupil of the celebrated Gravina, who inſpired him with a taſte for learning and poetry. An intelligent and learned Engliſh lord having brought him to London, introduced him to the royal family as a maſter of the Tuſcan language. Rolli remained in England till the death of queen Caroline his protector, and the patroneſs of literature in general. He returned to Italy in 1747, where he died in 1767, in the 80th year of his age, leaving behind him a very curious collection in natural hiſtory, &amp;c. and a valuable and well choſen library. His principal works firſt ap-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>