<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>every part of his life incapable of conducting himſelf. Not that he was entirely deſtitute of underſtanding, ſince he had made a tolerable proficiency in the Greek and Latin languages, and even wrote an hiſtory of his own time ; which, however deſtitute of other merit, was not contemptible in point of ſtyle. Nevertheleſs, with this ſhare of erudition, he was unable to advance himſelf in the ſtate, and ſeemed utterly neglected until he was placed all at once at the head of affairs. The commencement of his reign gave the moſt promiſing hopes oi an happy continuance. He began by paſſing an act of oblivion for all former words and actions, and diſannulled all the cruel edicts of Caligula. He forbade all perſons, upon ſevere penalties, to ſacriſice to him as they had done to Caligula ; was arduous in hearing and examining complaints ; and frequently adminiſtered juſtice in perſon ; tempering by his mildneſs the ſeverity of the law. We are told of his bringing a woman to acknowledge her ſon, by ad judging her to marry him. The tribunes of the people coming one day to attend hh when he was on his tribunal. he courteouſly excuſed himſelſ for not having room for them to fit down. By this deportment he ſo much gained the affections of the people, that upon a vague report of his being ſlain by ſurpriſe, they ran about the ſtreets in the utmoſt rage and conſternation, with horrid imprecations againſt all ſuch as were ac-ceſſary to his death ; nor could they be appeaſed, until they were aſſured, with certainty, of his ſafety. He •took a more than ordinary care that Ro"me ſhould be continually ſupplied with corn and proviſions, ſecuring the merchants againſt pirates. He was not leſs affi-duous in his buildings, in which he excelled almoſt all that went before him. He conſtructed a wonderful aquæduct, called after his own name, much ſurpafling any other in Rome, either for w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>orkroanffιip or plentiful ſupply. It-brought water from 40 miles diſtance, through great mountains, and over deep valleys ; being built on ſtately arches, and furniſhing the higheſt parts of the city. He made alſo an haven at Oſtia ; a work of ſuch immenſe expence, that his ſucceffors were unable to maintain it. But his greateſt work of all was the draining of the lake Fucinus, which was the largeſt in Italy, and bringing its water into the Tiber, in order to ſtrengthen the current of that river. For effecting this, among other vaſt difficulties, he mined through a mountain of ſtone three miles broad, and kept 30,000 men eu∣ployed for 11 years together.</p><p>To this ſolicitude for-the internal advantages of the ſtate, he added that of a watchful guardianſhip over the provinces. He reſtored Judea to Herod Agrippa, which Caligula had taken from Herod Antipas, his uncle, the man who had put John the Baptiſt to death, and who was baniſhed by order of the preſent emperor. Claudius alſo reſtored ſuch princes to their kingdoms as had been unjuſtly diſpoſſeſſed by his predeceſſors ; but deprived the Lycians and Rhodians of their liberty, for having promoted inſurrections, and crucified ſome citizens of Rome.</p><p>He even undertook to gratify the people by foreign conqueſt. The Britons, who had, for near too years, been left in ſole pofſeſfion of their own iſland, began to ſeek the mediation of Rome, to quell their inteſtine commotions. The principal man who deſired to ſubject his native country to the Roman dominion, was</p><lb/><p>one Bericus, who, by many arguments, perſuaded the emperor to make a deſcent upon the iſland, m.ιgnify-ing the advantages that would attend the conqneſt of it. In purſuance of his advice, therefore, Plautius the praetor was ordered to paſs over into Gaul, and make preparations for this great expedition. At firſt, indeed, his ſoldiers ſeemed backward to embark ; declaring, that they were unwilling to make war beyond the limits of the w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>orld, for ſo they judged Britain to be. However, they were at laſt perſuaded to go ; and the Britons, under the conduct of their king Cynobelinus, were ſeveral times overthrown. And theſe ſucceſſes ſoon after induced Claudius to go into Britain in perſon, upon pretence that the natives were ſtill ſeditious, and had not delivered up ſome Roman fugitives who had taken ſhelter among them ; but for a particular account of the exploits of the Romans in this iſland, ſee the article England.</p><p>But though Claudius gave in the beginning of his reign the higheſt hopes of an happy continuance, he ſoon be fan to leſſen his care for the public, and to commit to his favourites all the concerns of the empire. This weak prince was unable to act but under the direction of others. The chief of his directors was his wiſe Meſſalina : whoſe name is almoſt become a common appellation to women of abandoned characters. However, ſhe was not leſs remarkable for her cruelties than her luſts ; as by her intrigues ſhe deſtroyed many of the moſt illuſtrious families of Rome. Subordinate to her were the emperor’s'ſreedmen ; Pallas, the trea-ſurer ; Narciſſus, the ſecretary of ſtate ; and Calliſtus, the maſter of the requeſts. Theſe entirely governed Claudius; ſo that he was only left the.fatigues of ceremony, while they were poſſeſſed of all the power of the ſtate.</p><p>It would be tedious to enumerate the various cruelties which theſe inſidious adviſers obliged the feeble emperor to commit : thoſe againſt his own family will ſuſfice. Appius Silanus, a perſon of great merit, who had been married to the emperor’s mother-in-law, was put to death upon the ſuggeſtions of Meſſalina. After him lie flew both his ſons-in-law, Silanus and Pompey, and his two nieces the Livias, one the daughter of Druſus, the other of Germanicus ; and all without permitting them to plead in their defence, or even without affigning any cauſe for his diſpleaſure. Great numbers of others fell a ſacriſice to the jealouſy of Meſ-ſalina and her minions ; who bore ſo great a ſway in the ſtate, that all offices, dignities, and governments, were entirely at their diſpoſal. Every thing was put to ſale : they took money for pardons and penalties ; and accumulated, by theſe means, ſuch vaſt ſums, that the wealth of Crœfus was conſidered as nothing in compariſon. One day, the emperor complaining that his exchequer was exhauſted, he was ludicrouſly told, that it might be ſufficiently repleniſlied if his two ſreedmen would take him into partnerſhip. Still, however, during ſuch corruption, he regarded his favourites with the higheſt eſteem, and even ſolicited the ſenate to grant them peculiar marks of their approbation. Theſe diſorders in the miniſters of government did not fail to produce conſpiracies againſt the emperor. Statius Corvinus and Gallus Affinius formed a conſpiracy againſt him Two knights, whoſe names are not told us, privately combined to aſſaſſinate him. But the revolt</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>