<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>receive the ſame ſupport, and ſuffer the fame ſtrain, if, inſtead of the blocks E and G, we ſubſtſtute the ropes E <hi rend="italic">f e,</hi>  G <hi rend="italic">hg,</hi>  going over the pulleys <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  andy, and loaded with proper weights <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">g.</hi>  The weight <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  is equal to the ſupport given by the block E ; and <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  is equal to the ſupport given by G. The ſum of <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  and y is equal to W ; and, on whatever point W is hung, the weights <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  and y are to W in the proportion of Γ)G and DE to GE. Now, in this ſtate of things, it appears that the ſtrain on the ſection CD ariſes immediately from the upward action of the ropes F <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  and H <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  or the upward preſſions of the blocks E and G ; and that the office of the weight W is to oblige the beam to oppoſe this ſtrain. Things are in the ſame ſtate in reſpect of ſtrain as if a block were ſubſtituted at D for the weight W, and the weights <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  were hung on at E and G ; only the directions will be oppoſite. The beam tends to break in the ſection CD, becauſe the ropes pull it upwards at E and G, while a weight W holds it down at C. It tends to open at D, and C becomes the centre of fracture. The ſtrain therefore is the ſame as if the half ED were fixed in the wall, and a weight equal to <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  that is, to the half of W, were hung on at G.</p><p>Hence we conclude, that a beam ſupported at both ends, but not fixed there, and loaded in the middle, will carry twice as much weight as it can carry at its extremity, when the other extremity is faſt in a wall.</p><p>The ſtrain occaſioned at any point L by a weight W, hung on at any other point D, is — W ×</p><p>DE _ <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>, <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>,<hi rend="sub">z</hi>, .    <hi rend="sub">τττ</hi> ,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">j7q × LG. For EG is to ED as W to the preſſure</hi></p><p>occaſioned at G. This would be balanced by ſome weight ç acting over the pulley <hi rend="italic">h ;</hi>  and this tends to break the beam at L, by acting on the lever GL. The</p><p><hi rend="italic">BE</hi></p><p>preſſure at G is    and therefore the ſtrain at L</p><p>is W. jF~√∙ LG.</p><p>In like manner, the ſtrain occaſioned at the point DE</p><p>D by the weight W hung on there, is W X DG ;</p><p>which is therefore equal to ⅜ W, when D is the middle point.</p><p>Hence we ſee, that the general ſtrain on the beam ariſing from one weight, is proportionable to the rec-</p><p>, <hi rend="sub">r</hi> ,    <hi rend="sub">r</hi> ,    „ W.DE.DG .</p><p>tangle of the parts of the beam, (for---is as</p><p>DE.DG,, and is greateſt when the load is laid on the middle of the beam.</p><p>We alſo ſee, that the ſti ain at L, by a load at D, is equal to the ſtrain at D by the ſame load at L. And the ſtrain at L, from a load at D, is to the ſtrain by the ſame load at L as DE to LE. Theſe are all very obvious corollaries ; and they ſufficiently inform us concerning the ſtrains which are produced on any part of the timber by a load laid on any other part.</p><p>If we now ſuppoſe the beam to be ſixed at the two ends, that is, firmly framed, or held down by blocks at I and K, placed beyond E and G, or framed into poſts, it will cany twice as much as when its ends were free. For ſuppoſe it ſawn through at CD ; the weight λ⅞ hung on there will be juſt ſufficient to break it at E and G. Now reſtore the connection of the ſec</p><lb/><p>tion CD, it will require another weight W to break it there at the ſame time.</p><p>Therefore, when a rafter, or any piece of timber, ia firmly connected with three fixed points G, E, I, it will bear a greater load between any two of them than if its connection with the remote point were removed ; and if it be faſtened in four points, G, E, I, K, it will be twice as ſtrong in the middle part as without the two remote connections.</p><p>One is apt to expect from this that the joiſt of a floor will be nauch ſtrengthened by being firmly built in the wall. It is a little ſtrengthened ; but the hold which can thus be given it is much too ſhort to be of any ſenſible ſervice ; and it tends greatly to ſhatter the wall, becauſe, when it is bent down by a load, it forces up the wail with the momentum of a long lever. Judicious buildeιs therefore take care not to bind the joiſts tight in the wall. But when the joiſt3 of adjoining rooms lie in the ſame direction, it is a great advantage to make them of one piece. They are then twice as ſtrong as when made in two lengths.</p><p>It is eaſy to deduce from theſe premiſſes the ſtrain on any point which ariſes from the weight of the beam it-felt; or from any load which is uniformly diſſuſed over the whole or any part. We may always conſider thé whole of the weight which is thus uniformly diſſuſed over any part as united in the middle point of that part ; and if the load is not uniformly diſſuſed, we may ſtill ſuppoſe it united at its centre of gravity. Thus, to know the ſtrain at L ariſing from the weight of the whole beam, we may ſuppoſe the whole weight accu- . mulated in its middle point D. Alſo the ſtrain at L<hi rend="sub">t </hi>ariſing from the weight of the part ED, is the ſame as if this weight were accumulated in the middle point<hi rend="italic">ci </hi>of ED ; and it is the ſame as if half the weight of ED were hung on at D. For the real ſtrain at L is the upward preſſure at G, acting by the lever GL. Now call the weight of the part DE <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  ; this upward preſſure</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub">ι</hi> e×</hi>  √ E ί ſ × DE will be J£G ’ °<hi rend="sup">r</hi>  EG .</p><p>Therefore the ſtrain on the middle of a beam, ari≈ fing from its own weight, or from any uniform load, it</p><p>• , ED</p><p>the weight of the beam or its load × ∣τθ × DG; that</p><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi>s, half the weight of the ſheam or load multiplied or acting by the lever DG ; for ED . <hi rend="sub">ι</hi></p><p>E G <hi rend="sup">1S</hi></p><p>Alſo the ſtrain at L, ariſing from the weight of the beam, or the unifoim load, is { the weight of the beam or load acting by the lever LG. It is therefore proportional to LG, and is greateſt of all at D. Therefore a beam of uniform ſtrength throughout, uniformly loaded, will bιeak in the middle.</p><p>It is of importance to know the relation between the ſtrains ariſing from the weights of the beams, or from any uniformly diſſuſed load, and the relative ſtrength. We have already ſeen, that the relative</p><p><hi rend="italic">. rdb.d</hi></p><p>ſtrength is y^ <hi rend="italic">fiſſt</hi>  where <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  is a number to be diſcovered by experiment for every different ſpecies of materials. Leaving out every circumſtance but what depends on the dimenſions of tlie beam, viz. <hi rend="italic">d, b,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">l,</hi>  we</p><p><hi rend="italic">. .    ‘    d'b</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">ſee</hi>  that the relative ſtrength is in the proportion of</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>