<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>van-guard, put many of the Epirots to the ſword, and took ſome of their elephants. Curius encouraged with this ſucceſs, marched his army into theTauraſian fields, and drew it up in a plain which was wide enough for his troops, but too narrow for the Epirot phalanx, the phalangites being ſo crowded that they could not handle their arms without difficulty. But the king’s eagerneſs to try his ſtrength and ſkill with ſo renowned a com-’ mander, made him engage at that great diſadvantage. Upon the firſt ſignal the action began ; and one of the king’s wings giving way, the victory ſeemed to incline to the Romans. But that wing where the king fought in perſon repulſed the enemy, and drove them back quite to their intrenchments. This advantage was in great part owing to the elephants ; which Curius perceiving, commanded a corps de reſerve, which he had poſted near the camp, to advance and fall upon the elephants. Theſe carrying burning torches in one hand, and their ſwords in the other, threw the former at the elephants, and with the latter defended themſelves againſt their guides ; by which means they were both forced to give way. The elephants being put to flight broke into the phalanx, cloſe as it was, and there cauſed a general diſorder ; which was increaſed by a remarkable accident: for it is ſaid, that a young elephant being wounded, and thereupon making a dreadful noiſe, the mother quitting her rank, and haſtening to the aſſiſtance of her young one, put thoſe who ſtill kept their ranks into the utmoſt confuſion. But, however that be, it is certain that the Romans obtained at laſt a complete victory. Oroſius and Eutropius tell us that Pyrrhus’s army conſiſted of 80,000 foot and 6ooo horſe, including his Epirots and allies ; whereas the conſular army was ſcarce 20,000 ſtrong. Thoſe who exaggerate the king’s loſs ſay, that the number of the ſlain on his ſide amounted to 30,000 men ; but others reduce it to 20,000. All writers agree, that Curius took 1200 priſoners and eight elephants. This victory, which was the moſt deciſive Rome had ever gained, brought all Italy under ſubjection, and paved the way for thoſe vaſt conqueſts which afterwards made the Romans maſters of the whole know<hi rend="sup">r</hi>n world.</p><p>Pyrrhus being no way in a condition, after the great loſs he had ſuſtained, to keep the field, retired to Ta-rentuιh<hi rend="sup">,</hi>, attended only by a ſmall body of horſe, leaving the Romans in full poſſeſſion of his camp ; which they ſo much admired, that they made it ever after a model to form theirs by. And now the king of Epirus reſolved to leave Italy as ſoon as poſſible; but concealed his deſign, and endeavoured to keep up the drooping ſpirits of his allies, by giving them hopes of ſpeedy ſuccours from Greece. Accordingly he diſpatched ambaſſadors into Ætolia, Illyricum, and Macedon, demanding ſupplies of men and money. But the anſwers from thoſe courts not proving ſavourable, he forged ſuch as might pleaſe thoſe whom he was willing to deceive ; and by this means ſupported the courage of his friends, and kept his enemy in play. When he could conceal his departure no longer, he pretended to be on a ſudden in a great paſſion at the dilatorineſs of his friends in ſending him ſuccours ; and acquainted the Tarentines, that he muſt go and bring them over himſelf. However, he leſt behind him a ſtrong garriſon in the citadel of Tarentum, under the command of the ſame Milo who had kept it for him during his ſtay in Sicily. In order to keep this governor in his duty, he is ſaid to have made him a very ſtrange preſent,<hi rend="italic">viz. </hi>a chair covered with the fl&lt;in of Nicias, the treacherous phyſician, who had offered Fabricius to poiſon his ma-' ſter. After all theſe diſguiſes and precautions, Pyrrhus at laſt ſet ſail for Epirus, and arrived ſafe at Acrocerau-nimn with 8000 foot and 500 horſe; after having ſpent to no purpoſe ſix years in Italy and Sicily.</p><p>Though, from the manner in which Pyrrhus took his leave, his Italian allies had little reaſon to expect any further aſſiſtance from him, yet they continued to amuſe themſelves with vain hopes, till certain accounts arrived of his being killed at the ſiege of Argos, as has been related under the article Epirus. This threw the Samnites into deſpair : ſo that they put all to the iſſue of a general battle ; in which they were defeated with fιιch dreadful ſlaughter, that the nation is ſaid to have been almoſt exterminated. This overthrow was ſoon followed by the ſubmiſſion of the Lucanians, Bruttians, Tarentines, Sarcinates, Picentes, and Salentines ; ſo that Rome now became miſtreſs of all the nations from the remoteſt parts of Hetruria to the Ionian ſea, and from the Tyrrhenian ſea to the Adriatic. All theſe nations, however, did not enjoy the ſame privileges. Some were entirely ſubject to the republic, and had no laws but what they received from thence ; others retained their old laws and cuſtoms, but in ſubjection to the republic : ſome were tributary; and others allies, who were obliged to furniſh troops at their own expence when the Romans required. Some had the privilege of Roman citizenſhip, their ſoldiers being incorporated in the legions; while others had a right of ſuffrage in the elections made by the centuries. Theſe different degrees of honour, privileges, and liberty, were founded on the different terms granted to the conquered nations when they ſurrendered, and were afterwards increaſed according to their fidelity and the ſervices they did the republic.</p><p>The Romans now became reſpected by foreign nations, and received ambaſſadors from Ptolemy Philadel-phus king of Egypt, and from Apollonia a city of Macedon. Senſible of their own importance, they now granted protection to whatever nation requeſted it of them ; but this not with a view of ſerving one party, but that they might have an opportunity of ſubjecting both. In this manner they aſſiſted the Mamertines againſt Hiero king of Syracuſe, which brought on the wars with the Carthaginians, which terminated in the total deſtruction of that ancient republic, as has been related under the article Carthage. The interval between the firſt and ſecond Punic wars was by the Romans employed in reducing the Boii and Ligurians, who had revolted. Theſe were Gauliſh nations, who had always been very formidable to the Romans, and now gave one of their conſuls a notable defeat. However, he ſoon after ſufficiently revenged himſelf, and defeated the enemy with great ſlaughter ; though it was not till ſome time after, and with a good deal of difficulty, that they were totally ſubdued. During this interval alſo, the Romans ſeized on the iſlands of Sardinia, Corſica, and Malta ; and in the year 219 B. C. the two former were reduced to the form of a province. Papirius, who had ſubdued Corſica, demanded a triumph ; but not having intereſt enough to obtain it, he took a method entirely new to do himſelf juſtice. He put</p></body></text></TEI>