<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>edge of the quarters, eight feet aſunder ; frequently in ſingle croſs rows, in order to divide the ground into ſeparate wide plats or breaks, of from 20 to 30 or 40 feet wide, which alſo ſerves to ſhelter the ground a little in winter ; in all of which methods of planting them as ſtandards, they ſhould be generally trained up to a ſingle ſtem about a foot high, then ſuffered to branch out every way all around into buſhy heads, keeping the middle, however, open, and the branches moderately thin, to admit the fun and free air ; though if ſome are farmed, that is, trimmed on two ſides op-poſitely, ſo as to make the other branches range in a line like an eſpalier, they will take up much leſs of the ground, and, by admitting the fun and air more freely, they will produce large fair fruit. They are likewiſe trained againſt walls or palings, like other wall-trees, but principally ſome of the large red and white Dutch currants, in which they wall produce fine large fruit, and thoſe againſt any ſouth fence will ripen early, and be high flavoured ; but it is proper to plant a few both againſt ſouth, north, eaſt, and weft walls, in order to obtain the fruit ripe both early and late, in a long ſucceſſion. It is alſo proper to plant a few of the fineſt ſorts of gooſeberries againſt a warm fence, both to have early green gooſeberries for tarts, &amp;c. as well as to ripen early ; and they will grow very large and fine. Sometimes both currants and gooſeberries are alſo trained in low eſpaliers for variety, and they produce very fine fruit.</p><p>The fruits both of the currant and gooſeberry are of an acid and cooling nature, and as ſuch are ſome-times uſed in medicine, eſpecially the juice reduced to a jelly by boiling with ſugar. From the juice of currants alſo a very agreeable wine is made.</p><p>RICAUT, or Rycaut (Sir Paul), an eminent Engliſh traveller, of the time of whoſe birth we find no account ; but in 166r, he was appointed ſecretary to the earl of Winchelſea, who was ſent ambaſſador extraordinary to the Ottoman Porte. During his continuance in that ſtation, he wrote, “ The preſent State of the Ottoman Empire, in three books, containing the maxims of the Turkiſh policy, their religion, and military diſcipline,” London, folio, 1670. He afterwards reſided 1 x years as conſnl at Smyrna, where, at the command of Charles II. he compoſed “ The preſent ſtate of the Greek and Armenian Churches, <hi rend="italic">anno Cl)r∙ifti</hi>  1678.” On his return, Lord Clarendon being appointed lord-lieutenant of Ireland, made him his principal ſecretary for Leinſter and Connaught : king James II. knighted him ; and made him one of the privy council in Ireland, and judge of the court of admiralty ; all which he held to the Revolution. He was employed by King William as reſident at the Hanſe-towns in Lower Saxony, where he continued for ten years ; but being worn out with age and infirmities, he obtained leave to return in 1700, and died the fame year. Ricaut continued “ Knolles’s Hiſtory of the Turks, and Platina’s Lives of the Popes beſides which, there are ſome other productions under his name.</p><p>RICCIA, in botany : A genus of the natural order of algæ, belonging to the cryptogamia claſs of plants. There is no calyx, but a veſicular cavity within the ſub-ſtance of the leaf. There is no corolla ; the antheræ are cylindrical, and ſeſſile, placed on the germen, which is turbinated ; the ſtyle is filiform, perforating the an-</p><p>thera ; and the ſeed-caſe is ſpherical, crowned with the withered anthera ; the ſeeds are hemiſpherical and pedi-cellatcd.</p><p>RICE. SeeθRYZA. “ Rice <hi rend="italic">bras,</hi>  (ſays MrMarf∙ den) whilſt in the hulk, is in India called <hi rend="italic">paddee,</hi>  and aſſumes a different name in each of its other various ſtates. We obſerve no diſtinction of this kind in Europe, where our grain retains through all its ſtages, till it becomes flour, its original name of barley, -wheat, or oats. The following, beſide many others, are names applied to rice, in its different ſtages of growth and preparation: <hi rend="italic">paddee,</hi>  original name of the ſeed: <hi rend="italic">oojſay,</hi>  grain of laſt ſeaſon : <hi rend="italic">buηηee,</hi>  the plants before removed to the ſawoors : <hi rend="italic">bras</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">bray,</hi>  rice, the huſk of the paddee being taken off : <hi rend="italic">charroop,</hi>  rice cleaned for boiling ; <hi rend="italic">naſſe, </hi>boiled rice : <hi rend="italic">peeraηg,</hi>  yellow rice : <hi rend="italic">jambar,</hi>  a ſervice of rice, &amp;c.</p><p>Among people whoſe general objects of contemplation are few, thoſe which do of neceſſity engage their attention, are often more nicely diſcriminated than the fame objects among more enlightened people, whoſe ideas ranging over the extenſive field of art and ſeience, diſdain to fix long on obvious and common matters.* <hi rend="italic">Paddee, </hi>on Sumatra and the Malay iſlands, is diftin-guiſhed into two ſorts ; <hi rend="italic">Laddang</hi>  or up-land paddee, and <hi rend="italic">Saιvoor</hi>  or low-land, which are always kept ſeparate, and will not grow reciprocally. Of theſe the former bears the higher price, being a whiter, heartier, and better flavoured grain, and having the advantage in point of keeping. The latter is much more prolific from the ſeed, and liable to leſs rifle in the culture, but is of a watery ſubſtance, produces leſs increaſe in boiling, and is ſubject to a ſwiſter decay. It is, however, in more common uſe than the former. Beſide this general diſtinction, the paddee of each fort, particularly the Laddang, preſents a variety of ſpecies, which, as far as my information extends, I ſhall enumerate, and endeavour to deſcribe. The common kind of dry ground paddee : colour, light brown : the ſize rather large, and very little crooked at the extremity. Paddee <hi rend="italic">undallong: </hi>dry ground : ſhort round grain : grows in whorles or bunches round the ſtock. Paddee <hi rend="italic">ebbaſs:</hi>  dry ground : large grain : common. Paddee <hi rend="italic">gαlloo</hi>  .∙ dry ground : light coloured : ſcarce. Paddee <hi rend="italic">ſennee :</hi>  dry ground : deep coloured ; ſmall grain : ſcarce. Paddee <hi rend="italic">ejoo :</hi>  dry-ground ; light coloured. Paddee <hi rend="italic">kooning :</hi>  dry ground : deep yelfow : fine rice : crooked, and pointed. Paddee <hi rend="italic">coocoor ballum :</hi>  dry ground : much eſteemed : light coloured ; ſmall, and very much crooked, reſetnbling a dove’s nail, ſrom whence its name. Paddee <hi rend="italic">peſang : </hi>dιy ground : outer coat light brown ; inner red : longer, ſmaller, and leſs crooked than the <hi rend="italic">coocoor ballum. </hi>Paddee <hi rend="italic">Saηtong :</hi>  the fineſt ſort that is planted in wet ground : ſmall, ſtraight, and light coloured. In general it may be obſerved that the larger grained rice is the leaſt eſteemed, and the ſmaller and whiter the moſt prized. In the Lampoon country they make a diſtinction of paddee <hi rend="italic">cranυaηg</hi>  and paddee <hi rend="italic">jerroo ;</hi>  the former of which is a month earlier in growth than the latter.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">RιcB~Bird.</hi>  See Oryzivera.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R ιcE-Bnnting.</hi>  See Emberiza.</p><p>RICHARD I. II. and III. kings of England. See England.</p><p>RICHARDIA, in botany: A genus of the mono-gynia order, belonging to the hexandria claſs of plants;</p></body></text></TEI>