<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>memory with every reproach. H's ſtatues were commanded to be taken down ; and a decree was made, that all his inſeriptions ſhould be eraſed, his name ſtruck out of the regiſters of fame, and his funeral omitted. The people, who now took little part in the affairs of government, looked on his death with indifference ; the ſoldiers alone, whom he had loaded with favours, and enriched by largeſſes, ſincerely regretted their benefactor. The ſenate, therefore, reſolved to provide a ſucceſſor before the army could have an opportunity of taking the appointment upon themſelves ; and Cocceius Nerva was choſen to the empire the very day on which the tyrant was ſlain.</p><p>Nerva was of an illuſtrious family, as moſt ſay, by birth a Spaniard, and above 65 years old when he was called to the throne. He was, at that time, the moſt remarkable man in Rome, for his virtues, moderation, and reſpect to the laws ; and he owed his exaltation to the blameleſs conduct of his former life. When the ſenate went to pay him their ſubmiſſions, he received them with his accuſtomed humility ; while Arius Antonius, his moſt intimate friend, having embraced him with great familiarity, congratulated him on his acceſſion to the empire : and indeed no emperor had ever ſhewn himſelf more worthy of the throne than Nerva ; his only fault being that he was too indulgent, and often made a prey by his inſidious courtiers.</p><p>However, an exceſs of indulgence and humanity were faults that Rome could eaſily pardon, after the cruelties of ſuch an emperor as Domitian. Being long accuſtomed to tyranny, they regarded Nerva’s gentle reign with rapture, and even gave his imbecility the name of benevolence. Upon coming to the throne, he ſolemnly ſwore that no ſenator of Rome ſhould be put to death by his command, during his reign, though they gave ever ſo juſt a cauſe. He conferred great favours, and beſtowed large gifts, upon his particular friends. His liberality was ſo extenſive, that, upon his firſt promotion to the empire, he was conſtrained to ſell his gold and ſilver plate, with his other rich moveables, to enable him to continue his liberalities. He releaſed the cities of the empire from many ſevere impoſitions, which had been laid upon them by Veſpaſian ; took off a rigorous tribute, which had been laid upon carriages; and reſtored thoſe to their property who had been unjuſtly diſpoſſeſſed by Domitian.</p><p>During his ſhort reign he made ſeveral good laws. He particularly prohibited the caſtration of male children ; which had been likewiſe condemned by his predeceſſor, but not wholly removed. He put all thoſe ſlaves to death who had, during the laſt reign, informed againſt their maſters. He permitted no ſtatues to be erected to honour him, and converted into money ſuch of Domitian’s as had been ſpared by the ſenate. He ſold many rich robes, and much of the ſplendid furniture of the palace, and retrenched ſeveral unrea-fonable expences at court. At the ſame time, he had ſo little regard for money, that when Herodes Atticus, one of his ſubjects, had found a large treaſure, and wrote to the emperor how to diſpoſe of it, he received for anſwer, that he might <hi rend="italic">uſe it ;</hi>  but tire finder ſtill informing the emperor that it was a fortune too large for a private perſon, Nerva, admiring his honeſty, wrote him word, that then he might <hi rend="italic">abuſe it.</hi></p><p>A hſe of ſuch generoſity and mildneſs was not,</p><p>however, without its enemies. Calpurnius Craſſiis, with ſome others, formed a dangerous conſpiracy to deſtroy him ; but Nerva would uſe no ſeverity : he reſted ſatisfied with baniſhing thoſe who were culpable, though the ſenate were for inflicting more rigorous puniſhments. But the moſt dangerous inſurrection againſt his intereſts was from the prætorian bands ; who, headed by Caſpa-rius Olianus, inſiſted upon revenging the late emperor’s death, whoſe memory was ſtill dear to them from his frequent liberalities. Nerva, whoſe kindneſs to good men rendered him ſtill more obnoxious to the vicious, did all in his power to ſtop the progreſs of this inſurrection ; he preſented himſelf to the mutinous ſoldiers, and, opening his boſom, deſired them to ſtrike there, rather than be guilty of ſo much injuſtice. The ſoldiers, however, paid no regard to his remonſtrances ; but, ſeizing upon Petronius and Parthenius, flew the n in the moſt ignominious manner. Not content with this, they even compelled the emperor to approve of their ſedition, and to make a ſpeech to-the people, in which he thanked the cohorts ſor their fidelity. So diſagreeable a conſtraint upon the emperor’s inclinations was, in the end, attended with the moſt happy effects, as it cauſed the adoption of Trajan to ſucceed him in the empire. Nerva perceived that in the preſent turbulent diſpoſition of the times, he ſtood in need of an aſſiſtant in the empire, who might ſhare the fatigues of government, and contribute to keep the licentious in awe. For this purpoſe, ſetting aſide all his own relations, he fixed upon Ulpius Trajan, an utter ſtranger to his family, who was then governor in Upper Germany, to ſucceed him. Having put his determination in execution, and performed the accuſtomed ſolemnities, he inſtantly ſent off ambaſſadors to Cologne, where Trajan then reſided, intreating his aſſiſtance in puniſhing thoſe from whom he had received ſuch an inſult The adoption of this admirable man, proved ſo great a curb to the licentiouſneſs of the ſoldiery, that they continued in perfect obedience during the reſt of this reign ; and Caſparius being ſent to him, was, by his command, either baniſhed or put to death.</p><p>The adopting Trajan was the laſt public act of Nerva. In about three months after, having put him· ſelf in a violent paſſion with one Regulus a ſenator, he was ſeized with a fever, of which he ſhortly after died, after a ſhort reign of one year four months and nine days. He was the firſt foreign emperor who reigned in Rome, and juſtly reputed a prince of great generoſity and moderation. He is alſo celebrated for his wiſdom, though with leſs reaſon, the greateſt inſtance he gave of it, during his reign, being in the choice of his ſucceſſor.</p><p>Trajan’s family was originally ſrom Italy, but he himſelf was born in Seville in Spain. He very early accompanied his father, who was a general of the Romans, in his expeditions along the Euphrates and the Rhine ; and while yet very young, acquired a conſiderable reputation for military accompliſhments. He enured his body to fatigue ; he made long marches on foot ; and laboured to acquire all that ſkill in war which was neceſſary for a commander. When he was made general of the army in Lower Germany, which was one of the moſt conſiderable employments in the empire, it made no alteration in his manners or way of living ; and the commander was ſeen noway differing from the private tribune, except in his ſuperior wiſdom and vir-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>