<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>reſolved not to give him battle, but rather to diſtreſs him by keeping cloſe at his heels, ſtraitening his quarters, and cutting off his convoys. As he had frequent opportunities of coming to an engagement, but always declined it, his friends and ſubalterna began to put ill conſtructions on his dilatorineſs to his face.</p><p>Theſe, together with the complaints of his ſoldiers, made him at length reſolve to venture a general action. With this deſign he marched into a large plain near the cities of Pharſalia and Thebes ; which latter was alſo called <hi rend="italic">Philippi,</hi>  from Philip king of Macedon, and the father of Perſes, who, having reduced the Thebans, placed a colony of Macedonians in their city. This plain was watered by the Enipeus, and ſurrounded on all ſides by high mountains ; and Pompey, who was ſtill averſe from venturing an engagement, pitched his camp on the declivity of a ſteep mountain, in a place altogether inacceſſible. There he was joined by Scipio his father-in-law, at the head of the legions which he had brought with him from Syria and Cilicia. But notwithſtanding this reinforcement, he continued irre-ſolute, and unwilling to put all to the iſſue of a ſingle action ; being ſtill convinced of the wiſdom of his maxim, that it was better to deſtroy the enemy by fatigues and want, than to engage an army of brave veterans, who were in a manner reduced to deſpair. As he put off from day to day, under various pretences, deſcending into the plain where Cæſar was encamped, his officers forced him to call a council of war, when all to a man. were for venturing a general action the very next day. Thus was Pompey obliged to ſacriſice his own judgment to the blind ardour of the multitude ; and the neceſſary meaſures were taken for a general engagement.</p><p>The event of this battle was in the higheſt degree fortunate for Cæſar j- ; who reſolved to purſue his advantage, and follow Pompey to whatever country he ſhould retire. Hearing, therefore, of his being at Am-phipolis, he ſent off his troops before him, and then embarked on board a little frigate in order to croſs the Helleſpont ; but in the middle of the ſtrait, he ſell in with one of Pompey’s commanders, at the head of ten ſhips of war. Cæſar, noway terrified at the ſuperiority of his force, bore up to him, and commanded him to ſubmit. The other inſtantly obeyed, awed by the terror of Cæſar’s name, and ſurrendered himſelf and his fleet at diſcretion.</p><p>From thence he continued his voyage to Epheſus, then to Rhodes ; and being informed that Pompey had been there before him, he made no doubt but that he was fled to Egypt ; wherefore,, lofing no time, he ſet ſail for that kingdom, and arrived at Alexandria with about 4000 men ; a very inconſiderable force to keep ſuch a powerful kingdom under ſubjection. But he was now grown ſo ſecure in his good fortune, that he expected to find obedience everywhere. Upon his landing, the firſt accounts he received were of Pompey’s miſerable end, who had been aſſaſſinated by orders of the treacherous king as ſoon as he went on ſhore ; and ſoon after one of the murderers came with his head and ring as a moſt grateful preſent to the conqueror. But Cæſar turned away from it with horror, and ſhortly after ordered a magnificent tomb to be built to his memory on The ſpot where he was murdered ; and a temple near the place, to Nemeſis, who was the goddeſs</p><lb/><p>that puniſhed thoſe that were cruel to men in adverſity.</p><p>It ſhould ſeem that the Egyptians by this time had ſome hopes of breaking off all alliance with the Ro·» naans ; which they conſidered, as in fact it was, but a ſpecious ſubjection. They firſt began to take offence at Cæſar’s carrying the enſigns of Roman power before him as he entered the city. Photinus, the eunuch, alſo treated him with diſreſpect, and even attempted his liſe. Cæſar, however, concealed his reſentment till he had a force ſufficient to puniſh his treachery ; and ſending privately for the legions which had been formerly enrolled for Pompey’s ſervice, as being the neareſſ to E-gypt, he in the mean time pretended to repoſe an entire conſidence in the king’s minifter. However, he ſoon changed his manner when he found himſelf in no danger from his attempts ; and declared, that, as being a Roman conſul, it was his duty to ſettle the ſucceſſion to the Egyptian crown.</p><p>There were at that time two pretenders to the crown of Egypt : Ptolemy, the acknowledged king ; and the celebrated Cleopatra his ſiſſer ; who, by the cuftom of the country, was alſo his wiſe, and, by their father’s will, ſliared jointly in the ſucceſſion. However, not being contented with a bare participation of power, ſhe aimed at governing alone ; but being oppoſed in her views by the Roman ſenate, who confirmed her brother’s title to the crown, ſhe was banif∩ed into Syria with Ar-ſinoe her younger ſiſter.</p><p>Cæſar, however, gave her new hopes of obtaining the kingdom, and ſent both for her and her brother to plead their cauſe before him. Photinus, the young king’s guardian, who had long borne the moſt inveterate hatred as well to Cæſar as to Cleopatra; diſdained this propoſal, and backed his refuſal by ſending an army of 20,000 men to beſiege him in Alexandria. Cæſar bravely repulſed the enemy for ſome time ; but finding the city of too great extent to be defended by ſe&gt; ſmall an army as he then had with him, he retired to the palace, which commanded the harbour, where he purpo-ſed to make a ſtand. Achillas, who commanded the Egyptians, attacked him there with great vigour, and ſtill aimed at making himſelf maſter of the fleet that lay before the palace. Cæſar, however, too well knew the importance of thoſe ſhips in the hands of an enemy ; and therefore burnt them all in ſpite of every effort to prevent it. He next poſſeſſed himſelf of the iſte of Pharos, which was the key to the Alexandrian port, by which he was enabled to receive the ſup. plies ſent him from all ſides ; and in this ſituation he determined to withſtand the united force of all the Egyptians-</p><p>In the mean time, Cleopatra having heard of the preſent turn in her favour, reſolved to depend rather on Cæſar’s favour for gaining the government than her own forces. She had, in fact, aſſembled an army in Syria to ſupport her claims-; but now judged it the wiſeſt way to rely entirely on the deciſion of her ſelf-elected judge. But no arts, as ſhe juſtly conceived, were ſo likely to influence Cæſar, as the charms of her perſon. The difficulty was how to get at Cæſar, as her enemies were in poſſeſſion of all the avenues that led to the palace. For this purpoſe, ſhe went on board a ſmall veſſel, and in the evening landed near the palace j where, being wrapped up in a coverlet, ſhe wa&gt;</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>