<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to their camp, he was immediately proclaimed; and ſuch were the hopes of his virtues, that all men began to affect his intereſts.</p><p>Macrinus, who at this time was purſuing his pleaſures at Antioch, gave but little attention to the firſt report ; only ſending his lieutenant Julian, with ſome legions, to quell the inſurrection. However, theſe, like the reſt, ſoon declared for Heliogabalus, and flew their general. It was then that Macrinus found he had treated the rebellion too ſlightly ; he therefore reſolved, with his ſon, to march directly againſt the ſeditious legions, and force them to their duty. Both parties met on the confines of Syria : the battle was for ſome time furious and obſtinate ; but at laſt Macrinus was overthrown, and obliged to ſeek ſafety by flight. His principal aim was to get to Rome, where he knew his preſence was deſired ; wherefore he travelled through the provinces of Aſia Minor with the utmoſt expedition and privacy, but unfortunately ſell ſick at the city of Chalcedon. There thoſe who were ſent in purſuit, overtook and put him to death, together with his ſon Diadumenus, after a ſhort reign of one year and two months.</p><p>The ſenate and citizens of Rome being obliged to ſubmit to the appointment of the army as uſual, Heliogabalus aſcended the throne at the age of 14. One at ſo early an age, inveſted with unlimited power, and fur-rounded with flatterers, could be expected to act only as they thought proper to direct. This young emperor was entirely led by them ; and being ſenſible that it was in his power to indulge all his appetites, he ſtudied only their gratification. As he is deſcribed by hiſtorians, he appears a monſter of ſenſuality. His ſhort liſe therefore is but a tiſſue of effeminacy, luſt, and extravagance. He married, in the ſmall ſpace of four years, ſix wives, and divorced them all. He built a temple to the ſun ; and willing that his god ſhould have a wife as well as himſelf, he married him to Pallas, and ſhortly after to the moon. His palace was a place of rendezvous for all the proſtitutes of Rome, whom he frequently met naked, calling them <hi rend="italic">his fellow ſoldiers, and companions in the field.</hi>  He was ſo fond of the ſex, that he carried his mother with him to the ſenate-houſe, and demanded that ſhe ſhould always be preſent when matters of importance were debated. He even went ſo far as to build a ſenate-houſe for women, with ſuitable orders, habits, and diſtinctions, of which his mother was made preſident. They met ſeveral times ; all their debates turning upon the faſhions of the day, and the different formalities to be uſed in giving and receiving viſits. To theſe follies, he added great cruelty and boundleſs prodigality ; ſo that he was heard to ſay, that ſuch diſhes as were cheaply obtained were ſcarce worth eating. His ſuppers therefore generally coſt 6000 crowns, and oſten 60,000. He was always dreſſed in cloth of gold and purple, enriched with precious ſtones, and yet never wore the ſame habit twice. His palace, his chambers, and his beds, were all furniſhed of the richeſt ſtuffs, covered with gold and jewels. Whenever he took horſe, all the way between his apartment and the place of mounting was covered with gold and ſilver duſt ſtrewn at his approach.</p><p>Theſe exceſſes were ſoon perceived by his grandmother Mæfa , whoſe intrigues had firſt raiſed him to the throne ; ſo that ſhe thought to leſſen his power by di-</p><lb/><p>viding it. Tor this purpoſe, under a pretence of freeing him from the cares of public buſineſs, ſhe perſuaded him to adopt his couſin-german, Alexander, as his ſucceffor ; and likewiſe to make him his partner in the conſulſhip. Heliogabalus, having thus raiſed his couſin, had ſcarce given him his power, when he wiſhed again to take it away ; but the virtues of this young prince had ſo greatly endeared the people and the army to him, that the attempt had like to have been fatal to the tyrant himſelf. The prætorian ſoldiers mutinying, attempted to kill him as he was walking in his gardens; but he eſcaped, by hiding himſelf from their fury. However, upon returning to their camp, they continued the ſedition ; requiring that the emperor ſhould remove ſuch perſons from about him as oppreſſed the ſubject, and contributed to contaminate him. They required alſo the being permitted to guard the young prince themſelves, and that none of the emperor’s favourites or familiars ſhould ever be permitted to con-verſe with him. Heliogabalus was reluctantly obliged to comply ; and conſcious of the danger he was in, made preparations for death, when it ſhould arrive, in a manner truly whimſical and peculiar. He built a lofty tower with ſteps of gold and pearl, from whence to throw himſelf headlong in caſe of neceſſity. He alſe prepared cords of purple ſilk and gold to ſtrangle himſelf with ; he provided golden ſwords and daggers te ſtab himſelf with ; and poiſon to be kept in boxes of emerald, in order to obtain what death he choſe beſt Thus ſearing all things, but particularly ſuſpſeious of the deſigns of the ſenate, he baniſhed them all out of the city : he next attempted to poiſon Alexander, and ſpread a report of his death ; but perceiving the ſoldiers begin to mutiny, he immediately took him in his chariot to the canrp, where he experienced a freſh mortification, by finding all the acclamations of the army directed only to his ſucceſſor. This not a little raiſed his indignation, and excited his deſire of revenge. He returned towards the city, threatening the moſt ſevere puniſhments againſt thoſe who had diſpleaſed him, and meditating freſh cruelties. However, the ſoldiers were unwilling to give him time to put his deſigns in execution : they followed him directly to his palace, purſued him from apartment to apartment, and at laſt found him concealed in a privy ; a ſituation very different from that in which he expected to die. Having dragged him from thence through the ſtreets, with the moſt bitter invectives, and having diſpatched him, they attempted once more to ſqueeze his pampered body into a privy; but not eaſily effecting this, they threw it into the Tiber, with heavy weights, that none might afterwards find or give it burial. This was the miſerable and ignominious death of Heliogabalus, in the 18th year of his agc, after a deteſtable reign of four years. His mother alſo was ſlain at the ſame time by the ſoldiers ; as were alſo many of the opprobrious aſſociates of his criminal pleaſures.</p><p>Alexander being, without oppoſition, declared emperor, the ſenate, in their uſual method of adulation, were for conferring new titles upon him ; but he modeſtly declined them all, alleging, that titles were only honourable when given to virtue, not to ſtation. This outſet was an happy omen of his future virtues ; and few princes in hiſtory have been more commended by his contemporaries, or indeed more deſerved commenda-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>