<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Mr Bruce's description ofthe ſources of the Nile, and of the reſpect paid to the ſacred waters, has not a frowning feature ; and the hoſpitable old man, with his fair daughter Irepone, and the gentle prieſthood which peopled the little village of Geeſh, forms a contrait with the neighbouring Galla (among whom a military leader was called the <hi rend="italic">lamb,</hi>  becauſe he did not murder pregnant women), which very diſtinctly paints the inſpiring principle of this ſuperſtition. Pliny ſays (VIII. 8.) that at the ſource of the Clitumnus there is an ancient temple highly reſpected. The pre-ſence and the power of the divinity are expreſſed by the fates which ſtand in the veſtibule.—Around this temple are ſeveral little chapels, each of which covers a ſacred fountain ; for the Clitumnus is the father of ſeveral little rivers which unite their ſtreams with him. At ſome diſtance below the temple is a bridge which divides the ſacred waters from thoſe which ate open to common uſe. No one muſt preſume to ſet his foot in the ſtreams above this bridge ; and to ſtep over any of them is an indignity which renders a perſon infamous. They can only be viſited in a conſecrated boat. Below the bridge we are permitted to bathe, and the place is inceſſantly occupied by the neighbouring villagers. (See alſo <hi rend="italic">Vibius Sequeſtr. Orbelini,</hi>  p. ιoι— 103. and 221—223. alſo <hi rend="italic">Sueton. Calcula,</hi>  c. 43. <hi rend="italic">Vlrg. Georg. IL</hi>  146.)</p><p>What is the cauſe of all this ? The Clitumnus flows (near its ſource) through the richeſt paſtures, through which it was carefully diſtributed by numberleſs drains; and theſe nouriſhed cattle of ſuch ſpotleſs whiteneſs and extraordinary beauty, that they were fought for with eagerneſs over all Italy, as the moſt acceptable victims in their ſacriflces. Is not this ſuperſtition then an ef-fuſion of gratitude ?</p><p>Such are the dictates of kind-hearted nature in our breaſts, before it has been vitiated by vanity and ſelf-conceit, and we ſhould not be aſhamed of feeling the impreſſion. We hardly think of making any apology for dwelling a little on this incidental circumſtance of the ſuperſtitious veneration paid to rivers. We cannot think that our readers will be diſpleaſed at having agreeable ideas excited in their minds, being always of opinion that the torch of true philofophy will not only enlighten the underſtanding, but alſo warm and cheriſh the affections of the heart.</p><p>With reſpect to the origin of rivers, we have very little to offer in this place. It is obvious to every perſon, that beſides the torrents which carry down into the rivers what part of the rains and melted ſnows is not abforbed by the foil or taken up by the plants which cover the earth, they are fed either immediately or remotely by the ſprings. A few remarkable ſtreams ruſh at once out of the earth in force, and muſt be conſidered as the continuation of ſubterraneous rivers, whoſe origin we are therefore to ſeek out ; and we do not know any circumſtance in which their firſt beginnings differ from thoſe of other rivers, which are formed by the union of little ſtreams and rills, each of which has its own ſource in a ſpring or fountain. This queſtion, therefore, What is the proceſs of nature, and what are the ſupplies which fill our ſprings ? will be treated of under the word SpRing.</p><p>Whatever be the ſource of rivers, it is to be met with in almoſt every part of the globe. The cruſt of.</p><lb/><p>earth with which the rocky framing of thia globe is covered is generally ſtratified. Some of theſe ſtrataare extremely pervious to water, having but ſmall attrac∙ tion for its particles, and being very porous. Such is the quality of gravelly ſtrata in an eminent degree. Other ſtrata are much more firm, or attract water more ſtrongly, and refuſe it a paſſage. This is the caſe with firm rock and with clay. When a ſtratum of the firſt kind has one of the other immediately under it, the water remains in the upper ſtratum, and burſts out wherever the ſloping ſides of the hills cut off the ſtrata, and this will be in the form of a trickling ſpring, becauſe the water in the porous ſtratum is greatly obſtructed in its paſſage towards the outlet. As this irregular formation of the earth is very general, we muſt have ſprings, and of courſe rivers or rivulets, in every corner where there are high grounds.</p><p>Rivers flow from the higher to the low grounds. It is the arrangement of this elevation which diſtributes them over the ſurface of the earth. And this appears to<hi rend="sup">x</hi>be accompliſhed with conſiderable regularity; and, except the great deſert of Kobi on the confines of Chineſe Tartary, we do not remember any very extenſive track of ground that is deprived of thoſe channels for voiding the ſuperfluous waters ; and even there they are far ſrom being redundant.</p><p>The courſe of rivers give us the beſt general method for judging of the elevation of a country. Thus it appears that Savoy and Switzerland are the higheſt grounds of Europe, from whence the ground ſlopes in every direction. From the Alps proceed the Danube and the Rhine, whoſe courſes mark the two great valleys, into which many lateral ſtreams deſcend. The Po alſo and the Rhone come from the ſame head, and with a ſteeper and ſhorter courſe find their way to the ſea through valleys of leſs breadth and length. On the weſt ſide of the valleys of the Rhine and the Rhone the ground riſes pretty faſt, ſo that few tributary ſtreams come into them from that ſide ; and from this gentle elevation France ſlopes to the weſtward. If a line, nearly ſtraight, but bending a little to the northward, be drawn from the head of Savoy and Switzerland all the way to Solikamſkoy in Siberia, it will nearly paſs through the moſt elevated part of Europe ; for in this track moſt of the rivers have their riſe. On· the left go off the various feeders of the Elbe, the O-der, the Weſel, the Niemen, the Duna, the Neva, the Dwina, the Petzora. On the right, after paſſing the feeders of the Danube, we ſee the ſources of the Sereth and Pruth, the Dnieſter, the Bog, the Dnie∙ per, the Don, and the mighty Volga. The elevation, however, is extremely moderate ; and it appears from the levels taken with the barometer by the Abbé Chappe d’Auteroche, that the head of the Volga is not more than 470 feet above the ſurface of the ocean. And we may obſerve here by the bye, that its mouth, where it diſcharges its waters into the Caſpian ſea, is undoubtedly lower, by many feet, than the ſurface of the ocean. See Pneumatics, n<hi rend="sup">3</hi>277. Spain and Fin</p><p>land, with Lapland, Norway, and Sweden, form two detached parts, which have little ſymmetry with the reſt of Europe.</p><p>A chain of mountains begins in Nova Zembla, and ſtretches due ſouth to near the Caſpian Sea, dividing Europe from Aſia. About three or four degrees north</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>