<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>now ungovernable : having no enemy to wreck his reſentment upon, he turned it againſt his own commanders. He put many of his generals to death, as if the city had held out through their neglect or incapacity, while famine made great depredations upon the reſt of his army. Nothing now appeared on either ſide to terminate the conteſt, except the total deſtruction of either. But a mutiny in Maximinus’s own army a while reſcued the declining empire from deſtruction, and ſaved the lives of thouſands. The ſoldiers being long haraſſed by famine and fatigue, and hearing of revolts on every ſide, reſolved to terminate their calamities by the tyrant’s death. His great ſtrength, and his being always armed, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ere, at firſt, the principal motives to deter any from aſſaſſinating him ; but at length having made his guards accomplices in their deſign, they ſet upon him, while he ſlept at noon in his tent, and (lew both him and his ſon, whom he had made his partner in the empire, without any oppoſition, after an uſurpation of about three years, and in the 65th year of his age.</p><p>The tyrant being dead, and his body thrown to the dogs and birds of prey, Pupienus and Balbinus continued for ſome time emperors without oppoſition. But the prætorian ſoldiers, who had long been notorious for mutiny and treaſon, ſoon reſolved on further change. Nor did the diſſenſions between the new made emperors themſelves a little contribute to their downfall : for though both were remarkable for wiſdom and age, yet they could not reſtrain the mutual jealouſy of each other’s power. Pupienus claimed the ſuperiority from his great experience ; while Balbinus was equally aſpiring upon account of his family and fortune.</p><p>In this ill-judged conteſt, the prætorian ſoldiers, who were enemies to both, ſet upon them in their palace, at a time their guards were amuſed with ſeeing the Capitoline games. Pupienus perceiving their tumultuous approach, ſent with the utmoſt ſpeed for aſſiſtance from his colleague ; but he, out of a culpable ſuſpicion that ſomething was deſigned only againſt himſelf, refuſed to ſend ſuch of the German guards as were next his perſon. Thus the ſeditious ſoldiers found an eaſy acceſs to both the emperors apartments ; and dragging them from the palace towards the camp, flew them both, leaving their dead bodies in the ſtreets, as a dreadful inſtance of their ſedition.</p><p>In the midſt of this ſedition, as the mutineers were proceeding along, they by accident met Gordian, the grandſon of him who was ſlain in Africa, and declared him emperor on the ſpot. The ſenate and people had been loug reduced to the neceſſity of ſuffering their emperors to be nominated by the army ; ſo that all they could do in the preſent inſtance was to confirm their choice. This prince was but 16 years old when he began his reign, but his virtues ſeemed to compenſate for his want of experience. His principal aims were, to unite the oppoſing members of the government, and to reconcile the ſoldiers and citizens to each other. His learning is ſaid to have been equal to Lis virtues ; and we are aſſured that he had 62,000 books in his library. His reſpect for Mifithæus, his governor and inſtructor, was ſuch, that he married his daughter, and profited by his co-unſels in all the critical circumſtances of his reign.</p><p>The firſt four years of this emperor’s reign were attended with the utmoſt proſperity ; but in the fifth he was alarmed with accounts from the eaſt, that Sapor, king of Perſia, had furiouſly invaded the confines of the Roman empire, and having taken Antioch, had pillaged Syria and all the adjacent provinces. Beſides the Perſians, the Goths alſo invaded the empire ou their ſide, pouring down like an inundation from the north, and attempting to fix their reſidence in the kingdom of 1 hrace. To oppoſe both theſe invaſions, Gordian prepared an army ; and having gained ſome victories over the Goths, whom he obliged to retire, he turned his arms againſt the Perſians, whom he defeated upon ſeveral occaſions, and forced to return home with diſgrace. In gaining theſe advantages, Mifithæus, whom he had made prætorian prefect, had the principal ſhare ; but he dying ſoon after (as it is ſuppoſed being poiſoned by Philip an Arabian, who was appointed his ſucceſſor), the fortunes of Gordian ſeemed to die with him. The army began to be no longer ſupplied with proviſions as uſual ; murmurs were heard to prevail, and theſe were artfully fomented by Philip. Things thus proceeding from bad to worſe, Philip was at firſt made his equal in the command of the empire ; ſhortly after, inveſted with the ſole power ; and, at length, finding himſelf capable of perpetrating his long meditated cruelty, Gordian was, by his order, ſlain, in the 22d year of his age, after a ſucceſsful reign of near ſix years.</p><p>Philip having thus murdered his benefactor, was fo fortunate as to be immediately acknowledged emperor by the army. The ſenate alſo, though they ſeemed at firſt to oppoſe his power, confirmed his election, and gave him, as uſual, the tide of <hi rend="italic">Auguſtus.</hi>  Philip was about 40 years old when he came to the throne ; being the ſon of an obſcure Arabian, who had been captain of a band of robbers. Upon his exaltation, he aſſo-ciattd his ſon, a boy of fix years of age, as his partner in the empire ; and, in order to ſecure his power at home, made peace with the Perſians, and marched his army towards Rome. On his way, having conceived· a deſire to viſit his native country of Arabia, he built there a city called <hi rend="italic">Philippopolis ;</hi>  and from thence returning to Rome, he was received as emperor, and treated with all the marks of ſubmiſſion, though not of joy. To put the people in good humour, he cauſed the ſecular games to be celebrated, with a magnificence ſuperior to any of his predeceſſors, it being, juſt 1000 years after the building of the city. Upon occaſion of theſe games, we are told that both Philip and his ſorr were converted to Chriſtianity. However this be, a murderer and an ungrateful uſurper does no great honour to whatever opinion he may happen to embrace. We have little account of the latter part of his reign in the wretched and mutilated hiſtories of the times ; we only learn, that the Goths having invaded the empire, Marinus, Philip’s lieutenant, who was ſent againſt them, revolted, and cauſed himſelf to be declared emperor. This revolt, however, was but of ſhort duration ; for the army which had raiſed him repented of their raſhneſs, depoſed him with equal levity, and put him to death. Decius was the perſon whom Philip, appointed to command in the room of the revolting general» The chief merit of Decius with the emperor</p></body></text></TEI>