<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to put himſelf in a condition for carrying on the war, and ſhortly after declared it againſt hi n in form. All Antony’s followers were invited over to join him, with great promiſes of rewards : but they were not declared enemies, partly to prevent their growing deſperate, and partly to give a ſhow of moderation to his own party. At length both found themſelves in readineſs to begin the war, and their armies were anſwerable to the empire they contended for. The one was followed by all the forces of the eaſt ; the other drew all the ſtrength of the weſt to ſupport his pretenſions. Antony’s force compoſed a body of ιoo,coo foot and 12,000 horſe ; while his fleet amounted to 500 ſhips of war. The army of Octavianus muſtered but 80,000 foot, but equalled his adverſary’s in his number of cavalry : his fleet was but half as numerous as Antony’s ; however, his ſhips were better built, and manned with better ſoldiers.</p><p>The great deciſive engagement, which was a naval one, was fought near Actium, a city of Epirus, at the entrance of the gulph of Ambracia. Antony ranged his ſhips before the mouth of the gulph ; and Octavianus drew up his fleet in oppoſition. Neither general aſſumed any fixed ſtation to command in ; but went about from ſhip to ſhip wherever his preſence was neceſſary. In the mean time, the two land armies, on oppoſite ſides of the gulph, were drawn up, only as ſpectators of the engagement ; and encouraged the fleets by their ſhouts to engage. The battle began on both ſides with great ardour, and after a manner not practiſed upon former occaſions. The prows of their veſſels were armed with brazen points ; and with theſe they drove furiouſly againſt each other. In this conflict the ſhips of Antony came with greater force, but thoſe of Octavianus avoided the ſhock with greater dexterity. On Antony’s ſide, the Items of the ſhips were raiſed in form of a tower; ſrom whence they threw arrows from machines for that purpoſe. Thoſe of Octavianus made uſe of long poles hooked with iron, and fire-pots. They fought in this manner for ſome time with equal animoſity ; nor was there any advantage on either ſide, except a ſmall appearance of diſorder in the centre of Antony’s fleet. But all of a ſudden Cleopatra determined the fortune of the day. She was ſeen flying from the engagement attended by 60 ſail; ſtruck, perhaps, with the terrors natural to her ſex : but what increaſed the general amazement was, to behold Antony himſelf following ſoon after, and leaving his fleet at the mercy of the conquerers. The engagement, notwithſtanding, continued with great obſtinacy till five in the evening ; when Antony 's forces, partly conſtrained by the conduct of Agrippa, and partly perſuaded 'by the promiſes of Octavianus, ſubmitted to the-conqueror. The land-forces ſoon after followed the example of the navy ; and all yielded to the conqueι or without ſtriking a blow the fourth day after the battle.</p><p>λVhen Cleopatra fled, Antony purſued her in a five-oared galley ; and coming alongside of her ſhip entered, without ſeeing ör being ſeen by -her. She was in the ſtern, and he went to the prow, where he remained for ſome time ſilent, holding his head between his hands. In this manner he continued three whole days ; during which, either through indignation or ſhame, he neither ſaw nor ſpoke to Cleopatra. At laſt, when they were arrived at the promqntory of Tenants, the queen’s female attendants reconciled them, and everything went on as before. Still, however, he had the conſolation to ſuppoſe his army continued faithful to him ; and accordingly diſpatched orders to his lieutenant Canidius to conduct <hi rend="italic">it</hi>  into Aſia. However, he was ſoon undeceived when he arrived in Africa, where he was informed of their ſubmiſſion to his rival. This account ſo tranſported him with rage, that he was hardly prevented from killing himſelf; but at length, at the entreaty of his friends, he returned to Alexandria, in a very different ſituation from that in which Ke had left it ſome time before. Cleopatra, however, ſeemed to retain that fortitude in her misfortunes which had utterly abandoned her admirer. Having amaſſed conſiderable riches by means of confiſcation and other acts of violence, ſhe formed a very Angular and unheard of project ; this was to convey her whole fleet over the iſthmus of Suez into the Red Sea, and thereby ſave herſelf in another region beyond the reach of Rome, with all her treaſures. Some of her veſſels were actually tranſported thither, purſuant to her orders ; but the Arabians having burnt them, and Antony diſſuading her from the deſign, ſhe abandoned it for the more improbable ſeheme of defending Egypt againſt the conqueror.— She omitted nothing in her power to put his advice in practice, and made all kinds of preparations for war ; at leaſt hoping thereby to obtain better terms from Octavianus. In fact, ſhe had always loved Antony’s fortunes rather than his perſon ; and if ſhe could have fallen upon any method of ſaving herſelf, though even at his expence, there is no doubt but ſhe would have embraced it with gladneſs. She even ſtill had ſome hopes from the power of her charms, though ſhe was arrived almoſt at the age of 40 ; and was deſirous of trying upon Octavianus thoſe arts which had been ſo ſucceſsful with the greateſt men of Rome. Thus, in three embaſſies which were ſent one after another from Antony to his rival in Aſia, the queen had always her ſecret agents, charged with particular propoſals in her name. Antony deſired no more than that his liſe might be ſpared, and to have the liberty of paſſing the remainder of his days in ob-ſcurity. To theſe propoſals Octavianus made no reply. Cleopatra ſent him alſo public propoſals in favour of her children ; but at the ſame time privately reſigned him her crown, with all the enſigns of royalty. To the queen’s public propoſal no anſwer was given j to her private offer he replied, by giving her aſſurances of his ſavour in caſe, ſhe ſent away Antony or put him to death. Theſe negociations were not ſo private but they came to the knowledge of Antony, whoſe jealouſy and rage was now heightened by every concurrence. He built a ſmall folitary houſe upon a mole in the ſea ; and there he paſſed his time, ſhunning all commerce with mankind, and profeſſing to imitate Timon the rran-hater. However, his furious jealouſy drove him even from this retreat into ſociety; for hearing that Cleopatra had many ſecret conferences with one Thyrſus, an emiſſary from Octavianus, he ſeized upon him, and having ordered him to be cruelly ſcourged, he ſent him back to his patron. At the ſame time he ſent letters by him, importing, that he had chaſtiſed Thyrſus for inſulting a man in his misfortunes ; but withal he gave his rival permiſſion to avenge himſelf, by ſcourging Hiparchus, Antony’s freedman, in the fame manner. The revenge, in this caſe, would have</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>