<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and although we may ſay that the general ſlope is ne-ceiſarily ſecured by the cills of the flood-gates, which are paved with ſtone or covered with planks, yet this will not hinder this increaſed current from digging up the bottom in the intervals, undermining the banks, and lodging the mud and earth thus carried off in places where the current meets with any check. All theſe conſequences will aſſuredly follow il the increaſed velocity is greater than what correſponds to the regimen relative to the ſoil in which the river holds on its courſe.</p><p>In order therefore to procure durability to works oſ this kind, which are generally of enormous expence, the local circumſtances muſt be moſt ſcrupulouſly ſtu-died. It is not the ordinary hurried ſurvey of an engineer that will free us from the riſk of our navigation becoming very troubleſome by the riſe of the waters being diminiſhed from their former quantity, and banks formed at a ſmall diſtance below every ſluice. We muſt attentively ſtudy the nature of the ſoil, and diſcover experimentally the velocity which is not inconſiſtent with the permanency of the channel. If this be not a great deal leſs than that of the river when accelerated by freſhes, the regimen may be preſerved after the eſta-bliſhment of the gate, and no great changes in the channel will be neceſſary : but if, on the other hand, the natural velocity of the river during its freſhes greatly exceeds what is conſiſtent with ſtability, we muſt enlarge the width of the channel, that we may diminiſh the hydraulic mean depth, and along with this the velocity. Therefore, knowing the quantity diſeharged during the freſhes, divide it by the velocity of regimen, or rather by a velocity ſomewhat greater (for a reaſon which will appear by and by), the quotient will be the area of a new ſection. Then taking the natural ſlope of the river for the ſlope which it will preſerve in this enlarged channel, and after the cills of the flood-gates have been fixed, we muſt calculate the hydraulic mean depth, and then the other dimenſions of the channel. And, laſtly, from the known dimenſions of the channel and the diſeharge (which we muſt now compute), we proceed to calculate the height and the diſtances of the flood-gates, adjuſted to their widths, which muſt be regulated by the room which may be thought proper for the free paſſage of the lighters which are to ply on the river. An example will illuſtrate the whole of this proceſs.</p><p>Suppoſe then a ſmall river having a ſlope of 2 inches in 100 fathoms or <hi rend="sub">τ7</hi><hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="sub">5</hi>-<hi rend="sub">δ</hi>jwhich is a very uſual declivity of ſuch ſmall ſtreams, and whoſe depth in lummer is 2 feet, but ſubject to floods which raiſe it to nine feet. Let its breadth at the bottom be 18 feet, and the baſe qf its ſlanting ſides 4 of their height. All of theſe dimenſions are very conformable to the ordinary courſe of things. It is propoſed to make this river navigable in all ſeaſons by means of keeps and gates placed at proper diſtances ; and we want to know the dimenſions of a<hi rend="sub">j</hi>  channel which will be permanent, in a ſoil which begins to yield to a velocity of 80 inches per ſecond, but will be ſafe under a velocity of 24.</p><p>The primitive channel having the properties of a rectangular channel, its breadth during the freſhes muſt be B = 30 ſeet, or 360 inches, and its depth <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  9 feet or 1c8 inches ; therefore its hydraulic mean depth</p><lb/><p>B Z&gt;</p><p><hi rend="italic">d = —-</hi>_ = 61,88 inches. Its real velocity there-</p><p>B + 2Z&gt;    <hi rend="sup">7</hi></p><p>fore, during the freſhes, will be 38,9447 inches, and its diſcharge 15j4169 cubic inches, or 876⅛∙ cubic feet per ſecond. We ſee therefore that the natural channel will not be permanent, and will be very quickly deſtroyed or changed by this great velocity. We have two methods for procuring ſtability, viz. diminiſhing the ſlope, or widening the bed. The firſt method will require the courſe to be lengthened in the proportion of 24’ to 3988<hi rend="sup">i</hi>, or nearly of 36 to 100. —The expence of this would be enormous. The ſecond method will require the hydraulic mean depth to be increaſed nearly in the ſame proportion (becauſe the velocities are</p><p><hi rend="italic">∙</hi>∖<hi rend="italic">∕ d </hi>∖</p><p>nearly as —— 1. This will evidently be much leſs coſt-<hi rend="italic">V s</hi></p><p>ly, and, even to procure convenient room for the navigation, muſt be preferred.</p><p>We muſt now obſerve, that the great velocity, of which we are afraid, obtains only during the winter floods. If therefore we reduce this to 24 inches, it muſt happen that the autumnal freſhes, loaded with fand and mud, will certainly depoſit a part of it, and choak up bur channel below the flood-gates. We muſt therefore ſelect a mean velocity ſomewhat exceeding the regimen, that it may carry off theſe depoſitions. We ſhall take 27 inches, which will produce this effect on the looſe mud without endangering our channel in any remarkable degree.</p><p>Therefore we have, by the theorem for uniform mo.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">it    297(√df—0,1 )    , .-—</hi></p><p>non, V = 27, - -<hi rend="sub">z</hi>-A---==≠-o,3(√<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sub">j</hi>-</hi><hi rend="sub">0</hi>,ι).v <hi rend="italic">s—</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Lvj4i,6</hi></p><p>Calculating the diviſor of this formula, we find it</p><p><hi rend="sub">λλ τ</hi>-,    ∕~,    <hi rend="sup">2</hi>7 inch.</p><p>= 55,884. Hence <hi rend="italic">Yd —</hi>  0,1 = ---=</p><p>-A22--o,a</p><p>55,884    <hi rend="sup">,3</hi></p><p>5,3843, and therefore <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  = 30⅛. Having thus determined the hydraulic mean depth, we find the area 8 of the ſection by dividing the diſcharge 1514169 by the velocity 27. This gives us 56080,368. Then we get the breadth B by the formula formerly given,</p><p>∕7<hi rend="sup">-</hi>sT<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Iθ</p><p>B= ∕ Ç—-j    <hi rend="sup">2</hi>S∣+^j&gt; = 1802,296 inches, or</p><p>150,19 feet, and the depth <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  = 31,115 inches.</p><p>With theſe dimenſions of the ſection we are certain that the channel will be permanent ; and the cills of the flood-gates being all fixed agreeable to the primitive ſlope, we need not fear that it will be changed in the intervals by the action of the current. The gates being all open during the freſhes, the bottom will be cleared of all depoſited mud.</p><p>We muſt now ſtation the flood-gates along the new channel, at ſuch diſtances that we may have the depth of water which is proper for the lighters that are to be employed in the navigation. Suppoſe this to be four feet. We muſt firſt of all learn how high the water will be kept in this new channel during the ſummer droughts. There remained in the primitive channel only 2 feet, and the ſection in this caſe had 20 feet 8 inches mean width ; and the diſcharge correſponding to this ſection and ſlope of -j-<hi rend="sub">5</hi>-<hi rend="sup">,</hi>-<hi rend="sub">0</hi>-<hi rend="sub">g</hi>∙ is&gt; by ſh<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theorem of uniform motion, χ 30,849 cubic inches per ſecond. To</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>