<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of falſchood. They are led to conceive it their wtſeſt policy to ſhut their eyes upon realities; happy if by any perverſion of intellect they can perſuade themſelves that they were right in their firſt crude opinion of their companion.</p><p>“ So long as two human beings are forbidden by poſitive inſtitution to follow the dictates of their own mind, prejudice is alive and vigorous. So long as I ſeek to engroſs one woman to myſelf, and to prohibit my neighbour ſrom proving his ſuperior deſert and reaping the fruits of it, I am guilty of the moſt odious of all monopolies. Over this imaginary prize men watch with perpetual jealouſy ; and one man will find his de-ſires and his capacity to circumvent as much excited, as the other is excited to traverſe his projects and fruſtrate his hopes. As long as this ſtate of ſociety continues, philanthropy will be crcſſed and checked in a thouſand ways, and the ſtill augmenting ſtream of abuſe will continue to flow.</p><p>“ The abolition of marriage will be attended with no evils. The intercourſe of the ſexcs will fall under the ſame ſyſtem as any other ſpecies of friendſhip. Excluſively of all groundleſs and obſtinate attachments, it will be impoſſible for me to live in the world without finding one man of a worth ſuperior to that of any other whom I have an opportunity of obſerving. To this man I ſhall feel a kindneſs in exact proportion to my apprehenſion of his worth. The caſe will be pre-ciſely the ſame with reſpect to the ſemale ſex ; I ſhall aſſiduouſly cultivate the intercourse of that woman whoſe accompliſhments ſhall ſtrike me in the moſt poweiſſul manner. ‘ But it may happen that other men will feel for her the ſame preference that I do.’ This will create no difficulty. We may all enjoy her converſa-tion ; and we ſhall all be wile enough to conſider the ſtnſual intercourse as a very trivial object. This, like every other affair in which two perſons are concerned, muſt be regulated in each ſucceſſive inſtance by the unforced coulent of either party. It is a mark of the extreme depravity of our preſent habits, that we are inclined to ſuppoſe the ſenſual intercourſe anywiſe material to the advantages ariſing from the pureſt affec tion. Reaſonable men now eat and drink, not from the love of pleaſure, but becauſe eating and drinking are effential to our healthful exiſtence. Reaſonable men then will propagate their ſpecies, not becauſe a certain ſenſible pleaſure is annexed to this action, but becauſe it is right the ſpecies ſhould be propagated ; and the manner in wdrch they exerciſe this function will be regulated by the dictates of reaſon and duty.”</p><p>It is right then, according to this political innovator, that the ſpecies ſhould be propagated, and reaſonable men in his Utopian commonwealth would be inci∣cd by reaſon and duty to propagate them : but the way to fulbl this duty, experience, which is ſeldom at one with ſpeculative reformation, has already demonſtrated, not to conſiſt in the promiſcuous intercourſe of ſeveral men with one woman, but in the fidelity of individuals of the t∖*.o ſexes to each other. Common prtfſtitutes among us ſeldom prove with child ; and the ſociety of <hi rend="italic">Arreoys</hi>  in Otaheitee, who have completely diveſted themſelves of what our author calls <hi rend="italic">prejudice,</hi>  and are by no means guilty of his <hi rend="italic">maſt odious cſ all monopolies,</hi>  are for the moſt part childleſs (ſee Otaheitee). He ſeems to think that a ſtate of equal property would ne-</p><lb/><p>ceſſitrily deſtroy our reliſh for luxury, dtcreaſe our inordinate appetites of every kind, and lead us univerſally to prefer the pleaſures of intellect to the pleaſures of ſenſe. But here again experience is againft him. The <hi rend="italic">Arreοys,</hi>  who have a property in their women perfectly equal, are the moſt luxurious and ſenſual wretches on the face of the earth ; ſenſual indeed to a degree of which the moſt libidinous European can hardly form a conception.</p><p>By admitting it to be a duty to propagate the ſpecies, our author muſt neceſſarily grant that every thing is right which is requilite to the fulfilling of that duty, and the contrary wrong. If ſo, promiſcuous concubinage is wrong, ſince we have ſeen, that by a law of nature it is incompatible with the duty ; whence it follows on his own principles, that the ſexual union by pairs ' muſt be right. The only queſtion therefore to be decided between him and his opponents is, “ Whether ſhould that union be temporary or permanent ?” And we think the following obſervations by Mr Paley ſufficient to decide it to the conviction of every perſon not blinded by the rage of innovation.</p><p>“ A lawgiver, whoſe counrſels were directed by views of general utility, and obſtructed by no local impediments, would make the marriage-contract indiſſoluble during the joint lives of the parties, for the fake of the following advantages: Such a union tends to preſerve peace and concord between married perſons, by perpetuating their common intereſt, and by inducing a ne-ceſſity of mutual compliance. An earlier termination of it would produce a ſeparate intereſt. The wife would naturally look forward to the diſſolution of the partnerſhip, and endeavour to draw to herſelf a fund again!! the time when ſhe was no longer to have acceſs to the ſame reſources. This would beget peculation on one ſide, and miſtruſt on the other ; evils which at preſent very little diſturb the confidence of married life. The ſecond effect of making the union determinable only by death, is not leſs beneficial. It neceſſarily happens, that adverſe tempers, habits, and taſtes, oftentimes meet in marriage. In which caſe, each party muſt take pains to give up what offends, and practice what may gratiſy, the other. A man and woman in love with each other do this inſenſibly : but love is neither general nor durable ; and where that is wanting, no leffons of duty, no delicacy of ſentiment, will go half ſo far with the generality of mankind and womankind as this one intelligible reflection, that they muſt each make the beſt of their bargain ; and that ſeeing they muſt either both be miſerable or both ſhare in the ſame happineſs, neither can find their own comfort but in promoting the pleaſure of the other. Theſe compliances, though at firſt extorted by neceſſity, become in time eaſy and mutual; and though leſs endearing than aſſiduities which take their riſe from affection, generally procure to the married pair a repoſe and ſatisfaction ſufficient for their happinels.”</p><p>So differently from our author does this judicious writer reaſon concerning the effects of-a permanent union on the tempers of the married pair. Inſtead of ſubjecting them to ſome inevitable portion of thwarting, bickering, and unhappineſs, it lays them, in his opinion, under the neceſſity of curbing their unruly paſſions, and acquiring habits of gen tleneſs, forbearance, and peace. To this we may add, that both believing</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>