<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>grows to the height of about a yard ; the branches are numerous, produced irregularly, and covered with a purpliſh bark. The leaves are oval, ſpear-ſhaped, ſmall, and in the under ſurface of the colour of iron. The flowers are produced at the end of the branches in bunches, are of a wheel-ſhaped figure, pretty large, of a fine crimſon colour, and handſome appearance. They appear in June, and are ſucceeded by oval capſules containing ripe feeds in September. 4. The Dauricum, or Daurian dwarf roſe-bay, is a low deciduous ſhrub, and native of Dauria. Its branches are numerous, and covered with a browniſh bark. The flowers are wheel-ſhaped, large, and of a beautiful roſe-colour : they appear in May, and are ſucceeded by oval capſules full of feeds, which in England do not always ripen. 5. The maximum, or American mountain laurel, is an evergreen ſhrub, and native of Virginia, where it grows naturally on the higheſt mountains, and on the edges of cliffs, precipices, &amp;c. where it reaches the ſize of a moderate tree, though with us it ſeldom riſes higher than fix feet. The fl0wer3 continue by ſucceſſion ſometimes more than two months, and are ſucceeded by oval capſules full of feeds. 6. The Ponticum, or Pontic dwarf roſe-bay, is an evergreen ſhrub, native of the eaſt, and of moſt ſhady places near Gibraltar. It grows to the height of four or five feet. The leaves are ſpear-ſhaped, gloſſy on both ſides, acute, and placed on ſhort foot-ſtalks on the branches : the flowers, which are produced in cluſters, are bell-ſhaped, and of a fine purple colour. They appear in July, and are ſucceeded by oval capſules containing ſeeds, which in England ſeldom attain to maturity.</p><p>In Siberia, a ſpecies of this plant is uſed with great ſucceſs in gouty and rheumatic affections ; of which the following account is given in the 5th volume of the Medical Commentaries, p. 434. in a letter from Dr Guthrie of Peterſhurgh to Dr Duncan of Edinburgh. “ It is the rhododendrum chryſanthemum, nova ſpecies, belonging to the claſs of decandria, diſcovered by Profeſ-ſor Pallas in his tour through Siberia. This Alpine ſhrub grows near the tops of the high mountains named <hi rend="italic">Sajanes,</hi>  in the neighbourhood of the river Jeniſe in Siberia ; and delights in the ſkirts of the ſnow-covered ſummits, above the region that produces trees. When the inhabitants of that country mean to exhibit it in arthritic or rheumatic diſorders, they take about two drams of the dried ſhrub, ſtalk and leaves, with nine or ten ounces of boiling water, and putting them into an earthen pot, they lute on the head, and place them in an oven during the night. This infuſion (for it is not allowed to boil) the lick man drinks next morning for a doſe. It occaſions heat, together with a degree of intoxication, reſembling the effects of ſpirituous liquors, and a ſingular kind of uneaſy ſenſation in the parts affected, accompanied with a ſort of vermiculatio, which is likewiſe confined to the diſeaſed parts. The patient is not permitted to quench the thirl! which this medicine occaſions ; as fluids, particularly cold water, produce vomiting, which leſſens the power of the ſpe-cific. In a few hours, however, all the diſagreeable effects of the doſe diſappear, commonly with two or three ſtools. The patient then finds himſelf greatly relieved of his diſorder ; and has ſeldom occaſion to repeat the medicine above two or three times to complete a cure. The inhabitants of Siberia call this ſhrub <hi rend="italic">chei</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">tea,</hi>  from their drinking, in common, a weak infuſion of it, as we do the Chineſe plant of that name. This practice ſhows that the plant, uſed in ſmall quantities, muſt be innocent. Profeſſor Pallas informs me, that he ſent ſome time ago ſome of this ſhrub dried to Profeſſor Koelpin at Stetin ; and he ſhowed me a letter from that gentleman, where he ſays, that he has given It with ſucceſs in ſeveral caſes, particularly in what he calls the <hi rend="italic">arthritica venerea,</hi>  with a tophus arthriticus on the carpus, and it produced a complete cure. It muſt be remarked, that the doſe which theſe hardy Siberians take, who are alſo in the habit of drinking it. as tea, would, in all probability, be too ſtrong for our countrymen ; however, it is a medicine which we may certainly give with ſafety, beginning with ſmall doſes.”</p><p>RHŒA. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rhea.</hi></p><p>RHŒADEÆ <hi rend="italic">(rhaeas,</hi>  Linnaeus’s name, after Di-oſcorides, for the red poppy ), the name of the 27th order in Linnaeus’s fragments of a natural method, conſiſting of poppy and a few genera which reſemble it in habit and ſtructure. See Botany, p. 462.</p><p>RHOMBOÏDES, in geometry, a quadrilateral figure whoſe oppoſite ſides and angles are equal, but is neither equilateral nor equiangular.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rhomboïdes, in anatomy, a thin, broad, and obliquely ſquare fleihy muſcle, ſituated between the balis of the ſcapula and the ſpina dorſi ; ſo called from its figure. Its general uſe is to draw backward and upward the ſubſpinal portion of the baſis ſcapulae.</hi></p><p>RHOMBUS, in geometry, an oblique-angled parallelogram, or quadrilateral figure, whoſe ſides are equal and parallel, but the angles unequal, two of the oppoſite ones being obtuſe and two acute.</p><p>RHONE, one of the largeſt rivers in France, which, riling among the Alps of Switzerland, paſſes through the lake of Geneva, viſits that city, and then runs ſouth-weſt to Lyons ; where, joining the river Soane, it continues its courſe due ſouth, paſſing by Orange, Avignon, and Arles, and falls into the Mediterranean a little above Marſeilles.</p><p>RHOPIUM, in botany : A genus of the triandria order, belonging to the gynandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking with thoſe that are doubtful. The calyx is monophyllous and ſexpartite ; there is no corolla nor any ſtamina ; the three antheræ are each attached to one of the ſtyli ; the capſule is tri-coccous and ſexlocular, each containing two ſeeds. There is only one ſpecies, <hi rend="italic">viz</hi>. the meborea, a native of Guiana. This is a ſhrub riſing about three or four feet in height. The flowers grow in the form of a corymbus ; they are of a yellowiſh green colour ; the caρ-ſules are black.</p><p>RHOPOL A, in botany : A genus of the monogy-nia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking with thoſe that are doubtful. There is no calyx ; the petals are four, oblong, obtuſe, and narrowing at the baſe ; the ſtamina are four, inſerted in the corolla, and have large antheræ ; the feed-veſſel unilocular, and contains one ſeed. There is only one ſpecies, viz. the montana. This is a ſhrubby plant growing in Guiana, and remarkable for the great number of branches ſent off from its trunk in every direction, and for the fetid ſmcll of the wood and bark of this plant.</p></body></text></TEI>