<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>very acute and penetrating inſight into the real merits of each character, fairly deduced from the ſeveral circumſtances of his conduct exemplified in the hiſtory. For this work the Doctor got L.45oo Sterling.</p><p>In 1779, -^<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Robertſon publiſhed The Hiſtory of America, in two volumes quarto. This celebrated work may be conſidered with great propriety as a lequel to the preceding hiſtory. From the cloſe of the 15th centuι^y we date the moſt ſplendid era in the annals t&gt;f modern times. Diſeoveries were then made, the influence of which deſeended to poſterity ; and events happened that gave a new direction to the ſpirit of nations.</p><p>To the inhabitants of Europe, America was in every reſpect a new world. There the face of the earth changed its appearance. The plants and trees and animals were ſtrange ; and nature ſeemed no longer the ſame. A continent opened that appeared to have recently come ſrom the hands of the Creator, and which ſhowed lakes, rivers, and mountains, on a grander ſcale, and the vegetable kingdom in greater magnificence, than in the other quarters of the globe ; but the animal tribes in a ſtate of degradation, few in number, degenerated in kind, imperfect, and unfiniſhed. The human ſpecies in the earlieſt ſtage of its progreſs, vaſt and numerous nations in the rudeſt form of the ſavage ſtate which philoſophers have contemplated, and two great empires in the loweſt degree of civilization which any records have tranſmitted to our review, preſented to the philoſophic eye at this period the moſt fruitful ſubject of ſpeculation that was to be found in the annals of hiſtory.</p><p>The diſeovery of the New World, moreover, was not only a curious ſpcctacle to the philoſopher, but, by the change which it effected, an intereſting ſpectacle to the human race. When Columbus ſet ſail for unknown lands, he little expected that he was to make a revolution in the ſyſtem of human affairs, and to form the deſtiny of Europe for ages to come. d he importance and celebrity therefore of the ſubject had attracted the attention of philoſophers and hiſtorians. Views and ſketches of the new world had been given by able writers, and ſplendid portions of the American ſtory had been adorned with all the beauties of eloquence. But, prior to the appearance of Dr Robertſon’s hiſtory, no author had beſtowed the mature and profound inveſti-gation which ſuch a ſubject required, or had finiſhed, upon a regular plan, that complete narration and perfect whole which it is the province of the hiſtorian to tranſmit to poſterity. And as the ſubject upon which our author entered was grand, his execution was naaſterly. The character of his former works was immediately diſeerned in it. They had been read with uncommon admiration. When the Hiſtory of Scotland was firſt publiſhed, and the author altogether unknown, Lord Cheſterſield pronounced it to be equal in eloquence and beauty to the productions of Livy, the pu-reſt and moſt claflical of all the Roman hiſtorians. His literary reputation was not confined to his own country : the teſtimony of Europe was ſoon added to the voice of Britain. It may be mentioned, indeed, as the characteriſtic quality of our author’s manner, that he poſſeſſed in no common degree that ſupported elevation which is ſuitable to compoſitions of the higher claſs ; and, in his Hiſtory of America, he diſplayed that hap</p><lb/><p>py union of ſtrength and grace which becomes the majeſty of the hiſtoric muſe. In the fourth book of his firſt volume, which contains a deſcription of America when firſt diſcovered, and a philoſophſeal inquiry into the manners and policy of its ancient inhabitants, he diſ-plays, moreover, ſo much patient inveſtigation and found philoſophy, abounds in ſuch beautiful or intereſting deſcription, and exhibits ſuch variety and copiouſneſs of elegant writing, that future times will probably refer to it as that part of his works which gives the beſt idea of his genius, and is the moſt finiſhed of all his productions.</p><p>In 1787 appeared a tranſlation of the Abbé Clavi-gero’s Hiſtory of Mexico ; in which work the author threw out various reflections, tending in ſeveral inſtan-ces to impeach the credit of Dr Robertſon’s Hiſtory of America. This attack induced our learned hiſtorian to reviſe his work, and to inquire into the truth of the charges brought againſt it by the hiſtorian of New-Spain : and this he appears to have done with a becoming attention to the importance of the facts that are controverted, and to the common intereſts of truth. The reſult he publiſhed in 1788, under the title of Additions and Corrections to the former Editions of Dr Robertſon’s Hiſtory of America.—In many of the diſputed paſſages, he fully anſwered the Abbé Clavige-ro, and vindicated himſelf : in others he candidly ſub-mitted to correction, and thus gave additional value to his own work.</p><p>The literary labours of Dr Robertſon appear to have been terminated in 1791 by the publication of An Hiſtorical Diſquiſition concerning the Knowledge which the Ancients had of Tndia, and the Progreſs of Trade with that Country prior to the Diſeovery of the Paſſage to it by the Cape of Good Hope ; with an Appendix, containing Obſervations on the Civil Polity, the Laws, and Judicial Proceedings, the Arts, the Sciences, and Religious Inſtitutions of the Indians.— The perufal of Major RennelΓs Memoir, for illuſtrating his map of Hindoſtan, ſuggeſted to Dr Robertſon the deſign of examining more fully than he had done, in his Hiſtory of America, into the knowledge which the ancients had of India, and of conſidering what is certain, what is obſcure, and what is fabulous, in their accounts of that remote country. Of his various performances, this is not that of which the deſign is the moſt extenſive, or the execution the moſt elaborate ; but in this hiſtorical diſquiſition we perceive the ſame patient aſſiduity in collecting his materials, the ſame diſcernment in arranging them, the ſame perſpicuity of narrative, and the ſame power of illuſtration, which ſo eminently diſtinguiſh his other writings, and which have long rendered them the delight of the Britiſh reader at home and an honour to Britiſh literature abroad.</p><p>A truly uſeful life Dr Robertſon cloſed on the nth of June 1793, at Grange-Houſe, near Edinburgh, after a lingering illneſs, which he endured with exemplary fortitude and reſignation. It may be truly obſerved of him, that no man lived more reſpected, or died more ſincerely lamented. Indefatigable in his literary re-ſearches, and poſſeſſing from nature a found and vigorous underſtanding, he acquired a ſtore of uſeful knowledge, which afforded ample ſcope for the exertion of his extraordinary abilities, and raiſed him to the moſt diſtinguiſhed eminence ix» the republic of letters. As ∙</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>