<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to the houſe of the adulterer, there ſhowing him the apartments adorned with the ſpoils of his own palace ; and then conducting him to the prætorian camp, revived his courage by giving him aſſurances of the readineſs of the ſoldiers to defend h.im. Having thus artfully wrought upon his fears and reſentment, the wretched Silius was commanded to appear ; who, making no defence, was inſtantly put to death in the emperor’s preſence. Several others ſhared the ſame fate ; but Meſſalina ſtill flattered herſelf with hopes of pardon. She reſolved to leave neither prayers nor tears .unattempted to appeaſe the emperor. She ſometimes even gave a looſe to her reſentment, and threatened her ac-cuſers with vengeance. Nor did ſhe want ground for entertaining the moſt favourable expectations. Claudius having returned from the execution of her paramour, and having allayed his reſentment in a banquet, began to relent. He now therefore commanded his attendants to appriſe that miſerable creature, meaning Meſſalina, of his reſolution to hear her accuſation the next day, and ordered her to be in readineſs with her defence. The permiſſion to defend herſelf would have been fatal to Narciſſus ; wherefore he ruſhed out, and ordered the tribunes and centurions who were in readineſs to execute her immediately by the emperor’s Command. Claudius was informed of her death in the midſt of his banquet ; but this inſenſible idiot ſhowed not the leaſt appearance of emotion. He continued at table with his uſual tranquillity ; and the day following, while he was ſitting at dinner, he aſhed why Meſſalina was abſent, as if he had totally forgotten her crimes and her puniſhment.    «</p><p>Claudius being now a widower, declared publicly, that as he had hitherto been unfortunate in his marriages, he would remain ſingle for the future, and that he would be contented to forfeit his life in caſe he broke his reſolution. However, the reſolutions of Claudius were but of ſhort continuance. Having been accuſtomed to live under the controul of women, his preſent freedom was become irkſome to him, and he was entirely unable to live without a director. His freedmen therefore perceiving his inclinations, reſolved to procure him another wiſe ; and, after ſome deliberation, they fixed upon Agrippina, the daughter of his brother Germanicus. This woman was more practiſed in vice than even the former empreſs. Her cruelties were more dangerous, as they were directed with greater caution : ſhe had poiſoned her former huſhand, to be at liberty to attend the calls of ambition ; and, perfectly acquainted with all the infirmities of Claudius, only made uſe of his power to advance her own. However, as the late declaration of Claudius ſeemed to be an obſtacle to his marrying again, perſons were ſuborned to move in the ſenate, that he ſhould be compelled to take a wiſe, as a matter of great importance to the commonwealth ; and ſome more determined flatterers than the reſt left the houſe, as with a thorough reſolution, that inſtant, to conſtrain him. When this decree paſſed in the ſenate, Claudius had ſcarce patience to contain himſelf a day before the celebration of his nuptials. However, ſuch was the deteſtation in which the people in general held theſe inceſtuous matches, that though they were made lawful, yet only one of his tribunes, and one of his freedmen, followed his example.</p><p>Claudius having now received a new director, ſub*</p><lb/><p>mitted with more implicit obedience than in any former part of his reign. Agrippina’s chief aims were to gain the ſucceſſion in favour of her own ſon Nero, and to ſet aſide the claims of young Britannicus, ſon to the emperor and Meſſalina. For this purpoſe ſhe married Nero to the emperor’s daughter Octavia, a few days after her own marriage, Not long after this, ſhe urged the emperor to ſtrengthen the ſucceſſion, in imitation of his predeceſſors, by making a new adoption ; and cauſed him take in her ſon Nero, in ſome meaſure to divide the fatigues of government. Her next care was to increaſe her ſon’s popularity, by giving him Seneca for a tutor. This excellent man, by birth a Spaniard, had been baniſhed by Claudius, upon the falſe teſtimony of Meſſalina, who had accuſed him of adultery with Julia the emperor’s niece. The people loved and admired him ſor his genius, but ſtill more for his ſtrict morality ; and a part of his reputation neceſſarily devolved to his pupil. This ſubtle woman was not leſs aſſiduous in pretending the utmoſt affection for Britannicus ; whom, however, ſhe reſolved in a proper time to deſtroy : but her jealouſy was not confined to this child only ; ſhe, ſhortly after her acceſſion, procured the deaths of ſeveral ladies who had been her rival in the emperor’s affections. She diſplaced the captains of the guard, and appointed Burrhus to that command; a perſon of great military knowledge, and ſtrongly attached to her intereſts. From that time ſhe took left pains to diſguiſe her power, and frequently entered the Capitol in a chariot ; a privilege which none before were allowed, except of the ſacerdotal order.</p><p>In the 12th year of this monarch’s reign, ſhe perſuaded him to reſtore liberty to the Rhodians, of which he had deprived them ſome years before ; and to remit the taxes of the city Ilium, as having been the progenitors of Rome. Her deſign in this was to increaſe the popularity of Nero, who pleaded the cauſe of both cities with great approbation. Thus did this ambitious woman take every ſtep to aggrandize her ſon, and was even contented to become hateful herſelf to the public, merely to increaſe his popularity.</p><p>Such a very immoderate abuſe of her power ſerved at laſt to awaken the emperor’s ſuſpicions. Agrippina’s imperious temper began to grow inſupportable to him ; and he was heard to declare, when heated with wine, that it was his fate to ſuffer the diſorders of his wives, and to be their executioner. This expreſſion ſunk deep on her mind, and engaged all her faculties to prevent the blow. Her firſt care was to remove Narciſſus, whom ſhe hated upon many accounts, but particularly for his attachment to Claudius. This minifter, for ſome time, oppoſed her deſigns ; but at length thought fit to retire, by a voluntary exile, into Campania. The unhappy emperor, thus expoſed to all the machinations of his inſidious confort, ſeemed entirely regardleſs of the dangers that threatened his deſtruction. His affection ſor Britannicus was perceived every day to increaſe, which ſerved alſo to increaſe the vigilance and jealouſy of Agrippina. She now, therefore, reſolved not to defer a crime which ſhe had meditated a long while before ; namely, that of poiſoning her huſhand. She for ſome time, however, debated with herſelf in what manner ſhe ſhould adminiſter the poiſon ; as file feared too ſtrong a doſe would diſcover her treachery, and one too weak might fail of its effect</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>