<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a parallel. Many very ſtrange inſtances of his cruelty are related by the ancients He is ſaid to have cut aſunder a corpulent man whom he ſaw walking along the ſtreet; partly, to try his own ſtrength, in which he greatly excelled; and partly, as he himſelf owned, out of curioſity, to ſee his entrails drop out at once. He took pleaſure in cutting off the feet, and putting out the eyes, of ſuch as he met in his rambles through the city; telling the former, after he had thus maimed them, that now they belonged to the nation of <hi rend="italic">Mono-podii;</hi>  and the latter, that they were now become <hi rend="italic">Luſ-cinii,</hi>  alluding to the word <hi rend="italic">luſcus, "</hi>  one-eyed. ” Some he murdered becauſe they were negligently dreſſed; others, becauſe they ſeemed to be trimmed with too much nicety. He pretended to great ſkill in ſurgery, eſpecially at letting blood: but ſometimes, inſtead of eaſing by that means thoſe whom he viſited, or who were prevailed upon to recur to him, he cut off, by way of diverſion, their ears and noſes. His lewdneſs and debaucheries were equally remarkable, and equally infamous. However, he is ſaid to have been exceedingly well ſkilled in archery, and to have performed incredible feats in that way. He excelled all men in ſtrength; and is ſaid to have run an elephant through with his ſpear, and to have killed in the amphitheatre too lions, one after another, and each of them at one blow. Forgetful of his dignity, he entered the lilts with the common gladiators, and came off conqueror 735 times; whence he often ſubſcribed himſelf in his letters, <hi rend="italic">the conqueror of</hi>  1000 <hi rend="italic">gladiators.</hi></p><p>The public tranſactions of this reign were but very few. Soon after his father’s death, Commodus concluded a peace with the Marcommanni, Quadi, &amp;c. on</p><lb/><p>the following conditions. 1. That they ſhould not ſettle within five miles of the Danube. 2. That they ſhould deliver up their arms, and ſupply the. Romans with a certain number of troops when required. 3. That they ſhould aſſemble but once a month, in one place only, and that in preſence of a Roman centurion. 4. That they ſhould not make war upon the Ja-zyges, Buri, or Vandals, without the conſent of the people of Rome. On the other hand, Commodus promiſed to abandon, which accordingly he did, all the caſtles and fortreſſes held by the Romans in their country, excepting ſuch as were within five miles of the Danube. With the other German nations, whom his father had almoſt entirely reduced, he concluded a very diſhonourable peace; nay, of ſome he purchaſed it with large ſums of money.</p><p>Soon after the return of the emperor to Rome, his ſiſter Lucilla, perceiving that he was univerſally abhorred on account of his cruelty, formed a conſpiracy againſt his life. Among the conſpirators were many ſenators of diſtinction. It was agreed among them that they ſhould fall upon the emperor while he was going to the amphitheatre through a narrow and dark paſſage; and that Olaudius Pompeianus, to whom Lucilla had betrothed her daughter, ſhould give the firſt blow. But he, inſtead of ſtriking at once, ſhowed him the naked dagger, and cried out, “ This preſent the ſenate ſends you ſo that the guards had time to reſcue the emperor, and to ſeize the conſpirators, who were ſoon after put to death. The emperor baniſhed his ſiſter to the iſland of Capreæ, where he ſoon after cauſed her to be privately murdered.</p><p>The favourite miniſter of Commodus was one Pc-</p><lb/><p>real ſtrength of the monarchy. Their perſonal valour remained; but they no longer poſſeſſed that public courage which is nouriſhed by the love of independence, the ſenſe of national honour, the preſence of danger, and the habit of command. They received laws and governors from the will of their ſovereign, and truſted for their defence to a mercenary army. The poſterity of their boldeſt leaders were contented with the rank of citizens and ſubjects. The moſt aſpiring ſpirits reſorted to the court or ſtandard of the emperors; and the deſerted provinces, deprived of political ſtrength or union, inſenſibly ſunk into the languid indifference of private life.</p><p>“ The love of letters, almoſt inſeparable from peace and refinement, was faſhionable among the ſubjects of Adrian and the Antonines; who were themſelves men of learning and curioſity. It was diſſuſed over the whole extent of their empire; the moſt northern tribes of Britons had acquired a taſte for rhetoric; Homer as well as Virgil were tranſcribed and ſtudied on the banks of the Rhine and Danube; and the moſt liberal rewards ſought out the fainteſt glimmerings of literary merit. The ſciences of phyſic and aſtronomy were cultivated with ſome degree of reputation; but, if we except Lucian, an age of indolence paſſed away without producing a ſingle writer of genius who deſerved the attention of poſterity. The authority of Plato, of Ariſtotle, of Zeno, and Epicurus, ſtill reigned in the ſchools; and their ſyſtems, tranſmitted with blind deference from one generation of dif-ciples to another, precluded every generous attempt to correct the erroιs or enlarge the bounds of the human mind. The beauties of the poets and orators, inſtead of kindling a fire like their own, produced only ſervile imitations; or, if any ventured to deviate from theſe models, they deviated at the ſame time ſrom good ſenſe and propriety. The provincials of Rome, trained by an uniform artificial education, were engaged in a very unequal competition with thoſe bold ancients, who, by expreſſing their genuine feelings in their native tongue, had already occupied every place of honour. The name of <hi rend="italic">poet</hi>  was almoſt forgotten; that of <hi rend="italic">orator</hi>  was uſurped by the ſophiſts. A cloud of critics, of compilers, of commentators, darkened the face of learning, and the decline of genius was ſoon followed by the corruption of taſte.</p><p>“ Longinus obſerves and laments the degeneracy of his contemporaries, which debaſed their ſentiments, enervated their courage, and depreſſed their talents; comparing them to pigmies, whoſe ſtature has been diminiſhed by conſtant preſſure on their limbs. This diminutive ſtature of mankind was conſtantly ſinking below the old ſtandard, and the Roman world was indeed peopled by a race of pigmies; when the fierce giants of the north broke in and mended the puny breed. They reſtored a manly freedom; and, after the revolution of ten centuries, freedom became the happy parent of taſte and ſcience. ”</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>