<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Ardea, the capital of that nation, which lay about 20 miles from P.ome, in hopes of taking it without oppoſition. Contrary to his expectation, however, he λvas obliged to beſiege it in form ; and this conſtrained him to lay a heavy tax upon his ſubjects, which increaſed the number of malcontents, and diſpoſed every thing ſor a revolt. As the ſiege was carried on very ſlowly, the general officers frequently made entertainments for one another in their quarters. One day, when Sextus Tarquinius was entertaining his brothers, the converſation happened to turn upon their wives : every one extolled the good qualities of his own ; but Collatinus beſtowed ſuch extravagant praiſes on his Lucretia, that the diſpute ended in a kind of quarrel. It was then reſolved that they ſhould mount their horſes and ſurpriſe their wives by their unexpected return. The king’s daughters-in-law were employed in feaſting and diverſion, and ſeemed much diſconcerted by the appearance of their huſhands ; but Lucretia, though the night was far advanced, was found, with her maids about her, ſpinning and working in wool. She was not at all diſcompoſed by the company whom her huſhand brought with him, and they were all pleaſed with the reception ſhe gave them. As Lucretia was very beautiful, Sextus Tarquinius conceived a paſſion for her, which reſolving to ſatisfy at all events, he ſoon returned to Collatia in the abſence of Lucretia’s huſhand, and was entertained by her with great civility and reſpect. In the night-time he entered Lucretia’s apartment, and threatened her with immediate death if ſhe did not yield to his deſires. But finding her not to be intimidated with this menace, he told her, that, if ſhe ſtill perſiſted in her refuſal, he would kill one of her male ſlaves, and lay him naked by her when ſhe was dead, and then declare to all the world that he had only revenged the injury of Collatinus. On this the virtuous Lucretia (who, it ſeems, dreaded proſtitution leſs than the infamy attending it) ſubmitted to the deſires of Sextus ; but reſolved not to outlive the violence which had been offered her. She dreſſed herſelf in mourning, and took a poniard under her robe, having previouſly wrote to her huſhand to meet her at her father Lucretius’s houſe, where ſhe refuſed to diſcover the cauſe of her grief except in a full aſſembly of her friends and relations. Here, addreſſing herſelf to her huſhand Collatinus, ſhe acquainted them with the whole affair ; exhorted them to revenge the injury ; and proteſted that ſhe would not outlive the loſs of her honour. Every one preſent gave her a ſolemn promiſe that they would revenge her quarrel ; but while they endeavoured to comfort her, ſhe ſuddenly ſtabbed herſelf to the heart with the dagger which ſhe had concealed under her robe. See Chastity.</p><p>This extravagant action inflamed beyond meaſure the minds of all preſent. Brutus, laying aſide his pretended folly, drew the bloody dagger out of Lucretia’s body ; and, ſhowing it to the aſſembly, ſwore by the blood upon it that he would purſue Tarquin and his family with fire and ſword : nor would he ever ſuffer that or any other family to reign in Rome.. The ſame oath was taken by all the company ; who were ſo much ſurpriſed at the apparent tranſition of Brutus from folly to wiſdom, that they did whatever he deſired them.— By his advice the gates of the city were ſhut, that nobody might go out of it to inform Tarquin of what</p><lb/><p>was going forward ; which, as Lucretius had been left governor of the city by Tarquin, was put in execution without difficulty. The corpſe of Lucretia was then expoſed to public view ; and Brutus having made a ſpeech to the people, in which he explained the myſte-ry of his conduct in counterfeiting ſolly for many years paſt, proceeded to tell them that the patricians were come to a reſolution of depoſing the tyrant, and exhorted them to concur in the ſame deſign. The people teſtiſied their approbation, and called out for arms ; but Brutus did not think proper to truſt them with arms till he had firſt obtained a decree of the ſenate in favour of the deſign. This was eaſily procured : the ſenate enacted that Tarquin had forfeited all the prero- , gatives belonging to the regal authority, condemned him and all his poſterity to perpetual baniſhment, and devoted to the gods of hell every Roman who ſhould hereafter, by word or deed, endeavour his reſtoration ; and this decree was unanimouſiy confirmed by the curiæ.</p><p>Tarquin being thus depoſed, the form of government became the next object. Lucretius was for the preſent declared <hi rend="italic">Interrex ;</hi>  but Brutus being again conſulted, declared, that though it was by no means proper for the ſtate to be without ſupreme magiſtrates, yet it was equally neceſſary that the power ſhould not be centered in one man, and that it ſhould not be perpetual. For this reaſon he propoſed, that two magiſtrates, called <hi rend="italic">conſuls,</hi>  ſhould be elected annually ; that the ſtate ſhould thenceforth have the name of <hi rend="italic">republic ;</hi>  that the enſigns of royalty ſhould be aboliſhed ; and that the only en- ∙ ſigns of conſular dignity ſhould be an ivory chair, a white robe, and 12 lictors for their attendants. However, that he might not utterly aboliſh the name oſ <hi rend="italic">king,</hi>  he propoſed that this title ſhould be given to him who had the ſuperintendency of religious matters, who ſhould thenceforth be called <hi rend="italic">rex.ſacrorum,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">king oſſa-cred things.</hi></p><p>This ſeheme of Brutus being approved of, Brutus and Collatinus were propoſed by Lucretius as the two firſt conſuls, and unanimouſiy accepted by the people, who thought it was impoſſible to find more implacable enemies to the Tarquins. They entered on their office in the year 508 B. C. ; and Tullia, perceiving that now all was loſt, thought proper to leave the city, and retire to her huſhand at Ardea. She was ſuffered to depart without moleſtation, though the populace hooted at her, and curſed her as ſhe went along. Tarquin, in the’mean time, being informed by ſome who had got. out of Rome before the gates were ſhut, that Brutus was raiſing commotions to his prejudice, returned in haſte to the city, attended only by his ſons and a few friends ; but, finding the gates ſhut, and the people irr arms on the walls, lie returned again to the camp : but here again, to his ſurpriſe, he found that the conſuls had taken the opportunity of gaining over the army to their intereſt ; ſo that, being refuſed admittance into the camp alſo, he was forced to fly for refuge, at the age of 76, with his wiſe and three ſons, to Gabii, where Sextus had been made king. Here he continued for ſome time : but not rinding the Latins very forward to revenge his cauſe, he retired into Hetruria where, being the country of his mother’s family, he hoped to find more friends, and a readier aſſiſtance for attempting the recovery of his throne.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>