<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>nominated one to ſucceed him, the law will paſs without oppoſition.” Having thus ſpoken, he diſmiſſed the aſſembly, after having ſummoned them to meet again the next day.</p><p>And now Gracchus, being ſoured with the oppoſition he had met with from the rich, and from his obſtinate colleague, and being well appriſed that the law would paſs in any form in which he ſhould think fit to propoſe it, reſolved to revive it as it was at firſt paſſed, without abating any thing of its ſeverity. There was no exception in favour of the children in families ; or reimburſement promiled to thoſe who ſhould part with the lands they poſſeſſed above <hi rend="italic">ξoo</hi>  acres. The next day the people being aſſembled in vaſt crowds on this extraordinary occaſion, Gracchus made freſh applications io Octavius, but to no purpoſe; he obſtinately perſiſted in his oppoſition. Then Gracchus turning to the people, “ Judge you, (ſaid he), which of.us deſerves to be deprived of his office.” At theſe words the firſt tribe voted, and declared ſor the depoſition of Octavius. Upon which Gracchus, iulpending the ardour of the tribes, made another effort to bring over his opponent by gentle methods. But all his endeavours proving ineffectual,</p><p>the other tribes went on to vote in their turns, and followed the example of the firſt. Of 35 tribes, 17 had already declared againſt Octavius, and the 18∙th was juſt going to determine the affair, when Gracchus, being willing to try once more whether he could reclaim his colleague, ſuſpended the collecting of the ſuffrages; and addreſſing Octavius in the moſt preſſing terms, conjured him not to expoſe himſelf, by his obſtinacy, to ſo great a diſgrace, nor to give him the grief of having caſt a blennſh upon his colleague and friend, which neither time nor merit would ever wipe off. Octavius, however, continuing obſtinate, was depoſed, and the law paſſed as Gracchus had propoſed it the laſt time. The depoſed tribune was dragged from the roſtra by the incenſed multitude, who would have inſulted him further, had not the ſenators and his friends facilitated his eſcape.</p><p>The Licinian law being thus revived with one conſent both by the city and country tribes, Gracchus cauſed the people to appoint triumvirs, or three com-miſſioners, to haften its execution. In this commiſſion the people gave Gracchus the firſt place ; and he had intereſt enough to get his father-in-law Appius Claudius, and his brother Caius Gracchus, appointed his colleagues. Theſe three ſpent the whole ſummer in - travelling through all the Italian provinces, to examine •what lands were held by any perſon above 500 acres, in order to divide them among the poor citizens. When Gracchus returned from his progreſs, he found, by the death of his chief agent, that his abſence had not abated either the hatred of the rich, or the love of the poor, toward him. As it plainly appeared that the deceaſed had been poiſoned, the tribune took this occaſion to apply himſelf again to his protectors, and implore their aſſiſtance againſt the violence and treachery of his-ene-mies. The populace, more attached after this accident to their hero than ever, declared they would ſtand by him to the laſt drop of their blood ; and this their zeal encouraged him to add a new clauſe to the law, viz. that the commiſſioners ſhould likewiſe inquire what lands had been uſurped from the republic. This was touching the ſenators in a moſt tender point ; for moſt</p><p>of them had appropriated to themſelves lands belonging to the republic. But after all, the tribune, upon a ſtrict inquiry, found that the lands taken from the rich would not be enough to content all the poor citizens. But the following accident eaſed him of this difficulty, and enabled him to ſtop the murmurs of the malcontents , among the people.</p><p>Attalus Philometer, king of Pergamus, having bequeathed his dominions and effects to the Romans, Eudemus the Pergamean brought his treaſures to Rome at this time ; and Gracchus immediately got a new law paſſed, enacting, that this money ſhould be divided among the poor citizens who could not have lands ; and chat the diſpoſal of the revenues of Pergamus ſhould not be in the ſenate, but in the comitia. By theſe ſteps Gracchus moſt effectually humbled the ſenate; who, in order to diſcredit him among the people, gave out that Eudemus, who had brought the king’s will to Rome, had leſt with Gracchus the royal diadem and mantle of Attalus, which the law-making tribune was to uſe wher*he ſhould be proclaimed king of Rome. But theſe reports only ſerved to make Gracchus be more upon his guard, and to inſpire the people with an implacable hatred againſt the rich who were the authors of them. Gracchus being now, by his power-over the minds of the multitude, abſolute mälter of their ſuffrages, formed a deſign of raiſing his father-in-law Appius Claudius to the conſulate next year, of promoting his brother Caius to the tribuneſhip, and getting himſelf continued in the ſame office. The laſt was what moſt nearly concerned him ; his perſon, as long as he was in office; being ſacred and inviolable. As the ſenate was very active in endeavouring to get ſuch only elected into the college of tribunes as were enemies to Gracchus and his faction, the tribune left no ſtone unturned to ſecure his election. He told the people, that the rich had reſolved to aſſaſſinate him as ſoon as he was out of his office ; he appeared in mourning, as was the cuſtom in the greateſt calamities ; and bringing his children, yet young, into the forum, recommended them to the people in ſuch terms, as ſhowed that he deſpaired of his own preſervation. At this fight the populace returned no anſwer, but by outcries and menaces againſt the rich.</p><p>When the day appointed for the election of new tribunes came, the people were ordered to aſſemble in the capitol in the great court before the'temple of Jupiter. The tribes being met, Gracchus produced his petition, intreating the people to continue him one year longer in the office of tribune, in conſideration of the· great danger to which he was expoſed, the rich having vowed his deſtruction as ſoon as his perſon ſhould be no-more ſacred. This was indeed an unuſual requeſt, it having been long cuſtomary not to continue any tribune in his office above a year. However, the tribes began· to vote, and the two firſt declared for Gracchus. Hereupon the rich made great clamours ; which terrified Rubrius Varro, who preſided in the college of tribunes that day, to ſuch a degree, that he reſigned his place to Q. Mummius, who offered to preſide in. his room. But this raiſed a tumult among the tribunes themſelves ; ſo-that Gracchus wiſely diſmiſſed the aſſembly, and order·* ed them to meet again the next day.</p><p>In the mean time the people, being ſenſible of what importance it was to them to preſerve the life of fo</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>