<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:27:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>filbert-trees with their nuts. At the depth of about 28 feet, they find a bed of chalk, about 11 feet deep, which cuts very eaſily ; after this a bed of marſhy earth of about two feet, mixed with ruſhes, leaves, and branches. After this bed comes another of chalk, nearly of the ſame thickneſs ; and which ends at the depth oſ 42 feet. This is followed by another bed of marſhy earth like the former; after which comes a new chalk-bed, but thinner, which alſo has a marſhy bed underneath it. This ends at the depth of 63 feet ; after which they find sand mingled with ſmall gravel, and ſeveral marine ſhells. This stratum is uſually about five feet deep, and underneath it is a vaſt reſervoir of water. It is on account of this water that the soil is ſo frequently dug, and the ſtrata ſo well known in this part oſ the world. After coming to the ſandy bottom above-mentioned, the workmen pierce the ground with a terebra or auger, when the water immediately ſprings up with great force, and fills the west to the brim. The flow is perpetual, and neither increaſes by rain, nor decreaſes by drought. Sometimes the auger meets with great trees, which give the workmen much trouble ; they also ſometimes ſee at the bottom of theſe wells great bones, coals, flints, and pieces of iron.</p><p>It has been aſſerted by ſome, that the ſpecific gravity of the ſtrata conſtantly increaſed with the depth from the surface. But Dr Leigh, in his Natural Hiſtory of Lancaſhire, ſpeaking of the coal-pits, denies the ſtrata to lie according to the laws of gravitation ; obſerving, that the ſtrata there are firſt a bed of marle, then free-ſtone, next iron-ſtone, then coal, or channel mire, then ſome other ſtrata, then coal again, &amp;c. This determined Mr Derham to make a nicer inquiry into the matter : accordingly, in 1712, he cauſed divers places to be bored, laying the ſeveral ſtrata by themſelves ; and afterwards determined very carefully their ſpecific gravity. The reſult was, that in his yard the ſtrata were gradually ſpecifically heavier and heavier the lower and lower they went ; but in another place in his fields, he could not perceive any difference in the ſpecific gravities.</p><p>Acquainting the Royal Society therewith, their operator Mr Haukſbee was ordered to try the ſtrata of a coal pit, which he did to the depth of 30 ſtrata : the thickneſs and ſpecific gravity of each whereof he gives us in a table in the Philoſophical Transactions@@; and from the whole makes this inference, that it evidently appears the gravities of the ſeveral ſtrata are in no manner of order, but purely caſual, as if mixed by chance.</p><p>STRATAGEM, in the art of war, any device for deceiving and ſurprising an enemy. The ancients dealt very much in ſtratagems ; the moderns wage war more openly, and on the ſquare. Frontinus has made a collection of the ancient ſtratagems of war.</p><p>STRATEGUS, ςρατϓος in antiquity, an officer among the Athenians, whereof there were two choſen yearly, to command the troops of the ſtate.</p><p>Plutarch says, there was one choſen from out of each tribe ; but Pollux ſeems to ſay they were choſen indifferently out of the people. The people themſelves made the choice ; and that on the laſt day of the year, in a place called <hi rend="italic">Pnyx.</hi> The two st<hi rend="italic">rategy</hi> did not command together, but took their turns day by day ; as we find from Herodotus and Cornelius Nepos. Sometimes indeed, as when a perſon was found of merit vaſtly ſuperior, and exceedingly famed in war, the command was given to him alone : but it was ever a rule, not to put any person in the office but whoſe eſtate was in Attica, and who had children, that there might be ſome hoſtages and ſecurities for his conduct and fidelity. Conſtantine the Great, beſides many other privileges granted to the city of Athens, honoured its chief magiſtrate with the title of ϺεΓας ΣτϑαἸηος <hi rend="italic">Magnus Dux.</hi></p><p>STRATH, in the Scottiſh language, ſignifies a long narrow valley, with a river running along the bottom.</p><p>STRATHEARN, a beautiful and extenſive valley in Perthſhire, bounded on the north by the lofty ridge of mountains called the <hi rend="italic">Grampians,</hi> and on the ſouth by the Ochils, which are rounded on the tops and covered with verdure. It is called <hi rend="italic">Strαtheαrn</hi> from the river Earn, which runs through the middle of it from west to eaſt for about 30 miles. On each side of the banks of this beautiful ſtream are many villages and country-ſeats diſtinguiſhed for romantic situations. Were we to single out any of the villages, we would mention Crieff, which ſtands on a fine ſtoping ground on the north side of the Earn, and has been much admired by travellers for its ſituation, and the variety, contraſt, singularity, and beauty of the prospect which it affords.</p><p>STRATHNAVER, a ſubdiviſion or diſtrict of the county of Sutherland in Scotland ; bounded on the north by the ocean, on the eaſt by Caithness, on the ſouth by Sutherland properly ſo called, and on the west partly by Roſs and partly by the ocean.</p><p>STRATIOTES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Water-soldier,</hi> in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">polyandria, </hi>and to the order of h<hi rend="italic">exagynia ; </hi>and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the firſt order, <hi rend="italic">palmae.</hi> The ſpatha is diphyllous : the perianthium is trifid. There are three petals, and the berry is six-celled and inferior. There are three ſpecies, the aloides, the acoroides, and aliſmoides. The <hi rend="italic">αlοides</hi> alone is of Britiſh extraction, which is alſo called the <hi rend="italic">water αlοe,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">freſh-water soldier. </hi>The root conſiſts of long fibres tufted at the ends. The leaves are thick, triangular, pointed, and prickly at the edges. The flowers are white and floating on the water, and bloſſom in June. This plant may be ſeen in flow rivers and fens.</p><p>STRATO, a philoſopher oſ Lampſacus, diſciple and ſucceſſor in the ſchool of Theophraſtus, about 248 years before the Chriſtian era. He applied himself with uncommon induſtry to the ſtudy of nature ; and aſter the moſt mature inveſtigations, he ſupported that nature was inanimate, and that there was no god but nature. (See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Plastic</hi><hi rend="italic"> Nature).</hi> He was appointed preceptor to Ptolemy Philadelphus, who not only revered his abilities and learning, but alſo rewarded his labours with unbounded liberality. He wrote different treatiſes, all now lost.</p><p>STRAWBERRY, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Fragaria. </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Strawberry</hi><hi rend="italic">-Tree.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Arbutus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@[mu] Vol. xxvii. p 541</hi></p></body></text></TEI>