<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:23:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>perience of others. With what induſtry he proſecuted this plan, and with what ſucceſs his labours were crowned, may be ſeen in a ſeries of <hi rend="italic">Clinical and Anatomical Observatiοns,</hi> which were made by him during his attendance at the hoſpital, and were publiſhed after his death by his friend Dr Carmichael Smyth. Theſe obſervations give the public no cauſe to complain of want of candour in their author ; for whatever delicacy he may have obſerved, when relating the cases of patients treated by other phyſicians, he has related thoſe treated by himſelf with the utmoſt impartiality. Whilſt attending the hoſpital, he likewiſe employed himſelf in making experiments on the blood, and other animal fluids ; and alſo in a courſe of experiments in chemical pharmacy ; but though accounts of theſe experiments were left behind him, we believe they have not yet been given to the public.</p><p>In the year 1767 Mr Stark went abroad and obtained the degree of M. D. in the university of Leyden, publiſhing an inaugural diſſertation on the dyſentery. On his return to London, he recommenced his ſtudies at the hoſpital ; and when Ur Black was called to the chemical chair in Edinburgh, which he has long filled with ſo much honour to himſelf and credit to the univerſity, Dr Stark was solicited by ſeveral members of the univerſity of Glaſgow to ſtand a candidate for their profeſſorſhip of the theory and practice of phyſic, rendered vacant by Dr Black’s removal to Edinburgh. This however Dr Stark declined, being influenced by the advice of his Engliſh friends, who wiſhed to detain him in London, and having likewiſe ſome prospects of an appointment in the hoſpital.</p><p>In the mean time he had commenced (1769) a ſeries of experiments on diet, which he was encouraged to undertake by Sir John Pringle and Dr Franklin, whoſe friendſhip he enjoyed, and from whom he received many hints reſpecting both the plan and its execution. Theſe experiments, or rather the imprudent zeal with which he proſecuted them, proved in the opinion of his friends, fatal to himſelf ; for he began them on the 12th of July 1669 in perfect health and vigour, and from that day, though his health varied, it was ſeldom if ever good, till the 23d of February 1770, when he died, after ſuffering much uneaſineſs. His friend and biographer Dr Smyth thinks, that other cauſes, particularly chagrin and diſappointment, had no ſmall share in haſtening his death ; and as the Doctor was intimately acquainted with his character and diſpoſition, his opinion is probably well-founded, though the pernicious effects of the experiments are viſible in Dr Stark’s own journal. When he entered upon them, the weight of his body was 12 ſtone 3 lb. avoirdupois, which in a very few days was reduced to 11 ſtone 10 lb 8 oz: and though ſome kinds of food increaſed it, by much the greater part of what he uſed had a contrary effect, and it continued on the whole to decreaſe till the day of his death. This indeed can excite no wonder. Though the profeſſed object of his experiments was to prove that a <hi rend="italic">pleaſant</hi> and varied diet is equally conducive to health with a more ſtrict and simple one, moſt of the diſhes which he ate during theſe experiments were neither pleaſant nor simple, but compounds, ſuch as every ſtomach muſt nauſeate. He began with <hi rend="italic">bread</hi> and <hi rend="italic">water ;</hi> from which he proceeded to <hi rend="italic">bread, water,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ſugar</hi> ; then to <hi rend="italic">bread, water,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">oil of olives ;</hi> then to <hi rend="italic">bread</hi> and <hi rend="italic">water</hi> with</p><p><hi rend="italic">milk ;</hi> afterwards he tried <hi rend="italic">bread</hi> and <hi rend="italic">water</hi> with <hi rend="italic">roasted goose ; bread</hi> and <hi rend="italic">water</hi> with <hi rend="italic">boiled beef ; stewed lean of beef</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">gravy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">water</hi> without bread ; st<hi rend="italic">ewed lean of beeſ</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">gravy, oil</hi> of <hi rend="italic">fat</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ſuet</hi> and <hi rend="italic">water ; flour, oil of ſuet, water</hi> and sal<hi rend="italic">t ; flour, water,</hi> and sal<hi rend="italic">t ; </hi>and a number of others infinitely more diſagreeable to the ſtomach than even theſe, ſuch as <hi rend="italic">bread, fat of bacon ham, infusion of tea</hi> with <hi rend="italic">ſugar ;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bread</hi> or <hi rend="italic">flour</hi> with <hi rend="italic">honey</hi> and the infuſion of <hi rend="italic">rofemary.</hi> But though we conſider Dr Stark’s experiments as whimſical, it cannot be denied that they indicate eccentricity of genius in the perſon who made them ; and ſuch of our readers as think genius hereditary, may perhaps be of opinion, that he derived a ray from the celebrated <hi rend="smallcaps">Napier</hi> the inventor of the logarithms, who was his anceſtor by both parents. At any rate, theſe experiments, of which a full account is given in the ſame volume with his clinical and anatomical obſervations, diſplay an uncommon degree of fortitude, perſeverance, self-denial, and zeal for the promoting of uſeful knowledge in their author ; and with reſpect to his moral character, we believe it is with great juſtice that Dr Smyth compares him to Cato by applying to him what was ſaid of that virtuous Roman by Salluſt.—“ Non divitiis cum divite, neque factione cum factioſo; ſed cum ſtrenuo virtute, cum modeſto pudore, cum innocente abſtinentia certabat ; esse, quam videri, bonus malebat@@*."</p><p>STARLING. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sturnus.</hi></p><p>STATE <hi rend="smallcaps">of a Controversy.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Oratory, </hi>Part I. n⁰ 14.</p><p>STATES, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Estates,</hi> a term applied to ſeveral orders or claſſes of people aſſembled to conſult of matters for the public good.</p><p>Thus ſtates-general is the name of an aſſembly conſiſting of the deputies of the ſeven United Provinces. Theſe are uſually 30 in number, ſome provinces sending two, others more; and whatever reſolution the ſtates-general take, muſt be confirmed by every province, and by every city and republic in that province, before it has the force of a law. The deputies of each province, of what number ſoever they be, have only one voice, and are eſteemed as but one perſon, the votes being given by provinces. Each province preſides in the aſſembly in its turn, according to the order ſettled among them. Guelderland preſides first, then Holland, &amp;c.</p><p>States of Holland are the deputies of eighteen cities, and one repreſentative of the nobility, conſtituting the states of the province of Holland : the other provinces have likewiſe their states, repreſenting their ſovereignty; deputies from which make what they call the states-general. In an aſſembly oſ the states of a particular province, one diſſenting voice prevents their coming to any reſolution.</p><p>STATICE <hi rend="smallcaps">Thrift,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the class of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and order of p<hi rend="italic">entagynia;</hi> and in the natural ſystem ranging under the 48th order, <hi rend="italic">aggregates.</hi> The calyx is monophyllons, entire, folded, and ſcarioſe. There are five petals, with one ſuperior ſeed. There are 22 ſpecies, the armeria, pſeudarmeria, limonium, incana, cordata, reticulata, echioides, ſpecioſa, tatarica, echinus, flexuoſa, purpurata, minuta, ſuffruticoſa, monopetala, aurea, ferulacea, linifolia, pruinoſa, sinuata, mucronata, and lobata. Three of theſe are Britiſh plants.</p><p>I. The <hi rend="italic">armeria,</hi> thrift, or sea gilly-flower, has a simple</p><p>@@@[m]* Bellum Catilinarium.</p></body></text></TEI>