<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>very fine. The soil in the northern mountainous parts is not fertile ; but in the middle, where it is watered by the Trent, the third river in England, it is both fruitful and pleaſant, being a mixture of arable and meadow grounds. In the ſouth, it abounds not only with corn, but with mines of iron and pits of coal. The principal rivers of this county, beſides the Trent, which runs almoſt thro’ the middle of it, and abounds with ſalmon, are the Dove and Tame, both of which are well ſtored with fiſh. In this county are alſo a great many lakes, or meres and pools, as they are called ; which, having ſtreams either running into them or from them, cannot be ſuppoſed to be of any great prejudice to the air ; they yield plenty oſ fish. In divers parts of the county are medicinal waters, impregnated with different sorts of minerals, and consequently of different qualities and virtues ; as thoſe at Hints and Breſsford- houſe, which are mixed with bitumen ; thoſe at Ingeſtre, Codſalwood, and Willough-bridge park, which are ſulphureous. Of the ſaline kind are the Brine-pits at Chertley, Epſom, Penſnet-cloſe, of which very good ſalt is made. There is a well at Newcaſtle-under-Line that is ſaid to cure the king’s evil; another called <hi rend="italic">Elder- well</hi> near Blemhill, ſaid to be good for sore eyes ; and a third called the <hi rend="italic">Spa,</hi> near Wolverhampton.</p><p>Great flocks of sheep are bred in this county, eſpecially in the moorlands, or mountains of the northern part of it ; but the wool is ſaid to be ſomewhat coarſer than that of many other counties. Of this wool, however, they make a variety of manufactures, particularly felts. In the low grounds along the rivers are rich paſtures for black cattle ; and vaſt quantities of butter and cheeſe are made. In the middle and ſouthern parts not only grain of all kinds, but a great deal of hemp and flax are raised. This county produces alſo lead, copper, iron ; marble, alabaſter, millſtones, limeſtone ; coal, ſalt, and marks of ſeveral forts and colours; brickearth, fullers earth, and potters-clay@@*, particularly a sort uſed in the glaſs manufacture at Amblecot, and sold at ſeven-pence a buſhel ; tobacco pipe-clay ; a sort of reddiſh earth called <hi rend="italic">flip,</hi> uſed in painting divers vessels; red and yellow ochres ; fire-ſtones for hearths of iron furnaces, ovens, &amp;c. ; iron-ſtones of ſeveral sorts; blood- stones, or haematites, found in the brook Tent, which, when wet a little, will draw red lines like ruddle ; quarry-stones, and grind-stones. For fuel the county is well supplied with turf, peat, and coal of ſeveral forts, as cannel-coal, peacock coal, and pit-coal. The peacockcoal is ſo called, becauſe, when turned to the light, it diſplays all the colours of the peacock’s tail ; but it is fitter for the forge than the kitchen. Of the pit-coal there is an inexhauſtible ſtore : it burns into white ashes, and leaves no ſuch cinder as that of the New- caſtle coal. It is not uſed for malting till it is charred, and in that ſtate it makes admirable winter-fuel for a chamber.</p><p>This county is in the dioceſe of Litchfield and Coventry, and the Oxford circuit. It sends ten members to parliament ; namely, two for the county, two for the city of Litchfield, two for Stafford, two for Newcaſtle-under-Line, and two for Tamworth.</p><p>STAG, in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cervus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">STAG-Beetle.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Lucanus.</hi></p><p>STAGE, in the modern drama, the place of action and repreſentation included between the pit and the ſcenes, and anſwering to the proſcenium or pulpitum of the ancients. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Playhouse</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Theatre.</hi></p><p>STAGGERS. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Farriery,</hi>  xiii.</p><p>STAHL (George Erneſt), an eminent German chemiſt, was born in Franconia in 1660, and choſen profeſſor of medicine at Hall, when a univerſity was founded in that city in 1694. The excellency of his lectures while he filled that chair, the importance of his various publications, and his extenſive practice, soon raiſed his reputation to a very great height. He received an invitation to Berlin in 1716, which having accepted, he was made counſellor of ſtate and phyſician to the king. He died in 1734, in the 75th year of his age. Stahl is without doubt one of the greateſt men of which the annals of medicine can boaſt : his name marks the commencement of a new and more illustrious era in chemiſtry. He was the author of the doctrine of phlogiſton, which, though now completely overturned by the diſcoveries of Lavoiſier and others, was not without its uſe ; as it ſerved to combine the ſcattered fragments of former chemiſts into a ſyſtem, and as it gave riſe to more accurate expcriments and a more ſcientific view of the ſubject, to which many of the ſubſequent diſcoveries were owing. This theory maintained its ground for more than half a century, and was received and ſupported by ſome of the moſt eminent men which Europe has produced ; a ſufficient proof of the ingenuity and the abilities of its author. He was the author alſo of A Theory of Medicine, founded upon the notions which he entertained of the absolute dominion of mind over body ; in conſequence of which, he affirmed, that every muſcular action is a voluntary act of the mind, whether attended with conſciousneſs or not. This theory he and his followers carried a great deal too far, but the advices at leaſt which he gives to attend to the ſtate of the mind of the patient are worthy of the attention of phyſicians.</p><p>His principal works are, 1. <hi rend="italic">Experimenta et Observaciones Chemica et Physicae,</hi> Berlin, 1731, 8vo. 2. <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes Medica,</hi> Hall, 2 vols 4t0. This is a collection of theſes. 3. <hi rend="italic">Theoria Medica vera, 1737,</hi> 4to.	4. <hi rend="italic">0puſculum Chymico-physico medicum,</hi> 1740, 4to.	5, A Treatiſe on Sulphur, both Inflammable and Fixed, written in German. 6. <hi rend="italic">Negotium Otiosum,</hi> Hall, 1720, 4t0. It is in this treatiſe chiefly that he eſtabliſhes his ſyſtem concerning the action of the soul upon the body. 7. <hi rend="italic">Fundamenta Chymica Dogmatica et Experimentalis, </hi>Nuremberg, 1747, 3 vols 4to. 8. A Treatiſe on Salts, written in German. 9. <hi rend="italic">Commentarium in Metallurgiam Beccheri,</hi> 1723.</p><p>STAINING <hi rend="italic">or </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Colouring of BONE, Horn, Marble, Paper, Wood,</hi> &amp;c. See theſe articles.</p><p>STAIRCASE, in architecture, an aſcent incloſed between walls, or a baluſtrade conſiſting of flairs or ſteps, with landing places and rails, ſerving to make a communication between the ſeveral ſtories oſ a houſe. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Architecture,</hi> n⁰ 89, &amp;c.</p><p>STALACTITÆ, in natural hiſtory, cryſtalline ſpars formed into oblong, conical, round, or irregular bodies, composed of various crusts, and uſually found hanging in form of iſicles from the roofs of grottoes, &amp;c.</p><p>STALAGMITIS, in botany: A genus of the <hi rend="italic">monaecia</hi> order, belonging to the <hi rend="italic">polygamia</hi> claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 38th order, <hi rend="italic">Tricoccae.</hi> The calyx is either quadriphyllous or</p><p>@@@[m]* See STONE-Wear.</p></body></text></TEI>