<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:23:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>or decreaſe; the manner in which the territory of a country is poſſeſſed and cultivated ; the nature and amount of the various productions of the ſoil ; the value of the perſonal wealth or stock of the inhabitants, and how it can be augmented; the diſeaſes to which the people are ſubject, their cauſes and their cure ; the occupations of the people ; where they are entitled to encouragement, and where they ought to be ſuppreſſed ; the condition of the poor, the beſt mode of maintaining them, and of giving them employment ; the ſtate of ſchools, and other inſtitutions, formed for purpoſes of public utility; theſtate of the villages and towns, and the regulations beſt calculated for their police and good government; the ſtate of the manners, the morals, and the religious principles of the people, and the means by which their temporal and eternal intereſts can beſt be promoted.</p><p>To ſuch of our readers as have not an opportunity of peruſing this national work, or of examining its plan, we will preſent the ſcheme for the ſtatiſtical account of a parochial diſtrict which Sir John Sinclair publiſhed for the consideration of the clergy, and which has been generally followed by them, though often with great improvements.</p><p>The name of the pariſh and its origin ; ſituation and extent of the pariſh ; number of acres ; deſcription of the soil and ſurface ; nature and extent of the ſea-coaſt; lakes, rivers, iſlands, hills, rocks, caves, woods, orchards, &amp;c.; climate and diſeaſes ; inſtances of longevity ; ſtate oſ property; number of proprietors ; number of reſiding proprietors ; mode of cultivation; implements of huſbandry; manures; ſeedtime and harveſt; remarkable inſtances of good and bad ſeaſons; quantity and value of each ſpecies of crop; total value of the whole produce of the diſtrict ; total real and valued rent ; price of grain and proviſions ; total quantity of grain and other articles confirmed in the pariſh ; wages and price of labour ; ſervices, whether exacted or aboliſhed; commerce; manufactures; manufacture of kelp,its amount, and the number of people employed in it; fiſheries; towns and villages; police; inns and alehouſes; roads and bridges; harbours; ferries, and their ſtate; number of ſhips and veſſels; number of ſeamen; state of the church ; ſtipend, manſe, globe, and patron ; number of poor ; parochial funds, and the management of them ; ſtate of the ſchools, and number of scholars ; ancient ſtate of population ; cauſes of its increaſe or decreaſe ; number of families ; exact amount of the number of souls now living; diviſion of the inhabitants; I. by the place of their birth ; 2. by their ages ; 3. by their religious perſuaſions ; 4. by their occupations and ſituation in life; 5. by their reſidence, whether in town, village, or in the country ; number of houſes ; number of uninhabited houſes ; number of dovecots, and to what extent they are deſtructive to the crops ; number of horſes, their nature and value; number of cattle, their nature and value ; number of ſheep, their nature and value ; number of ſwine, their nature and value ; minerals in general; mineral ſprings; coal and fuel; eminent men; antiquities ; parochial records ; miscellaneous obſervations ; character of the people; their manners, customs, stature, &amp;c. ; advantages and diſadvantages ; means by which their ſituation could be meliorated.</p><p>If ſimilar ſurveys (says the public-ſpirited editor of this work) were inſtituted in the other kingdoms of Europe, it might be the means of eſtabliſhing, on ſure foundations, the principles of that moſt important of all ſciences, viz. political or ſtatiſtical philoſophy ; that is, the ſcience, which, in preference to every other, ought to be held in reverence. No ſcience can furniſh, to any mind capable of receiving uſeful information, ſo much real entertainment; none can yield ſuch important hints, for the improvement of agriculture, for the extenſion of commercial induſtry, for regulating the conduct of individuals, or for extending the prosperity of the ſtate ; none can tend ſo much to promote the general happineſs of the ſpecies.</p><p>STATIUS (Publius Papinius), a celebrated Latin poet of the firſt century, was born at Naples, and was the ſon of Statius, a native of Epirus, who went to Rome to teach poetry and eloquence, and had Domitian for his ſcholar. Statius the poet also obtained the favour and friendſhip of that prince ; and dedicated to him his Thebais and Achilleis ; the firſt in twelve books, and the lait in two. He died at Naples about the year 100. Beſides the above poems, there are alſo ſtill extant his <hi rend="italic">Sylva,</hi> in five books ; the ſtyle of which is purer, more agreeable, and more natural, than that of his Thebais and Achilleis.</p><p>STATUARY, a branch of ſculpture, employed in the making of ſtatues. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sculpture</hi> and the next article.</p><p>Statuary is one of thoſe arts wherein the ancients ſurpaſſed the moderns ; and indeed it was much more popular, and more cultivated, among the former than the latter. It is diſputed between ſtatuary and painting, which of the two is the moſt difficult and the moſt artful.</p><p>Statuary is alſo uſed for the artificer who makes ſtatues. Phidias was the greateſt ſtatuary among the ancients, and Michael Angelo among the moderns.</p><p>STATUE, is defined to be a piece of ſculpture in full relievo, repreſenting a human figure. Daviler more ſcientifcally defines ſtatue a repreſentation, in high relievo and insulate, of ſome perion diſtinguiſhed by his birth, merit, or great actions, placed as an ornament in a fine building, or expoſed in a public place, to preſerve the memory of his worth. In Greece one of the highest honours to which a citizen could aſpire was to obtain a ſtatue.</p><p>Statues are formed with the chiſel, of ſeveral matters, as ſtone, marble, plaſter, &amp;c. They are alſo cast of various kinds of metal, particularly gold, silver, brass, and lead. For the method of calling ſtatues, ſee the article <hi rend="italic smallcaps">FounderY</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Statues.</hi></p><p>Statues are uſually diſtinguiſhed into four general kinds. The firſt are thoſe leſs than the life ; of which kind we have ſeveral ſtatues of great men, of kings, and of gods themſelves. The second arc thoſe equal to the life ; in which manner it was that the ancients, at the public expence, uſed to make ſtatues of perſons eminent for virtue, learning, or the ſervices they had done. The third are thoſe that exceed the life ; among which thoſe that ſurpaſſed the life once and a half were for kings and emperors ; and thoſe double the life, ſor heroes. The fourth kind were thoſe that exceeded the life twice, thrice, and even more, and were called <hi rend="italic">colossuses.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Colossus.</hi></p><p>Every ſtatue reſembling the perſon whom it is intended to repreſent, is called <hi rend="italic">ſtatua iconica.</hi> Statues acquire various other denominations. 1. Thus, allegorical ſtatue is that which, under a human figure, or other ſymbol,</p></body></text></TEI>