<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-04-20T21:21:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>which God has of the human body as actually exiſting; that this <hi rend="italic"
                    >idea</hi> of the body, and the <hi rend="italic">body</hi> itſelf, are one and
                the ſame thing ; and that thinking and extended ſubſtances are in reality but one
                and the ſame ſubſtance, which is ſometimes comprehended under one attribute of the
                Deity, and ſometimes under another@@*.</p>
            <p>If this impious jargon be not Atheiſm, or as it has been ſometimes called Pantheiſm,
                we know not what it is (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Pantheism).</hi> According to
                Spinoza, there is but one ſubstance, which is extended, infinite, and indiviſible.
                That ſubstance indeed he calls God ; but he labours to prove that it is corporeal ;
                that there is no difference between mind and matter ; that both are attributes of
                the Deity variouſly considered ; that the human ſoul is a part of the intellect of
                God ; that the ſame ſoul is nothing but the idea of the human body ; that this idea
                of the body, and the body itſelf, are one and the ſame thing ; that God could not
                exiſt, or be conceived, were the visible univerſe annihilated ; and therefore that
                the viſible univerſe is either the one ſubstance, or at leaſt an eſſential attribute
                or modification of that ſubſtance. He ſometimes indeed ſpeaks of the <hi
                    rend="italic">power</hi> of this ſubſtance; but when he comes to explain
                himſelf, we find that by power he means nothing but blind neceſſity@@* ; and though
                he frequently talks of the <hi rend="italic">wiſdom</hi> of God, he ſeems to make
                uſe of the word without meaning. This we think evident from the long appendix to his
                36th proposition ; in which he labours to prove that the notion of final cauſes is
                an idle figment of the imagination, since, according to him, nothing but the
                prejudices of education could have led men to fancy that there is any real
                diſtinction between <hi rend="italic">good</hi> and <hi rend="italic">evil,
                    merit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">demerit, praiſe</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >reproach, order</hi> and <hi rend="italic">confusion ;</hi> that <hi
                    rend="italic">eyes</hi> were given them that they might be enabled to <hi
                    rend="italic">ſee ; teeth for</hi> the purpoſe of chewing their <hi
                    rend="italic">food ; herbs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">animals</hi> for the <hi
                    rend="italic">matter</hi> of that <hi rend="italic">food ;</hi> that the <hi
                    rend="italic">ſun</hi> was formed to give <hi rend="italic">light,</hi> or the
                    <hi rend="italic">ocean </hi>to nouriſh fish<hi rend="italic">es.</hi> If this
                be true, it is impoſſible to diſcover wiſdom in the operations of his <hi
                    rend="italic">one ſubſtance;</hi> since, in common apprehension, it is the very
                characteriſtic of folly to act without any end in view.</p>
            <p>Such are the reveries of that writer, whoſe works a German philoſopher of ſome name
                has lately recommended to the public, as calculated to convey to the mind more just
                and ſublime conceptions of God than are to be found in moſt other ſyſtems. The
                recommendation has had its effect. A literary journaliſt of our own, reviewing the
                volume in which it is given, feels a peculiar ſatisfaction from the diſcovery that
                Spinoza, inſtead of a formidable enemy to the cauſe of virtue and religion, was
                indeed their warmeſt friend ; and piouſly hopes that we ſhall become more cautious
                not to ſuffer ourſelves to be deceived by empty names, which thoſe who <hi
                    rend="italic">cannot</hi> reaſon ( Sir Iſaac Newton and Dr Clarke perhaps) give
                to thoſe who can (Hobbes, we ſuppoſe, and Spinoza). But though we have the honour to
                think on this queſtion with our illuſtrious countrymen, we have no desire to depict
                Spinoza as a <hi rend="italic">reprobate,</hi> which the critic ſays has often been
                done by ignorance and enthuſiaſm. We admit that his conduct in active life was
                irreproachable ; and for his ſpeculative opinions, he muſt ſtand or fall to his own
                Master. His <hi rend="italic">Ethics</hi> appear to us indeed a ſyſtem ſhockingly
                impious ; and in the tract intitled <hi rend="smallcaps">Politica, </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">power</hi> and <hi rend="italic">right</hi> are confounded as in
                the former volume ; but in the treatiſe <hi rend="smallcaps">De Intellectus
                    Emendatione,</hi> are ſcattered many precepts of practical wiſdom, as well as
                ſome judicious rules for conducting philoſophical inveſtigation ; and we only
                regret, that the reader muſt wade to them through pages of fataliſm, ſcepticiſm, and
                palpable contradictions. His <hi rend="italic">Compendium Grammatices Linguae
                    Hebraeae, </hi>though left imperfect, appears to have ſo much merit, that it is
                to be wiſhed he had fulfilled his intention of writing a philoſophical grammar of
                that language, inſtead of waſting his time on abſtruſe ſpeculations, which, though
                they ſeem not to have been injurious to his own virtue, are certainly not calculated
                to promote the virtue of others, or to increaſe the ſum of human happineſs.</p>
            <p>SPIRÆA, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic"
                    >icoſandria,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">pentagynia ;</hi> and in
                the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 26th order, <hi rend="italic">Pomacea.</hi>
                The calyx is quinquesid ; there are five petals; and the capſule is polyſpermous.
                There are 18 ſpecies ; of which two only are Britiſh, the fili- pendula and ulmaria.
                1. The fi<hi rend="italic">lipendula,</hi> dropwort, has pinnated leaves ; the
                leaflets are ſerrated ; the ſtalk is herbaceous, about a foot and a half high,
                terminated with a looſe umbel of white flowers, often tinged with red. The petals
                are generally six, and the ſegments of the calyx are reflexed : the ſtamina are 30
                or more ; the germina 12 or upwards. It grows in mountainous paſtures. 2. The <hi
                    rend="italic">ulmaria,</hi> meadow-ſweet. The leaves have only two or three pair
                of pinnæ, with a few ſmaller ones intermixed ; the extreme one being larger than the
                rest, and divided into three lobes. The calyx is reddiſh ; the petals white, and the
                number of capſules from six to ten twiſted <hi rend="italic">in a</hi> ſpiral. The
                tuberous pea, like roots of the filipendula dried and reduced to powder, have been
                uſed inſtead of bread in times of ſcarcity. Hogs are very fond of theſe roots. Cows,
                goats, ſheep, and ſwine, eat the plant ; but horſes refuſe it. The flowers of the
                ulmaria have a fragrant ſcent, which riſes in diſtillation. The whole plant indeed
                is extremely fragrant, ſo that the common people of Sweden ſtrew their floors with
                it on holidays. It has alſo an aſtringent quality, and has been found uſeful in
                dyſenteries, ruptures, and in tanning of leather.</p>
            <p>SPIRAL, in geometry, a curve line of the circular kind, which in its progreſs recedes
                from its centre.</p>
            <p>SPIRE, in architecture, was uſed by the ancients for the baſe of a column, and
                ſometimes for the aſtragal or tore ; but among the moderns it denotes a ſteeple that
                continually diminiſhes as it aſcends, whether conically or pyramidally.</p>
            <p>SPIRIT, in metaphyſics, an incorporeal being or</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Prop. vii. <gap> </gap>iii. xxi. Part 2.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Prop. xxxiii. Part <gap> </gap></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
