<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-04-20T21:20:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>SPECIFIC CONTD We ſee the ſame augmentation of the denſity of the ſalt in the diluted brines here as
                in the caſe of common ſalt. Thus a brine, of which the cubic foot weighs 1482
                ounces, or which has the ſpecific gravity 1,482, contains 800 ounces of dry alkali
                and 682 of water. Therefore, if we ſuppoſe the denſity of the water unchanged, there
                remains the bulk of 318 ounces of water to receive 840 ounces of ſalt: its denſity
                is therefore 800/318, = 2,512 nearly. But in the brine whoſe weight <hi
                    rend="italic">per </hi>foot is only 1016 there are 20 ounces of ſalt, and
                therefore 996 of water ; and there is only four ounce-meaſures of water, that is,
                the bulk of four ounces of water, to receive 20 ounces of ſalt. Its ſpecific gravity
                therefore is 20/4, ≡ 5, almoſt twice as great as in the ſtrong brine. Accordingly Mr
                Achard is diſpoſed to admit the abſorption (as it is careleſsly termed) in the caſe
                of ſal tart. But it is a general (we think an univerſal) fact in the ſolution of
                ſalts. It muſt be carefully diſtinguiſhed from the firſt contraction of bulk which
                ſalts undergo in passing from a ſolid to a fluid form. The contraction now under
                conſideration is analogous to the contraction of oil of virtriol when diluted with
                water ; for oil of vitriol muſt be conſidered as a very ſtrong brine which we cannot
                dephlegmate by diſtillation, and therefore cannot obtain the dry ſaline ingredient
                in a separate form, ſo as to obſerve its ſolid denſity, and ſay how much it
                contracts in firſt becoming fluid. The way of conceiving the first contraction in
                the act of ſolution as a lodging of the particles of the one ingredient on the
                interſtices of the other, “ <hi rend="italic">ou ils ſe nichent, en augmentant le
                    poids ſans affecter le volume de la ſaumure,"</hi> as Eller and Lambert expreſs
                themſelves, is impoſſible here, when both are fluids. Indeed it is but a ſlovenly
                way of thinking in either caſe, and ſhould be avoided, becauſe inadvertent perſons
                are apt to uſe as a phyſical principle what is merely a mode of ſpeech.</p>
            <p>We learn from the table, that a hydrometer with equidiſtant diviſions on a
                cylindrical or priſmatical stem is still more erroneous than in the brines of common
                ſalt.</p>
            <p>We learn from the experiments of Kirwan, Lavoisier, and others, that dry ſalt of
                tartar contains about ¼th of
                its weight of fixed air. In many applications of this ſalt to the purpoſes of
                manufacture, this ingredient is of no uſe. In ſome it is hurtful, and muſt be
                abstracted by lime. Soap-maker’s ley conſiſts of the pure alkaline ſalt dissolved in
                water. It is therefore of importance to aſcertain its quantity by means of the
                ſpecific gravity of the brine. For this purpoſe, we took a ley of ſal tart whoſe
                ſpecific gravity was 1,20417, containing 314 oz. of mild alkali in a cubic foot of
                ley, and we rendered it nearly cauſtic by lime. The ſpecific gravity was then
                1,1897. This is a very unexpected reſult. Nothing is employed with more ſucceſs than
                quick-lime for dephlegmating any watery fluid. We ſhould rather have expected an
                increaſe of ſpecific gravity by the abſtraction of ſome of the water of the
                menſtruum, and perhaps the water of the cryſtallization, and the aerial part of the
                ſalt. But we muſt aſcribe this to the great denſity in which the fixed air exiſts in
                the mild alkali.</p>
            <p>It is unneceſſary to give ſimilar tables for all the ſalts, unleſs we were writing a
                diſſertation on the theory of their ſolution. We ſhall only obſerve, that we
                examined with particular attention ſal ammoniac, becauſe Mr Achard, who denies what
                is called the abſorption of ſalts, finds himſelf obliged to allow ſomething like it
                in this ſalt. It does not, however, differ from thoſe of which we have given an
                account in detail in any other reſpect than this, that the changes of fluid denſity
                are much leſs than in others (inſtead of being greater, as Achard’s experiments seem
                to indicate) in all brines of moderate ſtrength. But in the very weak brines there
                is indeed a remarkable difference ; and if we have not committed an error in our
                examination, the addition of one part of ſal ammoniac to 64 of water occupies leſs
                room than the water alone. We think that we have met with this as an accidental
                remark by ſome author, whoſe work we do not recollect. But we do not choose to rest
                ſo much on our form of the experiment in ſuch weak brines. The following mixtures
                will abundantly ſerve for conſtructing the table of its ſtrength : Sal ammoniac =
                960 grains was diſſolved in 3506 grains of water, making a brine of 4466 grains. A
                phial which held 1600 grains water held 1698 of this brine. It contained
                1698x960/4460, or 365 grains of ſalt. The ſpecific gravity was 1690/1600,= 1061, and
                the cubic foot weighed 1061 ounces. It alſo contained1061x365/1698, or 228 ounces of
                ſalt. By repeated abſtraction of brine, and replacing with water, we had the
                following ſeries :</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Series.</cell>
                    <cell>Brine.</cell>
                    <cell>Sp. Gr.</cell>
                    <cell>Oz. Salt in Cub. F.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Weight of brine,</cell>
                    <cell>1<hi rend="italic">st,</hi> 1698</cell>
                    <cell>1,061</cell>
                    <cell>228</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>After taking out ¼,</cell>
                    <cell>2<hi rend="italic">d,</hi> 1676</cell>
                    <cell>1,048</cell>
                    <cell>171</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>After taking out <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                        >3</hi>,</cell>
                    <cell>3<hi rend="italic">d,</hi> 1653</cell>
                    <cell>1,033</cell>
                    <cell>114</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>After taking out ½,</cell>
                    <cell>4<hi rend="italic">th,</hi> 1630</cell>
                    <cell>1,019</cell>
                    <cell>57</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>After taking out ½,</cell>
                    <cell>5<hi rend="italic">th,</hi> 16l6</cell>
                    <cell>1,010</cell>
                    <cell>28½</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>½</cell>
                    <cell>>6<hi rend="italic">th,</hi> 1610</cell>
                    <cell>1,0063</cell>
                    <cell>14¼</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>½</cell>
                    <cell>7<hi rend="italic">th,</hi> 1605</cell>
                    <cell>1,0038</cell>
                    <cell>7<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi></cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>This ſeries is extremely regular, and the progreſs of denſity may be confidently
                deduced from it.</p>
            <p>From the whole of this diſquiſition on the relation between the ſpecific gravities of
                brines and the quantities of ſalt contained, we ſee in general that it may be
                gueſſed at, with a uſeful degree of preciſion, from the denſity or ſpecific gravity
                of ſaturated ſolutions. We therefore conclude with a list of the ſpecific gravities
                of ſeveral ſaturated ſolutions, made with great care by the bishop of
                Landaff.—Thetemperaturewas 42⁰. The first numerical column is the denſity of
                ſaturated brine, and the next is the denſity of a brine conſiſting of 12 parts (by
                weight) of water and one of ſalt. From this may be inferred the quantity in the
                ſaturated ſolution, and from this again may be inferred the quantity correſponding
                to inferior denſities.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Borax,</cell>
                    <cell>1,010</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Cor. Sublim.</cell>
                    <cell>1,037</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Alum,</cell>
                    <cell>1,033</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Glaub. Salt,</cell>
                    <cell>1,054</cell>
                    <cell>1,029</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Common Salt,</cell>
                    <cell>1,198</cell>
                    <cell>1,059</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Sal. cath. amar.</cell>
                    <cell>1,232</cell>
                    <cell>1,039</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Sal ammon.</cell>
                    <cell>1,072</cell>
                    <cell>1,026</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Vol. alk. mite,</cell>
                    <cell>1,087</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Nitre,</cell>
                    <cell>1,095</cell>
                    <cell>1,050</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Rochelle ſalt,</cell>
                    <cell>1,114</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Blue vitriol,</cell>
                    <cell>1,150</cell>
                    <cell>1,052</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Green vitriol,</cell>
                    <cell>1,157</cell>
                    <cell>1,043</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>White vitriol,</cell>
                    <cell>1,386</cell>
                    <cell>1,045</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Pearl aſh,</cell>
                    <cell>1,534</cell>
                    <cell/>
                </row>
            </table>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
