<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that our Engliſh writers call the ſun-fiſh. The Iriſh and Welſh give it the ſame name, from its lying as if to ſun itſelf on the ſurface of the water ; and for the ſame reaſon Mr Pennant calls it the baſking ſhark. It was long taken for a ſpecies of whale, till Mr Pennant pointed out the bronchial orifices on the ſides, and the perpendicular site of the tail. Theſe are migratory fiſh,or at leaſt it is but in a certain number of years that they are ſeen in multitudes on the Welſh ſeas, though in moſt ſummers a single, and perhaps a ſtrayed fiſh appears. They inhabit the northern ſeas, even as high as the arctic circle. They viſited the bays of Caernar- vonſhire and Angleſea in vaſt ſhoals in the ſummers of 1756 and a few ſucceeding years, continuing there only the hot months ; for they quitted the coaſt about Michaelmas, as if cold weather was diſagreeable to them. Some old people say they recollect the ſame sort of fiſh viſiting theſe ſeas in vaſt numbers about 40 years ago. They appear in the Frith of Clyde, and among the Hebrides, in the month of June, in ſmall droves of ſeven or eight, but oftener in pairs. They continue in thoſe ſeas till the latter end of July, when they diſappear.</p><p>They have nothing of the fierce and voracious nature of the ſhark kind, and are ſo tame as to ſuffer themſelves to be ſtroked ; they generally lie motionleſs on the ſurface, commonly on their bellies, but ſometimes, Eke tired ſwimmers, on their backs. Their food ſeems to conſiſt entirely of ſea plants, no remains of fiſh being ever diſcovered in the stomachs of numbers that were cut up, except ſome green fluff, the half digested parts of algæ, and the like. Linnæus ſays it feeds on meduſae.</p><p> At certain times, they are ſeen ſporting on the waves, and leaping with vast agility ſeveral feet out of the water. They ſwim very deliberately, with the dorſal fins above water. Their length is from three to twelve yards, and ſometimes even longer. Their form is rather ſlender, like others of the ſhark kind. The upper jaw is much longer than the lower, and blunt at the end. The tail is very large, and the upper part remarkably longer than the lower. The colour of the upper part of the body is a deep leaden ; the belly white. The ſkin is rough like ſhag- reen, but leſs ſo on the belly than the back. In the mouth, towards the throat, is a very ſhort sort of whale-bone. The liver is of a great size, but that of the female is the largest; ſome weigh above 1000 pounds, and yield a great quantity of pure and ſweet oil, fit for lamps, and alſo much uſed to cure bruiſes, burns, and rheumatic complaints. A large fiſh has afforded to the captors a profit of 20 l. They are viviparous ; a young one about a foot in length being found in the belly of a fiſh of this kind. The meaſurements of one found dead on the ſhore of Loch Ranza in the iſle of Arran were as follow: The whole length, 27 feet 4 inches ; firſt dorſal fin, 3 feet ; second, 1 foot ; pectoral fin, 4 feet ; ventral, 2 feet ; the upper lobe of the tail, 5 feet ; the lower, 3.</p><p>They will permit a boat to follow them, without accelerating their motion till it comes almoſt within contact when a harponeer strikes his weapon into them, as near to the gills as poſſible. But they are often ſo inſenſible as not to move till the united ſtrength of two men have forced in the harpoon deeper. As ſoon as thcy perceive themſelves wounded, they fling up their tail and plunge headlong to the bottom ; and frequently coil the rope round them in their agonies, attempting to diſengage the harpoon by rolling on the ground, for it is often found greatly bent. As ſoon as they diſcover that their efforts are in vain, they ſwim away with amazing rapidity, and with ſuch violence, that there has been an inſtance of a veſſel of 70 tons having been towed away againſt a freſh gale. They ſometimes run off with 200 fathoms of line, and with two harpoons in them ; and will employ the fiſhers for 12, and ſometimes for 24 hours, before they are ſubdued. When killed, they are either hauled on ſhore, or, if at a diſtance from land, to the vessel’s side. The liver (the only uſeful part), is taken out, and melted into oil in kettles provided for that purpoſe. A large fiſh will yield eight barrels of oil, and two of worthleſs ſediment.</p><p>II.	<hi rend="italic">Carcharias, requin,</hi> or white ſhark, is often 30 feet long, and according to Gillius weighs 4000 pounds. The mouth of this fiſh is ſometimes furniſhed with a six-fold row of teeth, flat, triangular, and exceedingly ſharp at their edges, and finely ſerrated. Mr Pennant had one rather more than an inch and a half long. Grew ſays, that thoſe in the jaws of a ſhark two yards in length are not half an inch ; ſo that the fiſh to which this tooth belonged muſt have been six yards long, provided the teeth and body keep pace in their growth.</p><p>This dreadful apparatus, when the fiſh is in a ſtate of repoſe, lies quite flat in the mouth ; but when he ſeizes his prey, he has power of erecting them by the help of a ſet of muſcles that join them to the jaw. The mouth is placed far beneath ; for which reaſon theſe, as well as the rest of the kind, are ſaid to be obliged to turn en their backs to ſeize their prey ; which is an obſervation as ancient as the days of Pliny. The eyes are large ; the back broad, flat, and ſhorter than that of other ſharks. The tail is of a ſemilunar form, but the upper part is longer than the lower. It has vaſt ſtrength in the tail, and can strike with great force ; ſo that the ſailors inſtantly cut it off with an axe as ſoon as they draw one on board. The pectoral fins are very large, which enables it to ſwim with great ſwiftneſs. The colour of the whole body and fins is a light aſh. The ancients were acquainted with this fish ; and Oppian gives a long and entertaining account of its capture. Their fleſh is ſometimes eaten, but is eſteemed coarſe and rank.—They are the dread of the ſailors in all hot climates, where they conſtantly attend the ships in expectation of what may drop over-board : a man that has that misfortune periſhes without redemption ; they have been ſeen to dart at him like gudgeons at a worm. A maſter of a Guinea ſhip informed Mr Pennant, that a rage of suicide prevailed among his new-bought ſlaves, from a notion the unhappy creatures had, that after death they ſhould be reſtored again to their families, friends, and country. To convince them at leaſt that they ſhould not reanimate their bodies, he orderd one of their corpſes to be tied by the heels to a rope and lowered into the ſea ; and though it was drawn up again as faſt as the united force of the crew could be exerted, yet in that ſhort ſpace the ſharks had devoured every part but the feet, which were ſecured at the end of the cord.</p><p>Swimmers very often periſh by them ; ſometimes</p></body></text></TEI>