<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-04-20T21:21:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>proper for the ſeveral kinds of working. Hemp, flax, nettle-thread, and other like
                vegetable matters, are to be wetted in ſpinning : ſilks, wools, &amp;<hi
                    rend="italic">c.</hi> are ſpun dry, and do not need water ; yet there is a way
                of ſpinning or reeling silk as it comes off the caſes or balls, where hot and even
                boiling water is to be uſed (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Silk). </hi>The vaſt variety,
                and the importance of thoſe branches of our manufactures, which are produced from
                cotton, wool, and flax, ſpun into yarn, together with the cheapneſs of proviſions,
                and the low price of labour in many foreign countries, which are our rivals in
                trade, have occaſioned many attempts at home to render ſpinning more eaſy, cheap,
                and expeditious. For which see <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Cotton</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> Spinning</hi> and <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Cotton</hi><hi
                    rend="italic"> Mills.</hi></p>
            <p>Theſe contrivances have in ſome parts of Scotland been applied to the ſpinning of
                flax;@@ but a very conſiderable improvement has lately been made by Mr Antis of
                Fulneck near Leeds of the common ſpinning wheel. It is well known, that hitherto
                much time has been loſt by ſtopping the wheel in order to ſhit the thread from one
                ſtaple on the flyer to another ; but in Mr Antis’s wheel the bobbin is made to move
                backwards and forwards, ſo as to prevent the neceſſity of this perpetual
                interruption, as well as to obviate the Ganger of breaking the thread and losing the
                end. This is effected by the axis of the great wheel being extended through the
                pillar next the ſpinner, and formed into a pinion of one leaf A, which takes into a
                wheel B, ſeven inches diameter, having on its periphery 97 teeth; ſo that 97
                revolutions of the great wheel caule one of the leſſer wheel. On this leſſer wheel
                is fixed a ring of wire c c c; which, being ſupported on six legs, ſtands obliquely
                to the wheel itſelf, touching it at one part, and projecting nearly three quarters
                of an inch at the oppoſite one ; near the side of this wheel is an upright lever C,
                about 15 inches long, moving on a centre, three inches from its lower extremity, and
                connected at the top to a Aiding bar D; from which rises an upright piece of braſs
                E, which working in the notch of a pulley drives the bobbin F backward and forward,
                according as the oblique wire forces a pin G in or out, as the wheel moves round. To
                regulate and asſiſt the alternate motion, a weight H hangs by a line to the sliding
                bar, aind paſſing over a pulley rises and falls as the bobbin advances or recedes,
                and tends conſtantly to keep the pin in contact with the wire. It is evident, from
                this deſcription. that one ſtaple only is wanted to the flyer ; which, being placed
                near the extremity K, the thread palling through it is by the motion of the bobbin
                laid regularly thereon. For this invention the Society inſtituted at London for the
                Encouragement of Arts, &amp;c. gave the author a premium of twenty guineas.</p>
            <p>SPINOSUS <hi rend="smallcaps">caulis,</hi> in botany ; a stem covered with strong
                woody prickles, whole roots are not ſuperficial, but proceeding from the body of the
                ſtem. When applied to a leaf, <hi rend="italic">ſpinoſum fοlium,</hi> it indicates
                the margin running out into rigid points or prickles, <hi rend="italic">quod margine
                    exit in acumina duriοra, rigida, pungentia.</hi></p>
            <p>SPINOUS, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Spinosus.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">SPInous</hi><hi rend="italic"> Fishes,</hi> ſuch as have
                ſome of the rays of the back-fins running out into thorns or prickles, as the perch,
                &amp;c.</p>
            <p>SPINOZA (Benedict), was born at Amſterdam the 34th November 1632, His father was a
                Jew of Portugal, by profeſſion a merchant. After being taught Latin by a physician,
                he applied himſelf for many years to the ſtudy of theology, and afterwards devoted
                himſelf entirely to philoſophy. He began very early to be diſſatisfied with the
                Jewiſh religion ; and as his temper was open, he did not conceal his doubts From the
                ſynagogue. The Jews, it is ſaid, offered to tolerate his infidelity, and even
                promiſed him a pension of a thouſand dollars <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> if he
                would remain in their ſociety, and continue outwardly to practiſe their ceremonies.
                But if this offer was really made, he rejected it, perhaps from his aversion to
                hypocriſy, or rather becauſe he could not endure the reſtraint which it would have
                imposed. He alſo refuſed the legacy of a very conſiderable fortune, to the prejudice
                of the natural heirs ; and he learned the art of poliſhing glaſs for ſpectacles,
                that he might ſubſiſt independently of every one.</p>
            <p>He would probably have continued in the ſynagogue for ſome time longer, if it had not
                been for an accident. As he was returning home one evening from the theatre, he was
                stabbed by a Jew : the wound was flight ; but the attempt naturally led Spinoza to
                conclude that the Jews had formed the deſign of aſſaſſinating him. After leaving the
                ſynagogue, he became a Chriſtian, and frequented the churches of the Lutherans and
                Calviniſts. He now devoted himſelf more than ever to his favourite philoſophical
                ſpeculations ; and finding himſelf frequently interrupted by the visits of his
                friends, he left Amſterdam, and settled at the Hague, where he often continued for
                three months together without ever ſtirring from his lodging. During his reſidence
                in that city, his hoſteſs, who was a Lutheran, asked him one day if ſhe could be
                ſaved while the continued in her religion ? “ Yes (replied Spinoza), “provided you
                join to your religion a peaceable and virtuous life ’’ From this anſwer it has been
                concluded that he was a Christan in appearance only, while in reality he regarded
                all religions as indifferent. But this concluſion would be too ſevere, even if the
                woman had been a Mahometan. H is <hi rend="italic">Tractatus
                    Theolοgico-politicus</hi>, which was publiſhed about that time, is a better
                proof of his inſincerity than a thouſand ſuch conclusions ; tor this book contains
                all thoſe doctrines in embryo which were afterwards unfolded in his Op<hi
                    rend="italic">era Posthuma,</hi> and which are generally conſidered as a ſyſtem
                of atheiſm.</p>
            <p>His fame, which had now ſpread far and wide, obliged him ſometimes to interrupt his
                philoſophical reveries. Learned men viſited him from all quarters While the prince
                of Condé commanded the French army in Utrecht, he intreated Spinoza to viſit him;
                and though he was abſent when the philoſopher arrived, he returned immediately, and
                spent a conſiderable time with him in converſation. The elector Palatine offered to
                make Spinoza profeſſor of philoſophy at Heidelberg ; which, however, he
                declined.</p>
            <p>He died of a conſumption at the Hague on the 21st February 1677, at the age or 45.
                His life was a perpetual contradiction to his opinions. He was temperate, liberal,
                and remarkably diſintereſted ; he was ſociable, affable, and friendly. His
                converſation was agreeable and inſtructive, and never deviated from the ſtricteſt
                propriety.</p>
            <p>The only edition of the works of Spinosa that we have ſeen is in two volumes ſmall
                4to; the former of</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Trans. of the Society for the encouragement of Arts, &amp;c.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
