<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>they lose an arm or leg, and ſometimes are bit quite aſunder, ſerving but for two morſels for this ravenous animal : a melancholy tale of this kind is related in a West India ballad, preſerved in Dr Percy’s Relics of ancient Engliſh Poetry.</p><p>This ſpecies inhabits the abyſs of the ocean, and only appears on the ſurface when allured by its prey. It is the moſt voracious of all animals, not even it is ſaid ſparing its own offspring, and often ſwallowing its prey entire. At the famous naval battle of the 12th of April 1782, when the Caeſar, one of the French ſhips of the line, was ſet on fire, the ſailors threw themſelves into the ſea, Sir Charles Douglas obſerved great numbers of theſe ſharks, which lay between the French and Britiſh fleets, inſtantly ſeize on the unhappy victims. He ſeveral times ſaw two of them diſputing about their prey, each ſeizing a leg, and at length disappearing, dragging the body along with them. Notwithſtanding the continued roar of artillery, he heard diſtinctly the cries of thoſe unhappy men.</p><p>12.	<hi rend="italic">Pristis, ſcie,</hi> or ſaw-fiſh, is sometimes 15 feet long, ſmooth, black on the upper parts, aſh coloured on the sides, and white underneath. The head is flat and conical ; the beak or ſnout projecting from the noſe is about five feet long, covered with a coriaceous ſkin, and armed on each side, generally with 24 long, ſtrong, and ſharp-pointed teeth ; but the number varies with age. The teeth are granulated ; the eyes large, the iris of a golden colour, and the ſpiracles five. The anterior dorſal fin correſponds to thoſe of the belly ; the poſterior is situated in the middle, between the former and apex of the tail ; the pectoral fins are broad and long ; the caudal is ſhorter than in the other ſpecies. It inhabits all the ſeas from Greenland to Brazil : and is found alſo in the Indian Ocean. It is harmleſs.</p><p>13.	<hi rend="italic">Spinax, ſagre,</hi> or picked dog-fiſh, takes its name from a ſtrong and ſharp ſpine placed juſt before each of the back-fins, diſtinguishing it at once from the reſt of the Britiſh ſharks. The noſe is long, and extends greatly beyond the mouth, but is blunt at the end. The teeth are diſpoſed in two rows, are ſmall and ſharp, and bend from the middle of each jaw towards the corners of the mouth. The back is of a browniſh aſh-colour ; the belly white.—It grows to the weight of about 20 pounds. This ſpecies ſwarms on the coaſts of Scotland, where it is taken, ſplit, and dried ; and is a food among the common people. It forms a sort of inland commerce, being carried on womens backs 14 or 16 miles up the country, and fold or exchanged for neceſſaries.</p><p>14.	<hi rend="italic">Squatina,</hi> angel-fiſh, is from six to eight feet long, has a large head ; teeth broad at their baſe, but ſlender and very ſharp above, and diſpoſed in five rows all round the jaws. Like thoſe of all ſharks, they are capable of being raiſed or depreſſed by means of muſcles uniting them to the jaws, not being lodged in ſockets as the teeth of cetaceous fiſh are. The back is of a pale aſh-colour, and very rough ; along the middle is a prickly tuberculated line : the belly is white and ſmooth. The pectoral fins are very large, and extend horizontally from the body to a great diſtance ; they have ſome reſemblance to wings, whence its name. The ventral fins are placed in the ſame manner, and the double penis is placed in them ; which forms another character of the males in this genus.</p><p>This is the fiſh which connects the genus of rays and ſharks, partaking ſomething of the character of both ; yet is an exception to each in the situation of the mouth, which is placed at the extremity of the head. It is a fiſh not unfrequent on moſt of our coaſts, where it prowls about for prey like others of the kind. It is extremely voracious ; and, like the ray, feeds on flounders and flat fiſh, which keep at the bottom of the water. It is extremely fierce, and dangerous to be approached Mr Pennant mentions a fiſherman whoſe leg was terribly torn by a large one of this ſpecies, which lay within his nets in ſhallow water, and which he went to lay hold of incautiouſly. The aſpect of theſe, as well as the reſt of the genus, have much malignity in them : their eyes are oblong, and placed lengthwiſe in their head, ſunk in it, and overhung by the ſkin, and ſeem fuller of malevolence than fire. Their skin is very rough ; the ancients made uſe of it to poliſh wood and ivory, as we do at preſent that of the greater dog-fiſh. The fleſh is now but little eſteemed on account of its coarſeneſs and rankneſs ; yet Archeſtratus (as quoted by Athenaeus, p. 319.), ſpeaking of the fiſh of Miletus, gives this the firſt place, in reſpect to delicacy, of the whole cartilaginous tribe. They grow to a great ſize ; being ſometimes near an hundred weight.</p><p>Sharks are ſeldom deſtructive in the temperate regions ; it is in the torrid zone that their ravages are moſt frequent. In the West Indies accidents happen from them almoſt every day.</p><p>“During the American war in 1780, while the Pallas frigate was lying in Kingſton harbour,@@ a young North American jumped overboard one evening to make his eſcape, and periſhed by a ſhark in a ſhocking manner.</p><p>“ He had been captured in a ſmall veſſel, loſt all his property, and was detained by compulsion in the Engliſh navy, to ſerve in a depredatory war againſt his country. But he, animated with that ſpirit which pervaded every boſom in America, reſolved, as ſoon as he arrived at ſome port, to releaſe himſelf from the mortifying ſtate of employing his life againſt his country, which, as he ſaid when dying, he was happy to lay down, as he could not employ it againſt her enemies.</p><p>“ He plunged into the water ; the Pallas was a quarter of a mile from the ſhore. A ſhark perceived him, and followed him, very quietly, till he came to a ſtate of reſt, near the ſhore : where, as he was hanging by a rope, that moored a veſſel to a wharf, ſcarcely out of his depth, the ſhark ſeized his right leg, and ſtripped the fleſh entirely away from the bones, and took the foot off at the ancle. He ſtill kept his hold, and called to the people in the veſſel near him, who were ſtanding on the deck and law the affair. The ſhark then ſeized his other leg, which the man by his ſtruggling diſengaged from his teeth, but with the fleſh cut through down to the bone, into a multitude of narrow ships/ The people in the veſſel threw billets of wood into the water, and frightened the ſhark away. The young man was brought on ſhore. Dr Moſeley was called to him ; but he had loſt ſo much blood before any aſſiſtance could be given him, that he expired before the mangled limbs could be taken off.</p><p>“A few weeks before this accident happened, a ſhark, of 12 feet in length, was caught in the harbour; and</p><p>@@@[mu] Moseley on Tropical Diseases</p></body></text></TEI>