<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:27:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>STRANGER, in law, denotes a perſon who is not privy or party to an act. Thus a ſtranger to a judgement is he to whom a judgment does not belong ; in which ſenſe the word ſtands directly oppoſed to party or privy.</p><p>STRANGLES, in <hi rend="smallcaps">Farriery.</hi> See that article, *xiv.</p><p>STRANGURY, a ſuppreſſion of urine. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 119</p><p>STRAP, among ſurgeons, a sort of band uſed to ſtretch out limbs in the ſetting of broken or disjointed bones.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Strap,</hi> in a ſhip, the rope which is ſpliced about any block, and made with an eye to taſten it anywhere on occaſion.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Straps,</hi> in the manege. The ſtraps of a ſaddle are ſmall leather ſtraps, nailed to the bows of the ſaddle, with which we make the girths fast to the ſaddle.</p><p>STRAPADO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Strappado,</hi> a kind of military puniſhment, wherein the criminals hands being tied behind him, he is hoiſted up with a rope to the top of a long piece of wood, and let fall again almoſt to the ground ; ſo that, by the weight of his body in the ſhock, his arms are diſlocated. Sometimes he is to undergo three ſtrapadoes or more.</p><p>STRASBURG, an ancient, large, handſome, populous, and ſtrong city of France in Alſace. It contains about 200 ſtreets, part of which are very narrow, and moſt of the houſes are built after the ancient taſte. However, there are a great number of handsome buildings, ſuch as the hotel of the marſhal of France, who is commander of the city ; the hotel of the cardinal of Rouen, the biſhops palace, the Jeſuits college, the royal hoſpital, the hotel of Heſſe-Darmſtadt, the arſenal, the town-houſe, and the cathedral. It has a wooden bridge over the Rhine, which is thought to be one of the fineſt in Europe ; as is likewiſe the cathedral church, whoſe tower is the handsomeſt in Germany, and the clock is greatly admired by all travellers. Some look upon it as one of the wonders of the world, and the ſteeple is allowed to be the higheſt in Europe. The clock not only ſhows the hours of the day, but the motion of the sun, moon, and ſtars. Among other things there is an angel, which turns an hour-glaſs every hour ; and the twelve apoſtles proclaim noon, by each of them ſtriking a blow with a hammer on a bell. There is likewiſe a cock, which is a piece of clock-work, that crows every hour. There are 700 ſteps up to the tower or ſteeple, it being 500 feet high. It was a free and imperial city; but the king of France became maſter of it in 1681, and greatly augmented the fortifications, though beſore it had as many cannon as there are days in the year. The inhabitants were formerly Proteſtants, and carried on a great trade ; but moſt of them have been obliged to embrace the Romiſh ſuperſtition, though there is ſtill a sort of toleration. Such was Straſburg before the French revolution ; what it is now we have not leiſure to inquire. It is ſeated on the river Ill, 55 miles north of Baſil, 112 ſouth-weſt of Mentz, and 255 eaſt of Paris. E. Long. 7. 51. N. Lat. 48. 35.</p><p>STRATA, in natural hiſtory, the ſeveral beds or layers of different matters whereof the earth is complied. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Quarry.</hi></p><p>The ſtrata whereof the earth is compoſed are ſo very different in different countries, that it is impoſſible to ſay any thing concerning them that may be generally applicable : and indeed the depths to which we can penetrate are ſo ſmall, that only a very few can be known</p><p>of his life, which we have laid beſore our readers, upon the expreſs condition that we ſhould not alter a <hi rend="italic">ſingle word oſ it ;</hi> as the compoſition, we were told, would do <hi rend="italic">honour to our work.</hi> We have obſerved the condition, and therefore cannot claim this honour to any of the uſual writers in the Encyclopædia Britannica. If Sir Robert’s more intimate friends ſhall be pleaſed with the article, their gratitude will be due not to us, but to ſome of his neareſt relations ; and what may appear its defects to others (for the taſtes of mankind are very different), we truſt will be ſupplied by the following authentic catalogue of his works ; Plate 1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Two</hi> Heads of the author—one an etching, the other a finiſhed proof, from a drawing by John Baptiſte Greuſe ; 2. The Return from Market, by Wouvermans ; 3. Cupid, by Vanloo ; 4. Mary Magdalen, by Guido ; 5. Cleopatra, by the ſame ; 6. The Madonna, by the ſame ; 7. The Angel Gabriel, by the ſame ; 8. The Virgin, holding in her hand a book, and attended by angels, by Carlo Maratt ; 9. The Virgin with the Child aſleep, by the ſame ; 10. Liberality and Modeſty, by Guido ; 1 1. Apollo rewarding Merit and puniſhing Arrogance, by Andrea Sacchi ; 12. The Finding of Romulus and Remus, by Pietro da Cortona; 13. Cseſar repudiating Pompeia, by the ſame; 14. Three Children of King Charles I. by Vandyke ; l5. Beliſarius, by Salvator Roſa ; 16. St Agnes, by Dominichino ; 17. The Judgment of Hercules, by Nicolas Pouſſin ; 18. Venus attired by the Graces, by Guido ; 19 and 20. Justice and Meekneſs, by Raphael ; 21. The Offspring of Love, by Guido ; 22. Cupid ſleeping, by the ſame ; 23. Abraham giving up the Handmaid Hagar, by Guercino ; 24. Eſther a Suppliant before Ahaſuerus, by the ſame ; 25. Joſeph and Potiphar’s Wife, by Guido ; 26. Venus Blinding Cupid, by Titian ; 27. Venus, by the ſame ; 28. Danae, by the ſame ; 29. Portrait of King Charles I. by Vandyke ; 30. The Madonna, by Correggio ; 31. St Caecilia, by Raphael ; 32. Mary Magdalen, by Guido ; 33. Our Saviour appearing to his Mother after his Reſurrection, by Guercino ; 34. A Mother and Child, by Parmegiano; 35. Cupid Meditating, by Schidoni ; 36. Laomedon King of Troy detected by Neptune and Apollo, by Salvator Roſa ; 37. The Death of Dido, by Guercino ; 38. Venus and Adonis, by Titian ; 30. Fortune, by Guido; 40. Cleopatra, by the ſame 541. Two Children at School, by Schidoni ; 42. Mary Magdalen, by Correggio ; 43. Portrait of King Charles I. attended by the Marquis of Hamilton, by Vandyke ; 44. Queen Henrietta, attended by the Prince of Wales, and holding in her Arms the Duke of York, by the ſame ; 45. Apotheosis of the Royal Children, by West ; 46. The Annunciation, by Guido ; 47. Portrait of Raphael Sancio D’Urbino, by himſelf ; 48. Sappho, by Carlo Dolci ; 49. Our Saviour aſleep, by Vandyke ; 50. St John in the Desert, by Murillo.</p></body></text></TEI>