<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-04-20T21:21:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>fore him, without attending to any thing elſe, or thinking of its paradoxical author,
                or even of the Great Being who created the matter both of him and of it ; but he
                cannot for an instant contemplate the yellow colour of its vellum boards without
                thinking of triple extenſion, or, in other words, of body. The book therefore is a
                    <hi rend="italic">ſubstance,</hi> becauſe conceivable by itſelf ; the colour is
                an <hi rend="italic">attribute</hi> or <hi rend="italic">quality,</hi> becauſe it
                cannot be conceived by itſelf, but neceſſarily leads to the conception of ſomething
                elſe. But if Spinoza’s meaning be, that nothing is a ſubſtance but what is conceived
                as exiſting from eternity, independent of every thing as a cauſe, his definition
                cannot be admitted : for every man conceives that which in himſelf thinks, and
                wills, and is conscious, as a ſubſtance ; at the same time that he has the beſt
                evidence poſſible that he exiſted not as a conſcious, thinking, and active being,
                from eternity.</p>
            <p>His fourth axiom is thus expreſſed : “ Effectus cognitio a cognitione causæ dependet,
                et eandem involvit;” and his fifth, "Quæ nihil commune cum se invicem habent, etiam
                per se invicem intelligi non poſſunt, live conceptus unius alterius conceptum non
                involvit.” The former of theſe propoſitions, ſo far from being ſelf-evident, is not
                even true ; and the latter is capable of two ſenſes very different from each other.
                That every effect proceeds from <hi rend="italic">a cauſe,</hi> is indeed an axiom ;
                but finely we may know the effect accurately, though we be ignorant of the <hi
                    rend="italic">particular</hi> cauſe from which it proceeds (ſee <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Philosophy,</hi> n⁰ 36 ; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Physics,</hi>
                n⁰ 91, &amp;C.) ; nor does the knowledge of the one by any means involve the
                knowledge of the other. If different things have nothing in common, it is indeed
                true that the knowledge of one of them will not give us an <hi rend="italic"
                    >adequate conception</hi> of the other ; but it will in many cases compel us to
                believe, that the other <hi rend="italic">exists</hi> or has exiſted. A parcel of
                gunpowder lying at rest has nothing in common with the velocity of a cannon-ball ;
                yet when we know that a ball has been driven with velocity from a cannon, we infer
                with certainty that there has been a parcel of powder at rest in the chamber of that
                cannon.</p>
            <p>It is upon ſuch ambiguous definitions and axioms as theſe that Spinoza has raiſed his
                pretended demonstrations, that one ſubſtance cannot produce another ; that every
                ſubſtance muſt neceſſarily be infinite ; that no ſubſtance exiſts or can be
                conceived beſides God ; and that extended ſubſtance or body is one of the infinite
                    <hi rend="italic">attributes</hi> of God. We ſhall not waste our own time or the
                reader’s with a formal confutation of theſe impious abſurdities. We truſt they are
                sufficiently confuted in other articles of this work (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Metaphysics, </hi>Part III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Providence,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Theology,</hi> Part I.) ; and whoever wiſhes for a more
                particular examination of the author’s principles, may find it in Dr Clarke’s
                Demonſtration of the Being and Attributes of God. The truth, however, is, that no
                man will need the aſſiſtance of that eminent metaphyſician to diſcover the fallacy
                of the reasoning by which they are attempted to be proved, if he affix <hi
                    rend="italic">any one preciſe meaning</hi> to the definitions and axioms, and
                adhere to that meaning ſteadily thro’ the whole procels of the pretended
                demonſtrations.</p>
            <p>By way of apology for this jargon, it has been lately ſaid, that “ Spinoza takes the
                word substa<hi rend="italic">nce</hi> in its moſt ſimple and perfect ſenſe; which is
                necessary, as he writes mathematically, and propoſes a simple idea as the foundation
                oſ his theory. @@What is the proper ſignification of a ſubſtance? Is it not that
                which ſtands alone, which has the cauſe of its exiſtence within itſelf ? I wiſh that
                this ſimple meaning of the word could be univerſally admitted in philoſophy.
                Strictly ſpeaking, no worldly thing is a ſubſtance ; ſince all mutually depend on
                each other, and finally on God, who, in this exalted ſenſe, is the only <hi
                    rend="italic">ſubstance.</hi> The word <hi rend="italic">modification</hi>
                founds harſh and improper, and therefore it cannot be expected to gain a place in
                philoſophy ; but if the ſchool of Leibnitz may term matter the <hi rend="italic"
                    >appearance of ſubstances, </hi>why may not Spinoza be allowed a bolder term?
                Worldly subſtances are kept in union by divine power, as it was by divine power that
                they had exiſtence. They repreſent also, if you pleaſe, <hi rend="italic"
                    >modified</hi> appearances of divine power ; each according to the ſtation, the
                time, and the organs, in and with which it appears. The phraſe uſed by Spinoza is
                concise, and it gives an unity and simplicity to his whole ſyſtem, however ſtrange
                it may found in our ears.”</p>
            <p>From this account of Spinoziſm, one who had never looked into the works of the author
                would be led to ſuppoſe that his ſyſtem is the same with that of Berkeley ; which,
                denying the exiſtence of material ſubſtance, attributes all our perceptions of what
                we call the qualities of body to the immediate agency oſ the Deity on our minds (ſee
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> Part II. Chap. 3.) But Spinoza’s doctrine
                is very different. According to him, bodies are either attributes or affections of
                God; and as he ſays there is but one extended ſubſtance, he affirms that ſubſtance
                to be indivisible, and employs a long ſcholium @@* to prove that thoſe are miſtaken
                who ſuppoſe it finite and not <hi rend="italic">esſential to the Deity.</hi> That we
                do not miſrepreſent his ſentiments, the learned reader will be convinced by the two
                following definitions, with which he introduces that part of his ethics which treats
                of the nature and origin of mind. 1. “ Per corpus intelligo modum, qui Dei
                eſſentiam, quatenus, ut res extenſa conſideratur, certo et determinato modo
                exprimit.” 2. “ Ad essentiam alicujus rei id pertinere dico, quo dato res neceſſario
                ponitur, et quo sublato res neceſſario tollitur ; vel id, fine quo res, et vice
                verſa quod fine re nec eſſe nec concipi poteſt.” In conformity with theſe
                definitions, he attempts to prove that God@@ is an extended as well as a thinking
                ſubſtance ; that as a thinking ſubſtance he is the cause of the idea of a circle,
                and as an extended ſubſtance of the <hi rend="italic">circle</hi> itſelf ; and that
                the minds of men are not ſubſtances, but certain modifications of the divine
                attributes ; or, as he sometimes expreſses it, “ Quod humanae mentis actuale
                conſtituit, eſt idea rei ſingularis actu exiſtentis.” Hence, he ſays, it follows
                that the human mind is a part of the intellect of the infinite God ; so that when we
                ſpeak of the human mind perceiving this or that, we can only mean that God, not as
                he is infinite, but as he appears in the human mind or conſtitutes its eſſence, has
                this or that idea ; and when we ſpeak of God’s having this or that idea, we muſt
                conceive of Him not only as conſtituting the human mind, but as, together with it,
                having the idea of something elſe @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> In another place
                he tells us, that the human mind is nothing but the <hi rend="italic">idea</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@[mu] Herder's Dialogues concerning God.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@[m]* See his Prop. xv. &amp;c.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@[m] Prop. ii. vii. xi. Part 2.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> Hinc sequitur mentem humanam partem eſſe infiniti
                intellectus Dei ; ac proinde cum dicimus, mentem humanam hoc vel illud percipere,
                nihil aliud dicimus quam quod Deus, non quatenus infinitus est, sed quatenus per
                naturam humanæ mentis explicatur, five quatenus humanæ mentis essentiam conſtituſt,
                hanc vel illam habet ideam : et cum dicimus Deum hanc vel illam ideam habere, non
                tantum, quatenus naturam humanæ mentis constituit ; sed quatenus simul cum mente
                humana alterius rei etiam habet ideam. <hi rend="italic">Corol.</hi> prop. xi. part
                2.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
