<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>choſen of a fine gold yellow, very fine, tender, and friable, and free from dirt.</p><p>STILAGO, in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">gynandria,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">triandria. </hi>There is one female. The calyx is monophyllous, and almoſt three-lobed. There is no corolla, and the berry is globular. There is only one ſpecies, the bunius.</p><p>STILBE, in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">polygamia,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">diaecia.</hi> The exterior calyx of the hermaphrodite flower is triphyllous ; the interior is quinquedentate and cartilaginous. The corolla is funnel-ſhaped and quinquefid. There are four ſtamina ; and there is one ſeed in the interior calyx calyptrate. The female flower is ſimilar, has no interior calyx nor fruit There are three ſpecies, the pinaſtra, ericoides, and cornua, all foreign plants.</p><p>STILE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Style.</hi></p><p>STILL, the name of an apparatus uſed in chemiſtry and in the diſtillation of ardent ſpirits. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistery</hi><hi rend="italic">-Index</hi> at <hi rend="italic">Distillatiοn</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Still.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">STILL-Bοttοms,</hi> in the diſtillery, a name given by the traders to what remains in the ſtill after working the wash into low wines. Theſe bottoms are procured in the greateſt quantity from the malt wash, and are of ſo much value to the diſtiller in the fattening of hogs, &amp;c. that he often finds them one of the moſt valuable articles of the buſineſs.</p><p>STILLINGFLEET (Edward), biſhop of Worceſter, was the ſon of Samuel Stillingfleet gentleman, and was born at Cranborn in Dorſetſhire in 1635. He was educated at St John’s College, Cambridge ; and having received holy orders, was, in 1657, preſented to the rectory ol Sutton in Nottinghamſhire. By publiſhing his <hi rend="italic">Origines Sacre,</hi> one of the ableſt defences of revealed religion that has ever been written, he ſoon acquired ſuch reputation, that he was appointed preacher of the Rolls Chapel; and in January 1665 was preſented to the rectory of St Andrew’s, Holborn. He was afterwards choſen lecturer at the Temple, and appointed chaplain in ordinary to king Charles II. In 1668 he took the degree of doctor of divinity ; and was ſoon after engaged in a diſpute with thoſe of the Romiſh religion, by publiſhing his diſcourſe concerning the idolatry and fanaticiſm of the church of Rome, which he aſterwards defended againſt ſeveral antagoniſts. In 1680 he preached at Guildhall chapel a ſermon on Phil. iii. 26. which he publiſhed under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Miſchief of Separation ;</hi> and this being immediately attacked by ſeveral writers, he in 1683 publiſhed his <hi rend="italic">Unreasonableneſs of Separation. </hi>In 1685 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Origines Britannica,</hi> or the Antiquities of the Britiſh Church, in folio. During the reign of king James II. he wrote ſeveral tracts againſt popery, and was prolocutor of the convocation, as he had likewiſe been under Charles II. After the Revolution he was advanced to the biſhoprſe of Worceſter, and was engaged in a diſpute with the Socinians, and alſo with Mr Locke ; in which laſt conteſt he is generally thought to have been unſucceſsful He died at Weſtminſter in 1699, and was interred in the cathedral of Worceſter, where a monument was erected to his memory by his ſon. Dr Stillingfleet wrote other works beſides thoſe here mentioned, which, with the above, have been reprinted in 6 vols, folio.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stillingfleet</hi> (Benjamin), an ingenious naturaliſt, was grandſon of the preceding. His father Edward was fellow of St John’s College in Cambridge, F. R. S. M. D. and Greſham profeſsor of phyſic : but marrying in 1692, he loſt his lucrative offices and his father’s favour ; a misfortune that affected both himſelf and his poſterity. However, going into orders, he obtained, by his father’s means, the living of Newington-Butts, which he immediately exchanged for thoſe of Wood-Norton and Swanton in Norfolk. He died in 1708.</p><p>Benjamin, his only ſon, was educated at Norwich ſchool, which he left in 1720, with the character of an excellent ſcholar. He then went to Trinity-College in Cambridge, at the requeſt of Dr Bentley, the maſter, who had been private tutor to his father, domeſtic chaplain to his grandfather, and much indebted to the family. Here he was a candidate for a fellowſhip, but was rejected by the matter's influence. This was a ſevere and unexpected diſappointment, and but little alleviated afterwards by the Doctor's apology, that it was a pity that a gentleman of Mr Stillingfleet’s parts ſhould be buried within the walls oſ a college.</p><p>Perhaps, however, this ingratitude of Dr Bentley was not of any real diſſervice to Mr Stillingfleet. By being thrown into the world, he formed many honourable and valuable connections. He dedicated ſome tranſlations of Linnæus to the late lord Lyttleton, partly, he ſays, from motives of private reſpect and honour. Lord Barrington gave him, in a very polite manner, the place of the maſter of the barracks at Kenſington ; a favour to which Mr Stillingfleet, in the dedication of his Calendar of Flora to that nobleman, alludes with equal politeneſs, as well as with the warmeſt gratitude. His Calendar of Flora was formed at Stratton in Norfolk in the year 1755, at the hoſpitable ſeat of his very worthy and ingenious friend Mr Marſham, who had made ſeveral obſervations of that kind, and had communicated to the public his curious obſervations on the growth of trees. But it was to Mr Wyndham of Felbrig in Norfolk that he appears to have had the greateſt obligations : he travelled abroad with him, ſpent much of his time at his houſe, and was appointed one of his executors (Mr Garrick was another), with a conſiderable addition to an annuity which that gentleman had ſettled upon him in his lifetime.</p><p>Mr Stillingfleet’s genius ſeems, if we may judge from his works, to have led him principally to the study of natural hiſtory ; which he prosecuted as an ingenious philoſopher, an uſeful citizen, and a good man. In this walk of learning he mentions, as his friends, Dr Watſon, Mr (afterwards Dr) Solander, Mr Hudson, Mr Price of Foxley, and ſome others ; to whom may be added the ingenious Mr Pennant. Nor can we omit the flattering mention which the late Mr Gray makes of him in one of his letters, dated from London in 1761 : “I have lately made an acquaintance with this philoſopher, who lives in a garret here in the winter, that he may ſupport ſome near relations  who depend upon him. He is always employed, conſequently (according to my old maxim) always happy, always cheerful, and ſeems to me a very worthy honeſt man. His preſent ſcheme is to ſend ſome perſons, properly qualified, to reſide a year or two in Attica, to make themſelves acquainted with the climate, productions,</p></body></text></TEI>