<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>own, truths which others have diſcovered before him. He is charmed to find on theſe occasions that he is not a firſt inventor, and that others have made a greater progreſs than he thought. Far from being a plagiary, he attributes ingenious ſolutions, which he gives to certain problems, to the hints he has found in others, although the connection is but very diſtant,” &amp;c.</p><p>Mr Stone was author and tranſlator of ſeveral uſeful works ; viz. I. A New Mathematical Dictionary, in 1 vol. 8vo, firſt printed in 1726.	2. Fluxions, in 1</p><p>vol. 8vo, 1730. The Direct Method is a translation from the French, of Hospital’s Analyſe des Infiniments Petits ; and the Inverſe Method was ſupplied by Stone himſelf. 3. The Elements of Euclid, in 2 vols. 8vo, 1731. A neat and uſeful edition of thoſe Elements, with an account of the life and writings of Euclid, and a defence of his elements againſt modern objectors. Beſide other ſmaller works. Stone was a fellow of the Royal Society, and had inſerted in the Philoſophical Tranſactions (vol. 41, p. 218) an “ Account of two ſpecies of lines of the 3d order, not mentioned by Sir Iſaac Newton or Mr Stirling.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi> (Jerome), the ſon of a reputable ſeaman, was born in the pariſh of Scoonie, in the county of Fife, North Britain. His father died abroad when he was but three years of age, and his mother, with her young family, was left in very narrow circumſtances. Jerome, like the rest of the children, having got the ordinary ſchool education, reading Engliſh, writing, and arithmetic, betook himſelf to the busineſs of a travelling chapman. But the dealing in buckles, garters, and ſuch ſmall articles, not ſuiting his ſuperior genius, he ſoon converted his little ſtock into books, and for ſome years went through the country, and attended the fairs as an itinerant bookſeller. There is great reaſon to believe that he engaged ill this new ſpecies of traffic, more with a view to the improvement of his mind than for any pecuniary emolument. Formed by nature for literature, he poſſeſſed a peculiar talent for acquiring languages with amazing facility. Whether from a desire to underſtand the Scriptures in their original languages, or from being informed that theſe languages are the parents of many others, he began his philological purſuits with the ſtudy of the Hebrew and Greek tongues ; and, by a wonderful effort of genius and application, made himſelf ſo far maſter of theſe, without any kind of aſſiſtance, as to be able to interpret the Hebrew Bible and Greek Teſtament into Engliſh <hi rend="italic">ad aperturam libri.</hi> At this time he did not know one word of Latin. Senſible that he could make no great progreſs in learning, without the knowledge of at leaſt the grammar of that language, he made application to the pariſh ſchoolmaſter for his aſſiſtance. Some time afterwards, he was encouraged to proſecute his ſtudies at the Univerſity of St Andrew’s. An unexampled proficiency in every branch of literature recommended him to the eſteem of the profeſſors ; and an uncommon fund of wit and pleaſantry rendered him, at the ſame time, the favourite of all his fellow ſtudents, ſome of whom ſpeak of him to this day with an enthusiaſtic degree of admiration and reſpect. About this period ſome very humorous poetical pieces of his composition were publiſhed in the Scots Magazine. Before he had finiſhed his third ſeſſion, or term, at St Andrew’s, on an application to the College by the maſter of the ſchool of Dunkeld for an uſher, Mr Stone was recommended as the beſt qualified for that office ; and about two or three years after, the maſter being removed to Perth, Mr Stone, by the favour of his Grace the Duke of Atholl, who had conceived a high opinion of his abilities, was appointed his ſuccessor.</p><p>When he firſt went to Dunkeld, he entertained but an unfavourable opinion of the Gaelic language, which he conſidered as nothing better than a barbarous inarticulate gibberiſh ; but being bent on inveſtigating the origin and deſcent of the ancient Scots, he ſuffered not his prejudices to make him neglect the ſtudy of their primitive tongue. Having, with his uſual aſſiduity and ſucceſs, mattered the grammatical difficulties which he encountered, he ſet himſelf to diſcover ſomething of the true genius and character of the language. He collected a number of ancient poems, the production, of Iriſh or Scottiſh bards, which, he ſaid, were daring, innocent, paſſionate, and bold. Some of theſe poems were tranſlated into Engliſh verſe, which ſeveral perſons now alive have ſeen in manuſcript, before Mr Macpherſon publiſhed any of his tranſlations from Offian.</p><p>He died while he was writing and preparing for the preſs a treatiſe, intitled, “ An Inquiry into the Original of the Nation and Language of the ancient Scots, with Conjectures about the Primitive State of the Celtic and other European Nations ;” an idea which could not have been conceived by an ordinary genius. In this treatiſe he proves that the Scots drew their original, as well as their language, from the ancient Gauls. Had Mr Stone lived to finish this work, which diſcovers great ingenuity, immenſe reading, and indefatigable industry, it would have thrown light upon the dark and early periods of the Scottiſh history, as he opens a new and plainpath for leading us through the unexplored labyrinths of antiquity. But a fever put an end to his life, his labours, and his uſefulneſs, in the year 1757, being then only in the 30th year of his age. He left, in manuſcript, a much eſteemed and well-known allegory, intitled “ The Immortality of Authors,” which has been publiſhed and often reprinted ſince his death, and will be a laſting monument of a lively fancy, ſound judgement, and correct taste. It was no ſmall ornament of this extraordinary character, that he paid a pious regard to his aged mother, who ſurvived him two years, and received an annual penſion from the Dutcheſs of Atholl as a testimony of reſpect to the memory of her ſon.</p><p>STONEHIVE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Stonehaven,</hi> a ſmall town in the county of Kincardine, in Scotland, 15 miles ſouth from Aberdeen. It was built in the time of Charles II. and ſtands at the foot of ſome high cliffs, in a ſmall bay, with a rocky bottom, opening a little in one part, ſo that ſmall veſſels may find admittance, but only at high water. A pier laps over this harbour from the north side to ſecure them after their entrance. The town contains about 800 inhabitants. The manufactures are sail-cloths and Oſnaburghs, knit worſted and thread stockings.</p><p>STONES, in natural history, bodies which are inſipid, not ductile, nor inflammable, nor ſoluble in water. But as this is the definition given of earths by chemists and naturaliſts, we muſt refer the reader to the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Earth,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mineralogy,</hi> Part II. claſs 1. for a</p></body></text></TEI>