<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>keep off naked animals that would approach to hurt them.</p><p>STING, art apparatus in the bodies oſ certain insects, in form of a little ſpear, ſerving them as a weapon oſ offence.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STING-Ray,</hi> in ichthyology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Raiλ.</hi></p><p>@@STINK-ΡΟΤ, an earthen jar or ſhell, charged with powder, grenadoes, and other materials of an offenſive and ſuffocating ſmell. It is frequently uſed by privateers, in the weſtern ocean, in the attack of an enemy whom he deſigns to board ; for which purpoſe it is furniſhed with a light fuſe at the opening or touch-hole. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Boarding.</hi></p><p>STINT, a ſpecies of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Tringa.</hi></p><p>STIPA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Feather Grass,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">triandria,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">digynia ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 4th order, <hi rend="italic">Gramina.</hi> The calyx is bivalved. The exterior valve of the corolla is terminated by an awn ; the baſe is jointed.</p><p>There are nine ſpecies, the pennata, juncea, capillata, ariſtella, tenaciſſima, avenacea, membranacea, arguens, and ſpicata. Of theſe one only is Britiſh, the <hi rend="italic">pennata </hi>or common feather graſs. The beards are feathered. The plant riſes to the height of 10 inches, grows on mountains, and flowers in July or August.</p><p>STIPEND, among the Romans, signifies the ſame with tribute ; and hence st<hi rend="italic">ipendarii</hi> were the ſame with <hi rend="italic">tributarii.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stipend,</hi> in Scots law. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Law,</hi> clix. 12.</p><p>STIPULA, in botany, one of the fulcra or props of plants, defined by Linnæus to be a ſcale, or ſmall leaf, stationed on each side the baſe of the footstalks of the flower and leaves, at their first appearance, for the purpoſe of ſupport. Elmgren reſtricts it to the footſtalks of the leaves only.</p><p>STIPULATION, in the civil law, the act of ſtipulating, that is, of treating and concluding terms und conditions to be inſerted in a contract. Stipulations were anciently performed at Rome, with abundance of ceremonies ; the first whereof was, that one party ſhould interrogate, and the other anſwer, to give his consent, and oblige himſelf. By the ancient Roman law, nobody couid stipulate but for himſelf ; but as the Tabelliones were public ſervants, they were allowed to stipulate for their maſters ; and the notaries ſucceeding the Tabelliones have inherited the ſame privilege.</p><p>STIRIA, a province of Germany, in the circle of Auſtria, with the title of a duchy. It is bounded on the north by the archduchy of Ayſtria, on the eaſt by Hungary, on the ſouth by Carmola, and on the west by Carinthia and the archbiſhopric of Saltſburg ; being 125 miles in length and 17 in breadth. It is ſaid to contain 22 cities, 95 towns, 338 caſtles, 15 convents, and 200,000 inhabitants. Though it is a mountainous country, yet there is a great deal of land fit for tillage, and the ſoil is ſo good, that the inhabitants never were in want of corn. It contains mines ot very good iron ; whence the arms made there are in great eſteem. The women differ greatly from the Auſtrians, and are very plain and downright, They have all swellings on their throats, called <hi rend="italic">bronchoceles.</hi> The men are also very simple, and are very zealous worſhippers of the Virgin Mary, They delight to sit at home in the chimney- corner, never troubling their heads about foreign affairs. The chief town is Gratz.</p><p>STIRLING, a town of Scotland, situated on the river Forth, 35 miles north-west of Edinburgh, in W. Long. 3. 59. N. Lat. 56. 6. It is alſo called <hi rend="italic">Sterling</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Striveling ;</hi> from the former of which Boethius falſely derives the name <hi rend="italic">Sterling money ;</hi> becauſe, ſays he, Oſheit, a Saxon prince, after the overthrow of the Scots, eſtabliſhed a mint there. The name of <hi rend="italic">Striveling</hi> is ſaid to have been derived from the frequency of ſtrifes or conflicts in the neighbourhood. The town contains about 4000 inhabitants. It has a manufacture of tartans and shalloons, and employs about 30 looms in that of carpets. The great ſtreet is very broad. In it is the tolbooth, where is kept the ſtandard for the wet meaſures of Scotland. The other streets are narrow and irregular.—Stirling is in miniature a reſemblance of Edinburgh ; being built on a rock of the ſame form, with a fortreſs on the ſummit. The origin of the caſtle is unknown. The rock of Stirling was strongly fortified by the Picts, amongſt whom architecture and ſeveral other useful arts had made a considerable progreſs. As it lay in the extremities of their kingdom, the posſeſſion of it was the occasion of frequent conteſts betwixt them and their neighbours the Scots and Northumbrians ; each of whoſe dominions did, for ſome time, terminate near it.</p><p>When the Scots, under Kenneth II. overthrew the Pictiſh empire near the middle of the ninth century, they endeavoured to obliterate every memorial of that people. They not only gave new names to provinces and towns, but, with all the rage of barbarians, demoliſhed many magnificent and useful edifices which had been reared up by them, and this fortreſs among the rest. It was, however, ſoon rebuilt, though upon an occaſion not very honourable to the Scots.</p><p>Upon the death of Kenneth II. in 855, his brother Donald V. mounted the throne of Scotland. In the beginning of his reign the kingdom was invaded by Oſbrecht and Ella, two Northumbrian princes, who, uniting their forces with the Cumbrian Britons, and a number of Picts, who upon their expulsion from their native country had taken refuge in England, advanced to Jedburgh, where Donald encountered them ; and, after a fierce and bloody battle, obtained a complete victory : but, having taken up his ſtation in Berwick, in ſupine ſecurity, the Northumbrians, informed of the careleſs poſture in which the Scottiſh army lay, ſurpriſed them by a haſty march, diſperſed them, and made a priſoner of the king. Purſuing the advantage they had gained, they marched northward, and ſubdued all before them to the Frith of Forth and the town or Stirling. But the forlorn situation of the Scots, without a king and without an army, obliging them to ſue for peace, they obtained it, upon condition that they ſhould pay a ſum of money for the ranſom of the king, and yield up all their dominions upon the ſouth side of the Forth to the conquerors.</p><p>The Northumbrians taking poſſeſſion of the territories ceded to them by this treaty, rebuilt the caſtle of Stirling, and planted it with a ſtrong garriſon, in order to preſerve their new conqueſts, upon the frontiers of which it was situated. Our authorities alſo inform</p><p>@@@[mu] Falconer. Marine Dictionary. </p></body></text></TEI>