<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><table><row><cell/><cell>Feet.</cell><cell>In.</cell></row><row><cell>Length of the cave from the rock without,</cell><cell>371</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>From the pitch of the arch,</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Breadth of ditto at the mouth,</cell><cell>53</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>At the farther end,</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Height of the arch at the mouth,</cell><cell>117</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>At the end,</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Height of an outſide pillar,</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Of one at the north west corner,</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Depth of water at the mouth,</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>At the bottom,</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>6</cell></row></table><p>" The cave runs into the rock in the direction of north-east by eaſt by the compaſs.</p><p>“ Proceeding farther to the north-west, you meet with the higheſt ranges of pillars ; the magnificent appearance of which is paſt all deſcription. Here they are bare to their very baſis, and the ſtratum below them is alſo viſible ; in a ſhort time, if riſes many feet above the water, and gives an opportunity of examining its quality. Its ſurface is rough, and has often large lumps of ſtone flicking in it as if half immerſed : itſelf, when broken, is compoſed of a thouſand heterogeneous parts, which together have very much the appearance of a lava : and the more ſo, as many of the lumps appear to be of the very ſame ſtone of which the pillars are formed. This whole ſtratum lies in an inclined position, dipping gradually towards the south-eaſt. As hereabouts is the ſituation of the higheſt pillars, I ſhall mention my meaſurements of them, and the different ſtrata in this place, premising, that the measurements were made with a line, held in the hand of a perſon who flood at the top of the cliff, and reaching to the bottom ; to the lower end of which was tied a white mark, which was obſerved by one who ſtaid below for the purpoſe : when this mark was ſet off from the water, the perſon below noted it down, and made signal to him above, who made then a mark in his rope : whenever this mark passed a notable place, the same ſignal was made, and the name of the place noted down as before : the line being all hauled up, and the diſtances between the marks meaſured and noted down, gave, when compared with the book kept below, the diſtances, as for inſtance in the cave :</p><p>“ N⁰ I. in the book below, was called from the water to the foot of the firſt pillar in the book above ; 23⁰ I. gave 56 feet 8 inches, the higheſt of that aſcent, which was compoſed of broken pillars.</p><p>“ N⁰ I. Pillar at the well corner of Fingal’s cave.</p><table><row><cell>1. From the water to the foot of the pillar,</cell><cell><p>Feet.</p><p>12</p></cell><cell><p>In.</p><p>10</p></cell></row><row><cell>2. Height of the pillar,	</cell><cell>3.7</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell><p>3 Stratum above the pillar,</p><p>“ N⁰ 2. Fingal’s cave. </p></cell><cell>66</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>1. From the water to the foot of the pillar,</cell><cell>3<hi rend="superscript">6</hi></cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>2. Height of the pillar,</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>3 From the top of the pillar to the top of the arch,	</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>31</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Thickneſs of the ſtratum above,</cell><cell>34</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>By adding together the three firſt meaſurements we got the height of the arch from the water,	</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell>117</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>“ N<hi rend="superscript">o⁰</hi> 3. Corner pillar to the weſtward of Fingal's cave.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Stratum below the pillar of lava-like matter,</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Length of pillar,</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table><table><row><cell>Stratum above the pillar</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>“ N⁰ 4. Another pillar to the Westward.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Stratum below the pillar,</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>I</cell></row><row><cell>Height of the pillar,</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Stratum above,</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>I</cell></row><row><cell>N⁰ 5. Another pillar farther to the weſt- ward.</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Stratum below the pillar,</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>8</cell></row><row><cell>Height oſ the pillar,	</cell><cell>55</cell><cell>I</cell></row><row><cell>Stratum above,</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>7</cell></row></table><p>“ The ſtratum above the pillars, which is here mentioned, is uniformly the ſame, consiſting of numberleſs ſmall pillars, bending and inclining in all directions, ſometimes ſo irregularly that the stones can only be ſaid to have an inclination to aſſume a columnar form ; in others more regular, but never breaking into or diſturbing the ſtratum of large pillars, whose tops everywhere keep an uniform and regular line.</p><p>“ Proceeding now along the ſhore round the north end of the iſland, you arrive at <hi rend="italic">Oua na scarve,</hi> or the Corvorant’s Cave. Here the ſtratum under the pillars is lifted up very high ; the pillars above it are considerably leſs than thoſe at the north west end of the iſland, but ſtill very considerable. Beyond is a bay, which cuts deep into the iſland, rendering it in that place not more than a quarter of a mile over. On the ſides of this bay, eſpecially beyond a little valley, which almoſt cuts the iſland into two, are two ſtages of pillars, but ſmall ; however, having a ſtratum between them exactly the ſame as that above them, formed of innumerable little pillars, ſhaken out of their places, and leaning in all directions.</p><p>“ Having paſſed this bay, the pillars totally ceaſe; the rock is of a dark-brown ſtone, and no signs of regularity occur till you have paſſed round the ſouth-eaſt end of the iſland (a ſpace almoſt as large as that occupied by the pillars), which you meet again on the west fide, beginning to form themſelves irregularly, as if the ſtratum had an inclination to that form, and ſoon arrive at the bending pillars where I began.</p><p>“ The ſtone of which the pillars are formed, is a coarſe kind of basaltes, very much reſembling the Giant’s Cauſeway in Ireland, though none of them are near ſo neat as the ſpecimens of the latter which I have ſeen at the Britiſh Muſeum; owing chiefly to the colour, which in ours is a dirty brown, in the Iriſh a fine black ; indeed the whole production items very much to reſemble the Giant’s Cauſeway.”</p><p>STAFFORD, the County town of Staffordſhire, in W. Long. 2. 0. N. Lat. 53. 0. It ſtands on the river Sow, has two-pariſh churches, a fine ſquare market-place, and a flourihing cloth-manufacture. It sends two members to parliament, and is 135 miles from London. <hi rend="italic">	.</hi></p><p>STAFFORDSHIRE, a county of England, bounded on the ſouth by Worceſterſhire, by Cheshire and Derbyſhire on the north, by Warwickſhire and Derbyſhire on the eaſt, and Shropshire and Cheſhire on the well. The length is reckoned 62 miles, the breadth 33, and the circumference 180. It contains 5 hundreds, 150 pariſhes, 810,000 acre's, and 18 market towns. The air, except in thoſe parts that are called the Moorlands and Woodlands, and about the mines, is good, eſpecially upon the hills, where it is accounted</p></body></text></TEI>