<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ceſſion of James I. ; and being therefore of a temporary nature, ought to have expired with the miſchief which it meant to remedy. For, in point of ſolid and ſubſtantial juſtice, it cannot be ſaid that the mode of killing, whether by ſtabbing, ſtrangling, or ſhooting, can either extenuate or enhance the guilt; unleſs where, as in the case of poiſoning, it carries with it internal evidence of cool and deliberate malice. @@But the benignity of the law hath conſtrued the statute ſo favourably in behalf of the ſubject, and ſo ſtrictly when againſt him, that the offence of ſtabbing now ſtands almoſt upon the ſame footing as it did at the common law. Thus, (not to repeat the cases mentioned under <hi rend="smallcaps">Manslaughter,</hi> of ſtabbing an adultereſs, &amp;c. which are barely manſlaughter, as at common law), in the conſtruction of this statute it hath been doubted, whether, if the deceaſed had ſtruck at all before the mortal blow given, this does not take it out oſ the statute, tho’ in the preceding quarrel the stabber had given the firſt blow ; and it ſeems to be the better opinion, that this is not within the ftatute. Alſo it hath been resolved, that the killing a man, by throwing a hammer or other weapon, is not within the statute ; and whether a ſhot with a pistol be ſo or not is doubted. But if the party ſlain had a cudgel in his hand, or had thrown a pot or a bottle, or diſcharged a pistol at the party ſtabbing, this is a ſufficient reaſon for having a weapon drawn on his side within the words of the statute.</p><p>STACHYS, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">didynamιa,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">gymnospermia; </hi>and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 42d order, V<hi rend="italic">erticillatae.</hi> The upper lip of the corolla is arched ; the lower lip reflexed, and the larger intermediate lacinia is marginated. The stamina, after ſhedding the farina, are bent towards the ſides. There are 17 ſpecies, the ſylvatica, paluſtris, alpina, germanica, lanata, cretica, glutinoſa, orientalis, palæstina, maritima, æthiopica, hirta, canariensis, recta, annua, and arvenſis. Four only are natives of Britain.</p><p>ι. <hi rend="italic">Sylvatica,</hi> hedge-nettle. The plant is hairy all over, erect, a yard high, and branched ; the hairs are jointed. The flowers are of a deep red colour, six or eight in a whirl, which terminates in a long ſpike deſtitute of leaves. The leaves are heart-shaped, and grow on footſtalks. The whole plant has a strong fetid ſmell. It grows commonly in woods and shady places, and flowers in July or Auguſt. 2. <hi rend="italic">Palustris,</hi> clown’s allheal. The roots are white and tuberous. The ſtalk is branched at the bottom, and two or three feet high. The flowers are red or purple, from six to ten in a whirl, ending in a long ſpike. The leaves are ſeſſile, narrow, pointed, and in part ſurrounding the ſtem. This plant has a fetid ſmell and bitter taste, and is reckoned a good vulnerary. It grows on the ſides of rivers and lakes, in low moiſt grounds, and ſometimes in corn-fields. 3. <hi rend="italic">Germanica,</hi> baſe hore-hound. The stem is downy, and about two feet high. The leaves are white, downy, wrinkled, and indented. The flowers are white; purpliſh within, and grow in multiflorous whirls. It grows in England. 4. <hi rend="italic">Arvensis,</hi> corn-stachys, petty iron- wort, or all-heal. The ſtalk is 10 or <hi rend="italic">12</hi> inches high, fquare, branched, and hairy. The leaves are heart- ſhaped, obtuae, bluntly ſerrated, and leſs hairy. The calyx is hairy and ſeſſile, and deeply divided into five acute dents of equal length. The flowers are fleſh-coloured, and grow from three to six in a whirl. The lower lip is trifid ; the middle ſegment ſpotted with red, but not emarginated according to the character of the genus. It is frequent in corn-fields, and grows from June to Auguſt.</p><p>STADIUM, an ancient Greek long meaſure, containing 125 geometrical paces, or 625 Roman feet, correſponding to our furlong. The word is ſaid to be formed from the Greek word ςασις “a ſtation,” or “ to ſtand,” becauſe it is reported that Hercules having run a stadium at one breath, flood still at the end of it. The Greeks uſually meaſured diſtances by ſtadia, which they called ςφαϐιασμς<hi rend="italic">.</hi> Stadium alſo signified the courſe on which their races were run.</p><p>STADTHOLDER, the principal magiſtrate or governor of the Seven United Provinces. This office is now aboliſhed by the republican influence of France ; but as the prince of Orange is in alliance with this country, our readers will probably not be ill pleaſed with a short account of his ſeveral powers and claims. To render that account the more intelligible, we ſhall trace the office of Stadtholder from its origin.</p><p>The Seven Provinces of the Low Countries were long governed by princes invested with the ſovereignty, though limited in their powers, and under various titles ; as <hi rend="italic">Counts of Holland, Dukes of Guelder, Bishop of Utrecht, &amp;c.</hi> When theſe countries fell to the princes of the houſe of Burgundy, and afterwards to thoſe of Austria, who had many other dominions, the abſence of the ſovereign was ſupplied by a ſtadtholder or governor, vested with very ample powers. Theſe ſtadtholders or lieutenants had the adminiſtration of the government, and preſided in the courts of juſtice, whole juriſdiction was not at that time confined merely to the trial of causes, but extended to affairs of ſtate. The ſtadt- holders ſwore allegiance to the princes at their inauguration, jointly with the states of the provinces they governed. They likewiſe took an oath to the states, by which they promiſed to maintain their fundamental laws and privileges.</p><p>It was upon this footing that William the Firſt, prince of Orange, was made governor and lieutenant- general of Holland, Zealand, and Utrecht, by Philip the Second, upon his leaving the Low Countries to go into Spain. The troubles beginning ſoon after, this prince found means to bring about an union, in 1576, between Holland and Zealand ; the states of which two provinces put into his hands, as far as was in their power, the ſovereign authority (for ſo long time as they ſhould remain in war and under arms), upon the ſame footing as Holland had intruſted him with in the year before. In 1581 the ſame authority was again renewed to him by Holland, as it was ſoon after by Zealand likewiſe ; and in 1584, being already elected count of Holland, upon certain conditions he would have been formally invested with the ſovereignty, had not a wretch, hired and employed by the court of Spain, put an end to his life by a horrid aſſaſſination.</p><p>In the preamble of the inſtruments by which the states in 1581 conferred the ſovereign authority upon prince William the Firſt, we find theſe remarkable words, which are there ſet down as fundamental rules :</p><p>That all republics and communities ought to preſerve, maintain, and fortify themſelves by unanimity ; which being impossible to be kept up always among ſo</p><p>@@@[mu] Blackest. Comment. vol. iv. p. 193. </p></body></text></TEI>