<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:26:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſon of fixing the manufacture in this ſpot, except for the convenience of plenty of coals, which abound under all the country.</p><p>The flints firſt are ground in mills, and the clay prepared by breaking, washing, and sifting, and then they are mixed in the requiſite proportions. The flints are bought firſt by the people about the country, and by them burnt and ground, and sold to the manufacturers by the peck.</p><p>The mixture is then laid in large quantities on kilns to evaporate the moiſture; but this is a nice work, as it muſt not be too dry ; next it is beat with large wooden hammers, and then is in order for throwing, and is moulded into the forms in which it is to remain : this is the moſt difficult work in the whole manufacture. A boy turns a perpendicular wheel, which by means of thongs turns a ſmall horizontal one, just before the thrower, with ſuch velocity, that it twirls round the lump of clay he lays on it into any form he directs it with his fingers.</p><p>There are 300 houſes which are calculated to employ, upon an average, twenty hands each, or 6000 in the whole ; but of all the variety of people that work in what may be called the preparation for the employment of the immediate manufacturers, the total number cannot be much short of 10,000, and it is increaſing every day. Large quantities are exported to Germany, Ireland, Holland, Russia, Spain, the Eaſt Indies, and much to America ; ſome of the fineſt sorts to France.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Stone</hi><hi rend="italic"> in the Bladder.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 400. <hi rend="smallcaps">Survey</hi><hi rend="italic">-Index ;</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Alkali,</hi> n⁰ 17, 18, 19.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone,</hi> in merchandize, denotes a certain weight for weighing commodities. A ſtone oſ beef at London is the quantity of eight pounds: in Herefordshire 12 pounds : in the North 16 pounds. A ſtone of glaſs is five pounds ; of wax eight pounds. A ſtone of wool according to the ſtatute of 11 Hen. VII.) is to weigh 14 pounds; yet in ſome places it is more, in others leſs ; as in Glouceſterſhire 15 pounds ; in Herefordſhire 12 pounds. Among horſe-courſers a ſtone is the weight of 14 pounds.</p><p>The reaſon of the name is evident. Weights at firſt were generally made of ſtone. See Deut. xxv. 13. where the word אבנ tranſlated <hi rend="italic">weight,</hi> properly ſignifies a st<hi rend="italic">one.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">STONEE-Chatter,</hi> in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Motacilla.</hi></p><p>STONEHENGE, a celebrated monument of antiquity, ſtands in the middle of a flat area near the summit of a hill six miles diſtant from Saliſhury. It is in- cloſed by a circular double bank and ditch near 30 feet broad, after croſſing which we aſcend 30 yards before we reach the work. The whole fabric conſiſted of two circles and two ovals.@@ The outer circle is about 108 feet diameter, conſiſting when entire of 60 ſtones, 30 uprights and 30 impoſts, of which remain only 24 uprights, 17 ſtanding and 7 down, 3½ feet aſunder, and 8 impoſts. Eleven uprights have their 5 impoſts on them by the grand entrance. Theſe ſtones are from 13 to 20 feet high. The leſſer circle is somewhat more than 8 feet from the inſide of the outer one, and conſiſted of 40 leſſer ſtones (the higheſt 6 feet), of which only 19 remain, and only 11 ſtanding : the walk between theſe two circles is 300 ſeet in circumference. The Adytum or Cell is an oval formed of 10 ſtones (from 16 to 22 ſeet high), in pairs, with impoſts, which Dr Stukeley calls <hi rend="italic">trilithons,</hi> and above 30 feet high, rising in height as they go round, and each pair ſeparate, and not connected as the outer pair ; the higheſt 8 feet. Within theſe are 19 more ſmaller ſingle ſtones, of which only 6 are ſtanding. At the upper end of the Adytum is the altar, a large ſlab of blue coarſe marble, 20 inches thick, 16 feet long, and 4 broad; preſſed down by the weight of the vaſt ſtones that have fallen upon it. The whole number of ſtones, uprights, impoſts, and altar, is exactly 140. The ſtones are far from being artificial, but were moſt probably brought from thoſe called the <hi rend="italic">Grey Weathers</hi> on Marlborough Downs, 15 or 16 miles off ; and if tried with a tool they appear of the ſame hardneſs, grain, and colour, generally reddiſh. The heads of oxen, deer, and other beaſts, have been found on digging in and about Stonehenge ; and human bones in the circumjacent barrows. There are three entrances from the plain to this ſtructure, the moſt conſiderable of which is from the north-eaſt, and at each of them were raiſed on the outſide of the trench two huge ſtones with two ſmaller within parallel to them.</p><p>It has been long a diſpute among the learned, by what nation, and for what purpoſe, theſe enormous ſtones were collected and arranged. The firſt account of this ſtructure we meet with is in Geoffroy of Monmouth, who, in the reign of King Stephen, wrote the hiſtory of the Britons in Latin. He tells us, that it was erected by the counſel of Merlin the Britiſh enchanter, at the command of Aurelius Ambroſius the laſt Britiſh king, in memory of 460 Britons who were murdered by Hengiſt the Saxon. The next account is that of Polydore Virgil, who ſays that the Britons erected this as a ſepulchral monument of Aurelius Ambroſius. Others ſuppoſe it to have been a ſepulchral monument of Boadicea the famous Britiſh Queen. Inigo Jones is of opinion, that it was a Roman temple ; from a ſtone 16 feet long, and ſour broad, placed in an exact poſition to the eaſtward, altar-faſhion. Mr Charlton attributed it to the Danes, who were two years maſters of Wiltſhire ; a tin tablet, on which were ſome unknown characters, ſuppoſed to be Punic, was digged up near it in the reign of Henry VIII. but is loſt ; probably that might have given ſome information reſpecting its founders. Its common name, <hi rend="italic">Stonehenge, </hi>is Saxon, and ſignifies a “ ſtone gallows,” to which thoſe ſtones, having tranſverſe impoſts, bear ſome reſemblance. It is also called in Welch <hi rend="italic">choir gour,</hi> or “ the giants dance.”</p><p>Mr Groſe thinks that Dr Stukeley has completely proved this ſtructure to have been a Britiſh temple in which the Druids officiated. He ſuppoſes it to have been the metropolitan temple of Great Britain, and tranſlates the words <hi rend="italic">choir gour</hi> “ the great choir or temple.” @@The learned Mr Bryant is of opinion that it was erected by a colony of Cuthites probably before the time of the Druids; becauſe it was uſual with them to place one vaſt ſtone upon another for a religious memorial; and theſe they often placed ſo equably, that even a breath of wind would ſometimes make them vibrate. Of ſuch ſtones one remains at this day in the pile of Stonehenge. The ancients diſtinguiſhed ſtones erected with a religious view, by the name of <hi rend="italic">amber ;</hi> by which was ſignified any thing solar and divine. The Grecians called them ωετραι αμϐροιαι	<hi rend="italic">petrae ambrosiae.</hi> Stonehenge,  ac-</p><p>@@@[mu] Gough's Edition of Cambden's Britannica, vol. i. p. 107.</p><p>@@@[mu] Grose's Antiquities, vol. iv. p. 40.</p></body></text></TEI>