<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:22:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>or continue to flow during the whole year ; others flow only during the rainy ſeaſon ; ſome ebb and flow. At Torbay there is one of this kind, which ebbs and flows five or six inches every hour. There is another near Coriſo in Italy, which ebbed and flowed three times a- day in the time of Pliny, and continues to do ſtill. A ſpring near Henly ſometimes flows for two years together, and then dries up for an equal period. The cauſe of this is explained under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Hydrostatics,</hi> n⁰ 26. For the ingredients found in ſprings, see <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Mineral</hi><hi rend="italic"> Waters, and</hi> W<hi rend="smallcaps">ater.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Spring,</hi> in mechanics, denotes a thin piece of tempered ſteel, or other elaſtic ſubſtance, which being wound up ſerves to put machines in motion by its elasticity, or endeavours to unbend itſelf ; ſuch is the ſpring of a watch, clock, or the like.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Spring, Ver,</hi> in coſmography, denotes one of the seaſons of the year ; commencing, in the northern parts of the world, on the day the ſun enters the firſt degree of Aries, which is about the 10th day of March, and ending when the ſun leaves Gemini ; or, more ſtrictly and generally, the ſpring begins on the day when the diſtance of the ſun’s meridian altitude from the zenith, being on the increaſe,is at a medium between the greateſt and leaſt. The end of the ſpring coincides with the beginning of ſummer. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Summer.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SPRING-Tide.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy-Index,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Tide.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Burning </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Springs.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">BURNING-Springs. </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Springer,</hi> or SPRI<hi rend="italic">NG-Bok,</hi> in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Capra.</hi></p><p>SPRIT, a ſmall boom or pole which crosſes the sail of a boat diagonally, from the mast to the upper hindmoſt corner of the ſail, which it is uſed to extend and elevate ; the lower end of the ſprit reſts in a fort of wreath or collar called the s<hi rend="italic">mοtter,</hi> which encircles the mast in that place.</p><p>SPRITSAIL. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sail</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Ship.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SPIRITSAIL-Topſail.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sail</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Ship. SPRUCE-tree.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Pinus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SPRUCE-Beer,</hi> a cheap and wholeſome liquor, which is thus made : Take of water 16 gallons, and boil the half of it. Put the water thus boiled, while in full heat, to the reſerved cold part, which ſhould be previouſly put into a barrel or other vessel ; then add 16 pounds of treacle or molasſes, with a few table ſpoonfuls of the eſsence of ſpruce, ſtirring the whole well together ; add half a pint of yeaſt, and keep it in a temperate situation, with the bung hole open, for two days, till the fermentation be abated. Then cloſe it up or bottle it off, and it will be fit for being drunk in a few days afterwards. In North America, and perhaps in other countries, where the black and white ſpruce-firs abound, inſtead of adding the es<hi rend="italic">ſence</hi> of the ſpruce at the ſame time with the molaſtes, they make a decoction of the leaves and ſmall branches of theſe trees, and find the liquor equally good. It is a powerful anti- ſporbutic, and may prove very uſeful in long ſea voyages.</p><p>SPUNGE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sponge.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Spongia.</hi></p><p>SPUNGING, in gunnery, the cleaning of the inside of a gun with a ſpunge, in order to prevent any ſparks of fire from remaining in it, which would endanger the life of him that ſhould load it again.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SPUN-yarn,</hi> among sailors, is a kind of line made from rope yarn, and uſed for ſeizing or faſtening things together.</p><p>SPUNK, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Boletus.</hi></p><p>SPUR, a piece of metal consiſting of two branches encompaſſing a horſeman’s heel, and a rowel in form of a ſtar, advancing out behind to prick the horſe.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SPUR-Winged Water Hen.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Parra.</hi></p><p>SPURGE, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Euphorbia. </hi><hi rend="italic">SPURGE-Laurel.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Daphne.</hi></p><p>SPURREY, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Spergula.</hi></p><p>SPY, a perſon hired to watch the actions, motions, &amp;c. of another ; particularly what paſſes in a camp. When a ſpy is discovered, he is hanged immediately.</p><p>SQUADRON, in military affairs, denotes a body of horſe whoſe number of men is not fixed ; but is uſually from 100 to 200.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Squadron</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Ships,</hi> either implies a detachment of ſhips employed on any particular expedition, or the third part of a naval armament.</p><p>SQUADS, in a military ſenſe, are certain diviſions of a company into ſo many ſquads, generally into three or four. The uſe of forming companies into as many ſquads of inſpection as it has ſerjeants and corporals, is proved by thoſe regiments who have practiſed that method ; as by it the irregularity of the ſoldiers is considerably reſtrained, their dress improved, and the diſcipline of the regiment in general moſt remarkably forwarded. Every officer ſhould have a roll of his company by ſquads.</p><p>SQUALL, a ſudden and violent blaſt of wind, uſually occasioned by the interruption and reverberation of the wind from high mountains. Theſe are very frequent in the Mediterranean, particularly that part of it which is known by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Levant,</hi> as produced by the repulſion and new direction which the wind meets within its paſſage between the various islands of the Archipelago.</p><p>SQUALUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Shark,</hi> in ichthyology ; a genus arranged by Linnæus under the claſs of <hi rend="italic">amphibia,</hi> and the order oſ <hi rend="italic">nantes,</hi> but by Gmelin referred to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pisces,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">chondropterygii.</hi> The head is obtuſe ; on the sides of the neck there are from 4 to 7 ſemilunar ſpiracles. The eyes are oblong, vertical, half covered, and before the <hi rend="italic">foramen temporale.</hi> The mouth is situated in the anterior and lower part of the head, and is armed with ſeveral rows of teeth, which are ſerrated, acute, partly moveable and partly fixed, and unequal in form. The body is oblong, tapering and rough, with very tender prickles. The ventral fins are much leſs than the pectoral, and are ſituated round the anus and genitals. There are 3 2 ſpecies ; the iſabella canicula or greater dog fiſh ; catulus or ſmaller dog-fiſh ; ſtellaris; galeus or tope ; muſtelus or ſmooth hound ; cirratus ; barbatus or barbu ; tigrinus or tigre ; Africanus or galonné ; ocellatus or oeillé ; zygæna or balance-fiſh ; tiburo or pantouflier of Broussonet ; griſeus or griſet ; vulpes or ſea-fox ; longicaudus ; glaucus or blue ſhark ; cornubius, porbeagle, or beaumaris-ſhark ; cinereus or perlon ; maximus ; carcharias or white ſhark ; priſtis or ſcie ; ſpinoſus or bouele ; acanthias or picked dog fiſh ſernandinus ; ſpinax or sagre ; ſquamoſus or ecailleux ; centrina or humantin ; indicus ; Americanus or liche; ſquatina or angel fiſh ; maſſaſa; and kumal. The following are the most remarkable :</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">iſabella</hi> has a wrinkly ſpotted ſkin, and the anterior dorſal fin is perpendicular to the abdominal fins. The body is ſomewhat flat ; the head ſhort, large, and</p></body></text></TEI>