<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-04-20T21:21:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>which was printed at Hamburg in the year 1670, and the latter we know not where, in
                1677, a few months after his death. In the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus
                    Theologico-politicus, </hi>already mentioned, he treats of <hi rend="italic"
                    >prophecy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">prophets ; </hi>and of the <hi
                    rend="italic">call of the Hebrews,</hi> whom he affirms to have been
                diſtinguiſhed from other nations only by the admirable form of their government, and
                the fitneſs of their laws for long preserving their political state. He is likewiſe
                of opinion, or at leaſt pretends to be ſo, that God may, in what we call a <hi
                    rend="italic">ſupernatural way,</hi> have given political inſtitutes to other
                nations as well as to the Hebrews, who were, he ſays, at no time a peculiar people
                to the Supreme Lord of heaven and earth ; for, according to him, all hiſtory, ſacred
                and profane, teſtifies that every nation was bleſſed with the light of prophecy.
                That light indeed, if his notions of it be just, was of very little value. He
                labours to prove, that the prophets were diſtinguiſhed from other men only by their
                piety and virtue ; that their revelations depended wholly on their imaginations and
                the diſpositions of their minds ; that they were often groſsly ignorant and highly
                prejudiced ; that the ſpeculative opinions of one prophet are ſeldom in uniſon with
                thoſe of another ; and that their writings are valuable to us only for the excellent
                rules which he acknowledges they contain reſpecting the practice of piety and
                virtue. He then proceeds to treat of the divine law and of miracles ; and endeavours
                to prove that no miracle, in the proper ſenſe of the word, can have been at any time
                performed ; becauſe every thing happens by a neceſſity of nature, the reſult of the
                divine decrees, which are from all eternity neceſſary themſelves. He acknowledges,
                that in the Scriptures, which he professes to admit as true hiſtory, miracles are
                often mentioned ; but he ſays that they were only Angular events which the ſacred
                hiſtorrans <hi rend="italic">imagined</hi> to be miraculous: and he then gives ſome
                very extraordinary rules for interpreting the books of the Old and New Teſtaments
                where they treat of miracles, or appear to foretel future events. See our articles
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Miracle</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Prophecy.</hi></p>
            <p>Having thus diveſted the Scriptures of every thing characteriſtic of a revelation
                from heaven, he next calls in queſtion their authenticity. He affirms, in
                contradiction to the cleareſt internal evidence, that the Pentateuch and all the
                other hiſtorical books muſt have been written by one man ; and that man, he thinks,
                could not have flourished at a period earlier than that of Ezra. The grounds of this
                opinion are unworthy of the talents of Spinoza; for that he had talents is
                incontrovertible. His principal objection to the authenticity of the Pentateuch is,
                that Moſes is made to ſpeak of himſelf in the third perſon, and to talk of the
                Canaanites being then in the land ; and becauſe he finds in his writings, as well as
                in the books of Joſhua, Judges, Ruth, Samuel, &amp;c. places deſigned by names which
                he suppoſes they had not in the early ages of which theſe books contain the hiſtory,
                he concludes that theſe writings muſt be one compilation from ancient records made
                at a very late period ; more eſpecially as the author often ſpeaks of things of
                great antiquity remaining to this day. The books of Eſther, Ezra, Nehemiah, and
                Chronicles, muſt have been compiled, he thinks, under the Maccabees ; and he ſeems
                to conſider as of equal value with them the ſtory of Tobit, and the other two
                apocryphal treatiſes intitled the Wiſdom of Solomon and Eccleſiaſticus.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſenſeleſs cavils, worthy only of one of thoſe modern freethinkers whoſe
                learning, in the opinion of Biſhop Warburton, is not ſufficient to carry them even
                to the confines of rational doubt, we have ſufficiently obviated in another place
                (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Scripture,</hi> n⁰ 8—31 ) Spinoza urges them against the
                other books of the Old Teſtament. The prophecies of Iſaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel,
                Daniel, Hoſea, and Jonah, are, as we have them, only fragments, he ſays, of the
                writings of thoſe men compiled by the Phariſees under the second temple from ancient
                and voluminous records.</p>
            <p>In the midſt of this dogmatical ſcepticiſm, if we may uſe ſuch a phraſe, he bears
                ſuch a teſtimony to the laſt chapters of the book of Daniel, as we ſhould not have
                looked for in the writings either of a Jew or of a Deiſt, After detailing the
                various hypotheſes which in his time were held reſpecting the author and the
                intention of the book of <hi rend="italic">Job ;</hi> in which, he ſays, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Momus</hi> is called <hi rend="smallcaps">Satan,</hi> he
                proceeds in theſe words : “ Tranſeo ad Danielis librum ; his fine dubio ex cap. 8.
                ipſius Danſelis ſcripta continet. Undenam autem priora ſeptem capita deſcripta
                fuerint, neſcio@@*;” thus admitting the famous prophecy of the ſeventy weeks. The
                canon of the Old Teſtament, he ſays, was finally ſettled by rabbins of the
                Phariſaical ſect, who wiſhed to exclude from it the books of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proverbs, Ecelesiastes,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Eseekiel,</hi> as they had
                actually excluded others of equal value ; but the three books in queſtion were
                inſerted by the influence of two of the rabbis of greater wiſdom and integrity than
                the rest.</p>
            <p>That ſo paradoxical a writer, who had been originally a Jew, and was now almoſt a
                Deiſt, ſhould have treated the New Teſtament with as little ceremony as the Old,
                will not ſurpriſe the intelligent reader. He begins his remarks, however, with
                affirming, that no man can peruſe the Chriſtian Scriptures, and not acknowlcdge the
                apoſtles to have been prophets ; but he thinks that their mode of propheſying was
                altogether different from that which prevailed under the Moſaic dispenſation ; and
                that the gift, whatever it was, forſook them the inſtant that they left off <hi
                    rend="italic">preaching,</hi> as their <hi rend="italic">writings</hi> have to
                him every appearance of human compoſitions. This diſtinction between Chriſtian and
                Jewiſh prophecy is the more wonderful, that he founds it principally on the
                diſſimilarity of sty<hi rend="italic">le</hi> viſible in the writings of the Old and
                New Teſtaments ; though, in his second chapter, which treats of the works of the
                Jewiſh prophets, he ſays expressly, “ Stylus deinde prophetiæ pro eloquentia
                cujuſque prophetæ variabat, prophetiae enim Ezekielis et Amosis non sunt, ut illæ
                Esaiæ, Nachumi eleganti, sed rudiore stylo scriptæ.” That the Hebrew ſcholar may be
                convinced of the truth of this remark, he recommends to him to ſtudy diligently the
                writings of theſe prophets, and to conſider the occaſions on which their prophecies
                were uttered : “ Quæ ſi omnia recte perpendentur (ſays he) facile oſtendant, Deum
                nullum habere ſtylum peculiarem dicendi, ſed tantum pro eruditione, et capacitate
                prephetæ eatenus effe elegantem, compendioſum, ſeverum, rudem, prolixum, et
                obſcurum.” Another objection brought by Spinoza againſt the prophecies of the New
                Teſtament ariſes from the authors of them having been</p>
            <p>@@@[m] Tractatus, cap. <gap> </gap>, p. 130.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
