<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-04-20T21:25:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>courſe of this , oppoſition to the court, his licence for acting plays was revoked, and his patent rendered ineffectual, at the inſtance of the lord chamberlain. He did his utmoſt to prevent ſo great a loſs ; and finding every direct avenue of approach to his royal maſter effectually barred againſt him by his powerful adverſary, he had recourſe to the method of applying to the public, in hopes that his complaints would reach the ear of his ſovereign, though in an indirect courſe, by that canal. In this ſpirit he formed the plan of a periodical paper, to be publiſhed twice a-week, under the title of the <hi rend="italic">Theatre ;</hi> the firſt number of which came out on the 2d of January 1719-20. In the mean time, the misfortune of being out of favour at court, like other misfortunes, drew after it a train oſ more. During the courſe of this paper, in which he had aſſumed the feigned name of <hi rend="italic">Sir John Edgar,</hi> he was outrageouſly attacked by Mr Dennis, the noted critic, in a very abuſive pamphlet, intitled <hi rend="italic">The Character and Conduct of Sir John Edgar.</hi> To this inſult our author made a proper reply in the Theatre.</p><p>While he was ſtruggling with all his might to ſave himſelf from ruin, he found time to turn his pen againſt the miſcſhievous South-Sea ſcheme, which had nearly brought the nation to ruin in 1720 ; and the next year he was reſtored to his office and authority in the play- houſe in Drury-Lane. Of this it was not long before he made an additional advantage, by bringing his celebrated comedy called the <hi rend="italic">Conscious Lovers</hi> upon that ſtage, where it was acted with prodigious ſucceſs ; ſo that the receipt there muſt have been very conſiderable, beſides the profits accruing by the ſale of the copy, and a purſe of 500 l. given to him by the king, to whom he dedicated it. Yet notwithſtanding theſe ample ſupplies, about the year following, being reduced to the utmoſt extremity, he ſold his ſhare in the play-houſe ; and ſoon after commenced a law-ſuit with the managers, which in 1726 was determined to his diſadvantage. Having now again, for the laſt time, brought his fortune, by the moſt heedleſs profuſion, into a deſperate condition, he was rendered altogether incapable of retrieving the loſs, by being ſeized with a paralytic diſorder, which greatly impaired bis underſtanding. In theſe unhappy circumſtances, he retired to his teat at Languanor near Caermarthen in Wales, where he paid the laſt debt to nature on the 21 ſt of September 1729, and was privately interred, according to his own desire, in the church of Caermarthen. Among his papers were found the manuscripts of two plays, one called <hi rend="italic">The Gentlemen,</hi> founded upon the eunuch of Terence, and the other intitled <hi rend="italic">The School oſ Action, </hi>both nearly finiſhed.</p><p>Sir Richard was a man of undiſſembled and extenſive benevolence, a friend to the friendleſs, and, as far as his circumſtances would permit, the father of every orphan. His works are chaſte and manly. He was a ſtranger to the moſt diſtant appearance of envy or malevolence ; never jealous of any man’s growing reputation ; and ſo far from arrogating any praiſe to himſelf from his conjunction with Mr Addiſon, that he was the firſt who deſired him to diſtinguiſh his papers. His greateſt error was want of economy : however, he was certainly the moſt agreeable, and (it we may be allowed the expreſſion) the moſt innocent rake that ever trod the rounds of diſſipation.</p><p>STEEPLE, an appendage erected generally on the weſtern end of churches, to hold the bells. Steeples are denominated from their form, either ſpires or towers: the firſt are ſuch as aſcend continually diminiſhing either conically or pyramidally ; the latter are mere parallelo- pipeds, and are covered a-top platform-like.</p><p>STEERAGE, on board a ſhip, that part of the ſhip next below the quarter-deck, before the bulk head of the great cabin where the ſteersman ſtands, in moſt ſhips of war. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Steering.</hi></p><p>STEERING, in navigation, the art of directing the ſhip’s way by the movements of the helm ; or of applying its efforts to regulate her courſe when ſhe advances.</p><p>The perfection of ſteering conſiſts in a vigilant attention to the motion of the ſhip’s head, ſo as to check every deviation from the line of her courſe in the firſt inſtant of its motion ; and in applying as little of the power of the helm as poſſible. By this ſhe will run more uniformly in a ſtraight path, as declining leſs to the right and left ; whereas, if a greater effort of the helm is employed, it will produce a greater declination from the courſe, and not only increaſe the difficulty of ſteering, but alſo make a crooked and irregular tract through the water. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Helm.</hi> The helmſman ſhould diligently watch the movements of the head by the land, clouds, moon, or ſtars ; becauſe, although the courſe is in general regulated by the compass, yet the vibrations of the needle are rot ſo quickly perceived as the ſallies of the ſhip’s head to the right or left, which, if not immediately reſtrained, will acquire additional velocity in every inſtant of their motion, and demand a more powerful impulſe of the helm to reduce them ; the application of which will operate to turn her head as far on the contrary side of her courſe, —The phraſes uſed in ſteering a ſhip vary according to the relation of the wind to her courſe. Thus, if the wind is fair or large, the phraſes uſed by the pilot or officer who ſuperintends the ſteerage are, <hi rend="italic">port, star-board,</hi> and st<hi rend="italic">eddy.</hi> The firſt is intended to direct the ſhip’s courſe farther to the right ; the second is to guide her farther to the left ; and the laſt is deſigned to keep her exactly in the line whereon ſhe advances, according to the courſe preſcribed. The excels of the firſt and ſecond movement is called <hi rend="italic">hard-a-port,</hi> and. <hi rend="italic">hard-a-starboard;</hi> the former of which gives her the greateſt poſſible inclination to the right, and the latter an equal tendency to the left.—If, on the contrary, the wind is foul or ſcant, the phraſes are <hi rend="italic">luff, thus,</hi> and no <hi rend="italic">nearer :</hi> the firſt of which is the order to keep her cloſe to the wind ; the ſecond, to retain her in her preſent ſituation ; and the third, to keep her sails full.</p><p>In a ſhip of war, the exerciſe of ſteering the ſhip it, uſually divided amongst a number of the moſt expert ſailors, who attend tire helm in their turns ; and are accordingly called <hi rend="italic">timoneers,</hi> from the French term <hi rend="italic">timonier,</hi> which signifies “helmſman.” The ſteerage is conſtantly ſuperviſed by the quarter-matters, who alſo attend the helm by rotation. In merchant-ſhips every ſeaman takes his turn in this ſervice, being directed therein by the mate of the watch, or ſome other officer. —As the ſafety of a ſhip, and all contained therein, depends in a great meaſure on the ſteerage or effects of the helm, the apparatus by which it is managed ſhould often be diligently examined by the proper officers. In</p></body></text></TEI>