<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0245.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0239-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SWIFT</label>
(Dr Jonathan), ſo univerſally admired as a wit and claſſical writer of the Engliſh language, was born in Dublin on November 30th 1667. His father was an attorney, and of a good family ; but dying poor, the expence of his ſon’s education was defrayed by his friends. At the age of six young Swift was ſent to the ſchool of Kilkenny,</p><p>whence he was removed in his 15th year to Trinity College, Dublin.</p><p>In his academical ſtudies (ſays Dr Johnſon) he was either not diligent or not happy. The truth appears to be, that he deſpiſed them as intricate and uſeleſs. He told Mr Sheridan, his laſt biographer, that he had made many efforts, upon his entering the college, to read ſome of the old treatiſes on logic writ by Smegleſius, Keckermannus, Burgerſdicitis, &amp;c. and that he never had patience to go thro’ three pages of any of them, he was ſo diſguſted at the ſtupidity of the work. When he was urged by his tutor to make himſelf matter oſ this branch, then in high eſtimation, and held eſſentially neceſſary to the taking of a degree, Swift aſked him, What it was he was to learn from thoſe books ? His tutor told him, The art of reaſoning. Swift ſaid, That he found no want of any ſuch art ; that he could reaſon very well without it ; and that, as far as he could obſerve, they who had made the greateſt proficiency in logic had, inſtead of the art of reaſoning, acquired the art of wrangling ; and inſtead of clearing up obſcurities, had learned how to perplex matters that were clear enough before. For his own part, he was contented with that portion of reaſon which God had given him; and he would leave it to time and experience to ſtrengthen and direct it properly ; nor would he run the riſk of having it warped or falſely biaſſed by any ſystem of rules laid down by ſuch ſtupid writers, of the bad effects of which he had but too many examples before his eyes in thoſe reckoned the moſt acute logicians. Accordingly, he made a firm reſolution, that he never would read any of thoſe books ; which he ſo pertinaciouſly adhered to, that though his degree was refuſed him the first time of fitting for it, on account of his not anſwering in that branch, he went into the hall a ſecond time as ill prepared as before; and would alſo have been stopped a ſecond time, on the ſame account, if the intereſt of his friends, who well knew the inflexibility of his temper, had not ſtepped in, and obtained it for him ; though in a manner little to his credit, as it was inſerted in the College Registry, that he obtained it <hi rend="italic">ſpeciali gratia,</hi> “ by ſpecial favour;” where it remains upon record.</p><p>He remained in the college near three years after this, not through choice, but neceſſity, little known or regarded. By ſcholars he was reckoned a blockhead ; and as the lowneſs of his circumſtances would not permit him to keep company with persons of an equal rank with himſelf, upon an equal footing, he ſcorned to take up with thoſe of a lowe claſs, or to be obliged to those of a higher. He lived therefore much alone, and his time was employed in purſuing his courſe of reading in hiſtory and poetry, then very unfaſhionable ſtudies for an academic ; or in gloomy meditations on his unhappy circumstances. Yet, under this heavy preſſure, the force of his genius broke out, in the first rude draught of the Tale of a Tub, written by him at the age of 19, though communicated to nobody but his chamber fellow Mr Waryng ; who, after the publication of the book, made no ſcruple to declare, that he had read the first ſketch of it in Swift’s handwriting when he was of that age.”</p><p>In 1688, being, by the death of Godwin Swift his uncle, who had chiefly ſupported him, left without subſiſtence, he went to conſult his mother, who then lived at Leiceſter, about the future courſe of his life; and, by her direction, ſolicited the advice and patronage of Sir William Temple, whoſe father had lived in great friendship with Godwin Swift. Temple received him with great kindneſs, and was ſo much pleased with his converſation, that he detained him two years in his houſe, and recommended him to king William, who offered to make him a captain of horſe. This not ſuiting his disposition, and Temple not having it quickly<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0246.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0240"/>
in his power to provide for him otherwiſe, Swift left his patron (1694) in discontent ; having previouſly taken his maſter’s degree at Oxford, by means of a testimonial from Dublin, in which the words of diſgrace were omitted. He was resolved to enter into the church, where his firſt preferment was only L.100 a-year, being the prebend of <hi rend="italic">Kilroot</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Conner</hi>; which ſome time afterwards, upon Sir William Temple’s earneſtly inviting him back to his houſe at Moorpark, he resigned in favour of a clergyman far advanced in years and burdened with a numerous family. For this man he solicited the prebend, to which he himſelf inducted him.</p><p>In 1699 Swift lost his patron Sir William Temple, who left him a legacy in money, with the property of his manuscripts ; and, on his death-bed, obtained for him a promiſe from the king of the firſt prebend that ſhould become vacant at Weſtminſter or Canterbury. That this promiſe might not be forgotten, Swift dedicated to the king the poſthumous works with which he was entruſted, and for a while attended the court ; but ſoon found his felicitations hopeless. He was then invited by the earl of Berkeley to accompany him into Ireland, where, after ſuffering some cruel diſappointments, he obtained the livings of Laracor and Rath- beggin in the dioceſe of Meath ; and ſoon afterwards invited over the unfortunate Stella, a young woman of the name of Johnſon, whoſe life he contrived to embitter, and whole days, though he certainly loved her, we may confidently affirm that he ſhortened by his caprice.</p><p>This lady is generally believed to have been the daughter of Sir William Temple’s ſteward ; but her niece, a Mrs Hearn, aſſured Mr Berkeley, the editor of a volume of letters intitled <hi rend="italic">Literary Relics,</hi> that her father was a merchant, and the youngeſt brother of a good family in Nottinghamſhire ; that her mother was the intimate friend of lady Gifford, Sir William’s ſiſter ; and that see herſelf was educated in the family with his niece, the late Mrs Temple of Moorpark by Farnham<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* See Inquiry into the Life of the Dean Swift, prefixed to Literary Relics, printed in 1789, for Elliot and Kay.</p></note> *. This ſtory would be intitled to the fulleſt credit, had not Mrs Hearn affirmed, in the ſame letter, that, before the death of Sir William Temple, Mrs Johnſon’s little fortune had been greatly injured by the South- Sea bubbles, which are known to have injured no person till the year 1720: (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Company,</hi> II. 1.) When one part of a narrative is ſo palpably falſe, the remainder will always be received with heſitation. But whether Miss Johnſon was the daughter of Temple’s steward or of the friend of lady Gifford, it is certain that Sir William left her L. 1000 ; and that, accompanied by Mrs Dingley, whoſe whole fortune amounted to an annuity of L.27 for life, ſhe went, in conſequence of Swift’s invitation, to Laracor. With theſe two ladies he paſſed his hours of relaxation, and to them he opened his bosom ; but they never reſided in the ſame houſe, nor did he ſee either without a witneſs.</p><p>In 1701 Swift publiſhed <hi rend="italic">A discοurse of the contests and dissensions in Athens and Rome.</hi> It was his firſt work, and indeed the only which he ever expreſsly acknowledged. According to his conſtant practice he had concealed his name ; but after its appearance, paying a viſit to some Iriſh biſhop, he was aſked by him if he had read that pamphlet, and what its reputation was in London. Upon his replying that he believed it was very well liked in London ; “ Very well liked!” ſaid the biſhop with some emotion. “ Yes, Sir, it is one of the fineſt tracts that ever was written, and biſhop Burnet is one of the beſt writers in the world.” Swift, who always hated Burnet with something more than political rancour, immediately queſtioned his right to the work, when he was told by the biſhop that he was “a young man ;” and ſtill perſiſting to doubt of the juſtice of Burners claim, on account of the dissimilarity of the ſtyle of the pamphlet from that of his other works, he was told that he was “a very positive young man,” as no perſon in England but biſhop Burnet was capable of writing it. Upon which Swift replied, with some indignation, I am to aſſure your lord ship, however, that biſhop Burnet did <hi rend="italic">not</hi> write the pamphlet, for I wrote it myſelf. And thus was he forced in the heat of argument to avow what otherwiſe he would have for ever concealed.</p><p>Early in the ensuing ſpring king William died ; and Swift, on his next viſit to London, found queen Anne upon the throne. It was generally thought, upon this event, that the Tory party would have had the aſcendant ; but, contrary to all expectation, the Whigs had managed matters ſo well as to get entirely into the queen’s confidence, and to have the whole adminiſtration of affairs in their hands. Swift’s friends were now in power; and the Whigs in general, knowing him to be the author of the Diſcourſe on the Conteſts, &amp;c. which was written in defence of king William and his miniſters againſt the violent proceedings of the houſe of commons, conſidered themſelves as much obliged to him, and looked upon him as faſt to their party. But Swift thought with the Whigs only in the ſtate ; for with reſpect to the church his principles were always thoſe of a Tory. He therefore declined any intimate connection with the leaders of the party, who at that time professed what was called <hi rend="italic">low church principles.</hi> But what above all ſhocked him, says Mr Sheridan, was their inviting Deists, Freethinkers, Atheiſts, Jews, and Infidels, to be of their party, under pretence of moderation, and allowing a general liberty of conſcience. As Swift was in his heart a man of true religion, he could not have borne, even in his private character, to have mixed with ſuch a motely crew. But when we conſider his principles in his political capacity, that he looked upon the church of England, as by law eſtabliſhed, to be the main pillar of our newly erected conſtitution, he could not, confidently with the character of a good citizen, join with thoſe who conſidered it more as an ornament than a ſupport to the edifice ; and could therefore look on with compoſure while it was undermining, or could even open the gate to a blind multitude, to try, like Sampson, their ſtrength againſt it, and conſider it only as ſport. With ſuch a party, neither his religious nor political principles would ſuffer him to join ; and with regard to the Tories, as is uſual in the violence of factions, they had run into oppoſite extremes, equally dangerous to the ſtate. He was therefore during the earlier part of the queen’s reign of no party, but employed himſelf in diſcharging the duties of his function, and in publiſhing from time to time ſuch tracts as he thought might be uſeſul. In the year 1704 he publiſhed the <hi rend="italic">Tale of a Tub,</hi> which, conſidered merely as a work of genius, is unqueſtionably the greateſt which he ever produced ; but the levity with which religion was thought to be there treated, raised up enemies to him among all parties, and eventually precluded him from a biſhopric. From that period till the year 1708, he ſeems to have employed himſelf in ſolitary ſtudy ; but he then gave ſucceſſively to the public <hi rend="italic">The Sentiments of a Church of England man,</hi> the ridicule of aſtrology under the name of <hi rend="italic">Bickerstaff,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Argument against abolishing Christianity,</hi> and the defence of the <hi rend="italic">Sacramental Test.</hi></p><p>Soon after began the buſy and important part of Swift’s life. He was employed (1710) by the primate of Ireland to solicit the queen for a remiſſion of the firſt fruits and twentieth parts to the Iriſh clergy. This introduced him to Mr Harley, afterwards earl of Oxford, who, though a Whig himſelf, was at the head of the Tory miniſtry, and in great need of an auxiliary ſo able as Swift, by whoſe pen he and the other miniſters might be ſupported in pamphlets,<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0247.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0241"/>
poems, and periodical papers. In the year 1710 was commenced the <hi rend="italic">Examiner;</hi> of which Swift wrote 33 papers, beginning his firſt part of it on the 10th of November 1711. The next year he publiſhed <hi rend="italic">the Conduct of the Allies</hi> ten days before the parliament aſſembled ; and ſoon afterwards, <hi rend="italic">Reflections on the barrier Treaty.</hi> The purpoſe of theſe pamphlets was to perſuade the nation to a peace, by ſhowing that " mines had been exhauſted and millions deſtroyed” to ſecure the Dutch and aggrandize the emperor, without any advantage whatever to Great Britain. Though theſe two publications, together with his <hi rend="italic">Remarks on the Biſhop of Sarum's Introduction to the third Volume of his History of the Reformation,</hi> certainly turned the tide of popular opinion, and effectually promoted the deſigns of the miniſtry, the beſt preferment which his friends could venture to give him was the deanery of St Patrick’s, which he accepted in 1713. In the midſt of his power and his politics he kept a journal of his viſits, his walks, his interviews with miniſters, and quarrels with his servant, and tranſmitted it to Mrs Johnſon and Mrs Dingley, to whom he knew that whatever befel him was intereſting ; but in 1714 an end was put to his power by the death of the queen, which broke down at once the whole ſyſtem of Tory politics, and nothing remained for him but to withdraw from perſecution to his deanery.</p><p>In the triumph of the Whigs, Swift met with every mortification that a ſpirit like his could poſſibly be expoſed to. The people of Ireland were irritated againſt him beyond meaſure ; and every indignity was offered him as he walked the ſtreets of Dublin. Nor was he only inſulted by the rabble, but perſons of diſtiguiſhed rank and character forgot the decorum of common civility to give him a perſonal affront. While his pride was hurt by ſuch indignities, his more tender feelings were alſo often wounded by Safe ingratitude. In ſuch a ſituation he found it in vain to ſtruggle againſt the tide that oppoſed him. He ſilently yielded to it, and retired from the world to diſcharge his duties as a clergyman, and attend to the care of his deanery. That no part of his time might lie heavy on his hands, he employed his leiſure hours on ſome hiſtorical attempts relating to the change of the miniſters and the conduct of the miniſtry ; and completed the hiſtory of the four laſt years of the queen, which had been begun in her lifetime, but which he never publiſhed. Of the work which bears that title, and is ſaid to be his, Dr Johnſon doubts the genuineneſs ; and it certainly is not ſuch as we ſhould have expected from a man of Swift’s fagacity and opportunities of information.</p><p>In the year 1716 he was privately married to Mrs Johnson by Dr Aſhe biſhop of Clogher ; but the marriage made no change in their ſituation, and it would be difficult to prove (says Lord Orrery) that they were ever afterwards together but in the preſence of a third perſon. The dean of St Patrick’s lived in a private manner, known and regarded only by his friends, till about the year 1720 that he publiſhed his firſt political pamphlet relative to Ireland, intitled <hi rend="italic">A Propoſal for the Universal Uſe of Iriſh Manufactures ;</hi> which ſo rouſed the indignation of the miniſtry that they commenced a proſecution againſt the printer, which drew the attention of the public to the pamphlet, and at once made its author popular.</p><p>Whilſt he was enjoying the laurels which this work had wreathed for him, his felicity, as well as that of his wife, was interrupted by the death of Mrs Van Homrigh, and the publication of his poem called <hi rend="italic">Cadenus and Vanessa,</hi> which brought upon him much merited obloquy. With Mrs Van Homrigh he became acquainted in London during his attendance at court ; and finding her possessed of genius and fond of literature, he took delight in directing her ſtudies, till he got inſensibly poſſeſſion of her heart. From being proud of his praiſe, ſhe grew fond of his perſon ; and deſpising vulgar reſtraints, ſhe made him ſensible that ſhe was ready to receive him as a husband. She had wit, youth, beauty, and a competent fortune to recommend her ; and for a while Swift ſeems to have been undetermined whether or not he ſhould comply with her wiſh. She had followed him to Ireland, where ſhe lived in a houſe about twelve miles diſtant from Dublin ; and he continued to visit her occasionally, and to direct her ſtudies as he had done in London ; but with theſe attentions ſhe was not ſatisfied, and at laſt ſent to him a letter written with great ardour and tenderness, inſiſting that he ſhould immediately accept or refuſe her as a wife. His anſwer, which probably contained the ſecret of his marriage, he carried himſelf ; and having indignantly thrown it on the lady’s table, inſtantly quitted the houſe, we believe without ſpeaking to her, and returned to Dublin to reflect on the conſequences of his own conduct. Theſe were dreadful. Mrs Van Homrigh ſurvived her diſappointment but a few weeks ; during which time ſhe cancelled a will that ſhe had made in his favour, and ordered the poem to be publiſhed in which Cadenus had proclaimed her excellence and confeſſed his love.</p><p>His patriotiſm again burſt forth in 1724 to obſtruct the currency of Wood’s halfpence ; and his zeal was crowned with ſucceſs. Wood had obtained a patent to coin 180,000 l. in halfpence and farthings for the kingdom of Ireland ; and was about to turn his braſs into gold, when Swift, finding that the metal was debaſed to an enormous degree, wrote letters under the name of <hi rend="italic">Μ. B. Drapier</hi> to ſhow the folly of giving gold and ſilver for coin not worth a third part of its nominal value. A proſecution was carried on againſt the printer; and lord Carteret, then lord lieutenant, iſſued a proclamation, offering L.300 for diſcovering the author of the fourth letter. The day after it was publiſhed there was a full levee at the caſtle. The lord-lieutenant was going round the circle, when Swift abruptly entered the chamber, and puſhing his way through the crowd, never stopped till he got within the circle; where, with marks of the higheſt indignation in his countenance, he addreſſed the lord-lieutenant with the voice of a Stentor, that re-echoed through the room, “ So, my lord lieutenant, this is a glorious exploit that you performed yeſterday, in iſſuing a proclamation againſt a poor ſhop-keeper, whoſe only crime is an honeſt endeavour to ſave his country from ruin. You have given a noble ſpecimen of what this devoted nation is to hope for from your government. I ſuppoſe you expect a ſtatue of copper will be erected to you for this ſervice done to Wood.” He then went on for a long time, inveighing in the bittereſt terms againſt the patent, and diſplaying in the ſtrongeſt colours all the fatal conſequences of introducing that execrable coin. The whole aſſembly were ſtruck mute with wonder at this unprecedented ſcene. For ſome time a profound ſilence enſued. When lord Carteret, who had liſtened with great compoſure to the whole speech, made this fine reply, in a line of Virgil’s :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Res dura,</hi> &amp; <hi rend="italic">regni novitas me talia cogunt Moliri.</hi></p><p>From this time Swift was known by the name of <hi rend="italic">the Dean, a</hi> nd was known by the populace as the champion, patron, and inſtructor of Ireland.</p><p>In 1727 he returned to England; where, in conjunction with Pope, he collected three volumes of miscellanies ; and the ſame year he ſent into the world his <hi rend="italic">Gulliver's Travels,</hi> a production which was read by the high and the low, and filled every reader with a mingled emotion of merriment and amazement. Whilſt he was enjoying the reputation of this work, he was ſuddenly called to a home oſ ſorrow. Poor Stella was sinking into the grave ; and after a languiſhing<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0248.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0242"/>
<hi rend="italic">decay</hi> of about two months, died in her 44th year, on January 28. 1728. How much he wiſhed her life is ſhown by his papers ; nor can it be doubted that he dreaded the death of her whom he loved moſt, aggravated by the consciouſness that himſelf had haſtened it. With her vaniſhed all his domeſtic enjoyments, and of courſe he turned his thoughts more to public affairs ; in the contemplation of which he could ſee nothing but what ſerved to increaſe the malady. The advances of old age, with all its attendant infirmities ; the death of almoſt all his old friends ; the frequent returns of his moſt diſpiriting maladies, deafneſs and giddineſs ; and, above all, the dreadful apprehenſions that he ſhould outlive his underſtanding, made life ſuch a burden to him, that he had no hope left but a ſpeedy diſſolution, which was the object of his daily prayer to the Almighty.</p><p>The ſeverity of his temper increaſing, he drove his acquaintance from his table, and wondered why he was deſerted. In 1732, he complains, in a letter to Mr Gay, that " he had a large houſe, and ſhould hardly find one viſitor if he was not able to hire him with a bottle of wine :” and, in another to Mr Pope, “ that he was in danger of dying poor and friendleſs, even his female friends having forſaken him ; which,” as he lays, “ vexed him moſt.” Theſe complaints were afterwards repeated in a ſtrain of yet greater senſibility : “ All my friends have forſaken me.</p><p><hi rend="italic">“ Vertiginoſus, inops, ſurdus, male gratus amicis.</hi></p><p>“Deaf, giddy, helpleſs, left alone,</p><p>“ To all my friends a burden grown.”</p><p>The fits of giddineſs and deafneſs to which he had been Subjected from his boyiſh years, and for which he thought walking or riding the beſt remedy, became more frequent and violent as he grew old ; and the preſentiment which he had long entertained of that wretchedneſs which would inevitably overtake him towards the cloſe of life, clouded his mind with melancholy and tinged every object around him. How miſerable he was rendered by that gloomy proſpect, we may learn from the following remarkable anecdote mentioned by Mr Faulkner in his letter to lord Cheſterfield.</p><p>One time, in a journey from Droqheda to Navan, the dean rode before the company, made a ſudden ſtop, diſmounted his horſe, fell on his knees, lifted up his hands, and prayed in the moſt devout manner. When his friends came up, he deſired and infiſted on their alighting ; which they did, and aſked him the meaning. “ Gentlemen,” ſaid he, “ pray join your hearts in servent prayers with mine, that I may never be like this oak-tree, which is decayed and withered at top, while the other parts are found.” In 1736, while he was writing a ſatire called the <hi rend="italic">Legion Club</hi> againſt the Iriſh parliament, he was ſeized with so dreadful a fit of his malady, that he left the poem unfiniſhed ; and never after attempted a composition that required a courſe of thinking. From this time his memory gradually declined, his paſſions perverted his underſtanding, and, in 1741, he became utterly incapable of converſation ; and it was found neceſſary to appoint legal guardians to his perſon and his fortune. He now loſt all ſenſe of diſtinction. His meat was brought to him cut into mouthfuls ; but he would never touch it while the servant ſtaid ; and at laſt, after it ſtood perhaps an hour, would eat it walking ; for he continued his old habit, and was on his feet ten hours a-day. During next year a ſhort interval of reaſon enſuing, gave hopes of his recovery ; but in a few days he sunk into lethargic ſtupidity, motionleſs, heedleſs, and ſpeechleſs. After a year of total ſilence, however, when his houſe-keeper told him that the uſual illuminations were preparing to celebrate his birth, he anſwered, “ It is all folly ; they had better let it alone.” He at laſt sunk into a perfect ſilence, which continued till the 29th of October 1745, when he expired without a ſtruggle, in his 78th year. The behaviour of the citizens on this occaſion gave the ſtrongeſt proof of the deep impreſſion he had made on their minds. Though he had been ſo many years to all intents and purpoſes dead to the world, and his departure from that ſtate ſeemed a thing rather to be wiſhed than deplored, yet no ſooner was his death announced, than they gathered from all quarters, and forced their way in crowds into the houſe, to pay the laſt tribute of grief to their departed benefactor. Nothing but lamentations were heard all around the quarter where he lived, as if he had been cut off in the vigour of his years. Happy were they who firſt got into the chamber where he lay, to procure, by bribes to the ſervants, locks of his hair, to be handed down as ſacred relics to their poſterity ; and ſo eager were numbers to obtain at any price this precious memorial, that in leſs than an hour, his venerable head was entirely ſtripped of all its ſilver ornaments, ſo that not a hair remained. By his will, which was dated in May 1740, just before he ceaſed to be a reasonable being, he left about L. 1200 in ſpecific legacies ; and the rest of his fortune, which amounted to about L. 11,000, to erect and endow an hoſpital for lunatics and idiots. He was buried in the moſt private manner, according to directions in his will, in the great aiſle of St Patrick’s cathedral, and, by way of monument, a ſlab of black marble was placed againſt the wall, on which was engraved the following Latin epitaph, written by himſelf :</p><p>Hic depoſitum est corpus <hi rend="smallcaps">Jonathan Swift,</hi> S. T. P. Hujus Ecclesiæ Cathedralis Decani :</p><p>Ubi sæva indignatio</p><p>Ulterius cor lacerare nequit.</p><p>Abi, viator,</p><p>Et imitare, si poteris,</p><p>Strenuum pro virili libertatis vindicem.</p><p>Obiit anno (1745)</p><p>Mensis (Octobris) die (29.)</p><p>Ætatis anno 78.</p><p>Swift undoubtedly was a man of native genius. His fancy was inexhauſtible ; his conceptions were lively and comprehenſive ; and he had the peculiar felicity of conveying them in language equally correct, free, and perſpicuous. His penetration was as quick as intuition ; he was indeed the critic of nature ; and no man ever wrote ſo much, and borrowed ſo little.</p><p>As his genius was of the firſt claſs, ſo were ſome of his virtues. The following anecdote will illuſtrate his filial piety. His mother died in 1710, as appears by a memorandum in one of the account-books which Dr Swift always made up yearly, and on each page entered minutely all his receipts and expences in every month, beginning his year from November I. He obſerved the ſame method all his lifetime till his laſt illneſs. At the foot of that page which includes his expences of the month of May 1710, at the glebe houſe of Laracor in the county of Meath, where he was then reſident, are theſe remarkable words, which ſhow at the same time his filial piety, and the religious uſe which he thought it his duty to make of that melancholy event. <hi rend="italic">“ Mem.</hi> On Wedneſday, between ſeven and eight in the evening, May 10. 1710, I received a letter in my chamber at Laracor (Mr Percival and Jo. Beaumont being by) from Mrs F—, dated May 9. with one incloſed, ſent by Mrs Worral at Leiceſter to Mrs F—, giving an account that my dear mother, Mrs Abigail Swift, died that morning, Monday April 24. 1710, about ten o’clock, after a long ſickneſs : being ill all winter, and lame ; and extremely ill about a month or six weeks before her death. I have now loſt my barrier between me and death. God grant I may live to be as well prepared<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0249.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0243"/>
for it as I confidently believe her to have been ! If the way to heaven be through piety, truth, juſtice, and charity, ſhe is there. J. S.” He always treated his mother, during her life, with the utmoſt duty and affection ; and ſhe ſometimes came to Ireland to viſit him after his ſettlement at Laracor.</p><p>The liberality of the dean hath been a topic of juſt encomium with all his admirers ; nor could his enemies deny him this praiſe. In his domeſtic affairs, he always acted with ſtrict economy. He kept the most regular accounts ; and he ſeems to have done this chiefly with a view to increaſe his power of being uſeful. “ His income, which was little more than L. 700 <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> he endeavoured to divide into three parts, for the following purposes. Firſt, to live upon one-third of it. Secondly, to give another third in penſions and charities, according to the manner in which perſons who received them had lived : and the other third he laid by, to build an hoſpital for the reception of idiots and lunatics.” “ What is remarkable in this generous man, is this (ſays Mr F.), that when he lent money upon bond or mortgage, he would not take the legal intereſt, but one <hi rend="italic">per cent,</hi> below it.”</p><p>His charity appears to have been a settled principle of duty more than an inſtinctive effort of good nature : but as it was thus founded and ſupported, it had extraordinary merit, and ſeldom failed to exert itſelf in a manner that contributed moſt to render it beneficial. He did not laviſh his money on the idle and the worthleſs. He nicely diſcriminated characters, and was ſeldom the dupe of impoſition. Hence his generoſity always turned to an uſeful account : while it relieved distreſs, it encouraged induſtry, and rewarded virtue. We dwell with great pleaſure on this truly excellent and diſtinguiſhing part of the dean’s character : and for the ſake of his charity we can overlook his oddities, and almoſt forgive his faults. He was a very peculiar man in every reſpect. Some have ſaid, “ What a man he would have been, had he been without thoſe whims and infirmities which ſhaded both his genius and his character!” But perhaps the peculiarities complained of were inſeparable from his genius. The vigour and fertility of the root could not fail now and then of throwing out ſuperfluous suckers. What produced theſe, produced alſo the more beautiful branches, and gave the fruit all its richneſs.</p><p>It muſt be acknowledged, that the dean’s fancy hurried him into great abſurdities and inconſiſtencies, for which nothing but his extraordinary talents and noble virtues, diſcovered in other inſtances, could have atoned. The rancour he diſcovered on all occaſions towards the dissenters is totally unjuſtifiable. No ſect could have merited it in the degree in which he always ſhowed it to them ; for, in some inſtances, it bordered on downright perſecution. He doubtleſs had his reaſons for expoſing their principles to ridicule, and might perhaps have ſufficient grounds for ſome of his accuſations againſt their principal leaders in Ireland ; but nothing could juſtify his virulence againſt the whole body. In a ſhort poem on one claſs of diſſenters he beſtowed a ſtricture upon Betteſworth, a lawyer eminent for his insolence to the clergy, which, from a very conſiderable reputation, brought him into immediate and univerſal contempt. Betteſworth, enraged at his diſgrace and loſs, went to the dean, and demanded whether he was the author of that poem? “ Mr Betteſworth (anſwered he), I was in my youth acquainted with great lawyers, who, knowing my diſpoſition to ſatire, adviſed me, if any <hi rend="italic">ſcoundrel</hi> or <hi rend="italic">blockhead</hi> whom I had lampooned ſhould aſk, ‘ Are you the author of this paper ?’ to tell him that I was not the author ; and therefore, I tell you, Mr Betteſworth, that I am not the author of theſe lines.”</p><p>Swift has been accuſed of irreligion and miſanthropy, on account of his Tale of a Tub, and his Yahoos in Gulliver’s Travels ; but both charges ſeem to be ill-founded, or at leaſt not ſupported by that evidence. The <hi rend="italic">Tale of a Tub</hi> holds up to ridicule ſuperſtitious and fanatical absurdities ; but it never attacks the eſſentials of religion : and in the ſtory of the <hi rend="italic">Taboos,</hi> diſguſting we confeſs, there appears to us as little evidence that the author hated his own ſpecies, as in the poems of <hi rend="italic">Strepbοn and Chloe,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Ladies Dressing Room,</hi> that he approved of groſſneſs and filth in the female ſex. We do not indeed, with his fondeſt admirers, perceive the moral tendency of the Voyage to the Houyhnhnms, or conſider it as a ſatire admirably calculated to reform mankind ; but neither do we think that it can poſſibly corrupt them, or lead them to think meanly of their rational nature. According to Sheridan, “ the deſign of this apologue is to place before the eyes of man a picture of the two different parts of his frame, detached from each other, in order that he may the better eſtimate the true value of each, and see the neceſſity there is that the one ſhould have an abſolute command over the other. In your merely animal capacity, says he to man, without reaſon to guide you, and actuated only by a blind inſtinct, I will ſhow you that you would be degraded below the beaſts of the field. That very form, that very body, you are now ſo proud of, as giving you ſuch a superiority over all other animals, I will ſhow you, owe all their beauty, and all their greateſt powers, to their being actuated by a rational soul. Let that be withdrawn, let the body be inhabited by the mind of a brute, let it be prone as theirs are, and ſuffered like theirs to take its natural courſe, without any aſſiſtance from art, you would in that caſe be the moſt deformed, as to your external appearance, the moſt deteſtable of all creatures. And with regard to your internal frame, filled with all the evil diſpoſitions and malignant paſſions of mankind, you would be the moſt miserable of beings, living in a continued ſtate of internal vexation, and of hatred and warfare with each other.</p><p>“ On the other hand, I will ſhow another picture of an animal endowed with a rational ſoul, and acting uniformly up to the dictates of right reaſon. Here you may ſee collected all the virtues, all the great qualities, which dignify man’s nature, and conſtitute the happineſs of his life. What is the natural inference to be drawn from theſe two different repreſentations ? Is it not evidently a lesson to mankind, warning them not to ſuffer the animal part to be predominant in them, lest they reſemble the vile Yahoo, and fall into vice and miſery ; but to emulate the noble and generous Houyhnhnm, by cultivating the rational faculty to the utmoſt ; which will lead them to a life of virtue and happineſs.”</p><p>Such <hi rend="italic">may</hi> have been the author’s intention ; but it is not ſufficiently obvious to produce the proper effect, and is indeed hardly conſiſtent with that incapability under which he repreſents the Yahoos of ever acquiring, by any culture, the virtues of the noble Houyhnhnms.</p><p>With reſpect to his religion, it is a fact unqueſtionable, that while the power of ſpeech remained, he continued constant in the performance of his private devotions ; and in proportion as his memory failed, they were gradually ſhortened, till at laſt he could only repeat the Lord’s prayer, which he continued to do till the power of utterance for ever ceaſed. Such a habit as this could not have been formed but by a man deeply impressed with a conviction of the truth and importance of revelation.</p><p>The moſt inexcuſable part of Swift’s conduct is his treatment of Stella and Vanessa, for which no proper apology can be made, and which the vain attempts of his friends have only tended to aggravate. One attributes his sin-<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0250.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0244"/>
gular conduct to a peculiarity in his conſtitution ; but if he knew that he was incapable of fulfilling the duties of the married ſtate, how came he to tie one of the ladies to himſelf by the marriage-ceremony, and in the moſt explicit terms to declare his paſſion to the other ? And what are we to think of the ſenſibility of a man who, ſtrongly attached as he ſeems to have been to both, could, without speaking, fling a paper on the table of the one, which “ proved (as our author expreſſes it) her death-warrant,” and could throw the other, his beloved Stella, in her laſt illneſs, into unſpeakable agonies, and “ never ſee her more, for only adjuring him, by their friendſhip, to let her have the ſatisfaction of dying at leaſt, though ſhe had not lived, his acknowledged wife?” Another apologiſt inſinuates, upon ſomething like evidence, that Stella bore a ſon to Swift, and yet labours to excuſe him for not declaring her his wife, becauſe she had agreed at the marriage that it ſhould remain a ſecret from all the world unless the diſcovery ſhould be called for by <hi rend="italic">urgent necesſity</hi>; but what could be meant by the term <hi rend="italic">urgent neceſſity,</hi> unleſs it alluded to the birth of children, he confesses that it would be hard to ſay. The truth we believe to be what has been ſaid by Johnſon, that the man whom Stella had the misfortune to love was fond of singularity, and desirous to make a mode of happineſs for himſelf, different from the general courſe of things and the order of Providence ; he wiſhed ſor all the pleaſures of perfect friendſhip, without the uneaſineſs of conjugal reſtraint. But with this ſtate poor Stella was not satisfied ; ſhe never was treated as a wife, and to the world ſhe had the appearance of a miſtreſs. She lived ſullenly on, hoping that in time he would own and receive her. This, we believe, he offered at laſt to do, but not till the change of his manners and the depravation of his mind made her tell him, that “ it was too late.”</p><p>The natural acrimony of Swift’s temper had been increaſed by repeated diſappointments. This gave a ſplenetic tincture to his writings, and amidſt the duties of private and domeſtic life it too frequently appeared to ſhade the luſtre of his more eminent virtues. — The dean hath been accuſed of avarice, but with the ſame truth as he hath been accuſed of infidelity. In detached views, no man was more liable to be miſtaken. Even his genius and good ſenſe might be queſtioned, if we were only to read ſome paſſages of his writings. To judge fairly and pronounce juſtly of him as a man and as an author, we ſhould examine the uniform tenor of his diſpoſition and conduct, and the general nature and deſign of his productions. In the latter he will appear great, and in the former good ; notwithſtanding the puns and puerilities of the one, and the abſurdities and inconſiſtencies of the other.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Swift,</hi> in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Hirundo.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>