<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0255.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0249-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SYENE</label>,
an ancient city of Egypt, ſituated, according to Mr Bruce, in north latitude 24⁰ 0' <hi rend="italic">45".</hi> Pliny and Strabo both say that it lay directly under the tropic of Cancer. Whether Mr Bruce’s authority be ſufficient to overturn the evidence of Pliny and Strabo, we ſhall leave to others to determine.</p><p>Syene is remarkable for being the place where the firſt attempt was made to meaſure the circumference of the earth. This was done by Eratoſthenes, whom Ptolemy Euergetes had invited from Athens to Alexandria. In this attempt two poſitions were affirmed, viz. that Alexandria and Syene were exactly 5000 ſtadia diſtant from each other, and that they were preciſely under the same meridian ; but both theſe are denied by Mr Bruce, who has made many obſervations on the ſubject, which our limits will not allow us to take notice of at preſent. He tells us, that there is at Aſum an obeliſk erected by Ptolemy Euergetes, the patron of Eratoſthenes, without hieroglyphics, directly facing the ſouth, with its top firſt cut into a narrow neck, then ſpread out like a fan into a ſemicircular form, with pavements curiouſly levelled to receive the ſhade, and make the ſeparation of the true ſhadow from the penumbra as diſtinct as poſſible. This is ſuppoſed by Mr Bruce to have been conſtructed with a deſign to vary the experiment of Eratoſthenes with a larger radius ; and the inquiry concerning the dimenſions of the earth, in our author’s opinion, was the occaſion of many obeliſks being erected in this kingdom ; a demonſtration of which is, that the figure of the top is varied ; being ſometimes very ſharp, and ſometimes a portion of a circle, in order to get rid of the great impediment ariſing from the penumbra, which makes it difficult to determine the length of the ſhadow with preciſion. It is now called As <hi rend="italic">ſouan.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>