<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0744-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0797.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROSSE, EARL OF</label> a title borne by the Irish family of Parsons. James
                    Parsons, a native of Leicestershire, who flourished in the x6th century, was the
                    father of Sir William Parsons (r. 1570-1650), one of the lords justices of
                    Ireland. Having crossed to Ireland in early life, William Parsons became
                    surveyor-general in 1602 and obtained land in various parts of the country. In
                    1620 he was made a baronet; in 1643 he was deprived of his office as lord
                    justice, and he died early in 1650. His great-grandson, Sir Richard Parsons,
                    bart. (c. 1657-1703), was created Baron Oxmantown and Viscount Rosse in 1681,
                    and Richard’s son and successor, Richard (d. 1741), was made earl of Rosse in
                    1718. The titles became extinct when Richard, the 2nd earl, died in August 1764,</p>
               <p>Sir William Parsons had two brothers, Sir Lawrence and Sir Fenton Parsons. Sir
                    Lawrence, second baron of the Irish exchequer, left a son, William (d. 1653),
                    who defended Birr Castle, King’s County, for over a year against the Irish
                    during</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0745" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0798.jp2"/>
               <p>the rebellion of 1641, and whose son, Sir Lawrence Parsons (d. 1698), was made a
                    baronet in 1677. This Sir Lawrence was a strong Protestant, and was found guilty
                    of high treason, being attainted and sentenced to death during the brief period
                    of James II.’s ascendancy in Ireland. He was not executed, however, and
                    afterwards he took some part in the struggle against the supporters of James II.
                    His descendant, Lawrence Harman Parsons (1749-1807), was created Baron Oxmantown
                    in 1792, Viscount Oxmantown in 1795, and earl of Rosse in 1806. He died on the
                    20th of April 1807, and was succeeded by his nephew Lawrence.</p>
               <p>Lawrence Parsons, 2nd earl of Rosse (1758-1841), the eldest son of Sir William
                    Parsons, bart. (d. 1791), of Birr Castle, was born on the 21st of May 1758.
                    Educated at Trinity College, Dublin, he entered the Irish parliament as member
                    for the university in 1782, and soon came to the front in debate. A friend and
                    follower of Henry Flood, he has been described as “ one of the very, very few
                    honest men in the Irish House of Commons.” He favoured some measure of relief to
                    Roman Catholics and also parliamentary reform, a speech which he delivered on
                    this question in 1793 being described by W. E. H. Lecky as <hi rend="sup">0</hi>
                    exceedingly valuable to students of Irish history”; but he disliked and opposed
                    the union of the parliaments of Great Britain and Ireland. After this event,
                    however, he represented King’s County in the united parliament until 1807, and
                    he was a representative peer for Ireland from 1809 to 1841. He died at Brighton
                    on the 24th of February 1841. Rosse wrote <hi rend="italic">Observations on the
                        Bequest of Henry Flood to Trinity College, Dublin, with a Defence of the
                        Ancient History of Ireland</hi> (Dublin, 1795). His eldest son was the
                    astronomer William Parsons, 3rd earl of Rosse (see below).</p>
 
 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
