<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0731-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0784.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROSEBERY, ARCHIBALD PHILIP PRIMROSE</label>, <hi rend="smallcaps">5th
                        Earl of</hi> (1847- ), British statesman, born in London on the</p>               <p>7th of May 1847, was the grandson and successor to the title of Archibald John
                    Primrose, 4th earl of Rosebery (1783-1868), a representative peer of Scotland,
                    who was in 1828 created a peer of the United Kingdom as Baron Rosebery, and was
                    an active supporter of the Reform Bill. The Scottish earldom was first conferred
                    in 1703 upon the 4th earl’s great-grandfather, Archibald Primrose of Dalmeny
                    (1664-1723), a staunch Whig and a commissioner for the Union. The 5th earl’s
                    mother was Catherine Lucy Wilhelmina, only daughter* of Philip Henry, 4th Earl
                    Stanhope; she was thus a sister of Earl Stanhope, the historian, and a niece of
                    Lady Hester Stanhope, who was the niece of William Pitt. A celebrated beauty, a
                    maid of honour and bridesmaid of Queen Victoria, she married, on the 20th of
                    December 1843, Archibald, Lord Dalmeny (1809-1851), member for the Stirling
                    Burghs, who became a lord of the admiralty under Melbourne. After his death she
                    became the wife of Harry George Vane, 4th duke of Cleveland, and died in 1901.</p>               <p>The young Lord Dalmeny was educated at Brighton and at Eton, where he had as
                    slightly junior contemporaries Mr A. J. Balfour and Lord Randolph Churchill. He
                    was described by the most brilliant Eton tutor of his day, William Johnson Cory
                    (author of <hi rend="italic">Ionica),</hi> as a “ portentously wise youth, not,
                    however, deficient in fun.” He added that Dalmeny “ desired the palm without the
                    dust.” In 1866 he matriculated at Christ Church, Oxford, but went down in 1868,
                    by the request of the dean, rather than abandon the possession of a small racing
                    stud. In the same year he succeeded to the earldom and to the family estates. In
                    February 1871 he seconded the Address in the House of Lords; a more original
                    effort followed in November 1871, when he delivered a remarkable essay on the
                    Union of Scotland and England at the Edinburgh Philosophical Institution. Three
                    years later he was elected president of the Social Science Congress at Glasgow,
                    where, on the 30th of September, he gave a striking address upon the discovery
                    of means for raising the condition of the working class as the “ true leverage
                    of empire.” In the meantime he travelled in the south of Europe and in North
                    America. On his return he acquired an English country house called The Durdans,
                    Epsom, which he largely rebuilt and adorned with some of the finest turf
                    portraits of George Stubbs. Following the example, as he declared, of Oliver
                    Cromwell (for whom he showed an admiration in other respects—culminating in 1900
                    in the erection of a statue outside Westminster Hall, which was not appreciated
                    either by the Irish Nationalist party or by others among his political
                    associates), he took a pride in owning racehorses, and afterwards won the Derby
                    three times, in 1894, 1895 and 1905. He was the first man to enjoy the
                    distinction of winning the Derby while prime minister; but though this was
                    popular enough among many classes, it did not please the Liberal Nonconformists
                    so much, who considered a racehorse a mere gambling-machine. On the 20th of
                    March 1878 Lord Rosebery married Hannah, only child of Baron Meyer Amschel de
                    Rothschild, of Mentmore, Bucks. The newly married couple took a lease of
                    Lansdowne House, which for several years was a salon for the Liberal party and a
                    centre of hospitality for a much wider circle.</p>               <p>Though impeded in his political career by his exclusion from the House of
                    Commons, Lord Rosebery’s reputation as a social reformer and orator was steadily
                    growing. In 1878 he was elected Lord Rector of Aberdeen and in 1880 of Edinburgh
                    University, where he gave an eloquent address upon Patriotism. In 1880 he
                    entertained Mr Gladstone at Dalmeny, and during the “ Mid Lothian campaign ” he
                    had much to do with the stage-management of the demonstrations. As was shown
                    later, he imported into his view of politics a warm sentiment and an imaginative
                    outlook; and he was an enthusiastic student of Lord Beaconsfield’s political
                    novels, more particularly of <hi rend="italic">Sybil,</hi> after the heroine in
                    which he named one of his daughters. In August i88r he became undersecretary at
                    the Home Office, his immediate chief being Sir William Harcourt. His work was
                    practically confined to the direction of the Scottish department of the Office.
                    A clamour was nevertheless' raised in regard to the incompatibility of the
                    under-secretaryship with a position in the House of Lords, and Lord Rosebery
                    resigned the post in June 1883. He and his wife utilized the interval to make a
                    trip round the world, being most warmly received in Australia, and returning by
                    way of India. At the close of 1884 he resumed office as first commissioner of
                    works with a seat in the cabinet, and his adherence carried with it a distinct
                    accession of strength to the Liberal ministry, which was much discredited by the
                    tragedy attached to the fate of Gordon. The attitude of the government on the
                    Afghan question and generally in regard to Russia was held by many to have been
                    perceptibly stiffened owing to Lord Rosebery’s influence.</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0732" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0785.jp2"/>
               <p>In June 1885 the Liberal administration broke up, but Lord Salisbury’s ministry,
                    which succeeded, was beaten early in February 1886, and when Mr Gladstone
                    adopted Home Rule, Lord Rosebery threw in his lot with the old leader, and was
                    made secretary of state for foreign affairs during the brief Liberal ministry
                    which followed. He rather distinguished himself in the Lucia Bay negotiations
                    then being carried on with Germany. If Busch is to be believed, Prince
                    Bismarck’s view was that Lord Rosebery had “ quite mesmerized ” Count Herbert
                    Bismarck; and the latter, from his father’s standpoint, conceded too much to
                    Lord Rosebery, who proved himself to be, in Bismarck’s language, “ very sharp.”
                    His views on foreign policy differed materially from those of Granville and
                    Gladstone. His mind was dwelling constantly upon the political legacy of the two
                    Pitts; he was a reader of Sir John Seeley; he had himself visited the colonies;
                    had predicted that a war would not, as was commonly said, disintegrate the
                    empire, but rather the reverse; had magnified the importance of taking colonial
                    opinion; and had always been a convinced advocate of some form of Imperial
                    Federation. He was already taunted with being an Imperialist, but his
                    independent attitude won public approval. Cambridge gave him the degree of LL.D.
                    in 1888; in January 1889 he was elected a member of the first county council of
                    London, and on the 12th of February he was elected chairman of that body by 104
                    votes to 17. The tact, assiduity and dignity with which he guided the
                    deliberations of the council made him exceedingly popular with its members. In
                    the spring of 1890 he presided over the Co-operative Congress, but with a view
                    to the impending political campaign he found it necessary to resign the
                    chairmanship of the county council in June. In November of this year, however,
                    Lady -Rosebery died, and he withdrew for a period from public business. In 1891
                    he made some brief continental visits, one to Madrid, and in October he saw
                    through the press his little monograph upon <hi rend="italic">William Pitt,</hi>
                    in the Twelve English Statesmen Series, of which it may be said that it competes
                    in interest with Viscount Morley’s <hi rend="italic">Walpole.</hi> In January
                    1892, upon a new election, he again for a few months became chairman of the
                    county council. It was already recognized that in him the country possessed not
                    only a public man of exceptionally attractive personality, but one whose
                    literary tastes were combined with a gift for expression which was at once
                    original and fluent. In October the Garter was conferred upon him by Queen
                    Victoria.</p>               <p>Meanwhile, in August, upon the return of Gladstone to power, he was induced with
                    some difficulty (for he was suffering at the time from insomnia) to resume his
                    position as foreign minister. His acceptance was construed as a security against
                    the suspicion of weakness abroad which the Liberal party had incurred by their
                    foreign policy during the ’eighties. He strongly opposed the evacuation of
                    Egypt; he insisted upon the exclusive control by Great Britain of the Upper Nile
                    Valley, and also upon the retention of Uganda. In 1893 the question of Siam came
                    near to causing serious trouble with France, but by the exercise of a
                    combination of firmness and forbearance on Lord Rosebery’s part the crisis was
                    averted, and the lines were laitl down for preserving Siam, if possible, as a
                    buffer state between the English and French frontiers in Indo-China. In the
                    spring of 1895 he was clear-sighted enough to refuse to join the anti-Japanese
                    League of Russia, France and Germany at the end of the China-Japan War.</p>               <p>Lord Rosebery’s personal popularity had been increased at home by his successful
                    intervention in the coal strike of December 1893, and when in March 1894 the
                    resignation of Gladstone was announced, his selection by Queen Victoria for the
                    premiership was welcomed by the public at large and by the majority of his own
                    party. On all hands he was then considered <hi rend="italic">dignus
                        im-perio</hi> —it was only as the new administration went to pieces that
                    people began to add <hi rend="italic">nisi imperasset.</hi> The conditions he
                    had to face were by no means hopeful. The Liberal majority of 44 was already
                    dwindling away, and the malcontents, who considered that Sir William Harcourt
                    should have been the prime minister, or who were perpetually intriguing against
                    a leader who did not satisfy their idea of Radicalism, made Lord Rosebery’s
                    personal position no easy one. A systematic policy of detraction was pursued by
                    the small section of the Radical party who objected to a peer premier as such,
                    and a great deal of adverse criticism was also aroused by a speech in which the
                    prime minister, taunted for not again bringing forward a Home Rule measure,
                    insisted upon the truism that the conversion of England, the “ predominant
                    partner,”, was a necessary condition of success. The support of the Irish
                    Nationalists was by no means secure. Lord Rosebery’s foreign policy, moreover,
                    was too Tory for his Radical followers; he insisted upon “ continuity of policy
                    in foreign affairs,” which meant carrying on the Conservative policy and not
                    upsetting it. The premier was thought to have shown a restlessness and a rawness
                    at the touch of censure which did not increase his reputation for reserve power
                    or strength, but this was undoubtedly due in large measure to the recrudescence
                    of the insomnia from which he had suffered in 1891. The government effected
                    little. In Mr Asquith’s phrase, it was “ ploughing the sands.” The Parish
                    Councils Act was only passed by compromising with the Opposition. Local Veto and
                    Disestablishment of the Welsh Church were put in the forefront of the party
                    programme, but the government was already to all appearances riding for a fall,
                    when on the 24th of June 1895 it <hi rend="sup">was</hi> beaten upon an adverse
                    vote in the Commons in regard to a question of the supply and reserve of small
                    arms ammunition.</p>               <p>The general election which followed after Lord Salisbury had formed his new
                    ministry was remarkable for the undisciplined state of the Liberal party. At the
                    Eighty Club and the Albert Hall Lord Rosebery advised them to concentrate upon
                    the reform of the House of Lords, that assembly being, as he said, a foremost
                    obstacle to the passing of legislation on the lines of the Newcastle programme;
                    but he was unable to suggest in what direction it should be reformed. Sir
                    William Harcourt and Mr John Morley, on the other hand, concentrated
                    respectively upon Local Option and Home Rule. The Liberals were quarrelling
                    among themselves, and the result was an overwhelming defeat. In Opposition Lord
                    Rosebery was now at a serious disadvantage as head of a parliamentary party; for
                    in any case he could not rally them as a loyally followed leader in the House of
                    Commons might have done. But his followers were not all loyal, and his rivals in
                    leadership were themselves in the House of Commons. Added to this there was
                    still in tbe background the veteran statesman to whom Liberalism owed an
                    unequalled obligation. When the <hi rend="sup">u</hi> Armenian atrocities ”
                    became a burning question in the country in 1896, and Mr Gladstone himself
                    emerged from his retirement to advocate intervention, Lord Rosebery’s
                    difficulties had taken their final form. He declined to support this demand at
                    the risk of a European war, and on the 8th of October 1896 he announced to the
                    Liberal whip, Mr Thomas Ellis, his resignation of the Liberal leadership. On the
                    following day he made a farewell speech at the Empire Theatre, Edinburgh, to
                    over four thousand people, and for some time he held aloof from party politics,
                    “ ploughing his furrow alone,” as he afterwards phrased it.</p>               <p>In 1898, on the death of Mr Gladstone, he paid a noble and eloquent tribute in
                    the House of Lords to the life and public services of his old leader. He was a
                    pall-bearer at his funeral on the 28th of May, as he had previously been at the
                    burials of Tennyson and Millais. His influence in the country was still a strong
                    one on personal grounds, and he came forward now and again to give expression
                    independently to popular feeling. In the autumn of 1898 he gave valuable support
                    to the attitude taken up by Lord Salisbury upon the Fashoda question. He was
                    indeed bound by consistency to withstand what his own government, by the words
                    of Sir Edward Grey, had declared would be an unfriendly act on the part of
                    France. Again, after Mr Kruger’s ultimatum in October 1899, Lord Rosebery spoke
                    upon the necessity of the nation closing its ranks and supporting the government
                    in the prosecution of war in South Africa. After Nicholson’s Nek he reiterated
                    the resolution of tbe country “ to see this thing through.” Nevertheless, in a
                    letter to Captain</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0733" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0786.jp2"/>
               <p>Lambton, an unsuccessful Liberal candidate for Newcastle, in September 1900, he
                    condemned the general conduct of affairs by Lord Salisbury’s government, while
                    in several speeches in the House of Lords he strongly urged the necessity of
                    army reform. Since his abandonment of the leadership in 1896, the lack of
                    coherence in the Liberal party had become more and more manifest. The war had
                    brought to the front a pro-Boer section, who seemed gradually to be compromising
                    the whole party, and had apparently succeeded in winning the support of Sir
                    Henry Campbell-Bannerman, the leader in the House of Commons. Lord Rosebery
                    maintained for the most part a sphinx-like seclusion, but in July 1901 he at
                    last came forward strongly as the champion of the Liberal Imperialist section.</p>               <p>In deference to the wishes of supporters such as Mr Asquith, Sir Henry Fowler
                    and Sir Edward Grey he determined to <hi rend="sup">(i</hi> put his views into
                    the common stock ” at a representative meeting of Liberals held at Chesterfield
                    in December 1901. There he advised the Liberal party that “ its slate must be
                    cleaned.” and, as he subsequently explained, this cleansing must involve the
                    elimination of Home Rule for Ireland. His appeal for “ spade work ” resulted in
                    the formation of the Liberal League, inside the Liberal Opposition; and what
                    Lord Rosebery himself described as his “ definite separation ” from Sir Henry
                    Campbell-Bannerman’s “ tabernacle ” took place. This announcement, however, was
                    no sooner made than it was explained away by the supporters of both, and early
                    in 1902 Lord Rosebery spoke at the National Liberal Club in a way which
                    indicated that an understanding might still be arrived at. But though Mr Asquith
                    and Sir Edward Grey adhered to the Liberal League, Sir Henry Campbell-Bannerman
                    retained the loyalty of the majority of the Liberal party, and Lord Spencer
                    threw his weight on the same side; and in a speech at the Liberal League dinner
                    on the 31st of July Lord Rosebery had to admit that their principles had not yet
                    prevailed, and that, until they did, a reconciliation between the two wings of
                    the party would be impossible. In January 1903 he addressed a Liberal meeting at
                    Plymouth, and appeared to be attempting to concentrate Opposition criticism upon
                    the points in the government policy which did not involve the Imperialist
                    difference; and in discussing War Office reform he advocated the appointment of
                    Lord Kitchener as secretary of state for war.</p>               <p>When Mr Chamberlain started his new fiscal programme, combining Tariff Reform
                    with Colonial Preference, Lord Rosebery at first seemed' inclined to treat it as
                    non-political, and on the 19th of May 1903 he declared in an address to the
                    Burnley Chamber of Commerce that he was not one of those who regarded Free Trade
                    as part of the Sermon on the Mount. This utterance led to an idea that he was
                    inclined to consider favourably the proposal for a preferential tariff, his
                    earlier enthusiasm for Imperial Federation making his support an interesting
                    political possibility. But this idea was quickly dispelled; on the 22nd he
                    expressed his surprise that anybody should have thought he intended to approve
                    of Mr Chamberlain’s plan; he was not prepared to dismiss in advance a proposal
                    for the consolidation of the empire made by the responsible government, but he
                    believed that the objections to a policy of preference were insurmountable. The
                    fact, no doubt, was that Mr Asquith, Lord Rosebery’s chief lieutenant in the
                    Liberal League, made himself from the outset a determined champion of free trade
                    in opposition to Mr Chamberlain; and Lord Rosebery quickly came into line with
                    the rest of the Liberal party on this question. On the 12th of June, addressing
                    the Liberal League, he admitted that as a lifelong Imperialist it was with pain
                    and grief that he could not support Mr Chamberlain’s scheme, but the empire had
                    been built upon free trade, and he only saw danger to the empire in these new
                    proposals. Speaking at Sheffield on the 13 th of October he criticized the
                    scheme in more detail, and, as an Imperialist, warned the country against it,
                    emphasizing his own ideal of the future of the empire—“ a strong mother with
                    strong children, each working out his own political and fiscal salvation.” His
                    attitude on the new issue undoubtedly affected public opinion, and helped to
                    draw him closer to the great body of the Liberal party, who saw that their
                    identification with the cause of free trade was doing much to remove the public
                    distrust associated with their support of Home Rule. On the 7th of November at
                    Leicester Lord Rosebery insisted that what the country wanted was not fiscal
                    reform but commercial reform, and he appealed to the free-trade section of the
                    Unionist party to join the Liberals in a united defence,—an appeal incidentally
                    for Liberal unity which was warmly seconded ten days later by Sir Henry
                    Campbell-Bannerman. On the 26th of November Lord Rosebery’s speech on the same
                    lines at a meeting in South London resulted in a powerful demonstration in
                    favour of his resuming the Liberal leadership, but he made no public response.
                    On the 10th of June 1904 he addressed a meeting of the Liberal League at the
                    Queen’s Hall, London, and sketched a programme of “sane and practical
                    Imperialism”; but he irritated the Home Rulers by again repudiating a parliament
                    in Dublin, and he perplexed the public generally by his adverse criticism on the
                    popular Anglo-French Agreement, which he was the only English statesman to
                    oppose, on the ground of its handing over Morocco to France.</p>               <p>At Glasgow on the 5th of December he again outlined a Liberal programme, this
                    and other speeches all leading to tbe assumption that his return to active
                    co-operation with the Liberal party in the general election—which could not be
                    long delayed—was fairly certain. Early in 1905 this impression gained such
                    strength and such polite references were made to one another in public by Lord
                    Rosebery and Sir Henry Campbell-Bannerman, that his assumption of office in a
                    Liberal ministry, possibly presided over by Earl Spencer, was confidently
                    anticipated. But these forecasts were ultimately upset, not only by Lord
                    Spencer’s illness and his removal from the list of possible Liberal prime
                    ministers, but by Sir Henry Campbell-Bannerman’s pronouncement at Stirling in
                    November on the subject of Irish Home Rule. Lord Rosebery had just gone down to
                    Cornwall to make a series of speeches in support of the Liberal programme, now
                    fairly well mapped out as regards those items which represented the strong
                    public opposition to what had been done by the Unionist government. It was
                    believed that an understanding had been come to between his Liberal League
                    henchmen (Mr Asquith, Sir E. Grey and Mr Haldane) and Sir Henry
                    Campbell-Bannerman, and that Lord Rosebery’s co-operation was to be secured by
                    the adoption of some formula which would temporarily take Home Rule out of the
                    official programme as a question of practical politics. But to the general
                    surprise and Lord Rosebery’s own very evident mortification Sir Henry went a
                    long way in his Stirling speech to nail the Home Rule colour to the mast; he did
                    not indeed propose to introduce a Home Rule Bill, but he declared his
                    determination to proceed in Irish legislation on lines which would lead up to
                    the same result. Lord Rosebery abruptly broke off his campaign, declaring at
                    Bodmin (26th of November) that he would never “ fight under that banner. ” From
                    the moment the apparent recrudescence of the Liberal split over this question
                    seemed to have misled Air Balfour, who resigned office on the 4th of December,
                    into thinking that difficulties would arise over the formation of a Liberal
                    cabinet; but, whether or not the rumour was correct that a
                    blunder had been made at Stirling and that explanations had ensued which
                    satisfied Mr Asquith and Sir Edward Grey, this anticipation proved unjustified.
                    Lord Rosebery himself, it is true, held aloof; his protest had been publicly
                    made and he adhered to it in the absence of any public withdrawal by Sir Henry
                    Campbell-Bannerman; but he encouraged his Liberal League supporters to be loyal
                    to the new prime minister, and Mr Asquith, Sir E. Grey and Air Haldane were
                    included in the Liberal cabinet. The overwhelming Liberal and Labour victory at
                    the general election of 1906 began a new era in the fortunes of the party, and
                    Lord Rosebery’s individuality once more sank back from any position of
                    prominence in regard to its new programme. He remained outside party politics,</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0734" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0787.jp2"/>
               <p>emerging only in 1909, first to attack Mr Lloyd George s budget in the country
                    as a “ revolution,” and then—to the general surprise—to condemn the House of
                    Lords in debate for rejecting it; and in 1910 (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Parliament)</hi> he appeared once more to be coming to the front, by the
                    resolutions he carried in regard to the remodelling of the Upper Chamber, when
                    the death of King Edward VII. caused a temporary postponement of the
                    constitutional crisis. In September 1910 he acted as head of the special mission
                    sent to the Austrian court by George V. to announce bis accession to the
                    throne,—a selection peculiarly appropriate, and cordially welcomed as such,
                    because of his well-known Austrian sympathies. Indeed, in the East European
                    crisis of 1909 Lord Rosebery had taken a somewhat isolated part in vindicating
                    the attitude of Austria and her right to annex Bosnia-Herzegovina, in opposition
                    to the criticisms generally passed in the English press.</p>               <p>After his retirement from active politics Lord Rosebery continually displayed
                    his great qualities as a public speaker by eloquent and witty addresses on
                    miscellaneous subjects. No public man of his time was more fitted to act as
                    unofficial national orator; none more happy in the touches with which he could
                    adorn a social or literary topic and charm a nonpolitical audience; and on
                    occasion he wrote as well as he spoke. His <hi rend="italic">Pitt</hi> has
                    already been mentioned; his <hi rend="italic">Apprecia-lions and Addresses</hi>
                    and his <hi rend="italic">Peel</hi> (containing a remarkable comment on the
                    position of an English prime minister) were published in 1899; his <hi
                        rend="italic">Napoleon: the Last Phase</hi> —an ingenious, if paradoxical,
                    attempt to justify Napoleon’s conduct in exile at St Helena—in 1900; his <hi
                        rend="italic">Cromwell</hi> in the same year. In 1906 he published an
                    appreciation of his old friend Lord Randolph Churchill, inspired by the
                    publication of Mr Winston Churchill’s Life of his father. In its detached yet
                    intimate way, this is a model of the art by which a good judge of men, possessed
                    at the same time of a just historical sense, may, from the point of view of a
                    contemporary on the opposite side in politics, correct the perspective of an
                    official biography written under the limitations of filial obligation, and give
                    tone and value to the picture of an interesting personality.</p>               <p>Lord Rosebery’s family consisted of two sons and two daughters. His eldest son,
                    Lord Dalmeny (b. Jan. 1882), who in 1909 married a daughter of Lord Henry
                    Grosvenor, 3rd son of the 1 st duke of Westminster, entered parliament in 1906
                    as Liberal member for Mid Lothian, but retired in 1910; he was well known as a
                    cricketer, captaining the Surrey eleven in 1905 and 1906. The younger son, the
                    Hon. Neil Primrose (b. Dec. 1882), took more actively than his brother to a
                    political career, and in January 1910 was returned as a Liberal for the Wisbech
                    division of Cambridgeshire. The elder daughter, Lady Sybil, in 1903 married
                    Captain Charles Grant; the younger, Lady Margaret, in 1899 married the 1st earl
                    of Crewe. (H. Ch.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
