<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0724-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0777.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROSARY</label> (Lat. <hi rend="italic">rosarium),</hi> a popular devotion
                    of the Roman Catholic Church, consisting of 15 Paternosters and Glorias and 150
                    Aves, recited on beads. It is divided into three parts, each containing five
                    decades, a decade comprising 1 Pater, 10 Aves and a Gloria, in addition to a
                    subject for meditation selected from the “ mysteries ” of the life of Christ and
                    of the Blessed Virgin. The Christian practice of repeating prayers is traceable
                    to early times: Sozomen mentions <hi rend="italic">(H.E.</hi> v. 29) the hermit
                    Paul of the 4th century who threw away a pebble as he recited each of his 300
                    daily prayers; and a canon of the English synod of Cealcythe in 816 (Mansi xiv.
                    360) directed <hi rend="italic">septem bellidwn Paternoster</hi> to be said for
                    a deceased bishop. In many orders the lay brothers daily said a large number of
                    Paternosters instead of reading the breviary; it was natural that the
                    Paternoster should be the prayer most often repeated. The Ave Maria is first
                    mentioned as a form of prayer in the second half of the nth century, but it was
                    not until the 16th century that it became general in its present form. It is not
                    known precisely when the mechanical device of the rosary was first used. William
                    of Malmesbury <hi rend="italic">(De gest. pont. Angl.</hi> iv. 4) says that
                    Godiva, who founded a religious house at Coventry in 1040, left a string of
                    jewels, on which she had told her prayers, that it might be hung on the statue
                    of the Blessed Virgin. Thomas of Chantimpr6, who wrote about the middle of the
                    13th century, first mentions the word “ rosary ” <hi rend="italic">(De
                        apibus,</hi> ii. 13), using it apparently in a mystical sense as Mary’s
                    rose-garden. There is no contemporary confirmation of the story that the rosary
                    was given to St Dominic through revelation of the Blessed Virgin and was
                    employed during the crusade against the Albigenses, although the story was later
                    accepted by Leo X., Pius V., Gregory XIII., Sixtus V., Alexander VII., Innocent
                    XI. and Clement XI. According to Benedict XIV. <hi rend="italic">(De Fest.</hi>
                    160), the belief rests on the tradition of the Dominican order. Whatever may
                    have been the origin of the rosary, the Dominicans did much to propagate the
                    devotion. The practice of meditating on the mysteries doubtless began with a
                    Dominican, Alanus de Rupe (born 1428), and another Dominican, Jacob Sprenger (d.
                    1495), grand-inquisitor in Germany, founded the first confraternity of the
                    rosary at Cologne in 1475. This society spread rapidly, and was specially
                    privileged by Sixtus IV., Innocent VIII. and Leo. X. After the battle of Lepanto
                    (1st Sunday in October 1571), which was won while the members of the
                    confraternity at Rome were making supplication for Christian success, Pius V.
                    ordered an annual commemoration of “St Mary of Victory,” and Gregory XIII., by
                    bull of the 1st of April 1583, set aside the 1st Sunday in October as the feast
                    of the Rosary of the Blessed Virgin Mary, to be observed in such churches as
                    maintained an altar in honour of the rosary. Clement XI., by bull of the 3rd of
                    October 1716, directed the observance of the feast by all Christendom. The
                    devotion has been particularly fostered by the Jesuits, St Ignatius Loyola
                    having expressly ordered its use. It has been repeatedly indulgenced by various
                    popes. Leo XIII. issued eight encyclicals on the devotion; he urged its
                    recitation throughout October, and directed (1883) the insertion of the title
                        <hi rend="italic">regina sacratissimi rosarii</hi> in the Litany. There are
                    several varieties of the rosary more or less in use by Roman Catholics: the
                    Passionists, or rosary of the five wounds, approved by Leo XII. in 1823; the
                    Crown of Our Lord, attributed to Michael of Florence, a Camaldolese monk (c.
                    1516), and consisting of 33 Paters, 5 Aves and a Credo; St Bridget’s, 7 Paters
                    and 63 Aves, in honour of the joys and sorrows of the Blessed Virgin and the 63
                    years of her life. The Living Rosary, in which 15 persons unite to say the
                    rosary every month, was approved by Gregory XVI. (1832) and placed in charge of
                    the Dominican order by Pius IX. (1877).</p>
               <p>Similar expedients to assist the memory in repetitions of prayers occur among
                    Buddhists and Mahommedans: in the former case the prayers are said on a string
                    of some hundred beads, called the <hi rend="italic">tibet-pren-ba</hi> or the
                        <hi rend="italic">ten-wa\</hi> in the latter case,</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0725" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0778.jp2"/>
               <p>the so-called <hi rend="italic">lasbik</hi> has 33, 66 or 99 beads, and is used
                    for the repetition of the 99 names which express the attributes of God.</p>
               <p>See the critical dissertation in the <hi rend="italic">Acta sanctorum, Aug.</hi>
                    1,422 sqq ; Quetif and Eehard, <hi rend="italic">Script. Ord. Praed.</hi> i. 411
                    sqq.;. Benedict XIV olim Prospéra de Lambertini, <hi rend="italic">De festis
                        B.V.M-</hi> i. 170 sqq.; H. Holzapfel, O.F.M., 5/ <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dominikus u. der Rosenkranz</hi> (Munich, 1903); Pradel, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rosenkranz-Büchel</hi> (Trier, 1885); D. Dahm, <hi rend="italic">Die
                        Bruderschaft vom hl. Rosenkranz</hi> (Trier, 1902). For the indulgences
                    attached to the devotion consult Beringer, S.J., <hi rend="italic">Die
                        Ablässe,</hi> nthed. 292 ff., 354 ff. (Paderborn, 1895). For the
                    corresponding devotion among lluddhists, consult Waddell, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Buddhism of Tibet, or Lamaism</hi> (London, 1895), and an article by Monier
                    Williams in the <hi rend="italic">Athenaeum,</hi> 9th of Feb. 1878; for that of
                    the Mahommedans, see L Petit, <hi rend="italic">Les Confrères musulmanes</hi>
                    (Paris, 1899), and E. Arnold, <hi rend="italic">Pearls of the Faith, or Islam's
                        Rosary</hi> (London, 1882). There is an excellent article “ Rosenkranz/’ by
                    Zöekler in Herzog Hauck, <hi rend="italic">Realency-klopadie,</hi> 3rd ed. vol.
                    17, pp. 144-50. (<hi rend="smallcaps">C. H. Ha.</hi>)</p>
 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
