<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0727-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0780.jp2" type="entry">
               <p>                   <label>ROSCOMMON, WENTWORTH DILLON</label>,
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">4th Earl of (c.</hi> 1630-1685), English poet, was born in
                    Ireland about 1630. He was a nephew of Thomas Wentworth, earl of Strafford, and
                    was educated partly under a tutor at his uncle’s seat in Yorkshire, partly at
                    Caen in Normandy and partly at Rome. After the Restoration he returned to
                    England, and was well received at court. In 1649 he had succeeded to the earldom
                    of Roscommon, which had been created in 1622 for his great-grandfather, James
                    Dillon; and he was now put in possession by act of parliament of all the lands
                    possessed by his family before the Civil War. As captain of the Gentleman
                    Pensioners he found abundant opportunity to indulge the love of gambling, which
                    appears to have been his only vice. Disputes with the Lord Privy Seal about his
                    Irish estates necessitated his presence in Ireland, where he gave proof of some
                    business capacity. On his return to London he was made master of the horse to
                    the duchess of York. He was twice married, in 1662 to Lady Frances Boyle, widow
                    of Colonel Francis Courtenay, and in 1674 to Isabella Boynton.</p>               <p>His reputation as a didactic writer and critic rests on his blank verse
                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Ars Poetica</hi> (1680) and his <hi
                        rend="italic">Essay on Translated Verse</hi> (1684). The essay contained the
                    first definite enunciation of the principles of “ poetic diction,” which were to
                    be fully developed in the reign of Queen Anne. Roscommon, who was fastidious in
                    his notions of “ dignified writing,” was himself a very correct writer, and
                    quite free from the indecencies of his contemporaries. Alexander Pope, who seems
                    to have learnt something from his carefully balanced phrases and the regular
                    cadence of his verse, says that “ In all Charles’s days, Roscommon only boasts
                    unspotted bays.” He saw clearly that a low code of morals was necessarily
                    followed by a corresponding degradation in literature, and he insists that
                    sincerity and sympathy with the subject in hand are essential qualities in the
                    poet. This elevated conception of his art is in itself no small merit. He has,
                    moreover, the distinction of having been the first critic to avow his admiration
                    for <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost.</hi> Roscommon formed a small literary
                    society which he hoped to develop into an academy with authority to formulate
                    rules on language and style, but its influence only extended to a limited
                    circle, and the scheme fell through after its promoter’s death. He was buried in
                    Westminster Abbey on the 21st of January 1685.</p>               <p>The title passed to his uncle, Carey Dillon (1627-1689). In 1746, on the death
                    of James, the 8th earl, it passed to Robert Dillon (d. 1770), a descendant of
                    the first earl. His family became extinct in 1816, and in 1828 Michael James
                    Robert Dillon, another descendant of the 1st earl, established his title to the
                    earldom before the House of Lords. When he died in May 1850 it became extinct.</p>               <p>Roscommon’s poems were collected in 1701, and are included in Anderson’s and
                    other collections of the British poets. He also translated into French from the
                    English of Dr W. Sherlock, <hi rend="italic">Traitté touchant lobéissance
                        passive</hi> (1686).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
