<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0735-05"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0788.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROSES, WARS OF THE</label> a name given to a series of civil wars in
                    England during the reigns of Henry VI., Edward IV. and Richard III. Their
                    importance in the general history of England is dealt with elsewhere, and their
                    significance in the history of the art and practice of war is small. They were
                    marked by a ferocity and brutality which are practically unknown in the history
                    of English wars before and since. The honest yeoman of Edward III.’s time had
                    evolved into a professional soldier of fortune, and had been demoralized by the
                    prolonged and dismal Hundred Years’ War, at the close of which many thousands of
                    ruffians, whose occupation had gone, had been let loose in England. At the same
                    time the power of feudalism had become concentrated in the hands of a few great
                    lords who were wealthy enough and powerful enough to become king-makers. The
                    disbanded mercenaries enlisted indifferently on either side, corrupting the
                    ordinary feudal tenantry with the evil habits of the French wars, and pillaged
                    the countryside, with accompaniments of murder and violence, wherever they went.
                    It is true that the sympathies of the people at large were to some extent
                    enlisted: London and, generally, the trading towns being Yorkist, the country
                    people Lancastrian—a division of factions which roughly corresponded to that of
                    the early part of the Great Rebellion, two centuries later, and similarly in a
                    measure indicative of the opposition of hereditary loyalty and desire for sound
                    and. effective government. But there was this difference, that in the 15th
                    century the feeling of loyalty was to a great extent focused upon the great
                    lords. Each lord could depend on his own tenantry, and he could, further, pay
                    large bands of retainers. Hence, much as the citizen desired a settlement, the
                    issue was in the hands of the magnates; and as accessions to and defections from
                    one party and the other constantly shifted the balance of power, the war dragged
                    on, becoming more and more brutal with every campaign.</p>
               <p>It is from the Wars of the Roses that there originated the deep.-rooted dislike
                    of the professional soldier which was for nearly four centuries a conspicuous
                    feature of the English social and governmental system, and it is therefore in
                    their results rather than their incidents that they have affected the evolution
                    of war. They withdrew the English army system from European battlefields
                    precisely at the moment of transition when the regimental and technical
                    organization of armies was becoming a science and seeking models, and the
                    all-powerful English longbow at the moment when the early, scarcely effective
                    firearms were, so to speak, struggling for recognition as army weapons. On the
                    other hand, they destroyed the British military organization. The national army,
                    aloof from the main streams of military progress, remained for 150 years an
                    aggregation of county levies armed with bills and bows. In so far as the king
                    was permitted or able to raise armies, they were small mercenary forces formed,
                    on a basis of unemployed professionals, from pressed men and criminals, and they
                    were</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0736" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0789.jp2"/>
               <p>disbanded as soon as the brief occasion for their services had passed.</p>
               <p>The first campaign, or rather episode, of these wars <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> The name, as is well known, comes
                        from the “ white rose of York ” and the “ red rose of Lancaster ” ; but
                        these badges, though more or less recognized as party distinctions, by no
                        means superseded the private devices of the various great lords, such as the
                        “falcon and fetterlock ” of Richard duke of York, the “ rose in sun ’’ of
                        Edward IV., the “ crowned swan ” of Margaret, the Vere star, and even the
                        revived “ white hart ” of Richard II. </note> began with an armed demand of
                    the Yorkist lords for the dismissal of the Lancastrian element in the king’s
                    council, Henry VI. himself being incapable of governing. The Lancastrians, and
                    the king with them, marched out of London to meet them, and the two small armies
                    (3000 Yorkists, 2000 Lancastrians) met at St Albans (May 22, 1455). The
                    encounter ended with the dispersion of the weaker force, and the king fell into
                    the hands of the Yorkists. Four years passed before the next important battle,
                    Blore Heath, was fought (Sept. 23, 1459). In this the earl of Salisbury trapped
                    a Lancastrian army in unfavourable ground near Market Drayton, and destroyed it;
                    but new political combinations rendered the Yorkist victory useless and sent the
                    leaders of the party into exile. They made a fresh attempt in 1460, and, thanks
                    partly to treason in the Lancastrian camp, partly to the generalship of Warwick,
                    won an important success and for the second time seized the king at Northampton
                    (July 10, 1460). Shortly afterwards, after a period of negotiation and threats,
                    there was a fresh conflict. <hi rend="underline">Richard</hi> duke of York went
                    north to fight the hostile army which gathered at York and consisted of
                    Lancashire and Midland Royalists, while his son Edward, earl of March, went into
                    the west. The father was ambushed and killed at Wakefield (Dec. 30, 1460), and
                    the Lancastrians, inspired as always by Queen Margaret of Anjou, moved south on
                    London, defeated Warwick at St Albans (Feb. 17, 1461), and regained possession
                    of the king’s person. But the young earl of M <hi rend="underline">arc</hi> h,
                    now duke of York, having raised an army in the west,"defeated the earl of
                    Pembroke (Feb. 2, 1461) at Mortimer’s Cross (5 m. W. of Leominster). This was
                    the first battle of the war which was characterized by the massacre of the
                    common folk and beheading of the captive gentlemen— invariable accompaniments of
                    Edward’s victories, and conspicuously absent in Warwick’s. Edward then pressed
                    on, joined Warwick, and entered London, the army of Margaret retreating before
                    them. The excesses of the northern Lancastrians in their advance produced bitter
                    fruit on the retreat, for men flocked to Edward’s standard. Marching north in
                    pursuit, the Yorkists brought their enemy to bay at Towton <hi rend="italic"
                        >(q.v.),</hi> 3 m. S. of Tadcaster, and utterly destroyed them (March 29,
                    1461). For three years after Towton the war consisted merely of desultory local
                    struggles of small bodies of Lancastrians against the inevitable. The duke of
                    York had become King Edward IV., and had established himself firmly. But in
                    1464, in the far north of England, the Red Rose was again in the field. Edward
                    acted with his usual decision. His lieutenant Montagu (Warwick’s brother)
                    defeated and slew Sir Ralph Percy at Hedgley Aloor, near Wooler (April 25,
                    1464), and immediately afterwards destroyed another Lancastrian army, with which
                    were both Henry VI. and Queen Margaret, at Hexham (Alay 8, 1464). The massacres
                    and executions</p>
               <p>which followed effectively crushed the revolt. For some years thereafter Edward
                    reigned peacefully, but Warwick the king-maker and all the Neville following
                    having turned against him (1470), he was driven into exile. But at a favourable
                    moment he sailed from Flushing with 1500 retainers and Burgundian mercenaries,
                    and eluding the Lancastrian fleet and the coast defence troops, landed at
                    Ravenspur (Spurn Head) in Yorkshire in March 1471. His force was hardly more
                    than a bodyguard; the gates of the towns were shut against him, and the country
                    people fled. But by his personal charm, diplomacy, fair promises and an oath of
                    allegiance to King Henry VI., sworn solemnly at York, he disarmed hostility and,
                    eluding Montagu’s army, reached his own estates in the Wakefield district, where
                    many of his old retainers joined him. As he advanced south, a few Yorkist nobles
                    with their following rallied to him, but it was far more the disunion of the
                    Warwick and the real Lancastrian parties than his own strength which enabled him
                    to meet Warwick’s forces in a pitched battle. At Bamet, on Easter Eve, April 14,
                    1471, the decisive engagement was fought. But in the midst of the battle
                    reinforcements coming up under the earl of Oxford to join Warwick came into
                    conflict with their own party, the badge of the Vere star being mistaken for
                    Edward’s <hi rend="italic">Rose-en-soleil.</hi> From that point all the mutually
                    distrustful elements of Warwick’s army fell apart, and Warwick himself, with his
                    brother Montagu, was slain. For the last time the unhappy Henry VI. fell into
                    the hands of his enemies. He was relegated to the Tower, and Edward, disbanding
                    his army, reoccupied the throne. But Margaret of Anjou, his untiring opponent,
                    who had been in France while her cause and Warwick’s was being lost, had landed
                    in the west shortly after Barnet, and Edward had to take the field at once.
                    Assembling a fresh army at Windsor, whence he could march to interpose between
                    Margaret and her north Welsh allies, or directly bar her road to London, he
                    marched into the west on the 24th of April. On the 29th he was at Ciiencester,
                    Margaret, engaged chiefly in recruiting an army, near Bath. Edward hurried on,
                    but Margaret eluded him and marched for Gloucester. At that place the governor
                    refused the Lancastrians admittance, and seeking to cross the Severn out of
                    reach of the Yorkists, they pushed on by forced marches to Tewkesbury. But
                    Edward too knew how to march, and caught them up. The battle of Tewkesbury (May
                    4,1471) ended with the destruction of Margaret’s force, the captivity of
                    Margaret, the death of her son Edward (who, it is sometimes said, was stabbed by
                    Edward IV. himself after the battle) and the execution of sixteen of the
                    principal Lancastrians.</p>
               <p>This was Edward’s last battle. The rest of his eventful reign was similar in
                    many ways to that of his contemporary Louis XI., being devoted to the
                    consolidation of his power, by fair means and foul, at the expense of the great
                    feudatories. But the Wars of the Roses were not yet at an end. For fourteen
                    years, except for local outbreaks, the land had peace, and then Richard III.’s
                    crown, struck from his head on Bosworth Field (Aug. 22, 1485), was presented to
                    Henry earl of Richmond, who, as Henry VII., established the kingship on a secure
                    foundation. A last feeble attempt to renew the war, made by an army gathered to
                    uphold the pretender Lambert Simnel, was crushed by Henry VII. at Stoke Field (4
                    m. S.W. of Newark) on the 16th of June 1487.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
