<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0729-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0782.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROSE</label>
                    <hi rend="italic">(Rosa).</hi> The rose has for all ages been the favourite
                    flower, and as such it has a place in general literature that no other plant can
                    rival. In most cases the rose of the poets and the rose of the botanist are one
                    and the same in kind, but popular usage has attached the name rose to a variety
                    of plants whose kinship to the true plant no botanist would for a moment admit.
                    In this place we shall employ the word in its strict botanical significance, and
                    in commenting on it treat it solely from the botanical point of view. The rose
                    gives its name to the order Rosaceae, of which it may be considered the type.
                    The genus consists of species varying in number, according to the diverse
                    opinions of botanists of opposite schools, from thirty to one hundred and
                    eighty, or even two hundred and fifty, exclusive of the many hundreds of mere
                    garden varieties. While the lowest estimate is doubtless too low, the highest is
                    enormously too large, but in any case the wide discrepancies above alluded to
                    illustrate very forcibly the extreme variability of the plants, their
                    adaptability to various conditions, and consequently their wide dispersion over
                    the globe, the facility with which they are cultivated, and the readiness 'with
                    which new varieties are continually being produced in gardens by the art of the
                    hybridizer or the careful selection of the raiser. The species are natives of
                    all parts of the northern hemisphere, but are scantily represented in the
                    tropics unless at considerable elevations.</p>
               <p>They are erect or climbing shrubs, never herbs or trees, generally more or less
                    copiously provided with straight or hooked prickles of various shapes and with
                    glandular hairs, as in the sweet-brier or in the moss-rose of gardens. The
                    prickles serve the purpose of enabling the shrub to sustain itself amid other
                    vegetation. The viscid hairs which are specially frequent on the flower stalks
                    or in the neighbourhood of the flower serve to arrest the progress of
                    undesirable visitants, while the perfume emitted by the glands in question may
                    co-operate with the fragrance and colour of the flower to attract those insects
                    whose presence is desirable. The leaves are invariably alternate, provided with
                    stipules, and unequally pinnate, the leaflets varying in number from one (as in
                        <hi rend="italic">R. simplici-folia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">berberi
                        folia}</hi> to 11 and even 15, the odd leaflet always being at the apex, the
                    others in pairs. The flowers are solitary or in loose cymes (eluster-roses)
                    produced on the ends of the snoots. The flower-stalk expands into a vase- or
                    urn-shaped dilatation, called the receptacle or receptacular tube, which
                    ultimately becomes fleshy and encloses in its cavity the numerous carpels or
                    fruits. From the edge of the urn or “ hip !’ proceed five sepals, often more or
                    less compound like the leaves and overlapping in the bud. Within the sepals are
                    five petals, generally broad or roundish in outline, with a very short stalk or
                    none at all, and of very various shades of white, yellow or red. The very
                    numerous stamens originate slightly above the sepals and petals; each has a
                    slender filament and a small two-celled anther. The inner portion of the
                    receptacular tube whence the stamens spring is thick and fleshy, and is
                    occasionally spoken of as the “ disk but, as in this case it does not represent
                    any separate organ, it is better <hi rend="italic">to</hi> avoid the use of the
                    term. The carpels are very numerous, ultimately hard in texture, covered with
                    hairs, and each provided with a long style and button-like stigma. The carpels
                    are concealed within the receptacular tube and only the stigmas as a rule
                    protrude from its mouth. Each carpel contains one ovule. The so-called fruit is
                    merely the receptacular tube, which, as previously mentioned, becomes fleshy and
                    brightly coloured as an attraction to birds, which devour the hips and thus
                    secure the dispersion of the seed. The dry one-seeaed fruits (achenes) are
                    densely packed inside the hip, and are covered with stiff hairs which cling to
                    the bird’s beak. The stamens are in whorls, and, according to Payer, they
                    originate in pairs one on each side of the base of</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0730" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0783.jp2"/>
               <p>each petal so that there are ten in each row; a second row of ten alternates
                    with the first, a third with the second, and so on. By repeated radial and
                    tangential branching a vast number of stamens are ultimately produced, and when
                    these stamens assume a petaloid aspect we have as a consequence the double
                    flowers which are so much admired. The carpels are much less subject to this
                    petaloid change, and, as it generally happens in the most double of roses that
                    some few at least of the anthers are formed with pollen, the production of seed
                    and the possibility of cross-breeding become intelligible. Under natural
                    circumstances rose flowers do not secrete honey, the attraction for insects
                    being provided bv the colour and perfume and the abundance of pollen for food. I
                    he stigmas and anthers come to maturity at the same time, and thus, while
                    cross-fertilization by insect agency is doubtless most common,
                    self-fertilization is not prevented.</p>
               <p>The large number of species, subspecies, varieties and forms described as
                    British may be included under about a dozen species. Among them may be mentioned
                    2?. <hi rend="italic">spinosissima,</hi> the Scotch rose, much less variable
                    than the others; <hi rend="italic">R. rubiginosa</hi> (or <hi rend="italic">R.
                        eglantcria),</hi> the sweet-brier, represented by several varieties; <hi
                        rend="italic">R. canina</hi> , the dog rose (see fig.)» including</p>
               <p>numerous subspecies and varieties; the large-fruited apple rose,</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">R. pomífera;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">R. arvensis,</hi> the
                    parent of the Ayrshire roses. Cultivated roses are frequently “ buddecj ” or
                    worked upon the stems of the brier or <hi rend="italic">R. canina,</hi> or upon
                    young seedling plants of the same species; and upon stems of an Italian rose
                    called the Manetti, raised in the Milan Botanic Gardens about 1837. Other
                    species, notably <hi rend="italic">R. polyantha,</hi> also are used for stocks.</p>
               <p>Roses have been grown for so many centuries and have been crossed and recrossed
                    so often that it is difficult to refer the cultivated forms to their wild
                    prototypes. The older roses doubtless originated from <hi rend="italic">R.
                        gallica,</hi> a native of central and southern Europe. <hi rend="italic">R.
                        centifolia</hi> (the cabbage rose), a native of the Caucasus, contributed
                    its share. A cross between the two species named.may have been the source whence
                    originated the Bourbon roses. The yellow-flowered Austrian and Persian brier
                    originated from <hi rend="italic">R. lútea,</hi> a native of Austria and the
                    East. The monthly or China roses sprang from the Chinese <hi rend="italic">R.
                        Índica,</hi> and these, crossed with others of the <hi rend="italic">R.
                        centifolia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gallica</hi> type, are the source of
                    the <hi rend="sup">a</hi> hybrid perpetuáis ” so commonly grown nowadays,
                    because, in addition to their other attractions, their blooming season is
                    relatively prolonged, and, moreover, is repeated in the autumn. Tea roses and
                    noisettes, it is to be presumed, also acknowledge <hi rend="italic">R.
                        indica</hi> as one of their progenitors.. A magnificent race called “hybrid
                    teas” have been evolved of late years, by crossing the tea roses and hybrid
                    perpetuáis. They are much more vigorous in constitution than the true tea roses,
                    while quite as beautiful in blossom and more perpetual in bloom than the hybrid
                    perpetuáis. Recently, by crossing the Japanese <hi rend="italic">R.
                        Wichuraiana</hi> with hybrid perpetuáis, a beautiful and vigorous race of
                    climbers has been produced. The Banksian rose is a Chinese ^limbing species,
                    with small white or fawn-coloured flowers of great beauty, but rarely seen; the
                    Macartney rose (2?. <hi rend="italic">bracteata)</hi> is also of Chinese origin.
                    Its nearly evergreen deep green leaves and large white flowers are very
                    striking. The Japanese <hi rend="italic">R. rugosa</hi> is also a remarkable
                    species, notable for its bold rugose foliage, its large white or pink flowers,
                    and its conspicuous globular fruit. <hi rend="italic">R. damascena</hi> is
                    cultivated in some parts of the Balkans for the purpose of making attar of
                    roses. In Germany the same variety of rose is used, while at Grasse a strain of
                    the Provence rose is cultivated for the same purpose. In India <hi rend="italic"
                        >R. damascena</hi> is grown largely near Ghazipur for the purpose of
                    procuring attar of roses and rose water.</p>
               <p>Rose water is chiefly produced in Europe from the Provence or cabbage rose, <hi
                        rend="italic">R. centifolia,</hi> grown for the purpose at Mitcham and much
                    more abundantly in the south of-France. Conserve of roses and infusion of roses,
                    two medicinal preparations retained for their agreeable qualities rather than
                    for any special virtue, are prepared from the petals of <hi rend="italic">R.
                        gallica,</hi> one variety of which was formerly grown for the purpose near
                    the town of Provins. Conserve of dog rose is made from the ripe hips of the dog
                    rose, <hi rend="italic">R. canina.</hi> Its only use is in the manufacture of
                    pills.</p>
               <p>The rose is so universal a favourite that some portion of the garden must
                    necessarily be devoted to it, if the situation be at all favourable. Many choice
                    roses will not, however, thrive in the vicinity of large towns, since they
                    require a pure air, and do not endure a smoky atmosphere. The best, soil for
                    them is a deep rich strong loam free from stagnant moisture. Very light sandy or
                    gravelly soils, or soils which are clayey and badly drained, are not suitable,
                    and both must be greatly improved if rose-growing on them is attempted. Light
                    soils would be improved by a dressing of strong loam in conjunction with
                    cow-dung or nightsoil; the latter, provided it is properly prepared and not too
                    fresh, is indeed the very best manure for roses in all but soils which are
                    naturally very rich. Heavy soils are improved by adding burned earth or gritty
                    refuse, with stable manure and leaf-mould, peat moss litter, &amp;c. ; and
                    damp soils must necessarily be drained by trenching. Tea roses may, however, be
                    grown to perfection in a gravel soil, provided it be well manured, cow manure
                    being best. Roses generally require a constant annual supply of manure, and, if
                    this is given as a mulching in autumn, it serves to protect their roots through
                    the winter. They also require liberal supplies of water during the growing
                    season, unless the surface is mulched or top-dressed from time to time with
                    well-rotted manure. Aphides and caterpillars of all kinds may be checked by
                    syringing with dilute tobacco water or some of the many insecticides now
                    provided to facilitate this rather troublesome task.</p>
               <p>Some growers prefer roses grown on their own roots, some on the Manetti and
                    others on the brier stock. There is this to be said in favour of their own roots
                    that, if the tops are killed down by accident or by severe weather, the roots
                    will usually throw up new shoots true to their kind, which cannot be looked for
                    if they are worked ; though it is sometimes recommended to plant deep in order
                    that the rose itself may learn to do without its foster parent the stock. Too
                    often, however, in the case of persons unfamiliar with roses, the choice rose
                    dies, and the stock usurps its place. This is especially true of the Manetti
                    stock, as its foliage is more like that of many cultivated forms than the brier,
                    and therefore more easily overlooked. Where standards or half-standards are
                    required, the brier stock from the hedges is always used. It forms the most
                    reliable stock for dwarfs of all kinds, and especially for tea roses, most of
                    which fail on the Manetti stock.</p>
               <p>An open situation, not shaded but sheltered from strong winds, is what the rose
                    prefers. October and November are the best months for planting roses, but if the
                    weather be wet or frosty and the soil sticky, the plants should be placed in a
                    sheltered place and protected by green boughs or matting until suitable
                    conditions prevail. The planting should never be deep, the uppermost layer of
                    roots being about J or 3 in. below the general level of the surface, and the
                    soil should always be kept stirred with the hoe during the summer months. In
                    regard to pruning, roses vary considerably, some requiring close cutting and
                    others only thinning out; some again, such as strong growing climbers, may be
                    safely pruned in autumn, and others are better left till spring. Instructions on
                    this point as to the several groups of varieties will be found in most rose
                    catalogues, and may be followed, provided the variety is true to name. It may.be
                    laid down as a general rule that the more strongly growing varieties should be
                    less severely cut back than the weakly varieties; and, again, the more tender
                    the variety, the later in the spring should the pruning be done, April being the
                    best month for pruning teas and noisettes. It should be remembered also that no</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0731" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0784.jp2"/>
               <p>amount of correct pruning will improve a rose bush that has been badly planted
                    or placed in a quite unsuitable position.</p>
               <p>Where dwarf beds of roses are required, a good plan is to peg down to within
                    about 6 in. from the ground the strong one-year-old shoots from the root. In due
                    time blooming shoots break out from nearly every eye, and masses of flowers are
                    secured, while strong young shoots are thrown up from, the centre, the plant
                    being on its own roots. Before winter sets in, the old shoots which have thus
                    flowered and exhausted themselves, are cut away, and three or four or more of
                    the strongest and best ripened young shoots are reserved for pegging down the
                    following season, which should be done about February, fn the meantime, after
                    the pruning, has been effected, plenty of good manure should have been dug in
                    lightly about the roots. Thus treated, the plants never fail to produce plenty
                    of strong wood for pegging down each succeeding season.</p>
               <p>The most troublesome fungoid pest of the rose is undoubtedly the mildew <hi
                        rend="italic">(Sphaerotheca pannosa).</hi> The young shoots, leaves ana
                    flower-buds frequently become covered with a delicate white mycelium, which by
                    means of the suckers it sends into the underlying cells robs its host of
                    considerable amounts of food, and causes the leaves to curl and fall early. The
                    spores are produced in great abundance and carried by animals and the wind to
                    other plants, and so the disease is rapidly spread. Later the mycelium increases
                    and forms a thick velvety coating on the young shoots, and in this.the winter
                    state of the fungus is produced. . Spraying with potassium sulphide (i oz. to 2
                    to 3 gallons of water) is the best means of checking the spread of the disease.
                    The rose rust <hi rend="italic">(Phragmidium sub-corticatum)</hi> appears on
                    both cultivated and wild roses in the spring, bursting through the bark in the
                    form of copious masses of orange powder consisting of the spores of the fungus.
                    These spores infect the leaves, and produce on them in the summer small.dots of
                    an orange colour and, later, groups of spores that are able to live through the
                    winter. The last, the teleutospores, are of a dark colour, and it is by these
                    that the disease is started in the spring. It is therefore important that all
                    the affected leaves should be destroyed in the autumn, and the bushes should be
                    sprayed with Bordeaux mixture or ammoniacal copper carbonate in the spring to
                    prevent the infection of the leaves by spores brought from a distance. Many
                    other fungi attack the rose, but perhaps the only other one that merits mention
                    here is <hi rend="italic">Actinonema Rosae.</hi> This attacks the leaves,
                    forming large dark blotches upon them and frequently causing them to fall
                    prematurely.</p>
               <p>A very large number of insect pests are found upon the rose, but the best known
                    and most formidable on account of their great powers of reproduction are the
                    aphides. More than one species is found upon the rose, though <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aphis Rosae</hi> is the commonest. Their attack should be checked by the
                    use of a spray made by boiling 4 oz. quassia.chips for an hour or so in a gallon
                    of soft water, straining off the solution and dissolving therein 4 oz. of soft
                    soap while it is still warm, afterwards adding 1 or 2 gallons of soft water
                    according to the age of the rose leaves that are to be sprayed. Any delay in
                    dealing with the pest gives the opportunity for its increase, even a day being
                    sufficient materially to augment their numbers. The larvae of some of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Tortrix</hi> moths fola the leaves almost as soon as they arc
                    developed from the bud, and do considerable damage in this way and by devouring
                    the leaves, while several ” looper ” caterpillars are also found feeding on the
                    foliage. Many species of saw-fly larvae are also known to attack the rose,
                    feeding either upon the leaves or devouring the young shoot. These larvae should
                    be carefully searched for and destroyed whenever found. One of the leaf-cutting
                    bees, <hi rend="italic">Megachile,</hi> cuts pieces out of the leaves with which
                    to line its nest, materially reducing their effective surface. The bees may be
                    caught in a butterfly net or traced to their nests, which should be destroyed.</p>
               <p>For further information see the late Dean Hole’s <hi rend="italic">Book about
                        Roses</hi> (1894); <hi rend="italic">Book of the Rose,</hi> by Rev. A.
                    Foster Mellias (1905); <hi rend="italic">Beautiful Roses for Garden and
                        Greenhouse,</hi> by J. Weathers (1903); and <hi rend="italic">Roses, their
                        History, Development and Cultivation,</hi> by the Rev. J. H. Pemberton
                    (1908).</p>
 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
