<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>trade in hardware being especially large. Among its manufactures are agricultural machinery (especially seeding machines) and tools, automobiles, pianos, lawn-mowers, roller-skates, foundry and machine-shop products, furniture, burial caskets, and flour. In 1905 its factory product was valued at $6,731,740, an increase of 41-6% since 1900. Pipe lines supply the city with natural gas. The municipality owns and operates the electric lighting  plant. In 1806 Friends from North Carolina and Pennsylvania settled near here, and Richmond was platted in 1816. Its growth was slow until the opening of the National Road, which entered Indiana near the city, and the construction of railways. Richmond was incorporated as a village in 1818 and chartered as a borough in 1834 and as a city in 1840.</p><p>RICHMOND, a city and the county-seat of Madison county, Kentucky, U.S.A., about 95 m. S.E. of Louisville. Pop. (1890) 5073; (1900) 4653, of whom 2087 were negroes; (1910) 5340. It is served by the Louisville &amp; Atlantic and the Louisville &amp; Nashville railways. It is situated in the “ Blue Grass Region/ near the foothills of the Cumberland Mountains. It is the seat of Madison Institute for girls (1856) and of the Eastern Kentucky State Normal School (1906). From 1874 to 1901 it was the seat of Central University, which in the latter year was consolidated with Centre College at Danville, Ky. (q.v.). The surrounding country is devoted largely to the cultivation of tobacco, Indian corn and wheat, and the breeding of fine horses and cattle; and Richmond is an important live-stock market. Among the manufactures are bricks, flour, tobacco and cigars, and carriages. On the 30th of August 1862 a Confederate force of about 7000 men under General Edmund Kirby Smith won a decisive victory here over a Union force of a nearly equal number under Generals Mahlon D. Manson (1820-1895) and William Nelson.</p><p>RICHMOND, a municipal borough in the Kingston parliamentary division of Surrey, England, 9 m. W.S.W. of Charing Cross, London. Pop. (1891) 26,875; (1901) 31,672. It lies on the right bank of the Thames, which is here crossed by a bridge carrying the road to Twickenham. Through its pleasant situation Richmond has grown into a large residential suburb of the metropolis. The town was anciently called <hi rend="italic">Syenes</hi>  and afterwards <hi rend="italic">Schene</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Sheen</hi>  (a name preserved in the village of East Sheen, adjacent on the London side) until the name was in 1500 changed to Richmond by command of Henry VII., who was earl of Richmond in Yorkshire. It grew up round the royal manor house, which became a frequent residence of sovereigns, but of which nothing more than a gateway remains. Edward I. received the Scotch commissioners at his manor of Sheen in 1300. The palace was rebuilt by Edward III., who died here in 1377. It was frequently used by Richard II., and here his wife Anne of Bohemia died, upon which he cursed the place and “ caused it to be thrown down and defaced.” By Henry V., however, it was rebuilt, and a great tournament was held here in 1492 by Henry VII., who after its destruction by fire in 1498 restored it. Henry VIII. gave it to Wolsey to reside in, after the latter presented him with the new palace of Hampton Court. James I. settled it on his son Henry, prince of Wales, who restored and embellished it at great expense. Charles I. added to it the new deer park generally known as Richmond Park, 2253 acres in extent, which is surrounded by a wall 11 m. in length. After the execution of the king, the parliament presented the park to the citizens of London, who again presented it to Charles II. at the Restoration. Though partly dismantled, the palace was the residence of the queen dowager till 1665, and by James II. it was used as a nursery for the young prince; but, gradually falling into decay, it was parcelled into tenements about 1720. In the old deer park extending northwards from the site of the palace, Kew Observatory was erected in 1769, occupying the site of a Carthusian convent founded by Henry V., and a dwelling-house in which Swift for some time resided. The White Lodge was built by George I., and has been a residence of various members of the royal family. To the south-east of the town, at the entrance to Richmond Park, is Richmond Hill, from which is seen a famous view of the Thames with the surrounding country to the west. This view was secured to the public by an agreement, sealed on the 7th of February 1896, between the corporation and the trustees of the earl of Dysart, by an act of Parliament of 1902, and by the acquisition in the same year, by the London County Council, with the assistance of the borough of Richmond and other interested local authorities, of the Marble Hill Estate and other property on the Middlesex shore. The church of St Mary Magdalen is of considerable antiquity, but almost entirely rebuilt; it contains a large number of monuments to celebrated persons. A theatre, first established in 1719, was during his later years leased by Edmund Kean. The town has a Wesleyan theological college, founded in 1834. Richmond, which was incorporated in 1890, is governed by a mayor, 10 aldermen and 30 councillors. The borough includes Kew <hi rend="italic">Cq.v.},</hi>  Petersham and North Sheen. Area, 2491 acres.</p><p>RICHMOND, a market town and municipal borough in the Richmond parliamentary division of the North Riding of Yorkshire, England, 50 m. N.W. from York, the terminus of a branch of the North-Eastern railway. Pop. (1901) 3837. It is finely ‘situated on the left bank of the Swale, the valley of which is narrow and the banks steep. The interest of the town centres in the castle founded about 1071 by Alan Rufus, a son of Odo, count of Penthièvre in Brittany, who is also said to have rebuilt the town on obtaining from William the Conqueror, among other possessions, the estates of the Saxon earl Edwin, embracing some two hundred manors of Richmond and extending over nearly a third of the North Riding. This tract, comprising five wapentakes, was called Richmondshire at this time, but the date of the creation of the shire is uncertain. When Henry VII. came to the throne these possessions reverted to the crown. Henry VIII. gave them to his son Henry, afterwards duke of Richmond, by a daughter of Sir John Blount, and Charles II. bestowed the title of duke of Richmond on his son by the duchess of Portsmouth. The castle is situated on a perpendicular rock rising about 100 ft. above the Swale, and from its great strength was considered impregnable. Originally it covered an area of 5 acres, but the only portions of it remaining are the Norman keep, with pinnacled tower and walls 100 ft. high by 11 ft. thick, and some other smaller towers. The view from the keep is very fine, extending westward up the bold valley and Overthehillswhich wallit, and eastward over the rich plain of the centre of the county. The church of St Mary is transitional Norman, Decorated and Perpendicular, and is largely restored. The church of the Holy Trinity retains only the nave and the detached tower. The building is ancient but was restored to use from ruins. Close to the town are ruins of Easby Abbey, a Premonstratensian foundation by Roald, constable of Richmond Castle in 1152, beautifully situated by the river. The remains, which are considerable, include a Decorated gateway, an Early English chapel and fragments of the transepts and choir of the church, with sufficient portions of the domestic buildings to enable the complete plan to be traced. For the free grammar-school founded by Elizabeth a Gothic building was erected in 1850, in memory of the Rev. James Tate, a former master. The tower of a Franciscan abbey founded in 1258 remains. The chief modem buildings are the town hall, market hall and ‘the mechanics’ institute. The principal trade is in agricultural produce, but there are a paper mill and an iron and brass foundry. An annual meeting is held on the racecourse in September. In 1889 Richmond became the seat of a suffragan bishop in the diocese of Ripon. The town is governed by a mayor, 4 aldermen and 12 councillors. Area, 2520 acres.</p><p>The nameof Richmond (<hi rend="italic">Richemont, Richemund)</hi>  has not been traced further back than 1145 But it is probable that there was a settlement on the site of the present town before that date. Possibly it was the Hindrelaghe of the Domesday Survey, a place which, although large enough to have a church in 1086, appears to have vanished before the close of the 12th century. As far as is known the earliest charter was granted in 1145. But a later charter (1146) shows that the burgesses had enjoyed some municipal</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>