<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>same type as the jibs can be set on the stays between the masts of a fully rigged ship, and are then known as staysails. But it can only be repeated that the variations are innumerable. Studding;sails are pieces added to increase the breadth (spread) of sails, and require the support of special yards, booms and tackle.</p><p>The development of the rigging of ships is a very obscure subject. It was the work of centuries, and of practical men who wrote no treatises. It has never been universal. A comparison of the four - masted junk given above with</p><p>the figures of ships on medieval seals shows at least much similarity. Yet by selecting a few leading types of successive periods it is possible to follow </p><p>the growth of the fully rigged ship, at least in its main lines, in modern</p><p>times.</p><p>Fig· 8 gives the sail plan of the “ Santa Maria,” the flagship of Columbus. lt is a modern reconstruction, made in 1893 in Spain at the Carraca arsenal, but is based on good authority.</p><p>She has only the fixed bowsprit, with a yard and a sail hanging from it, the Spritsail yard and spritsail.</p><p>The foremast has one course, the mainmast a course and topsail, the mizzen a Jateen sail. Fig. 9 is the “ Sovereign of the Seas,” a British warship of 1637, She still has only the fixed bowsprit, but a small upright mast has been erected at the end, which serves to spread a sprit topsail. In some cases at least a sprit topgallant sail was used. The mizzenmast still carries a lateen sail, but topsails have been added, and the whole rigging has multiplied and developed. Between the “ Sovereign of the Seas ” and the fully developed ship given in fig. 1 the most apparent differences are in the rigging of the bowsprit and the mizzenmast. The sprit topmast has disappeared, and is replaced</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>