<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Statute of 1432 <hi rend="italic">de Odmissione ad pelluram).</hi> Students, and even
                doctors in theology <hi rend="italic">(Mun. Acad.</hi> ü. 393), were also
                restricted to budge, and to sad-coloured habits. The robes of masters were to be
                flowing and reach to the ankles (see <hi rend="italic">Mun. Acad. </hi>p. 212, an
                order of 1358 to the tailors not to stint the robes, which should be “ <hi
                    rend="italic">largae et Ialaresf<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi> because clerks should
                be distinguished from the laity).</p>
            <p>The Cope, worn as part of academic dress over the gown, probably originated in the
                ordinary <hi rend="italic">cappa clericalis,</hi> or everyday mantle of the clergy,
                which had been introduced into general use in England by synods of 1222, 1237 and
                    1268.@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>This kind of cope, closed in front, and originally
                black in colour, is generally known as the<hi rend="italic">cappa clausa,</hi> and
                sometimes, for convenience’ sake, had a slit in front to allow of the passage of the
                hands. It was worn by Regent Masters when lecturing</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">{Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 421) and as a full dress by certain doctors. By
                the second half of the 14th century differences of colour occur; <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.g.</hi> the Chancellor represented in a 14th-century miniature in the Oxford
                    <hi rend="italic">Chancellors Book</hi> (reproduced by J. W. Wells, <hi
                    rend="italic">The Oxford Degree Ceremony</hi> (1906), facing p. 19) wears a
                scarlet cope closed in front, lined with miniver and with tippet and hood of
                miniver, and there is also a mention in an ancient statute of Cambridge of a red
                cope worn by Inceptors in Canon Law (Clark, p. 102). The Rev. N. F. Robinson <hi
                    rend="italic">(loc. cit.</hi> p. 195) quotes the will of R. Browne, archdeacon
                of Rochester (d. 1452), to prove that the habit of a doctor of civil law was
                violet; he also thinks that that of a doctor of theology was green, and of a doctor
                of canon law scarlet. By the 16th century all copes were scarlet. Clark (p. 138)
                gives as evidence “ Stokys<hi rend="sup">i</hi> picture ” in the Cambridge
                Registrary. The scarlet<hi rend="italic">cappa clausa</hi> has survived to the
                present day at Cambridge as the dress worn by the Vice-Chancellor and by Regius
                Professors of Divinity, Law and Medicine when presenting for degrees. It is now
                open down the front, but the fur edging only reaches half-way down, marking the
                place where the slit used to be. At Oxford the so-called “ cope ” which is the
                Convocation robe of certain doctors is not a real cope, but is probably derived from
                the medieval tabard, the out-of-door dress worn by the clergy and others, it having
                become customary by the beginning of the 16th century for Regent Masters to wear the
                tabard at lectures as more convenient than the cope (Rashdall, II. ii. 639, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 421, where the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi>
                is spoken of as an alternative to the <hi rend="italic">cappa clausa.</hi> The <hi
                    rend="italic">pallium</hi> is most probably to be Identified with theta
                    bard).@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The<hi rend="italic">capa manicala</hi> mentioned
                in Anstey <hi rend="italic">(Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 421, &amp;c.) seems to have been a
                shorter gown with bell-shaped sleeves reaching to the elbow, and lined with fur,
                worn by masters and bachelors of arts (see Druitt, p. 124), and a shorter tabard is
                also occasionally found (Robinson’s <hi rend="italic">Tabcrdum ad medias
                    tibias).</hi> These are illustrated in fig. 6 from a MS. of the 15th century at
                New College, Oxford.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The D.D.’s wear the<hi rend="italic"
                    >cappa clausa,</hi> the other doctors tabards (see also pi. iii., xvi. in <hi
                    rend="italic">Archaeologia,</hi> where William of Wykeham and all the doctors
                wear long sweeping tabards, as ample as copes), the Warden a shorter tabard,
                reaching just below the knees, and the M.A.’s gowns or tabards with false
                sleeves.</p>
            <p>The Hood was originally worn by all scholars, as by everybody, and had evidently no
                academic significance. Sometimes a cap was also worn, the hood being thrown back
                (Chaucer’s “ clerk of Oxenford ” in the Ellesmere MS. illumination wears a red
                skull-cap, and a furred tippet and hood, with the hood falling rather back, though
                not on his shoulders). The liripipe<hi rend="sup">4 </hi>became somewhat elongated,
                as is seen in the hoods of the so-called M.A. group in the Chandler MS. An early
                mention of the undergraduate hood is the much-discussed Oxford Statute of 1489<hi
                    rend="italic">(Mun. Acad.</hi> p. 360), which reads: “ ut nullus de cetero
                scholaris non-graduatus (nobiH sanguine insignitis &amp;c. exceptis) capitio quovis
                utatur pubhce. .. nisi liripipium consutum habeat et non contextum, prout antiqua
                Universitatis IaudabiHs consuetudo exposcit...”@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> but the
                undergraduate</p>
            <p>@@@ See Rev. T. A. Lacey in<hi rend="italic">Transactions of the St Paul’s
                    Ecclesio-logical Society,</hi> vol. iv. (1900), p. 128, &amp;c. Also Rev. N. F.
                Robinson in the same (1898), pp. 181-220.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@ Clark (pp. 138-39) treats of the<hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> and tabard as two
                separate garments, deciding that the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> was a kind of
                tippet. Robinson considers the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> to correspond to the
                tabard, his <hi rend="italic">labordum talare,</hi> which the Rev. T. A. Lacey (p.
                128) also compares with the chimere of Anglican bishops. (See article Chimere<hi
                    rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sub">1</hi></hi> where the chimere is likewise traced
                to the tabard.) Moroni, <hi rend="italic">Dizionario delF erudizione
                    storica-ecclesiastica,</hi> s.v. <hi rend="italic">zimarra,</hi> says that
                professors of the university of Rome wear black <hi rend="italic">zimarrc</hi> while
                teaching. This recalls the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> of Regent Masters <hi
                    rend="italic">(Mum Acad.</hi> p. 421) and Inceptors in arts and medicine <hi
                    rend="italic">(id.</hi> p. 430).</p>
            <p>@@@ The Chandler MS. The drawings from which the illustration is taken are reproduced
                in the<hi rend="italic">Transactions of the St Paul’s Ecclesio-logical Society,</hi>
                p. 208, with an explanatory article by the Rev. N. F. Robinson, and in <hi
                    rend="italic">Archaeologia,</hi> vol. liii. pl. i., with notes by T. F. Kirby.
                Robinson identifies the various groups of the Society of New College on his plate i.
                (xv. in <hi rend="italic">Arehaeol.)</hi> by the aid of a statute of the College
                settling the order of standing in choir and at processions, and thus claims to
                settle the question of the dress of the various kinds of Doctor and Bachelor,
                M.A.’s, &amp;c., at the period.</p>
            <p>@@@4 In the present article “ liripipe ” will be used of the tail of the hood, “
                tippet ” of the shoulder-cape, sometimes forming part of the same garment as the
                hood, sometimes not, and “ scarf ” of the “ tippet ” or scarf, <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.g.</hi> of D.D.’s, Anglican clergy.</p>
            <p>@@@ “that no non-graduate scholar (with the usual exceptions of noblemen, &amp;c.)
                shall wear any kind of hood in public, unless it have the liripipe sewn on, and not
                woven in one piece, as the ancient and venerable custom of the university demands.”
                The meaning of this is not clear; Anstey (marginal note<hi rend="italic">ad
                    loc.)</hi> takes it to mean that the tail of the hood should be sewn to the
                hood; others that the tail of the hood should be sewn down to the gown; cf.
                    Chaucer, <hi rend="italic">Prol. to Canon’s, Yeoman’s Tale:</hi> “Till that I
                understood How that his cloke was sowed to his hood, For which, whan I hadde long
                avysed me, I demed him some Chanoun for to be,” which shows that this method of
                sewing the hood, whatever it were, was used to define rank; others again hold that “
                    <hi rend="italic">liripipium ’’</hi> here means a tippet or shoulder-cape, and
                that for some reason the. hood was to be sewn to the tippet and not made all in one
                piece with it. Rashdall reads <hi rend="italic">“ Consuetum ’’</hi> instead of “ <hi
                    rend="italic">consutum ”</hi> (footnote, ii. p. 641). The Constitution of
                Archbishop Bourchier (1463) forbids undergraduates to use liripipes or “ tippets ”
                round the neck in public (Clark, p. 85), so the sewing down of the liripipe at the
                back may</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
