<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>though we cannot subscribe to his view that the artist calculated the effect of natural illumination upon the relief, it remains true that they are eminently pictorial compositions in respect of their depth of focus, yet without sacrifice of plastic effect (Plate II. fig. 14). So far as bas-relief is concerned, the problem of representing form in open space is here solved. Equally admirable in technique, though of less historical importance, are the circular medallions <hi rend="italic">(tondi)</hi>  which now adorn the Arch of Constantine, but originally belonged (as the present writer has shown)@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  to a monument of the Flavian period, perhaps the “ temple of the Flavian house ” erected by Domitian. The one shown (Plate III. fig. 18) is remarkable in that the head of the emperor has been replaced by a portrait, not of Constantine, but (in all probability) of Claudius Gothicus<hi rend="smallcaps">(a.d.</hi>  268-70), who was the first to divert these sculptures from their original destination.</p><p>Flavian portraits,@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> of which two are here figured,—a bust of Vespasian in the Museo delle Terme (Plate I. fig. 4) and a bust, now in the Lateran, found in the tomb of the IIaterii, which, as is shown by the snake, represents a physician (Plate I. fig. 5),—must rank as the masterpieces of Roman art. Their extraordinarily lifelike character is due to the fact that the artist, without accumulating unnecessary detail, has contrived to catch the characteristic expression of his subject, and to render it with the utmost technical virtuosity. These portraits differ from the works of the Greek masters, who always subordinated the individual to the type, and therefore gave a less complete impression of reality than the Roman artists.</p><p>The same tendency has been noted in ornamental work which may be dated to the Flavian period. Wickhoff selected a pilaster from the monument of the Haterii (Plate II. fig. 15) upon which a column entwined with roses is carved. The flowers are not in fact represented with precise fidelity to nature, but the illusion of reality is no less great than in more accurately worked examples.</p><p>Roman sculpture soon passed the zenith of its achievement. We are not able to assign any historical monuments to the earlier years of Trajan’s reign, but the portraits of the emperor betray a certain hardness of touch which makes them less interesting than those of the Flavian period. To the latter part of the reign belong a number of monuments which represent Trajanic art at its best. First and foremost come the reliefs, colossal in scale, which appear to have decorated the walls of Trajan’s Forum. Four slabs were removed by Constantine’s order and used to adorn the central passage and the shorter sides of the attic of his arch. The first of these (Plate II. fig. 16) shows the victorious charge of the Roman cavalry, with the emperor at its head, against their Dacian enemies. Other fragments of this frieze are extant in the Louvre,@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> and a much-restored relief, walled up in the garden of the Villa Medici, shows a Dacian on horseback swimming the Danube with Trajan’s Bridge in the background. The composition of the battle-scene is very fine, and the heads of the Dacians are full of character; but, although details of armour, &amp;c., are carefully and accurately reproduced, we see clear signs of technical decadence, both in the fact that the human eye is in many cases represented as though in full face on heads which are shown in profile, and also in the naïve attempt to render several files of troops in perspective by means of superposed rows of heads.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> The reliefs of the spiral</p><lb/><p>column in the Basilica Ulpia tell the same tale. The designer borrowed certain motives from Hellenistic art; <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  we find the suicide of the Dacian king Decebalus represented in precisely the same way as that of a Gallic chief on the well-known sarcophagus in the Capitoline Museum representing a battle between Greeks and Gauls; again, the symmetry of the scene in which the fall of Sarmizegetusa (the Dacian capital) is depicted recalls that of Greek monuments— particularly the painting of the fall of Troy by Polygnotus, described by Pausanias at Delphi. But the loving care with which the arms and accoutrements of the Roman troops— both regular and irregular—are rendered@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  betrays the nationality of the artist; and his technical deficiencies, especially in the matter of perspective, point in the same direction. It seems probable, moreover, that the artistic conception of a column ornamented with a band of relief was new, and that the designer had to find his own solution for the problem. We find, in fact, that he tells his story in more than one way:<hi rend="italic">(a)</hi>  Considerable portions of the narrative, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  Trajan’s march in the opening campaign, consist in a series of isolated and successive scenes; the divisions are usually marked by some conventional means, such as the insertion of a tree, or a change of direction in the action, (ά) At other times the scenes unfold themselves against a continuous background, and merge almost insensibly into those which succeed them; to this form of narrative the term “ continuous style,” brought into use by Wickhoff, more properly applies, (c) The direct progress of the narrative is sometimes broken by passages which can only be called “ panoramic the great composition showing the siege and fall of Sarmizegetusa falls under this head, and the “ continuous ” narration of Trajan’s journey at the outset of the second war is followed by an extensive panorama illustrating the operations in Moesia in <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>  105.</p><p>The reliefs (as already indicated) tell the story of both of Trajan’s wars with the Dacians, a formal division between the two narratives being made by a figure of Victory setting up a trophy; and the design of the second series shows a decided advance in artistic and dramatic effect on that of the first. Clearly the artist learnt the laws of composition applicable to his problem in the course of his work.</p><p>Before leaving the Trajanic period a word must be said as to the arch erected at Benevento (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Triumphal Arch,</hi>  fig. 2), from which point a new road—the Via Trajana—ran to Brun-disium. The inscription on this arch bears the date <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>  114, but the prominence given to Hadrian has led to the supposition that the reliefs were executed after his accession. We have already noted that the use of relief as ornament is here carried to excess in the artist’s desire to present a summary of Trajan’s achievements at home and abroad.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi>  The arrangement of the panels is calculated and significant. On the side which faces the town of Benevento the subjects have reference to Trajan’s work in Rome. On the attic we see, to the left, a group of gods with the Capitoline triad—Jupiter, Juno and Minerva— in the foreground; to the right, Trajan welcomed at the entrance to the Capitol by the goddess Roma, the penates and the consuls. He is accompanied by Hadrian, who is designated by the gesture of Roma as the emperor’s successor. The two lowest panels likewise form a single picture. To the right Trajan appears at the entrance of the Forum, where he is welcomed by the<hi rend="italic">praefectus urbi;</hi>  to the left, with the Curia as background, we see the representatives of senate, knights and people. The central panels symbolize the military and civil aspects of Trajan’s government—veterans to left, merchants to right, are the recipients of imperial favour. On the other</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="italic">
                       Papers of the British School at Rome,</hi>  vol. iii. pp. 229 ff. Sieve-king <hi rend="italic">[Rom. Mitth.</hi>  (1907) pp. 345 ff.) believes that four of the medallions only belong to the Flavian period and the rest to Hadrian’s reign.</p><p>@@@    On this subject sec Mr Crowfoot’s paper in<hi rend="italic">Journal of Hellenic Studies,</hi>  xx. (1900) pp. 31 ff. A list of examples is given by Mr Wace in <hi rend="italic">Papers of the British School at Rome,</hi>  vol. iii. pp. 290 ff.</p><p>@@@Mr Wace has recently identified the reliefs which show an emperor sacrificing before the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus as a part of the frieze<hi rend="italic">(Papers of the British School at Rome,</hi>  iv. pp. 229 ff.).</p><p>@@@ These features make it clear that the reliefs in the Villa Borghese, formerly supposed to belong to an arch of Claudius, are Trajanic; see<hi rend="italic">Papers of the British School at Rome,</hi>  iii. pp. 215 ff. (Stuart Jones).</p><lb/><p>@@@    Thus Cichorius, in his publication of the reliefs, has been able to identify several of the corps which took part in the war;<hi rend="italic">e.g. </hi>the “ cohorts of Roman citizens” are distinguished from the barbarian auxiliaries by the national emblems on their shields.</p><p>@@@    The significance of these reliefs was first demonstrated by Domaszewski<hi rend="italic">(Jahreshefte des österreichischen archäologischen Instituts,</hi>  ii. 1899, pp. 173 ff.); a full account will be found in Mrs Strong’s <hi rend="italic">Roman Sculpttire,</hi>  ch. 9.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>