<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>RICCI CONTD in China, he also devoted much time to answering the letters of the priests under
                him, a matter on which he spared no pains or detail. New converts had to be attended
                to—always welcomed, and never hustled away. Besides these came the composition of
                his Chinese books, the teaching of his people and the maintenance of the record of
                the mission history which had been enjoined upon him by the general of the order,
                and which he kept well up to date. Thus his labours were wearing and incessant. In
                May 1610 he broke down, and after an illness of eight days died on the nth of that
                month. His colleague Pantoja applied to the emperor for a burying-place outside
                the city. This was granted, with the most honourable official testimonies to the
                reputation and character of Ricci; and a large building in the neighbourhood of the
                city was at the same time bestowed upon the mission for their residence.</p>
            <p>Ricci’s work was the foundation of the subsequent success attained by the Roman
                Catholic Church in China. When the missionaries of other Roman Catholic orders made
                their way into China, twenty years later, they found great fault with the manner in
                which certain Chinese practices had been dealt with by the Jesuits, a matter in
                which Ricci's action and policy had given the tone to the mission in China—though in
                fact that tone was rather inherent in the Jesuit system than the outcome
                of individual character, for controversies of an exactly parallel nature arose two
                generations later in southern India, between the Jesuits and Capuchins, regarding
                what were called “ Malabar rites.” The controversy thus kindled in China burned
                for considerably more than a century with great fierceness.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                The chief points were (1) the lawfulness and expediency of certain terms employed by
                the Jesuits in naming God Almighty, such as <hi rend="italic">Tien, “</hi> Heaven'
                and <hi rend="italic">Shangai,</hi> “ Supreme Ruler ” or “ Emperor<hi rend="sup"
                    >1</hi> instead of<hi rend="italic">Tien-Chu,</hi> “ Lord of Heaven’ and in
                particular the erection of inscribed tablets in the churches, on which these terms
                were made use of;@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> (2) in respect to the ceremonial offerings
                made in honour of Confucius, and of personal ancestors, which Ricci had recognized
                as merely “ civil ” observances; (3) the erection of tablets in honour of ancestors
                in private houses; and (4), more generally sanction and favour accorded to ancient
                Chinese sacred books and philosophical doctrine, as not really trespassing on
                Christian faith.</p>
            <p>Probably no European name of past centuries is so well known in China as that of <hi
                    rend="italic">Li-ma-leu,</hi> the form in which the name of Ricci (Rt-cci <hi
                    rend="italic">Mat-leo)</hi> was adapted to Chinese usage, and by which he
                appears in Chinese records.<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The works which he composed in
                Chinese are numerous; a list of them (apparently by no means complete, however) will
                be found in Kircher<hi rend="sup">i</hi>S <hi rend="italic">China Illustrata,</hi>
                and also in Abel <hi rend="italic">Remusat''sNouveasuzanges Asiatiques</hi> (ii.
                213-15). They are said to display an aptitude for clothing ideas in a Chinese dress
                very rare and remarkable in a foreigner. One of the first which attracted attention
                and reputation among Chinese readers was a Treatise upon Friendship, in the form of
                a dialogue containing short and pithy paragraphs; this is stated in the <hi
                    rend="italic">De Expeditione</hi> to have been suggested during Ricci’s stay at
                Nan-chang by a conversation with the prince of Kien-ngan, who asked questions
                regarding the laws of friendship in the West.</p>
            <p>@@@The list of the literature of this controversy occupies forty-one columns in M.
                Cordier’s excellent<hi rend="italic">Bibliographie de la Chine.</hi></p>
            <p>@@@ Compare Browning,<hi rend="italic">The Ring ana the Book,</hi> x., The Pope,
                1589-1603.</p>
            <p>’The name comes forward prominently in the mouth of the emperor Kang-hi, in a
                dialogue which took place between him ana Monsgr. Maigrot, the leader of the
                anti-Jesuit movement (mentionea in Browning’s lines referred to above), at the
                summer residence in Tartary, August 1706—a dialogue which the Jesuits have reported
                with not a little malice:—</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">ii</hi>Emperor,</hi> ‘ Tell me why do the people
                call me <hi rend="italic">Van-sui</hi> .(10,000 years)/ <hi rend="italic">The Most
                    Reverend (i.e.</hi> Maigrot), <hi rend="sup">4</hi> To express their desire for
                your Majesty’s long life.’<hi rend="italic">Emp.</hi> * Good. You see, then, Chinese
                words are not always to be taken literally. We pay cult to Confucius and to the dead
                to express our respect for them. How is that inconsistent with your religion? When
                did it begin to be so? Is it since Ly-Mattheu’s time? Hast thou ever read Ly-Mattheu
                ? ’ <hi rend="italic">The Most Reverend,</hi> turning to P. Parenin, whispers, *
                Who’s he ? ’ and learning that it was P. Matteo Ricci, . . . answered the emperor:
                ‘1 have not read that book.’. <hi rend="italic">Emp. </hi><hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                Ly-Mattheu and his fellows came hither some two centuries ago; and before their time
                China never heard anything of the Incarnation, anything of<hi rend="italic"
                    >Tien-chu,</hi> who had not become incarnate in this part of the world. Why
                then, if it was lawful to call God <hi rend="italic">Tien </hi>before Ly-Mattheu’s
                time, should it be improper now?’ ”—<hi rend="italic">Epistola de Eventu Apostolicae
                    Legationis, scripta a PP. Missionariis . . . ad Praepositum Generalem S.
                    J.,</hi> An. 1706, 1 Novembris.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>In the early part of his residence <hi rend="bold">at </hi>Peking, when enjoying
                constant intercourse with scholars of high position, Ricci brought out the <hi
                    rend="italic">T’ien-chu shih-i,</hi> or “ Veritable Doctrine of the Lord
                of Heaven,” which deals with the divine character and attributes under eight heads.
                “ This work,” says A. Wylie, “ contains some acute reasoning in support of the
                propositions laid down, but the doctrine of faith in Christ is very slightly touched
                upon. The teachings of Buddhism are vigorously attacked, whilst the author tries to
                draw a parallel between Christianity and the teachings of the Chinese literati.”</p>
            <p>In 1604 Ricci completed the <hi rend="italic">Erh-shih-wu yen,</hi> a scries of short
                articles of moral bearing, but exhibiting little of the essential doctrines of
                Christianity. <hi rend="italic">C hi-j en shih pien</hi> is another of
                his productions, completed in 1608, and consisting of a record of ten conversations
                held with Chinese of high position. The subjects are: (1) Years past no [longer
                ours; (2) Man a sojourner on earth; (3) Advantage of frequent contemplation of
                eternity; (4) Preparation for judgment by such contemplation; (5) The good man not
                desirous of talking; (6) Abstinence, and its distinction from the prohibition to
                take life; (7) Self-examination and self-reproof inconsistent with inaction; (8)
                Future reward and punishment; (9) Piydng into futurity hastens calamity; (10) Wealth
                with covetousness more wretched than poverty with contentment. To this work is
                appended a translation of eight European hymns, with elucidations, written in
                1609.</p>
            <p>Some of the characteristics thus indicated may have suggested the bitterness of
                attacks afterwards made upon Ricci’s theology. An example of these is found in the
                work called <hi rend="italic">Anecdotes sur Vêlai de religion dans la Chine</hi>
                (Paris, 1733-35), the author of which (Abbé Villers) speaks of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >T’icn-chu shih-i</hi> in this fashion: “The Jesuit was also so ill versed in
                the particulars of the faith that, as the holy bishop of Conon, Monsgr.
                Maigrot, says of him, one need merely read his book on the true religion to convince
                oneself that he had never imbibed the first elements of theology.” . . .</p>
            <p>Ricci’s pointed attacks on Buddhism, and the wide circulation of his books, called
                forth the opposition of the Buddhist clergy. One of the ablest who took their part
                was Chu-hang, a priest of Hang-chow, who had abandoned the literary status for
                the Buddhist cloister. He wrote three articles against the doctrine of the
                missionaries. These were brought to Ricci’s notice in an ostensible tone of candour
                by Yu-chim-he, a high mandarin at the capital. This letter, with Ricci’s reply, the
                three Buddhist declamations and Ricci’s confutation, were published in a collected
                form by the Christian Sen-Kwang-K’e.</p>
            <p>Another work of Ricci’s which attracted attention was the <hi rend="italic">Hsi-kuo
                    fa,</hi> or “ Art of Memory as practised in the West.” Ricd was himself a great
                expert in <hi rend="italic">memoria technica,</hi> and astonished the Chinese by his
                performances in this line. He also wrote or edited various Chinese works on
                geography, the celestial and terrestrial spheres, geometry and arithmetic. And the
                detailed history of the mission was drawn out by him, which after his death was
                brought home by P. Nicolas Trigault, and published at Augsburg, and later in a
                complete form at Lyons under the name <hi rend="italic">De Expeditione Christiana
                    apud Sinas Suscepta, 'ab Soc. Jesu,</hi> Ex P. Mat. Ricci ejusdem Societatis <hi
                    rend="italic">Commentariis,</hi> Trigault himself adding many interesting notes
                on China and the Chinese.</p>
            <p>Among the scientific works which Ricci took into China was a set of maps, which at
                first created great interest, but afterwards disgust when the Chinese came to
                perceive the insignificant place assigned to the “ Middle Kingdom,” thrust, as it
                seemed, into a corner, instead of being set in the centre of the world like the gem
                in a ring. Ricci, seeing their dissatisfaction, set about constructing a map of the
                hemisphere on a great scale, so adjusted that China, with its subject states, filled
                the central</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
