<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>like Condé was content to draw aside the curtains for him to pass, and to sue for the hand of Richelieu’s niece for his son, the “ Great Condé.” His pride and ambition were gratified by the foundation of a sort of dynasty of his nephews and nieces, whose hands were sought by the noblest in the realm. Like all statesmen of his time, Richelieu made money out of politics. He came to court in 1617 with an income of 25,000 livres from his ecclesiastical benefices. In the later years of his life it exceeded 3,000,000 livres. He lived in imperial state, building himself the great Palais CardinaI, now the Palais Royal, in Paris, another at Rueil near Paris, and re-building his ancestral château in Poitou. His table cost him a thousand crowns a day, aIthough he himself lived simply. He celebrated his triumphs to the full with gorgeous fêtes in his palace, especially with lavish theatrical representations. In January 1641 the tragedy of <hi rend="italic">Mirame,</hi>  said to have been his own, was produced with great magnificence. Richelieu was anxious for literary fame, and his writings are not unworthy of him. But more important than his own efforts as an author were his protection and patronage of literary men, especially of Corneille, and his creation of the French Academy in 1635. His influence upon French literature was considerable and lasting. Hardly less important was his rebuilding of the Sorbonne and his endowments there. When he died, on the 4th of December 1642, he was buried in the chapel of the Sorbonne, which still stands as he built it. His tomb, erected in 1694, though rifled at the Revolution, still exists.</p><p>Many writings are attributed to Richelieu, although owing to his habit of working with substitutes and assistants it is difficult to settle how much of what passes under his name is authentic. <hi rend="italic">Les Thuileries, La Grande Pastorale, Mirame,</hi>  and the other plays, over whose fate he trembled as over the result of an embassy or a campaign, have long been forgotten; but a permanent interest attaches to his <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi>  and correspondence: <hi rend="italic">Mémoire d’Armand du Plessis de Richelieu, évêque de Luçon, écrit de sa main, l’année ιόογ ou 1610, alors qu’il méditait de paraître à la cour,</hi>  edited by Armand Baschet (1880); <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la mère et du fils (i.e.</hi>  of Marie de Medici and Louis XIII.), sometimes attributed to Mézeray, published at Amsterdam in 1730 and, under the title <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la régence de reine Marie de Médicis, femme de Henry IV.,</hi>  at the Hague in 1743; <hi rend="italic">Mémoires sur la règne de Louis XIII.,</hi>  extending from 1610 to 1638, and of which the earlier portion is a reprint of the <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la mère et du fils,</hi>  published in PetitoFs collection (Paris, 1823 seq.) ; <hi rend="italic">Testament politique d’Armand du Plessis, cardinal de Richelieu </hi>(Amsterdam, 1687 seq ) ; <hi rend="italic">Journal de 1630-31</hi>  (Paris, 1645) ; “ Lettres, instructions diplomatiques, et papiers d’état,” published by G. d’Avenel in the <hi rend="italic">Coll, de doc. inéd.</hi>  (Paris, 1853-77); and “ Maximes d’état et fragments politiques,” published by G. Hanotauxin <hi rend="italic">Mélanges historiques: Choix de doc. iii.,</hi>  in the same collection.</p><p>See G. Hanotaux, <hi rend="italic">Cardinal Richelieu</hi>  (1893), one volume of the four then promised, an exhaustive history of the period down to 1614; ana G. d’Avenel, <hi rend="italic">Richelieu et la monarchie absolue</hi>  (4 vols., 1895). The most important sources for Richelieu’s statesmanship are the “ Lettres, instructions diplomatiques, et papiers d’état mentioned above, and Richelieu’s <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi>  (1610-38) may be consulted in Petitot’s and J. F. Michaud and J. Poujoulat's collections. Innumerable memoirs of the time also béar upon his life, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  those of Madame de Motteville, Mathieu Molé, De Brienne, and Bassom-pierre. In English there are short biographies by Richard Lodge (in the Foreign Statesmen series, 1896) and by J. B. Perkins (in Heroes of the Nations series, 1900).    (J. T. S.*)</p><p><hi rend="bold">RICHELIEU, LOUIS FRANÇOIS ARMAND DU PLESSIS,</hi></p><p>Duc <hi rend="smallcaps">de</hi>  (1696-1788), marshal of France, was <hi rend="bold">a </hi>grandnephew of Cardinal Richelieu, and was bom in Paris on the 13th of March 1696. Apart from his reputation as a man of exceptionally loose morals, he attained, in spite of a deplorably defective education, distinction as a diplomatist and general. As ambassador to Vienna (1725-29) he settled in 1727 the preliminaries of peace; in 1733-34 he served in the Rhine campaign. His real public career began ten years later. He fought with distinction at Dettingen and Fontenoy, where he directed the grapeshot upon the English columns, and three years afterwards he made a brilliant defence of Genoa; in 1756 he expelled the English from Minorca by the capture of the San Felipe fortress; and in 1757-58 he closed his military career by those pillaging campaigns in Hanover which procured him the sobriquet of <hi rend="italic">Petit Père de la Maraude. </hi>After the wars he plunged again into court intrigue, favoured the comtesse du Barry and supported his nephew the duc d’Aiguilon. Louis XVI., however, was not favourably inclined to him. In his early days he was thrice imprisoned in the Bastille: in 1711 at the instance of his stepfather, in 1716 in consequence of a duel, and in 1719 for his share in AIberonis conspiracy against the regent Orleans. He was thrice married: first, against his will, at the age of fourteen to Anne Catherine de Noailles; secondly, in 1734, by the intrigues (according to the witty Frenchman’s own account) of Voltaire, to Marie Elisabeth Sophie, Mademoiselle de Guise; and thirdly, when he was eighty-four years old, to an Irish lady. He died in Paris on the 8th of August 1788. Marshal Richelieu’s <hi rend="italic">Mémoires, </hi>published by J. L. Soulavie in nine volumes (1790), are partially spurious.</p><p>See H. Noel Williams, <hi rend="italic">The Fascinating Duc de Richelieu</hi>  (1910).</p><p><hi rend="bold">RICHEPIN, JEAN </hi>(1849-    ), French poet, novelist and</p><p>dramatist, the son of an army doctor, was born at Medea (Algeria) on the 4th of February 1849. At school and at the École normale he gave evidence of brilliant, if somewhat undisciplined, powers, for which he found physical vent in different directions—first as a <hi rend="italic">franc-tireur</hi>  in the Franco-German War, and afterwards as actor, sailor and stevedore—and an intellectual outlet in the writing of poems, plays and novels which vividly reflected his erratic but unmistakable talent. A play, <hi rend="italic">U Étoile,</hi>  written by him in collaboration with André Gill(1840-1885), was produced in 1873; but Richepin was virtually unknown untfl the publication, in 1876, of a volume of verse entitled <hi rend="italic">Chanson des gueux,</hi>  when his outspokenness resulted in his being imprisoned and fined for <hi rend="italic">outrage aux mœurs. </hi>The same quality has characterized his succeeding volumes of verse: <hi rend="italic">Les Caresses</hi>  (1877), <hi rend="italic">Les Blasphèmes</hi>  (1884), <hi rend="italic">La Mer </hi>(1886), <hi rend="italic">Mes paradis</hi>  (1894), <hi rend="italic">La Bombarde</hi>  (1899). His novels have developed in style from the morbidity and brutality of <hi rend="italic">Les Morts bizarres</hi>  (1876), <hi rend="italic">La Glu (ιΖΖι)</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Le Pave</hi>  (1883) to the more thoughtful psychology of <hi rend="italic">Madame André</hi>  (1878), <hi rend="italic">Sophie Monnier</hi>  (1884), <hi rend="italic">Césanne</hi>  (1888), <hi rend="italic">L<hi rend="sup">i</hi>Aimé</hi>  (1893), <hi rend="italic">Grandes amoureuses</hi>  (1896) and <hi rend="italic">Lagibasse</hi>  (1899), and the more simple portrayal of life in <hi rend="italic">Miarka</hi>  (1883), <hi rend="italic">Les Braves Gens</hi>  (1886), <hi rend="italic">Tniandailles</hi>  (1890), <hi rend="italic">La Miseloqiie</hi>  (1892) and <hi rend="italic">Plamboche</hi>  (1895). His plays, though OccasioriaUy marred by his characteristic proneness to violence of thought and language, constitute in many respects his best work. The most notable are <hi rend="italic">Nana Sahib </hi>(1883), <hi rend="italic">Monsieur Scapin</hi>  (1886), <hi rend="italic">Le Pilibustier</hi>  (1888), <hi rend="italic">Par le glaive</hi>  (1892), <hi rend="italic">Vers la joie</hi>  (1894), <hi rend="italic">Le Chemineau</hi>  (1897), <hi rend="italic">Le Chien de garde</hi>  (1898), <hi rend="italic">Les Truands</hi>  (1899), <hi rend="italic">Don Quichotte</hi>  (1905), most of which were produced at the Comédie française. He also wrote <hi rend="italic">Miarka</hi>  (1905), adapted from his novel, for the music of Alexandre Georges, and <hi rend="italic">Le Mage</hi>  (1897) for the music of Jules Massenet.</p><p>His son, Jacques Richepin (b. 1880), the author of <hi rend="italic">La Reine de Tyr</hi>  (1899), <hi rend="italic">La Cavalière</hi>  (1901), <hi rend="italic">Cadet-Roussel</hi>  (1903) and <hi rend="italic">Palstaf</hi>  (1904), based on Shakespeare’s <hi rend="italic">HenryIV.,</hi>  gave promise of making his mark as a dramatist.</p><p>RICHERUS, monk of St Remi at Reims, and a chronicler of the 10th century, son of Rodulf, a trusty counciUor and captain of Louis IV. He studied at Reims under Gerbert, afterwards Pope SUvester II., who taught him mathematics, history, letters and eloquence. He was also well versed in the medical science of his time, and in 991 traveled to Chartres to consult the medical MSS. there. He was StiU living in 998, but there is no mention of him after that date. In spite of his violent partisanship,—for Richerus was an ardent upholder of the Carolings and French supremacy,—of great defects of style, and of an utter disregard of accuracy and truth, his <hi rend="italic">Historiae </hi>has a unique value as giving us the only tolerably fuU account by a contemporary of the memorabIe revolution of 987, which placed the Capets on the throne of France. The <hi rend="italic">History,</hi>  in four books, begins with Charles the Fat and Eudes, and goes down to the year 995. From 969 onwards Richerus had no earlier history before him, and his work is the chief source for the period. It was first edited in Pertz’s <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Germaniae, </hi>vol. iii.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>