<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tured at Vienna in a mean disguise (December 20th, 1192) and strictly confined in the duke’s castle of DUrenstein on the Danube. His mishap was soon known to England, but the regents were for some weeks uncertain of his whereabouts. This is the foundation for the tale of bis discovery by the faithful minstrel Blondel, which first occurs in a French romantic chronicle of the next century. Early in 1193 Leopold surrendered his prize, under compulsion, to the emperor Henry VI., who was aggrieved both by the support which the PIantagenets had given to the family of Henry the Lion and also by Richard’s recognition of Tancred in Sicily. Although the detention of a crusader was contrary to public law, Richard was compelled to purchase his release by the payment of a heavy ransom and by doing homage to the emperor for England. The ransom demanded was 150,000 marks; though it was never discharged in full, the resources of England were taxed to the utmost for the first instalments; and to this occasion we may trace the beginning of secular taxation levied on movable property.</p><p>Richard reappeared in England in March 1194; Out his stay lasted only a few weeks, and the rcmainder of his reign was entirely devoted to his continental interests. He left England to be governed by Hubert Walter <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi>  and his personal authority was seldom asserted except by demands for new subsidies. The rule of the Plantagenets was still popular in Normandy and Aquitaine; but thesc provinces were unable or unwilling to pay for their own defence. Though Richard proved himself consistently the superior of Philip in the field, the difficulty of raising and paying forces to resist the French increased year by year. Richard could only stand on the defensive; the keynote of his later policy is given by the building of the famous Château Gaillard at Les Andelys (1196) to protect the lower courses of the Seine against invasion from the side of France. He did not live to see the futility of such bulwarks. In 1199 a claim to treasure-trove embroiled him with the viscount of Limoges. He harried the Limousin and laid siege to the castle of Chalus; while directing an assault he was wounded in the shoulder by a crossbow bolt, and, the wound mortifying from unskilful treatment or his own want of care, he died on the 6th of April 1199. He was buried by his own desire at his father’s feet in the church of Fontevrault. Here his effigy may still be seen.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Though contemporary, it does not altogether agree with the portraits on his Great Seal, which give the impression of greater strength and even of cruelty. The Fontevrault bust is no doubt idealized.</p><p>The most accomplished and versatile representative of his gifted family, Richard was, in his lifetime and long afterwards, a favourite hero with troubadours and romancers. This was natural, as he belonged to their brotherhood and himself wrote lyrics of no mean quality. But his history shows that he by no means embodied the current ideal of chivalrous excellence. His memory is stained by one act of needless cruelty, thc massacre of over two thousand Saracen prisoners at Acre; and his fury, when thwarted or humbled, was ungovernable. A brave soldier, an experienced and astute general, he was never happier than when engaged in war. As a ruler he was equally profuse and rapacious. Not one useful measure can be placed to his credit; and it was by a fortunate accident that he found, in Hubert Walter, an administrator who had the skill to mitigate the consequences of a reckless fiscal policy. Richard’s wife was Berengaria, daughter of Sancho VI., king of Navarre, whom he married in Cyprus in May 1191. She was with the king at Acre later in the same year, and during his imprisonment passed her time in Sicily, in Rome and in France. Husband and wife met again in 1195, and the queen long survived the king, residing chiefly at Le Mans. She died soon after 1230. Berengaria founded a Cistercian monastery at Espau.</p><p>@@@ The remains of Richard, together with those of Henrys II. and his queen Eleanor, were removed in thc 17th century from their tombs to another part of the church. They were rediscovered in 1910 during the restoration of the abbey undertaken by the French government.</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Authorities.—The more important of the general chronicles arc: the </hi><hi rend="italic">Gesta Henrici Secundi</hi>  ascribed to Benedict of Peterborough (Rolls Series, 2 vols., 1867); the <hi rend="italic">Chronica</hi>  of Roger of Hovedcn (Rolls Series, 4 vols., 1868-71); the <hi rend="italic">Chronica</hi>  of Gervase of Canterbury (Rolls Series, 1879); thc <hi rend="italic">Imagines Historiarum</hi>  of Ralph of Diccto (Rolls Series, 2 vols., 1876); the <hi rend="italic">Historia Rerum Angli-carurn</hi>  of William of Newburgh (in <hi rend="italic">Chronicles of the Reigns of Stephen, </hi>&amp;c., Rolls Series, 2 vols., 1884-85); thc <hi rend="italic">De rebus gestis Ricardi Primi </hi>of Richard of Devizes (in <hi rend="italic">Chronicles of the Reigns of Stephen,</hi>  &amp;c., vol. iii., Rolls Series, 1886); the <hi rend="italic">Chronicon Anglicanum</hi>  of Ralph of COggcshall (Rolls Series, 1875); thc <hi rend="italic">Flores Historiarum</hi>  of Roger of Wendovcr (Rolls Series, 3 vols., 1886-89); the <hi rend="italic">Gesta Philippi Augusti </hi>of Rigord <hi rend="italic">(Société de l’histoire de France,</hi>  Paris, 1882) and of Guillaume le Breton <hi rend="italic">(op. cit.).</hi>  A detailed narrative of Richard’s crusade is given in <hi rend="italic">L’Estoire de la guerre sainte,</hi>  a rhyming French chronicle by the minstrel Ambroise (cd. Gaston Paris, Paris, 1897), and in the Latin prose version known as thc <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium O. Peregrinorum et gesta Regis Ricardi;</hi>  this last, with some valuable historical letters, is printed in W. Stubbs’s <hi rend="italic">Chronicles and Memorials of the Reign of Richard I.</hi>  (Rolls Series, 2 vols., 1864-65). Of modern works the following arc useful: W. Stubbs’s preface to vols. iii. and iv. of Hoveden; the same author’s <hi rend="italic">Constitutional History of England, </hi>vol. i. (Oxford, 1897); Miss K. Norgate’s <hi rend="italic">England under the Angevin Kings,</hi>  vol. ii. (London, 1887); Sir J. H. Ramsay’s <hi rend="italic">Angevin Empire </hi>(London, 1903); R. Röhricht’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Königreichs Jerusalem </hi>(1898); W. B. Stevenson’s <hi rend="italic">Crusaders in the East</hi>  (Cambridge, 1907); A. CartellierPs <hi rend="italic">Philipp II. August</hi>  (Leipzig, 1899, &amp;c.).</p><p>(H. W. C. D.)    </p><p>RICHARD II. (1367-1400), king of England, younger son of Edward the Black Prince by Joan “ the Fair Maid of Kent,” was born at Bordeaux on the 6th of January 1367. He was brought to England in 1371, and after his father’s death was, on the petition of the Commons in parliament, created prince of Wales on the 20th of November 1376. When Edward III. died, on the 21st of June 1377, Richard became king. Popular opinion had credited John of Gaunt with designs on the throne. This was not justified; nevertheless, the rivalry of the boy-king’s uncles added another to the troubles due to the war, the Black Death and the prospect of a long minority. At first the government was conducted by a council appointed by parliament. The council was honest, but the difficulties of the situation were too great. The ill-considered poll-tax of 1381 was the occasion, though not the real cause, of the Peasants’ Revolt in that year. The ministcrs were quite unequal to the crisis, and when Wat Tyler and bis followers got possession of London, it was Richard who showed a precocious tact and confidence in handling it. It was the boy-king who met and temporized with the rebels on the 13th of June at Mile End, and again next day at Smithfield; and be who, with courageous presence of mind, saved the situation when Tyler was killed, by calling on them to take him for their leader. From this time Richard began to assert himself. His chief ministers, appointed by parliament in 1382, were thc carl of Arundel and Michael de la Pole. Arundel Richard disliked, and dismissed next year, when he began his personal government. Pole, whom he retained as chancellor and made earl of Suffolk, was a well-chosen adviser. But others, and especially his youthful favourite Robert de Vere, promoted by unheard-of honour to be marquess of Dublin and duke of Ireland, were less worthy. Further, Richard made his own position difficult by lavish extravagance and unseemly outbursts of temper. He chafed under the restraint of his relatives, and therefore encouraged John of Gaunt in his Spanish enterprise. This gave the less scrupulous Thomas of Gloucester his opportunity. Gloucester, supported by Arundel, attacked his nephew’s ministers in the parliament of 1386, and by open hints at deposition forced Richard to submit to a council of control. When Richard, with the aid of his friends and by the advice of subservient judges, planned a reversal of the parliament, Gloucester, at the head of the so-called lords appellant, anticipated him. Richard had been premature and ill-advised. Gloucester had the advantage of posing as the head of the constitutional party. The king’s friends were driven into exile or executed, and he himself forced to submit to thc loss of all real power (May 1388). Richard changed his</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>