<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r02-0611-02" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0635.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>ROCH</label>
Sτ (Lat. <hi rend="italic">Rochus ;</hi> Ital. <hi rend="italic">Rocco</hi> ; Span. <hi rend="italic">Rogue ;</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic">Roch</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Rogue),</hi> according to the <hi rend="italic">Roman Breviary,</hi> was a native of Montpellier, France. The name of his father was John and that of his mother Franca or Libera. He was born with the mark of a red cross upon his person, and this was at once interpreted as signifying his future eminence. In his twelfth year he began to manifest strict asceticism and great devoutness, and on the death of his parents in his twentieth year he gave all his substance to the poor and joined the Franciscan Tertiaries. Coming to Italy during an epidemic of plague, he was very diligent in tending the sick in the public hospitals at Aquapendente, Cesena, and Rome, and effected many miraculous cures by prayer and simple contact. After similar ministries at Piacenza he himself fell ill, and would have perished as he passed through the forest had not the dog of a certain nobleman daily supplied him with bread. On his return to Montpellier he was arrested as a spy and thrown into prison, where he died, having previously obtained from God this favour, that all plague-stricken persons invoking him should be healed. The date of his death was 16th August 1327, in the thirty-second year of his age. During the sittings of the council of Constance in 1414, when the city was visited with the plague, the efficacy of St Roch’s intercession was “ most manifestly ” experienced. His remains were removed in 1385 to Venice, where they now lie. He is commemorated, chiefly in Italy and France, as the patron of the sick, and especially of the plague-stricken.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>