<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r02-0546-01" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0566.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RICHMOND</label>
Legh (1772-1827), writer of tracts, was born 29th January 1772 at Liverpool, where his father was a physician. He was educated at Trinity College, Cambridge, where he graduated B.A. in 1794 and M.A. in 1797. In 1798 he was appointed to the joint curacies of Brading and Yaverland in the Isle of Wight. Through the perusal of Wilberforce’s <hi rend="italic">Practical View</hi> an evangelical bias was given to his mind, which led him to devote himself with great earnestness to the reclamation of the masses. He took a prominent interest in the British and Foreign Bible Society, the Church Missionary Society, and various other institutions of a similar kind. In 1805 he became chaplain to the Lock Hospital, London, and in the same year was presented to the rectory of Turvey, Bedfordshire, where he remained till his death, 8th May 1827. He was also appointed chaplain to the duke of Kent. The best known of the tracts of Legh Richmond is the <hi rend="italic">Dairymanhs Daughter,</hi> of which as many as four millions in nineteen languages were circulated before 1849. A collected edition of his tracts was first published in 1814 under the title of <hi rend="italic">Annals of the Poor.</hi> He was also the author of <hi rend="italic">Domestic Portraiture,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of his Three Children·,</hi> and he edited a series of the <hi rend="italic">Fathers of the English Church.</hi></p><p>See Memoirs by Grimshawe, 1828 ; Life by Bedell, 1829.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>