<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0818.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0812-08" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STOVE</label>
for heating apartments, greenhouſes, hot- houſes, fruit-walls, &amp;c.</p><p>When treating of the mechanical properties oſ air, we explained in sufficient detail the manner in which the expansion produced in a maſs of air by heat produces that motion up our chimneys which is called the draught of the chimney ; and, in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Smoke,</hi> we considered the circumſtances which tend to check, to promote, or to direct this current, ſo as to free us from the ſmoke and vitiated air which necessarily accom. panies the conſumption of the fuel, In <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics</hi> we alſo attended to the manner in which our fires immediately operate in warming our apartments. At preſent, when about to describe a method oſ warming intrinsically different, we muſt pay ſome more attention to the diſtinguiſhing circumſtance. Without pretending to explain the physical connection of heat and light, it may ſuffice to obſerve, that heat, as well as light, is communicated to diſtant bodies in an inſtant by radiation. A perſon paſſing haſtily by the door of a glaſs-houſe feels the glow of heat in the very moment he ſees the dazzling light of the furnace mouth, and it is interrupted by merely ſcreening his face with his hand. In this way is an apartment partly warmed by an open fire ; and we avoid the oppreſſive heat by fitting where the fire is not ſeen, or by interposing a ſcreen. We are apt to connect this ſo ſtrongly in the imagination with the light emitted by the fire, that we attribute the heat to the immediate action of the light. But this opinion is ſhown to be gratuitous by a curious experiment made before the Royal Society by Dr Hooke, and afterwards, with more care and accurate examination, by Mr Scheele. They found, that by bringing a plate of the most tranſparent glaſs briſkly between the fire and one’s face, the heat is immediately intercepted without any ſenfible diminution of the light. Scheele, by a very pretty inveſtigation, diſcovered that the glaſs made the ſeparation, and did it both in refraction and reflection ; for he found, that when the light of the ſame fire was collected into a focus by means of a poliſhed metal concave ſpeculum, a thermometer placed there was <hi rend="italic">instantly</hi> affected. But if we employ a glaſs ſpeculum foiled in the uſual manner with quickſilver, of the ſame diameter and focal diſtance, and of equally brilliant reflection, there is hardly any ſensible heat produced in the focus, and the thermometer muſt remain there for a very long while before it is ſenſibly affected. When we repeated this curious experiment, we found, that after the glaſs has remained a long while in this position, whether tranſmitting or reflecting the light, it loses in a great meaſure its power of intercepting the heat. By varying this obſervation in many of its circumſtances, we think ourſelves entitled to conclude, that the glaſs abſorbs the heat which it intercepts, and is very quickly heated by the abſorption. While it riſes in its own temperature, it intercepts the heat powerfully ; but when it is, as it were, ſaturated, attracting no more than what it immediately imparts to the air in corporeal contact with it, the heat paſſes freely through along with the light. If the glaſs be held ſo near the fire that the ſurrounding air is very much heated, no ſensible interruption of heat is perceived after the glaſs is thus ſaturated. We found the cheek more quickly ſensible than the thermometer of this inſtantaneous radiation of the heat which accompanies the light, or is ſeparated from it in this experiment. It is a very inſtructive experiment in the physiology of heat.</p><p>We cannot lay how far this radiation of heat may extend, nor whether the accompanyment of light is abſolutely neceſſary. The mathematician proceeds on the ſuppoſition that it extends as far as the radiation of light, and that, being alſo rectilineal, the denſity of the heat is proportional to that of the light. But theſe notions arc ſomewhat gratuitous ; and there are<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0819.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0813"/>
appearances which render them doubtful. When with a lens of an inch in diameter we form a focus on a piece of black unpoliſhed marble of an inch diameter, the mathematician muſt allow that no more rays fall on the marble than if the lens were away : therefore the marble ſhould be equally warmed in either caſe. But it is by no means ſo, as we have repeatedly found by exposing it during equal times, and then dropping it into water. The water which is heated by the marble on which the focus has been formed will be found to have acquired from it much more heat than from the other. The tops of lofty mountains which are never ſhaded by clouds, but enjoy perpetual ſunſhine and ſerenity, instead of being warmer than the valleys below, are covered with never-melting ſnow ; and we have ſome grounds to ſuſpect that the genial influence of the ſun requires the co-operation of the atmoſphere, and to doubt whether there is any warmth at the moon, on which no atmoſphere like ours can be obſerved. Perhaps the heat which cheers us, and fertilizes our earth, is chemically ſeparated from our atmoſphere by its elective attraction for the light of the ſun. Our ſucceſſors in the ſtudy of meteorology need not fear that the ſubject of their reſearch will be soon deprived of ſcientific allurements. We know but little of it after all the progreſs we have made during this laſt century, and it ſtill preſents an ample field of diſcuſſion.</p><p>We ſaid that the accompanyment of light is not demonſtrably necessary. We are certain that heat may be imparted without any ſenſible light, in a manner which we can hardly ſuppoſe any thing but radiation. If a piece of very hot iron be placed a little without the principal focus of a metallic concave ſpeculum, and a very ſenſible air-thermometer be placed in its conjugate focus, it will inſtantly ſhow an elevation of temperature, although the iron is quite imperceptible to an eye which has even been along while in the dark. No ſuch riſe of temperature is obſerved if the thermometer be placed a little to one side of the focus of the ſpeculum ; therefore the phenomenon is preciſely ſimilar to the radiation of light. We are obliged therefore to acknowledge that the heat is radiated in this experiment in the ſame way that light is in the common optical experiments.</p><p>Although this is the moſt uſual way that we in this country employ fuel for warming our apartments, it is by no means the only way in which the heat diffuſed from this fuel may be imparted to diſtant bodies. It is not even the moſt effectual method ; it is diffuſed alſo by immediate communication to bodies in contact. The air in immediate contact with the burning fuel is heated, and imparts ſome of its heat to the air lying beyond it, and this is partly ſhared with the air which is ſtill farther off ; and this diffuſion, by communication <hi rend="italic">in contactu,</hi> goes on till the remote air contiguous to the walls, the floor, the ceiling, the furniture, the company, all get a ſhare of it in proportion to their attractions and their capacities. And as the air is thus continually supplied, and continually gives out heat, the walls, &amp;c. become gradually wanner, and the room becomes comfortable and pleaſant. But we apprehend that no great proportion of the heat actually acquired by the room is communicated in this way. This diffuſion by contact is but flow, eſpecially in air which is very dry ; ſo flow indeed, that the air in the immediate neighbourhood of the fuel is burned up the chimney before it has time to impart any of the heat received in contact. We know that the time employed in diffuſing itſelf in this way through ſtagnant air to any moderate diſtance is very conſiderable. We imagine therefore that the heat communicated to our rooms by an open fire is chiefly by radiation, but in a way ſomething different from what we mentioned before. We imagine, that as the piece of glaſs in Dr Hooke’s experiment abſorbs the heat, ſo the whole maſs of air which fills the room intercepts the radiated heat in every part of the room where the fire is ſeen, and is as it were ſaturated with it throughout, and ready to impart it to every body immerſed in it... We cannot otherwiſe account for the <hi rend="italic">equability</hi> of the heat in the different parts of the room. Mere radiation on the ſolid bodies would warm them in the inverſe duplicate ratio of their diſtances from the fire ; and diffuſion by contact, if compatible with the rapid current up the chimney, would heat the room ſtill more unequably. Recollect how ſlowly, and with what rapid diminution of intensity, the colour of blue vitriol is communicated to water even to a very ſmall diſtance. But becauſe all parts of the air of the room abſorb radiated heat, what is saturated at a higher temperature, being nearer to the fire, rises to the ceiling, ſpreads outwards along the ceiling, and has its place ſupplied by the air, which is thus puſhed towards the fire from the places which are not directly illuminated.</p><p>Far different is the method of warming the room by a ſtove. Here the radiation, if any, is very feeble or ſcanty ; and if a paſſage were allowed up the chimney for the warmed air, it would be quickly carried off. This is well known to the Engliſh who reſide in the cold climates of St Peterſburgh, Archangel, &amp;c. They love the exhilarating flutter of an open fire, and often have one in their parlour ; but this, ſo far from warming the room during the extreme cold weather, obliges them to heat their ſtoves more frequently, and even abſtracts the heat from a whole fuite oſ apartments. But all paſſages this way is ſhut up when we warm a room by ſtoves. The air immediately contiguous to the ſtove is heated by contact, and this heat is gradually, though ſlowly, diffuſed through the whole room. The diffusion would however be very slow indeed, were it not for the great expansibility of air by heat. But the air ſurrounding the ſtove quickly expands and rises to the ceiling, while the neighbouring air slides in to ſupply the place, nay is even puſhed in by the air which goes outwards aloft. Thus the whole air is ſoon mixed, and the room acquires almoſt an equal temperature throughout.</p><p>The warming by ſtoves muſt therefore be managed upon very different principles from thoſe adopted in the employment of open fires. The general principle is, 1st <hi rend="italic">,</hi> To employ the fuel in the moſt effectual manner for heating the external part of the ſtove, which is immediately efficient in warming the contiguous air; and, 2d, To keep in the room the air already warmed, at leaſt as much as is conſiſtent with wholesomeneſs and cleanlineſs.</p><p>The firſt purpoſe is accompliſhed by conducting the flue of the furnace round its external parts, or, in ſhort, by making every part of the flue external. Of all forms, that of a long pipe, returned backwards and forwards, up and down (provided only that the place of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0820.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0814"/>
its laſt diſcharge be conſiderably higher than its entry from the fire-place), would be the moſt effectual. We have ſeen a very ſmall ſtove conſtructed in this way, the whole being incloſed in a handſome caſe of poliſhed iron plate, pierced arid cut into elegant foliage like the cock oſ a watch, ſo that the odd looking pipes were completely concealed. Though only three feet long, one foot thick, and six feet high, it warmed a very lofty room of 24 feet by 18, and conſumed leſs than half the fuel of a ſtove of the more uſual make, which did not ſo fully warm a ſmaller chamber.</p><p>It would occupy a volume to deſcribe the immenſe variety of ſtoves which ingenuity or architectonic taſte has conſtructed. We ſhall content ourſelves with giving a ſpecimen of the two chief classes into which they may be diſtinguiſhed.</p><p>The air of a room may be equally warmed, either by applying it to the ſurface of a ſmall ſtove made very hot, or to the surface of a much larger ſtove more moderately heated. The firſt kind is chiefly uſed in Holland, Flanders, and the milder climates of Germany and Poland. The laſt are universally uſed in the frozen climates of Ruſſia and Sweden. The firſt are generally made of caſt-iron, and the laſt of brick-work covered with glazed tiles or ſtucco.</p><p><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Plate CCCCLXXIV.</p></note> Fig. I. repreſents a ſmall German ſtove fully sufficient for warming a room of 24 feet by 18. The baſe is about three feet broad and 14 inches deep, that is, from back to front, and six or seven feet high. The decoration is in the faſhion of that country ; but the operative ſtructure of it will admit of any ſtyle of ornament. A, is the fire-place, and the wood or charred coal is laid on the bottom, which has no bars. Bars would admit the air too freely among the fuel, and would both conſume it too faſt and raiſe too great a heat. That no heat may be uſeleſsly expended, the ſole of the fire-place and the whole bottom of the ſtove is raiſed an inch or two above the floor of the room, and the air is therefore warmed by it in ſucceſſion, and riſes upwards. For the ſame reaſon the back of the ſtove is not in contact with the wall of the room, or of the niche in which it is placed. The fire-place is ſhut up by a door which fits cloſely to its caſe, and has a small wicket at the bottom, whoſe aperture is regulated by a sliding plate, ſo as to admit no more air than what suffices for slowly conſuming the fuel. The flame and heated air rise to the top of the fire-place three or four inches above the arch or mantle-piece, and get out laterally by two narrow passages B, B, immediately below the top plate of the baſe. The current bends downward on each side, passes at C, C, under the partition plates which divide the two side chambers, and then riſes upwards through the outer diviſion of each, and passes through narrow slits I), D, in the top plate, and from thence along the two hollow piers E, E. The two lateral currents unite at the top of the arch, and go through the ſingle paſſage F into the larger hollow behind the eſcutcheon G. From this place it either goes ſtraight upwards into the vent in the wall by a pipe on the top of the ſtove, or it goes into the wall behind by a pipe inſerted in the back of the ſtove. The propriety oſ this conſtruction is very obvious. The current of hot air is applied to exterior parts of the ſtove everywhere except in the two side chambers of the baſe, where the partition-plates form one side of the canal. Even this might be avoided by making each of theſe side-chambers a detached hollow pillar. But this would greatly increaſe the trouble of conſtruction and joining together, and is by no means neceſſary. The arch H has a graceful appearance, and affords a very warm ſituation for any thing that requires it, ſuch as a drink in a ſick perſon’s bed-chamber, &amp;c. Perſons of a certain claſs uſe this place for keeping a diſh warm ; nay, the lower part of the arch is frequently occupied by an incloſed chamber, where the heat riſes high enough even for dreſſing victuals, as will be eaſily imagined when we reflect that the ſole of it is the roof of the fire place.</p><p>The ſtove now deſcribed is ſupplied with fuel and with air by the front door opening into the room. That there may be room for fuel, this middle part projects a few inches before the two side chambers. Theſe laſt, with the whole upper part of the ſtove, are not more than ten inches deep. The passages, therefore, from the fire-place are towards the back of it ; ſo that if we have a mind to ſee the fire (which is always cheerful), the door may be thrown open, and there is no danger of the ſmoke coming out after the current has once warmed the upper part of the ſtove. When the ſtove is of ſuch dimenſions that the baſe is about two feet and a half or three feet high, the fire-place may be furniſhed with a ſmall grate in the Britiſh ſtyle. If the door is ſo hung that it can not only be thrown back, but lifted off its hinges, we have a ſtove grate of the completeſt kind, fully adequate, in our mild climate, to warm a handſome apartment, even with an open fire ; and when we hang on the door, and ſhut up the fire-place, a ſtove of the dimenſions already given is almoſt too much for a large drawing-room.</p><p>We have frequently remarked, that one side of theſe ſtoves grows much warmer than the other, and that it was difficult to prevent or remedy this ; and we imagine that this is an unavoidable defect in all ſtoves with a double flue. It is ſcarcely poſſible to make the fire ſo equable in the fire-place, that one side ſhall not be a little warmer than the other, and a briſker current will then be produced in it. This muſt increaſe the conſumption of the fuel on this side, which will increaſe the current, will heat this side ſtill more, and thus go on continually till the fuel on this side is expendcd ; after which the other side will obtain and increaſe the ſuperiority. The flue is made double, that the fire-place may occupy the middle of the front ; and it will be difficult to gain this point of ſymmetry with one flue. The inconvenience may, however, be corrected by damping valves placed in ſome part of the upright funnels E, E.</p><p>In the colder winters on the continent, it is thought neceſſary to increaſe the effect by making the fire-place open to the back of the ſtove. Its mouth or door communicates with or is joined to an opening of the ſame dimenſions formed in the wall, and the door is on the other side in an antichamber or lobby. In Weſtphalia, and other places of Germany, the apartments are diſpoſed round a ſpacious lobby, into which all their fireplaces open, and are there ſupplied with fuel. By this conſtruction it is plain that the air of the room, already warmed by the ſtove, is not carried off, and the room is more heated. But this method is very unfavourable to cheerfulneſs and health. The ſame air confined, and<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0821.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0815"/>
repeatedly breathed and compounded with all the volatile emanations of the room, quickly loses that refreſhing quality that is ſo deſirable, and even ſo necessary for health. It is never renewed except by very partial admixtures when the room doors are thrown open, and becomes diſagreeable to any perſon coming in from the open air ; and in the houses of the leſs opulent becomes really offenſive and nauſeous.</p><p>Something of this is unavoidable in all rooms heated by ſtoves. Even in our apartments in this island, persons of delicate nerves are hurt by what they call the cloſe air of a room ; and it is long before the ſmell of dinner is quite removed from a dining-room, notwithstanding the copious current up the chimney. This muſt be incomparably more ſenſible in a room heated by a ſtove ; and this inconvenience is peculiarly ſenſible with respeect to the ſtove which we are conſidering at preſent, where we employ a ſmall ſurface heated to a great degree.</p><p>Such ſtoves are ſeldom made of any thing elſe than caſt-iron. This (in thoſe parts at leaſt which are in immediate contact with the fuel) is in a ſtate of continual calcination, and even throwing off ſcales. This indeed is not ſeen, becauſe it is the bottom or ſole of the fire-place which is ſo heated : but the effect on the air of the room is the ſame. The calcination of the iron is occaſioned by the combination of pure vital air with the iron. This is abstracted from the general maſs of atmoſpheric air in the room, of which it usually conſtitutes about <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> ths. By this abstraction the remainder becomes leſs fit for ſupporting animal life or flame, and may even become highly deleterious. In every degree the remainder becomes leſs refreſhing, and grows dull and oppreſſive. This is always accompanied by a peculiar ſmell, which, though not diſguſting, is unpleaſant. It reſembles the ſmell of burnt feathers, or more exactly the ſmell we feel if we rub violently for ſome time the palms of our hands together when perfectly dry.</p><p>For ſimilar reaſons theſe iron ſtoves occaſion a ſickly ſmell, by burning every particle of dust which falls on the hot parts ; and if they be wiped with a woollen cloth, or any cloth not perfectly free from every kind of greaſy or oily matter, a ſmell is produced for a day or days afterwards; ſo that without the moſt ſcrupulous attention we ſuffer by our very cleanlineſs.</p><p>For ſuch reaſons we think that the flows of brickwork covered with ſtucco or with glazed tiles are vaſtly preferable. Theſe are much uſed in the genteeler houſes in Flanders and Holland, where they are made in the moſt elegant forms, and decorated with beautiful ſculpture or enamel ; but it is plain that they cannot be ſo effectual, nor equally warm a room with the ſame expence of fuel. Earthen ware, eſpecially when covered with porous ſtucco, is far inferior to metal in its power of conducting heat. If built of bricks, they muſt be vaſtly more bulky when the fire-place and flues are of the same dimenſions. The moſt perfect way of constructing them would certainly be to make them of pottery, in parts exactly fitted to each other, and joined by a proper cement. This mode of conſtructing would admit of every elegance of form or richneſs of ornament, and would not be ſo bulky as thoſe which are built of bricks. The great difficulty is to prevent their cracking by the heat. Different parts of the ſtove being of very different heats, they expand unequally, and there is no cement which can withſtand this, eſpecially when we recollect that the ſame heat which expands the baked earth cauſes the clay or cement, with which the parts of the ſtove are put together or covered, to contract. Accordingly thoſe earthen ware stoves ſeldom ſtand a winter or two without cracking in ſome place or other, even when strengthened by iron hoops and cramρs judiciouſly diſpoſed within them. Even hooping them externally, which would be very unsightly, will not prevent this ; for nothing can resiſt the expanſion and contraction by heat and cold. When a crack happens in a ſtove, it is not only unſightly, but highly dangerous ; becauſe it may be ſo ſituated, that it will diſcharge into the room the air vitiated by the fire.</p><p>For theſe and other reaſons, we can ſcarcely hope tσ make ſtoves of brick-work or pottery which ſhall bear the necessary heat without cracking ; and their uſe muſt therefore be confined to cases where very moderate heat is ſufficient. We need not deſcribe their conſtruction. It is evident that it ſhould be more simple than that of iron ſtoves ; and we imagine that in the very few caſes in which they are likely to be employed in this country, a single fire place and an arch over it, divided, if we pleaſe, by a partition or two of thin tile to lengthen the flue, will be quite enough. If the ſtove is made in whole or in part of potters ware, a baſe for the fire-place, with an urn, column, obeliſk, or pyramid above it, for increasing the ſurface, will alſo be ſufficient. The failure commonly happens at the joinings, where the different pieces of a different heat, and perhaps of a different baking, are apt to expand unequally, and by working on each other one of them muſt give way. Therefore, inſtead of making the joints cloſe and using any cement, the upper piece ſhould ſtand in a groove formed in the undermoſt, having a little powdered chalk or clay ſprinkled over it, which will effectually prevent the paſſage of any air ; and room being thus given for the unequal expanſion, the joint remains entire. This may be considered as a general direction for all furnacework, where it is in vain to attempt to hinder the mutual working of the parts.</p><p>We have ſeen ſtoves in ſmall apartments at St Peterſburg, which were made internally of potters ware, in a great variety of forms, and then covered with a thick coat of ſtucco, finiſhed externally with the utmoſt elegance of ornament, and we were informed that they were very rarely ſubject to crack. They did not give much heat, on account of the very low conducting power of the porous ſtucco ; but we imagine that they would be abundantly warm for a moderate room in this country.</p><p>When fitted up in theſe situations, and with theſe precautions, the brick or pottery ſtoves are incomparably more ſweet and pleaſant than the iron ones.</p><p>But in the intenſe colds of Ruſſia and Sweden, or even for very large rooms in this kingdom, ſtoves of theſe ſmall dimenſions are not ſufficiently powerful, and we muſt follow the practice of thoſe countries where they are made of great ſize, and very moderately heated. It is needleſs to deſcribe their external form, which may be varied at pleaſure. Their internal ſtructure is the ſame in all, and is diſtinctly deſcribed in <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics,</hi> n⁰ 364, We ſhall only enlarge a little on the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0822.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0816"/>
peculiarities connected with the general principle of their conſtruction.</p><p>The ſtove is intended as a fort oſ magazine, in which a great quantity of heat may be quickly accumulated, to be afterwards ſlowly communicated to the air of the room. The ſtove is therefore built extremely maſſive ; and it is found that they are more powerful when coated with clay as wet as can be made to hang together. We imagine the reaſon of this to be, that very wet clay, and more particularly ſtucco, muſt be exceedingly porous when dry, and therefore a very slow conductor of heat. Inſtead of sticking on the glazed tiles with no more clay or ſtucco than is sufficient to attach them, each tile has at its back a sort of box baked in one piece about two or three inches deep. It is represented in fig. 2. This is filled with mortar, and then ſtuck on the brick-work of the ſtove, which has a great number of iron pins or hooks driven into the joints, which may sink into this clay and keep it firmly attached when dry. This coating, with the maſſive brick-work, forms a great maſs of matter to be heated by the fuel. The loweſt chamber, which is the fire-place, is ſomewhat wider, and considerably thicker than the ſtories above, which are merely flues. When the fire-place is finiſhed and about to be arched over, a flat iron bar of ſmall thickneſs is laid along the top of the ſide-wall on both ſides, a ſet of finiſhing bricks being moulded on purpoſe with a notch to receive the iron bar. Croſs bars are laid over theſe, one at each end and one or two between, having a bit turned down at the ends, which takes hold of the longitudinal bars, and keeps them from being thruſt outwards either by the preſſure of the arch or by the ſwelling in conſequence of the heat. In fig. 3. A is the croſs ſection of one of the long bars, and BC is part of one of the croſs bars, and CD is the clench which confines the bar A. This precaution is chiefly neceſſary, becauſe the contraction of the ſtove upwards obliges the walls of the other stories to bear a little on the arch of the fire-place. The building above is kept together in like manner by other courſes of iron bars at every ſecond return of the flue. The top of the ſtove is finiſhed by a pretty thick covering of brick-work. The laſt paſſage for the air at H (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics,</hi> fig. 62.) has a ring lining its upper extremity, and projecting an inch or two above it. The flat round it is covered with sand. When we would stop this paſſage, a cover ſhaped like a baſon or cover for diſhes at table is whelmed over it. The rim of this, reſting on the sand, effectually prevents all air from coming through and getting up the vent. Acceſs is had to this damper by a door which can be ſhut tight enough to prevent the heated air of the room from wasting itſelf up the vent. When the room is too warm, it may be very rapidly cooled by opening this door. The warm air ruſhes up with great rapidity, and is replaced by cool air from without.</p><p>The management of the ſtove is as follows. About eight o’clock in the morning the p <hi rend="italic">ietchnick,</hi> or servant who has the charge of the ſtoves, takes off the cover, ſhuts the damper-door, and opens the fire-place door. He then puts in a handful of wood ſhavings orſtraw, and kindles it. This warms the ſtove and vent, and begins a current of air through it. He then lays a few chips on the ſole of the fire-place, immediately within the door; and behind this he arranges the billets oſ birchwood, with their ends inwards. Then he lays on more wood in the front, till he thinks there is enough. He ſets fire to the chips, ſhuts the door, and opens the ſmall wicket at its bottom. The air blows the flame of the chips upon the billets behind them, and thus kindles them. They conſume ſlowly, while the billets in front remain untouched by the fire. The fervant, having made his firſt round of the rooms, returns to this ſtove, and opens the door above to admit air into the vent. This is to ſupply its draught, and thus to check the draught in the body of the ſtove, which is generally too ſtrong at this time, and would coniume the fuel too faſt. By this time the billets in the front are burning, firſt at the bottom, and the rest in ſucceſſion as they sink down on the embers and come oppoſite to the wicket. The room does not yet feel any effect from the fire, the heat of which has not yet reached its external ſurface ; but in about half an hour this grows warm. The upper door is ſhut again, that no heat may now be wasted. The pietchnik by and by ſpreads the embers and allies over the whole bottom of the fire-place with a rake, by which the bottom is greatly heated, and heats the air contiguous to it externally (for it ſtands on little pillars) very powerfully. He takes care to bring up to the top of the aſhes every bit of wood or coal that is not yet conſumed, that all may be completely expended. He does this as briskly as poſſible, that the room may not loſe much warmed air by keeping open the fire-place door. At his laſt viſit, when he obſerves no more glowing embers, he ſhuts the fire-place door and wicket, and puts the damper on the paſſage above, and ſhuts its door.—All this is over in about an hour and a half after kindling the fire. All current of air is now at an end within the ſtove, and it is now a great maſs of brick-work, heated to a great degree within, but only about blood-warm externally. The heat gradually ſpreads outwards, and the external ſurface of the ſtove acquires its greateſt heat about three o’clock in the afternoon; after which it gradually cools till next morning.</p><p>This heat ſeldom is so great that one cannot bear to touch the ſtove with his cheek, and to keep it there. In conſequence of this it can burn none of the dust which unavoidably falls on the ſtove, and we are never troubled with the ſickening ſmells that are unavoidable when we employ the ſmall caſt iron ſtoves much heated. The great expence of heat in a room ariſes from the glaſs windows. The pane is ſo thin that the external air keeps it continually cold, and thus the windows are continually robbing the air of the room of its heat. This expence of heat is reduced to leſs than one third by double caſements. The inner caſement is about as much colder than the room as the outer caſement is warmer than the air of the fields; and we have the singular advantage of having no ice formed on the glaſſes. But to enſure this laſt advantage, the seams of the inner caſement muſt be pasted with paper, and thoſe of the outer caſement muſt be left unpaſted. If we do the contrary, we ſhall certainly have ice on the outer caſement ; the reaſon of which is eaſily ſeen.</p><p>We have been thus particular in our deſcription of the management, becauſe the reaſons of ſome particulars are not very obvious, and the practice would not readily occur to us in this country; so that a person who, on the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0823.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0817"/>
faith of our recommendation, ſhould prefer one of theſe ſtoves to the German stove, whoſe management is simple and obvious, might be greatly disappointed. But by following this method, we are confident that the Russian ſtove will be found much ſuperior both in warmth and agreeable air. The ſpreading out of the embers, and waiting till all is reduced to aſhes before the doors are ſhut, is alſo abſolutely necessary, and a neglect of it would expoſe us to imminent danger of ſuffocation by fixed air; and this is the only inconvenience of the Russian ſtove, from which the other ſtove is free. The fixed air has no ſmell ; and the firſt indication of its preſence is a slight giddineſs and laſſitude, which diſpoſes us to sit down and to ſleep. This would be fatal; and we muſt immediately open the upper paſſage and the fire-place door, ſo as to produce a ſtrong current to carry the vitiated air of the room up the chimney. Throwing up the ſaſhes, or at leaſt opening all the doors, is proper on ſuch an occasion.</p><p>If we burn pit-coal, either raw or charred, this precaution is ſtill more necessary; becauſe the cinder is not ſo eaſily or ſo ſoon completely confirmed. This fuel will require a little difference in the management from wood fuel, but which is eaſily ſeen by any perſon of reflection. The ſafe way would be to rake out all half-burnt coal before ſhutting up the doors.</p><p>If we uſe raw pit-coal, great care is necessary to prevent the accumulation of soot in the upper part of the ſtove. It is an inaccessible place for the chimney ſweep; and if we attempt to burn it out, we run a great risk of ſplitting that part of the ſtove which is the moſt slightly conſtructed. It is adviſable therefore to burn it away every day, by giving a brisk draught with an open door for five minutes. With wood or coak there is no danger.</p><p>It will not be improper in this place to give ſome instructions for the conſtruction of ſtoves for warming ſeveral floors in a great manufactory, ſuch as a cottonmill, or a public library or muſeum.</p><p>In ſuch situations we think cleanliness, wholesomeneſs, and ſweetneſs of air, no leſs necessary than in the drawing room of a man of opulence. We therefore recommend the brick-ſtove in preference to the iron one; and though it would not be the beſt or moſt economical practice to heat it but once a-day, and we ſhould rather prefer the German practice oſ constant feeding, we still think it highly proper to limit the heat to a very moderate degree, and employ a large ſurface.</p><p>If the dispoſition of the rooms allows us the conveniency of a thick party-wall, we would place the ſtove in the middle of this wall, in an arch which pierces through the wall. Immediately above this arch we would carry up a very wide chimney through the whole height. This chimney muſt have a passage opening into each floor on both ſides, which may be very accurately ſhut up by a door. The ſtove being ſet up under the arch, it muſt have a pipe communicating with its flue, and rising up through this chimney. Could an earthen pipe be properly ſupported, and ſecured from ſplitting by hoops, we ſhould prefer it for the reaſons already given. But as this is perhaps expecting too much, we muſt admit the uſe of a cast iron pipe. This is the real chimney or flue of the ſtove, and muſt be of as great diameter as poſſible, that it may act, by an extensive ſurface, all the way up.</p><p>The ſtove ſtands under the arch in the wall ; but the air that is warmed by its ſurface would eſcape on both tides, and would be expended in that single floor. To prevent this, the ſtove muſt be incloſed in a caſe : this may be of brick-work, at the diſtance of two or three inches from the ſtove all round. It muſt be well ſhut in above, and at the foundation muſt have a row of ſmall holes to admit the air all around it. This air will then be warmed over the whole ſpace between the ſtove and the caſe, pal’s up the chimney, and there receive additional heat from the flue-pipe which is in the middle. Great care muſt be taken that the fire-place door have no communication with the ſpace between the ſtove and its caſe, but be incloſed in a mouth-piece which comes through the caſe, and opens into the feeding room. Thus all the air which goes up to the rooms will be pure and wholeſome, provided we take care that every thing be kept clean and ſweet about the air holes below. Obſerve that thoſe air-holes which are near the furnace door muſt be incloſed in a wooden trunk which takes in its air at ſome diſtance from this door ; for ſince the current between the ſtove and caſe may be almoſt as great as the current within the ſtove (nay, when a puff of wind beats down the chimney, it may even exceed it), there is a risk of ſome vitiated air and ſrnoke being drawn into the caſe.</p><p>If the ſtove cannot be placed in the arch of a partywall, it may be ſet adjoining to a ſide or outer wall, and furniſhed with a caſe, a large chimrrey, and a fluepipe, in the ſame manner. But in this caſe a great deal of heat is wasted on this outer wall, and carried off by the external air. In this ſituation we would recommend to line that part of the wall which is behind the ſtove (at two or three inches diſtance), and the whole of the chimney, with platter on laths. Theſe ſhould be nailed on battens properly fattened on the wall, leaving a ſpace of an inch between the laths and the wall. The platter ſhould be of the moſt ſpungy kind, having in it a quantity of clay in powder inſtead of the full proportion of land. Horſe-dung, waſhed with water and ſtrained through coarſe flannel, leaves a great portion of unaſſimilated vegetable fibre, which will mix very intimately in the plaſter, and make it a ſubſtance very unfit for conducting heat. There is no danger of catching fire by this lining. We have ſeen a moſt tremendous fire rage for three hours, in contact with a partition of lath and plaſter (on the plaſter-ſide however), without diſcolouring the thin laths on the other ſide. We once ſaw a cottage chimney on fire, and burn till the ſoot was conſumed. This chimney was nothing but a pipe of a foot wide, made of lathes, and plaſtered on the inside and outſide; and it paſſed through a thatched roof. We therefore recommend this in place of the brick-caſe for incloſing the ſtove. It would save heat; and as it might be made in pieces on detached frames, which could be joined by iron ſtraps and hinges, any part of the ſtove could be laid open for repairs at pleaſure.</p><p>We have no heſitation in saying that a ſtove conſtructed in this manner would be greatly ſuperior in power to any we have ſeen, and would be free from many of their diſguſting defects. We beg leave therefore to conclude this part of the ſubject by describing one which was to have been erected in one of the churches of the city of Edinburgh.</p><p>Fig. 4. is a sketch of the plan of the church contain<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0824.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0818"/>
ed in the parallelogram AFED. P marks the place of the pulpit, and LMNO the front of the galleries. Theſe are carried back to the side walls AB and DC. But at the end oppoſite to the pulpit they do not reach ſo far, but leave a ſpace BFEC about 12 ſeet wide. Below the back of the galleries, on each side, there is a paſſage ABGH, KICD, ſeparated from the ſeated part of the church by partitions which reach from the floor to the galleries, ſo that the ſpace HGIK is completely shut in. The church is an ancient Gothic building, of a light and airy structure, having two rows of large windows above the arcades, and a ſpacious window in the eaſt end above the pulpit. The congregation complain of a cold air, which they feel pouring down upon their heads. This is more particularly felt by thoſe fitting in the fronts of the galleries. We imagine that this ariſes chiefly from the extenſive ſurface of the upper row of windows, and of the cold ſtone-walls above, which robs the air of its heat as it glides up along the ſides of the church. It becomes heavier by collapſing, and in this state deſcends in the middle of the church.</p><p>The ſtove S is placed againſt the middle of the west wall at the diſtance of a lew inches, and is completely incloſed in a caſe of lath and plaſter. The vent, which is to carry off the ſmoke and burnt air, is conveyed up or along the wall, and through the roof or side-wall, but without any communication with the case. In like manner the fire-place door is open to the paſſage, without communicating with the caſe; and care is taken that the holes which admit the air into the caſe are ſo diſpoſed that they ſhall run no riſk of drawing in any air from the fire-place door.</p><p>From the top of this caſe proceed two trunks Q,R, each of which is two feet broad and six inches deep, coated within and without with the moſt spungy plaſter that can be compoſed. For this purpoſe we ſhould recommend a compoſition of powdered charcoal and as much clay and quicklime as will give it a very slight coheſion. We know that a piece of this may be held in the hand, without inconvenience, within an inch of where it is of a glowing red heat.—Theſe trunks open into another trunk XVTYZ, which ranges along the partition immediately under the galleries, and may be formed externally into a corniche, a little massive indeed, but not unſightly in a building of this ſtyle. This trunk is coated in the ſame manner. It has ſeveral openings <hi rend="italic">a, a, &amp;c.</hi> which have sliders that can be drawn aſide by means of handles acceſſible from the outer paſſage.—At the extremities X and Z of this trunk are two perpendicular trunks which come up through the galleries, and are continued to a conſiderable height. At their junction with the horizontal trunk are two doors large enough to admit a lamp. Each perpendicular trunk has alſo a valve by which it can be completely stopped.</p><p>The ſtove is managed as follows : Early in the morning the ſuperintendant ſhuts all the sliders, and ſets a lamp (burning) in each of the trunks X and Z; and ſhuts the doors. He then puts on and kindles the fire in the ſtove, and manages it either in the Russian or German method. Perhaps the latter is preferable, as being liable to feweſt accidents from miſtake or neglect.</p><p>The lamps ſet in the lower ends of the upright trunks preſently warm them, and produce a current of air upwards. This muſt be ſupplied by the horizontal trunk, which muſt take it from the caſe round the ſtove. Thus a current is begun in the direction we wiſh. By and by the air in the caſe acquires heat from the ſtove, and the current becomes extremely briſk. When the manager perceives this, he removes the lamps, ſhuts the valves, and opens the holes <hi rend="italic">a, a,</hi> &amp;c. beginning with the moſt remote, and proceeding ſlowly towards the ſtove from each extremity of the horizontal branches. The heated air now iſſues by theſe holes, glides along the ceiling below the galleries, and eſcapes, by rising up along the fronts of the galleries, and will be ſenſibly felt by thoſe sitting there, coming on their faces with a gentle warmth. It will then riſe (in great part) ſtraight up, while ſome of it will glide backwards, to the comfort of thoſe who sit behind.</p><p>The propriety of ſhuttſhg the valves of the upright trunks is evident. If they were left open, no air would come out by the holes <hi rend="italic">a, a,</hi> &amp;c. ; but, on the contrary, the air would go in at theſe holes to ſupply the current, and the ſtove be rendered uſeleſs. The air delivered by theſe holes will keep cloſe to the ceiling, and will not, as we imagine, incommode thoſe who fit below the galleries. But if it ſhould be found to render theſe parts too warm, holes may be pierced through the ceiling, by which it will riſe among the people above, and muſt be very comfortable. It will require the careful attention of ſome intelligent perlon to bring all this into a proper train at first, by finding the proper apertures of the different holes, ſo as to render the heat equable through the whole ſpace. But this being once aicertained the difficulty is over.</p><p>The air trunks muſt be very capacious, but may be contracted towards the extremities as their lateral diſcharges diminiſh ; and the row of holes which admit the air to the caſe round the ſtove muſt be fully able to ſupply them.</p><p>It muſt be obſerved, that in this conſtruction the aſcenſional force is but ſmall. It is only the height of a ſhort column of warm air from the ground to the galleries. At first indeed it is great, having the unlimited height of the perpendicular trunks at X and Z ; but during the uſe of the ſtove it is reduced to nine or ten feet. it is necessary, therefore, that the ſtove be highly heated, perhaps conſiderably beyond the Russian practice, but yet inferior to the heat of the German iron ſtoves. But ſtill we ſtrongly recommend the brick or pottery ſtoves, on account of the wholesome ſweetness of the air which they furniſh ; and we are certain that a ſtove of moderate dimenſions, eight feet long, for inſtance. by eight feet high, will be sufficient for warming a church holding 1200 or 1500 people. If the ſtove could be placed lower, which in many ſitua- tions is very practicable, its effect would be proportionally greater, becauſe all depends on the rapidity of the current. When we are limited in height, we muſt extend the ſtove ſo much the more in length, and make the air trunks more capacious. Theſe and many other circumſtances of local modification muſt be attended to by the erector of the ſtove ; and without the judicious attention of an intelligent artiſt, we may expect nothing but diſappointment. It is hardly poſſible to give inſtructions ſuited to every ſituation ; but a careful attention to the general principle which determines the aſe cenſional force will free the artiſt from any great riſk of failure.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0825.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0819"/>
We may ſay the ſame thing oſ ſtoves for conſervatories, hot houſes, hot walls, &amp;c. and can hardly add any thing of conſequence to what we have already ſaid on theſe heads in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics.</hi></p><p>We muſt not, however, diſmiſs the ſubject: without taking notice of the very ſpecious projects which have been frequently offered for drying malt by ſtoves. Many of theſe are to be ſeen in the publications of the Academies of Stockholm, Upſal, Copenhagen, and ſome have been erected in this kingdom ; but they have not been found to anſwer.</p><p>We apprehend that they cannot anſwer. To dry malt, and make it fit for the ales and beers for which this iſland is ſo famous, it is by no means enough that we give it a proper and an equable ſupply of heat.— Tlιis alone would bake it and make it flinty, cauſing the moiſture to penetrate the mealy particles of the grain ; and, by completely diſſolving the ſoluble parts, would render each kernel an uniform maſs, which would dry into a flinty grain, breaking like a piece of glaſs. — A grain of malt is not an inert pulp. It is a <hi rend="smallcaps">seed,</hi> in an active ſtate, growing, and of an organized ſtructure. We with to ſtop it in this ſtate, and kill it, not by heating it, but by abſtracting its moiſture. We thus leave it in its granulated or organized form, ſpungy, and fit for imbibing water in the maſh tub, without running into a paſte.</p><p>To accompliſh theſe purpoſes, the conſtruction of our malt kilns ſeems very well adapted. The kiln is the only flue of the furnace, and a copious <hi rend="italic">current of air is</hi> formed through among the grains, carrying off with it the water which is evaporating by the beat. But this evaporation, being chiefly in conſequence of the vapour being immediately diſſolved by the paſſing air, will ſtop as ſoon as the current of air ſtops. This current has to make its way through moiſt grain, laid in a pretty thick bed, and matted together. Some force, therefore, is neceſſary to drive it through. This is furniſhed by the draught of the kiln. Subſtituting a ſtove, immediately applied to the malt, will not have this effect. The only way in which we think this can be done different from the preſent, is to have a horizontal flue, as has been propoſed in theſe projects, ſpread out at a ſmall diſtance below the grate on which the malt is laid, and to cover the whole with a high dome, like a glaſs houſe dome. This being filled with a tall column of hot air, and having no paſſage into it but through the malt, would produce the current which we want. We are convinced that this will make much leſs fuel ſerve ; but we are by no means certain that the ſulphureous and carbonic acid which accompanies the air in our common kiln is not a neceſſary or a uſeful ingredient in the proceſs. It is well known that different coaks, cinders, or chai coals, impart different qualities to the malts, and are preferred <hi rend="italic">each for its own purpoſe.</hi> Were this a matter of indifference, we know a method of rapidly drying malt much more economical and expeditious than by either kiln or ſtove. But this has nothing to do with our preſent ſubject, of which we now take leave.</p></div></body></text></TEI>