<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0737.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0731-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STATISTICS</label>,
a word lately introduced to express a view or ſurvey of any kingdom, county, or parish.</p><p>A Statiſtical view of Germany was publiſhed in 1790 by Mr B. Clarke; giving an account of the imperial and territorial constitutions, forms of government, legiſlation, adminiſtration of justice, and of the eccleliaſtical ſtate ; with a sketch of the character and genius of the Germans ; a ſhort inquiry into the ſtate of their trade and commerce; and giving a distinct view of the dominions, extent, number of inhabitants to a ſquare mile ; chief towns, with their ſize and population; revenues, expences, debts, and military ſtrength oſ each ſtate. In Pruſſia, in Saxony, Sardinia, and Tuſcany, attempts have alſo been made to draw up ſtatiſtical accounts; but they were done rather with a view of ascertaining the preſent ſtate of theſe countries, than as the means of future improvement.</p><p>A grand and extensive work of this kind, founded on a judicious plan, conducted by the moſt patriotic and enlightened motives, and drawn up from the communications of the whole body of the clergy, was undertaken in Scotland in the year 1790 by Sir John Sinclair of Ulbſter, one of the moſt uſeful members of his country. Many praiſes are heaped upon genius and learning; but to genius and learning no applauſe is due, except when exerted for the benefit of mankind: but gratitude and praiſe is due to him whoſe talents ſhine only in great undertakings, whoſe happineſs ſeems to conſiſt in patriotic exertions, and whoſe judgment is uniformly approved by his ſuccess. A work of this kind, ſo important in its object, io comprehensive in its range, ſo judicious in its plan, and drawn up by more than 900 men of literary education, many of them men of great genius and learning, muſt be of immenſe value. Sixteen volumes octavo are already publiſhed ; and it is ſuppoſed that the work will be completed in two or three additional volumes.</p><p>The great object of this work is to give an accurate view of the ſtate of the country, its agriculture, its manufactures, and its commerce; the means of improvement, of which they are reſpectively capable; the amount of the population of a ſtate, and the cauſes of its increase<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0738.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0732"/>
or decreaſe; the manner in which the territory of a country is poſſeſſed and cultivated ; the nature and amount of the various productions of the ſoil ; the value of the perſonal wealth or stock of the inhabitants, and how it can be augmented; the diſeaſes to which the people are ſubject, their cauſes and their cure ; the occupations of the people ; where they are entitled to encouragement, and where they ought to be ſuppreſſed ; the condition of the poor, the beſt mode of maintaining them, and of giving them employment ; the ſtate of ſchools, and other inſtitutions, formed for purpoſes of public utility; theſtate of the villages and towns, and the regulations beſt calculated for their police and good government; the ſtate of the manners, the morals, and the religious principles of the people, and the means by which their temporal and eternal intereſts can beſt be promoted.</p><p>To ſuch of our readers as have not an opportunity of peruſing this national work, or of examining its plan, we will preſent the ſcheme for the ſtatiſtical account of a parochial diſtrict which Sir John Sinclair publiſhed for the consideration of the clergy, and which has been generally followed by them, though often with great improvements.</p><p>The name of the pariſh and its origin ; ſituation and extent of the pariſh ; number of acres ; deſcription of the soil and ſurface ; nature and extent of the ſea-coaſt; lakes, rivers, iſlands, hills, rocks, caves, woods, orchards, &amp;c.; climate and diſeaſes ; inſtances of longevity ; ſtate oſ property; number of proprietors ; number of reſiding proprietors ; mode of cultivation; implements of huſbandry; manures; ſeedtime and harveſt; remarkable inſtances of good and bad ſeaſons; quantity and value of each ſpecies of crop; total value of the whole produce of the diſtrict ; total real and valued rent ; price of grain and proviſions ; total quantity of grain and other articles confirmed in the pariſh ; wages and price of labour ; ſervices, whether exacted or aboliſhed; commerce; manufactures; manufacture of kelp,its amount, and the number of people employed in it; fiſheries; towns and villages; police; inns and alehouſes; roads and bridges; harbours; ferries, and their ſtate; number of ſhips and veſſels; number of ſeamen; state of the church ; ſtipend, manſe, globe, and patron ; number of poor ; parochial funds, and the management of them ; ſtate of the ſchools, and number of scholars ; ancient ſtate of population ; cauſes of its increaſe or decreaſe ; number of families ; exact amount of the number of souls now living; diviſion of the inhabitants; I. by the place of their birth ; 2. by their ages ; 3. by their religious perſuaſions ; 4. by their occupations and ſituation in life; 5. by their reſidence, whether in town, village, or in the country ; number of houſes ; number of uninhabited houſes ; number of dovecots, and to what extent they are deſtructive to the crops ; number of horſes, their nature and value; number of cattle, their nature and value ; number of ſheep, their nature and value ; number of ſwine, their nature and value ; minerals in general; mineral ſprings; coal and fuel; eminent men; antiquities ; parochial records ; miscellaneous obſervations ; character of the people; their manners, customs, stature, &amp;c. ; advantages and diſadvantages ; means by which their ſituation could be meliorated.</p><p>If ſimilar ſurveys (says the public-ſpirited editor of this work) were inſtituted in the other kingdoms of Europe, it might be the means of eſtabliſhing, on ſure foundations, the principles of that moſt important of all ſciences, viz. political or ſtatiſtical philoſophy ; that is, the ſcience, which, in preference to every other, ought to be held in reverence. No ſcience can furniſh, to any mind capable of receiving uſeful information, ſo much real entertainment; none can yield ſuch important hints, for the improvement of agriculture, for the extenſion of commercial induſtry, for regulating the conduct of individuals, or for extending the prosperity of the ſtate ; none can tend ſo much to promote the general happineſs of the ſpecies.</p></div></body></text></TEI>