<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0800.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0794-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STERNA</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">Tern;</hi> a genus of birds arranged under the order of <hi rend="italic">palmipedes.</hi> The marks of this genus are a ſtraight, ſlender, pointed bill, linear nostrils, a ſlender and ſharp tongue, very long wings, a ſmall back toe, and a forked tail. There are 25 ſpecies, according to Dr Latham ; the caſpia, cayana, ſurinamenſis, fuliginoſa, africana, ſtolida, philippina, ſimplex, nilotica, boysii, ſtriata, vittata, ſpadicea, piſcata, hirundo, panaya, cinerea, alba, minuta, ſinendis, auſtralis, metopoleucos, fiſſipes, nigra, and obſcura. Three of theſe only are found in Great Britain ; the hirundo, minuta, and fiſſipes.</p><p>I. The hi <hi rend="italic">rundo,</hi> common tern, or great ſea-ſwallow, weighs four ounces one-quarter; the length is 14 inches; the breadth 30 ; the bill and feet are of a fine crimſon ; the former tipt with black, ſtraight, ſlender, and ſharp-pointed ; the crown, and hind part of the head, black ; the throat, and whole underſide of the body, white ; the upper part, and the coverts of the wings, a fine pale grey. The tail conſiſts of 12 feathers ; the exterior edges of the three outmoſt are grey, the rest white ; the exterior on each side is two inches longer than the others : in flying, the bird frequently cloſes them together, ſo as to make them appear one ſlender feather.</p><p><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Latham's Synopsis, vol. vii.</p></note> This is a very common ſpecies ; frequents our ſea- coaſts and banks of lakes and rivers during the ſummer, but moſt common in the neighbourhood of the ſea. It is found alſo in various parts of Europe and Aſia, according to the ſeaſon ; in the ſummer as far as Greenland and Spitzbergen, migrating in turn to the ſouth of Auſtria and Greece. It lays three or four eggs about the month of June, of a dull olive colour, an inch and three quarters in length, marked with irregular black ſpots, intermixed with ſome others of a ſmaller ſize, and leſs bright : the little end is almoſt free from any markings. Theſe are laid among the graſs or moſs. The young are hatched in July, and quit the neſt very ſoon after. They are carefully fed by their parents, and fly in about six weeks. This bird appears to have all the actions on the water which the ſwallow has on land, ſkimming on the ſurface, and ſeizing on every infect which comes in its way ; beſides which, the moment it spies a fiſh in the water, it darts into that clement, and ſeizing its prey ariſes as quickly to the place from which it dipped.</p><p>Theſe birds are alſo found in America ; come into New England in May, and go away in autumn, and are called there the mackarel gull. At Hudſon’s Bay they are known by the name of black-head. They are obſerved to lay their eggs in ſmall hollows on the shore, ſometimes lined with a few leaves. They are often found in great numbers on the iſlets in the middle of the rivers, and are thought good eating. The natives of Hudſon’s Bay call them <hi rend="italic">Kenouch ene ou keask.</hi> They are bold, not fearing mankind, and in the time of incubation will attack any one, frequently darting down ſo as to touch a perſon’s. hat, without his giving the leaſt offence.</p><p>2. The <hi rend="italic">minuta,</hi> or ſmaller ſea-ſwallow, (called by Linnæus <hi rend="italic">larus minuta),</hi> weighs only two ounces five grains ; 'the length 8 inches and a half; the breadth 19 and a half. The bill is yellow, tipt with black ; the forehead and cheeks white ; from the eyes to the bill is a black line ; the top of the head and hind part black ; the breaſt and under side of the body clothed with feathers ſo cloſely ſet together, and or ſuch an exquiſite rich gloſs and ſo fine a white, that no ſatin can be compared to it: the back and wings of a pale grey : the tail ſhort, leſs forked than that of the former, and white : the legs yellow : the irides dusky.—Theſe two ſpecies are very delicate, and ſeem unable to bear the inclemency of the weather on our ſhores during winter, for we obſerve that they quit their breeding places at the approach of it, and do not return till ſpring. The manners, haunts, and food of this ſpecies are the ſame with thoſe of the former ; but they are far leſs numerous.</p><p>3. The fissip <hi rend="italic">es,</hi> or black tern, is of a middle ſize between the first and second ſpecies. The usual length is 10 inches ; the breadth 24 ; the weight two ounces and a hall The head, neck, breaſt, and belly, as far as the vent, are black ; beyond is white ; the male has a white foot under its chin ; the back and wings are of a deep ash colour : the tail is ſhort and forked ; the exterior feather on each side is white ; the others aſh-coloured : the legs and feet oſ a dusky red. Mr Ray calls this a <hi rend="italic">cloven-footed gull,</hi> as the webs are depreſsed in the middle, and form a creſcent. Theſe birds frequent freſh waters, breed on their banks, and lay three ſmall eggs of a deep olive colour, much ſpotted with black. They are found during ſpring and ſummer in vaſt numbers in the Fens of Lincolnſhire, make an incessant noiſe, and feed on flies as well as water infects and ſmall fiſh. Birds of this ſpecies are ſeen very remote from land. Kalm law flocks of hundreds in the Atlantic Ocean, midway between England and America, and a later voyager saw one 240 leagues from the Lizard, in the ſame ocean.</p></div></body></text></TEI>