<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0781.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0775-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STEEL</label>
·, iron united with carbone. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Iron.</hi></p><p>Steel has properties diſtinct from thoſe of iron, which render it of ſuperior value. From its higher degree of hardneſs it admits a finer poliſh and aſſumes a brighter colour. When tempered, it poſſesses a higher degree of elaſticity, and is alſo more ſonorous. It is more weakly attracted by the loadſtone, it receives more ſlowly the magnetic power, but it preſerves it longer. When expoſed to a moist air, it does not contract ruſt ſo eaſily as<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0782.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0776"/>
iron. It is alſo heavier, increaſing in weight, according to Chaptal, one hundred and ſeventieth part. M. Rin- man has given as the remit of ſeveral accurate experiments on different kinds of ſteel the following specific gravity 7,795, while he makes ductile iron 7,700, and crude iron 7,251.</p><p>All iron is convertible into ſteel by exposing it to a certain degree oſ heat for a certain time along with a quantity of charcoal. Chemiſts differ in opinion concerning the nature and effects of this proceſs. Some ſay that ſteel is produced by abſorbing a quantity of caloric or heat in a latent ſtate, as the older chemiſts had ſaid it; was formed by abſorbing phlogiston. Lavoiſier ſeems to have aſcribed the qualities of ſteel to a slight degree of oxidation, others to a combination with plumbago or black lead, and others to a union with carbone. In agreeing with thoſe who ſay the formation of ſteel is owing to carbone, we do not differ effen- tially from thoſe who attribute it to plumbago ; for the art of chemiſtry has now found that theſe ſubſtances are very nearly allied. Plumbago is a true charcoal combined with a little iron. The brilliant charcoal of certain vegetable ſubſtances, more eſpecially when formed by diſtillation in cloſe veſſels, posseſſes all the characters of plumbago.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Chaptal's Chemistry, vol. ii. p. 347.</p></note> The charcoal of animal ſubſtances poffeſſes characters ſtill more peculiarly reſembling it. Like it they are difficult to incinerate, they leave the ſame impreſſion on the hands and upon paper; they likewise contain iron, and become converted into carbonic acid by combuſtion. When animal ſubſtances are diſtilled by a ſtrong fire, a very fine powder sublimes, which attaches itſelf to the inner part ot the neck of the retort, and this ſubſtance may be made into excellent black lead pencils.</p><p>There are two ways oſ making ſteel, namely, by fu- ſion and by cementation. The firſt way is uſed to convert iron into ſteel immediately from the ore, or from crude or caſt-iron. By the ſecond way, bar-iron is expoſed to a long continued heat ſurrounded by charcoal. Each of theſe ways has advantages peculiar to itſelf ; but the ſame cauſes in fact predominate in both, for both kinds of ſteel are produced by heat and charcoal. The only difference between the two methods is this ; in making ſteel by fuſion the charcoal is not ſo equally defended from the acceſs of air as in the other way.</p><p>Swedenborgius has given the following deſcription oſ the method uſed in Dalecarlia for making ſteel from caſt-iron. The ore from which the crude iron to be converted into ſteel is obtained is of a good kind. It is black, friable, and compoſed of many ſmall grains, and it produces very tough iron. The converſion into ſteel is made upon a forge-hearth, ſomething ſmaller than common. The sides and bottom are made of caſt-iron. The tuyere is placed, with very little inclination, on one of the ſide-plates. The breadth of the fire-place is fourteen inches ; its length is greater. The lower part of the tuyere is fix inches and a half above the bottom. In the interior part of the fire-place there is an oblong opening for the flowing of the superfluous scoriæ. The workmen firſt put scoriæ on the bottom, then charcoal and powder of charcoal, and upon theſe the caſt-iron run or cut into ſmall pieces. They cover the iron with more charcoal, and excite the fire. When the pieces of iron are of a red white, and before they begin to melt, they ſtop the bellows, and carry the maſs under a large hammer, where they break it into pieces of three or four pounds each. The pieces are again brought to the hearth, and laid within reach of the workman, who plunges ſome of them into the fire, and covers them with coal. The bellows are made to blow ſlowly till the iron is liquefied. Then the fire is increaſed ; and when the fuſion has been long enough continued, the scoriæ are allowed to flow out ; and at that time the iron hardens. The workman adds more of the pieces of crude iron, which he treats in the ſame manner ; and ſo on a third and a fourth time, till he obtains a maſs of ſteel of about a hundred pounds, which is generally done in about four hours. This maſs is raiſed and carried to the hammer, where it is forged, and cut into four pieces, which are farther beat into ſquare bars four or five feet long. When the ſteel is thus forged, it is thrown into water that it may be eaſily broken ; for it is yet crude and coarſe-grained. The ſteel is then carried to another hearth ſimilar to the former, and there broken in pieces. Theſe pieces are laid regularly in the fire-place, firſt two parallel, upon which ſeven or eight others are placed acroſs ; then a third row acroſs the ſecond, in ſuch a manner that there is ſpace left between thoſe of the ſame row. The whole is then covered with charcoal, and the fire is excited. In about half or three quarters of an hour the pieces are made hot enough, and are then taken from the fire, one by one, to the hammer, to be forged into little bars from half a foot to two feet long, and while hot are thrown into water to be hardened. Of theſe pieces sixteen or twenty are put together ſo as to make a bundle, which is heated and welded, and afterwards forged into bars four inches thick, which are then broken into pieces of convenient length for uſe.</p><p>The method of converting iron into ſteel by cementation is a very simple proceſs. It consists ſolely in ex- posing it for a certain time to a ſtrong degree of heat, while cloſely covered with charcoal and defended from the external air. The furnaces employed for converting iron into ſteel (ſays a manufacturer of this metal) are of different sizes ; ſome capable of converting only three or four tons weight, while others are capacious enough to contain from ſeven to eight or ten tons. The outſides of theſe furnaces riſe up in the form of a cone, or ſugar-loaf, to the height of a very conſiderable number of feet. In the inside, oppoſite to each other, are placed two very long cheſts, made either of ſtone, or of bricks capable of bearing the ſtrongeſt fire ; which is placed between the two cheſts. The bars of iron, after the bottom is furniſhed with a neceſſary quantity of charcoal duſt, are laid in st <hi rend="italic">ratum ſuper stratum,</hi> with intermediate beds of the charcoal duſt, to ſuch a height of the cheſts as only to admit of a good bed at top ; which is then all covered over, to prevent the admiſſion of the common air ; which, could it procure an entrance, would greatly injure the operation. The iron being thus situated, the fire is lighted ; which is ſome time before it can be raiſed to a ſufficient degree of heat to produce any conſiderable effect. After which it is continued for ſo many days as the operator may judge proper ; only now and then drawing out what they call a proof bar. This is done by openings fit for the pur- poſe at the ends of the cheſt, which are easily and with expedition stopped up again, without occaſioning any injury to the contents left behind. When the opera<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0783.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0777"/>
tor apprehends the converſion is sufficiently completed, the fire is ſuffered to go out, and the furnace, with its contents, is left gradually to cool. This may take up ſeveral days : after which the furnace is diſcharged, by taking out the bars of ſteel and the remainder of the charcoal duſt.</p><p>There is a manufactory eſtabliſhed in the pariſh of Cramond, about five miles from Edinburgh, in which this method is practiſed with great ſucceſs. Great quantities of ſteel are made there, which we have reaſon to believe is of as excellent a quality as any that can be procured from other countries.</p><p>When the charcoal is taken out, it is found as black as before it was introduced into the furnace, unleſs by accident the external air has got admittance. The bars preſerve their exterior form only ; the ſurface frequently exhibits a great number of tumors or bliſters, whence they are called <hi rend="italic">blistered steel.</hi></p><p>The hardneſs of ſteel is much increaſed by tempering. This conſiſts in heating it to a red heat, and then plunging it ſuddenly into cold water. If it be allowed to cool ſlowly, it still preſerves its ductility ; or if it be heated again after being tempered, it loses its hardneſs, and again becomes ductile. In heating ſteel for tempering it, the moſt remarkable circumſtance is, the different colours it aſſumes, according to the degree of heat it has received. As it is gradually heated, it becomes white, then yellow, orange, purple, violet, and at laſt of a deep blue colour.</p><p>According to Reaumur, the ſteel which is moſt heated in tempering is generally the hardeſt. Hence it is believed, that the more violent the heat to which ſteel is expoſed, and the more ſuddenly it is plunged into cold water, the harder the ſteel will be. Rinman, again, has deduced a conclusion directly oppoſite, that the ſteel which is naturally hardeſt demands the leaſt degree of heat to temper it. Different methods have been propoſed to determine what degree oſ heat is moſt proper ; but the easieſt method is to take a bar of ſteel, ſo long, that while one end is expoſed to a violent heat, the other may be kept cold. By examining the intermediate portions, it may be found what degree of heat has produced the greateſt hardneſs.</p><p>By tempering, ſteel is ſaid to increaſe both in bulk and in weight. Reaumur ſays, that a ſmall bar six inches long, six lines broad, and halt an inch thick, was increaſed at leaſt a line in length after being tempered to a reddiſh white colour ; that is, ſuppoſing the dilatation proportional in all dimenſions increaſing at the rate of 48 to 49. Iron alſo expands when heated ; but when the heat passes off, it returns to its former dimenſions. That the weight of ſteel is alſo augmented by tempering, has been found by experiment. Rinman having weighed exactly in an hydroſtatic balance two kinds of fine ſteel made by cementation, and not tempered, found their denſity to be to that of water as 7,991 to 1 ; after being tempered, the denſity of the one was 7,553, and that of the other 7,708. Μ. de Morveau took three bars juſt of a ſize to enter a certain caliber 28 lines long, and each side two lines broad; one of the bars was ſoft iron, and the two others were taken from the ſame piece of fine ſteel. In order to communicate an equal degree of heat to each, in an earthen veſſel in the midſt of a wind furnace, the bar of ſoft iron and one of the bars of ſteel were thrown into cold water; the other bar of ſteel was cooled ſlowly over ſome pieces of charcoal at a diſtance from the furnace. The bar of iron and the one of ſteel that was allowed to cool ſlowly paſſed eaſily into the caliber again ; but the bar of tempered ſteel was lengthened almoſt one- ninth of a line.</p><p>There is no doubt but tempering changes the grain; that is, the appearance of the texture of a piece of ſteel when broken. This is the mark which is uſually obſerved in judging of the quality of ſteel, or of the tempering which ſuits it beſt. The tempered bar is broken in ſeveral places after having received different degrees of heat in different places. What proves completely the effect of heat upon the grain, at leaſt in ſome kinds of ſteel, is, that a bar of ſteel expoſed to all the intermediate degrees of heat, from the ſmalleſt ſenſible heat to a red heat, is found to increaſe in fineneſs of grain from the ſlightly heated to the ſtrongly heated end. The celebrated Rinman has made many experiments on the qualities of ſteel expoſed to different degrees of heat in tempering, but particularly to three kinds, viz. ſteel heated to an obſcure red, to a bright red, and to a red white. Hard brittle ſteel, made by cementation, and heated to an obſcure red and tempered, exhibited a fine grain, ſomewhat ſhining, and was of a yellow white colour. When tempered at a bright red heat, the grain was coarſer and more shining ; when tempered at a red white heat, the grain was alſo coarſe and ſhining.</p><p>With a view to determine how far ſteel might be improved in its grain by tempering it in different ways, Μ. de Morveau took a bar of bliſtered ſteel, and broke it into four parts nearly of the ſame weight. They were all heated to a red heat in the ſame furnace, and withdrawn from the fire at the ſame inſtant. One of the pieces was left at the side of the furnace to cool in the air, the ſecond was plunged into cold water, the third into oil, and the fourth into mercury. The piece of ſteel that was cooled in the air refilled the hammer a long time before it was broken ; it was necessary to notch it by the file, and even then it was broken with difficulty. It ſhowed in its fracture a grain ſenſibly more fine and more ſhining than it was before. The ſecond piece, which had been plunged into water, broke eaſily : its grain was rather finer than the first, and almoſt of the ſame white colour. The third piece, which was tempered in oil, appeared very hard when tried by the file ; it was ſcarcely poſſible to break it. Its grain was as fine, but not quite ſo bright, as that which was tempered in water. The fourth piece, which was dipped into mercury, was evidently ſuperior to all the rest in the fineneſs and colour of the grain. It broke into many fragments with the first ſtroke of the hammer, the fractures being generally tranſverſe.</p><p>Μ. de Morveau was not altogether ſatisfied with theſe experiments, and therefore thought it necessary to repeat them with finer ſteel. He took a bar of ſteel two lines ſquare, ſuch as is uſed in Germany for tools by engravers and watchmakers ; he divided it into four pieces, and treated them in the ſame way as he had done the bliſtered ſteel. The first piece, which was cooled in the air, it was very difficult to break : the fracture appeared in the midſt of the grain very fine, but white and ſhining. The ſecond, which was tempered in water, was broken into three fragments at the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0784.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0778"/>
firſt blow ; its grain was perfectly equal, of a grey aſh- colour, and of remarkable fineneſs. One of its ſides was poliſhed, and a drop of the nitrous acid which was poured upon it left a black ſpot, but not deep. But when a drop of the ſame acid was poured on the middle of the fracture, after it had been equally poliſhed, it left a black ſpot much deeper. The third piece, which was plunged in oil, bent as eaſily as the piece which was cooled in the air ; the file made an impreſſion on it with difficulty ; it was neceſſary to break it with a vice : its grain was inferior in fineness to the ſecond, but it was of a darker colour. The fourth, which was tempered in mercury, exhibited a grain of an intermediate fineneſs between the ſecond and the third. From theſe experiments, it appears that ſteel may be hardened by tempering it, not only with water, but with any other liquid which is capable of accelerating its cooling.</p><p>Steel may be unmade, or reduced to the ſtate of iron, by a management ſimilar to that by which it is made, that is, by cementation. But the cement uſed for this purpoſe muſt be compoſed of ſubſtances entirely free from inflammable matter, and rather capable of abſorbing it, as calcareous earth or quicklime. By a cementation with calcareous earth, continued during eight or ten hours, ſteel is reduced to the state of iron. After it has been tempered, it may be again untempered, and ſoftened to any degree that we think proper ; for which purpoſe we have only to heat it more or leſs, and to let it cool ſlowly. By this method we may ſoften the hardeſt-tempered ſteel.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Steel-Bow</hi> <hi rend="italic">Tenants.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Tenure.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Salt of</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Steel.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> n⁰ 697.</p><p><hi rend="italic">STEEL-Tard,</hi> is one of the moſt ancient preſents which ſcience has made to ſociety ; and though long in deſuetude in this country, is in moſt nations of the world the only inſtrument for aſcertaining the weight of bodies. What is tranſlated <hi rend="italic">balance</hi> in the Pentateuch, is in fact ſteelyard, being the word uſed by the Arabs to this day for their inſtrument, which is a ſteelyard. It is in common uſe in all the Aſiatic nations. It was the sta <hi rend="italic">tera</hi> of the Greeks and Romans, and ſeems to have been more confided in by them than the balance ; for which reaſon it was uſed by the goldſmiths, while the balance was the inſtrument of the people. — <hi rend="italic">Non aurificis Jlatera Jed populari trutina examinare.</hi> Cic. de Or. 238.</p><p>The ſteelyard is a lever of unequal arms, and, in its moſt perfect form, is conſtructed much like a common balance.@@ It hangs in ſheers E (fig. 1.) reſting on the nail C, and the ſcale L for holding the goods hangs by a nail D on the ſhort arm BC. The counter weight P hangs by a ring of tempered ſteel, made ſharp in the inside, that it may bear by an edge on the long arm CA of the ſteelyard. The under edge of the centre nail C, and the upper edge of the nail D, are in the ſtraight line formed by the upper edge of the long arm. Thus the three points of ſuſpenſion are in one ſtraight line. The needle or index of the ſteelyard is perpendicular to the line of the arms, and plays between the ſheers. The ſhort arm may be made ſo maſſive, that, together with the ſcale, it will balance the long arm. unloaded. When no goods are in the ſcale, and the counter weight with its hook are removed, the ſteelyard acquires a horizontal poſition, in conſequence of its centre of gravity being below the axis of ſuſpenſion, The rules for its accurate conſtruction are the ſame as for a common balance.</p><p>The inſtrument indicates different weights in the following manner : The diſtance CD of the two nails is conſidered as an unit, and the long arm is divided into a number of parts equal to it ; and theſe are ſubdivided as low as is thought proper : or in general, the long arm is made a ſcale of equal parts, commencing at the edge of the nail C; and the ſhort arm contains ſome determined number of thoſe equal parts. Suppoſe, then ;that a weight A of 10 pounds is put into the ſcale L. The counterpoiſe P muſt be of ſuch a weight, that, when hanging at the diviſion 10, it ſhall balance this weight A. Now let any unknown weight W be put into the ſcale. Slide the book of the counterpoiſe along the long arm till it balances this weight Suppoſe it then hanging at the diviſion 38. We conclude that there is 38 pounds in the ſcale. This we do on the authority of the fundamental property of the lever, that forces acting on it, and balancing each other, are in the inverſe proportion of the diſtances from the fulcrum to their lines of direction. Whatever weight the counterpoiſe is, it is to A as CD to 10, and it is to the weight W as CD to 38 ; therefore A is to the weight W as 10 to 38, and W is 38 pounds: and thus the weight in the ſcale will always be indicated by the diviſion at which it is balanced by the counterpoiſe.</p><p>Our well informed readers know that this fundamental property of the lever was diſcovered by the renowned Archimedes, or at leaſt firſt demonſtrated by him ;, and that his demonſtration, beſides the defect of being applicable only to commenſurable lengths of the arms, has been thought by metaphyſicians of the firſt note to proceed on a poſtulate which ſeems equally to need a demonſtration. It has accordingly employed the utmoſt refinement of the firſt mathematicians oſ Europe to furniſh a demonſtration free from objection. Mr D’Alembert has given two, remarkable for their ingenuity and ſubtlety ; Foncenex has done the ſame ; and Profeſſor Hamilton of Trinity-college, Dublin, has given one which is thought the leaſt exceptionable. But critics have even objected to this, as depending on a poſtulate which ſhould have been demonſtrated.</p><p>Since we publiſhed the volume containing the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Mechanics,</hi> there has appeared (Phil. Trani. 1794) a demonſtration by Mr Vince, which we think unexceptionable, and of ſuch ſimplicity that it is aſtoniſhing that it has not occurred to any perſon who thinks on the ſubject. Our readers will not be diſpleaſed with an account of it.</p><p>Let AE (fig. 2.) be a mathematical lever, or inflexible ſtraight line, reſting on the prop A, and ſupported at E by a force acting upwards. Let two equal weights <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d</hi> be hung on at B and D, equidiſtant from A and E. Preſſures are now exerted at A and E ; and becauſe every circumſtance of weight and diſtance is the ſame, the preſſure at E, ariſing from the action of the weight <hi rend="italic">b</hi> on the point B, muſt be the ſame with the preſſure at A, ariſing from the action of the weight <hi rend="italic">d</hi> on the point D ; and the preſſure at E, occaſioned by the weight <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> muſt be the ſame with the preſſure at A, occaſioned by the weight <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> This muſt be the caſe wherever the weights are hung, provided that the diſtance AB and DE are equal, Moreover, @@@[mu] Plate CCCCLXXXI.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0785.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0779"/>
the ſum of the preſſures at A and E is unqueſtionably equal to the ſum of the weights, becauſe the weights are ſupported ſolely at A and E. Let the two weights be hung on at C the middle point ; the preſſure at E is ſtill the same. Therefore, in general, the preſſure excited at the point E, by two equal weights hanging at any points B and D, is the ſame as if they were hung on at the middle point between them : but the preſſure excited at E is a juſt meaſure of the effort or energy of the weights <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d</hi> to urge the lever round the point A. It is, at leaſt, a meaſure of the oppoſite force which muſt b applied at E to ſuſtain or balance this preſſure. A very faſtidious metaphysician may ſtill ſay, that the demonſtration is limited to a point E, whoſe diſtance from A is twice AC, or = AB + AD. But it extends to any other point, on the authority of a postulate which cannot be refuſed, viz. that in whatever proportion the preſſure at E is augmented or diminiſhed, the preſſure at this other point muſt augment or diminiſh in the same proportion. This being proved, the general theorem may be demonſtrated in all proportions of diſtance, in the manner of Archimedes, at once the moſt ſimple, perſpicuous, and elegant of all.</p><p>We cannot help obſerving, that all this difficulty (and it is a real one to the philoſopher who aims at rendering mechanics a demonſtrative ſcience) has ariſen from an improper ſearch after ſimplicity. Had Archimedes taken a lever as it really exiſts in nature, and conſidered it as <hi rend="italic">material,</hi> conſiſting of atoms united by coheſion ; and had he traced the intermediate preſſures by whole means the two external weights are put in oppoſition to each other, or rather to the ſupport given to the fulcrum; all difficulty would have vaniſhed. (See what is ſaid on this ſubject in the article <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Strength</hi> <hi rend="italic">of Timber,</hi> &amp;c. )</p><p>The quantity of goods which may be weighed by th is inſtrument depends on the weight of the counterpoiſe, and on the diſtance CD from the fulcrum at which the goods are ſuſpended. A double counter- poiſe hanging at the ſame diviſion will balance or indicate a double quantity of goods hanging at D ; and any counterpoise will balance and indicate a double quantity of goods, if the diſtance CD be reduced to one- half. Many ſteelyards have two or more points oſ suspenſion D, to which the ſcale may occaſionally be attached. Fig. 6. of Plate XCI. Vol. II. repreſents one of theſe. It is evident, that in this caſe the value or indication of the diviſions of the long arm will be different, according to the point from which the ſcale is ſuſpended. The ſame diviſion which would indicate 20 pounds when CD is three inches, will indicate 30 pounds when it is two inches. As it would expoſe to chance of miſtakes, and be otherwiſe troubleſome to make this reduction, it is uſual to make as many divided ſcales on the long arm as there are points of ſuſpenſion D on the ſhort arm ; and each ſcale having its own numbers, all trouble and all chance of miſtake is avoided.</p><p>But the range of this inſtrument is not altogether at the pleaſure of the maker. Beſides the inability of a slender beam to carry a great load, the diviſions of the ſcale anſwering to pounds or half-pounds become very minute when the diſtance CD is very ſhort ; and the balance becomes leſs delicate, that is, leſs ſenſibly affected by ſmall differences of weight. This is becauſe in ſuch caſes the thickneſs which it is neceſſary to give the edges of the nails does then bear a senſible proportion to the diſtance CD between them; ſo that when the balance inclines to one side, that arm is ſenſibly ſhortened, and therefore the energy of the preponderating weight is leſſened.</p><p>We have hitherto ſuppoſed the ſteelyard to be in equilibrio when not loaded. But this is not neceſſary, nor is it uſual in thoſe which are commonly made. The long arm commonly preponderates conſiderably. This makes no difference, except in the beginning of the ſcale. The preponderancy of the long arm is equivalent to ſome goods already in the ſcale, ſuppoſe four pounds. Therefore when there are really 10 pounds in the ſcale, the counterpoiſe will balance it when hanging at the diviſion 6. This diviſion is therefore reckoned 10, and the rest of the diviſions are numbered accordingly.</p><p>A scientific examination of the ſteelyard will convince us that it is inferior to the balance of equal arms in point of ſenſibility : But it is extremely compendious and convenient ; and when accurately made and attentively uſed, it is abundantly exact for moſt commercial purpoſes. We have ſeen one at Leipzig which has been in use since the year 1718, which is very ſenſible to a difference of one pound, when loaded with nearly three tons on the ſhort arm ; and we ſaw a waggon loaded with more than two tons weighed by it in about six minutes.</p><p>The ſteelyard in common uſe in the different countries of Europe is of a conſtruction ſtill ſimpler than what we have deſcribed. It consists of a batten of hard wood, having a heavy lump A (fig. 3.) at one end, and a ſwivel-hook B at the other. The goods to be weighed are ſuſpended on the hook, and the whole is carried in a loop of whip-cord C, in which it is ſlid backward and forward, till the goods are balanced by the weight of the other end. The weight of the goods is eſtimated by the place of the loop on a ſcale of diviſions in harmonic progression. They are marked (we preſume) by trial with known weights.</p><p>The chief uſe that is now made of the ſteelyard in theſe kingdoms is for the weighing of loaded waggons and carts. For this it is extremely convenient, and more than sufficiently exact for the purpoſe in view. We ſhall deſcribe one or two of the moſt remarkable ; and we ſhall begin with that at Leipzig already mentioned.</p><p>This ſteelyard is repreſented in fig. 4. as run out, and juſt about to be hooked for lifting up the load. The ſteelyard itſelf is OPQ, and is about 12 feet long. The ſhort arm PQ has two points of ſuſpenſion <hi rend="italic">c</hi> and b; ; and the ſtirrup which carries the chains for holding the load is made with a double hook, inſtead of a doubſe. eye, that it may be eaſily removed from the one pin to the other. For this purpoſe the two hooks are connected above by an haſp or ſtaple, which goes over the arm oſ the ſteelyard like an arch. This is repreſented in the little figure above the ſteelyard. The ſuſpenſion is shifted when the ſteelyard is run in under cover, by hooking to this ſtaple the running block of a ſmall tackle which hangs in the door through which the ſteelyard is run out and in. This operation is easy,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0786.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0780"/>
but neceſſary, becauſe the ſtirrup, chains, and the ſtage on which the load is placed, weigh ſome hundreds.</p><p>The outer pin <hi rend="italic">b</hi> is 14 inches, and the inner one <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is ſeven inches, diſtant from the great nail which reſts in the sheers. The other arm is about 10 1/2 feet long, formed with an obtuſe edge above. On the inclined plane on each side of the ridge is drawn the ſcale of weights adapted to the inner pin <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> The ſcales correſponding to the outer pin <hi rend="italic">b</hi> are drawn on the upright ſides. The counterpoiſe slides along this arm, hanging from a ſaddle-piece made of braſs, that it may not contract rust. The motion is made eaſy by means of rollers. This is neceſſary, becauſe the counterpoiſe is greatly above a hundred weight. This ſaddle piece has like two laps on each side, on which are engraved vernier ſcales, which divide their reſpective ſcales on the arm to quarters of a pound. Above the ſaddle is an arch, from the ſummit of which hangs a little plummet, which ſhows the equilibrium of the steelyard to the weigher, becauſe the ſheers are four feet out of the houſe, and he cannot ſee their coincidence with the needle of the steelyard. Lastly, near the end of the long arm are two pins <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> for ſuſpending occasionally two eke weights for continuing the ſcale. Theſe are kept hanging on adjoining hooks, ready to be lifted on by a little tackle, which is alſo hooked immediately above the pins <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and e <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p><p>The ſcales of weights are laid down on the arm as follows. Let the eke-weights appropriated to the pins <hi rend="italic">d</hi> and <hi rend="italic">e</hi> be called D and E, and call the counterpoiſe C. Although the stirrup with its chains and ſtage weigh ſome hundreds, yet the length and size of the arm OP gives it a preponderancy of 300 pounds. Here, then, the ſcale of weights muſt commence. The counterpoiſe weighs about 125 pounds. Therefore,</p><p>1. When the load hangs by the pin <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> 14 inches from the centre, the diſtance from one hundred to another on the ſcale is about 11 inches, and the firſt ſcale (on the side of the arm) reaches from 300 to 1200. In order to repeat or continue this, the eke-weight E is hung on the pin <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and the counterpoiſe C is brought back to the mark 300 ; and the two together balance 1100 pounds hanging at <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Therefore a ſecond ſcale is begun on the side of the arm, and continued as far out as the firſt, and therefore its extremity marks 2000 ; that is, the counterpoiſe C at 2000 and the eke-weight E at <hi rend="italic">e</hi> balance 2000 hanging at <hi rend="italic">b.</hi></p><p>2. To continue the ſcale beyond 2000, the load muſt be hung on the inner pin <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> The eke-weight E is taken off, and the eke weight D is hung on its pin <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> The general counterpoiſe being now brought cloſe to the ſheers, it, together with the weight D at <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> balance 2000 pounds hanging at <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> A ſcale is therefore begun on one of the inclined planes a-top, and continued out to 4000, which falls very near to the pin <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> each hundred pounds occupying about five inches on the arm. To complete the ſcale, hang on the eke- weight E on its pin <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and bring back the counterpoiſe to the ſheers, and the three together balance 3800 hanging at <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> Therefore when the counterpoiſe is now ſlid out to 4000, it muſt complete the balance with 5800 hanging at c.</p><p>It required a little consideration to find out what proportion of the three weights C, D, and E, would make the repetitious of the ſcale extend as far as poſſible, having very little of it expreſſed twice, or upon two ſcales, as is the caſe here. We ſee that the ſpace correſponding to a single pound is a very ſenſible quantity on both ſcales, being one-ninth or an inch on the firſt two ſcales, and one twentieth on the laſt two.</p><p>This very ponderous machine, with its massy weights, cannot be easily managed without ſome aſſiſtance from mechanics. It is extremely proper to have it ſuſceptible of motion out and in, that it may be protected from the weather, which would ſoon deſtroy it by rust. The contrivance here is very effectual, and abundantly simple.</p><p>When the steelyard is not in uſe, it is ſupported at one end by the iron-rod F, into which the upper end of the ſheers is hooked. The upper end of this rod has a ſtrong hook E, and a little below at <hi rend="italic">a</hi> it is pierced, with a hole, in which is a very ſtrong bolt or pin of tempered steel, having a roller on each end cloſe to the rod on each fide. Theſe rollers rest on two joiſts, one of which is repreſented by M N, which traverſe the building, with juſt room enough between them to allow the rod F to hang ſreely down. The other end O of the steelyard rests in the bight of a large flat hook at the end of a chain W, which hangs down between the joiſts, and is ſupported on them by a frame with rollers IT. This is connected with the rollers at G, which carry the ſheers by means of two iron-rods, of which one only can be ſeen. Theſe connect the two ſets of rollers in ſuch a manner that they muſt always move together, and keep their diſtance invariable, This motion is produced by means of an endleſs rope HI ZLKVH paſſing over the pulleys I and K, which turn between the joiſts, and hanging down in a bight between them. It is evident that by pulling on the part LZ we pull the frame of rollers in the direction GH, and thus bring the whole into the houſe in the position marked by the dotted figure. It is alſo plain, that by pulling on the part LK we force the roller frame and the whole apparatus out again.</p><p>It remains to ſhow how the load is raiſed from the ground and weighed. When the steelyard 13 run out for uſe, the upper hook E juſt enters into the ring D, which hangs from the end of the great oaken lever BCA about 22 feet long, turning on gudgeons at G about 5 feet from this end. From the other end A deſcends a long iron-rod SR, which has one side formed into a toothed rack that is acted on by a frame of wheel-work turned by an endleſs ſcrew and winch Therefore when the hook E is well engaged in the ring D, a man turns the winch, and thus brings down the end A of the great lever, and raiſes the load two or three inches from the ground. Every thing is now at liberty, and the weigher now manages his weights on the arm of the steelyard till he has made an equilibrium.</p><p>We need not deſcribe the operation of letting down the load, diſengaging the steelyard from the great lever, and bringing it again under cover. The whole of this ſervice is performed by two men, and may be done in ſucceſſion by one, and is over in five or six minutes.</p><p>The moſt compendious and economical machine of this kind that we have ſeen is one, firſt uſed (we have heard) for weighing the riders of race-horſes, and af<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0787.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0781"/>
terwards applied to the more reputable ſervice of weighing loaded carriages.</p><p>Fig. 5. is a plan of the machine. KLMN is the plan of a rectangular box, which has a platform lid or cover, of ſize sufficient for placing the wheels of a cart or waggon. The box is about a foot deep, and is ſunk into the ground till the platform cover is even with the ſurface. In the middle of the box is an iron lever ſupported on the fulcrum pin i <hi rend="italic">k,</hi> formed like the nail of balance, which reſts with its edge on arches of hardened ſteel firmly faſtened to the bottom of the box. This lever goes through one side of the box, and is furniſhed at its extremity with a hard steel pin <hi rend="italic">l m,</hi> alſo formed to an edge below. In the very middle of the box it is croſſed by a third nail of hardened ſteel <hi rend="italic">g h,</hi> alſo formed to an edge, but on the upper side. Theſe three edges are in one horizontal plane, as in a well made balance.</p><p>In the four corners A, A', E', E, of the box are firmly fixed four blocks of tempered ſteel, having their upper ſurfaces formed into ſpherical cavities, well polihed and hard tempered. ABODE repreſents the upper edge of an iron bar of conſiderable strength, which reſts on the cavities of the ſteel blocks in A and E, by means of two hard ſteel ſtuds projecting from its under edge, and formed into obtuſe angled points or cones. Theſe points are in a ſtraight line parallel to the side KN of the box. The middle part C of this crooked bar is faced with hard-tempered ſteel below, and is there formed into an edge parallel to AE and KN, by which it reſts on the upper edge of the ſteel pin <hi rend="italic">g b</hi> which is in the lever. In a line parallel to AE, and on the upper fide of the crooked bar ACE, are fixed two ſtuds or points of hardened ſteel B and D projecting upwards above half an inch. The platform-cover has four ſhort feet like a ſtool, terminated by hard ſteel ſtuds, which are ſhaped into ſpherical cavities and well poliſhed. With theſe it reſts on the four ſteel points B, B ,D',D. The bar ACE is kneed in ſuch a manner vertically, that the points A, B, D, E and the edge C are all in a horizontal plane. Theſe particulars will he better underſtood by looking at the elevation in fig. 6. What has been ſaid of the bar ACE muſt be underſtood as alſo ſaid of the bar A' C E'.</p><p>Draw through the centre of the box the line <hi rend="italic">a b c</hi> perpendicular to the line AE, BD. It is evident that the bar ACE is equivalent to a lever <hi rend="italic">a b c,</hi> having the fulcrum or axis AE reſting with its extremity C on the pin <hi rend="italic">h g</hi> and loaded at <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> It is alſo evident that <hi rend="italic">a</hi> C is to <hi rend="italic">a b</hi> as the load on this lever to the preſſure which it exerts on the pin gh, and that the ſame proportion ſubsiſts between the whole load on. the platform and the presſure which it exerts on the pin g h. It will alſo appear, on an attentive consideration, that this proportion is nowiſe deranged in whatever manner the load is placed on the platform. If very unequably, the two ends of the pin h may be unequally preſſed, and the lever wrenched and ſtrained a little; but the total preſſure is not changed.</p><p>If there be now placed a balance or ſteelyard at the side LK, in ſuch a manner that one end of it may be directly above the pin <hi rend="italic">l m</hi> in the end of the lever EOF, they may be connected by a wire or ſlender rod, and a weight on the other arm of the balance or ſteelyard may be put in equilibrio with any load that can be laid on the platform. A ſmall counterpoiſe being first hung on to balance the apparatus when unloaded, any additional weight will meaſure the load really laid on the platform. If <hi rend="italic">a b</hi> be to <hi rend="italic">a c</hi> as 1 to 8, and EO to E F alſo as 1 to 8, and if a common balance be uſed above, 64 pounds on the platform will be balanced by one pound in the ſcale, and every pound will be balanced by ¼th of an ounce. This would be a very convenient partition for moſt purpoſes, as it would enable us to uſe a common balance and common weights to complete the machine : Or it may be made with a balance of unequal arms, or with a ſteelyard.</p><p>Some have thought to improve this inſtrument by using edges like thoſe of the nails of a balance, instead of points. But unlefs made with uncommon accuracy, they will render the balance very dull. The ſmall deviation of the two edges A and E, or of B and D, from perfect paralleliſm to KN, is equivalent to a broad ſurface equal to the whole deviation. We imagine that, with no extraordinary care, the machine may be made to weigh within 1/2000th of the truth, which is exact enough for any purpoſe in commerce.</p><p>It is neceſſary that the points be attached to the bars. Some have put the points at A and E in the blocks of ſteel faſtened to the bottom, becauſe the cavity there lodged water or dirt, which ſoon deſtroyed the inſtrument with ruſt. But this occasions a change of proportion in the first lever by any ſhifting of the crooked bars ; and this will frequently happen when the wheels of a loaded cart are puſhed on the platform. The cavity in the ſteel ſtud ſhould have a little rim round it, and it ſhould be kept full of oil. In a nice machine a quarter of an inch of quickſilver would effectually prevent all theſe inconveniences.</p><p>The ſimpleſt and moſt economical form of this machine is to have no balance or ſecond ſteelyard ; but to make the first ſteelyard EOF a lever of the first kind, viz. having the fulcrum between O and F, and allow it to project far beyond the box. The long or outward arm of this lever is then divided into a ſcale of weights, commencing at the side of the box. A counterpoiſe muſt be choſen, ſuch as will, when at the beginning of the ſcale, balance the ſmalleſt load that will probably be examined. It will be convenient to carry on this ſcale by means of eke-weights hung on at the <hi rend="italic">extremity</hi> of the lever, and to uſe but one moveable weight. By this method the divisions of the ſcale will have always one value. The beſt arrangement is as follows: Place the mark O at the beginning of the ſcale, and let it extend only to 100, if for pounds ; or to 112, if for cwts.; or to 10, if for stones ; and let the eke-weights be numbered 1, 2, 3, &amp;c. Let the loweſt weight be marked on the beam. This is always to be added to the weight ſhown by the operation. Let the eke-weights ſtand at the end of the beam, and let the. general counterpoiſe always hang at O. When the cart is put on the platform, the end of the beam tilts up. Hang on the heavieſt eke-weight that is not sufficient to preſs it down. Now complete the balance by sliding out the counterpoiſe. Suppoſe the confiant load to be 312 lb. and that the counterpoiſe ſtands at 86, and that the eke-weight is 9 ; we have the load= 986+312,= 1298 lbs</p></div></body></text></TEI>