<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0698.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0692-16" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPINNING</label>,
in commerce, the act or art of reducing ſilk, flax, hemp, wool, hair, or other matters, into thread. Spinning is either performed on the wheel, or with a diſtaff and ſpindle, or with other machines<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0699.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0693"/>
proper for the ſeveral kinds of working. Hemp, flax, nettle-thread, and other like vegetable matters, are to be wetted in ſpinning : ſilks, wools, &amp; <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> are ſpun dry, and do not need water ; yet there is a way of ſpinning or reeling silk as it comes off the caſes or balls, where hot and even boiling water is to be uſed (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Silk).</hi> The vaſt variety, and the importance of thoſe branches of our manufactures, which are produced from cotton, wool, and flax, ſpun into yarn, together with the cheapneſs of proviſions, and the low price of labour in many foreign countries, which are our rivals in trade, have occaſioned many attempts at home to render ſpinning more eaſy, cheap, and expeditious. For which see <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Cotton</hi> <hi rend="italic">Spinning</hi> and <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Cotton</hi> <hi rend="italic">Mills.</hi></p><p>Theſe contrivances have in ſome parts of Scotland been applied to the ſpinning of flax;<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Trans. of the Society for the encouragement of Arts, &amp;c.</p></note> but a very conſiderable improvement has lately been made by Mr Antis of Fulneck near Leeds of the common ſpinning wheel. It is well known, that hitherto much time has been loſt by ſtopping the wheel in order to ſhit the thread from one ſtaple on the flyer to another ; but in Mr Antis’s wheel the bobbin is made to move backwards and forwards, ſo as to prevent the neceſſity of this perpetual interruption, as well as to obviate the Ganger of breaking the thread and losing the end. This is effected by the axis of the great wheel being extended through the pillar next the ſpinner, and formed into a pinion of one leaf A, which takes into a wheel B, ſeven inches diameter, having on its periphery 97 teeth; ſo that 97 revolutions of the great wheel caule one of the leſſer wheel. On this leſſer wheel is fixed a ring of wire c c c; which, being ſupported on six legs, ſtands obliquely to the wheel itſelf, touching it at one part, and projecting nearly three quarters of an inch at the oppoſite one ; near the side of this wheel is an upright lever C, about 15 inches long, moving on a centre, three inches from its lower extremity, and connected at the top to a Aiding bar D; from which rises an upright piece of braſs E, which working in the notch of a pulley drives the bobbin F backward and forward, according as the oblique wire forces a pin G in or out, as the wheel moves round. To regulate and asſiſt the alternate motion, a weight H hangs by a line to the sliding bar, aind paſſing over a pulley rises and falls as the bobbin advances or recedes, and tends conſtantly to keep the pin in contact with the wire. It is evident, from this deſcription. that one ſtaple only is wanted to the flyer ; which, being placed near the extremity K, the thread palling through it is by the motion of the bobbin laid regularly thereon. For this invention the Society inſtituted at London for the Encouragement of Arts, &amp;c. gave the author a premium of twenty guineas.</p></div></body></text></TEI>