<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0805.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0799-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STILLINGFLEET</label>
(Edward), biſhop of Worceſter, was the ſon of Samuel Stillingfleet gentleman, and was born at Cranborn in Dorſetſhire in 1635. He was educated at St John’s College, Cambridge ; and having received holy orders, was, in 1657, preſented to the rectory ol Sutton in Nottinghamſhire. By publiſhing his <hi rend="italic">Origines Sacre,</hi> one of the ableſt defences of revealed religion that has ever been written, he ſoon acquired ſuch reputation, that he was appointed preacher of the Rolls Chapel; and in January 1665 was preſented to the rectory of St Andrew’s, Holborn. He was afterwards choſen lecturer at the Temple, and appointed chaplain in ordinary to king Charles II. In 1668 he took the degree of doctor of divinity ; and was ſoon after engaged in a diſpute with thoſe of the Romiſh religion, by publiſhing his diſcourſe concerning the idolatry and fanaticiſm of the church of Rome, which he aſterwards defended againſt ſeveral antagoniſts. In 1680 he preached at Guildhall chapel a ſermon on Phil. iii. 26. which he publiſhed under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Miſchief of Separation ;</hi> and this being immediately attacked by ſeveral writers, he in 1683 publiſhed his <hi rend="italic">Unreasonableneſs of Separation.</hi> In 1685 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Origines Britannica,</hi> or the Antiquities of the Britiſh Church, in folio. During the reign of king James II. he wrote ſeveral tracts againſt popery, and was prolocutor of the convocation, as he had likewiſe been under Charles II. After the Revolution he was advanced to the biſhoprſe of Worceſter, and was engaged in a diſpute with the Socinians, and alſo with Mr Locke ; in which laſt conteſt he is generally thought to have been unſucceſsful He died at Weſtminſter in 1699, and was interred in the cathedral of Worceſter, where a monument was erected to his memory by his ſon. Dr Stillingfleet wrote other works beſides thoſe here mentioned, which, with the above, have been reprinted in 6 vols, folio.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Stillingfleet</hi> (Benjamin), an ingenious naturaliſt, was grandſon of the preceding. His father Edward was fellow of St John’s College in Cambridge, F. R. S. M. D. and Greſham profeſsor of phyſic : but marrying in 1692, he loſt his lucrative offices and his father’s favour ; a misfortune that affected both himſelf and his poſterity. However, going into orders, he obtained, by his father’s means, the living of Newington-Butts, which he immediately exchanged for thoſe of Wood-Norton and Swanton in Norfolk. He died in 1708.</p><p>Benjamin, his only ſon, was educated at Norwich ſchool, which he left in 1720, with the character of an excellent ſcholar. He then went to Trinity-College in Cambridge, at the requeſt of Dr Bentley, the maſter, who had been private tutor to his father, domeſtic chaplain to his grandfather, and much indebted to the family. Here he was a candidate for a fellowſhip, but was rejected by the matter's influence. This was a ſevere and unexpected diſappointment, and but little alleviated afterwards by the Doctor's apology, that it was a pity that a gentleman of Mr Stillingfleet’s parts ſhould be buried within the walls oſ a college.</p><p>Perhaps, however, this ingratitude of Dr Bentley was not of any real diſſervice to Mr Stillingfleet. By being thrown into the world, he formed many honourable and valuable connections. He dedicated ſome tranſlations of Linnæus to the late lord Lyttleton, partly, he ſays, from motives of private reſpect and honour. Lord Barrington gave him, in a very polite manner, the place of the maſter of the barracks at Kenſington ; a favour to which Mr Stillingfleet, in the dedication of his Calendar of Flora to that nobleman, alludes with equal politeneſs, as well as with the warmeſt gratitude. His Calendar of Flora was formed at Stratton in Norfolk in the year 1755, at the hoſpitable ſeat of his very worthy and ingenious friend Mr Marſham, who had made ſeveral obſervations of that kind, and had communicated to the public his curious obſervations on the growth of trees. But it was to Mr Wyndham of Felbrig in Norfolk that he appears to have had the greateſt obligations : he travelled abroad with him, ſpent much of his time at his houſe, and was appointed one of his executors (Mr Garrick was another), with a conſiderable addition to an annuity which that gentleman had ſettled upon him in his lifetime.</p><p>Mr Stillingfleet’s genius ſeems, if we may judge from his works, to have led him principally to the study of natural hiſtory ; which he prosecuted as an ingenious philoſopher, an uſeful citizen, and a good man. In this walk of learning he mentions, as his friends, Dr Watſon, Mr (afterwards Dr) Solander, Mr Hudson, Mr Price of Foxley, and ſome others ; to whom may be added the ingenious Mr Pennant. Nor can we omit the flattering mention which the late Mr Gray makes of him in one of his letters, dated from London in 1761 : “I have lately made an acquaintance with this philoſopher, who lives in a garret here in the winter, that he may ſupport ſome near relations who depend upon him. He is always employed, conſequently (according to my old maxim) always happy, always cheerful, and ſeems to me a very worthy honeſt man. His preſent ſcheme is to ſend ſome perſons, properly qualified, to reſide a year or two in Attica, to make themſelves acquainted with the climate, productions,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0806.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0800"/>
and natural hiſtory of the country, that we may underſtand Ariſtotle, Theophraſtus, &amp;c. who have been heathen Greek to us for ſo many ages ; and this he has got propoſed to lord Bute, no unlikely perſon to put it in execution, as he is himſelf a botaniſt.”</p><p>Mr Stillingfleet publiſhed a volume of miſcellaneous tracts, which is in much eſteem, and does great honour to his head and heart. They are chiefly tranſlations of ſome essays in the <hi rend="italic">Amanitates Academica,</hi> publiſhed by Linnæus, interſperſed with ſome obſervations and additions of his own. In this volume he ſhows alſo a taſte for claſſical learning, and entertains us with ſome elegant poetical effusions of his own. But his Eſſay on Conversation, publiſhed in the firſt volume of Dodſley’s Collection oſ Poems, entitles him to a diſtinguiſhed rank among our Engliſh poets. This poem is addreſſed to Mr Wyndham, with all that warmth of friendſhip which diſtinguiſhes Mr Stillingfleet. As it is chiefly didactic, it does not admit of ſo many ornaments as ſome compoſitions of other kinds. However, it contains much good ſenſe, ſhows a conſiderable knowledge of mankind, and has ſeveral paſſages that in point of harmony and easy versification would not disgrace the writings of our moſt admired poets. Here more than once Mr Stillingfleet ſhows himſelf ſtill ſore for Dr Bentley’s cruel treatment of him ; and towards the beautiful and moral cloſe of it (where it is ſuppoſed he gives us a sketch of himſelf) ſeems to hint at a mortification of a more delicate nature, which he is ſaid to have ſuffered from the other ſex.</p><p>To theſe diſappointments it was perhaps owing that Mr Stillingfleet neither married nor went into orders. His London residence was at a ſaddler’s in Piccadilly ; where he died in 1771, aged above 70, leaving ſeveral valuable papers behind him. He was buried in St James’s church, without the ſlighteſt monument of his having exiſted.</p></div></body></text></TEI>