<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0210-04"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0216.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RHINEGAU</label>, a beautiful diſtrict of the electorate of Mentz, is
                    ſituated on the Rhine, about three miles from the clty of Mentz, and is fo
                    populous that lt looks like one entire town intermixed with gardens and
                    vineyards. The Rhine here grows aſtoniſhingly wide, and forms a kmd of ſea, near
                    a mſle bioad, in wſuch are ſeveral well wooded little lſiands. I lie Rhmegau
                    forms an amphitheatre, tlie beauties of whicli are beyond all deſeriptlon. At
                    walluf, the very high hills come nearly down to the river ſide ; from thence
                    they recede agam mto tlie country, formmg a kmd of half circle, the otlier end
                    of which is'15 miles off at Rude-ſheim’ θη the banks of the Rhine. ſhe banks of
                    the river, the hills wliicli form the circles, and the ſlopes oſ tlie great
                    mountams, are thick ſown with vil lages and hamlets. The white appearance of the
                    buildings, and the ſine blue ſlated roofs of the houſes playing amidſt the
                    various green of the landſeape, have an admirable effect. In the ſpace of every
                    mile, as you ſail down the river, you meet with a village which in any other
                    place would paſs for a town, blany of the νιί-lages contain from 300 to 400
                    families ; and there are 36 of them in a ſpace of 15 miles long and ſtx miles
                    broad, which ls the width of this heautiful amphitheatre. The declivities of all
                    the hills and mountains are planted thick with vineyards and fruit trees, and
                    the thick wooded tops of the hills caſt a gloomy horror over the otherwiſe
                    cheerful landſeape. Every now and then a row of rugged hills run directly down
                    to the ſhore, and dommeer majcſtically over the leffer hills un-der them. On one
                    of theſe great mountains, juſt about the middle of the Rhinegau, you meet with
                        <hi rend="italic">Johannis-Berg,</hi> a village which produces ſome of the
                    beſt Rheniſh. Before this village is a pretty little riling, and near the banks
                    oſ the river there is a very ſine old caſtle, which gives unſpeakable majeſty to
                    the whole landſcape. Indeed, in every village, you meet with ſome or other large
                    building, which contributes very much to the de-coration of the whole. This
                    country is indebted for its riches to this ſemicirci/ar hill, which protects it
                    from the cold winds of the eaſt and north, at the ſame time that it leaves room
                    enough for the ſun to exerciſe his benign influences. The groves and higher
                    Hopes of the hills make excellent paſtures, and produce large quantities of
                    dung, which, in a country of this fort, is of ineſtimable value.</p>
                <p>The bank of the Rhine, oppoſite to tbe Rhinegau, is exceedingly barren, and
                    heightens tbe beauty of the proſpect on the other ſide by the contraſt it
                    exhibits ; on this ſide, you hardly meet above three or four villages, and theſe
                    are ſar diſtant from each other. The great interval between them is occupied by
                    heaths and mea-dows, only here and there a thick buſh affords ſome ſhade, and a
                    few corn fields among the viliages enliven the gloomy landſcape. The back ground
                    of this coun-try is the moſt pictureſque part of it. It is formed by a narrow
                    gullet of mountains, which diminiſh in perſpective between Rudeſheim and Bingen.
                    Perpendicular mountains and rocks hang over the Rhine in this place, and ſeem to
                    make it the dominion of eternal night. At a diſtance, the Rhine ſeems to come
                    out of this land-ſeape through a hole under ground ; and it appears to run
                    tediouſſy, in order to enjoy its courſe through a pleaſant country the longer.
                    Amidſt the darkneſs which covers this back ground, the celebrated Monſe tower
                    ſeems to fwim upon the river. In a word, there is not any thing in this whole
                    tract that does not contribute ſomething to the beauty and magnificence of the
                    whole ; or, if I may be permitted the expreffion, to make the paradiſe more
                    welcome. As you ſail along the Rhine, between Mentz and Bingen, the banks of the
                    river form an oval amphitheatre, which makes one of the richeſt and moſt
                    pictureſquc landſcapes to be ſeen in Europe. The inhabitants of theſe regions
                    arer ſome of them extremely rich, and ſome extremely poor. The happy middle
                    ſtate is not for countries the chief product of which is wine ; ſor, beſides
                    that the culti-vation of the vineyard is inſinitely more troubleſoma and
                    expenſive than agriculture, it is ſubjected to revolutions, which in an inſtant
                    reduce the holder of land to the condition of a day-labourer. It is a great
                    miſ-fortune for this country, that, though reſtrained by law,, the nobility are,
                    through connivance of the Elector, allowed to purchaſe as much land as they
                    pleaſe. The peaſant generally begins by running in debt for his vineyard ; ſo
                    that if it does not turn out well, he is reduced to day-labour, and the rich man
                    extends his poſ-ſeffions to the great detriment of the conntry. There are
                    ſeveral peaſants here, who having incomes of 30, 50, or ιοο,οοο guilders a-year,
                    have laid aſide the pea-ſant, and affumed the wine-merchant ; but, ſplendid as
                    their ſituation is, it does not compenſatb, in the eyes of the humane man, for
                    the ſight of ſo many poor people with which the villages ſwarm. In order to
                    render a country of this kind proſperous, the ſtate ſhould ap-propriate a fund
                    to the purpoſe of maintaining the pea-ſant in bad years, and giving him the
                    aſſiſtance which his neceffities, and his want of ready money, may from time to
                    time make convenient.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants of the Rhinegau are a handſome and uncommonly ſtrong race of men.
                    You ſee at the very ſirſt aſpect that their wine gives them merry hearts and
                    ſound bodies. They have a great deal of natural wit, and a vivacity and
                    jocoſeneſs, which diſtinguiſhes them</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0211" facs="gri_33125011196389_0217.tif"/>
                <p>very much from their neighbours. You need only compare them with ſome of theſe,
                    to be convinced that the drinker of wine excels the drinker of beer and water,
                    both in body and mind, and that the inhabitant of the ſouth is much ſſouter than
                    he who lives in the north ; for though the wine drinker may not have quite as
                    much fleſh as he who drinks only beer, he has better blood, and can bear much
                    more work. Tacitus had already obſerved this, in his treatiſe <hi rend="italic"
                        >De moribus Germanorum.</hi> “ The large and corpulent bodies of the Germans
                    (ſays he) have a great appearance, but are not made to laſt.” At that time
                    almoſt all the Germans drank only water ; but the mere drinking of wine has
                    effected a revolution in ſeveral parts of Germany, which makes the preſent
                    inhabitants of theſe countries very different from thoſe deſcribed by Tacitus.
                    Black and brown hair is much commoner here than the white, which made the
                    Germans ſo famous in old Rome. “ It wili be eaſily imagined (ſays Baron
                    Reiſheck), that the monks fare particularly well in fo rich a country, we made a
                    viſit to the prelate of Erbach. Theſe lordly monks, for ſo in every reſpect they
                    are, have an excellent hunt, rooms magnificently furniſhed, billiard tables,
                    half a dozen beautiful ſinging women, and a ſtu-pendous wine cellar, the well
                    ranged batteries of which made me ſhudder. A monk, who ſaw my aſto-niſhment at
                    the number of the caſks, affured me, that, without the benign influence which
                    flowed from them, it would be totally impoffible for the cloiſter to ſubſiſt in
                    fo damp a ſituation.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
