<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0044.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0038-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STRUTHIO</label>,
in natural hiſtory ; a genus of birds belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">grallae</hi> of Linnaeus ; but, according to the new claſſification of Dr Latham, it forms, along with the dodo, caſſuarius, and rhea, a ſeparate order under the name of st <hi rend="italic">ruthiοus.</hi> As the dodo or didus, and rhea, have been already deſcribed in their proper place, we will now give ſome account of the oſtrich and caſſowary.</p><p>I.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Plate CCCCLXXXVI.</p></note> The <hi rend="smallcaps">Ostrich</hi> (the <hi rend="italic">Camelus</hi> of Linnasus) has a bill ſomewhat conical ; the wings are ſo ſhort as to be unfit for flying ; the thighs and sides of the body are naked ; the feet are formed for running, having two toes, one only of which is furniſhed with a nail. In this respect it differs entirely from the caſſowary, which has three toes complete. The oſtrich is without doubt the largeſt of all birds : it is nearly eight feet in length, and when ſtanding upright from six to eight feet in height. We are told in the Gentleman’s Magazine<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Vol xx. p. 536.</p></note> *, that two oſtriches were ſhown in London in the year 1750, and that the male was 10 feet in height, and weighed three hundred weight and a quarter. The head and bill ſomewhat reſemble those of a duck ; and the neck may be likened to that of a ſwan, but that it is much longer; the legs and thighs reſemble thoſe of an hen; though the whole appearance bears a ſtrong reſemblance to that of a camel. But though uſually ſeven feet high from the top of the head to the ground, from the back it is only four ; ſo that the head and neck are above three feet long. From the top of the head to the rump, when the neck is ſtretched out in a right line, it is six feet long, and the tail is about a foot more. One of the wings, without the feathers, is a foot and an half; and being ſtretched out, with the feathers, is three feet.</p><p>The plumage is much alike in all; that is, generally black and white; though ſome of them are ſaid to be grey. There are no feathers on the ſides, nor yet on the thighs, nor under the wings. The lower part of the neck, about half way, is covered with ſtill ſmaller feathers than thoſe on the belly and back ; and thoſe alſo are of different colours.</p><p>All theſe feathers are of the ſame kind, and peculiar to the oſtrich ; for other birds have ſeveral forts, some of which are ſoft and downy, and others hard and ſtrong. Oſtrich-feathers are almoſt all as ſoft as down, being utterly unfit to ſerve the animal for flying, and ſtill leſs adapted to be a proper defence against external injury. The feathers<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0045.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0039"/>
of other birds have the webs broader on one side than the other, but thoſe of the oſtrich have their ſhaft exactly in the middle. The upper part of the head and neck are covered with a very fine clear white hair, that ſhines like the briſtles of a hog ; and in ſome places there are ſmall tufts of it, conſiſting of about 12 hairs, which grow from a single ſhaft about the thickneſs of a pin.</p><p>At the end of each wing there is a kind of ſpur almoſt like the quill of a porcupine. It is an inch long, being hollow and of an horny ſubſtance. There are two of theſe on each wing ; the largest of which is at the extremity of the bone of the wing, and the other a foot lower. The neck seems to be more slender in proportion to that of other birds, from its not being furniſhed with feathers. The ſkirt in this part is of a livid fleſh-colour, which ſome, improperly, would have to be blue. The bill is ſhort and pointed, and two inches and an half at the beginning. The external form of the eye is like that of a man, the upper eye-lid being adorned with eye-lashes which are longer than thole on the lid below. The tongue is ſmall, very ſhort, and compoſed of cartilages, ligaments, and membranes, intermixed with fleſhy fibres. In some it is about an inch long, and very thick at the bottom ; in others it is but half an inch, being a little forked at the end.</p><p>The thighs are very fleſhy and large, being covered with a white ſkin inclining to redneſs, and wrinkled in the manner of a net, whoſe meſhes will admit the end of the finger. Some have very ſmall feathers here and there on the thighs; and others again have neither feathers nor wrinkles. What are called the legs of birds, in this are covered before with large ſcales. The end of the foot is cloven, and has two very large toes, which, like the leg, are covered with ſcales.Theſe toes are of unequal ſizes The largeſt, which is on the inside, is ſeven inches long, including the claw, which is near three-fourths of an inch in length, and almoſt as broad. The other toe is but four inches long, and is without a claw.</p><p>The internal parts of this animal are formed with no leſs ſurpriſing peculiarity. At the top of the breaſt, under the skin, the fat is two inches thick ; and on the fore-part of the belly it is as hard as ſuet, and about two inches and an half thick in ſome places. It has two diſtinct ſtomachs. The firſt, which is lowermoſt, in its natural ſituation ſomewhat reſembles the crop in other birds; but it is conſiderably larger than the other ſtomach, and is furniſhed with, strong muſcular fibres, as well circular as longitudinal. The ſecond ſtomach or gizzard has outwardly the ſhape of the ſtomach of a man ; and upon opening is always found filled with a variety of diſcordant ſubſtances ; hay, graſs, barley, beans, bones, and ſtones, ſome of which exceed in ſize a pullet’s egg. The kidneys are eight inches long and two broad, and differ from those of other birds in not being divided into lobes. The heart and lungs are ſeparated by a midriff as in quadrupeds ; and the parts of generation alſo bear a very ſtrong reſemblance and analogy.</p><p>The oſtrich is a native only of the torrid regions of Africa, and has long been celebrated by thoſe who have had occaſion to mention the animals of that region. Its fleſh is proſcribed in Scripture as unfit to be eaten ; and moſt of the ancient writers deſcribe it as well known in their times. Like the race of the elephant, it is tranſmitted down without mixture ; and has never been known to breed out of that country which ſirſt produced it. It ſeems formed to live among the ſandy and burning deſerts of the torrid zone ; and, as in ſome meaſure it owes its birth to their genial influence, ſo it ſeldom migrates into tracts more mild er more fertile. The Arabians affert that the oſtrich never drinks ; and the place of its habitation ſeems to confirm the aſſertion. In theſe formidable regions oſtriches are ſeen in large flocks, which to the diſtant ſpectator appear like a regiment of cavalry, and have often alarmed a whole caravan. There is no deſert, how barren ſoever, but what is capable of ſupplying theſe animals with proviſion ; they eat almoſt every thing ; and theſe barren tracts are thus doubly grateful, as they afford both food and ſecurity. The oſtrich is of all other animals the moſt voracious. It will devour leather, graſs, hair, iron, ſtones, or any thing that is given. Thoſe ſubſtances which the coats of the ſtomach cannot ſoften, paſs whole ; ſo that glaſs, ſtones, or iron, are excluded in the form in which they were devoured. In an oſtrich dissected by Ranby, there appeared ſuch a quantity of heterogeneous ſubſtances, that it was wonderful how any animal could digeſt ſuch an overcharge of nouriſhment. Valiſnieri alſo found the firſt ſtomach filled with a quantity of incongruous ſubſtances ; graſs, nuts, cords, ſtones, glaſs, braſs, copper, iron, tin, lead, and wood ; a piece of ſtone was found among the rest that weighed more than a pound. He ſaw one of theſe animals that was killed by devouring a quantity of quicklime. It would seem that the oſtrich is obliged to fill up the great capacity of its ſtomach in order to be at eaſe ; but that nutritious ſubſtances not occurring, it pours in whatever offers to ſupply the void.</p><p>In their native deſerts, however, it is probable they live chiefly upon vegetables, where they lead an inoffenſive and ſocial life ; the male, as Thevenot aſſures us, aſſorting with the female with connubial fidelity. They are ſaid to be very much inclined to venery ; and the make of the parts in both ſexes ſeems to confirm the report. It is probable alſo they copulate like other birds, by compreſſion. They lay very large eggs, ſome of them being above five inches in diameter, and weighing above fifteen pounds. Theſe eggs have a very hard ſhell, ſomewhat reſembling thoſe of the crocodile, except that thoſe of the latter are leſs and rounder.</p><p>The ſeaſon for laying depends on the climate where the animal is bred. In the northern parts of Africa, this ſeaſon is about the beginning of July; in the ſouth, it is about the latter end of December. Theſe birds are very prolific, and lay generally from 40 to 50 eggs at one clutch, which are as big as a child’s head. It has been commonly reported, that the female depoſits them in the sand, and covering them up, leaves them to be hatched by the heat of the climate, and then permits the young to ſhift for themſelves. Very little of this, however, is true : no bird has a ſtronger affection for her young than the oſtrich, nor none watches her eggs with greater aſſiduity. It happens, indeed, in thoſe hot climates, that there is leſs neceſſity for the continual incubation of the female ; and ſhe more frequently leaves her eggs, which are in no danger of being chilled by the weather ; but though ſhe ſometimes forſakes them by day, ſhe always carefully broods over them by night ; and Kolben, who has ſeen great numbers of them at the Cape of Good Hope, affirms, that they sit on their eggs like other birds, and that the male and the female take this office by turns, as he had frequent opportunities of obſerving. Nor is it more true what is ſaid of their forſaking their young after they are excluded the ſhell. On the contrary, the young ones are not even able to walk for ſeveral days after they are hatched. During this time the old ones are very aſſiduous in ſupplying them with graſs, and very careful to defend them from danger ; nay, they encounter every danger in their defence. The young, when brought forth, are of an aſh-colour the firſt year, and are covered with feathers all over. But in time theſe feathers drop ; and thoſe parts<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0046.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0040"/>
which are covered aſſume a different and more becoming plumage.</p><p>The beauty of a part of this plumage, particularly the long feathers that compoſe the wings and tail, is the chief reaſon that man has been ſo active in purſuing this harmleſs bird to its deſerts, and hunting it with no ſmall degree of expence and labour. The ancients uſed thoſe plumes in their helmets; our military wear them in their hats; and the ladies make them an ornament in their dreſs. Thoſe feathers which are plucked from the animal while alive are much more valued than thoſe taken when dead, the latter being dry, light, and ſubject to be worm-eaten.</p><p>Beſide the value ot their plumage, ſome of the ſavage nations of Africa hunt them alſo for their fleſh ; which they conſider as a dainty. They ſometimes also breed theſe birds tame, to eat the young ones, of which the females are ſaid to Be the greateſt delicacy. Some nations have obtained the name of <hi rend="italic">Struthophagi,</hi> or ostr <hi rend="italic">ich eaters,</hi> from their peculiar fondneſs for this food ; and even the Romans themſelves were not averſe to it. Even among the Europeans now, the eggs of the oſtrich are ſaid to be well taſted, and extremely nouriſhing ; but they are too ſcarce to be fed upon, although a single egg be a sufficient entertainment for eight men.</p><p>As the ſpoils of the oſtrich are thus valuable, it is not to Be wondered at that man has become their most aſſiduous purſuer. For this purpoſe, the Arabians train up their best and fleeteſt horſes, and hunt the oſtrich ſtill in view. Perhaps, of all other varieties of the chase, this, though the moſt laborious, is yet the moſt entertaining. As ſoon as the hunter comes within sight of his prey, he puts on his horſe with a gentle gallop, ſo as to keep the oſtrich ſtill in sight ; yet not ſo as to terrify him from the plain into the mountains. Of all known animals, the oſtrich is by far the swifteſt in running ; upon obſerving himself, therefore purſued at a diſtance, he begins to run at firſt but gently ; either inſenſible of his danger, or hire of eſcaping. In this ſituation, he ſomewhat reſembles a man at full ſpeed ; his wings, like two arms, keep working with a motion correſpondent to that of his legs ; and his ſpeed would very ſoon ſnatch him from the view of his purſuers ; but, unfortunately for the ſilly creature, inſtead of going off in a direct line, he takes his courſe in circles ; while the hunters ſtill make a ſmall courſe within, relieve each other, meet him at unexpected turns, and keep him thus ſtill employed, ſtill followed, for two or three days together. At laſt, ſpent with fatigue and famine, and finding all power of eſcape impoſſible, he endeavours to hide himſelf from thoſe enemies he cannot avoid, and covers his head in the land or the firſt thicket he meets. Sometimes, however, he attempts to face his purſuers ; and though in general the moſt gentle animal in nature, when driven to desperation he defends himſelf with his beak, his wings, and his feet. Such is the force of his motion, that a man would be utterly unable to withſtand him in the ſhock.</p><p>The Struthophagi have another method of taking this bird : they cover themſelves with an oſtrich’s ſkin, and paſſing up an arm through the neck, thus counterfeit all the motions of this animal. By this artifice they approach the oſtrich, which becomes an eaſy prey. He is ſometimes alſo taken by dogs and nets ; but the moſt uſual way is that mentioned above.</p><p>When the Arabians have thus taken an oſtrich, they cut its throat ; and making a ligament below the opening, they ſhake the bird as one would rinſe a barrel; then taking off the ligature, there runs out from the wound in the throat a conſiderable quantity of blood mixed with the fat of the animal ; and this is conſidered as one of their greateſt dainties. They next flea the bird ; and of the ſkin, which is ſtrong and thick, ſometimes make a kind of veſt, which anſwers the purpoſes of a cuirass and a buckler.</p><p>There are others who, more compaſſionate or more provident, do not kill their captive, but endeavour to tame it, for the purpoſes of ſupplying thoſe feathers which are in ſo great requeſt. The inhabitants of Dara and Lybia breed up whole flocks of them, and they are tamed with very little trouble. But it is not for their feathers alone that they are prized in this domeſtic ſtate ; they are often ridden upon and uſed as horſes. Moore aſſures us, that at Joar he law a man travelling upon an oſtrich ; and Adanſon aſſerts, that at the factory of Podore he had two oſtriches, which were then young, the ſtrongeſt of which ran ſwifter than the beſt Engliſh racer, although he carried two negroes on his back. As ſoon as the animal perceived that it was thus loaded, it ſet off running with all its force, and made ſeveral circuits round the village ; till at length the people were obliged to ſtop it by barring up the way. How far this ſtrength and ſwiftneſs maybe uſeful to mankind, even in a polished ſtate, is a matter that perhaps deferves inquiry.</p><p>IT. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Cassowary</hi> (the <hi rend="italic">Casuarius</hi> of Linnaeus, and <hi rend="italic">Galeated Caſſowary</hi> of Dr Latham) was ſirſt brought into Europe from Java by the Dutch about the year 1597. It is nearly equal in ſize to the oſtrich, but its legs are much thicker and ſtronger in proportion. This conformation gives it an air of ſtrength and force, which the fierceneſs and Angularity of its countenance conſpire to render formidable. It is five feet and an half long from the point of the bill to the extremity of the claws. The legs are two feet and an half high from the belly to the end oſ the claws. The head and neck together are a foot and an half ; and the largeſt toe, including the claw, is five inches long. The claw alone of the leaſt toe is three inches and a half in length. The wing is ſo ſmall that it does not appear, it being hid under the feathers of the back. In other birds, a part of the feathers ſerve for flight, and are different from thoſe that ſerve merely for covering ; but in the caſſowary all the feathers are of the fame kind, and outwardly of the ſame colour. They are generally double, having two long ſhafts, which grow out of a ſhort one, which is fixed in the ſkin. Thoſe that are double are always of an unequal length ; for ſome are 14 inches long, particularly on the rump, while others are not above three. The beards that adorn the ſtem br shaft are about half-way to the end, very long, and as thick as an horſe-hair, without- being ſubdivided into fibres. The ſtem or ſhaft is flat, ſhining, black, and knotted below; and from each knot there proceeds a beard ; likewise the beards at the end of the large feathers are perfectly black, and towards the root of a grey tawny colour ; ſhorter, more ſoft, and throwing out fine fibres like down; ſo that nothing appears except the ends, which are hard and black ; becauſe the other part, compoſed of down, is quite covered. There are feathers on the head and neck ; but they are ſo ſhort and thinly ſown, that the bird’s ſkin appears naked, except towards the hinder part of the head, where they are a little longer. The feathers which adorn the rump are extremely thick ; but do not differ in other reſpects from the reſt, excepting their being longer. The wings, when they are deprived of their feathers, are but three inches long ; and the feathers are like thoſe on other parts of the body. The ends of the wings are adorned with five prickles, of different lengths and thickneſs, which bend like a bow: theſe are hollow from the roots to the very points, having only that flight ſubſtance within which all quills are known to have. The longeſt of theſe prickles is 11 inches ; and it is a quarter of an inch in diameter at the root, being thicker there than towards the extremity ; the point ſeems broken off.<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0047.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0041"/>
The part, however, which moſt diſtinguiſhes this animal is the head ; which, though ſmall, like that of an oſtrich, does not fail to inſpire ſome degree of terror. It is bare of feathers, and is in a manner armed with an helmet of horny ſubſtance, that covers it from the root of the bill to near half the head backwards. This helmet is black before and yellow behind. Its ſubſtance is very hard, being formed by the elevation of the bone of the ſkull ; and it conſiſts of ſeveral plates, one over another, like the horn of an ox. Some have ſuppoſed that this was ſhed every year with the feathers ; but the moſt probable opinion is, that it only exfoliates slowly like the beak. To the peculiar oddity of this natural armour may be added the colour of the eye in this animal, which is a bright yellow; and the globe being above an inch and a half in diameter, give it an air equally fierce and extraordinary. The hole of the ear is very large and open, being only covered with ſmall black feathers. The ſides of the head, about the eye and ear, being deſtitute of any covering, are blue, except the middle of the lower eyelid, which is white. The part of the bill which anſwers to the upper jaw in other animals is very hard at the edges above, and the extremity of it is like that of a turkey-cock. The end of the lower mandible is ſlightly notched, and the whole is of a greyiſh brown, except a green ſpot on each ſide. As the beak admits a very wide opening, this contributes not a little to the bird’s menacing appearance. The neck is of a violet colour, inclining to that of slate ; and it is red behind in ſeveral places, but chiefly in the middle. About the middle of the neck before, at the rise of the large feathers, there are two procesſes formed by the ſkin, which reſemble ſomewhat the gills of a cock, but that they are blue as well as red. The ſkin which covers the forepart of the breaſt, on which this bird leans and reſts, is hard, callous, and without feathers. The thighs and legs are covered with feathers, and are extremely thick, ſtrong, ſtraight, and covered with ſcales of ſeveral ſhapes ; but the legs are thicker a little above the foot than in any other place. The toes are likewiſe covered with ſcales, and are but three in number ; for that which ſhould be behind is wanting. The claws are of a hard ſolid ſubſtance, black without and white within.</p><p>The internal parts are equally remarkable. The caſſowary unites with the double ſtomach of animals that live upon vegetables the ſhort inteſtines of thoſe that live upon fleſh. The inteſtines of the cassowary are 13 times ſhorter than thoſe of the oſtrich. The heart is very ſmall, being but an inch and an half long, and an inch broad at the baſe. Upon the whole, it has the head of a warrior, the eye of a lion, the defence of a porcupine, and the ſwiftneſs of a courſer.</p><p>Thus formed for a life of hoſtility, for terrifying others, and for its own defence, it might be expected that the caſsowary was one of the moſt fierce and terrible animals of the creation. But nothing is ſo oppoſite to its natural character : it never attacks others ; and inſtead of the bill, when attacked, it rather makes uſe of its legs, and kicks like a horſe, or runs againſt its purſuer, beats him down, and treads him to the ground.</p><p>The manner in which this animal moves is not leſs extraordinary than its appearance. Inſtead of going directly forward, it ſeems to kick up behind with one leg ; and then making a bound onward with the other, it goes with ſuch prodigious velocity, that the ſwifteſt racer would be left far behind.</p><p>The ſame degree of voraciouſneſs which we perceived in the oſtrich obtains as ſtrongly here. The caiſowary ſwallows every thing that comes within the capacity of its gullet. The Dutch assert, that it can devour not only glaſs, iron, and ſtones, but even live and burning coals, without teſtifying the ſmalleſt fear or feeling the leaſt injury. It is ſaid, that the passage of the food through its gullet is performed ſo ſpeedily, that even the very eggs which it has ſwallowed whole paſs through it unbroken in the ſame form they went down. In fact, the alimentary canal of this animal, as was obſerved above, is extremely ſhort ; and it may happen, that many kinds of food are indigeſtible in its ſtomach, as wheat or currants are to man, when ſwallowed whole.</p><p>The caſſowary’s eggs are of a grey-aſh colour, inclining to green. They are not ſo large nor ſo round as thoſe of the oſtrich. They are marked with a number of little tubercles of a deep green, and the ſhell is not very thick. The largeſt of theſe is found to be 15 inches round one way, and about 12 the other.</p><p>The ſouthern parts of the moſt eaſtern Indies ſeem to be the natural climate of the caffowary. His domain, if we may ſo call it, begins where that of the oſtrich terminates. The latter has never been found beyond the Ganges; while the caiſowary is never ſeen nearer than the iſlands of Banda, Sumatra, Java, the Molucca iſlands, and the correſponding parts of the continent. Yet even here this animal ſeems not to have multiplied in any conſiderable degree, as we find one of the kings of Java making a preſent of one of theſe birds to the captain of a Dutch ſhip, conſidering it as a very great rarity.</p><p>2. The <hi rend="italic">Caſuarius Novae Hollandiae,</hi> or New Holland caſſowary, differs conſiderably from the common casſowary. It is a much larger bird, ſtanding higher on its legs, and having the neck longer than in the common one. Total length ſeven feet two inches. The bill is not greatly different from that of the common caiſowary ; but the horny appendage or helmet on the top of the head in this ſpecies is totally wanting : the whole of the head and neck is alſo covered with feathers, except the throat and fore part of the neck about half way, which are not ſo well feathered as the rest ; whereas in the common caiſowary the head and neck are bare and carunculated as in the turkey.</p><p>The plumage in general conſiſts of a mixture of brown and grey, and the feathers are ſomewhat curled or bent at the ends in the natural ſtate : the wings are ſo very ſhort as to be totally uſeleſs for flight, and indeed are ſcarcely to be distinguiſhed from the reſt of the plumage, were it not for their ſtanding out a little. The long ſpines which are ſeen in the wings of the common sort are in this not obſervable, nor is there any appearance of a tail. The legs are ſtout, formed much as in the galeated casſowary, with the addition of their being jagged or ſawed the whole of their length at the back part.</p><p>This bird is not uncommon in New Holland, as ſeveral of them have been ſeen about Botany Bay and other parts. Although it cannot fly, it runs ſo swiftly, that a greyhound can ſcarcely overtake it. The fleſh is ſaid to be in taſte not unlike beef.</p></div></body></text></TEI>