<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:40:02Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>blood. Owing to its colloid character, it is absorbed with difficulty, and its action is thus exerted throughout the greater part of the intestinal canal.</p><p>SENNACHERIB. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Babylonia,</hi> vol. iii. p. 187, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Israel,</hi> vol. xiii. p. 413 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p><p>SENNÁR. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Senaar.</hi></p><p>SENS, a town of France, chef-lieu of an arrondissement in the department of Yonne, lies on the right side of the Yonne near its confluence with the Vanne, and on the railway from Paris to Lyons, 70 miles south-east of the former city at the intersection of the line from Orleans to Troyes. It derives its importance from its antiquity and its archiepiscopal see. The cathedral of St Étienne occupies the site of an ancient temple on which St Savinian is said to have built, at the close of the 3d century, a little church consecrated to the Virgin. The present Gothic cathedral, erected between 1122 and 1168, subsequently underwent alteration in the 13th century and again under Louis XII. The west front measures 154 feet in breadth ; the middle portal has good sculptures, representing the parable of the virgins and the story of St Stephen. The right-hand portal contains twenty-two remarkable statuettes of the prophets, which have suffered considerable injuries. Above this portal rises the stone tower, decorated with armorial bearings and with statues representing the principal benefactors of the church. The bells in the campanile, by which the tower is surmounted, enjoyed immense reputation in the Middle Ages ; the two which still remain, La Savinienne and La Potentienne, weigh respectively 15 tons 7 cwts and 13 tons 13 cwts. The left portal is adorned with two bas-reliefs, Liberality and Avarice, as well as with the story of John the Baptist. The portal on the north side of the cathedral is one of the finest examples of French 16th-century sculpture. Glass windows of the 12th to the 16th century are preserved, some of them representing the legend of St Thomas of Canterbury. Among the interior adornments are an altarpiece finely carved in stone, the tomb of the dauphin (son of Louis XV.) and his consort, Marie Josèphe of Saxony, one of the masterpieces of Coustou, and bas-reliefs from the mausoleum of Cardinal Duprat. The treasury contains a fragment of the true cross presented by Charlemagne, and the vestments of St Thomas of Canterbury. It was in the cathedral of Sens that St Louis, in 1234, married Marguerite of Provence, and five years later deposited the crown of thorns. The official buildings of the cathedral, dating from the 13th century, have been restored by Viollet-le-Duc. The old judgment-hall and the dungeons had remained intact ; in the first story is the synod hall, vaulted with stone and lighted by beautiful grisaille windows. A Renaissance structure connects the buildings with the archiepiscopal palace, which also dates from that period. The oldest of the other churches of Sens is St Savinian, the foundation of which dates from the 3d century, while the crypt is of the early part of the 11th, and the upper portions of the bell-tower of the first years of the 13th. The contents of the museum of sculptured stones have been mainly derived from the old fortifications, which were themselves constructed during barbarian invasion from the ruins of public monuments. The only town gate still preserved is that known as the dauphin’s (1777). In the public library are a number of MSS. and a famous missal with ivory covers. The chemist Thenard has his statue in the town. The population in 1881 numbered 13,440.</p><p>Sens, when the capital of the Senones, one of the most powerful peoples of Gaul, bore the name of Agenticum. It was not finally subdued by the Romans till after the defeat of Vercingetorix. On the division of Gaul into seventeen provinces under the emperor Valens, Agenticum became the metropolis of the 4th Lugdunensis. Theatres, circuses, amphitheatres, triumphal arches, and aqueducts were all built in the town by the Romans. It was the meeting point of six great highways. The inhabitants, converted to Chris</p><p>tianity by the martyrs Savinian and Γotentian, held out against the Alemanni and the Franks in 356, against the Saracens in 731 or 738, and finally against the Normans in 886,—the last having besieged the town for six months. At the commencement of the feudal period Sens was governed by counts, who had become hereditary towards the middle of the 10th century ; and the contests of these counts with the archbishops or with their feudal superiors often led to much bloodshed and disaster. Several councils were held at Sens, notably that at which St Bernard and Abelard met. The burgesses in the middle of the 12th century formed a defensive association which carried on war against the clergy, and Philip Augustus restored the commune. In the ardour of its Catholicism Sens massacred the Protestants in 1562, and it was one of the first towns to join the League. Henry IV. did not effect his entrance till 1594, and he then deprived the town of its privileges. In 1622 Paris, hitherto suffragan to Sens, was made an archbishopric, and the bishoprics of Chartres, Orleans, and Meaux were transferred to the new jurisdiction. In 1791 the archbishopric was reduced to a bishopric of the department of Yonne. Suppressed in 1801, the see was restored in 1807 with the rank of archbishopric. The town was occupied by the invaders in 1814 and 1870-71.</p><p>SENSITIVE PLANT. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mimosa;</hi> comp. <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology,</hi> vol. xix. p. 62.</p><p>SEONI, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Seonee,</hi> a British district of India, in the Central Provinces, lying between 21° 36' and 22° 58' N. lat. and 79° 14' and 80° 19' E. long., with an area of 3247 square miles, is bounded on the N. by Jabalpur, on the E. by Mandla and Bálághát, on the S. by Nagpur and Bhan- dâra, and on the W. by Narsinhpur and Chhindwára. Seoni is a portion of the upland tract formed by the Sátpura Hills which extend along the south bank of the Narbadá (Nerbudda) from the plains of Broach on the west to the Maikal range in the east ; and it is remarkable for the beauty of its scenery and the fertility of its valleys. The northern and western portions of the district include the plateaus of Lakhnádon and Seoni ; the eastern section consists of the watershed and elevated basin of the Wain- ganga ; and in the south-west is a narrow strip of rocky land known as Dongartál. The plateaus of Seoni and Lakhnádon vary in height from 1800 to 2000 feet; they are well cultivated, clear of jungle, and their temperature is always moderate and healthy. Geologically the north part of Seoni consists of trap hills and the south of crystalline rock. The soil of the plateaus is the rich black cotton soil formed by disintegrated trap, of which about two-thirds of the district are said to consist, but towards the south, where cliffs of gneiss and other primitive formations occur, the soil is silicious and contains a large proportion of clay. Seoni is hilly throughout, the hills for the most part being clothed with small stunted trees ; but in the valleys and on the plateaus forest trees are very thinly scattered and are seldom of large size. The chief river of the district is the Wainganga, with its affluents the Hirí, Ságar, Thelí, Bijná, and Thánwar ; other streams are the Tímar and the Sher, affluents of the Narbadá. The average annual rainfall is about 50 inches.</p><p>The census of 1881 returned the population of Seoni district at 334,733 (males 167,925, females 166,808); of these 179,705 were Hindus, 13,442 Mohammedans, 99 Christians, and 139,444 aboriginals. <hi rend="smallcaps">Seoni </hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> is the only town with a population exceeding 10,000. Of the total district area of 3247 square miles only 1098 are cultivated, and of the portion lying waste 613 are returned as cultivable. Wheat forms the staple crop ; rice and other food-grains are also extensively grown ; and among miscellaneous products are cotton, fibres, and sugar-cane. In 1883-84 the gross revenue of Seoni amounted to £35,419, of which the land-tax yielded £15,379. Trade is chiefly carried on by means of markets in the towns. Manufactures consist of coarse cloth and some pottery of superior- quality made at Kánhiwára. At Khawása, in the midst of the forest, leather is beautifully tanned. The only means of communication is by road, the aggregate length of which is estimated at 90 miles. Seoni came under British rule early in the 19th century, on the downfall of the Nagpúr power, and it was formed into a separate district in 1861.</p><p>SEONI, principal town and administrative headquarters of the above district, is situated in 22° 5' 30" N. lat. and 79° 35' E. long., midway between Nagpur and Jabalpur.</p></body></text></TEI>