<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-12T18:39:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>all the Semitic languages, the termination h <hi rend="italic">(hú)</hi> as the
                suffix of the third person singular, is the Sabæan properly speaking. The other,
                which expresses the causative by <hi rend="italic">sa</hi> (corresponding to the
                Shaphel of the Aramæans and others), and for the suffix uses <hi rend="italic"
                    >s</hi> (like the Assyrian <hi rend="italic">sh</hi>), is the Minaic. To this
                latter branch belong the numerous South Arabic inscriptions recently found in the
                north of the Hijaz, near Hejr, where the Minæans must have had a commercial
                settlement. The difference between the two classes of inscriptions is no doubt
                ultimately based upon a real divergence of dialect. But the singular manner in which
                districts containing Sabæan inscriptions and those containing Minaic alternate with
                one another seems to point in part to a mere hieratic practice of clinging to
                ancient modes of expression. Indeed it is very probably due to conscious literary
                conservatism that the language of the inscriptions remains almost entirely unchanged
                through many centuries. A few inscriptions from districts rather more to the east
                exhibit certain linguistic peculiarities, which, however, may perhaps be explained
                by the supposition that the writers did not, as a rule, speak this dialect, and
                therefore were but imperfectly acquainted with it.</p>
            <p>As the Sabæan writing seldom indicates the vowels, our knowledge of the language is
                necessarily very incomplete ; and the unvarying style of the inscriptions excludes a
                great number of the commonest grammatical forms. Not a single occurrence of the
                first or second person has yet been detected, with the possible exception of one
                proper name, in which “ our god ” apparently occurs. But the knowledge which we
                already possess amply suffices to prove that Sabæan is closely related to Arabic as
                we are acquainted with it. The former language possesses the same phonetic elements
                as the latter, except that it has at least one additional sibilant, which appears to
                have been lost in Arabic. It possesses the broken plural, a dual form resembling
                that used in Arabic, &amp;c. It is especially important to notice that Sabæan
                expresses the idea of indefiniteness by means of an appended <hi rend="italic"
                    >m,</hi> just as Arabic expresses it by means of an <hi rend="italic">n,</hi>
                which in all probability is a modification of the former sound. Both in this point
                and in some others Sabæan appears more primitive than Arabic, as might be expected
                from the earlier date of its monuments. The article is formed by appending an <hi
                    rend="italic">n.</hi> In its vocabulary also Sabæan bears a great resemblance to
                Arabic, although, on the other hand, it often approaches more nearly to the northern
                Semitic languages in this respect; and it possesses much that is peculiar to itself.
                    @@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p>
            <p>Soon after the Christian era Sabæan civilization began to decline, and completely
                perished in the wars with the Abyssinians, who several times occupied the country,
                and in the 6th century remained in possession of it for a considerable period. In
                that age the language of central Arabia was already penetrating into the Sabæan
                domain. It is further possible that many tribes which dwelt not far to the north of
                the civilized districts had always spoken dialects resembling central Arabic rather
                than Sabæan. About the year 600 “ Arabic ” was the language of all Yemen, with the
                exception perhaps of a few isolated districts, and this process of assimilation
                continued in later times. Several centuries after Mohammed learned Yemenites were
                acquainted with the characters of the inscriptions which abounded in their country ;
                they were also able to decipher the proper names and a small number of Sabæan words
                the meaning of which was still known to them, but they could no longer understand
                the inscriptions as a whole. Being zealous local patriots, they discovered in those inscriptions which they
                imagined themselves to be capable of deciphering many fabulous stories respecting
                the glory of the ancient Yemenites.</p>
            <p>Farther to the east, in the sea-coast districts of Shihr and Mahra, up to the borders
                of the barren desert of the interior, and also, we are told, in the island of
                Socotra, dialects very unlike Arabic are still spoken. Allusions to this fact are
                found in Arabic writers of the 10th century. These dialects depart widely from the
                ancient Semitic type, but bear some resemblance to the Sabæan, although they cannot
                be regarded as actually descended from the latter. One feature which they have in
                common with Sabæan is the habit of appending an <hi rend="italic">n</hi> to the
                imperfect. Like the Ethiopic, and probably also the Sabæan, they use <hi
                    rend="italic">k</hi> (instead of t) in the terminations of the first person
                singular and the second person singular and plural of the perfect tense. In the
                suffixes of the third person there appears, at least in the feminine, an <hi
                    rend="italic">s,</hi> as in the Minaic. Unfortunately the information which we
                have hitherto possessed respecting these dialects is meagre and inexact, in part
                very inexact.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> It is much to be wished that soon they
                may all be investigated as carefully as possible, the more so as there is danger in
                delay, for Arabic is gradually supplanting them.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Ethiopic..—</hi>In Abyssinia, too, and in the neighbouring
                countries we find languages which bear a certain resemblance to Arabic. The Geez or
                Ethiopic @@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> proper, the language of the ancient
                kingdom of Aksúm, was reduced to writing at an early date. To judge by the few
                passages communicated by Salt, the back of the inscription of Aeizanas, king of
                Aksúm about 350, exhibits writing in the Sabæan language, which appears to prove
                that the development of the Geez character out of the Sabæan, and the elevation of
                Geez to the rank of a literary language, must have taken place after the year 350.
                The oldest monuments of this language which are known with certainty are the two
                great inscriptions of Tázéná, a heathen king of Aksúm, dating from about 500.
                Hitherto our acquaintance with these inscriptions has been derived from very
                imperfect drawings @@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> ; but they amply suffice to show
                that we have here the same language as that in which the Ethiopic Bible is written,
                with the very same exact indication of the vowels,—a point in which Ethiopic has an
                advantage over all other Semitic characters. Who introduced this vocalization is
                unknown. When the above- mentioned inscriptions were made the Bible had probably
                been already translated into Geez from the Greek, perhaps in part by Jews; for Jews
                and Christians were at that time actively competing with one another, both in Arabia
                and in Abyssinia; nor were the former unsuccessful in making proselytes. The
                missionaries who gave the Bible to the Abyssinians must, at least in some cases,
                have spoken Aramaic as their mother-tongue, for this alone can explain the fact that
                in the Ethiopic Bible certain religious conceptions are expressed by Aramaic words.
                During the following centuries various works were produced by the Abyssinians in
                this language ; they were all, so far as we are able to judge, of a more or less
                theological character, almost invariably translations from the Greek. We cannot say
                with certainty when Geez ceased to be the language of the people, but it was
                probably about a thousand years ago. From the time when the Abyssinian kingdom was
                reconstituted, towards the end of the 13th century, by the so-called Solomonian
                dynasty (which was of southern origin), the language of the court and of the
                Government was Amharic ; but Geez remained the ecclesiastical and literary language,
                and Geez literature even showed a certain</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> The literature relating to these inscriptions is
                widely scattered. Before the Parisian <hi rend="italic">Corpus</hi> supplies us with
                the collected materials, we may hope to see the Sabæan grammar of D. H. Müller, who,
                with Halévy, has lately rendered the greatest services in this department.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> See especially Maltzan, in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Z.D.M.G.,</hi> vols. xxv. and xxvii.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> This name is due to the fact that the Abyssinians,
                under the influence of false erudition, applied the name <hi rend="italic"
                    >klθιoπia</hi> to their own kingdom.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> The authorities of the library of Frankfort have
                kindly enabled the present writer to consult Rüppell’s copies, which are more
                accurate than the lithographs in his book. The English in 1868 did not seize the
                opportunity to examine thoroughly the antiquities of Aksum, and since then no
                traveller has taken the trouble to procure accurate copies of these extremely
                important monuments.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
