<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:40:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>(4) <hi rend="italic">Brevissima Apologia pro Symphoriano Camρegio in Leonardum Fuchsium,</hi> 1536, 12mo ; no extant copy is known ; Tollin has reprinted an extract from it. (5) <hi rend="italic">Syruporum Universa Ratio,</hi> &amp;c., Paris, 1537, 16mo; there were four subsequent editions, the last being Venice, 1548 (six lectures on digestion, the composition and use of syrups being treated in the fifth lecture). (6) <hi rend="italic">In quondam Medicum Apologetica Disceptatio pro Astrologia,</hi> Paris, 1538, 16mo ; reprinted, Berlin, 1880 ; the <hi rend="italic">medicus</hi> is Jean Tagault, who had interrupted the lectures of Servetus on astronomy, under which he included meteorology. (7) <hi rend="italic">Biblia Sacra ex Santis Pagnini Trala- tione . . . recognita, et scholiis illustrata,</hi> &amp;c., Lyons (Hugo à Porta), 1542, fol., remarkable for its theory of prophecy, explained in the preface and illustrated in the notes. (8) D’Artigny says that Servetus “fit les argumens” to a Spanish version of the <hi rend="italic">Summa </hi>of Aquinas ; but nothing is known of this or of the “ divers traités de grammaire ” which he translated from Latin into Spanish. (9) <hi rend="italic">Christianismi Restitutio,</hi> &amp;c., 1553, 8vo (perfect copies in Vienna and Paris, an imperfect copy in Edinburgh), partly reprinted, London, 1723; 4to (copies in London and Paris), reprinted 1790 ; 8vo, by Rau at Nuremberg for De Murr, from the Vienna copy ; manuscript copies are rare ; the Paris library has a manuscript copy of an earlier recension of several books, including the often- quoted description of the pulmonary circulation. This work is often called anonymous, but the initials M. S. V. are given at the end and the full name at p. 199 ; the volume is not a single treatise but an assemblage of theological tracts written in a nervous and epigrammatic style and with great command of very various learning ; the <hi rend="italic">Apologia</hi> addressed to Melanchthon, with which it concludes, is in the writer’s best manner. Two treatises, <hi rend="italic">Desiderius (amte 1542)</hi> and <hi rend="italic">De Tribus Impostoribus</hi> (1598), have been erroneously assigned to Servetus. Of his few remaining letters most will be found in Mosheim.</p><p>The literature relating to Servetus is very large, but the following are some of the most important pieces. Calvin’s <hi rend="italic">Defensio Orthodoae Fidei,</hi> &amp;c., 1554, 4to (also in French, <hi rend="italic">Déclaration pour maintenir,</hi> &amp;c., 16mo, same date), is the source of many prevalent misconceptions respecting the opinions of Servetus and his attitude on his trial. De la Roche's <hi rend="italic">Historical Account, </hi>&amp;c.<hi rend="italic">,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Mem. of Lit.,</hi> 1711-12 (reproduced in French, <hi rend="italic">Βiblioth. Angl.,</hi> Amsterdam, 1717,18mo), was followed by <hi rend="italic">An Impartial History,</hi> &amp;c., 1724, 8vo (said to be by Nathaniel Hodges, a Baptist minister, afterwards knighted). Allwoerden’s <hi rend="italic">Historia,</hi> &amp;c., 1728, 4to (materials furnished by Mosheim), is superseded by Mosheim’s <hi rend="italic">Anderweitiger Versuch,</hi> &amp;c., 1748, 4to, with its appendix, <hi rend="italic">Neue Nachrichten,</hi> 1750, 4to, issued after the publication of the records of the Vienne trial by D’Artigny, in <hi rend="italic">Nouveaux Mémoires d'Hist.,</hi> Ac., vol. ii., 1749, 12mo. Chaufepié’s valuable article in <hi rend="italic">Nouv. Dict. Historique,</hi> vol. iv., 1756, fol. (translated separately by Rev. James Yair, 1771, 8vo), makes no use of Mosheim's later researches. Trechsel, in <hi rend="italic">Die prot. Antitrinitarier vor F. Socin,</hi> Ac., bk. 1., 1839, 8vo, uses all available materials up to date. Since then the investigations of H. Tollin (published in a series of some forty separate articles in various journals from 1874 to 1885) have thrown light on every portion of the subject. The records of the Geneva trial, first published by De la Roche, and reproduced in Rilliet's <hi rend="italic">Relation,</hi> Ac., 1844, 8vo, and elsewhere, are best given in vol. viii. (1870) of the edition of Calvin’s works by Baum, Cunitz, and Reuss ; Roget, in <hi rend="italic">Hist. du Peuple de Genève,</hi> vol. iv., 1877, has a good account of both trials. The passage describing the pulmonary circulation is first noticed by W. Wotton, in <hi rend="italic">Reflections upon Ancient and Mod. Learning,</hi> 1694, and has given rise to a literature of its own;—see especially Tollin’s <hi rend="italic">Die Entdeckung des Blutkreislaufs,</hi> Ac., 1876, Huxley, in <hi rend="italic">Fortnightly Rev.,</hi> February 1878; and Tollin’s <hi rend="italic">Kritische Bemerkungen über Harvey und seine Vorgänger,</hi> 1882. Other physiological speculations of Servetus are noted by Sigmond <hi rend="italic">(The Unnoticed Theories of Servetus,</hi> 1826); but it has escaped Sigmond that Servetus had an idea of the composition of water and of air. As a thinker, Servetus is claimed on superficial grounds by Unitarians (see Wallace, <hi rend="italic">Antitrin. Biog.,</hi> 1850, i. 420), who have written several accounts of him, of which R. Wright’s <hi rend="italic">Apology,</hi> Ac., 1807, 8vo, is the worst, and J. S. Porter’s <hi rend="italic">Servetus and Calvin,</hi> Ac., 1854, 8vo, perhaps the best. Saisset, in <hi rend="italic">Rev. des Deux Mondes,</hi> 1848, treats Servetus as a pantheist ; he is followed by Willis, in his <hi rend="italic">Servetus and Calvin,</hi> 1877, 8vo, a most unsatisfactory book (comp. <hi rend="italic">Theol. Rev.,</hi> April and July 1878). Tollin’s <hi rend="italic">Das Lehrsystem Michael Servers,</hi> 3 vols., 1876-78, 8vo, and Pünjer’s compendious <hi rend="italic">De Michaelis Served Doctrina,</hi> Ac., 1876, 8vo, are valuable digests of his opinions, from different points of view. Of Servetus's personal character the best vindication is Tollin’s <hi rend="italic">Characterbild Michael Servers,</hi> 1876, 8vo (in French with additions by Dardier, <hi rend="italic">Portrait Caractère,</hi> 1879, 8vo). His story has been dramatized by Max Ring, <hi rend="italic">Die Genfer</hi> (1850), by José Echegaray, <hi rend="italic">La Muerte en los Labios</hi> (1880), and by Albert Hamann, <hi rend="italic">Servet</hi> (1881). The recent discovery at the Record Office, London, (U. 140) and the British Museum (Cotton MSS., Galba B. x.) of intercepted letters from Servetus at Louvain in 1538 adds considerably to our information about his family and early friends, but introduces new problems as to the details of his fitful career.	(A. GO.)</p><p>SERVIA, a kingdom belonging to the Balkan peninsula of Europe, lying between Bosnia on the west and Bulgaria and Roumania on the east, and between the Turkish province of Albania on the south and the Austrian Military Frontier on the north. From Bosnia it is separated by the Drina, from Austrian and Roumanian territory by the Danube and the Save, and from Bulgaria partly by the Timok. Some parts of the southern frontier are indicated by mountains, but elsewhere there are no natural boundaries. In shape Servia is an irregular trapezium, situated between about 42° 30' and 45° N. lat. and 19° and 22° 30' E. long. The area is about 18,760 square miles, and the population (1,667,159 in 1874) was estimated at the end of 1884 to be 1,902,419, thus giving a density of about</p><p>100 to the square mile. This low density, only about one- third of that of the United Kingdom, is explained by the nature of the surface, the inland position, the defective communications with the exterior, and the absence of manufacturing industries.</p><p>The surface is for the most part mountainous or hilly, though there are no well-defined mountain ranges of any extent. The highest summits lie near the middle of the southern frontier, where Mount Kopaonik attains the height of nearly 7000 feet. Towards the Bosnian frontier the mountains are pretty closely massed together, and some of the summits approach 4000 feet ; this height is exceeded on the eastern side of the country, where the mountains, forming a continuation of the Carpathians, are in many places more rugged and precipitous than anywhere else in the kingdom. The Rudnik Mountains, which begin immediately to the north of the Servian Morava, have their highest parts in the south and gradually sink towards the north from nearly 3000 to less than 2000 feet. Still lower are the elevations in the provinces in the extreme south acquired in 1878 under the treaty of Berlin. As a general rule the Servian highlands consist of detached groups of mountains and conical hills with gentle slopes rising from verdant valleys, and they are mostly covered to the top with forests, chiefly of oak and beech, the higher summits in the south also with conifers. But the plains, though numerous, are of no great extent, and occur chiefly along the banks of the rivers. Apart from frontier rivers, the most important stream is the Morava, which, rising on the western slopes of the Kara Dagh, a little beyond the Servian frontier, enters the country with a north-easterly course near the extreme south-east, and then turns north-north-west and flows almost in a straight line through the heart of the kingdom to the Danube. In the upper part of its course it is known as the Bulgarian Morava, and only after receiving the Servian Morava on the left is it known as the Morava simply or as the Great Morava. The only other important tributary is the Nishava, which it receives from the right at Nish. The valleys of all these rivers, especially those of the Bulgarian and the Great Morava, and of the Nishava, contain considerable areas of level or low-lying country well suited for the growth of corn, and the low grounds along the Save and the Danube from the Drina to the Morava are also well adapted for agriculture, though for the most part devoted only to pasture. Altogether no more than one-sixth of the surface is estimated to be occupied by cultivated fields and vineyards, while one-fifth is estimated to form pasture land and about an equal area woodland. Nearly one-half of the entire area is believed to be unproductive.</p><p>Besides the frontier streams on the north and west, the only river of any importance for navigation is the Morava, which is navigable for steamers of light draught as high as Tiupriia about 60 miles from its mouth, but its valley is important as the main highway of the country, and all the more since the introduction of railways. Railways both to Constantinople and to Salonica are now (1886) in course of construction under a convention concluded with Austria in 1881. The section common to the two systems, that from Belgrade to Nish, 152 miles in length, was opened for traffic in September 1884, and the line (76 miles) from Nish to Vranja was completed in March 1886, but the connexion with the Turkish railway from Salonica remains to be completed. At present, in consequence of the unsatisfactory communication with the south, only about 7 or 8 per cent. of the Servian imports enter by the southern frontier, 85 per cent. coming through Austria- Hungary. In the beginning of 1886 work had been begun on only one-half of the line from Nish to Pirot, on the other system.</p></body></text></TEI>