<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-12T18:39:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>the latest official figures (1882) giving 685,950 for the province, exclusive of the
                Kuldja region. Of these Russians numbered, according to Kostenko, 44,585, 20,640
                being Cossacks, who are very poor as compared with the free Russian emigrants. The
                majority of the population are Kirghiz (595,237) ; next come Tarantchis (36,265),
                Kalmucks (about 25,000), Mongols and Manchurians (22,000), and Dungans (19,657),
                these last two mostly in Kuldja ; while Tatars and Sarts are each represented by
                some 3000 or 3500 (all the foregoing figures include those for Kuldja). The</p>
            <p>province is subdivided into five districts ; Vyernyi (18,423 inhabitants in 1879, of
                whom 3586 were military), the chief town of the province, formerly Almaty, is
                situated at the foot of the Trans-Ilian Ala-tau, and has a mixed population of
                Russians, Tatars, Sarts, Kirghiz, Kalmucks, and Jews ; its trade with Kuldja and
                Kashgar is increasing rapidly, and it has now two lyceums, for boys and girls, and
                several other schools. The other towns—Kopal (5450 inhabitants), Serghiopol (1045),
                Tokmak (1770), and Karakol (2780) —are merely administrative centres.</p>
            <p>THE name “Semitic languages ” is used to designate a group of Asiatic and African
                languages, some living and some dead, namely, Hebrew and Phoenician, Aramaic,
                Assyrian, Arabic, Ethiopic (Geez and Amharic). The name, which was introduced by
                Eichhorn, @@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> is derived from the fact that most nations
                which speak or spoke these languages are descended, according to Genesis, from Shem,
                son of Noah. But the classification of nations in Genesis X. is founded neither upon
                linguistic nor upon ethnographical principles : it is determined rather by
                geographical and political considerations. For this reason Elam and Lud are also
                included among the children of Shem; but neither the Elamites (in Susiana) nor the
                Lydians appear to have spoken a language connected with Hebrew. On the other hand,
                the Phoenicians (Canaanites), whose dialect closely resembled that of Israel, are
                not counted as children of Shem. Moreover, the compiler of the list in Genesis x.
                had no clear conceptions about the peoples of south Arabia and Ethiopia.
                Nevertheless it would be undesirable to give up the universally received terms “
                Semites ” and “ Semitic.” There exist large groups of languages and peoples which
                bear no natural collective appellations, because the peoples grew up unconscious of
                their mutual relationship ; so science must needs give them artificial designations,
                and it would be well if all such terms were as short and precise as “ Semitic.”</p>
            <p>The connexion of the Semitic languages with one another is somewhat close, in any
                case closer than that of the Indo-European languages. The more ancient Semitic
                tongues differ from one another scarcely more than do the various Teutonic dialects.
                Hence even in the 17th century such learned Orientalists as Hottinger, Bochart,
                Castell, and Ludolf had a tolerably clear notion of the relationship between the
                different Semitic languages with which they were acquainted ; indeed the same may be
                said of some Jewish scholars who lived many centuries earlier, as, for instance,
                Jehuda ben Koraish. It is not difficult to point out a series of characteristic
                marks common to these languages,—the predominance of triconsonantal roots, or of
                roots formed after the analogy of such, similarity in the formation of nominal and
                verbal stems, a great resemblance in the forms of the personal pronouns and in their
                use for the purpose of verbal inflexion, the two principal tenses, the importance
                attached to the change of vowels in the interior of words, and lastly considerable
                agreement with regard to order and the construction of sentences. Yet even so
                ancient a Semitic language as the Assyrian appears to lack some of these features,
                and in certain modern dialects, such as New Syriac, Mahri, and more particularly
                Amharic, many of the characteristics of older Semitic speech have disappeared. But
                the resemblance in vocabulary generally diminishes in proportion to the modernness
                of the dialects. Still we can trace the connexion between the modern and the ancient
                dialects, and show, at least approximately, how the former were developed out of the
                latter. Where a development of this kind can be proved to have taken place, there a
                relationship must</p>
            <p>exist, however much the individual features may have been effaced. The question here
                is not of logical categories but of organic groups.</p>
            <p>All these languages are descendants of a primitive Semitic stock which has long been
                extinct. Many of its most important features may be reconstructed with at least
                tolerable certainty, but we must beware of attempting too much in this respect. When
                the various cognate languages of a group diverge in essential points, it is by no
                means always possible to determine which of them has retained the more primitive
                form. The history of the development of these tongues during the period anterior to
                the documents which we possess is often extremely obscure in its details. Even when
                several Semitic languages agree in important points of grammar we cannot always be
                sure that in these particulars we have what is primitive, since in many cases
                analogous changes have taken place independently. To one who should assert the
                complete reconstruction of the primitive Semitic language to be possible, we might
                put the question, Would the man who is best acquainted with all the Romance
                languages be in a position to reconstruct their common mother, Latin, if the
                knowledge of it were lost ? And yet there are but few Semitic languages which we can
                know as accurately as the Romance languages are known. As far as the vocabulary is
                concerned, we may indeed maintain with certainty that a considerable number of words
                which have in various Semitic languages the form proper to each were a part of
                primitive Semitic speech. Nevertheless even then we are apt to be misled by
                independent but analogous formations and by words borrowed at a very remote
                    period.@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> Each Semitic language or group of languages
                has, however, many words which we cannot point out in the others. Of such words a
                great number no doubt belonged to primitive Semitic speech, and either disappeared
                in some of these languages or else remained in use, but not so as to be recognizable
                by us. Yet many isolated words and roots may in very early times have been borrowed
                by the Hebrew, the Aramaic, the Ethiopic, &amp;c., perhaps from wholly different
                languages, of which no trace is left.</p>
            <p>The question which of the known Semitic dialects most resembles the primitive Semitic
                language is less important than one might at first suppose, since the question is
                one not of absolute but only of relative priority. After scholars had given up the
                notion (which, however, was not the fruit of scientific research) that all Semitic
                languages, and indeed all the languages in the world, were descendants of Hebrew or
                of Aramaic, it was long the fashion to maintain that Arabic bore a close resemblance
                to the primitive Semitic language.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> But, just as it is
                now recognized with ever-increasing clearness that Sanskrit is far from having
                retained in such a degree as was even lately supposed the characteristics of
                primitive Indo-European</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@1</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Einleitung in das A.T.,</hi> 2d ed., i. 45 (Leipsic, 1787).</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> The more alike two languages are the more difficult
                it usually is to detect, as borrowed elements, those words which have passed from
                one language into the other.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> This theory is carried to its extreme limit in
                Olshausen’s very valuable <hi rend="italic">Hebrew Grammar</hi> (Brunswick,
                1861).</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
