<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>would perhaps ere this time have been loſt in oblivion. Individuals in private life ſeldom engage the attention of the hiſtorian ; his object is to record the actions of princes, warriors, and ſtateſmen. Had not the profeſ-ſors of Chriſtianity in the. earlier ages of its exiſtence been expofed to perſecutlons, and unjuſt âcculations ſrom which they were called on to vindicate themſelves, we ſhonld be ſtrangers to the names and virtues of ſaints and martyrs, and to the learning and endowments of the firſt apologiſts for Chriſtianity. We cap therefore only trace the general influence of the mſti-tutions of Chriſtianity on ſociety. We cannot hope to make an accurate enumeration of particulars. In many of the countries in which it has been eſtabliſhed, it has produced a very favourable change on the circumſtaiices of domeſtic life. Polygamy, a practice repugnant to. the will of our Creator (fee Polygamy), who has declared his intentions in this inſtance in the plaineſt manner, by cauſing nearly equal numbers ol males and females to be brought into the world, was never com-pletely abohſhed but by Chriſtianity.</p><p>‘ The practice of divorce, too, though in ſome caſes proper and even neceffary, had been lo much abuſed at the time of our Saviour’s appearance in the world, that he found reaſon to declare it unlawful, unleſs in the eaſe of adultery. The propriety and reaſonableneſs of this prohibition will ſufficiently appear, if we conlideι, that when divorces<hi rend="sup">z</hi>are eaſily obtained, both parties will often have nothing elfe in view at the period of marriage than the diffolution of their nuptial engagements after a ſhort cohabitation ; the intereſts of the huſhand and the wife will almoſt always be ſeparate ; and tbe children of ſuch a marriage are ſcarce likely to enjoy the cordial affection and tender watchful care of either parent. The huſhand in fuch a caſe will naturally bc to his wife, not a friend and protector, but a tyrant ; fear and deceit, not love, gratitude, or a ſenſe of duty, will be the principles of the wife’s obedience.</p><p>In another iwſtance, likewiſe, Chriſtianity has produced an happy changé on the circumſtances of domeſtic life ; it muſt be acknowledged to havc contributed greatly to the abolition of ſtavery, or at leaſt to the mi-tip ation of the rigour of ſervitude. The cuſtoms and laws of the Romans in relation to ſlaves were cruel and ſevere. Maſters were often ſo inhuman as to remove aged, ſick, or infirm ſtaves, into an iſland in the Tiber, where they fuffered them to periſh without pity or aſſiſtance. The greater part of the ſubjects of many of thoſe republics which enjoyed the moſt liberty, groaned under tyrannical oppreffion ; they were condemned to drag out a miſerable exiſtence in hard labour, under inhuman uſage, and to be transferred like beaſts from one maſter to another. The ſhardſhips of ſiavery were eaſed, not by any particular precept of the Gofpel, but by the o∙entle and humane ſpirit which breathed through the general tenor of the whole ſyſtctn of dortrines and precepts oſ which the Goſpel conſiſts. It muſt indeed be allowed, that a trade in ſiaves is at preſent carried on by people who prefume to call themſelves Chriſtians, and protected by the legiſiature of Chriſtian ſtates: but the ſpirit of the Chriſtian code condemns the practice, and the true Chriſtian will not engage in it.</p><p>Partly by the direct and conſpicuous, partly by the ſecret and unſeen, influence of Chriſtianity fince its promulgation in the world, the hearts of men have been</p><p>gradually ſoftened; even barbarians have been formed to mildneſs and humanity ; the influence of ſelfiſhneſs has been checked and reſtrained; and even war, amid all the pernicious improvements by which men have fought to render it more terrible, has affirmed much more of the ſpirit of mildnefε and peace than ever entered into it during the reign of heatheniſm.</p><p>If we review the hiſtory of mankind with a view to their political circumſtances, we ſhall ſind, that by ſome means or other, it has happened, ſince the time when the Goſpel was firſt preached, that both ſyſtems of legiſlature and forms of government have been raiſed to much greater perfection, at leaſt in thoſe parts of the world into which the religion of Jeſus has made its way, and obtained an eſtabliſhment.</p><p>The popular government of the Romans, notwithſtanding the multiplicity of their laws, and the imperfections oſ their political conſtitution, was, no doubt, happily enough adapted to promote the increafe of the power and the extenſion of the empire of Rome. In Greece there were various republics, the wiſdom and impartiality of whoſe laws have been highly celebrated. But we apprehend that there is a ſufficient number of well authenticated facts to warrant us to affirm, that ſince Chriſtianity has been propagated, and has had ſuf-ſicient time to produce its full effect on arts, manners, and literature, even under governments the form oi which might appear leſs favourable than tlm celebrated models of antiquity to the liberty and happineſs ol the people in general, theſe actually have been much better provided for than under the laws of Athens or Sparta, or even of Rome in the days of the conſuls. It is a juft and happy obiewatiυn of Monteiquieu, who has attributed ſo much to the influence of climate and local circumſtances, that “ the mildneſs ſo frequently recommended in the Goſpel is incompatible with the deſpotic rage with which an arbitrary tyrant puniſhes lus ſubjects, and exerciſes himſelf in cruelty. Tt is the Chriſtian religion (ſays he) which, in ſpite of the extent of empire, and the influence of climate, has hindered deſpotiſm from being eſtabliſhed in Ethiopia, and has carried into Africa the manners of Europe. The heir to the empire of Ethiopia enjoys a principality, and gives to other ſubjects an example of love and obedience— Not far from hence may be ſeen the Mahometan ſhut-ting up the children of the king of Sennaar, at whoſe death the council fends to murder them in favour of the prince who aſcends the throne. Let us ſet before our eyes (continues that eloquent writer), in the third chapter of the 24th book of his Spirit of Laws, on one hand the continual ιnaffacres of the kings and generals of the Greeks and Romans, and on the other the deduction of people and cities by the famous conquerors-Timur Beg and Jenghiz Kan, who ravaged Aſia, and we ſhall perceive, that we owe to Chriſtianity in government a certain political law, and in war a certain law of nations, which allows to the conquered the great-</p><p>advantages of liberty, laws, wealth, and always religion, when the conqueror is not blind to his own intereſt.”</p><p>Theſe are the reflections of no common judge in this matter, but one who had long ſtudied the hiſtory of nations, and obſerved the phenomena of the various forms of ſociety, with ſuch fucceſs as few others have attained.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>