<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Pencil pf </hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rays,</hi></hi>  a number of rays iſſuing from a point of an object, and diverging in the form of a cone.</p><p>RAZOR, a well-known inſtrument, uſed by fur-gcons, barbers, &amp;c. for (having off the hair from va-rious parts of the body.—As ſhaving to many people is a moſt painful operation, cutlers in different cotιn-tries have long applied their ſkill to remove that inconvenience. Some have invented ſoaps of a peculiar kind to make the operation more eaſy, and ſome have invented ſtraps. with reſpect to razors, ſome artiſts have ſucceeded rather by accident than from any fixed principle ; and therefore we have found great inequality in the goodnefs of razors made by the ſame artiſt.</p><p>A correſpondent aſſures us, that he has for 40 years paſt been at much pains to find out razors made by the beſt makers both in England and Scotland, and was fortunate enough, about 22 years ago, to diſcover a kind made by a Scotchman of the name of <hi rend="italic">Logan,</hi>  which he called magnetical razors, becauſe they were directed to be touched with an artificial magnet before ufing. Theſe, our friend aſſures us, are moſt excellent razors, and he has uſed them for upwards of 20 years. He fays likewiſe that they continue in good order, without requiring to be ground ; but that the great draw-back on their being generally uſed, is the price, which is higher than moſt people are able or diſpoſed to give ' for that jnſtrument. ‘ ûur correſpondent, who reſides in the vicinity of London, alio informs us, that lately the famous ſurgeon’s inſtrument-maker, Mr Savigny in Pall Mall, after numberleſs experiments, in the courſe of above 20 years, has at length brought razors to a degree of perfection never yet equalled ; and with ſuch certainty, that the purchaſer is in no danger of a diſappointment, though the price is very moderate. By theſe, we are told, the operation of ſtiaving is performed with greater eaſe, more perfectly, and more ex-</p><p>peditiouſiy, than with any other.</p><p>RE, in grammar, an inſeparable particle added to the beginning of words to double or otherwiſe modify their meaning ; as in re-action, re-move, τe-export, &amp;c.</p><p>RE-ACTION, in phyfiology, the refiſtance made by all bodies to the action or impulſe of others that endeavour to change its ſtate whether of motion or reſt, &amp;c.</p><p>READING, the art of delivering written language with propriety, force, and elegance.</p><p>" we muſt not judge ſo unfavourably of eloquence or good reading (ſays the illuſtrious Fenelon), as to reckon it only a frivolous art, that a declaimer uſes to impoſe upon the weak imagination of the multitude, and to ſerve his own ends. It is a very ſerious art, defigned to inſtruct people ; to ſuppreſs their paſſions and reform their manners ; to ſupport the laws, direct public councils, and to make men good and happy.”</p><p>Reaſon and experience demonſtrate, that <hi rend="italic">delivery in reading ought to be leſs animated thaq in interefledſpeaking. </hi>In every exerciſe of the faculty of ſpeech, and thoſe expreſſions of countenance and geſture with which it is generally attended^ wε may be confidered to be always in one of the two following fituations : Firſt, delivering our <hi rend="italic">boſom fentiτnents</hi>  on circumſtances which relate to ourſelves or others, or, ſecondly, <hi rend="italic">repeating</hi>  ſomething that was ſpoken on a certain occaſion for the amuſe-</p><p>ment or information of an auditor. Now, if we obſerve the deliveries natural to theſe two ſituations, we ſſiall find, that the firſt may be accompanied with every degree of expreſſion which can manifeſt itſelf in us, from the loweſt of ſympathy to the moſt violent and energe-tic of the ſuperior paſſions ; while the latter, from the ſpeaker’s chief buiineſs being to repeat what he heard <hi rend="italic">with accuracy,</hi>  diſcovers only a faint imitation of thoſe ſigns of the emotions which we ſuppoſe agitated him from whom the words were firſt borrowed.—The uſe and neceſſity of this difference of manner is evident ; . and if we are attentive to theſe natural figns of ex-preſſion, we ſliall find them conforming with the great-eſt nicety to the ſlighteſt and moſt minute movements of the breaſt.</p><p>This repetition of another’s words might be ſuppoſed. to paſs through the mouth oſ a ſecond or third perſon ; and in theſe caſes, ſince they were not ear and eye wit-neſſes of him who firſt ſpoke them, their manner oſ de-livery would want the advantage neceſſarily arifing from an immediate idea of the original one ; hence, on this account, this would be a ſtill lefs lively repreſentation than that of the firft <hi rend="italic">repeater.</hi>  But as, from a daily obſervation of every variety of ſpeeeh and its aſſociated figns of emo-tion, mankind foon become pretty well acquainted with them, and this in different degrees, according to their diſcernment, ſenfibility, &amp;c. experience (hows us that theſe latter <hi rend="italic">repeaters</hi>  (as we call them) might conceive and uſe a manner of delivery which, though lefs <hi rend="italic">charafie-rijlic</hi>  perhaps, would on the whole be no way inferior to the fiiſt, as to the <hi rend="italic">common</hi>  natural expreſſion proper for their fituation. It appears, therefore, that repeaters <hi rend="italic">of every degree</hi>  may be eſteemed upon a level as to anima-tion, and that our twofold diſtinction above contains accurately enough the whole variety of ordinary delivery ;—we ſay <hi rend="italic">ordinary,</hi>  becauſe</p><p>There is another very peculiar kind of delivery ſometimes uſed in the perſon of a <hi rend="italic">repeater,</hi>  of which it will in this place be neceſſary to take ſome notice, what we mean here is <hi rend="italic">mimicry;</hi>  an accompliſſiment whieh, when perfectly and properly diſplayed, never fails of yielding a high degree of pleaſure. But fince this pleaſure chiefly ’reſults from the principle of <hi rend="italic">imitation </hi>reſpecting <hi rend="italic">manner,</hi>  and not from the purport of the <hi rend="italic">matter</hi>  communicated ; fince, comparatively ſpeaking, it is only attainable by few perſons, and practiſed only on particular occafions;—on theſe accounts it muſt fie refuſed a place among the modes of uſeful delivery taught us by <hi rend="italic">general</hi>  nature, and eſteemed a qualifica-tion purely anomalous.</p><p>Theſe diſtinctions with regard to a ſpeaker’s ſituation of mind premiſed, let .us fee to which of them an <hi rend="italic">author</hi>  and his <hi rend="italic">reader</hi>  may moſt properly be referred, and how they are circumſtanced. with regaιd to one another.</p><p>The matter of all books is, either what the author ſays in his <hi rend="italic">own</hi>  perſon, or an acknowledged recital of the words of <hi rend="italic">others :</hi>  hence an author may be eſteemed both an <hi rend="italic">original</hi>  fpeaker and a <hi rend="italic">repeater,</hi>  according as what he writes is ©f the firſt or fecond kind. Now a reader muſt be ſuppofed either actually to perſonate the author, or one whoſe office is barely to communicate what he has ſaid to an auditor. But in the firſt of theſe ſuppoſitions he<hi rend="sub">β</hi>would, in the delivery of what is the au-thor’sown, evidently commence, <hi rend="italic">mimic;</hi>  which being, as</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>