<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>army of ſatyrs have been only a race of mountaineers, whom Rama, if ſuch a monarch ever exiſted, had civilized ? However that may be, the large breed of Indian apes is at this moment held in high veneration by tlie Hindoos, and fed with devotion by the Brahmans, who ſeent in two or three places on the banks of the Ganges to have a regular endowment for the ſupport of them : they live in tribes of three or four hundred, are wonderfully gentle (I ſpeak as an eye-witneſs), and ap-pear to have fome kind of order and ſubordination in their little ſylvan polity.” The feſtival of Rhama is held on the 9th day of the new moon of Chaitra, on which the war of Lauca is dramatically repreſented, conclu-ding with an exhibition of the fire ordeal, by which the victor’s wife Sita gave proof of her connubial fidelity. Among the Hindoos there are a variety of very fine dramas of great antiquity ®n the ſtory of Rhama.</p><p>There are three Rhamas mentioned in the Indian mythology, who, together with Criſhna, the darling god of the Indian women, are defcribed as youths of perfect beauty. The third Rhama is Criſhna’s elder brother, and is conſidered as the eighth Avatar @@(b), in-veſted with an emanation of his divine radiance. Like all the Avatars, Rhama is painted with gemmed Ethi-opian or Parthian coronets ; with rays encircling his head, jewels in his ears, two necklaces, oae ſtraight and one pendant on his boſom, with dropping gems ; garlands of well-diſpofed many-coloured flowers, or collars of pearls, hanging down below his waiſt ; looſe mantles of golden tiffue or dyed ſſlk, embroidered on the hems with flowérs elegantly thrown over one ſhoulder, and folded like ribbands acloſs the breaſt ; with bracelets, two on one arm and on each wriſt : all the Avatars are naked to the waiſſs, and uniformly with dark azure fleſh, in alluſion probably to the tint of that primordial fluid on which Narayan moved in the beginning of time ; but their ſkirts are bright yellow, the colour of the curious pericarpium in the centre of the water-lily.</p><p>RHAMNUS, the buckthorn, in botany : A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the pentan-dria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 43d order, <hi rend="italic">Dumofœ.</hi>  The calyx is tubulous, with five minute ſcales ſurrounding the ſtamina ; there is no corolla ; the fruit is a berry. There are 27 ſpe-cies ; of which the moſt remarkable are,</p><p>I. The catharticus, or common purging buckthorn, growing naturally in ſome parts of Britain. This glows to the height of. 12 or 14 feet, with many irregular branches at the extremities. The leaves are oval-lan-ceolate, finely ſerrated on the edges, their nerves con-verging together. The flowers grow in cluſters, one on each footſtalk, white, and in this ſpecies divided into four ſegments : the fruit is a round black berry, containing four feeds. The juice of the berries is a</p><p>ſtrong purgative, and is made ufe of for making the common ſyrup of buckthorn kept in the ſhops. The bark is emetic : the juice of the unripe berries with alum dyes yellow, of the ripe ones a ſine green ; the bark alſo dyes yellow. The green colour yielded by the berries, called by the French <hi rend="italic">verde-vefjie,</hi>  is much eſteemed by miniature painters.</p><p>Of this ſpecies there are two varieties, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>  the dwarf buckthorn, a ſhrub of about a yard high, of a greeniſh colour but little ſhow; and the long-leaved dwarf buck-thorn, which is a larger ſhrub, with leaves fomewhat larger, but in other reſpects very ſimilar to tlie dwarf buckthorn.</p><p>2.    The zizyphus is the ſpecies in which the lac in-ſect* forms its cells, and produces the wax callecl <hi rend="italic">gum-lac.</hi>  See Lacca.</p><p>3.    The lotus has the leaves, prickles, flowers, and fruit, of the zizyphus or jubeb ; only with this difference, that the fruit is here round, ſmaller, and more lufeious, and at the ſame time the branches, like thofe of the paliurus, are neither ſo much jointed nor crook-ed. Ί he fruit is in great repute, taſtes ſomething like gingerbread, and is fold in the markets all over the ſouthern diſtricts of theſe kingdoms. The Arabs call it <hi rend="italic">aneb enta el feedra,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">the jubeb of the feedra ;</hi>  which Olavus Celſius had ſo high an opinion of, that he has deſcribed it as the dudaim of the ſcriptures. This ſpe-cies is very common in the Jereede and other parts of Bombay ; and has been ſuppoſed by ſome to be the ſame plant with that celebrated by Homer for its en-chanting property; though the latter is more generally ſuppoſed to have been a ſpecies of Diospyros (which ſee). It is proper, however, to diſtinguiſh between both theſe ſhrubs and an herb often mentioned by the ancients under the name of <hi rend="italic">lotus,</hi>  which Homer men-tions as being fed upon by the horſes of Achilles, and Virgil as proper to increafe the milk of ſheep (ſee Lotus). They are alſo different from the Egyptian lo« tus deſcribed by Herodotus; ſor which ſee Nym-PHÆA.</p><p>4.    The frangula, or berry-bearing alder, is a deciduous ſhrub, a native of England and moſt of the north-era parts of Europe, and affords ſeveral varieties.</p><p>5.    The Alpine, rough-leaved frangula, or berrybearing alder, is alſo a deciduous ſhrub, and native of the Alps. It differs in no reſpect from the common fort, except that it has no thorns, and that it will grow to be rather taller, with tough, large, and doubly laci-niated leaves. The ſmooth-leaved Alpine frangula is a variety of this ſpecies, with ſmooth leaves and of a lower growth.</p><p>6.    The paliurus, or thorn of Chriſt, is a deciduous ſhrub or tree, a native of Paleſtine, Spain, Portugal, and Italy. It will grow to nearly the height of 14,</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b) </hi><hi rend="italic">Avatar</hi>  means the defcent of the deity in his capacity of preſerver. The three ſirſt of theſe defcents re· late to ſome ſtupendous convulſion of our globe from the fountains of the deep, and the fourth exhibits the miraculous puniſhment of pride and impiety, appearing to refer to the deluge. Three of the others were ordaiued for the overthrow of tyrants or giants. Of theſe Avatars we have mentioned in the text, that Rhama is the eighth ; Buddha, who appears to have been a reformer of the doctrines contained in Vedas, is the ninth : the tenth Avatar, we are told, is yet to come, and is expected to appear mounted (like the crowned conqueror in the Apocalypſe) on a white horſe, with a ſcimeter blazing like a comet to mow down all ^corrigible and impe·» ſutent offenders who ſhall then be on the earth.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>