<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ty a prey to infinite multitudes of animals reſerved for paſtime, had always been numbered among the ſevere grievances of the French peaſantry. Theſe were therefore renounced, along with the excluſive rights of rabbit warrens, ſiſheries, and dovecotes. The fale of offices was aboliſhed, and the fees exacted from the poor, together with the privilege of holding a plurality of livings, were relinquiſhed by the clergy. The deputies of the <hi rend="italic">Pais d’Etat,</hi>  or privileged provinces, with the deputies of Dauphiné at their head, next came forward, and offered a ſurrender of their ancient privileges, re-queſting that the kingdom might no longer remain parcelled out among Dauphinois, Bretons, Provençaux, &amp;c. but that they ſhould all form one great mafs of French citizens. They were followed by the reprefentatives of Paris, Marſeilles, Lyons, Bourdeaux, Straſfeourg, &amp;c. who requeſted leave to renounce all their feparate privileges as incorporations, for the fake of placing every man and every village in the nation upon a footing of equality. Thus the Aſſembly proceeded, till every member had exhauſted his imagination upon the ſubject of reform. To cloſe the whole, the Duc de Liancourt propoſed that a ſolemn <hi rend="italic">Te Deιιm</hi>  ſhould be performed, that a medal ſhould be ſtruck in commemoration of the events of that night ; and that the title of Restorer of Gallic Liberty ſhould be beſtowed upon the reigning monarch. A deputation was accordingly ap-pointed to wait upon the king, refpectfully to inform him of theſe decrees.</p><p>Several ſucceeding days were neceſſary to form into laws the decrees of the 4tl1 Auguſt, and commitees were appointed to make out reports for that purpoſe. Οηε of theſe reports having included the tithes and revenues of the clergy among the abuſes that were to be done away, and having propofed in lieu of them to grant a "certain ſtipend to the different miniſters of religion to be payable by the nation, the clergy attempted to make a Hand in defence of their property, and violent debates enſued. In theſe they were ably ſupported by the Abbé Sieyes : but as the clergy had formerly deferted the nobles, ſo they were now in their turn abandoned to their fate by the hereditary ariſtocracy. The popular party had long regarded the wealth of the church as an eaſy reſource for fupplying the wants of the ſtate.— Never was there a more complete proof of the influence of opinion over the affairs of men. The Catholic clergy of France, though poffeffed of more property than they enjoyed at the time when princes took up arms or laid them down at their command, now found ſo few defenders, that they were terrified into a voluntary ſurrender of all that they and their predeceffors had poffeffed for ages. In their overthrow, they ſcarcely enjoyed even the barren honour of having fallen the laſt of thoſe privileged orders that ſo long had ruled over this ancient kingdom. They and the nobles, and the king, ſtill poſſeſled their former titles and nominal dignity ; but all of them were now ſubdued, and at the mercy of the commons of France, who ſpeedily diſ-miſſtd them at their pleaſure.</p><p>As a ſhort ſeaſon of tranquillity in the Court and the National Aſſembly ſucceeded theſe great popular ſacri-fices, the King laid hold of it as a fit opportunity for the appointment of a new miniſtry. They conſiſted of the Archbiſhop of vienne, the Archbiſhop of Bour-deaux, M. Neckar, the Count de St Prieſt, Count de</p><p>Montmorin, the Count de Ia Luzerne, and the Count de la Tour du Pin Paulin. M. Ncckar, as miniſter of finance, having ſtated the diſtreſſed fituation of the revenue, preſented the plan of a loan of thirty millions of livres. But M. Mirabeau, from a ſpirit of rivalſhip, as if would feem, to M. Neckar, prevailed with the Affembly to alter and to narrow the conditions of it in ſuch a degree that very few ſubſcribers were found, and the loan could not be filled up. This failure involved the Aſſembly in a conſiderable degree of unpopularity; in conſcquence of which they allowed M. Neckar to preſcribe his own terms for the purpoſe of obtaining a loan of eighty millions. But the happy inſtant of pub-lic confidence had been allowed to paſs away, and this loan was never more than half filled up. Recourſe was next had to patriotic contributions; and great numbers of gold rings, ſilver buckles, and pieces of plate, were preſented to the Aſſembly. The Royal family themſelves ſent their plate to the mint, either to give counte-nance to theſe donations, or, as M. Neckar has ſince aſſerted, through abſolute neceſſity, for the purpoſe of fupporting themſelves and their family. The confuſion into which the nation had been thrown by the late events had produced a ſuſpenſion of the payment of all taxes. There exiſted, in fact, no efficient government; and if ſociety eſcaped entire diſſolution, it was merely in conſequence of thoſe habits of order which are produced by a ſtate of long continued civilization. The buſineſs of government could not be tranſacted without money, and many vain efforts were made by the mini-ſtry to procure it. At length M. Neckar was driven to the deſperate refource of propoiing a <hi rend="italic">compulfory loan, </hi>or that every individual poffeffed of property ſhould advance to the ſtate a ſum equal to one-fourth of his an-nual income. This bold propoſition was fupported by Mirabeau, and adopted by the Aſſembly ; but it does not appear to have ever been effectually executed.</p><p>In the mean time, the Aſſembly was buſily occupied in framing the celebrated declaration of the <hi rend="italic">Rights oſ Man,</hi>  which was afterwards prefixed to the new conſtitution. This was followed by the diſcuſſion of a point of much delicacy and difficulty ; viz. what ſhare of le-giſlative authority the king ought to poſſeſs under the new conſtitution ; whether an abſolute negative or <hi rend="italic">veto, </hi>a ſuſpenſive <hi rend="italic">veto,</hi>  or no <hi rend="italic">veto</hi>  at all ? This queſtion opera-ted like a touchſtone for trying the ſentiments of eve-ry perſon ; and the aſſembly, confiſting of 1200 men, was now ſeen to arrange itſelf into two violent contending factions. The debates were vehement and tumultuous, and continued for many days. As the aſſembly fat in public, and as multitudes of people of all deſcrip-tions were admitted into the galleries, and even into the body of the hall among the members, many indecent ſcenes took place in conſequence oſ the interference of the ſpectators to applaud or cenſure the ſenti-mtfnts which were delivered. Thus the public at large became ſpeedily intereſted in the diſcuſſion ; the city "of Paris took a ſide in oppofition to the <hi rend="italic">veto,</hi>  and the whole empire was thrown into agitation by new and ſpeculative queſtions. The diſtinguiſhed place which France holds among the nations of Europe rendered theſe ſingular events and diſcuſſions the object of univerſal attention. The contagious love of novelty ſpread rapidly abroad, and gave rife to that well-founded jea-louſy on the part of the monarchs of Europe, which</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>