<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Rut we cannot give an equally favourable account of its influence on the ſei¢nces. There was little in that ſyſtem that could contribute to call forth reaſon. AVe may grant indeed, that if reaſon can be ſo ſhocked with abſurdity as to be rouled to a more vigorous exertion of her powers, and a more determined affertion of her rights in conlequence of furveying it ; in that caſe this ſyſtem of mythology might be favourable to the exer-¢iſe and improvement of reaſon ; not otherwiſe.</p><p>The connection of paganiſm with morality was too imperfect for it to produce any very important effects on the morals of its votaries. Sacrifices and prayers, and temples and feſtivals, not purity of heart and integrity of life, were the means preſcribed for propitia-ting tlie favour of the deities adored by the Pagans. There were other means, too, befides true heroiſm and patriotiſm, of gaining admiſljon into the Elyfian fields, or obtaining a feat in tbe council of the gods. Xenophon, in one of the moſt beautiful parts of his Memoirs of Socrates, repreſeuts Hercules wooed by virtue and Pleaſure in two fair female forms, and deliberating with much anxiety which of the two he ſhould prefer. But this is the fiction of a philoſopher délirons to improve the fables of antiquity in ſuch a way as to render them truly uſeful. Hercules does not appear, from tho tales which are told us of his adventures, to have been at any ſuch pains in choofing his way of life. He was received into the palace of Jove, without having occaſion to plead that he had through life been the faithful follower of that σoddefs to whom the philoſopher makes him give the preference ; his being the ſon of Jove, and his wild adventures, were ſuſſicient without any other merits to gain him that honour. The ſame may be ſaid concerning many of the other demi-gods and heroes who were advanced to heaven, or conveyed to the bleſs-.ful fields of Elyſium. And whatever might be the good effects of the religion of Greece and Rome in <hi rend="italic">general</hi>  upon the civil and political eſtabliſhments, and in ſome few inſtances on the manners of the people, yet ſtill it muſt be acknowledged to have been but ill calculated to impreſs the heart with ſuch principles as might in all circumftanceε direct to a firm, uniform, tenor of virtuous conduct.</p><p>But after what has been ſaid on the character of this religion elſewhere (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Polytheism),</hi>  and in the ſecond part of this article, we cannot without repetition enlarge farther on it here, of the Jewiſh religion, however, we have as yet ſaid little, having on purpoſe reſerved to this place whatever we mean to in-troduce under the article, concerning its influence on ſociety.</p><p>3d, when we take a general view of the circumſtances in which the Jewilh religion was eſtabliſhed, the effects which it produced on the character and fortune of the nation, the rites and ceremonies which it enjoined, and the ſingular political inſtitutions to which it gave a fonction, it may perhaps appear hard to deter-mine, whether it were upon the whole more or leſs beneficial to ſociety than the pυlytheifm of the Egyp. tians, Greeks, and Romans. But if ſuch be the judgement which preconceived prejudices, or an haſty and careleſs view, have induced fome to form of this celebrated ſyſtem ; there are others who, with equal keenneſs, and founder reaſoning, maintain, that it was happily calculated, not only to accompliſh the great deſign of</p><p>preparing the w⅞y for the promulgation ⅛f the Gyfpel, but likewiſe to render tbe Jews a more refined and virtuous people, and a better regulated community, than a∏y neighbouring nation. ' In the ſirſt place, the attributes of the Deity were very clearly exhibited to the Jews in the eſtabliſhment of their religion. The miracles by which he delivered them from ſcrvſtude, and conducted them out of Egypt, were ſtriking demonſtrations of his power ; that condeſcenſion with which he forgave their repeated acta of perverſeneſs and rebel-lion, was a moſt convincing proof of his benevolence ; and the impartiality with which the obſervance and thc violation of his laws were rewarded and puniſhed, even in the preſent life, might well convince them of his juſtice. A part of the laws which he dictated to Moſes are of eternal and univerfol obligation ; others of them were local and particular, ſuited to the character ot the Jews, and their circumſtances in the land of Canaan. The Jewiſh code, taken altogether, is not to be conſidered as a complete ſyſtem of religion, or laws calculated for all countries and all ages of fociety. When we conſider the expediency of this ſyſtem, we muſt take care not to overlook the deſign for which the Jews are foid to have been ſeparated from other nations, the circumſtances in which they had lived in Egypt, the cu∙ ſtoms and manners which they had contracted by their intercourfe with the natives of that country, the manner in which they were to acquire to themfelves feulements by extirpating the nations of Canaan, the rank which they were to hold among the nations of Syria and the adjacent countries, together with the difficulty of reſtraining a people ſo little civilized and enlightened from the idolatrous worſhip which prevailed among their neighbours : All thcſe circumſtances were certainly to be taken into account j and had the legiſlator of the Jews not attended to them, his inſtitutions muſt have remained in force only for a ſhort period ; nor could they have produced auy laſtſhg effects on the character of the nation, with a due attention to theſe circumſtances, let us deſcend to an examination oſ particulars.</p><p>Although in every religion or ſuperſtition that has prevailed through the world, we ſind one part of its in-ſtitutions to conſiſt in the enjoining of certain feſtivals to be celebrated by relaxation from labour, and the per· ſormance of certain ceremonies in honour of the gods ; yet in none, or almoſt none beſides the Jewiſh, do we ſind every ſeventh day ordained to be regularly kept holy. One great end which the legiſlator of the Jews had in view in the inſtitution of the Sabbath was, to impreſs them with a belief that God was the maker of the univerſe. In the early ages of the world a great part of mankind imagined the ſtars, the ſun, the moon, and the other planets, to be eternal, and consequently objects highly worthy of adoration. To convince the Iſraelites of the abſurdity of this belief, and prevent them from adopting that idolatry, Moſes taught them, that thoſe confpicuδus objects which the Gentile nations regarded as eternal, and endowed with divine power and intelligence, were created by the hand of Gβd } who, after bringing all things out of nothing, and giving them form, order, and harmony, in the ſpace of fix days, reſted on the ſeventh ſrom all his works. Van-ous paſſages in the OΓd Teſtament concur to ſhow, that this was one great end of the uiſtitution of the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>