<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by his Maker ; and though this doctrine, in large and permanent ſocieties, might certainly be conveyed more or leſs pure to late poſterity through the channel of tra-dition—we are far from attributing ſo much to tradition as fome writers are difpoſed to do, or thinking it the only fource from which mankind could derive the belief of their exiſtence beyond the grave. In fmall tribes of ſavages ſuch a tradition could hardly be preſerved ; and yet ſome indiſtinct notions of a future ſtate have been found among tribes who are ſaid to have loſt all tradi-tionary notions even of the being of a God.</p><p>others, therefore, are inclined to believe that, in-dependent of any traditions, mankind might be led by certain phenomena to form ſome conjectures of a future <hi rend="sub">1</hi>ftate. They obſerve, that although a few individuals perhaps may, yet it ſeldom happens that the whole individuals of any nation are exempted from dreaming : They obſerve, too, and this obſervation is founded on experience, that the images of the dead are from the remaining impreſſions of memory frequently ſummoned up in the fancy ; and that it appears from all the lan-guages of rude nations, who pay the greateſt attention to their dreams, and who ſpeak of feeing the dead in their viſions, that theſe images ( A ) have always been taken by them for realities ; nay, ſome of the learned, and the celebrated Baxter is of the number, are diſpo-ſed to doubt whether theſe appearances be not ſome-thing more than illuſions of the brain : But whether they really be ſo or not, one thing is certain, that all nations in all countries, in the darkeſt ages and the ru-deſt periods, are accuſtomed to dream ; and whether ſleeping or waking, in the ſtillneſs of the night, in the gloom of ſolitude, in the fondneſs of friendſhip, in the rovings of love, the delirium of fever, and the anguiſh of remorfe,<hi rend="sub">l</hi>to ſee and converſe with the ſhades of the departed; and Lucretius * has remarked,, that even the inferior animals are not exempted from ſuch illuſions of a reſtleſs fancy.</p><p>Fβr often ſleeping racers pant and fweat,</p><p>Breathe ſhort, as if they ran their ſecond heat ;</p><p>As if the barrier down with eager pace</p><p>They ſtretch’d, as when contending for the race.</p><p>And often hounds, when ſleep hath clos’d their eyes&gt;</p><p>They toſs, and tumble, and attempt to riſe ;</p><p>They open often, often ſnuff the air,</p><p>As if they preſt the footſteps of the deer ;</p><p>And ſometimes wak’d, purſue their fancy’d prey,</p><p>The fancy’d deer, that ſcem to run away,</p><p>Till quite awak’d, the follow’d ſhapes decay,</p><p>And ſofter curs, that lie and ſleep at home,</p><p>Do often rouſe, and walk about the room,</p><p>And'bark, as if they ſaw ſome ſtrangers come?</p><p>And birds will ſtart, and ſeek the woods, by night,} whene’er the fancy’d hawk appears in fight,    Ç</p><p>Whene’er they ſee his wing or hear him fight.    j</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Çkbech.</hi></p><p>Theſe powers of fancy extend wide over animal crea</p><p>tion ; and it is on this general principle that necr&lt;s-mancers and dreamers have in all ages eſtabliſhed their trade, that the ſtories of goblins have at all times ſo very eaſily procured belief, and that</p><p>The village matron, round the blazing hearth, Suſpends the infant audience with her tales, Breathing aſtoniſhment ! Qf witching rhymes And evil ſpirits ; of the deathbed call of him who robb’d the widow and devour’d The orphan’s portion ; of unquiet fouls Ris’n from the grave to eaſe the heavy guilt of deeds in life' conceal’d ; of ſhapes that walk At dead of night, and clank their chains, and wave The torch of hell around the murderer’s head.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Aikenside.</hi></p><p>Mankind in general would willingly dſſpenſe with theſe troubleſome viſits of the dead. To prevent the return of the <hi rend="italic">zumbi</hi>  or the ghoſt, fome nations of Afri-ca ufe many ſuperſtitious rites*; and Kolben tells us<hi rend="sub">r </hi>that the frighted Hottentots leave in the hut where a perſon has died all the utenſils and furniture, leſt the angry ghoſt, incenſed at their avarice, ſhould haunt them in their dreams, and infeſt. them in the night. Divines and moraliſts have laboured to ſhow that theſe are merely imaginary terrors: but God and nature ſeem to have determined that they ſhall produce the ſame effects upon certain minds as if they were real y and that while there is any ſenſibility in the heart, while there is any remembrance of the paſt, and any conju-ring power in the fancy ; the ignorant, the benighted, the timid, ſhall often meet with the goblins of darkneſs, the ſpectres of the tomb, the apparitions that hover round the grave, and the forms of the dead in the midnight dream. See Spectre.</p><p>From theſe phenomena, which have been fo common in all countries and in all ages, what- would mankind naturally infer ? would they not infer, that there is ſomething in the nature of man that ſurvives death, and that there is a future ſtate of exiſtence beyond ſthc grave ? Are not ſtill many ſpecimens of this reafoning preferved in the ancient poets ? and is it not thus that Achillesf reafons after imagining that he faw the ghoſt of his friend Patroclus ?</p><p><hi rend="sup">,</hi>Tis true, ’tis certain, man, though dead, retains</p><p>Part of himſelf ; the immortal mind remains :</p><p>The form ſubſiſts without the body’s aid,</p><p>Aerial ſemblance, and an empty ſhade.</p><p>This night my friend, ſo late in battle Ioſt,</p><p>Stood at my ſide- a penfive plaintive ghoſt j</p><p>Ev’n now familiar as in life he came,</p><p>Alas! how diff’rent, yet how like the ſame. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pope,</hi></p><p>Lucretius*, a ſtudious obſerver of nature, though no friend to the ſoul’s immortality, acknowledges frankly that theſe phantoms often terrify the mind, haunt us in our ſleep, and meet us while awake. He confeffes, too, that by ſuch appearances mankind have been led</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi>  Theſe images were called by the Greeks E∙J<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ωλ*<hi rend="italic">Garni»,</hi>  ; and among the Romans they had various names, as <hi rend="italic">umbra, lemures, manes, larvœ,</hi>  and were ſometimes called <hi rend="italic">occurſacula noctium, buβorum fornddamina<hi rend="sub">3</hi>  fepukhrt}-&gt; </hi><hi rend="italic">rum temculamenta<hi rend="sub">9</hi>  animœ errantes,</hi>  which are all comprehended under the <hi rend="italic">ſpecies τnortuorum,</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>