<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><table><row><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rank</hi>  between the Army, Navy, and Governors.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Army.</hi></p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Navy.</hi></p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Governors.</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>General in chief</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Admiral in chief</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Commander in chief of the forces in America</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Generals of horſe</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Admiral with a flag at the main-top-maſt</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Captain-general of provinces</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lieutenant-generals</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>vice-admirals</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lieutenant-generals of provinces</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Major-generals</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Rear-admirals</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lieutenant-governors and preſidents</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Colonels</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Poſt-captains of 3 years</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lieutenant-governors not commanding</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lieutenant-colonels</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Poſt-captains</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Governors of charter colonies</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Majors</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Captains</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Deputy-governors</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Captains</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Lieutenants</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Eſtabliſhed by the king, 1760</p></cell></row></table><lb/><p><hi rend="italic">Doubting oſ the RANKS,</hi>  is the placing two ranks in one, frequently uſed in the manœuvres of a regiment.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ranks and Files,</hi></hi>  are the horizontal and vertical lines of ſoldiers when drawn up for ſervice.</p><p>RANSOM, a ſum of money paid for the redemption of a ſlave, or the liberty of a priſoner of war. In our law-books, ranſom is alſo uſed for a fum paid for the pardon of ſome great offence, and to obtain the offender’s liberty.</p><p>RANULA, a tumor under a child’s tongue, which, like a ligature, hinders it from ſpeaking or fucking.</p><p>RANUNCULUS, crowfoot : A genus of the polygamia order, belonging to the polyandria clafs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 26th order, <hi rend="italic">Mult'ιfitiquα.</hi>  The calyx is pentaphyllous ; there are five petals, each with a melliferous pore on the inſide of the heel ; the feeds naked.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Species.</hi>  There arc near 40 different ſpecies of this genus, ſix or eight of which claim general eſteem as flowery plants for ornamenting the gardens, and a great number are common weeds in the fields, waters, and paſture ground, not having merit for garden culture. Οί the garden kinds, the principal fort is the Aſiatic or Turkey and Perſian ranunculus, which com-prifes many hundred varieties of large, double, moſt beautiful flowers of various colours : but feveral other ſpecies having varieties with fine double flowers, make a good appearance in a collection, though as thoſe of each ſpecies conſiſt only of one colour, ſome white, others yellow, they are inferior to the Aſiatic ranun-culus, which is large, and diverſified a thouſand ways in rich colours, in different varieties. However, all the garden kinds in general effect a very agreeable diverſity in affemblage in the flower compartments, &amp;c. and they being all very hardy, ſucceed in any open beds and bor-ders, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Culture.</hi>  The Aſiatic ſpecies in all its varieties will ſucceed in any light, rich, garden earth ; but the flo-riſts often prepare a particular compoſt for the fine varieties, conſiſting of good garden-mould or paſture-earth, fward and all, a fourth part of rotted cow-dung,</p><p>' and the like portion of ſea-ſand ; and with this they</p><p>prepare beds four feet wide and two deep : however, in default of fuch compoſt, ufe beds of any good light earth of your garden ; or, if neceffary, it may be made light and ιich with a portion of drift-ſand and rotten dung, cow-dung is moſt commonly recommended ; but they will alſo thrive in beds of well-wrought kitchen-garden earth, and they often profper well in the com-mon flower-borders.</p><p>The ſeafon for planting the roots is both in autumn and ſpring ; the autumn plantings generally flower ſtrongeſt and ſooneſt by a month at leaſt, and are ſucceeded by the ſpring-planting in May and June. Per-form the autumnal planting in october and early part of November, but fome plant towards the Iatter end of September in order to have a very early bloom ; but thoſe planted in that month and beginning of Gctober often come up with rank leaves ſoon after, in winter, ſo as to require protection in hard froſts ; thoſe, hς&gt;wever, planted about the middle or latter end of october, and beginning of November, rarely ſhoot up ſtrong till towards ſpring, and will not require ſo much care of cover-ing during winter ; and the ſpring-planting may be per-formed the end of January or beginning of February, or as ſoon as the weather is ſettled ; they will not require any trouble of covering, and will ſucceed the autumnal plants regularly in bloom, and will flower in good perfection. Thus by two or three different plant-ings you may obtain a fucceſſion of thefe beautiful flowers in conſtant bloom from April till the middle of June ; but the autumnal plants, for the general part, not only flower ſtrongeſt, but the roots increaſe more in ſize, and furniſh the beſt off-fets for propagation : it is, however, proper to plant both in ſpring and au-tumn.</p><p>Prepare for the choicer ſorts four-feet beds of light earth, and rake the ſurface ſmooth; then plant the roots in rows lengthwiſe the beds, either by drilling them in two inches deep, and ſix inches diſtance in the row, and the rows ſix or eight afunder ; or you may ph nt them by bedding-in, or by dibble planting, the ſame depth and diſtance.</p><p>Thoſe deſigned for the borders fiιould be planted ge-</p></body></text></TEI>