<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſtood to have been intended for the purpoſe oſ concluding a league for the invaſion of France, the new-modelling of its government, and the partition of fome of its fair-eſt provinces. The following paper has been repeated-ly publiſhed as the copy of a treaty concluded and ſigned at Pavia, and is generally underſtood to have been identical with, and therefore known by, the name of the <hi rend="italic">Treaty of Pilnitz.</hi>  we are far from vouching for its authenticity. It may have been fabricated by the French aſſembly, to unite all parties in the nation againſt the foreign powers which threatened to invade them. But in ſtating the events of this revolution, it is perhaps ſtill more neceſſary, for the purpoſe of rendering the actions of men comprehenſible, to give an account of what was at the time <hi rend="italic">believed</hi>  to have occurred, than it now is to aſcertain what was actually true.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Partition Treaty between the Courts in Concert, concluded and figned at Pavia, in the Month oſ July</hi>  1791.</p><p>His majeſty the emperor will take all that LouisXIV. conquered in the Auſtrian Netherlands, will give them to his ſerene highneſs the elector Palatine ; ſo that theſe new poſſeffions, added to the Palatinate, may here-after have the name of <hi rend="italic">Aufirafia.</hi></p><p>His majeſty will preſerve for ever the property and poſſeffion of Bavaria, to make in future an indiviſible maſs with the domains and hereditary poffeffions of the houſe of Auſſria.</p><p>Her ſerenc highneſs the archducheſs Maria Chriſtina ſhall be, conjointly with his ferene highneſs her ne-phew the archduke Charles, put into hereditary poſſeſ-ſion of the duchy of Lorraine.</p><p>Alſace ſhall be reftored to the empire ; and the biſhop of Straſhourg, as well as the chapter, ſhall recover their ancient privileges, and the eccleſiaſtical ſovereigns of Germany ſhall do the ſame.</p><p>If the Swiſs Cantons conſcnt to accede to the coalition, it may be propoſed to them to annex to the Hel-vetic league the biſhopric of Porentrui, the defiles of Franche Comté, and even thoſe of Tyrol, with the neighbouring bailiwicks, as well as the territory of Ver-ſoy, which interſccts the Pays de Vaud.</p><p>Should his majeſty the king of Sardinia fubſcribe to the coalition, La Breſſe, Le Bugey, and the Pays de Gex, uſurped by France from Savoy, ſhall be reſtored to him.</p><p>In caſe his Sardinian majeſty can make a grand di-verſion, he ſhall be ſuſſered to take Dauphiné, to belong to him for ever as the neareſt deſcendant of the ancient dauphins.</p><p>His majeſty the king of Spain ſhall have Rouffillon and Bearn, with the iſſand of Corſſca; and he ſhall have the French part of the iſſand of St Domingo.</p><p>Her majeſty the empreſs of all the Ruffias ſhall take upon herſclf the invaſſon of Poland, and at the ſame time retain Kaminiech, with that part of Padolia which borders on Moldavia.</p><p>His majeſty the emperor ſhall oblige the Port£ to give up Chocſim, as well as the ſmall forts of Servia, and tliofe on the river Lurna.</p><p>His majeſty tlie king of Pruffia, by means of the above-mentioned invaſion of the empreſs oſ all the Ruſc fias into Poland, ſhall make an acquiſition oſ Thorn and Dantzic, and there unite the Palatinate on the eaſt to the confines oſ Sileſia.</p><p>His majeſty the king of Pruffia ſhall beſides acquire Luſace ; and hie ſcrene highneſs the elector oſ Saxony ſhall in exchange receive the reſt oſ Poland, and oc-cupy the throne as hereditary ſovereign.</p><p>. His majeſty the preſent king of’Poland ſhall abdicate the throne on receiving a ſuitable annuity.</p><p>His royal highneſs the elector oſ Saxony ſhall give his daughter in marriage to his ſerene highneſs the youngeſt ſon of his royal highneſs the grand duke of all the Ruffias, who will be the father of the race of the hereditary kings of Poland and Lithuania. (Signed) Leopold. Prince Nassau. CountFloriba Blan-ca. Bischoffswerder.</p><p>In the mean time, the national aſſembly was haſſen-ing faſt to the completion of the new conſtitution. It was ſiniſhed on the 3d of September, and prefented to the king. It begins with the following declaration of the rights of a man and a citizen, and thereafter foliow the different branches; the chief of which are here translated.</p><p>I.    All men are born, and remain, free and equal in rights : ſocial diſtinctions cannot be founded but on common utility.</p><p>II.    The end of all political aſſociations is the pre-ſervation of the natural and impreſcriptihle rights of man : theſc rights are liberty, property, ſecurity, and reſiſtance againſt oppreſſion.</p><p>III.    The principle of <hi rend="italic">ſovereignty</hi>  reſides eſſentially in the nation : <hi rend="italic">no body of men,</hi>  no <hi rend="italic">individual,</hi>  can exer* ciſe an authority that does not emanate expreſsly from that fource.</p><p>IV.    <hi rend="italic">Liberty</hi>  conſiſts in the power of doing every thing except that which is hurtful to another : hence the exercife of the natural rights of every man has no other bounds than thoſc that are neceſſary to enſure to the other members of ſociety the enjoyment of the ſame rights : thoſe bounds can be determined by the law only.</p><p>V.    The law has a right to forbid thoſc actions alone that are hurtful to ſociety. whatever is not forbid-den by the law, cannot be hindered ; and no perſon can be conſtrained to do that which the law ordaineth not.</p><p>VI.    The law is the expreffion of the general will : all the citizens have a right to concur perſonally, or by their repreſentatives, to the formation oſ the law : it ought to be the ſame for all, whether it protect, or whether it puniſh. All citizens being equal in the eye of the law, are equally admiffible to dignities, places, and public offices, according to their capacity, and without any other diſtinction but that of their virtue and their talents.</p><p>VII.    No man can be accuſcd, arreſted, or detained, except in cafes determined by the law, and according to the forms which the law hath preſcribed. Thoſc who folicit, diſpatch, execute, or cauſe to be executed, arbitrary orders, ought to be pnniſhed ; but every citi-zen that is ſummoned or ſeized in virtue of the law, ought to obey inſtantly—he becomes culpable by reſiſtance.</p><p>VIII.    The law ought to eſtabliſh ſuch puniſhments only as are ſtrictly and evidently neceſſary ; and no perſon can be puniſhed but in virtue of a law eſta-bliſhed and promulgated prior to the offence, and le-gally applied.</p><p>IN. Evcry man being preſumed innocent till ſuch</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>