<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>REFUGEES, a term at firſt applied to the French Proteſtants, who, by the revocation of the edict of Nantz, were conſtrained to fly from perſeeution, and take refuge in foreign countries. Since that time, however, it has been extended to all ſuch as leave their country in times of diſtreſs ; and hence, ſince the revolt of the Britiſii colonies in America, we have frequently heard of <hi rend="italic">American refugees.</hi></p><p>REGALE, a magnificent entertainment or treat, given to ambaiſadors and other perſons of diſtinction, to entertain or do them honour.</p><p>It is uſual in Italy, at the arriv∙al of a traveller of eminence, to ſend him a regale, that is, a prefent of ſweetmeats, fruits, ,&amp;c. by way of refreſhment.</p><p>REGALIA, in law, the lights and prerogatives of a king. See Prerogative.</p><p>Regalia is aſſo uſed for the apparatus of a coronation ; as the crown, the ſceptre with the crofs, that with the dove, St Edward’s ſtaff, the globe, and the erb with the croſs, four ſeveral ſwords, &amp;c.—The re-galia of Scotland were depofited in the caſtle of Edinburgh in the year 1707, in what is called the <hi rend="italic">Jewel GJfi.ee.</hi>  This room was lately opened by ſome commſſ-fioners appointed by the king, when the large cheſt in which it is ſhppoſed they were placed was found ; but as it has not, that we have heard of, been opened, it is impoſſible to ſay whether they be there or not. It is very generally thought they were carried to the Tower of London in the reign of Queen Anne ; and a crown is there ſhewn which is called the Scotch crown. AVe do not believe, however, that that is the real crown of Scotland; and think it probable that the Scotch regalia are in the cheſt which was lately found. If they are not there, they muſt have been taken away by ſtealth, and either deſtroyed or melted down, for we do not believe that they are in the Tower of London.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Lord </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi>  REGALITY, in Scots law. See Law, b<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">0</hi></hi>  clviii. 4.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Court </hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi>  REGARD. See <hi rend="italic">FoRεsτ∙Courts.</hi></p><p>REGARDANT, ill heraldry, fignifies looking behind ; and it is uſed for a lion, or other beaſt, with his face turned towards his tail.</p><p>REGARDER, an ancient officer of the king’s fo-reſt, fworn to make the regard of the foreſt every year ; that is, to take a view of its limits, to inquire into all offences and defaults committed by the foreſters within the foreft, and to obſerve whether all the officers executed their reſpective duties. See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Foresî-Laιυs.</hi></hi></p><p>REGATA, or Regatta, a ſpecies of amuſement peculiar to the republic of venice. This fpectacle has the power of exciting the greateſt emotions of the heart, admiration, enthufiaſm, a ſenſe of glory, and the whole train of our beſt feelings. The grand regata is only exhibited on particular occaſions, as the vifits of foreign princes and kings at venice.</p><p>It is difficult to givc a juſt idea of the ardour that the notice of a <hi rend="italic">regata</hi>  ſpreads among all claffes of the inhabitants of venice. Proud of the exclufive privilege of giving inch a fpectacle, through the wonderful local cir-cumſtances of their city, they are highly delighted with making preparations a long tinie before, in order to contribute all they can towards the perfection and enjoyment of the fpectacle. A thouſand intereſts are formed and augmented every day ; parties in favour of the different competitors who are known j the protection of young</p><p>noblemen given to the gondoliers in their ſervice ; the deiire ot honours and rewards in the aſpirants ; aud, in thc midft of all this, that ingenious national induſtry, which awakes the Venetians from their habitual indolence, to derive advantage from the bufineſs and agita-tioπ of the moment : all theſe circumſtances united give to the numerous inhabitants of this lively city a degree of ſpirit and animation which render it during that time a delightful abode in the eyes of the philoſopher and the ſtranger. Crowds of people flock from the adjacent parts, and travellers joyfully repair to thi3 ſcene of gaiety and pleaſure.</p><p>Although it is allowable for any man to go and in-ſcribe his name in the liſt of combatants until the fixed number is complete, it will not be amiſs to remark one thing, which has relation to more ancient times. The ſtate of a gondolier * is of much confideration among the people ; whieh is very natural, that having been the primitive condition of the inhabitants of this country. But, befides this general confideration, there are among them ſome families truly diſtinguiſhed and reſpected by their equals, whoſe antiquity is acknowledged, and who, on account of a. ſucceſiion of virtuous men, able in their profeſſion, and honoured for the prizes they have carried oft in theſe conteſts, form the body of noble gondoliers ; often more worthy of that title than the higher order of nobility, who only derive their honours from the merit of their anceſtors, or from their own riches. The confideration for thoſe families is carried ſo far, that, in the diſputes frequently arifing among· the gondoliers in their ordinary paffage of the canals, we ſometimes ſee a quarrel inffantly made up, by the fimple interpofition of a third perſon, who has chanced to be of this reverend body. They are rigid with reſpect to mif∙ alliances in their families, and they endeavour reciprocally to give and take their wives among thoſe of their own rank. But we muſt remark here, with pleaſure, that thefe diſtinctions infer no inequality of condition, nor admit any oppreſſion of inferiors, being founded ſolely on laudable and virtuous opinions. Diſtinctions derived ſrom fortune only, are thoſe which always out-rage nature, and often virtue.</p><p>In general, the competitors at the great regatas are choſen from among thele families ol reputation. As ſoon as they are fixed upon for this exploit, they ſpend the intermediate time in preparing themſelves for it, by a daily aſſiduous and fatiguing exerciſe» If they are in ſervice, their maſters during that time not only give them their liberty, but aſſo augment their wages. This cuſtom would ſeem to indicate, that they look upon them as perſons coniecrated to the honour of the nation, and under a fort of obligation to contribute to its glory.</p><p>At laſt the great day arrives. Their relations affem-ble together : they encourage the heroes, by calling to their minds the records of their families ; the women preſent the oar, beſeeching them, in an epic tone, to remember that they are the ſons of famous men, whoſe ſteps they will be expected to follow : this they do with as much ſolemnity as the Spartan women preſented the ſhield to their ſons, bidding them either return with or upon it. Religion, as practiſed among the lower claſs of people,<hi rend="sub">j</hi> has its flιare in the preparations for this en» terprize. They cauſe maffes to be ſaid ; they make vows to ſome particular church ; and they arm their boats for the contell with, the images of thoſe faint» who are moſt in vogue. Sorcerers are not forgotten</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>