<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>verſariee, by way of contempt. Their fate was very ſevere, being perſecuted with unparalleled fury ; and though many princes of the blood, and of the firſt nobility, had embraced their ſentiments, yet in no part of the world did the reformers ſuffer ſo muchf. At laſt all commotions were quelled by the fortitude and mag-<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  nanimity of Henry IV. who in the year 1598 granted all his ſubjects full liberty of conſcience by the famous Edict of Nantes, and ſeemed to have thoroughly eſtabliſhed the reformation throughout his dominions. Du-ring the minority of Louis XIV. however, this edict was revoked by Cardinal Mazarine, -ſince which time the Proteſtants have often been cruelly perſecuted ; nor was the profeſſion of the reformed religion in France at any time fo ſafe as in moſt other countries of Europe. See Revolution.</p><p>In the other parts of Europe the oppoſition to the church of Rome was but faint and ambiguous before the diet of Augſhurg. Before that period, however, it appears from undoubted teſtimony, that the doctrine of Luther had made a conſiderable, though probably ſecret, progreſs through Spain, Hungary, Bohemia, Britain, Poland, and the Netherlands ; and had in all theſe countries many friends, of whom ſeveral repaired to wittemberg, in order to enlarge their knowledge by means of Luther’s converfation. Some of theſe countries threw off the Romiſh yoke entirely, and in others a prodigious number of families embraced the principles of the reformed religion. 'It is certain in-deed, and the Roman-catholics themſelves acknowledge it without heſitation, that the Papal doctrines and authority would have fallen into ruin in all parts of the world at once, had not the force of the ſecular arm been employed to ſupport the tottering edifice. In the Netherlands particularly, the moſt grievous perſecutions took place, fo that by the emperor Charles V. upwards of 100,000 were deſtroyed, while ſtill greater cruelties were exerciſed upon the people by his ſon Philip II. The revolt of the United Provinces, however, and motives of real policy, at laſt put a ſtop to theſe furiou3 proceedings ; and, though in many provinces of the Netherlands, the eſtabliſhment of the Popiſh religion was ſtill continued, the Proteſtants have been long free of the dangeι of perſecution on account of their principles.</p><p>The reformation made a conſiderable progreſs in Spain and Italy foon after the rupture between Luther and the Roman pontiff. In ail the provinces of Italy, but more eſpecially in the territories of venice, Tuſcany, and Naples, the ſuperſtition of Rome loſt ground, and great numbers of people of all ranks expreſſed an averſion to the Papal yoke. This occafioned violent and dangerous commotions in the kingdom cf Naples in the year 1546 ; which, however, were at laſt quelled by the united efforts of Charles V. and his viceroy Don Pedro di Toledo. In ſeveral places the pope put a ſtop to the progreſs of the reformation, by letting lo»fe the inquiſitors ; who ſpread dreadful marks ©f their barbarity through the greattſt part of Italy. Theſe formidable miniſters of ſuperſtition put ſo many to death, and perpetrated ſuch horrid acts of cruelty and .oppreſſion, that moſt of the reformed conſulted their ſafety by a voluntary exile, while others returned to the religion of Rome, at leaſt in external appearance. 'But the inquiſition, which frighted into the profeſſion of Popery ſeveral Proteſtants in other parts of Italy,</p><p>could never make its way into thc kingdom of Naples; nor could either the authority or intreaties of the pope engage the NeapoIitans to admit even vifiting in-quiſitors.</p><p>In Spain, ſeveral people embraced the Proteſtant. religion, not only from the controverses of Luther, but even from thoſe divines whom Charles V. had brought with him into Germany in order to refute the doctrines of Luther. For theſe doctors imbibed the pre-tended hereſy inſtead of refuting it, and propagated it more or leſs on their return home. But the inquiſition, which could obtain no footing in Naples, reigned triumphant in Spain, and by the moſt dreadful methods frightened the people back into Popery, and ſuppreſſcd the deſire of exchanging their ſuperſtition for a more rational plan of ιeligion. It was indeed preſumed that Charles himfelf died a Proteſtant ; and it ſeems to be certain, that, when the approach of dcath had diſſipated thofe ſchemes of ambition and grandeur which had fo long blinded him, his ſentimeuts became much more rational and agreeable to Chriſtianity than they had ever been. All the eccleſiaſtics who had attended him, as ſoon as he expired, were ſent to the inquiſition, and committed to the flames, or put to death by ſome other method equally terrible. Such was the fate of Auguſtine Caſal, the emperor’s preacher ; of Conſtantine Pontius, his confeſſor ; of Egidius, whom he had named to the biſhopric of Tortoſa; of Bartholomew de Caranza, a Dominican, who had been confeſſor to King Philip and Queen Mary ; with 20 others, of leſs note.</p><p>In England, the principles of the reformation began to be adopted as ſoon as an account of Luther’s doctrines could be conveyed thither. In that kingdom there werc ſtill great remains of the ſect called Lo∕-<hi rend="italic">lards<hi rend="sub">t</hi></hi>  whoſe doctrine reſembled that of Luther ; and among whom, of conſequence, the ſentiments of our reformer gained great credit. Henry VIII. king of England at that time was a violent partiſan of the church of Rome, and had a particular veneration for the writings of Thomas Aψιinas. Being informed that Luther ſpoke of his favourite author with con-tempt, he conceived a violent prejudice "againſt the reformer, and even wrote againſt him, as we have already obſerved. Luther did not heſitate at writing againſt his majeſty, overcame him in argument, and treated him with very little ceremony. The firſt ſtep towards public reformation, however, was not taken till the year *529. Great complaints had been made in Eng-land, and of a very ancient date, of the uſurpations of the clergy ; and by the prevalence of the Lutheran opinions, thefe complaints were now become more general than before. The Houfe of Commons, finding the occaſion favourable, paſſed ſeveral bills, reſtraining the impoſitions of the clergy : but what threatened the eccleſiaſtical order with the greateſt danger were the ſevere rt proaches thrown out almoſt without oppoſition in the houſe againſt the diffolute lives, ambition, and avarice of the prieſts, and their continual encroach-ments on the privileges of the laity. The bills for regulating the clergy met with oppoſition in the Houſe of Lords ; and biſhop Fiſher imputed them to want of faith in the Commons, and to a formed deſign, pro-ceeding from heretical and Lutheran principles, of robbing the church of her patrimony, and overturning the national religion. The Commons., however, complain-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>