<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>alI its tones. But from what was faid above, of the difference between reading and ſpeaking, it follows, that theſe ſigns of the emotions ihould be leſs ftrongly characteriſed in the former article than in the latter. Again, as ſeveral of tlieſe tones of expreſſion are in themſelves agreeable to the mind, and raiſe in us agree-able emotions (as thoſe of <hi rend="italic">pity, benevolence,</hi>  or whatever indicates <hi rend="italic">happineſs,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">goodnefs</hi>  of heart), and others diſagreeable (as thoſe of a <hi rend="italic">boiflerous, malevolent,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">depraved</hi>  nature, &amp;c.) it farther appears, ſince reading is an art <hi rend="italic">improving</hi>  and not <hi rend="italic">imitating</hi>  nature, that, in what-ever degree we abate the expreſſions of the tones above alluded to in the ſirſt caſe, it would be eligible to make a greater abatement in the latter. But as to the quantities and proportional magnitudes of theſe abate-ments, they, like many other particulars of the ſame nature, muſt be left ſolely to the taſte and judgment of the reader.</p><p>To add one more remark, which may be of ſervice on more accounts than in ſuggeſting another reaſon for the doctrine above. Let it be remembered, that tho’ in order to acquit himſelf agreeably in this article of expreſſion, it will be neceffary every reader ihould <hi rend="italic">feel </hi>his ſubject as well as <hi rend="italic">underjland</hi>  it ; yet, that he may preſerve a proper eaſe and mafterlineſs of delivery, it is alſo neceffary he ſſiould guard againft diſcovering too much emotion and perturbation.</p><p>From this reaſoning we deduce the following rule, for the tones which indicate the paſſions and emotions*</p><p>" In reading, let all your tones of expreſſion be bor-rowed from thoſe of common ſpeech, but ſomething more faintly characteriſed. Let thoſe tones which ſignify any diſagreeable paſſion of the mind, be ſtill more faint than thoſe which indicate their contrary ; and pre-ſerve yourſelf ſo far from being affected with the fub-ject, as to be able to proceed through it with that peculiar kind of eaſe and maſterlinefs, which has its charms in this as well as every other art.”</p><p>we ſſiall conclude this ſection with the following ob-ſervation, which relates to ſpeaking as well as reading, when words fall in our way, whoſe " founds ſeem an echo to the ſenſe,” as <hi rend="italic">ſquirr, buzz, hum, rattle, hfs,jar, </hi>&amp;c. we ought not to pronounce them in ſuch a manner as to heighten the imitation, except in light and ludicrous ſubjects. For inftance, they ſſiould not in any other caſe be founded <hi rend="italic">ſquir.r.r—buzz.z.z—hum.m.m— r.r.rattle,</hi>  &amp;c. Οη the contrary, when the imitation lies in the <hi rend="italic">movement,</hi>  or<hi rend="italic">flow andflrufiure of a whole paſſage</hi>  (which frequently happens in poetry), the delivery may always be allowed to give a heightening to it with the greateſt propriety ; as in the following inſtances, out of a number more which every experienced reader will .quickly recollect.</p><p>In theſe deep folitudes and awful cells,</p><p><hi rend="italic">Where heav’ nly-penfive Contemplation dwells, .</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">And ever-mufing Melancholy reigns-—</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Pope's Eloiſa to Abelard.</hi></p><p>with eafy courfe</p><p>The veffels glide, unleſs their ſpeed be ſtopp’d</p><p>J¾<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="italic">dead calms, that oſt Ue on theſe ſmooth ſeas.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Dyer’s Fleece.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Softly ſweet in Lydian meaſure,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Soon he ſooth’d her ſoul to pleaſure.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Dryden’s Ode on St Cecilia’s day.</hi></p><p>Still gathering force it ſmokes, and, urg’d amain, whirls, leaps, and <hi rend="italic">thunders down impetuous to the plain.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Pope’s Iliad,</hi>  B. 13. For who to dumb forgetfulneſs a prey,</p><p>This pleaſing anxious being ere refign'd,</p><p>Left the warm precincts of the cheerful day,</p><p>Nor caſt <hi rend="italic">one longing ling’ring look behind ?</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Grey’s Elegy.</hi></p><p>2. Beſides the particular tones and modifications of voice above deſcribed, which always accompany and expreſs our inward agitations, nature has in theſe caſes endowed us with another language, which, inſtead of the ear, addreffes itſelf to the eye, thereby giving the communications of the heart a double advantage over thofe of the underſtanding, and <hi rend="italic">us</hi>  a double chance to preſerve fo ineſtirnable a bleſſing. This language is what ariſes from the different, almoſt involuntary movements and configurations of the face and body in our emotions and paſſions, and which, like that' of tones, every one is formed to underſtand by a kind of intuition.</p><p>when men are in any violent agitation of mind, this co-operating <hi rend="italic">expreſfion</hi>  (as it is called) of face and <hi rend="italic">geſture</hi>  is very ſtrongly marked, and totally free from the mixture of any thing which has a regard to gracefulnefs, or what appearance they may make in the eyes of others. But in ordinary converſation, and where the emotions are not fo warm, faſſiionable people are perpe-tually infinuatſhg, into their countenance and action, whatever they imagine will add to the eaſe and elegance of their deportment, or impreſs on the ſpectator an idea of their amiableneſs and breeding. Now, though the above-mentioned natural organical figns of the emotions ſhould accompany every thing fpoken, yet from what was obſerved in the introductory part of this article (like the tones we have juſt-treated upon), they ſhould in reading he much leſs ſtrongly expreffed, and thoſe fuffer the greateſt diminution that are in themfeives the moſt ungainly. And as it was in the laſt ſection re-commended tβ the reader to preſerve himſelf as far from being affected in all paſſionate ſubjects as to be able to keep a temperate command over the various affections oſ the voice, &amp;c. fo under the ſanction of this ſubor-dinate feeling he may accompany his delivery more frequently with any eaſy action or change of face, which will contribute to ſet off his manner, and make it agree-able on the principles of art.</p><p>As theſe calm decorations oſ action (as we may call them) are not altogether natural, but have their rife ſrom a kind of inttitution, they muſt be modelled by the practices of the polite. And though mankind differ from one another ſcarce more in any particular than in that of talents for adopting the graceful actions of the body, and hence nothing determinate can be ſaid of their nature and frequency, yet even thoſe, moſt happily calculated to acquit themfelves well in their uſe, might profit by confidering that it is better greatly to abridge the diſplay, than to over-do it ever fo little; For the peculiar modeſty of deportment with which the inhabitants of this kingdom are endowed, makes us in common endeavour to ſuppreſs many figns of an agitated mind ; and in ſuch caſes the bodily ones in par-tic ular are very ſparingly uſed. we have alfo a natural and rooted diſlike to any kind of affectation ; and to no</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>