<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>their joint bended backwards. This joint, which, when the animal lies, is covered with a remarkable fold of the ſkin, appears when he ſtands. The tail is thin, and proportionally ſhort ; that of the rhinoceros ſo often mentioned, exceeded not 16 or 17 inches in length. It turns a little thicker at the extremity, which is garniſhed with ſome ſhort, thick, hard hairs. The form of the penis is very extraordinary. It is contained in a prepuce or ſheath like that of the horſe ; and the ſirſt thing that appears in the time of erection is a fecond prepuce, of a ſſeſh-colour, from which there iffues a hollow tube, in the form of a funnel cut and bordered fomewhat like a flower-de-luce, and conſtitutes tlie glans and extremity of the penis. This anomalous glans is of à paler ſſeſh-colour than the ſecond prepuce. Tn the moſt vigorous erection, tlie penis extends not above eight inches out of the body ; and it is eaſily procured by rubbing the animal witli a liandſul of ſtraw wlien lie lies at his eaſe. The direction of this organ is not ſtraiglit, but bended backward. Hence lie throws out his urine behind ; and from this circumſtance, it may be inferred that the male covers not the female, but that they unite with their cruppers to each other. The female organs are ſituated like thoſe of the cow ; and ſhe exactly reſembles the male in ſigure and groffneſs of body. The ſkin is ſo thick and impenetrable, that when a man lays hold of any of the folds, he would imagine he is touching a wooden plank of half an inch thick @@(b). when tanned, Dr Grew remarks, it is exceffively hard, and thicker than the hide of any other terreſtrial animal. It is everywhere covered more or leſs with in-eruſtations in the form of galls or tuberoſities, which are pretty ſmall on the top of the neck and back, but become larger on the ſides. The largeſt are on the ſhoul-ders and crupper, are ſtill pretty large on the thighs and legs, upon which they are ſpread all round, and even on thc feet. But between the folds thc ſkin is penetrable, delicate, and as ſoft to the touch as ſilk, while the external part of the fold is equally hard with the reſt. This tender ſkin between the folds is of a light fleſh-colour ; and the ſkin of the belly is nearly of the ſame colour and conſiſtence. Theſe galls or tubero-ſities ſhould not be compared, as fome authors have done, to ſcales. They are only ſtmple indurations of the ſkin, without any regularity in their ſigure or ſymmetry in their reſpective poſitions. The flexibility of the ſkin in the folds enables the rhinoceros to move with facility his head, neck, and members. The whole body, except at the joints, is inflexible, and reſembles a coat of mail. Dr Parſons remarks, that this animal liſtened with a deep and long continued attention to any kind of noiſe ; and that, though he was ſſeeping,</p><p>eating, or obeying any other preffing, demands of nature, he raifed his head, aud liſtened till the noiſe ceaſed.”</p><p>Theſe animals never affemble or march together in troops like elephants. Being of a more ſolitary and ſa-vage diſpoſition, they are more difficult to hunt and to overcome. They never attack men, however, except when they are provoked, when they are very furious and formidable ; but as they fee only before them,<hi rend="sub">;</hi> and</p><p>not very ſharply, and as they turn with great difficulty, they may be eaſily avoided. The ſkin of theſe animals is ſo extremely hard as to reſiſt ſabres, lances, javelins, and even muſket balls, the only penetrable parts being the belly, the eyes, and about the ears. Hence the hunters generally attack them wlien they lie down to ſleep.— Their ſleſh is conſidered as excellent hy the Indians and Africans, but eſpecially by the Hottentots ; and if they were trained when young, they might be rendered, domeſtic, in which caſe they would multiply more eaſtly than the elephant. They inhabit Bengal, Siam, Col-chin-China, Quangſi in China, the iſles of Java and· Sumatra, Congo, Angola, Ethiopia, and the country as low as the Cape. They love ſhady foreſts, the neigh-bourhood of rivers, and marſhy places. They wallow in the mire like hogs, and are ſaid by that means to give ſhelter in the folds of their ſkins to ſcorpions, centipedes, and other infects. This is denied by Buffon and Ed-wards, though the ſurgeon of the Shafteſhury had ob-ſerved in a rhinoceros, newly taken after having welter-ed in the mud, ſeveral infects concealed under the ply of the ſkin. This carries with it every appearance of probability ; for as the creature welters in mud, it is impoffible for it to do ſo without bringing up with it ſome of the infects which live in that mud ; and when this is the caſe, it ſurely cannot be unnatural to ſuppoſe that they would ſhelter themſelves under the plaits of the ſkin. Mr Bruce had an opportunity of examining the ſkin of a rhinoceros before his muddy covering had been ſcraped off, and ſaw under it ſeveral very large worms, but not of the carnivorous kind. He ſaw like-wiſe ſeveral ſmaller animals reſembling car-wigs, which he took to be young fcolopendræ ; and, though he ſearched no farther, we muſt certainly conſlder this as a proof of what the ſurgeon of the Shafteſhury re-lated. Mr Bruce ſuppoſes, too, that they welter in mire, partly in order to ſereen themſelves by a caſe of mud from the attacks of that miſchievous fly which in-feſts the animals of Abyffinia to filch a degree. " The time of the fly (ſays he) being in the rainy ſeaſon, the whole black earth turns into mire.- In the night, when the fly is at reſt, the rhinoceros chooſes a convenient place, and there, rolling himſelf in tlie mud, he clothes himſelf with a kind of caſe, which defends him againſt his enemy the following day. The wrinkles and plaits of his ſkin ſerve to keep this muddy plaſter ſirm up-on him, all but about his hips, ſhoulders, and legs,, where it cracks and falls off by motion, and leaves hime expoſed in thoſe places to the attacks of the fly. The itching and pain which follow occaſion him to rub him-ſelf in thoſe parts againſt the rougheſt trees ; and this is at leaſt one cauſe of the puſtules or tubercles whichi we ſee upon theſe places, both on the elephant and rhino-ceros.” They bring forth only one young at a time,, about which they are very ſolicitous- They are ſaid to confort with tygers ; a ſtory founded merely on their common attachment t© the ſides of rivers, by which, means they are often found near each other. Their ſkin,, fleſh, hoofs, teeth, and even dung, are uſed in India medicinally. The horn, eſpecially that of a virgin rhino-· ceros, is conſidered as an antidote againſt poiſon. Every</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b)</hi>  This Mr Bruce denies to be the caſe, and ſuſpects, where it does occur, that it is the effect of diſeaſe, or oſ a different habit acquired by keeping. In their natural ſtate, he thinks they prevent this rigidity by wallowing· in the mud.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>