<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>miniſhed in a greater proportion than can be compen-fated by the power of ſolution in the body of air, in which the portion expired is at firſt immerſed. To ex-plain rain ſrom this cauſe, we muſt always ſuppoſe a conſtant diminution of heat to take place at the moment of the condenſation of the vapour ; but we actu-ally find that the change from a ſtate of vapour to the fluid ſtate is attended with heat ; ſo that rain muſt at once oppoſe its own cauſe, and continued rains would be impoſſible, without calling in the aid of other caufes. From his own ſyſtem, Dr Hutton endcavourβ to ex-plain the regular and irregular ſeaſons of rain, either reſpecting the generality of its appearance, or the re-gularity of its return And to obviate the apparent ex-ceptions of the theory, from the generality of rain, he explains the proportional quantities of rain, and adds a comparative eſtimate of climates, in relation to rain, with the meteorological obſervations made in our own climate. As his principle is at leaſt inſufficient, and we think erroneous, it would be uſeleſs, even were this a proper place for it, to purſue theſe various brân-ches, which muſt partakc of the errors of the ſyſtem. In theſe branches we ought to obſerve, that there are ſeveral juſt obſervations, mixed with errors, becauſe eva-poration and condenſation muſt at laſt be the great ba-ſis of every theory : the miſtakes ariſe from not being aware of all the cauſes, and miſrepreſenting the opera-tion of thoſe which do exiſt.</p><p>In a work entitled Thoughts on Meteorology, V0-lume II. M. de Luc conſiders very particularly the grand phenomenon of rain, and the numerous circumſtances connected with it. He examines the ſeveral hypotheſes with conſiderable care ; but thinks them, even if admiffible, utterly inſufficient to account for the forma-tion of rain. The grand queſtion in this inquiry is, what becomes of the water that riſes in vapour into the atmoſphere ? or what ſtate it ſubſiſts in there, between the time of its evaporation and its falling down again in rain ? If it continues in the ſtate of watery vapour, or ſuch as is the immediate product of evaporation, it muſt poſſeſs the diſtinctive characters eſſential to that fluid : it muſt make the hygrometer move towards hu-midity, in proportion as the vapour is more or leſs· abundant in the air : on a diminution of heat, the humidity, as ſhown by the hygrometer, muſt increafe; and on an increaſe of the heat the humidity muſt diminiſh ∙, and the introduction of other hygroſcopic ſubſtances, drier than the air, muſt have the ſame effeéf as an aug-mentatioπ of heat. Theſe are the properties of watery vapour, on every hypotheſis of evaporation ; and there -fυre all the water that exiſts in the atmoſphere without poffeffing theſe properties, is no longer vapour, but muſt have changed its nature. M. de Luc ſhows, that the water which forms rain, though it has ever been, conſidered and reaſoned upon as producing humidity, does not poſſeſs theſe properties, and muſt therefore have paſſed into another ſtate. See a full account of his reaſoning, and the ſteps by which he proceeded, in the article Meteorology, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>  7, &amp;c. Ashe thinks that the vapour paſſes into an inviſible ſtate in the interval be-tween evaporation and its falling again in rain, and that in that ſtate it is not ſenſible to the hygrometer, he conſiders the laws of hygrolυgy as inſufficient for explaining the formation of rain ; but he does not pre-tend tohave diſcovered thejmmediate cauſe of the ſor-e</p><lb/><p>mation of clouds and rain. If it is not in the imme-diate product of evaporation that rain has its ſource » if the vapours change their nature in the atmofphere&gt; ſo as no longer to be ſenſible to the hygrometer, or to the eye ; if they do not become vapour again till clouds appear ; and if, when the clouds are formed, no altera-tion is perceived in the quality of the air—we muſt acknowledge it to be very probable, that the interme-diate ſtate of vapour is no other than air—and that the clouds do not proceed from any diſtinct fluid contained in the atmoſphere, but from a decompoſition of a part of the air itſelf, perfectly ſimilar to the reſt.</p><p>It appears, to us at leaſt, that M. de Luc’s mode of reaſening on this ſubject agrees better with the phe-nomena than Dr Hutton’s. The Doctor, however, thinks differently, and publiſhed anſwers to the objections of M. de Luc with regard to his theory of rain ; to which M. de Luc replied in a letter which was printed in the Appendix to the 8iſt volume of the Monthly Review : but it would extend our article beyond its due bounds, to give a view of this controver-ſy. See vapour, water, weather, and wind.</p><p>As to the general quantity of rain that falls, and its-proportion in ſeveral places at the ſame time, and in the ſame place at ſeveral times, we have many obſervations, journals, &amp;c. in the Memoirs of the French A-cademy, the Philofophical Tranſactions, &amp;c. Upon meaſuring, then, the rain falling yearly, its depth, at a medium, and its proportion, in ſeveral places, is found as in the following table :    Inches.</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>At Townley, in Lancaſhire, obſerved by Mr Townley    -    -</p><p>Upminſter, in Eſſex, by Dr Derham</p><p>Zurich, in Swiſſerland, by Dr Scheuchzer Piſa, in Italy, by Dr Mich. Ang. Tilli</p><p>Paris, in France, by M. de la Hire</p><p>Liſle, in Flanders, by M. de vauban</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>42⅛</p><p>19i 32τ 43⅛∙</p><p>L<hi rend="sub">9</hi></p><p>24</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>At Upminſter.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>At Paris.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1700    19 Inch. .03</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21 Inch. .37</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1701    18    .69</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>27    .77</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1702    20    .38</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi>7    ∙45</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1703    23    .99</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>18    .51</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1704    15    .80</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21    .20</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1705    16    .93</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14    .82·</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row></table><lb/><p>From the Meteorological Journal of the Royal Society, kept by order of the preſident and council, it ap-pears that the whole quantity of rain at London, in each of the years ſpeciſied below, was as follows<hi rend="sub">j</hi></p><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>viz.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1774</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>»</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>26</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.328</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1775</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>24</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">∙<hi rend="sup">c8</hi>3 v</hi></p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1776</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>•354</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1777</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>•371</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1778</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>•772-</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17 79</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>26</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.785</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1780</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">1</hi>7</hi></p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>∙3<hi rend="sup">1</hi>3</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>The quantity of rain in</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>the four following years at Lon-</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>don was,</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>In 1789</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>•976</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1790</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.052</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1791</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.310</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>179-2</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi>9</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.489</p></cell></row></table><lb/></body></text></TEI>