<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Γo that, when all was made ſmooth, it madc a perfect cube, of which the perforated braſs plate made the poop.</p><p>The apparatus being now expofed to the ſtream, with the perforated plate looking down the ſtream,</p><p>The hole A indicated a non-preſſion -    = 7,2</p><p>B    -    .    -    8</p><p><hi rend="sup">C</hi> . ’ <hi rend="sup">6</hi></p><p>Here was a great diminution of the non-preſſions produced by the diſtance between the prow and the poop.</p><p>This box was then fitted in the ſame manner, ſo as to make the poop of a box three feet long. In this •fituation the non-preſſures were as follow î</p><p>Hole A    -    -    - <hi rend="sub">k</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi>&gt;5</p><p>B    3&gt;.<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>The non-preſſions were ſtill farther diminiſhed by this increaſe of length.</p><p>The box was then expofed with all the holes open, in three different iituations :</p><p>ift, Single, giving a non-preffute -    I3’<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>ad, Making the poop of a cube    -    5’3</p><p>3d, Making the poop of a box three feet long 3,0</p><p>Another larger box :</p><p>iſt, Single    .    -    12,2</p><p>2d, Poop of a cube    -    -    5’</p><p>3d, Poop of the long box    -    3’<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>Theſe are moſt valuable experiments. They plainly ſhow how important it is to confider the action on the hinder part of the body. For the whole impulſe or refiſtance, which muſt be withſtood or overcome by the external force, is the ſum of the active preffure on the fore-part, and of the non-preffure on the hinder-part ; and they ſſiow that this does not depend ſolely on the form of the prow and poop, but alſo, and perhaps chiefly, on the length of the body. We ſee that the non-preffure on the hinder-part was prodigiouſly diminiſhed (reduced to one-fourth) by making the length of the body triple of the breadth. And hence it appears, that merely lengthening a ſhip, without making any change in the form either of her prow or her poop, will greatly diminiſh the refiſtance to her motion through the water ; and this increaſe of length may be made by continuing the form of the midſhip frame in ſeveral timbers along the keel, by which the capacity of the ſhip, and her power of carrying fail, will be greatly increaſed, and her other qualities improved, while her ſpeed is augmented.</p><p>It is ſurely of importance to confider a little the phyfical cauſe of this change. The motions are extremely complicated, and we muſt be contented if we can but perceive a few leading circumſtances.</p><p>The water is turned aſide by the anterior part of the body, and the velocity of the filaments is increafed, and they acquire a divergent motion, by which they alſo puſh afide the ſurrounding water. Οη each fide of the body, therefore, they are moving in a divergent direc-tion, and with an increaſed velocity. But as they are on all tides preſſed by the fluid without them, their motions gradually approach to parallelism, and their velocities to an equality with the ſtream. The progreſ-five velocity, or that in the direction of the ſtream, is checked, at leaſt at firſt. But fince we obſerve the fi-laments conſtipated round the body, and that they are got deflected at right angles to their former direction,</p><p>it is plain that the real velocity of a filament in its ob-lique path is augmented. We always obferve, that a ſtone lying in the ſand, and expofed to the waih of the lea, is laid bare at the bottom, and the ſand is generally waſhed away to ſome diſtance all round. This is owing to the increaſed velocity of the water which comes into contact with the ſtone. It takes up more ſand than it can keep floating, and it depofits it at a little diſtance all around, forming a little bank, which fur-rounds the ſtone at a ſmall diſtance. when the filaments of water have paffed the body, they are preſſid by the ambient fluid into the place which it has quitted, and they glide round its ſtern, and fill up the ſpace behind. '1 he more divergent and the more rapid they are, when about to fall in behind, the more of the circumambient preffure muſt be employed to turn them in-to the trough behind the body, and leſs of it will remain to preſs them to the body itſelf. The extreme of this muſt obtain when the liream is obſtructed by a thin plane only. But when there is fome diſtance between the prow and the poop, the divergency of the fi-laments which had been turned afide by the prow, ia diminiſhed by the time that they have come abreaſt of the ſtern, and ſhould turn in behind it. They are therefore more readily made to converge behind the body, and a more confiderable part of the ſurrounding preſſure remains unexpended, and therefore preſſes the water againſt the fiern ; and it is evident that this advantage muſt be ſo much the greater as the body is longer. But the advantage will ſoon be ſuſceptible of no very confiderable increaſe : for the lateral and divergent, and accelerated filaments, will ſoon become ſo nearly parallel and equally rapid with the reſt of thc ſtream, that a great increafe of length will not make any confiderable change in thefe particulars ; and it muſt be accompanied with an increaſe of friction.</p><p>Theſe are very obvious reflections. And if we attend minutςly to the way in which thc almoſt ſtagnant ſtuid behind the body is expended and renewed, we ſhall ſee all theſe effects confirmed and augmented. But as we cannot ſay any thing on this ſubject that is preciſe, or that can be made the ſubject of computation, it is needleſs to enter into a more minute diſcuſſion. The diminution of the non-preſſure towards the centra moſt probably arifes from the ſmaller force which is ne-ceſſary to be expended in the inflection of the lateral fi . laments, already inflected in ſome degree, and having their velocity diminiſhed. But it 13 a ſubject highly defer vi ng the attention of the mathematicians ; and we preſume to invite them to the ſtudy of the motions of thefe lateral filaments, paſſing the body, and preſſed into its wake by forces which are ſufceptible of no difficult inveſtigation. It ſeems highly probable, that if a prifmatic box, with a fquare ſtern, were fitted with an addition precifely ſhaped like the water which would (abſtracting tenacity and friction) have been ſtagnant behind it, the quantity of non-preſſion would be thc fmalleſt poſſible. The mathematician would ſurely diſ-cover circumſtances which would furniſh ſome maxims of conſtruction for the hinder part as well as for the prow. And as h,is ſpeculations on tins laſt have not been wholly fruitleſs, we may expect advantages from his attention to this part, ſo much neglected.</p><p>In the mean time, let us attend to the deductions' which Mr de Buat has made from his few experiments.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>