<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>qttence ariſe from thus founding diſtinctions on ratios of time, which it may be ſaid are too nice to be often rightly hit upon : for if a confuſion ſhould happen between that of the <hi rend="italic">colon</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">period,</hi>  there is perhaps fo trifling a difference between the nature of the paffages they ſucceed, as to make a ſmall inaccuracy of no con-ſequence. And as to the reſts of the ſemicolon and period, it will not be eaſy to miſtake about them, as their, ratio is that of two to one. Add to this the power which the matter and introduction of-the ſub-ſequent paffages have to rectify any flight errδr here made, and we ſhall be fully ſatisſied, that the pauſes as uſually explained, with the cadence above defcribed, and a proper knowledge of the language, will convey fufficient information to the underſtanding of the con-ſtructive nature of the paffages after which they are found.</p><p>It may be obſerved, that in natural fpeech, accord-ing to the warmth and agitation of the ſpeaker, the reſts are often ſhort and injudiciouſly proportioned, and hence that eveιy thing thus delivered cannot be ſo grace-ful as it might have been from a proper attention to their magnitude and effects.</p><p>Pauſes then, though chiefly ſubjected to the ſenſe, are, as was remarked at the outſet, ſerviceable in beautifying the modulation, &amp;c.—And ſince books are often inaccurately printed as to points, and peo-ple’s taſtes differ fome little about their place and va-Iue, it appears, that, " although in reading great attention ſhould be paid to the ſtops, yet a greater ihould be given to the ſenſe, and their coreſpondent times occafionally lengthened beyond what is uſual in common ſpeech which obſervation contains all that we ſhall pretend to lay down by way of rule for the management of pauſes in the delivery of written language.</p><p>As there are two or three ſpecies of writing, which have ſomething ſingular in them, and with regard to the manner in which they ſhould be read, a few <hi rend="italic">particular</hi>  remarks ſeem neceffarily required, we ſhall con-clude this article with laying them before the reader :</p><p>1.    of <hi rend="smallcaps">Plays,</hi>  and ſuch like <hi rend="smallcaps">conversation-pièces. </hi>Writings of this kind maybe conſidered as intended for two different purpoſes ; one to unfold ſubject matter for the exercife of theatric powers ; and the other to convey amuſement, merely as fable replete with pleaſing incidents and characteriſtic maimers. Hence there appears to be great latitude for the diſplay of a <hi rend="italic">conſflent</hi>  delivery of theſe performances : for while, on one hand, a good reader of very inferior talents for mimicry may be heard with a tolerable degree of pleaſure ; on the other, if any perſon is qualified to give a higher degree of life and force to the dialogue and characters by delivering them as an actor, he muſt be fully at liberty to ſtart from the confinement of a chair to a poſture and area more ſuit-ed to his abilities ; and, if he be not deceived in himſelf,</p><p>his hearers will be conſiderable gainers by the change._</p><p>The next article is,</p><p>2.    <hi rend="smallcaps">Sermons</hi>  or other <hi rend="smallcaps">orations,</hi>  which in like man-tier may be conceived intended for a double purpoſe. Firſt, as matter for the diſplay of oratorical powers ; aιwl, ſecondly, as perſuaſive diſcourſes, &amp;c. which may be read like any other book. Therefore it appears (for reaſons ſimilar to thoſe above) that according as clergymen are poffeffed of the talents of elocution, they may conſiſtently either rehearſe their fermons, in the manner of an extemporary harangue, or deliver them in the more humble capacity of one -who is content to entertain and inſtruct his hearers with reading to them his own or ſome other perſon’s written diſcourſe.</p><p>Ί hat either of theſe manners of delivery (or a mixture of them), in either of the cafes above-mentioned, is agreeable, we find on a careful exa. ſination. For this will ſhow us how frequently they run into one another; and that we are ſo far from thinking ſuch tranſitions wrong, that, without a particular attention that way, we fcarce ever perceive them at all.</p><p>3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Poetry</hi>  is the next and laſt object of our prefent remarks. This is a very peculiar kind of writing, and as much different from the language of ordinary difcourſe as the movements of the dance are from common w..<hi rend="sub">i</hi>k-ing. 1 o ornament and improve whatever is ſubfervient to the pleaſures and amufements of life, is the delight of human nature, we are alfo pleaſed with a kind o£ <hi rend="italic">excefi.</hi>  in any thing which has a power to amuſe the fart-cy, inſpire us with enthuſiaſm, or awaken the ſoul to 3 conſciouſneſs of its own importance and dignity. Hence one pleaſure, at leaft, takes its riſe, that we feel in con-templating the performances of every art ; and hence the language", of poetry, conſiſting of a meaſured ryth-mus, harmonious cadences, and an elevated pictureſqn¢ diction, has been ſtudied by the ingenious, and found to have a powerful influence over the human breaſt in every age and region. There is ſuch an affinity between this language and muſic, that they were in the earlier ages never ſeparated; and though modern refinement has in a great meaſure deſtroyed this union, yet it is with fome degree of difficulty in rehearfing thefe divine compofitions we can forget tlie finging of the muſe.</p><p>From theſe confiderations (and ſome kindred ones mentioned in ſect. iii.) in repeating verſes, they are ge-nerally accompanied with a modulation rather more or-namented and mufical than is uſed in any other kind of writing. And accordingly, as there ſeems to bc the greateſt propriety in the practice, the rule for this par-ticular in the ſection juſt referred to, will allow any lati∙&gt; tude in it that can gain the ſanction of taſte and pleaſure.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rhymes</hi>  in the lighter and more ſoothing provinces of poetry are found to have a good effect ; and hence (for reaſons like thoſe juſt ſuggeſted) it is certainly abſurd to endeavour to {mother them by a feeble pro* nuπciation, and running one line precipitately into another, as is often affected to be done by many of our modern readers and ſpeakers. By this method they not on» ly deftroy one ſource of pleaſure intended by the com-poſer (which though not great is nevertheleſs genuine), but even often ſupply its place with what is really diſa-greeable, by making the rhymes, as they are interruptedly perceived, appear accidental blemiſhes of a different ſtyle, arifing from an unmeaning recurrence of fimilar founds, with regard then to reading verſes terminated with rhyme, the common rule, which directs to prδ-nounce the final words <hi rend="italic">full,</hi>  and to diſtinguiſh them by a flight pauſe even where there is none required by the fen le, ſeems the moſt rational, and conſequently moſt worthy, of being followed. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Declamation, Na&amp;-</hi>RAτi0N,and <hi rend="smallcaps">oratory.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reading,</hi>  a town of Berkſhire in England, plea·* ſantly ſeated on the river Kenneth, near the confluence with the Thames, it had onc≤ a ſiae rich monaſtery,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>