<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">« Sixthly,</hi>  Infects being thctr food, I never ſaw any toad ſhow any liking or diſlike to any plant (d).</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Seventhly,</hi>  1 hardly remember any perfops taking it up except my father and myielf ; 1 do not know whether it had any particular attachment to us.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Eighthly,</hi>  In reſpect to its end, I anſwer this laſt query. Had it not been for a tame raven, I make no doubt but it would have been now living ; who one day feeing it at the month of its hole, pulled it out, and although I reſcued it, pulled out one eye, and hurt it ſo, that notwithſtanding its living a twelvemonth it never enjoyed itſelf, and had a difficulty of taking its food, miffing the mark for want of its eye : before that accèdent it had all the appearance of perfect health.”</p><p>6.    The rubeta, or natter-jack, frequents dry and fan-dy places : it is found on Putney common, and alſo near Reveſhy abbey, Lmcolnſhire. It never leaps, neither does it crawl with the flow pace of a toad, but its motion is liker to running. Several are found commonly together, and like others of the genus they appear in the evenings. The upper part of the body is of a dirty yellow, clouded with brown, and covered with porous pimples,of unequal ſizes : on the back is a yellow line. The upper fide of the body is of a paler hue, marked with black ſpots, which are rather rough. Οη the fore-feet are four divided toes ; on the hind five, a little webbed. The length of the body is two inches and a quarter; the breadth, one and a quarter: the length of the fore-legs, one inch one-ſixth ; of the hind legs, two inches, we are indebted to SirJoſeph Banks, for this account.</p><p>7.    The pipal, or Surinam toad, is more ugly than even the common one. The body is flat and broad ; the head ſmall ; the jaws, like thoſe of a mole, are extended, and evidently formed for rooting in the ground : tlιe ſkin of the neck forms a fort of wrinkled collar: the.colour of the head is of a dark cheſnut, and the eyes are ſmall : the back, which is vcry broad, is of a hghtiſh grey, and feems covered over with a number of ſmall eyes, which are round, and placed at nearly equal diſtances. Theſe eyes are very different from what they ſeem : they are the animal’s eggs, covered with their ſhells, and placed therc for hatching. Thefe eggs are buried deep in the ſkin, and in the beginning of incubation but juſt appear j and are very viſible when the young animal is about to burſt from its confinement. They are of a reddiſh, ihining yellow colour ; and the ſpaces between them are full oſ ſmall warts, reſembling pearls.</p><p>This is their ſituation previous to their coming forth ; but nothing ſo much demands our admiration as the</p><lb/><p>manner of their production. The egga, when formed i∏ tſie ovary, are ſent, by ſome internal canals, which anatomiſts have not hitherto deſcribed, to lie aηd come to maturity under the bony ſubſtance of the back : in this ſtate they are impregnated by the male, whoſe ſeed finds its way by pores very ſingularly contrived, and pierces not only the ſkin but the perioſteum : the ſkin, however, is ſtill apparently entire, and forms a very thick covering ever the whole brood ; but as they advance to maturity, at different intervals, one after another, the egg ſeems to ſtart forward, and burgeons from the back, becomes more yellow, and at laſt breaks j when the young one puts forth its head : it ſtill, however, keeps its ſituation until it has acquired a proper degree of ſtrength, and then it leaves the ſhell, but ſtill continues to keep upon the back of the parent. In this manner the pipal is ſeen travelling with her won-derous family on her back, in all the different ſtages of maturity. Some of the ſtrange progeny, not yet come to ſufficient perfection, appear quite torpid, and as yet without life in the egg : others ſeem juſt beginning tts riſe through the ſkin ; here peeping forth from the ſhell, and there having entirely forſaken their priſon ; ſome are ſpprting at large upon the parent’s back, and others defcending to the ground to try their own fortune below. The male pipal is every way larger than the fe-male, and has the ſkin leſs tightly drawn round the body. The whole body is covered with pullules, reſembling pearls ; and the belly, which is of a bright yel-low, ſeems as if it were ſewed up from the throat to the vent,. a feam being ſeen to run in that direction. This animal, like the reſt of the frog kind, is moſt probably harmleſs.</p><p>8.    The water frog of Cateſhy has large black eyes* yellow irides, and long limbs : the upper part of the head and body is of a duſky green, fpotted with black ; and from each eye to the noſe is a white line ; and alfi&gt; a yellow line along the ſides to the rump. They fre-quent rivulets and ditches, which they do not quit for the dry land. It is ſaid they will ſpring five or ſix yards at a leap.</p><p>9.    The rana arborea, or green tree frog of Cateſhy, is of a ſlender ſhape and bright green colour, marked or» each ſide with a line of yellow : the eyes are black ; the irides yellow ; they have four toes before and five behind ; at the end of each toe there ia a round membrane, concave beneath, and not unlike the mouth of a leech. They lurk under the lower fides of leaves, even of the talleſt trees, and adhere firmly, by means of the membranes at the ends of their toes, {ticking to the ſmootheſt ſurface t a looking-glaſs was held before one,.</p><lb/><p>threw on the <hi rend="italic">curious impertinent</hi>  a fixed look that marked his diſquietneſs and fear ; but he ſoon re⅛∙,ιr.ned to. his work with rnoie precipitation than before, aad a moment after he appeared undetermined whether he ſhould. continue it or not. The female likewiſe diſcovered her uneaſineſs at the fight of the ſtranger, by motions that interrupted fometimes the male in his operation. At length, whether the ſilence and ſteady poſture of the fpec-tator had diſſipated their fear, or that the <hi rend="italic">caſe</hi>  was urgent, tlie raalereſumed his work with the ſame vigour, and ſuccefsfully performed his function.”</p><p>(u) Thia queſtion aroſe from an aſſertion of Linnaeus, that the toad delighted in filthy herbs. <hi rend="italic">Delectatur co-tula, actna, Jiach∖&lt;ιle fcetide.</hi>  The unhappy deformity of the animal ſeems to be the only ground of this as vveli as another miſreprefentation, of its conveying a poiſon with its pimples, its touch, and even its. breath» <hi rend="italic">Vtrru^ t¢ iacteſcentes vcnena!x infufi% tactu<hi rend="sub">i</hi>  anhelitν,</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>