<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Dr Derhatn accounted for the precipitation of the drops of ram from the veficulæ being full of air, and meeting with an air colder than they contained, the air they contained was of conſequence contracted into a fmaller ſpace ; and conſequently the watery ſhell rendered thicker, and thus ſpecifically heavier, than the common atmoſphere. But it has been ſhown, that the veficulæ, if ſuch they are, of vapour, are not ſilled with air, but with ſire, or heat ; and conſequent-ly, till they part with this latent heat, the vapour can-not be condenſtd §. Now, cold is not always ſufficient to effect this, ſince in the moſt ſevere froſts the air is very often ſerene, and parts with little or none of its va-pour for a very conſiderable time. Neither can we admit the winds to have any conſiderable agency in this matter, ſince we ſind that blowing upon vapour is ſo far from condenſing it, that it unites it more cloſely with the air, and wind is found to be a great promoter of evaporation.</p><p>According to Rohault, the great cauſe of rain is the heat of the air ; which, after continuing for ſome time near the earth, is raiſed on high by a wind, and there thawing the ſnowy villi or flocks of half-frozen veficulæ, reduces them to drops ; which, coaleſcing, de-ſcend. Here, however, we ought to be informed by what means theſe veficulæ are ſuſpended in their half-frozen ſtate ; fince the thawing of them can make but little difference in their ſpeciſic gravity, and it is cer-tain that they afcended through the air not in a fro-zen but in an aqueous ſtate.</p><p>Dr Clarke and others afcribe this defcent of the rain rather to an alteration of the atmoſphere than of the veficulæ ; and ſuppoſe it to ariſe from a diminution of the elaſtic force of the air. This elaſticity, which, they ſay, depends chiefly or wholly upon terrene exhalations, being weakened, the atmofphere links under its burden, and the clouds fall. Now, the little veſicles being once upon the deſcent, will continue there-in, notwithſtanding the increaſe of reſiſtance they <hi rend="sub">j </hi>every moment meet with. For, as they all tend to the centre of the earth, the farther they fall, the more coalitions they will make ; and the more coalitions, rhe more matter will there be under the ſame ſurface ; the furface increafing only as the ſquares, but the ſolidity as the cubes ; and the more matter under the ſame furface, the leſs reſiſtance will there be to the fame matter. Thus, if the cold, wind, &amp;c. act early enough to precipitate the aſcending veſicles before they are arrived at any conſiderable height, the coalitions being but few, the drops will be proportionably ſmall ; and thus is formed a dew. If the vapours be more copious, and riſe a little higher, we have a miſt or fog. A little higher ſtill, and they produce a ſmall ιain ; if they neither meet with cold nor wind, they form a heavy thick dark ſky. This hypotheſis is equally unſatisfactory with the' others ; for, granting that the de-ſcent and condenſation of the vapours are owing to a diminution of the atmofphere’s elaſticity, by what is this diminution occaſioned ? To fay that it is owing to ter-rene exhalations, is only ſolving one difficulty by another ; ſince we are totally unacquainted both with the mature and operation of theſe exhalations. Beſides, let us ſuppoſe the cauſe to be what it will, if it acts equally and at once upon all the vapour in the air, then ail that vapour muſt be precipitated at once ; and thus, inſtead of gentle ſhowers continuing for a confiderable length of time, we ſhould have the moſt violent water-ſpouts, continuing only for a few minutes, or perhaps ſeconds, which, inſtead of refreſhing the earth, would drown and lay waſte every thing before them.</p><p>Since philoſophers have admitted the electric fluid to ſuch a large ſhare in the operations of nature, al-moſt all the natural phenomena have been accounted for by the action of that fluid ; and rain, among others, has been reckoned an effect of electricity. But this word, unleſs it is explained, makes us no wiſer .than we were before ; the phenomena of artificial electricity having been explained on principles which could ſcarce apply in any degree to the electricity of nature : and therefore all the ſolution we can obtain of the natural appearances of which we ſpeak, comes to this, that rain is occaſioned by a moderate electrification, hail and ſnow by one more violent, and thunder by the moſt violent of all ; but in what manner this electrification is occa-ſioned, hath not yet been explained. Throughout the various parts of this work where electricity hath been occafionally mentioned, the principles of artificial electricity j∣, laid down in the treatiſe appropriated to that ſubject, have been applied to the ſolution ot the phenomena of nature ; thoſe which are necefl’ary to be attend-ed to here are the following :</p><p>1.    The electric fluid and ſolar light are the ſame fubſtance in two different modifications.</p><p>2.    Electricity is the motion of the fluid when running, or attempting to run, in a continued ſtream from one place to another : heat is when the fluid has no tendency but to vibrate outwards and inwards to and from a centre ; or at leaſt when its ſtreams converge to a point or focus.</p><p>3.    The fluid acting as electricity, like water, or any other fluid, always tends to the place where there is leaſt reſiſtance.</p><p>Οη theſe three principles may the phenomena of at-moſpherical electricity, and the deſcent of rain by its means, be explained as follows :</p><p>i The light or heat of thc ſun, acting in that pe-cüliar manner which we call <hi rend="italic">heat,</hi>  unites itſelf with the moiſture of the earth, and forms it into vapour, which thus becomes ſpecifically lighter than air, and of conlequence aſcends in the atmoſphere to a certain height.</p><p>2.    Befides the quantity of light which is thus united to the water, and forms it into vapour, a very con-fiderable quantity enters the earth, where it affumes the nature of electric fluid.</p><p>3.    As the earth is always full of that fluid, every quantity which enters muſt difplace an equal quantity which is already there.</p><p>4.    This quantity which is difplaced muſt eſcape ei-ther at a diitance from the place where the other en-ters, or very near it.</p><p>5.    At whatever place a quantity of electric matter eſcapes, it muſt electrify the air above that place where it has eſcaped ; and as a confiderable quantity of light muſt always be reflected from the earth into the atmoſphere, where it does not combine with the aqueous vapour, we have thence another ſource of electricity to the air ; as this quantity muſt undoubt-edly affume the action of electric fluid, elpecially after the action of the ſun has ceaſed. Hence the rea-</p></body></text></TEI>