<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>againſt the walls ſtones of 150 pounds weight. The towers, being thus furiouſly battered night and day, began to totter, and ſeveral breaches were opened in the walls : but the Rhodians, unexpectedly ſallying out, drove the enemy from their poſt, overturned their machines, and made a moſt dreadful havock ; inſomuch that ſome of them retired on board their veſſels, and were with much ado prevailed upon to come aſhore again.</p><p>Demetrius now ordered a ſcalade by ſea and land at the ſame time ; and ſo employed the beſieged, that they were at a loſs what place they ſhould chiefly de-fend. The attack was carried on with the utmoſt fury onall ſides, and the beſieged defended themſelves with the greateſt intrepidity. Such of the enemy as advan-ced firſt were thrown down from the ladders, and mi-ſerably bruiſed. Several of the chief officers, having mounted the walls to encourage the ſoldiers by their example, were there either killed or taken priſon-ers. After the combat had laſted many hours, with great ſlaughter on both ſides, Demetrius, notwith-ſtanding all his valour, thought it neceſſary to retire, in order to repair his engines, and give his men ſome days reft,</p><p>Demetrius being ſenſible that he could not reduce the city till he was maſter of the port, after having refreſhed his men, he returned with new vigour againſt the fortifications which defended the entry into the harbour, when he came within the caſt of a dart, he cauſed a vaſt quantity of burning torches and firebrands to be thrown into the Rhodian ſhips, which were riding there ; and at the fame time galled, with dreadful ſhowers of darts, arrows, and ſtones, ſuch as offered to extinguiſh the flames. However, in ſpite of their utmoſt efforts, the -Rhodians put a ſtop to the fire ; and, having with great expedition manned three of their ſtrongeſt ſhips, drove with ſuch violence againſt the veſſels on which the enemy’s machines were planted, that they were ſhattered in pieces, and the engines diſmounted and thrown into the ſea. Exceſtus the Rhodian admiral, being encouraged by this ſuccefs, attacked the enemy’s fleet with his three ſhips, and ſunk a great many veſſels ; but was himſelf at laſt taken priſoner : the other two veſſels made their eſcape, and</p><p>regained the port.</p><p>As unfortunate as this laſt attack had proved to De-metrius, he determined to undertake another ; and, in order to ſucceed in his attempt, he ordered a machine of a new invention to be built, which was thrice the height and breadth of thoſe he had lately loſt. when the work was finiſhed, he cauſed the engine to be placed near the port, which he was reſolved, at all adventures, to force. But as it was upon the point of entering the harbour, a dreadful ſtorm ariſing, drove it againſt the ſhore, with the veſſels on which it had been reared. The beſieged, who were attentive to improve all favourable conjunctures, while the tempeſt was ſtill raging, made a ſally againſt thoſe who defended the eminence mentioned above ; and, though repulſed ſeveral times, carried it at laſt, obliging the Demetrians, to the number of 400, to throw down their arms and ſubmit. After this victory gained by the Rhodians, there arrived to their aid 150 Gnoſ-ſians, and 500 men fent by Ptolemy from Egypt, moſt of them being natives of Rhodes, who had ſerved among the king’s troops.</p><p>Demetrius being extremely mortified toſee all his batteries againſt the harbour rendered ineffectual, re-ſolved to employ them by land, in hopes of carrying the city by aſſault, or at leaſt reducing it to the neceſſity of capitulating, with this view, having got together avaſt quantity of timber and other materials, he framed the famous engine called <hi rend="italic">helepolis, </hi>which was by many degrees larger than any that, had ever been invented before. Tts baſis was fquare, each ſide being in length near 50 cubits, and made up of ſquare pieces of timber, bound together with plates of iron. In the middle part he placed thick planks, about a cubit diſtance from each other ; and on theſe the men were to ſtand who forced the engine forward. The whole was moved upon eight ſtrong and large wheels, whoſe felloes were ſtrengthened with ſtrong iron plates. In order to facilitate and vary the move-ments of the helepolis, caſters were placed under it, whereby it was turned in an inſtant to what ſide the workmen and engineers pleaſed. From each of the four angles a large pillar of wood was carried to about the height of 100 cubits, and inclining to each other; the whole machine conſiſting of nine ſtories, whoſe dimenſions gradually leſſened in the aſcent. The firſt ſtory was ſupported by 43 beams, and the laſt by no more than nine. Three ſides of the machine were plated over with iron, to prevent its being damaged by the fire that might be thrown from the city. In the front of each ſtory were windows of the ſame ſize and ſhape as the engines that were to be diſcharged from thence. To each window were ſhutters, to draw up for the defence of thoſe who managed the machines, and to deaden the force of the ſtones thrown by the enemy, the ſhutters being covered with ſkins ſtuffed with wool. Every ſtory was furniſhed with two large ſtaircaſes, that whatever was neceſſary might be brought up by one, while others were going down by the other, and ſo every thing may be diſpatched without tumult or confuſion. This huge machine was moved forwards by 3000 of the ſtrongeſt men of the whole army ; but the art with which it was built greatly facilitated the motion. Demetrius cauſed likewiſe to be made ſeveral teſtudoes or pent houſes, to cover his men while they advanced to ſill up the trenches and ditches ; and invented a new ſort of galleries, through which thoſe who were employed at the ſiege might paſs and re-paſs at their pleaſure, without the leaſt danger. He employed all his ſeamen in levelling the ground over which the machines were to be brought up, to the ſpace of four furlongs. The number of workmen who were employed on this occaſion amounted to 30,000.</p><p>In the mean time, the Rhodians, obſerving theſe formidable preparations, were buſy in raiſing a new wall within that which the enemy intended to batter with the helepolis. In order to accompliſh this work, they pulled down the wall which ſurrounded the theatre, ſome neighbouring houſes, and even ſome temples, after having ſolemnly promiſed to build more magnifi-cent ſtructures in honour of the gods, if the city were preſerved. At the ſame time, they ſent out nine of their beſt ſhips to ſeize ſuch of the enemy’s veſſels as they could meet with, and thereby diſtreſsthem for</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>