<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>an axis <hi rend="italic">e f</hi>  of ſtiff-tempered ſteel-wire, ſo that the fur-face on which the fluid is to act may be inclined to the ſtream in the preciſe angle we deſire. Let this axis have hooks at its extremities, which are hitched into the loops of four equal threads, ſuſpeuded fιom the hooks <hi rend="italic">a, b,</hi>  c, <hi rend="italic">cl ;</hi>  and let He be a ſilth thread, ſuſpended from the middle of the line joining the points of fuſpenſion <hi rend="italic">a, b.</hi>  Let HIK be a graduated arch, whole centre is H, and whoſe plane is in the direction of the ſtream. It is evident that the impulle on the body G will be meaſured (by a proceſs well known to every mathematician) by the deviation of the thread He from the vertical line HI ; and this will be done without any intricacy of calculation, or any attention to the centres of gravity, of oſcillation, or of percuſſion. Theſe muſt be accurately afcertained with reſpect to that form in which the pendulum has always been employed for meafuring the impulſe or velocity of a ſtream. Theſe advantages ariſe from the circumſtance, that the axis <hi rend="italic">cſ</hi>  remains always parallel to the horizon, we may be allowed to obſerve, by the by, that this would have been a great improvement of the beautiful experiments of Mr Robins and Dr Hutton on the velocities of cannon-ſhot, and would have ſaved much intricate calculation, and been attended with many important ad-vantages.</p><p>The great difficulty is, as we have obſerved, to mea-fure the velocity of the ſtream. Even this may be done in this way w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ith fome preciſion. Let two floating bo-dies be dragged along the ſurface, as in the experiments of the academy, at fome diſtance from each other late-rally, ſo. that the water between them may not be ſen-ſibly diſturbed. Let a horizontal bar be attached to them, tranſverſe to the direction of their motion, at a proper height above the furface, and let a ſpherical pen-duλum be iuſpended from this, or let it be ſuſpended from four points, as here deſcribed. Now let the deviation of this pendulum be noted in a variety of velo-cities. This will give us the law of relation between the velocity and the deviation of the pendulum. Now, in making experiments on the refiſtance of bodies, let the velocity of the ſtream, in the very filament in which the refiſtance is meafnred, be determined by the devia-t.ion of this pendulum.</p><p>It were greatly to be wiſhed that ſome more palpable argument could be found for the exiſtence of a quantity of ſtagnant fluid at the anterior and poſterior patts of tlie body. The one already given, derived from the confideration that no motion changes either its velocity or direction by finite quantities in an inſtant, is unex-ceptionable. But it gives us little information. The finalleit conceivable extent of the curve FM in fig. 16. will anſwer this condition, provided only that it touch-es the axis in ſome peint F, and the body in ſome point M, fo as not to make a finite angle with either. But ſurely there are circumſtances which rigorouſiy determine the extent of this ſtagnant fluid. And it appears without doubt, that if there were no coheſion or fric-tion, this ſpace will have a determined ratio to the fize of the body (the figures of the bodies being ſuppoſed ſimilar).. Suppoſe a plane ſurfaee AB, as in ſig. io. there can be no doubt but that the figure A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  D <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  B will in every caſe be ſimilar. But if we ſuppoſe an adheſion or tenacity which is conſtant, this may make θ change both in its extent and its form : ſor its con-ſtancy oſ form depends on the diſturbing forces being alwayβ as the ſquares of the velocity ; and this ratio oſ the diſturbing forces is preſerved, while the inertia of the fluid is the only agent and patient in the proceſs. But when we add to this the conſtant (that is, invariable) diſturbing force of tenacity, a change of form and dimenlions muſt happen. In like manner, the friction, or ſomething analogous to friction, which produces an effect proportional to the velocity, muſt alter this ne-ceſlhry ratio of the whole diſturbing forces. We may conclude, that the effect of both theſe circumſtances will be to diminiſh the quantity of this ſtagnant fluid, by licking it away externally ; and to this we muſt afcribe the fact, that the part FAM is never perfectly ſtagnant, but is generally diſturbed with a whirling motion. we may alſo conclude, that this ſtagnant ſiuid. will be more ineurvated between F and M than it would, have been, independent of tenacity and friction ; and that the arch LR. will, on the contrary, be leſs incur-vated.—And, laſtly, we may conclude, that there will be ſomething oppoſite to preffure, or ſomething which we may call <hi rend="italic">abjtra£lion,</hi>  exerted on the poſterior part of the body which moves in a tenacious fluid, or is expo-fed to the ſtream of ſuch a fluid ; lor the ſtagnant ſtuid LCR adheres to the ſurfaee LC ; and the paſ-ſing ſtuid tends to draw it away both by its tenacity and by its friction. This mnſt augment the apparent impulſe of the ſtream on fuch a body ; and it muſt greatly augment the reſiſtance, that is, the motion loſt by this body in its progrefs through the tenacious fluid : for the body muſt drag along with it this ſtagnant fluid, and drag it in oppoſition. to the tenacity and friction of the ſurrounding fluid. The effect of this is moſt remarkably ſeen in the reſiſtances to the motion of pen-dulums : and the chevalier Boat, in his examination of Newton’s experiments, clearly ſhows that this conſti-tutes the greateſt part of the reſiſtance.</p><p>This moſt ingenious writer has paid great attention to this part of the proceſs of nature, and has laid the foundation of a theory of reſiſtance entirely different from all the preceding. We cannot abridge it ; and it is too imperfect in its preſent condition to be offered as a body βf doctrine : but we hope that the ingenious au-thor wiſl proſecute the ſubject.</p><p>WE cannot conclude this differtation (which we acknowledge to be very unſatisfactory and imperfect) better, than by giving an account of ſome experiments of the chevalier Buat, which ſeem of immenſe conſequence, and tend to give us very new views of the fub-ject. Mr Buat obſerved the motion of water iffuing from a glaſs cylinder through a narrow ring formed by a bottom of ſmaller diameter ; that is, the cylinder was open at both ends, and there was placed at its lower end a circle of ſmaller diameter, by way of bottom, which left a ring all around. He threw ſome powdered ſealing wax into the water, and obſerved with great attention the motion of its ſmall particles. He law thoſe which happened to be in the very axis of the cylinder deſcend along the axis with a motion pretty uniform, till they came very near the bottom from<hi rend="sub">i </hi>this they continued to deſcend very ſlowly, till they were almoſt in contact with the bottom ; they then deviated from the centre, and approached the orifice in.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>