<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fecti¢n of the plane (which we have ealled its baſe), perpendicular to the direction of the ſtream. In AC produced, take any leαgth CG; and on CG deſcribe the ſemicircle CHG, and complete the rectangle BCGO. Through any point p of the curve draw ED parallel to AC, and meeting BC and Ο G in Q_ and P- Let DF touch the curve in D, and draw the chord GH parallel to DF, aud HKM perpendi-cular to CG, meeting ED in M. Suppoſe this to be done for every point of the curve ADB, and let LMN be the curve which paffes through all the points of interſection of the parallels EDP and the correſponding perpendiculars HKM.</p><p>The effective impulſe on the curve furface ADB in the direction of the ſtream, is to its direct impnlſe on the baſe BC as the area BCNL is to the rectangle BCGO.</p><p>Draw <hi rend="italic">edqτnp</hi>  parallel to EP and extremely near it. The arch D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  of the curve may be conceived as the ſection of an elementary plane, having the pofitioπ of the tangent DF. The angle EDF is the angle of in-cidence of the filament ED <hi rend="italic">d e.</hi>  T his is equal to COH, becaufe ED, DF, are parallel to CG, GH ; and (be-caufe CHG is a ſemicircle) CH is perpendicular to GH. Aſſo CG : CH = CH : CK, and CG : CK == CG’ : CH<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, = rad.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  : find, CGH, =rad.<hi rend="sup">i</hi>  : find in-cid. Therefore if CG, or its equal DP, repreſent the direct impulſe on the point Q^of tlie baſe, CK, or its equal QM, will repreſent the effective iιnpulfe on the point D of the curve. And thus, Q y ∕&gt; P will repreſent the direct impulſe of the filament on the element Q 7 of the baſe, and Qjr<hi rend="italic">m</hi>  M will repreſent the effective impulſe of the ſame ſilament on the element D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  of the curve. Aud, as this is true of the whole curve ADB, the effective impulſe on the whole curve will be repreſented by the area BCNML ; and the direct impulſe on the baſe will be repreſented by the rectangle BCGO; and therefore the impulſe on the curve-furface is to the impulſe on the baſe as the area BLMNC is to the rectangle BOGC.</p><p>It is plain, from the conftruction, that if the tangent to the curve at A is perpendicular to AC, the point N will coincide with G. Alſo, if the tangent to the curve at B is parallel to AC, the point L will coincide with B.</p><p>whenever, therefore, the curve ADB is fuch that an equation can be had to exhibit the general relation between the abſciffa AR and the ordinate DR, we ihall deduce an equation which exhibits the relation between the abfciſs CK and the ordinate KM of the curve LMN ; and this will give us the ratio of BLNC to BOGC.</p><p>Thus, if the ſurface is that of a cylinder, fo that the curve BDA <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  (fig. 5.), which receives the impulſe of the fluid, is a ſemicircle, make CG equal to AC, and conftruct the figure as before. The curve BMG is a parabola, whoſe axis is CG, whoſe vertex is G, and whoſe parameter is equal to CG. For it is plain, that CG = DC, and GH = <hi rend="smallcaps">CQ<hi rend="sub">λ</hi>  = MK.</hi>  And CG × GK = GH<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  — KM<hi rend="sup">3</hi>. That is, the curve is ſueh, that the ſquare of the ordinate KM is equal to the rectangle of the abſciffa GK arfd a conftant line GC; and it is.there-fore a parabola whoſe vertex is G. Now, jt iβ well</p><p>known, that the parabolic area BMGC is two thirds of the parallelogram BCGO. Therefore the impull'e on the quadrant ADB is two thirds of the impulfe on the baſe BC. The ſame may bc faid of the quadrant <hi rend="italic">fodb</hi>  and its baſe <hi rend="italic">c b.</hi>  Therefore, <hi rend="italic">The impulſe on</hi>  α <hi rend="italic">cylinder or half cylinder is t wo thirds of the direct impulfe on its tranfverſe plane through the axis ;</hi>  or it is two thirds of the direct impulſe on one ſide of a parallelopiped of thc ſame breadth and height.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Pk,op.</hi>  VI,—If the body be a ſolid generated by the revolution of the figure BDAC (ſig. 4.) round the axis AC ; and if it be expoi¢d to the action of a ſtream <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">q(</hi></hi>  ſiuid moving in the direction of the axis AC; then the effective impulſe in the direction of the ſtream is to the direct impulſe on its baſe, as the ſolid generated by the revolution of the figure BLMNC round the axis CN to the cylinder generated by th¢ revolution of the rectangle BOGC.</p><p>This ſcarcely needs â demonſtration. The figure</p><p>ADBLMNA is a ſection of theſe folids by a plane paſſing through the axis ; and what has been demon-ſtrated of this ſection is true of every other, becauſe they are all equal and ſimilar. It 15 therefore true of the whole ſolids, and (their baſe) the circle generated by the revolution of BC round the axis AC.</p><p>Hence we eaſily deduce, that <hi rend="italic">The impulfe on a ſphere is one half of the direct impulſe on its great circle, or on the bafe of a cylinder of equal diameter.</hi></p><p>For in this caſe the curve BMN (ſig. 5.) which generates the ſolid expreſſiug the impulſe on the ſphere is a parabola, and the ſolid is a parabolic conoid. Now this conoid is to the cylinder generated by the revolution of the rectangle BOGC round the axis CG, as the film of all the circles generated by the revolution of ordinates to the parabola fuch as KM, to the ſum of as many circles generated by the ordinates to the rectangle ſuch as K’ſ; or as the ſum of all the ſquares deſcribed on the ordinates KM to the ſum of as many ſquares deſcribed on the ordinates KT. Draw BG cut-ting MK in S. The ſquare on MK is to the ſquare on BC or TK as the abfcifla GK to the abſciffa GC (by the nature of the parabola), or as SK to BC ; becauſe SK and BCare refpectively equal toGK andGC. 1 herefore the ſum of all the ſquares on ordinates, ſuch as MK, is to the ſum of as many fquares on ordinates, ſuch as TK, as the ſum of all the lines SK to the film of as many lines TK ; that is, as the triangle BGC to the rectangle BOGC ; that is, as one to two : and therefore the impulſe on the ſphere is one half of the direct impulſe on its great circle.</p><p>From the ſame conſtruction we may very eafily deduce a very curious and ſeemingly uſeful truth, that of all conical bodies having the circle whoſe diameter is AB (fig. 2.) for its baſe, and FD for its height, the one which ſuſtains the ſmalleſt impulſe or meets with the ſmalleſt refiſtance is the fruſtum AGHB of a cone ACB ſo conſtructed, that EF being taken equal to ED, EA is equal to EC. This fruſtum, though more capacious than the cone AFB of the ſame height, will be leſs reſiſted.</p><p>Alſo, if the ſolid generated by the revolution of BDAC (ſig. 4.) have its anterior part covered with 3 fruſtum of a cone generated by the lines D <hi rend="italic">a, a A,</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>