<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>markabIe as the body is larger, and eſpecially as it is longer. This may be diſtinctly obſerved. All floating bodies go into the ſtream of the river, becaufe there they find the ſmalleſt obſtruction to the acquiſition of this motion along the inclined plane ; and when a number of bodies are thus floating down the ftream, the largeft and longeft outſtrip the reft. A log of wood floating down in this manner may be obſerved to make its way very faſt among the chips and ſaw-duſt which float a-longſide of it.</p><p>Now when, in the courſe of our experiments, a body is ſupported againſt the action of a ſtream, and the im-pulſe is meaſured by .the force employed to fupport it, it ⅛ plain that part of this force is employed to act againſt that tendency which the body has to outſtrip the ſtream. This does not appear in our experiment, when we move a body with the velocity of this ſtream through ſtill water having a horizontal furface.</p><p>The other diſtinguiſhing circumſtance is, that the re-tardations of a ſtream ariſing from friction are found to be nearly as the velocities, when, therefore, a ſtream moving in a limited canal is checked by a body put in its way, the diminution of velocity occaſioned by the friction of the ſtream having already produced its effect, the impulſe is not affected by it ; but when the body puts the ftill water in motion, the friction of the bottom produces ſome effect, by retarding the receſs of the water. This, however, muſt be next to no-thing.</p><p>The chief difference will ariſe from its being almoſt impoſſible to make an exact compariſon of the veloci-ties : for when a body is moved againſt the ftream, the relative velocity is the ſame in all the filaments. But ■when we expoſe a body to a ftream, the velocity of the different filaments is not the ſame ; becauſe it decreaſes from the middle of the flream to the ſides.</p><p>Mr Buat found the total ſenſible refιftance of a plate 12 inches ſquare, and meaſured, not by the height of water in the tube of the perforated box, but by weights acting on the arm of a balance, having its centre 15 inches under the ſurface of a ſtream moving three feet per ſecond, to be 19,46 pounds; that of a cube of the ſame dimenfions was 15,22 ; and that of a priſm three feet long was 13,87 ; that of a priſm fix feet long was 14,27. The three ſirſt agree extremely well with the determination of <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">q,</hi>  by the experiments with the perforated box. The total reſiſtance of the laſt was undoubtedly much increaſed by friction, and by the retrograde force of ſo long a priſm floating in an in-clined ſtream. This laſt by computation is 0,223 pounds; this added to <hi rend="italic">h (m</hi>  -j- y), which is 13,59,gives <hi rend="sup">l</hi>3&gt;θ<hi rend="sup">1</hi>, leaving 0,46 for the effect of friction.</p><p>If the ſame reſiſtances be computed on the ſuppoſi-tion that the body moves in ſtill water, in which caſe we have <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  = 1, and <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  for a thin plate = 0,433 » and if <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  be computed for the lengths of the other two bo-</p><p>dies by the formula 1 — L 1,42 +^^7- ; we ſhall get for <hi rend="italic">q    Vs</hi></p><p>the reſiſtances 14,94; 12,22 ; and 11,49.</p><p>Hence Mr Buat concludes, that the reſiſtances in theſe two ſtates are nearly in the ratio of 13 to ιo⅛ This, he thinks, will account for the difference ohſer-ved in the experiments of different authors.</p><p>Mr Buat next endeavours to afeertain the quantity of water which is made to adhere in ſome degree to a</p><p>body which is carried along thro’ ſtill water, or which remains nearly ſtagnant in the midſt of a ſtream. He takes the ſum of the motions in the direction of the ſtream, viz. the ſum of the actual motions of all thoſe particles which have loſt part of their motion, and he divides this ſum by the general velocity of the ſtream. The quotient is equivalent to a certain quantity of water perfectly ſtagnant round the body, without being able to determine this with precilion, he obſerves, that it augments as the reſiſtance diminiſhes ; for in the caſe of a longer body, the filaments are obferved to con-verge to a greater diſtance behind the body. The ſtagnant maſs a-head of the body is more conſtant ; for the deflection and reſiſtance at the prow are obſervcd not to be affected by the length of the body. Mr Buat, by a very nice analyſis of many circumſtances, comes to this conclufion, that the whole quantity of fluid, which in this manner accompanies the ſolid body, re-mains the ſame whatever is the velocity. He might have deduced it at once, from the conſtderation that the curves deſcribed by the filaments are the ſame in all ve-locities.</p><p>He then relates a number of experiments made to ſ certain the abſolute quantity thus made to accompany the body. Theſe were made by cauſing pendulums to oſcillate in fluids. Newton had determined the re-ſiſtances to fuch oſcillation by the diminution of the arches of vibration. Mr Buat determines the quantity of dragged fluid by the increaſe of their duration ; for this ſtagnation or dragging is in fact adding a quantity of matter to be moved, without any addition to the moving force. It was ingeniouſly obſerved by Newton, that the time of oſcillation was not fenſibly affected by the reſiſtance of the fluid : a compenfation, almoſt complete, being made by the diminution of the arches of vihration ; and experiment confirmed this. If, there-fore, a great augmentation of the time of vibration be obſerved, it muſt be afcribed to the additional quantity of matter which is thus dragged into motion, and it may be employed for its meafurement. Thus, let a be the length of a pendulum ſwinging féconds in vacuo, and <hi rend="italic">I</hi>  the length of a ſecond’s pendulum ſwinging in a fluid. Let <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  be the weight of the body in the fluid, and P the weight of the fluid diſplaced by it j. P -j- <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  will ex-</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">P+λ</hi></p><p>preſs its weight in vacuo, and ■ ∙~ will be the ratio p 4. A</p><p>of theſe weights. We ſhall therefore have ■—-    —</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">a</hi>- j ,</hi><hi rend="sup">a</hi>P</p><p><hi rend="italic">I</hi>  and ∕- <hi rend="sub">p+</hi>^.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  P expreſs the ſum of the fluid difp!⅛ced, and the fluid dragged along, <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  being a number greater than unity, to be determined by experiment. The maſs in motion is no longer P -f- <hi rend="italic">p<hi rend="sub">y</hi></hi>  but P 4- <hi rend="italic">η</hi>  P, while its weight in the fluid is ſtill <hi rend="italic">ρ.</hi>  Therefore we nauſt have</p><p><hi rend="italic">, <hi rend="sup">a</hi>P    “_ , _( ∕<hi rend="sup">a</hi> ∖</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">l</hi>~nPJ<hi rend="sub">r</hi>p=</hi>     <hi rend="sup">P</hi>  V~"~<hi rend="sup">1</hi>)'</p><p><hi rend="italic">P <hi rend="sup">+</hi></hi></p><p>A prodigious number of experiments· made by Mr Baat on ſpheres vibrating in water gave values of », which were very conſtant, namely, ſrom 1,5 to 1,7 ; and by conſidering the circumſtances which accompa-nied the variations of <hi rend="italic">n (</hi>  which he found to ariſe chiefly from the curvature of the path deſcribed by the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>