<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tertſt to ſubmit to him : or to iιnprefs the whole with a belief that, weak and pitiful as he himielf may appear, when viewed ſingly in oppoſition to them all, yet by tbe aſſiſtance of ſome awful inviſible beings, his friends and protectors, he is ſo powerful, that any attempts to reſiſt his authority muſt prove preſumptuous folly. Here, then, the aid of religion becomes requiſite. Religious fentiments are the moſt happily calculated to ſerve this purpofe. Scarce ever was there a ſociety formed, a inode of government eſtabliihed, or a code oi laws framed and enacted, without having the religious fentiments of mankind, their notions of the exiſtence of fuperior invιhble beings, and their hopes and fears from thoſe beings, as its fundamental principle. Now, we believe, it is almoſt univerſally agreed, that even the rndeſt form of ſociety is more favourable to the happineſs of mankind, and the dignity ot the human character, than a ſolitary and lavage ſtate.. And if this, with what we have afferted concerning religion as the baſis of civil government, be both granted, it will follow, that even the moſt imperfect religious notions, the moſt fooliih and abſurd rites, and the wildeſt ideas that have been entertained concerning the moral government of the univerſe by ſuperior beings, and a future ſtate of retribution, have been more advantageous than atheιfm to the happinefs and virtue of human life, we have already granted, nor can it be denied, indeed, that many of the religious opinions which prevailed among the ancient heathens, did contribute, in ſome degree, to the depravation ©f their morals : and' all that we argue tor is, that on a comparative view oi the evil and the good which reſulted from them, the latter muſt appear more than adequate to counterbalance the effects of the former.</p><p>But if ſuch be the natural tendency of thoſe principles by which the human heart is made ſuſceptible of re=∙ ligious fentiments, that even enthuſiaſm and abſurd ſuperſtition are productive of beneficial teffects more than iufficient to counterbalance whatever is malignant in their influence on ſociety finely a pure rational religion, the doctrines of which are founded in undeniable truth, and all the obfervances which it enjoins, calculated to promote by their direct and immediate effects ſome uſeful purpoſes, muſt be in a very high degree conducive to the dignity and the happineſs of human nature. Indeed one collateral prooſ ol the truth of any religion, which muſt have very conſiderable weight with all who are not of opinion that the ſyſtem of the univerſe has been produced and hitherto maintained in order and exiſtence by blind chance, will be its having a ſtronger and more direct tendency than others to promote the intereſts of moral virtue and the happineſs of mankind in the preſent life. Even the teſtimony of thoufands, even miracles, prophecies, and the lanction of remote antiquity, will ſcarce have ſuſſicient weight to perfiιade us, that a religion is of divine origin, it its general tendency appear to be rather unfavourable than advantageous to moral virtue.</p><p>III. We ſſiall therefore, in the next place, endeavour to determine, from a comparative view of the effects produced on the character and circumſtances of fociety by the moſt eminent of theſe various ſyſtems of religion which have been in different ages or in different countries eſtabliſſied in the world, how far any cne of them has in this reſpect the advantage over the yeſt <hi rend="italic">; and,</hi>  if the utility of a ſyſtem of religion were to</p><p>be received as a teſt of its truth, what particular fyſtem might, with the beſt reaſon, be received as true, while the reſt were rejected.</p><p>iſt,. The principle upon which we here fet out is, that all, or almoft all, fyſtems of religion with which we are acquainted, whether true or falfe, contribute more or leſs to the welfare of fociety. But as, one field is more fruitful, and one garden leſs overgrown with weeds than another; ſo, in the fame manner, one ſyſtem of religious opinions and ceremonies may be more happily calculated than others to promote the trueſt intereſts of mankind. In oppofition to th∩fe philoſophers who are ſo vehement in their declamations againſt the inequality of ranks, we have ever been of opinion, that refinement and civilization contribute to the hap-pineſs of human life. The character of the ſolitary ſavage is, we are told, more dignified and reſpectabte than that of the philoſopher and the hero, in proportion as he is more independent. He is indeed more independent ; but his independence is that of a ſtone, which receives no nouriſhment from the earth or air, and communicates none to animals or vegetables around it. In point of happineſs, and in point of reſpectability, we cannot hefitate a moment, let philofophers fay what they will, to prefer a virtu-ous<hi rend="sub">i</hi>  enlightened, and poliſhed Briton to any of the rudeſt ſavages, the leaſt acquainted with tbe reſtraints and the ſympathies of ſocial life, that wander through the wild foreſts of the weſtern world. But if we prefer civilization to barbariſm, we muſt admit, that in this view Chriſtianity has the advantage over every other religious ſyſtem which has in any age or country prevailed among men ; for nowhere has civilization and uſeful ſcicnce been carried to ſuch a height as among Chriſtians.</p><p>It is not, indeed, in any confiderable degree that the abſurd ſuperſtitions of thole rude tribes, who can lcarce be laid to be formed into any regular ſociety, can contribute to their happineſs. Among them the faculty ol reaſon is but in a very low ſtate; and the moral principle uſually follows the improvement or the depreſſion ol the reaſoning faculty. Their appetites and merely animal paſſions are almoſt their only principles ot action : their firſt religious notions, if we ſuppoſe them, not to be derived from revelation or tradition, are produced by the operation of gratitude, or grief, or hope,, or fear, upon their imaginations. And to theſe, however wild aud fanciful, it is not improbable that they may owe fome of their earlieſt moral notions. The idea of ſuperior powers naturally leads to the thought that thofe powers have ſome influence on human life, from this they will moſt probably proceed to fancy one fet of actions agreeable, another offenſive, to thoſe beings to whom they believe themſelves ſubject. And this,, perhaps, is the ſirſt diſtinction that favages can be ſup-pofed to form between actions, as right or wrong, to be performed or to be avoided. But if this be the eaſe, we muſt acknowledge that the religious notions of the ſavage, however abſurd, contribute to elevate his character, and to improve his happineſs, when, they call forth the moral principle implanted in his breaſt.</p><p>But iſ the ſocial ſtate be preferable to a ſtate of wild, and ſolitary independence, even the rude fuperſtitions of unenlightened tribes of favages are in another reſpect beneficial to thole among whom they prevail. They</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>