<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>nations, and on the probability that, in the ſtate of fo-ciety in which mankind were during the earlier period of the Jewiſh hiſtory, the Jews, by mixing with other nations, would rather have been themſelves converted to idolatry than have converted idolatrous nations to the worſhip of the true God ; we cannot but be ſatisfied, that even this, however it may at firſt appear, was a benefit, not a diſadvantage ; and in the author of their legiilation wiſdom, not caprice.</p><p>But not only in the diſtinctions of meats, and between clean and unclean animals, does the legiſlator of the Jews appear to have laboured to fix a barrier be-tween them and other nations which might preſerve them from the contagion of idolatry—we ſhall not err, perhaps, if we aſcnbe many particulars of their worſhip to this defign in the inſtitutor. The heathens had gods who preſided over woods, rivers, mountains, and valleys, and to each of theſe they offered ſacrifices, and performed other rites oſ worſhip in a ſuitable place. Sometimes the gr®ve, ſometimes the mountain top, at ■other times the bank oſ the river or the brink of the ſpring, was the ſceae of their devotions. But as the •unity of the divine nature was the truth the moſt ear-neſtly inculcated on the children- of Iſrael ; ſo in order to impreſs that truth on their minds with the more powerful efficacy, they were taught to offer their facri-ſices and other offerings only in one place, the place choſen by the Lord ; and death waβ threatened to thoſe who dared to diſobey the command. To confirm this idea, one of the prophets intimates, that when idolatry ſhould be aboliſhed, the worſhip of God ſhould not be confined to Jeruſalem, but it would then be lawful to worſhip him anywhere.</p><p>The whole inſtitutions and obſervances of the Jewiſh religion appear to have been deſigned and happily calculated to impreſs the minds of the people with veneration and reſpect for the Deity. All the feſtivals which either commemorated ſome gracious diſpenlation ef his providence towards their anceſtors, or ſerved as days of thankſgiving for the conſtant returns of his goodnefs to thoſe who celebrated them, and all the other rites defigned to fortify them againſt idolatry, ſerved at the fame time to impreſs their hearts with awful reverence for the God of Jacob, various other particulars in the inſtitutions of the Jewiſh economy appear to have been directed ſolely to that end. Into the moſt focred place, the Holy of Holies, none but the high prieſt was admitted, and he only once a year. No five was ufed in ſacrifice but what was taken from the altar. Severe puniſhments were on various occafions inflicted on ſuch as preſumed to intermeddle in the ſervice of the foil ctuary in a manner contrary to what the law had directed. All the laws reſpecting the character, tlιe cireumſtances, and the ſervices, of the prieſts and the Levites, appear plainly to have a fimilar ten-dency.</p><p>In compliance with the notions of Deity which naturally prevailed among a groſs and rude people, though •no vifible object of worſhip was granted to the Jews, yet they were allowed in their wanderings through the wilderneſs to have a tabernacle or portable temple, in which the ſovereign oſ the univerſe ſometimes deigned to diſplay ſome rays of his glory. Incapable as they were of conceiving aright concerning the ſpiritual nature and the omniprcſence of the Deity, they might poſſibly have thought Jehovah careleſs and indifferent about them, had they been at no time favoured with a vifible demonſtration of his preſence.</p><p>The ſacrifices in uſe among the Gentiles in their ' worſhip of idols were permitted by the Jewiſh legiſla-tor ; but he directed them to be offered with views very different from thoſe with which the Gentiles ſacri-ficed to their idols. Some of the ſacrifices of the Jewiſh ritual were deſigned to avert the indignation oi the Deity ; ſome to expiate offences and purify the heart ; and all of them to aboliſh or remove idolatry. Lultra-tions or ablutions entered likewiſe into the Jewiſh ritual; but theſe were recommended and enjoined by Moſes for purpofes widely different from thoſe which induced the heathens to place ſo high a value upon them. The heathens practiſed them with magical and fuperſtitious ceremonics ; but in the Jewiſh ritual they were intended limply for the cleanfing away of impurities and pol-lutions.</p><p>The theocratical form of government to which the Jews were ſubject, the rewards which they were ſure of receiving, and the puniſhments which they were equally liable to ſuffer in the preſent life, had a powerful effect to remove ſuperftition and preſerve them from idolatry, as well as to ſupport all the ſocial virtues among them. They were promiſed a numerous offspring, a land flowing' with milk and honey, long life, and victory over their enemies, on the condition of their paying a faithful obedience to the will of their heavenly Sovereign ; plague, famine, diſeaſe, defeats, and death, were threatened as the puniflιments to be inflicted on thoſe who violated his laws 5 and theſe fonctions, it muſt be allowed, were happily accommodated to the genius of a rude and carnal-minded people, attentive only to pre-ſent objects, and not likely to be influenced by remote and ſpiritual conſiderations.</p><p>There were other rites and prohibitions in the Mo-foic law, which appear to have^had but little connection with religion, morals, or policy. Theſe may be more liable to be objected againſt, as adding an unneceſſary weight to a buιden which, though heavy, might yet have been otherwiſe borne in conſideration of the advantages connected with it. Even theſe, however, may perhaps admit oſ being viewed in a light in which they flιall appear to have been in no way unfavourable to the happineſs of tho'ſe to whom they were enjoined. They appear to have had none of them an immoral tendency; all of them had, in all probability, a tendency to re-move or prevent idolatry, or to ſupport, in ſome way or other, the religious and the civil eſtabliſhment to which they belonged.</p><p>From theſe views of the ſpirit and tendency of the Jewiſh religion, we may fairly conclude it to have been happily calculated to promote the welfare of ſociety. In comparing it with other religions, it is neceffary to reflect on the peculiar purpoſes tor which it was given ; that its two principal objects were to preſerve the Jews a ſeparate people, and to guard them againſt the contagion of the ſurrounding idolatry, when theſe things are taken into conlideration, every candid mind acquainted with the hiſtory of ancient nations will readily acknowledge that the whole ſyſtem, though calculated in-deed in a peculiar manner for them, was as happily adapted for the purpoſes for which it had been wifely and graciouſly intended, as it is poffible to imagine any</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>