<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>on the minds of his followers. Paradiſe was to abound with rivers, trees, fruits, and ſhady groves ; wine which would not intoxicate was to be there plentifully ſerved up to believers ; the inhabitants of that happy region were all to enjoy perpetual youth ; and their powers of enjoyment were to be enlarged and invigorated, in order that ſo many fine things might not be thrown away upon them. " Inſtead of inſpiring the bleffed inhabitants of paradiſe with a liberal taſte for harmony and fcience, converſation,and friendſhip (ſays Mr Gibbon), Mahomet idly celebrates tbe pearls and diamonds, the robes of ſilk, palaces of marble, diſhes of gold, rich wines, artificial dainties, numerous attendants, and the whole train of ſenſual luxury.—Seventy two houris, or black-eyed girls of refplendent beauty, blooming youth, virgin purity, and exquifite ſenfibility, will be created for the uſe of the meaneſt believer ; a moment of pleaſure will be prolonged for ι ooo years, and his faculties will be increaſed ioo fold, to render him worthy of his felicity.” It muſt be acknowledged that he allows believers other more refined enjoyments than theſe ; thus they are to ſee the face of God morn-ing and evening ; a pleaſure which is far to exceed all the other pleaſures of paradiſe. The following is his deſcription of the puniſhments of hell : The wicked are there to drink nothing but boiling ſtinking water ; breathe nothing but hot winds ; dwell for ever in continual burning fire and fmoke ; eat nothing but briars and thorns, and the fruit of a tree that rifeth out of the bottom of hell, whoſe branches reſemble the heads of devils, and whole fruits fiιall be in their bellies like burning pitch.</p><p>All that we can conclude from a general view of the religion of Mahomet, from confidering the character oſ the prophet, er from reviewing the hiſtory of the nations among whom it has been eſtabliſhed, is, that it is one tiffue of abſurdities, with a few truths, however, and valuable precepts incongruouſly intermixed ; that a great part of it is unfavourable to virtuous manners, to wiſe and equal laws, and to the progreſs of knowledge and refinement. It often inculcates in a direct manner ſentiments that are highly immoral ; it fubſtitutes trifling, ſuperſtitious obfervaπces in the room of genuine piety and moral virtue; and it gives ſuch views of futurity as render purity of heart no neceffary qualification for feeing God.</p><p>Surely, therefore, even the deiſt, who rejects all but natural religion, would not hefitate to prefer Chriſtianity, and even Judaiſm, to the religion of Mahomet. Judaiſm, calculated for a peculiar people, was undoubtedly much more fublime and much more happily framed to render that people virtuous and·happy in the·circumſtances in which they were placed; and Chriſtianity we find to be an univerſal religion, ſuited to all circumſtances and to all the ſtages of ſociety, and acting, wherever it is received, with more or lets'force to the ſupport of civil order, virtuous manners, improvement of arts, and the advancement· of fctcnce. However, as Mahometaniſm forms in feme meaſure a regular ſyſtem, as it has borrowed many of the precepts and doctrines of Judaiſm and Chriſtianity, not indeed without corrupting and degrading them; and- as it has contributed conſiderably to the ſupport of civil government, although ⅛ a very imperfect form, in thoſe countries in which ſt has obtained an eſtabliſhment ; for all theſe</p><p>reafons we canaot but give it the preference to the ſu-perſtitions of Paganiſm.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The whole reſult of our inquiries under this article, therefore, is, I. That as man, by the conſtitution of his mind, is naturally fitted for acquiring certain no-tions concerning the exiſtence of invifible, ſuperior be-ings, and their influence on human life ; ſo the reli-gious ideas which we find to have in all ages of the world, and in all the different ſtages of the progteſs of ſociety, prevailed among mankind, appear to have originated partly from the natural exertions of the human imagination, underſtanding, and paſſions, in various cir- ~ cumſtances, and partly from ſupernatural revelation.</hi></p><p>2.    That though religious opinions, together with the moral precepts, and the rites of worſhip connected with them, may appear to have been in numerous inſtances injurious to the virtue and happinefs of ſociety ; yet<hi rend="sub">r </hi>as they have often contributed to lead the mind to form moral diſtinctions, when it would otherwiſe in all probability have been an entire ſtranger to ſuch diſtinctions ; and as they lrave always contributed in an effential manner to the eſtabliſhment and the ſupport of civil government—it muſt therefore be acknowledged that they have always, even in their humbleſt ſtate, ∙ been more beneficial than hurtful to mankind.</p><p>3.    That when the different ſyſtems of religion that have prevailed in the world are comparatively viewed with reſpect to their influence on the welfare of ſociety, we find reaſon to prefer the polytheiſin of the Greeks and Romans to the ruder, wilder, religious ideas and ceremonies that have prevailed among ſavages ; Mahometaniſm, perhaps in ſorne reſpects, to the pol⅛theifm of the Greeks and Romans ; Judaiſin however to Mahometaniſm ; and Chriſtianity to all of them.</p><p>RELIGIOUS, in a general ſenſe, ſomething that relates to religion.—we ſay, a religious life, religious ſociety, &amp;c.—Churches and church-yards^are religious places.—A religious war is alſo called a <hi rend="italic">croifade.</hi>  See ’ Croisade.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Religious, is alſo uſed .ſubſtantially for a perſon engaged by ſolemn vows to the monaſtic life; or a perſon ſhut up in a monaſtery to lead a life of devotion and -auſterity, under ſome rule or inſtitution. The male religious we popularly call </hi><hi rend="italic">monks</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">friars ;</hi>  the female, <hi rend="italic">nuns</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">canonejfes.</hi></p><p>REMBR ANDT (Van Rhin), a Flemiſh painter and engraver of great eminence, was born in 16c6, in a mill upon the banks of the Rhine, from whence he derived his name of <hi rend="italic">Van Rhin.</hi>  This maſter was born -with a creative- genius, which never attained perfection. It was ſaid of him, that he" would have invent" ed painting, if he had not found it already difcovered, without ſtudy, without the aſſiſtance of any maſter, but by his- own inſtinctj he formed rules, and a certain practical method for colouring ; and the mixture produced the defιgκed effect. Nature is not ſet off to the greateſt advantage in his pictures; but there is ſuch. a ſtriking truth and ſimplicity in them,, that his heads, particularly his - portraits, ∙. ſeem animated, and rifing from the canvas. He was fond of ſtrong contraſts of light and fiιade⅛ The light entered in his working-room only by a hole, in- the manner of a camera obſcura, by which he judged with greater certainty of his product</p><p>■ tions... This artiſt conſidered painting like the ſtage,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>