<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>our Lord ſoretels that the third day after his death he ſhall riſe from the grave. Here no place was reſerved ſor deception. The ſect of the Phariſees and the chief prieſts are openly warned and put upon their guard ; and, very fortunately for the cauſe of Chriſtianity, this ſingular prediction was not heard with ſcorn, or indeed, if with ſcorn, it was only affected, we know from the ſentiments expreffed in the council, that our Lord was ſecretly dreaded by the rulers ; that his miracles were far from being diſcredited ; and that his predictions, in their private opinion, were not to be flighted. The means accordingly which they employed to prevent, even in the very appearance, the completion of his prophecy, were admirably calculated to remove the ſcruples of the moſt wary and ſceptical inquirers, if their object was only to ſearch after truth. At the next feſtival of the paſs-over, when the ſcheme of Caiaphas was put in execution, and when it was deemed expedient by the council that he ſhould die, to fave the nation from the jealouſy of the Romans ; as a proof of their ſteady loyalty to Rome he was apprehended, was tried as an enemy to her government, was at laſt condemned upon falſe evidence, and ſuſpended on a croſs until they were fully ſa-tisfied of his death. Even after his death, the fpear of a ſoldier was thruſt into his ſide ; and the water that guſhed out with the blood is a proof to thoſe who are acquainted with the ſtructure and economy of living bodies, that he muſt have been ſome time dead.</p><p>After he was taken down from the croſs, a ſeal was put on the door of the ſepulchre in which he was laid, as the beſt check againſt ſecret fraud ; and a guard of ſoldiers was ſtationed around it, as the beſt ſecurity againſt open violence. In ſpite, however, of all theſe precautions, the prediction was accompliſhed ; the angel of God, deſcending from heaven with a countenance like lightning, and with raiment white as ſnow ; the watch ſhake, and become as dead men ; the earth quakes ; the ſtone is rolled from the mouth of the fe-pulchre ; thç angel fits on it, and our Lord comes forth.</p><p>It was in vain for the Jews to allege that his difciples came in the night, and ſtole him away, while the watch were aſleep. Οηε muſt ſmile at theſe puerile aſ-ſertions. How came the diſciples to know that the watch were aſleep ; or what excuſe had the watch for ſleeping, and incurring a puniſhment which they knew ⅛o be capital in the Roman law ? and how came they, in the name of wonder, to be brought as an evidence for thoſe tranſactions that happened at the time when they were aſleep ?</p><p>whatever credit may be given by modern infidels to this ill-framed ſtory, it is paſt diſpute that it had none •among the Jewiſh rulers at the time that it was current. Not long after our Saviour’s reſurrection, the apoſtles were called before the council, and threatened with death for teaching in the name of Jeſus. Their bold-neſs upon that occaſion was ſo provoking to the rulers, that the threat would have been inſtantly put in execu-tion, had not Gamaliel, a doctor of the law of high re-putation, put them in mind of other impoſtors who had periſhed in their attempts to miſlead the people ; and concluded a very ſenſible ſpeech with thefe remarkable words : " And now, I ſay unto you, refrain from theſe men, and let them alone ; for if this counſel, or this work, be of men, it will come to nought j but <hi rend="italic">if </hi><hi rend="italic">it be</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">of God,</hi>  ye cannot overthrow it, leſt haply ye be found even to light againſt God.” This advice the council followed. But is it poſſible that Gamaliel could have given it, or the council paid the leaſt regard to it, had the ſtory of the diſciples ſtealſhg the body been then credited ? Surely ſome among them would have obſer-ved, that a work or counſel, founded on impoſture and fraud, could not be <hi rend="italic">∕uppojed to be of God,</hi>  and they .would unqueſtionably have ſlain the apoſtles.</p><p>The ſtory of ſtealing the body is indeed one of the moſt ſenſeleſs fictions that ever was invented in ſupport of a bad cauſe. our Lord was on earth 40 days after he aroſe. He appeared frequently to his diſciples. He ate and drank in their preſence ; atad when ſome of them doubted, he bade them handle him and ſee that he was not a ſpectre, ſhowed the mark of the ſpear in his fide, and the prints of the nails in his feet and hands. Be-ſides thus appearing to his diſciples, he was ſeen by more than 500 brethren at one time ; all of whom, as well as his diſciples, muſt neceffarily have known him previous to his ſuffering, and could therefore atteſt that he was the perſon who was once dead, but was then alive. Yet for ſtrangers in general, who had not ſeen him previous to his death, and could not therefore iden-tify his perfon after he aroſe, our Lord reſerved many other proofs that were equally convincing. Before his aſcenſion, he bade his difciples wait till they received power, by the Holy Ghoſt deſcending upon them : That then they ſhould be witneffes with him, both in Jeruſalem, and in all Judea, and in Samaria, and unto the uttermoft ends of the earth ; in order that the people of all theſe nations, obſerving the miracles wrought in his name, might themſelves become ocular witneffes that thoſe who preached his reſurrection were warranted to do fo by his authority ; and that this au-thority, on which ſo numerous miracles attended, muſt be divine.</p><p>we intend not here to examine the minute objections and cavils that have been advanced reflecting the truth of this important fact. The kinds, however, we ſhall mention iq general. Some have doubted of our Lord’s reſurrection, as being an event which is not confirmed by general experience, becauſe they imagine that what happens once ſhould happen again, and even repeatedly, in order to be true. Some, taking their own to be pre-ferable ſchemes, have objected to the way in which it happened, and to the manner in which it is narrated.—-Some have imagined, that poſſibly the goſpel hiſtory may be falſe ; that poſſibly the diſciples were very ig-norant, and might be deceived ; that poſſibly, too, they were deep politicians, and a ſet of impoſtors ; and that poffιbly the writings which detected their falſehoods may have been deſtroyed. It is difficult to reaſon, and worſe to convince, againſt this evidence of poſſibilities : but we flatter ourſelves, that to the candid reader it will appear ſuſſiciently overturned in our article Miracle; where it is ſhown that neither clowns nor politicians could have a ted the part that was acted by the apoſtles, had not the reſurrection been an undoubted fact.</p><p>Some of the objectors to it have alſo maintained, that poſſibly there is nothing material without us, that there is nothing mental within us, and that poſſibly the whole world is ideas. This mode of arguing we pretend not to explain ; it is thought by ſome to proceed entirely from a perverſeneſs of mind or diſpofition, whiic in books</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>