<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tit&gt;U3 and ignorant. They were, however, paffionately devoted to their monarch, and whatever concerned him. In 1754, when Louis XV. was taken ill at Metz, the whole nation was truly in a kind of deſpair. The cou-rier and his horfe that brought the news of his recovery to Paris were both almoſt ſuffocated by the embraces of the people.</p><p>w^e have faid that the French monarch was deſpo-tic. His power was ſupported by his army and by a watchful police, having in pay an infinite hoſt of ſpies and other ſervants. In France no man was ſafe. The ſecrets of private families were ſearched into. Nothing was unknown to the jealous inquiſition of the police. Men were ſeized by <hi rend="italic">lettres de cachet</hi>  when they leaſt ex-pected it, and their families had no means of diſcovering their fate. The ſentence of a court of law againſt a nobleman was uſually reverfed by the miniſter. No book was publiſhed without the licence of a cenſor-ge-neral appointed by the court, and the miniſter was ac-countable to none but the king. No account was given of the expenditure of thc public money. Enormous gratifications and penfions were given as the reward of the moſt infamous ſervices. The ſupreme power of the ſtate was uſually lodged with a favourite miſtreſs, and ſhe was ſometimes a woman taken from public proſtitution. This was not indeed the cafe under Louis XVI. but it was nevertheless one of the mis-fortunes of his life that he was far from being abſolute in his own family. Still, however, with all its faults, the French court was the moſt ſplendid and poliſhed in Europe. It was more' the reſort of men of talents and literature of every kind, and there they met with more ample protection, than anywhere elſe. The court was often jealous of their productions, but they met with the moſt diſtinguiſhed attention from men of fortune and rank ; inſomuch that for a century ſſaſt the French have given the law to Europe in all queſtions of taſte, of literature, and of every polite accompliſh-ment. The gay elegance that prevailed at court dif-fuſed itſelf through the nation ; and amidſt much internal miſery, gave it to a foreigner the appearance of hap-pineſs, or at leaſt of levity and vanity.</p><p>Such as it was, this government had ſtood for ages, and might have continued, had not a concurrence of cauſes contributed to its overthrow. The inferior orders of clergy, excluded from all chance of preferment, regarded their ſuperiors with jealouſy and envy, and were ready to join the laity of their own rank in any popular commotion. The inferior provincial nobleſſe beheld with contempt and indignation the vices and the power of the courtiers, and the higher nobility wiſhed to diminiſh the power of the crown. The practiſing lawyers, almoſt entirely excluded from the chance of becoming judges, wiſhed eagerly for a change of affairs, not doubting that their talents and profeſſional ſkill would render them neceſſary amidſt any alterations that could occur- Accordingly, they were the firſt inſtruments in producing the. revolution, and have been its moſt active ſupporters. The monied intereſt wiſhed ca-gerly for the downfal of the ancient nobility. As for the great mafs of the common people, they were too ignorant, too firperſtitiouſly attached to old eſtabliſh-wιents, and too much depreſſed, to have any conception of the nature of political liberty, or any hope of obtaining it. we have already ſtated the leading circum-ſtances which led to the French revolution (ſee Franck, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 184, &amp;c. ) ; but there were other circumſtances which contributed in an equal degree both to its commence-ment and its progreſs.</p><p>For 40 years the principles of liberty had been diſſe-minated with eagerneſs in France by ſome men of great talents, as Rouſſeau, Helvetius, and Raynal, to whom the celebrated Montefquieu had led the way. Beſides thefe, there was in France a vaſt multitude of what were called <hi rend="italic">men oſ letters,</hi>  or perſons who gave this account of the manner in which they fpent their time. All theſe were deeply engaged on the fide of ſome kind of political reform. The men of letters in Paris alone are ſaid to have amounted to 20,000. Cue of the laſt acts of the admiiiiſtration of the archbiſhop of Thouloufe was, on the 5th July 1788, to publiſh a refolution of the king in council, inviting all his ſubjects to give him their advice with regard to the ſtate of affairs. This was confidered as a conceſſion of an unlimited liberty of the preſs ; and it is ſcarcely poſſible to form an idea of the infinite variety of political publications which from that period diffuſed among the people a diſſatisfaction with the order of things in which they had hitherto lived.</p><p>The eſtabliſhed religion of France had for fome time paſt been gradually undermined. It had been ſolemnly aſſaulted by philoſophers in various elaborate performances ; and men ©f wit, among ∖vlιom voltaire took the lead, had attacked it with the dangerous weapon of ridicule. The Roman Catholic religion is much expofed in this reſpect, in conſequence of the multitude of falfe miracles and legendary tales with which its hiſtory abounds, without diſcriminating betwixt the refpect-able principles on which it reſts, and the fuperſtitious follies by which they had been defaced, the French nation learned to laugh at the whole, and rejected inſtead of reforming the religion of their fathers. Thus the firſt order in the ſtate had already begun to be regarded as uſeleſs, and the minds of men were prepared for important changes.</p><p>The immenſe population of the city of Paris, amounting to upwards of 800,000 fouls, rendered it an important engine in the hands of the conductors of the revolution. An overgrown capital has always proved dangerous to a government that is or attempts to be deſpotic, as appears ſrom thc hiſtory of ancient Babylon and Rome, as well as of modern Conſtantinople, of London under Charles I. and Paris under ſeveral of its kings.</p><p>we cannot here avoid mentioning a phyfical event, which affiſted not a little in producing many of the convulſions attending the revolution, a general ſcarcity of grain, which occurred about that period. Οη Sun-day the 13thof July 1788, about nine in the morning, without any eclipſe, a dreadful darknefe ’ſuddenly over-fprcad ſeveral parts of France. It was the prelude of ſuch a tempeſt as is unexampled in the temperate climates of Europe, wind, rain, hail, and thunder, feemed to contend in impetuoſity ; but the hail was the great inſtrument of ruin. Inſtead of the rich proſpects of an early autumn, the face of nature in the ſpace of an hour preſented the dreary afpect of ιιniverfal winter. The foil was converted into a morals, the .ſtanding corn beaten into the quagmire, the vines broken to pieces, the fruit trees demoli.ſhed, and unmelted hail ly-iπg in heaps like rocks of fold ice. Even the robcſt</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>