<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ries, feſtorw. foliages, and other ornaments oſ friezes, Demi·relievo"is when one half of the figure riſes from the plane, when, in a baſſo-rehevo, there are parts that ſtand clear out, detached ſrom the reſt, the work is called a <hi rend="italic">demid&gt;∏Jfo,</hi></p><p>In architecture, the relievo or projecture of the orna-ments ought always to be proportioned to the magnitude of the building it adorns, and to the diſtance at which 'it is to be viewed.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Relievo, or </hi><hi rend="italic">Relief,</hi>  in painting, is the degree of bold-nefs with which the figures ſeem, at a due diſtance, to ſtand out from the ground of the painting.</p><p>The relievo depends much upon thc depth of the ſhadow, and the ſtrength of the light ; or on the height of the different colours, bordering on one another ; and particularly on the difference of the colour of the figure from that of the ground : thus, when the light is fo diſpoſed as to make the neareſt paιts of the figure advance, and is well diffuſed on the maiſes, yet infenſibly diminiſhing, and terminating in a large ſpacious ſhadow, brought off inſenſibly, tbe relievo is ſaid to be bold, and the clair obſcure well under-ſtood.</p><p>RELIGION (Rf.ltgio), is a Latin word derived, according to Cicero*,from <hi rend="italic">rc/egere,</hi>  “ to re-confiderſ’but according to Servius and moſt modern grammarians, from <hi rend="italic">relιgare,<hi rend="sup">ti</hi></hi>  to bind faſt. <hi rend="sup">,</hi>  lhe reaſon aſſigned by the Roman orator for deducing<hi rend="italic">religio</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">relego,</hi>  is in theſe words, " qui autem omnia, quæ ad cultum deo-rum pertinerent, diligenter retracterent, et tanquam re-legerent, ſunt dicti <hi rend="italic">relifiοfi</hi>  ex relegendo.” The reaſon given by Servius ſor his derivation of the word is, “ quod mentem religio religet.” If the Ciceronian etymology be the true one, the word <hi rend="italic">religion</hi>  will denote the diligent ſtudy of whatever pertains to the worſhip of the’gods ; but according to the other derivation, which we are inclined to prefer, it denotes that obligation which we feel on our minds from the relation in which we ſtand to feme ſuperior power. In either cafe, the import of the word <hi rend="italic">religion</hi>  is different from that of <hi rend="italic">theology,</hi>  as the former fignifies a number of practical duties, and the latter a ſyſtem of ſpeculative truths. <hi rend="italic">Theology</hi>  is therefore the foundation of <hi rend="italic">religion,</hi>  or the ſcience from which it ſprings ; for no man can ſtudy -what pertains to the worſhip of ſuperior powers Jill he believe that .ſhch powers exiſt, or feel any obligation on his mind from a relation of which he knows nothing.</p><p>This idea ©f religion, as diſtinguiſhed from theo-logy, comprehends the duties not only of thofe more re-fined and complicated ſyſtems of theiſm or polytheiſm which have prevailed among civilized and enlightened nations, ſuch as the polytheiſm of the Greeks and Romans, and the theiſm of the Jews, the Mahometans, and the Chriſtians ; it comprehends every ſentiment of obligation which human beings have ever conceived themſelves under to ſuperior powers, as well as all the forms of worſhip which have ever been practiſed through the world, however fantaſtic, immoral, or abſurd.</p><p>when we turn our eyes to this feature of the human character, we find it peculiarly intereſting. Mankind are diſtinguiſhed from the brutal tribes, and elevated to an higher rank, by the rational and moral faculties with which they are endowed ; but they are ſtiil more widely diſtinguiſhed from the inferior creation, and more highly exalted above them, by being made capable of religious notions and religious ſentiments. The ſlighteſt knowledge of hiſtory is ſufficient to inform us, that religion has ever had a powerful influence in moulding the ſentiments and manners of men. It has ſometimes dignified, and ſometimes degraded, the human character. In one region or age it has been favourable to ci-vilization and refinement ; in another, it has occafionally cramped the genius, depraved the morals, and deform-ed the manners of men. The varieties ot religion are innumerable ; and the members of every diſtinct ſect muſt view all who differ from them as more or leſs miſtaken with reſpect to the moſt important concerns of man. Religion ſeems to be congenial to the heart of man ; for wherever human ſociety ſubſiſts, there we are certain of finding religious opinions and ſentiments.</p><p>It muſt, therefore, be an important fubject of ſpecu-lation to the man and the philoſopher to confider the origin of religion ; to inquire, How far religion in general has a tendency to promote or to injn-e the order and happineſs of ſociety ? and, above all, to examine, what particular religion is beſt calculated to produce an happy influence on human life ?</p><p>ΛVe ſhall endeavour to give a fatisfactory anſwer to each of thefe queſtions, referving to the article Theology the conſideration of the dogmas of that particular religion which, from our preſent inquiries, ſhall appear to be true, and to have the happieſt influence on human life and manners.</p><p>I. The foundation of all religion reſts on the belief of the exiſtence of one or more ſuperior beings, who govern the world, and upon whom the happinefs or mi-ſery of mankind ultimately depends. Οί this belief, as it may be faid to have been univerlal, there ſeem to be but three ſources that can be conceived. Either the image of Deity mnſt be ſtamped on the mind of every human being, the ſavage as well as the fage; or the founders of ſocieties, and other eminent perſons, tracing by the efforts of their own reaſon viſible effects to inviſible caufes, muſt have difcovered the exiſtence of ſuperior powers, and communicated the diſcovery to their aſſociates and fol-lowers ; or, laſtly, the univeτfal belief in ſuch powers muſt have been derived by tradition from a primaeval re-velation, communicated to the progenitors ωf the hu-man race.</p><p>Οηε or other of theſe hypotheſes muſt be true, becaufe a fourth cannot be framed. But we have elſewhere (Polytheism, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 2.) examined the reaſoning which has been employed to eſtabliſh the firſt, and ſhewn that it proceeds upon falſe notions of human nature, we ſhould likewiſe pronounce it contrary to fact, could we believe, on the authority of ſome of its patrons, who are not aſhamed to contradict one another, that the Kamtſchatkans, and other tribes, in the loweſt ſtate of reaſoning and morals, haVe no ideas whatever of Deity. we proceed, therefore, to conſider the ſecond hypotheſis, which is much more plauſible, and will beara ſtricter ſcrutiny.</p><p>That the exiſtence and many oſ the attributes of the Deity are capable of rigid demonſtration, is a truth which cannot be controverted either by the philoſopher or the Chriſtian ; for " the invifible things ot Him from the creation of the world are clearly ſeen, being under-ſtood by the things that are made, even His eternal power and Godhead,” (fee <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi>  Part III.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>