<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>no uΓe. So imperfect is our mathematical knowledge, that even Mr d’Alembert has not been able to exem-plify the application of the equation to the ſimpleſt caſe which can be propoſed, ſuch as the direct impulſe on a plane ſurface wholly immerſed in the ſtuid. All that he is enabled to do, is to apply it (by ſome modifications and ſubſtitutions which take it out of its ſtate of extreme generality) to the direct impulſe of a vein of ſiuid on a plane which deflects it wholly, and thus to ſhow its conformity to the ſolutioh given by Daniel Bernoulli, and to obſervation and experience. He ſhows, that this impulſe (independent of the deficiency arifing from the plane’s not being of infinite extent) is ſomewhat lefs than the weight of a column whoſe baſe is the ſection of the vein, and whoſe height is twice the fall neceffary for communicating the velocity. This great philoſopher and geometer concludes by faying, that he does not believe that any method can be found for ſolving this problem that is more direct and ſimple ; and imagines, that if the deductions from it ſhall be found not to agree with experiment, we muſt give up all hopes of determining the reſiſtance of fluids by theory and analytical calculus. He ſays <hi rend="italic">analytical calculus ; </hi>for all the phyfical principles on which the calculus pro-ceeds are rigorouſly demonſtrated, and will not admit of a doubt. There is only one hypotheſis introduced in his inveſtigation, and this is not a phyſtcal hypothe-ſis, but a hypotheſis of calculation. It is, that the quantities which determine the ratios of the fecond ſiu-xions of the velocities, eſtimated in the directions pa-railel and perpendicular to the axis AC (fig. 16.) are functions of the abſciffa AP, and ordinate PM of the curve. Any perſon, in the leaſt acquainted with mathematical analyſis, will ſee, that without this ſuppoſi-tion no analyſis or calculus whatever can be inſtituted. But let üs ſee what is the <hi rend="italic">phyβcal</hi>  meaning of this hypothecs. It is ſimply this, that the motion of the par-ticle M depends on its ſituation only. It appears im-poſſible to form any other opinion ; and if we could form Juch an opinion, it is as clear as day-light that the caſe is deſperate, and that we muſt renounce all hopes.</p><p>W¢ are forry to bring our labours to this concluſion; but we are of opinion, that the only thing that remains is, for mathematicians to attach themſelves with ſirm-neſs and vigour to fome ſimple cafes ; and, without aiming at generality, to apply Mr d’Alembert’s or Bernoulli’s mode of procedure to the particular circum-ſtances of the cafe. It is not improbable but that, in the ſolutions which may be obtained of theſc particular cafes, circumftances may occur which are of a more ge-neral nature. Theſe will be ſo many laws of hydraulics to be added to our preſent very ſcanty ſtock ; and thele may have points of reſemblance, which will give birth to laws of ſtill greater generality. And we repeat our expreſſion of hopes of ſome ſucceſs, by endea-vouring to determine, in ſome ſimple caſes, the <hi rend="italic">minimum poflibile</hi>  of motion. The attempts of the Jeſuit commentators on the <hi rend="italic">Prindpia</hi>  to aſcertain this on the New-tonian hypotheſis do them honour, anil have really given us great aſſiſtance in thc particular caſe which came through their hands.</p><p>And we ſhould multiply experiments on the reſiſtance of bodies. Thoſe of the French academy are undoubtedly of ineſtimable value, and will always be ap-</p><p>peaied to. But there are circumſtaiices in thofe experiments which render them more complicated than is proper tor a general theory, and which therefore limit the concluſions which we wiſh to draw from them. The bodies Were floating on the ſurface. This greatly modifies the deflections of the filaments of water, cauſing ſome to deflect laterally, which would otherwiſe have remained in one vertical plane ; and this circumſtance alſo neceffarily produced what the academicians callcd the <hi rend="italic">remou,</hi>  or accumulation on the anterior part of the body, and depreſſion behind it. This produced an ad-ditional reſiſtance, which was meaſured with great diffi-culty and uncertainty. The effect of adheſion mull alſo havc been very conſiderable, and very different ill the different caſes ; and it is of difficult calculation. It cannot perhaps be totally removed in any experiment, and it is neceffary to conſider it as making part of the reſiſtance in the moil important practical caſes, viz. the motion of ſhips. Here we ſee that its effect is very great. Every ſeaman knows that the ſpeed, even of a copper-ſheathed ſhip, is <hi rend="italic">greatly</hi>  increaſed bygrealing her bottom. The difference is too remarkable to admit of a doubt : nor ſhould we be ſurpriſed at this, when we attend to the diminution of the motion of water in long pipes. A fmooth pipe four and an half inches diameter, and 500 yards long, yields but one-fifth of the quantity which it ought to do independent of friction. But adheſion does a great deal which cannot be corn-pared with friction, we ſee that water flowing thro’ a hole in a thin plate will be increaſed in quantity fully one-third, by adding a little tube wlioſe length is about twice the diameter of the hole. The adheſion therefore will greatly modify the action of the fila-ments both on the ſolid body and on each other, and will change both the forms of the curves and the velo-cities in different points ; and this is a fort of objec-tion to the only hypotheſis introduced by d'Alembert&gt;, Yet it is only a fort oſ objection ; for the effect of this adheſion, too, mull undoubtedly depend on the fituation of the particle.</p><p>The form of thefe experiments of the academy is ilI-fuited to the examination of the reſiſtance of bodies wholly immerſed in the fluid. The form of experiment adopted by Robins for the reſiſtance of air, and afterwards by the Chevalier Borda for water, is tree from theſe inconveniences, and is ſuſceptible of equal accuracy. The great advantage of both is the exact knowledge which they give us of the velocity of the motion ; a circumſtance effentially ncceffary, and but imperfectly known in the experiments of Mariotte and others, who examined quieſcent bodies expofed to the action oſ a- ſtream. It is extremely difficult to meaſure the velocity of a ſtream. It is very different in its different parts. It is ſwifteft of all in the middle ſuperſi-cial filament, and diminiſhes as we recede from this towards the ſides or bottom, and the rate of diminution is not preciſely known. Could this be afcertained with the neceffary preciſion, we ſhould recommend the fol-lowing form of experiment as the moſt ſtmple, eaſy, eco-Homical, and accurate.</p><p>Let /7, <hi rend="italic">b, c, d,</hi>  (ſig. 19.) be four hooks placed in a horizontal plane at the corners of a rectangular parallelogram, the ſides <hi rend="italic">tιr, Id</hi>  being parallel to the direction of the ſtream ABCD, and "the ſides <hi rend="italic">ab, ai</hi>  being perpendicular to it. Let the body G be fattened to</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>