<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">proportion</hi>  of the direct and oblique refiſtances of plane furſaces, he conſiders the refiſtances to ariſe from mutual colliſions of the furface and fluid, repeated at intervals of time too fmall to be perceived. But in making this compariſon, he has no occaſion whatever to conſi. der this <hi rend="italic">repetition ;</hi>  and when he aſſigns the proportion between the reſiftance of a cone and of its baſe, he, in fact, aſſigns the proportion between two <hi rend="italic">fimultaneous </hi>and inftantaneous impulſes. But the mathematicians who followed him have conſidered this repetition as equivalent to an augmentation of the initial or ſirft im-pulſe ; and in this way have attempted to demonftrate that the reſiſtances are as the ſquares of the velocities, when the velocity is double, each impulſe is double, and the number in a given time is double ; therefore, ſay they, the reſiſtance, and the force which will with-ſtand it, is quadruple ; and obſervation confirms their deduction : yet nothing is more gratuitous and illogi-cal. It is very true that the refiſtance, conceived as Newton conceives it, the loſs of motion ſuſtained by a body moving in the fluid, is quadruple ; but the ſhſtan-taneous impulſe, and the force which can withſtand it, is, by all the laws of mechanics, only double, wha tis the force which can withſtand a double impulſe ? Nothing but a double impulſe. Nothing but impulſe can be oppoſed to impulſe ; and it is a groſs miſconception to think of ſtating any kind of compariſon between im-pulſe and preffure. It is this which has given riſe to much jargon and falſe reaſoning about the force of percuſſion. This is ſtated as infinitely greater than any preffure, and as equivalent to a preffure infinitely repeated. It forced the abettors of theſe doctrines at laſt to deny the exiſtence of all preffures whatever, and to affert that all motion, and tendency to motion, was the reſult of impulſe. The celebrated Euler, perhaps the firſt mathematician, and the loweſt philoſopher, of this century, fays, “ ſince motion and impulfe are ſeen to exiſt, and fince we ſee that by means of motion preſ-ſure may be produced, as when a body in motion ſtrikes another, or as when a body moving in a curved channel preffes upon it, merely in conſequence of its curvilineal motion, and the exertion of a centrifugal force ; and fince Nature is moſt wifely economical in all her operations; it is abſurd to ſuppoſe that preffure, or tendency to motion, has any other origin ; and it is the buſineſs of a philoſopher to diſcover by what motions any obſerved preffure is produced.” whenever any preffure is ob-ferved, iuch as the preffure of gravity, of magnetiſm, of electricity, of condenſed air, nay, of a ſpri'ng, and of elaſticity and cohefιon themſelves, however difparate, nay, oppoſite, the philoſopher muft immediately caſt about, and contrive a ſet of motions (creating <hi rend="italic">pro re natd</hi>  the movers) which will produce a preffure like the one obſerved. Having pleaſed his fancy with this, he cries out ⅛"** “ this <hi rend="italic">will produce</hi>  the preffure;” <hi rend="italic">et frujlra fit per ρlura quod fieri potefi per pauciora, <hi rend="sup">ii</hi></hi>  therefore in this way the preffure <hi rend="italic">is</hi>  produced.” Thus the vortices of Deſcartes are brought back in triumph, and have produced vortices without number, which fill the univerſe with motion and preffure.</p><p>Such bold attempts to overturn long-received doc-trines in mechanics, could not be received without much criticiſm and oppofition ; and many able differtations appeared from time to time in defence of the common doctrines. In conſequence of the many objections to the compariſon of pure preffure with pure percuffion or impulſe, John Bernoulli and others were at laft obli-ged to affert that there were no perfectly hard bodies in nature, nor could be, but that all bodies were elaſtic ; and that in the communication of motion by percuſſion, the velocities of both bodies were <hi rend="italic">gradually</hi>  changed by their mutual elaſticity acting during the finite but imperceptible time of the collifion. This was, in fact, giving up the whole argument, and baniſhing percuſ-fion, while their aim was to get rid of preffure. For what is elafticity but a preffure ? and how ſhall <hi rend="italic">it</hi>  be produced ? To act in this inſtance, muſt it ariſe from a ſtill ſmaller impulſe ? But this will require another ela-fticity, and ſo on without end.</p><p>Theſe are all legitimate conſequences of this attempt to ſtate a compariſon between percuſſion and preffure. Numberleſs experiments have been made to confirm the ſtatement ; and there is hardly an itinerant-lecturing ſhowman who does not exhibit among his apparatus Graveſande’s machine (V0I. I. plate xxxv. fig. 4). But nothing affords ſo ſpecious an argument as the ex-perimented proportionality of the impulſe of fluids to the ſquare oſ the velocity. Here is every appearance of the accumulation of an inſtnity of minute impulſes, in the known ratio of the velocity, each to each, pro-ducing preffures which are in the ratio of the ſquares of the velocities.</p><p>The preffures are obſerved ; but the impulſes or per-cuſſions, whoſe accumulation produces theſe preffures, are only ſuppoſed. The rare fluid, introduced by New-ton for the purpoſe already mentioned, either does not exiſt in nature, or does not act in the manner we have ſaid, the particles making their impulſe, and then eſcaping through among the reſt without affecting their motion. we cannot indeed ſay what may be the proportion between the diameter and the diftance of the particles. The firft may be incomparably ſmaller than the ſecond, even in mercury, the denſeſt fluid which we are familiarly acquainted with ; but although they do not touch each other, they act. nearly as if they did, in conſequence of their mutual attractions and repulfions, we have ſeen air a thouſand times rarer in ſome experi-ments than in others, and therefore the diſtance of the particles at leaſt ten times greater than their diameters ; and yet, in this rare ſtate, it propagates all preſthres or impulſes made on any part of it to a great diſtance, almoft in an inftant. It cannot be, therefore, that fluids act on bodies by impulſe. It is very poſſible to conceive a fluid advancing with a flat iurface againſt the flat ſurface of a ſolid. The very firſt and iuperficial particles may make an impulſe ; and if they were annihi-lated, the next might do the ſame : and if the velocity were double, theſe impulſes would be double, and would be withſtood by a double force, and not a quadruple, a&amp; is obſerved : and this very circumſtance, that a qua-druple force is neceffary, ſhould have made us conclude that it was not to impulſe that this force was oppoſed. The firſt particles having made their ſtroke, and not be-ing annihilated, muſt eſcape laterally. In their efca-ping, they effectually prevent every farther impulſe, becaufe they come in the way of thofe filaments which would have ſtruck the body. The whole proceſs teems to be ſomewhat as follows :</p><p>when the flat ſurface of the fluid has come into con-tact with the plane ſurface AD (fig, 6.), perpendicular</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>