<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the moſt .eaſy is by means of the pentagraph, or paral-klogram ; but this hath its defects. See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Pen-</hi>TAGRAPH.</p><p>The beſt and moſt ufual methods of reduction are as follow: i. To reduce a figure, as ABCDE (n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>ι.), into a lefs compaſs. About the middle of the figure, as z, pitch on a point, and from this point draw lines to its feveral angles A, B, C, &amp;c. then drawing the line<hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  parallel to AB, <hi rend="italic">b c</hi>  parallel to BC, &amp;c. you will have the figure <hi rend="italic">αb e de</hi>  fimilar to ABCDE.</p><p>If the figure <hi rend="italic">abode</hi>  had been required to be enlarged, there needed nothing but to produce the lines from the point beyond the angles, as <hi rend="italic">z</hi>  D, <hi rend="italic">ζ</hi>  C, &amp;c. and to draw lines, viz. DC, CB, &amp;c. parallel to the ſides <hi rend="italic">d c, cb, </hi>&amp;c.</p><p>2.    To reduce a figure by the angle of proportion, ſuppofe the figure ABCDE (n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>2.) required to be diminiſhed in the proportion of the line AB to<hi rend="italic">a b </hi>(n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>3.), draw the indefinite line GH (n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>4.), and frofn G to H ſet off the line AB. Οη G defcribe the arch HI. Set off the line<hi rend="italic">a b</hi>  as a chord on HI, and draw GI. Then with the angle IGH, you have all the meafures of the figure to be drawn. Thus to lay down the point <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  take the interval BC, and upon the point G deſcribe the arch KL. Alſo on the point G deſcribe MN ; and upon A, with the diſtance MN, deſcribe an arch cutting the preceding one in <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>  which will determine the fide <hi rend="italic">b c.</hi>  And after the ſame manner are the other ſides and angles to be deſcribed. The ſame proceſs will alſo ſerve to enlarge the figure.</p><p>3.    To reduce a figure by a ſcale. Meaſure all the fides of the figure, as ABCDE (n<hi rend="sup">0</hi><hi rend="italic">2.}</hi>  by a ſcale, and lay down the ſame meafures refpectively from a fmaller fcale in the proportion required.</p><p>4.    To reduce a map, defign, or figure, by ſquares. Divide the original into little fquares, and divide a freſh paper of the dimenfions required into the ſame number of ſquares, which are to be larger or leſs than the former, as the map is to be enlarged or diminiſhed. This done in every ſquare of the ſecond figure, draw what you find in its correſpondent one in the firſt.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reduction,</hi>  in metallurgy, is the bringing back metalline fubſtances which have been changed into fcoriæ or aſhes, or· otherwiſe diverted of their metallic form, into their natural and original ſtate of metals again. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Metallurgy, </hi><hi rend="italic">I<hi rend="sup">a</hi>Jfi<hi rend="sup">m</hi>  &gt;</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi>  n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>  140.. and 320.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reduction,</hi>  in ſurgery, denotes an operation whereby a diſlocated, luxated, or fractured bone, is reſtored to its former ſtate or place.</p><p>REDUNDANCY, a fault in diſcourſe, conſiſting in the uſe of a ſuperfluity of words, words perfects ly fynonymous are redundant, and ought to be re-trenched.</p><p>REDUNDANT, in muſic. what the French' call <hi rend="italic">we accordfuperflue,</hi>  which we have tranſlated <hi rend="italic">a redundant chord</hi>  in the article Music (from D’Alembert), has by others been rendered <hi rend="italic">a chord extremely ſharp,</hi>  as in the tranſlation of Rameau’s Principle? of Compofi-tion. Their nature will be beſt underſtood by a few examples, and an account of the number of tones, ſemi-tones, or leſſer intervals, contained in each.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">ſecond redundant</hi>  is compofed of a major tone, and a minor ſemitone; as from <hi rend="sub">t</hi>∕α to<hi rend="italic">fil</hi>  ſharp. Its proportion is as 64 to 75«</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">third redundant</hi>  confiſts of two tones and a ſemitone, as <hi rend="italic">fa, la,</hi>  ſharp. Its proportion is as 96 to 125.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">fourth redundant</hi>  is the ſame with the tritone.</p><p>From theſe examples compared with the ſame inter-vals in their natural ſtate, the reader may form a general idea of what is meant by <hi rend="italic">redundant.</hi></p><p>REE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Reis,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Res,</hi>  a little Portugueſe coin. See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Money-Table.</hi></hi></p><p>REED, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Arundo</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Bamboo.</hi></p><p>There are two forts of reeds, ſays Haſſelquiſt, grow-ing near the Nile. Οηε of them has ſcarce any branches ; but is furniſhed with numerous leaves^ which are narrow, ſmooth, channelled on the upper ſurſace ; and the plant is about 11 feet high. The Egyptians make ropes ©f the leaves. They lay them in water like hemp, and then make them into good ſtrong cables. Theſe, with the bark of the date-tree, form almoit tlie only cable uſed in the Nile. The other fort is of great con-ſequence. It is a ſmall reed, about two or three feet high, full branched, with ſhort, ſharp, lancet-ſhaped leaves. The roots, which are as thick as the ſtem, creep and mat themſelves together to a conſiderable dr-ſtance. This plant ſeems uſeleſs in common life : but to it, continues the learned author, is the very foil of Egypt owing : for the matted roots have ſtopped the earth which floated in the waters, and thus formed, out of the ſea, a country that is habitable.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Fire-RKEDs.</hi>  See <hi rend="italic">FiRE-Ship.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reed,</hi>  a term in the weſt of England for the ſtraw uſed by thatchers, which is wheat ſtraw finely combed, conſiſting of ſtiff, unbruiſed, and unbroken ſtalks of great length, carefully ſeparated from the ſtraw uſed for fodder by the threſher, and bound in ſheaves or nitches, each of which weighs 28 lb. and are fold from 21 s. to 31 s. per hundred nitches, according to the ſeaſon. This is a great improvement in the art of thatching, as it gives a finiſh to the work which- cannot be attained by ſtraw, rough and tumbled together, without any ſeparation of the long and ſhort : it alſo is a readier mode of working.</p><p>REEF, a term in ∙ navigation, when there is a great gale of wind, they commonly roll up part of thc ſail below, that by this means -it may become the narrower, and not draw ſo much wind 5 which contract- ■ ing or taking up the fail they call a <hi rend="italic">reef,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">reefing the fail :</hi>  ſo alſo when ,a <hi rend="italic">top-mafi is fprung,</hi>  as they call it, that is, when it is cracked^ or almoſt broken in the cap·, they cut off the.lower piece that was near broken off, and ſetting the other part, now much ſhorter,- in the ſtep again, they call it a <hi rend="italic">reefed top-mafi.</hi></p><p>REEL, in the manufactories, a machine ſerving for·, the office of reeling. There aie various kinds of reels 5 ſome very ſimple, others very complex.</p><p>REELING, in the manufactories, the winding of ſilk, cotton, or the like, into a ſkain, or upon a button, to prevent its entangling. It is· alſo uſed for the changing or diſcharging of bobbins, or quills, to. uſe them in the manufacture of different ſtuffs, as thread, ſilk, cot-ton, &amp;c. Reeling is performed in different ways, and on different engines.</p><p>REEVING, in the fea-language, the putting a rope through a block : hence to pull a rope out of a block is called <hi rend="italic">unreeving.</hi></p><p>RE-EXCHANGE, in commerce, a ſecond payment of the price of exchange, or rather the price of</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>