<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>this notch embraces and preſſes againſt the ſteel arbor (d). This end of the frame may be raiſed or depreſſed by moving the priſmatic ſlide (u), which may be fixed at any height by the four ſteel-ſcrews (v).</p><p>“ The bottom of this ſlide has a notch (k); whoſe pjane is parallel to the endleſs-ſcrew; and by the point of the arbor (d) reſting in this notch, this end of the frame is prevented from tilting. The ſcrew S is pre-vented from unturning, by tightening the finger-nut (w).</p><p>" The teeth on the circumference of the wheel were cut by the following method :</p><p>" Having conſidered what number of teeth on the circumference would be moſt convenient, which in this engine is 2160, or 360 multiplied by 6, I made two ſcrews of the ſame dimenſions, of tempered ſteel, in the manner hereafter deſcribed, the interval between the threads being ſuch as I knew by calculation would come within the limits of what might be turned off the circumference of the wheel : one of theſe ſcrews, which was intended for ratching or cutting the teeth, was notched acroſs the threads, ſo that the fcrew, when preſſed againſt the edge of the wheel and turned round, cut in the manner of a ſaw. Then having a ſegment of a circle a little greater than 60 degrees, of about the ſame radius with the wheel, and the circumference made true, from a very fine centre, I defcribed an arch near the edge, and ſet off the chord of 60 degrees on this arch. This ſegment was put in the place of the wheel, the edge of it was ratched, and the number of revolutions and parts of the ſcrew contained between the interval of the 60 degrees were counted. The radius was corrected in the proportion of 360 revolu-tions, which ought to have been in 60 degrees, to the number actually found ; and the radius, ſh corrected, was taken in a pair of beam∙compaffes : while the wheel was on the lath, one foot of the compaffes was put in the centre, and with the other a circle was de-ſcribed on the ring ; then half the depth of the threads of the ſcrew being taken in dividers, was ſet from this circle outwards, and another circle was deſcribed cutting this point ; a hollow was then turned on the edge of the wheel of the ſame curvature as that of the ſcrew at the bottom of the threads : the bottom of this hollow was turned to the ſame radius or diſtance from the centre of the wheel, as the outward of the two circles before-mentioned,</p><p>" The wheel was now taken off the lath ; and the bell-metal piece D was fcrewed on as before directed, which after this ought not to be removed.</p><p>" From a very exact centre a circle was deſcribed on the ring C, about √⅛∙ of an inch within where the bottom of the teeth would come. This circle was di-vided with the greateſt exactneſs I was capable of, ſirſt into five parts, and each of theſe into three. Theſe parts were then biſected four times : (that is to ſay) ſuppoſing the whole circumference of the wheel t© con-tain 2160 teeth, this being divided into five parts, each would contain 432 teeth; which being divided into three parts, each of them would contain 144 ; and this ſpace biſected four times would givç 72, 36, 18, and $5 ther¢* fore each of the iaſt diviſions would contain nine teeth. But, as I was apprehenſive ſome error might ariſe from quinqueſection and triſcction, in order to examine the accuracy of the diviſions, I deſcribed another circle on the ring C, <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>⅛ inch within the former, and divided it by continual biſections, as 2160, 1080, 540, 270, 135, 67r, and 331 ; and as the fixed wire (to be deſcribed preſently) croſſed both the circles, I could examine their agreement at every 135 revolutions; (after ratching, could examine it at every 33l) : but, not finding any ſenſible difference between the two ſets of diviſions, I, for ratching, made choice of the former ; and,aβ the coincidence of the fixed wire with an interſection could be more exactly determined than with a dot or diviſion, I therefore made uſe of interſections in both circles before deſcribed.</p><p>" The arms of the frame L were connected by a thin piece of braſs of ∣ of an inch broad, having a hole in the middle of √⅛ of an inch in diameter ; acroſs this hole a ſilver wire was fixed exactly in a line to the cen-tre of the wheel ; the coincidence of this wire with thc interſections was examined by a lens <hi rend="sub">x</hi>⅛ inch focus, fixed in a tube which was attached to one of the arms L <hi rend="smallcaps">(a). Now a handle or winch being fixed on the end of the ſcrew, the diviſion marked 10 on the circle K was ſet to its index, and, by means of a clamp and adjuſting ſcrew for that purpoſe, the interſection mark-ed i on the circle </hi>C was ſet exactly to coincide with the fixed wire ; the ſcrew was then carefully preſſed againſt the circumference of the wheel, by turning the finger-ſcrew S ; then, removing the clamp, I turned the ſcrew by its handle 9 revolutions, till the interfec-tion marked 240 came nearly to the wire ; then, un-turning the finger-ſcrew S, I releaſed the ſcrew from the wheel, and turned the wheel back till the interſection marked 2 exactly coincided with the wire, and, by means of the clamp before-mentioned, the diviſion 1 o on the circle being ſet to its index, the ſcrew was preſſed againſt the edge of the wheel by the finger-ſcrew S ; the clamps were removed, and the ſcrew turned nine revolutions till the interſection marked 1 nearly coincided with the fixed wire ; the ſcrew was releaſed from the wheel by unturning the finger-ſcrew S as before, the wheel was turned back till the interſection 3 coincided with the fixed wire; the diviſion 10 on the circle being ſet to its index, the ſcrew was preſſed againſt the wheel as before, and the ſcrew was turned 9 revolutions, till the interſection 2 nearly coincided with the fixed wire, and the ſcrew was releaſed ; and I proceeded in this manner till the teeth were marked round the whole circumference of the wheel. This was repeated three times round, to make the impreffion of the ſcrew deeper. I then ratched the wheel round continually in the ſame direction without ever diſengaging the ſcrew; and, in ratching the wheel about 300 times round, the teeth were finiſhed.</p><p>" Now it is evident, if the circumference of the wheel was even one tooth or ten minutes greater than the ſcrew would require, this error would in the firſt in-</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a) The interſections are marked for the faite of illuſtration, though properly inviſible, they lying under the braſs plate.    </hi><hi rend="sup">6</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>