<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>open offence. The Emperor even prohibited all affem-blages of emigrants within his ſtates ; and the King intimated to the Aſſembly that he had declared to the Elector of Treves, that unleſs the emigrants ſhould ceaſe before tbe 15th of January to make hoſtile preparations within his territories, he would be conſidered as the enemy of France. All this, however, did not preſerve the court from ſuſpicion ; for although the diffe-rent foreign courts had openly declared pacific inten-tions, yet the French emigrants boldly aſſerted, that all Europe was actually arming in their favour. Accordingly they ceaſed not to ſolicit their equals in rank, wlio ſtill remained within tlie country, to leave it to îoin witli tliem in what tliey called the <hi rend="italic">royal cauſe.— </hi>The unhappy Louis, placed between a republican party that was gradually gathering ſtrengtli, and an ariſtocratical party that was rouſing Europe to arms againſt a nation of wliich he was the conſtitutional chief, and a combination of Princes juſtly ſuſpected of wiſhing to ſeize upon a part of his dominions, ſtood in .a ſituation which would have perplexed tlie moſt ſkilful ſtateſman ; and it is no proof of incapacity that he ſell a ſacrifice to circumſtances which miglit have overwhelmed any known meaſure of human ingenuity. Addreffes were crowding into the Aſſembly, diſapproving the conduct of the court. M. Montmorin reſigned ; M. Deleſſart ſucceeded him ; and M. Caluer de Ger-villc became miniſter of the interior. M. du Portail reſigned alfo, and M. Narbonne ſucceeded him as ml-niſter of war. In the month of November, M. Bailly’s mayoralty terminated ; and the once popular La Fayette appeared as a candidate to ſucceed him. But he was ſucceſsfully oppoſed by M. Petion, a violent Jacobin, and a declared republican, who was elected mayor of Paris by a great majority.</p><p>At this period the moderate men, who were friends of the conſtitution, attempted to counteract the influence of the Jacobin club by the eſtabliſhment of a ſi-milar one. It derived its name from the vacant convent of the <hi rend="italic">Feudlans,</hi>  111 whlch lt affembled. ſt he moſt active members of the Conſtituent Affembly belonged to it, ſuch as Μ. M. D’ Andre, Barnave, the Lametbs, Du Port, Rabaud, Sieyes, Chapelier, Thouret, La-bord, Taleyrand, Montefquieu, Beaumetz, &amp;c. The Jacobins contrived to excite a riot at the place of their meeting, which was in the vicinity of the hall of the National Aſſembly. This afforded a pretext for ap-plying to the Affembly for tbe removal of the new clilb. The A ſſembly ſhowed their diſpoſition, by complying with this requeftt</p><p>At the end of this year, the kingdom of France was by no means proſperous. The public revenue had fallen far ſhort of the expenditure. The emigrant no-bility had carried out of the kingdom tbe greater part of the current coin, and a variety of manufacturers, who depended upon their oftentatious luxury, were re-duced to much diſtrefs. The diſpoſitions of foreign courts appeared very doubtful. The new year, how-ever, opened with deluſive proſpects of tranquillity.— The German Princes appeared ſatisfied with the mode of compenfation whieh the French had offered for the loſs of their poffeffions in Alſace and Lorraine. The Prince of Loweſtein accepted of an indemnification.— The Princes of Hohenlohe and Salm-Salm declared themſelves ready to treat upon the ſame terms. Prince</p><lb/><p>Maximilian, and tlie Dukes of wirtemberg and Deux-Ponts, freely ncgociated. It is unneceffary to ftate in detail the ſubterfuges employed, in the mean time, by the crafty Leopold, for amuſing the French with the appearances of peace. M. Deleſſart, miniſter for fo-reign affairs, fell a ſacriſice to them, and probably to the undecided character of Louis. He was accufed by M. Briffot of not having given timely notice to the National Aſſembly of the diſpoſitions of foreign powers, and of not preffing proper meaſures for ſecuring the ho-nour and ſafety of the nation. A decree of accuſation paffed againſt him in his ab fence. He was apprehend-ed, tried by the high national court at Orleans, and executed in conſequence of its ſentence. '</p><p>The ſudden death of Leopold on the ſirſt of March gave riſe to a tranſient hope that peace might ſtill be preſerved. A ſuſpicion of poiſon ſell upon the French, but it was removed by the detail of his diſeaſe that was ſpeedily piibliſhed. On the 16th of the fame month, the King of Sweden was wounded by a nobleman of the name of Ankerſtrom, ftnd died on the 29th. This enterpriſing Prince had overturned the conſtitution of his own conntry, and he had formed the project of con-ducting in perſon his troops to the frontiers of France, and of commanding or accompanying the combined ar-mies of Europe in their attempt to avenge the cauſe of inſulted royalty. It was in a great meaſure to counter-act this ſeheme that he was aſſaffinated.</p><p>The ſudden fall, however, of thefe two enemies rather accelerated than retarded the meditated hoſtilities. The young King of Hungary, who ſucceeded to the empire, made no ſecret either of his own intentions or of the exiſtence of a <hi rend="italic">concert of Princes</hi>  againſt France. M. Dumourier was now at the head of the war-office, M. Rolland was miniſter of the interior, and M. Cla-viere miniſter of finance. The Jacobins were all-powerful. The Court gave way to the torrent. The property of the emigrants was conſiſeated, reſerving the rights of creditors. The Imperial miniſter, Prince Kaunitz, demanded three things of France; <hi rend="italic">lſt,</hi>  Tile reſtitution of their feudal rights to the German Princes; <hi rend="italic">zdly,</hi>  To reſtore Avignon to the Pope, the inhabitants of which had fome time before thrown off their allegiance, and prevailed with the Conſtituent Affembly to receive their country as a part of France ; and <hi rend="italic">laſtly, </hi>Prince Kaunitz demanded, that " the neighbouring powers ſhould have no reaſon for apprehenſion from the preſent weakneſs of the internal government of France.” On receiving thefe demands, the king propoſed a decla-ration of war, which was decreed by the National Aſe ſembly on the 20th of April, againſt <hi rend="italic">the King oſ Hungary and Bohemia.</hi></p><p>The French immediately began the war, by attack-ing in three different columns the Auſtrian Netherlands. M. Theobald Dillon advanced from Liile to Tournay, where he found a ſtrong body of Auſtrians ready to receive him. The national troops, unaccuſtomed to ſuſtain the ſire of regular ſoldiers, were inſtantly thrown into confuſion, and fled even to the gates of Liſie. The cry of <hi rend="italic">treaſon</hi>  refounded on all ſides; and their com. mander, an experienced and faithful officer, was murdered by bis own ſoldiers and the mob. A ſecond diviſion of 10,000 men, under Lieutenant-General Birofi, took poffeffion of Quiverain on the 29th, and marched towards Mons, General Biron was here attacked hy</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>