<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in the neighbourhood of Maeſtricht. On the 15th of September the French attacked the whole Auſtrian poſts in a.k extent of ſive leagues from Liege to Mae* ſtricht. On that and the following day the loſſes were nearly equal. On the 17th the French with 50 pieces of cannon attacked General Kray in his entrenched camp before Maeſtrſcht. M. de Kray was already re-tiring when General Clairfait arrived with a ſtrong <hi rend="italic">re-</hi>inforcement, and after a ſevere combat the French were once more compelled to retire. On the 18th the French renewed the attack with tenfold fury upon every part of the Auſtrian line, and the whole was compelled to fly to the neighbourhood of Aix-la-Cha-pelle. General Clairſait now choſe a ſtrong pofition on the banks <hi rend="italic">of</hi>  the Roer, where he even declared it to be his wiſh that he might be attacked. But by this time the ſpirit of his army was humbled, deſertions became numerous, and the want of diſcipline was extreme. On tlie iſt of October the French croſſed the Maeſe and the Roer, and attacked the whole Auſtrian poſts from Ruremond down to Juliers. After a bloody engagement, the brave and active, though unfortunate, General Clairfait was compelled haſtily to croſs the Rhine, with the lofs of 10 or 1 2,000 men. The French general did not attempt to croſs that river, but one detachment of his army took poſſeſſion of Coblentz, while others laid cloſe ſiege to Venlo and Maeſtricht, which ſoon ſurrendered.</p><p>The diviſion of the French army, in the mean time, under General Pichegru came down upon Holland, and attacked the allied army under the duke of York between Bois-leduc and Grave. They forced the advanced poſt of Boxtel. Lieutenant-general Abercromby was ſent to attempt to recover this poſt on the 15th of September, but he found the French in ſuch force that he was obliged to retreat. Indeed tlie French were difcovered to be no lefs than 80,000 ſtrong in that neighbourhood. The duke of York was unable to contend againſt a for-ce ſo ſuperior, and retired acroſs the Maeſe with the loſs of fomewhat leſs than 1500 men. Pichegru immediately laid ſiege to Bois-le-duc. On the 30th of September, Crevecœur was taken, and bois-leduc ſurrendered in 10 days thereafter. In it 408 French emigrants were taken griſoners ; and theſe, as well as 700 that had been taken at Nieuportf 500 at Sluys, and ι ico at Valenciennes, were all put to death, agreeably tt&gt; the rigorous law formerly made by the convention. The French now followed the duke of York acroſs the Maeſe. Lſpon this the greater part of the allied army under his royal highneſs croſſed the Rhine and took poſt at Arnheim. The remaining part of the army ſol-lewed ſoon after, and Nimeguen was occupied by the French on the 7th of November. The duke of Brunfwick was at this time requeſted to take the command of the allied army, to protect Holland, if poffible. He came to Arnheim forthat purpofe; but after examining the ſtate of things there, he declined the undertaking. The allied troops had now ſo often fled before their victorious and almoſt innumerable enemies, they had ſo often been in want of every neceſſary, and had been received ſo ill by the inhabitants of the countries through which they paſſed, among whom the French cauſe was extremely popular, that they had loſt that regularity of conduct and diſcipline which alone can afford a ſecure proſpect ef Iucceſa in military affaira.</p><lb/><p>The French, on the contrary, well received, nbmſhdlng in every thing, and proud of fighting in a popular cauſe, now acted with much order, and ſubmitted to the ſtricteſt diſeipline. ln addition to all tlieſe advantages, the French leaders had the dexterity to pejſuade the world that new and unknown arts were employed to give aid to their cauſe. At this period the <hi rend="italic">télégraphe</hi>  was ſirſt uſed ſor conveying intelligence from the frontiers to the capital, and from tlie capital to the frontiers. (See Télégraphe). Balloons were alſo uſed by the French during this campaign to procure knowledge of the po-ſition of the enemy. A11 engineer afcended with the balloon, which was ſuffered to riſe to a great height, but prevented from flying away by a long cord. He made plans of the enemies encampment ; and during an attack he ſent down notice of every hoſtile move-ment. In the affairs of men, and more eſpecially in military tranfactions, opinion is of more importance than reality. The French ſoldiers confided in their own officers as men poſſeſſed of a kind of omniſeience, while the allied troops, no doubt, beheld with anxiety a new contrivance employed againſt them, whoſe import-ance would be readily magnified by credulity and ignorance. with all theſe advantages, however, after the capture of Nimeguen, they once more made a halt in their carrier, and abſtained from the attack of Holland, which now ſeemed almoſt proſtrate before them.</p><p>while theſe events occurred in the north, the French arms were fcarcely leſs ſucceſsful on the ſide ef Spain. Bellegarde was taken ; in the weſtern Pyrenees, Fon-tarabia ſurrendered, and alſo St Sebaſtian ; the whole kingdom of Spain ſeemed panic ſtruck. That feeble government, with an almoſt impregnable frontier, and the moſt powerful fortreſſes, could make little reſiſtance ; and the difficult nature of their country was their only protection. The hiſtory of this war is only a hiſtory of victories on the part of the French. In the Eaſtern Pyrenees, on the 17th of November, the French <hi rend="italic">general</hi>  Dugommier was killed in an engagement, in which his army was ſucceſsful. On the 20th of that month the French again attacked the Spaniards, and routed them by meansof the bayonet, without firing a ſingle muſket-ſhot. Tents, baggage, and cannon, for an ar-my of 50,000 men, fell into the hand of the conquerors, along with a great part of the province of Navarre. Towards the end of the year, an army of 40,000 Spa-niards, entrenched behind 80 redoubts, the labour of ſix monthe, ſuffered themſelves to be completely routed ; their general count de La Union was found dead on the field of battle, and the whole Spaniſh artillery was taken. In three days thereafter, the ſort Fernando de Figuieres, containing a garriſon of 9107 men, ſurrendered, although it mounted 171 pieces of cannon, and poſſeſſed abundance of proviſions. The French continued their conqueſts ; Rofas was taken, and the whole province of Catalonia was left at the mercy of the invaders.</p><p>The ſuccefſes of this wonderful campaign were not yet terminated ; and the laſt part of them is perhaps the moſt important, although no great effort was neceffary to its execution. The winter now ſet in with uncom-mon ſeverity. For ſome years paſt the ſeaſons of Eu« rope had been uncommonly mild ; there had been lit-tle froſt in winter, and no intenfe heat in ſummer. But during the late ſeaſon. thc weather had long been re-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>