<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>time as he has becn declared guilty, if it ſhall be deem-ed abfolutely neceffary to arreſt a man, every kind of rigour employed, not neceſſary to ſecure his perſon, ought to be ſeverely repreffed by the law.</p><p>X.    No perfon ſhall be moleſted for his opinions, even ſuch as are religious, provided tliat tlie manifeſtation of thoſe opinions does not diſturb tlie public order eſta-bliſhed by the law.</p><p>XI.    The free communication of thought, and of opinion, is one of the moſt precious rights oſ man. Every citizen, therefore, may freely ſpeak, write, and publiſh, his ſentiments ; ſubject, however, to anſwer for the abuſe of that liberty, in cafes determined by the law.</p><p>XII.    The guarantee of the Rights of Man and Ci-tizens, involves a neceffity of <hi rend="italic">public force :</hi>  this force is then inſtituted for the advantage of all, and not for the particular utility of tliofe to whom it is confided.</p><p>XIII.    For the maintenance of public force, and for tlie expences of adminiſtration, a common contribution is indiſpenſably neceſſary : this contribution ſhould be equally divided amongſt all the citizens, in proportion to their abilities.</p><p>XIV.    Every citizen lias a right, by himſelf, or by his repreſentatives, to decide concerning the neceffity of the public contribution ; to conſent to it freely ; to look after the employment of it ; to determine the quantity, the diſtribution, the collection, and duration.</p><p>XV.    Tlie ſociety has a right to demand from every public agent an account of his adminiſtration.</p><p>XVI.    Every ſociety, in which the guarantee of rights is not affured, nor the ſeparation of powers deter-mined, lias <hi rend="italic">no conßitution.</hi></p><p>XVII.    Property being a right inviolable and ſacred, no perſon can be deprived of it, except when the pub-lic neceffity, legally aſcertained, ſhall evidently require it, and on condition of a juſt and previous·indemniſica-tion.</p><p>The conſtitution guarantees, as natural and civil</p><p>rights,</p><p>1.    That all citizens are admiffible to places and employments without any diſtinction, but that of ability and virtue.</p><p>2.    That all contributions ſhall be divided equally among all the citizens, in proportion to their means.</p><p>3.    That the ſame crimes ſhall be fubject to the ſame puniſhments, without any diſtinction of perſons.</p><p>The conſtitution in like manner guarantees, as natu-ral and civil rights,</p><p>Liberty to all men of going, ſtaying, or departing, without being arreſted, or detained, but according to the forms preſcribed by the conſtſtution.</p><p>Liberty to all men cf fpeaking, writing, printing, and " publiſhing their thoughts, without having their writings ſubjected to any examination or inſpection be-fore publication and of exerciſing the religious wor-ſhip to which they are attached.</p><p>Liberty to all citizens of affembling peaceably, and without arms, complying with tbe laws of police.</p><p>Xſiberty of addreſſmg to all conſtitutional authorities petitions individually ſigned.</p><p>The ccnſtitution guarantees the inviolability of pro-perty, or a juſt and previous indemnity for that of which public neceffity, legally proved, ſhall require tlie ſacriſice«.</p><p>A public inſtruction ſhall be created and organized, common to all citizens, gratuitous with regard to thoſe parts oſ tuition indiſpenſable ſor all men, and of which tile eſtabliſhment ſhall be gradually diſtributed in a pro-portion combined with the diviſion oſ the kingdom. *</p><p>" The kingdom is one and indiviſible;” its territory, ſor adminiſtration, is diſtributed into 83 departments, each department into diſtricts, each diſtrict into cantons.</p><p>Thoſe are French citizens,</p><p>who are born in France, oſ a French ſather ;</p><p>who having been born in France oſ a foreign fa</p><p>ther, have ſixed their reſidence in the kingdom ;</p><p>who having been born in a foreign country, oſ a</p><p>French ſather, have returned to fettle in France, and have taken the civic oath:</p><p>In ſine, who having been born in a foreign country, being deſcended in whatever degree ſrom a Frenchman or a Frenchwoman, who have leſt their country ſrom religious motives, come to reſide in France, and take the civic oath.</p><p>The right oſ French citizenſhip is loſt, iſt, By naturalization in a foreign country ;</p><p>2dly, By being condemned to penalties which involve</p><p>the civic degradation, provided the perſon condemned* be not reinſtated ;</p><p>ßdly, By a ſentenee of contumacy, providéd the fen-tence be not annulled ; .</p><p>4thly, By initiation into any foreign order or body-which ſuppoſes either proofs of nobility " or diſtinctions of birth, or requires religious vows.”</p><p>" The law conſiders marriage only as a civil con-, tract.”</p><p>The ſovereignty is one, indiviſible, " inalienable, and impreſcriptible,” and it belongs to the nation : no-· fection of the people^ or individual, can arrogate the· exerciſe of it.</p><p>The nation, from which alone flow all powers, cannot exercife them but by delegation.</p><p>The French conſtſtution is repreſentative : the repreſentatives arc the legiſſative body and-the king.</p><p>The National Affembly, forming the legiſſative body, is permanent, and conſiſts of one chamber only.</p><p>It ſhall be formed by new elections, every two years»</p><p>The legiſſative body cannot be diffolved by the king.</p><p>The number of reprefentatives to the legiſſative' body ſhall be 745, 011 account of the 83 departments' of which the kingdom is compofed ; and independent, of thoſe that may be granted to the colonies.</p><p>The repreſentatives ſhall be diſtributed among the 83 departments, according to the three proportions or' land, of population, and the contribution direct:</p><p>Of the 745 repreſentatives 247 are attached to the* land. Of tlieſe each department ſhall nominate three,· except the department of Palis, which ſhall nominate only one.</p><p>Two hundred and forty-nine repreſentatives are attached to the population. The total maſs of the active· population of the kingdom is divided into 249 parts, and each department nominates as many of the·, deputies as it contains parts of the population.</p><p>Two hundrcd and forty-nine repreſentatives are at-tachedtothe contribution direct. The ſum total of the direct contribution bf the kingdom is likewiſe divided into 249 parts-; and each department nominates as many deputies as it pays parts of the contribution.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>