<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fèrtation (in the 8th volume of the <hi rend="italic">Com. Petropol.} </hi>on the action and reſiftance of fluids, limited to a very particular caſe ; namely, to the impulfe of a vein of fluid falling perpendicularly on an infinitely extended plane ſurface. This he demonſirates to be equal to the weight of a column ot the fluid whoſe baſe is the area oſ the vein, and whoſe height is twice the fall producing the velocity. Tins demonftration is drawn front the true principles of mechanics and the acknowledged laws of hydraulics, and may be received as a ſtrict phy-flcal demonftration. As it is the only propofition in the whole theory that has as yet received a demonftration acceſſible to readers not verfant in all the refinement of modern analyfis·; and as the principles on which it pro-ceeds will undoubtedly lead to a folution of every pro-blem which can be propoled, once that our mathemati-cal knowledge ſſiall enable us to apply them—we think it our duty to give it in this place, although we muſt acknowledge, that this problem is ſo very limited, that, it will hardly bear an applicatiαn to any caſe that dif</p><p>fers but a little from the expreſs conditions of the pro-blem. 1 here do occur caſes however in practice, where it may be applied to very great advantage.</p><p>Daniel Bernoulli gives two demonſtrations ; one of which may be called a popular one, and the other is more fcientil∣c and introductory to further inveft⅛ιtion. we ſſiall give both.</p><p>Bernoulli firſt determines the whole action exerted m the efflux of the vein of fluid. Suppofe the velocity of efflux <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  is that which would be acquired by falling through the height <hi rend="italic">h.</hi>  It is well known that a body moving during the time of this fall with the velocity <hi rend="italic">v </hi>would deſcribe a ſpace 2 <hi rend="italic">h.</hi>  The effect, therefore, of the hydraulic action is, that in the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi>  of the fall <hi rend="italic">h, </hi>there iffues a cylinder or prifrn of water whoſe baſe is the croſs lection <hi rend="italic">J</hi>  or area of the vein, and whofe length is 2∕&gt;. And this quantity of matter is now moving with the velocity τ&gt;. The quantity of motion, therefore, which is thus produced is 2 <hi rend="italic">s hν ;</hi>  and this quantity of motion is produced in the time Λ And this is the ac-cumulated effect of all the expelling forces, eſtimated in. the direction of the efflux. Now, to compare this with trie exertion oi ſome preſſing power with which we. are familiarly acquainted, let us fuppoſe this pillar 2 <hi rend="italic">s h</hi>  to be frozen, and, being held in the hand, to be dropped. It is well known, that in the time <hi rend="italic">t</hi>  it will fall through the height Z&gt;, and will acquire the velocity</p><p><hi rend="italic">v,</hi>  and now poffeſſes the quantity of motion 2 <hi rend="italic">s h ∙υ_</hi></p><p>and all this is the effect of its weight. The weight, theιefore, of the pillar 2 <hi rend="italic">s h</hi>  produces the ſame effect, and in the ſame time, and (as may eahly be ſeen j in the fame .gιadual manner, with the expelling forces of the fluid in the veffel, which expelling forces ariſe from the preffure of all the fluid in the veffel. Therefore the accumulated hydraulic preffure, by which a vein of a heavy fluid is forced out through an orifice in the bottom or fide oi a veffel, is equal (when eſtimated in thedirec-ι∙ion of the efflux) to the weight of a column of the fluid, having for its baſe the lection of the vein, and twice the fall productive of the velocity of efflux for its height.</p><p>Now let ABDC (fig. 11.) be a quadrangular veffel v. ιth upιight plane fides, in one of which is an orifice EF. From every point of the circumference of this</p><p>orifice, ſuppoſe horizontal lines Ef, F∕, &amp;c. which will mark a fimilar ſurface on the oppofite fide of the veffel. Suppoſe the orifice EF to be ſſiut. There can be no doubt but that the ſurfaces EF and <hi rend="italic">ef</hi>  will be equally preffed in oppofite directions. Now open the orifice EF ; the water will ruſh out, and the preffure on EF is now removed. There will therefore be a tendency in the veffel to move back in the direction E <hi rend="italic">e.</hi>  And this tendency mnſt be preciſely equal and oppofite to the whole effort of the expelling forces. This is a conclu-lion as evident as any propofition in mechanics. It is thus that a gun recoils and a rocket riſes in the air; and on this is founded the operation of Mr Parents or Dr Barker’s mill, defcribed in all treatiſes of mechanics, and moſt learnedly treated by Euler in the Berlin Memoirs.</p><p>Now, let this ſtream of water be received on a circular plane MN, perpendicular to its axis, and let this circular plane be of ſuch extent, that the vein eſcapes from its fides in an infinitely thin ſſieet, the water flowing off in a direction parallel to the plane. The vein by this means will expand into a trumpet-like ſſiape, having curved fides, EKG,FLH. w<hi rend="sub">e</hi> abftract at pre-ſent the action of gravity which would cauſe the vein to bend downwards, and occafion a greater velocity at II than at G ; and we fuppoſe the velocity equal in every point of the circumference. It is plain, that if the action of gravity be neglected after the water has iffued through the orifice EF, the velocity in every point of the circumference of the plane MN will be that of the efflux through EF.</p><p>Now, becauſe EKG is the natural ſſiape affirmed by the vein, it is plain, that if the whole vein were covered by a tube or mouth-piece, fitted to its ihape, and perfectly poliſhed, ſo that the water ſſiall glide along it, without any friction (a thing which we may always iuppoie), the water will exert no preffure whatever on this trumpet mouth-piece. Laftly, let us ſuppoſe that the plane MN is attached to the mouth-piece by ſome bits of wire, lo as to allow the water to eſcape all round ∙ by the narrow chink between the mouth-piece and the plane : We have now a veffel confiſting of the upright</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">K<hi rend="sup">ab</hi>,<hi rend="sup">dc,</hi></hi>  the tr.<hi rend="sup">um</hi>P<hi rend="sup">et</hi>  GKEFLH, and the plane MN ; and the water is eſcaping from every point oſ the circumference of the chink GHNM with the velocity <hi rend="italic">ν.</hi>  If any part of this chink were ſſiut up, there would be a preffure on that part equivalent to the force of efflux from the oppofite parr. Therefore, when all is <hi rend="sup">o</hi>pe∏, thete efforts oi efflux balance each other all round.</p><p>1    here is not therefore any tendency in this compound veffel to move to any fide. . But take away the plane MN, and there would immediately ariſe a preffure in the direction E <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  equal to the weight of the column</p><p>2    j /?. This is therefore balanced by the preffure on the circular plane MN, which is therefore equal to this weight, and the propofition is demonſtrated. "</p><p>A number of experiments were made by Profeffor Kraft at St Peterſhurg, by receiving the vein on a plane MN (hg. <hi rend="smallcaps">ii.)</hi>  which was faſtened to the arm of a balance    having a ſcale R hanging on the oppofite</p><p>arm. I he refiſtance or preffure on the plane was mea-iùred by weights put into the ſcale R; and the velocity of the jet was meaſured by means of the diſtance KR, to which it· fpouted on a horizontal' plane.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>