<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>oſſ the menſtmum, the extract left from the tincture of the Eaſt India rhubarb proved conſiderably the ftrongeſt.</p><p>Rhubarb has been cultivated of late in this country with conſiderable ſucceſs, and for medical purpoſes is ſound to equal that of foreign growth, as is proved hy the Tranſactions of the London Society for encoura-ging Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, who have re-warded ſeveral perſons both for cultivating and curing it. In the Tranſactions ſor 1792, the gold medal was adjudged to Sir william Fordyce, for raiſing from ſeed in the year 1791 upwards oſ 300 plants of the true rhubarb, or rheum palmatum of the London Pharmacopoeia 1788, which in the ſecond and third weeks of October were tranſplanted into a deep loam, at four ſeet diſtance from each other, according to rules laid down by the ſociety. In 1793 it was adjudged to Mr Thomas Jones, from whofe papers we derive the follow-ing information.</p><p>After giving an accurate account of his experiments and obſervations, he concludes, that the ſeaſon ſor ſowing is the ſpring about March or April, or in autumn about Auguſt and September; that thoſe plants which are raiſed in the ſpring ſhould be tranſplanted in autumn, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa ;</hi>  that they cannot have too much room ; that room and time are eſſentially neceffary to their be-ing large, off a good appearance, and perhaps to the in-creaſe of their purgative qualities ; that to effect theſe purpoſes, the foil muſt be hght, loamy, and rich, but not too much ſo, leſt the roots ſhould be too fibrous ; that their ſituation can ſcarcely be too dry, as more ' evils are to be expected from a ſuperabundancy of moiſture than any actual want of it : and laſtly, we may conclude, that in particular the injuries which they are fubject to are principally during their inſancy, and. to be imputed to infects and inattention to the planting ſeaſon ; afterwards, from too great an expoſure to froſt : but that none can be dreaded from heat ; and that in general they are hardy and eaſy of cultivation, when arrived beyond a certain term.</p><p>The method of curing rhubarb, as propoſed by Dr Tirruogel of Stockholm, is as follows: " No roots ſhould be taken up till they have been planted ten years : they ſhonld be taken out of the ground either in winter, before the froſt ſets in, or in the beginning of ſpring, and immediately cut into pieces, and carefully barked ; let them be ſpread upon a table ſor three or four days, and be frequently turned, that the juices may thicken or condenſe within the roots. After this procefs, make a hole in each piece, and put a thread through it ; by which let them hang ſeparately, either within doors, or in ſome ſheltereſt ſhady ſhed. Some perſons dry them in a different way : they incloſe the roots in clay, and make a hole in the clay, about the thickneſs of a gooſe-quill, and in this manner bang up each piece to dry ſeparately, that the moiſture may not evaporate, nor the ſtrength of the root be weakened. But the methods which the Tartars follow is a bad one : they dig the roots out of the deſerts where they grow, bark them, and immediately ſtring them, and hang them round the necks of their camels, that they may dry as they travel ; but this greatly leſſens the medicinal virtue of the root.”</p><p>Mr Thomas Halley of Pontefract in Yorkſhire, to whom the London Society voted the ſilver medal in</p><lb/><p>1793, inſorms us, that his father tried various experiments for curing rhubarb, as waſhing, bruſhing, bark-ing, and peeling, and he dried them in the ſun, on a kiln, in a ſtove, or in a warm kitchen. But of the ſuc-ceſs of all or either of theſe methods we have no ac-count, owing to the death of Mr Halley’s father. He ſent, however,to them ſive different ſpecimens, which the Society acknowledges to be ſuperſor to any rhubarb hitherto cured in England, and produced to them. The roots ſent, Mr Halley ſays, were planted about the year 1781 in a light ſandyiſh foil, but were much neglected. They were taken up in the ſpring of 1792, and being thoroughly diveſted of the adhering earth, were placed for ſome weeks on the floor of a cool ware-houſe : the ſibres were then taken off, cut up, and dried on the flue of a green-llouſe ; but, from miſmanage-ment, were entirely ſpoiled. The prime roots were fevered in ſmall pieces, peeled clean, and thoroughly cleared of every particle of unſoundneſs. Part was ſeparately laid in lieves, and the remainder perforated, ſtrung, and ſuſpended in ſeſtoons from the cieling of a warm kitchen. The manner of dreffing conflits in pa-ring off the external coat with a ſharp knife, as thin and clean as poffible, and then ſiniſhing it off by a piece of ſiſh ſkin, with its own -powder ; wliich powder may be procured from the chips and ſmall pieces, either by grinding or pounding it in a large mortar.</p><p>In the year 1794 the Society adjudged the gold medal to Mr william Hayward of Hanbury, Oxford-ſhire, for propagating rhubarb by offsets taken from the crowns of large plants, inſtead of ſeeds, for the pur-poſe of bringing it to perfection in a ſhorter time, which fully anſwered his expectations. Mr Hayward was a candidate in the year 1789 for the gold medal ; but having miſunderſtood their rules, he was not entitled to it, though with great propriety they voted to him the ſilver medal ; in confequence of which he ſent them his method of culture and cure. His method of cultiva-ting Turkey rhubarb from ſeed is thus explained to the Society : “ I have uſually ſown the feed about the beginning of February, on a bed of good foil (if rather ſandy the better), expoſed to an eaſt or weſt aſpect, in preference to the ſouth ; obſerving a full ſun to be prejudicial to the vegetation of the feeds, and to the plants whilſt young. The ſeeds are beſt ſown moderately thick (broaſhcaſt), treading them regularly in, as ia uſual with parſueps and other light ſeeds, and then ra-king the ground ſmooth. I have ſometimes, when the ſeaſon has been wet, made a bed for ſowing the rhu-barb ſeeds upon, about two ſeet thick, with new dung from · the ſtable, covering it near one foot thick with good foil. The intent of this bed is not for the ſake of warmth, but ſolely to prevent the riſing of earthworms, which, in a moiſt ſeaſon, will frequently deſtroy the young ciop. If the ſeed is good, the plants often riſe too thick ; if ſo, when they have attained ſix leaves they ſhould be taken carefully up (where too cloſe), leaving the ſtanding crop eight or ten inches apart : thoſe taken up may be planted at the ſame diſtance, in a freſh fpot of ground, in order to ſurniſh other plantations. when the plants in general are grown to the ſizc that cabbage-plants are uſually ſet out for a ſtanding crop, they are beſt planted where they are to remain, in beds four feet wide, one row along the middle of the bed, leaving two yards diſtance betwixt the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>