<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>on his journey, the mayor of that city hearing that her majeſty was fending a meffenger into Ireland, and he being a churchman, waited on the Doctor, who in diſcourſe with the mayor taketh out of a cloke-bag a leather box, faying unto him, <hi rend="italic">Here is a commjffton that fijall !afii the Heretics of Ireland,</hi>  calling the Proteſtants by that title. The good woman of the houſe being-well affected to the Proteftant religion, and alſo having a brother named <hi rend="italic">John Edmonds</hi>  of the ſame, then a citizen in Dublin, was much troubled at the Doctor’s words ; but watching her convenient time while the mayor took his leave, and the Doctor complimented him down the flairs, ſhe opens the box, takes the commiſſion out, and places in lieu thereof a ſheet of paper with a pack of cards wrapt up therein, the knave of clubs being faced uppermoſt. The Doctor coming up to his chamber, ſuſpecting nothing of what had been done, put up the box as formerly. The next day going to tbe water.ſide, wind and weather ſerving him, he fails towards Ireland, and landed on the 7th of Gc-tober 1558 at Dublin. Then coming to the eaſtle, the Lord Fitz-AYalters being lord-deputy, ſent for him to come before him and the privy-council ; who, coming in, after he had made a fpeech relating upon what account he came over, he preſents the box unto the lord-deputy ; who cauſing it to be opened, that the .fecretary might read the commiſſion, there was nothing</p><p>ſave a pack of cards with the knave of clubs uppermoſt ; which not only ſtartlcd the lord-deputy and council, but the Doctor, who affured them he had a commiſſion, but knew not how it was gone. Then the lord-deputy made anſwer : Let us have another commiſſion, and we will ſhuffle the cards in the meanwhile. The Doctor being troubled in his mind, went away, and returned into England, and coming to the court obtained another commiſſion ; but flaying for a wind on the water-iide, news came to him that the queen was dead : and thus God preſerved the Proteſtants of Ireland.” Queen Elizabeth was ſo delighted with this ſtory, which was related to her by lord Fitz-walter on his return to England, that file ſent for Elizabeth Edmonds, whoſe huſhand’s name was <hi rend="italic">Matterjhad,</hi>  and gave her a penſion of 40 1. during her life.</p><p>In Scotland, the feeds oſ reformation were very early ſown, by ſeveral noblemen who had reſided in Germany during the religious diſputes there. But ſor many years it was ſuppreffed by the power of the pope, ſeconded by inhuman laws and barbarous executions. The moſt eminent oppoſer of the Papal juriſdiction was John Knox, a diſciple of Calvin, a man of great zeal and invincible fortitude. On all occaſions he raiſed the drooping ſpi-rits of the reformers, and encouraged them to go on with their work notwithſtanding the oppoſition and treachery of the queen-regent; till at laſt, in 1561, by the aſſiſtance of an Engliſh army ſent by Elizabeth, Po-pery was in a manner totally extirpated throughout the kingdom. From this period the form of doctrine, wor-Ihip, and diſcipline eſtabliſhed by Calvin at Geneva, has had the aſcendancy in Scotland. But for an account of the difficulties which the Scottiſh reformers had to ſtruggle with, and the manner ia which theſe were overcome, &amp;c. ſee Scotlanb.</p><p>For further information on the ſubject of the reformation in general, we refer our readers to the works of Burnet and Brandt, to Beauſobre’s <hi rend="italic">Hifloire de la </hi><hi rend="italic">Reformation duns VEmpire, et les Etats de la </hi><hi rend="italic">Conſeſſton</hi></p><lb/><p><hi rend="italic">d'Augfiourg depuis</hi>  1517— 1530, in 4 vols 8vθ, Berlin 1785, and Moſheim’s Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory. . See alſo Sleidan <hi rend="italic">De Statu Religionis</hi>  f⅛<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="italic">Republic# Carolo V. ; Caſaris Commentant ;</hi>  and Father Paul’s Hiſtory oſ the Council of Trent.</p><p>REFRACTION, in general, is the deviation of a moving body from its direct courſe, occaſioned by the different denſity of the medium in which it moves ; or it is a change of direction occaſioned by a body’s falling obliquely out oſ one medium into another. The word is chiefly made uſe of with regard to the rays of light. See 0ptics <hi rend="italic">(Index}</hi>  at <hi rend="italic">Refraction.</hi></p><p>REFRANGTBILITY <hi rend="smallcaps">θf Eight, the diſpoſition of rays to be refracted. ∙ The term is chiefly applied to the diſpolition of rays to produce different colours, according to their different degrees of reſrangibility. See Chromatics and optics </hi><hi rend="italic">paſftm.</hi></p><p>REFRIGERATIVE, in medicyιe, a remedy which reſreſhes the inward parts by cooling them ; as clyſters, ptiſans, &amp;c.</p><p>REFRIGERATORY, in chemiſtry, a veffel filled with cold water, through which the worm paffes in di-Λillations ; the ufe of which is to condenſe the vapours as they paſs through the worm.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Cities of REFUGE, were places provided as </hi><hi rend="italic">Aſy-la,</hi>  for ſuch as againſt their will ſhould happen to kill a man. of thefe cities there were three on each ſide Jordan: on this ſide were Kedeſh of Naphtali, Hebron, and Schechem; beyond Jordan were Bezer, Golan, and Ramoth-Gilead, when any of the Hebrews, or ſtrangers that dwelt in their country, happened to ſpill the^ blood of a man, they might retire thither to be out of the reach of the violent attempts of the relations of the deceaſed, and to prepare for their defence and juſtifica-tion before the judges. Themanſtayer underwent two, trials : ſirſt before the judges of the city of refuge t® which he had fled ; and ſecondly before the judges of his own city. If found guilty, he was put to death-with all the ſeverity of the law. If he was acquitted, he was not immediately ſet at liberty ;L&gt;ut, to inſpire a degree of horror againſt even involuntary homicide, he<hi rend="sup">-</hi>was reconducted to the place of refuge, and obliged to-continue there in a fort of baniſhment till the death of the high-prieſt. If, before this time, he ventured out, the revenger of blood might freely kill him ; but after the high-prieſt’s death he was at liberty to<hi rend="italic">go</hi>  where he pleaſed without moleſtation. It was neceffary that' the perſon. who fled to any of the cſties of refuge ihould underhand ſome trade or calling, that: he might not be burthenſome to the inhabitants. The cities of refuge were required to be well ſupplied' with water and neceffary proviſtons. They were alſo to be of eaſy acceſs, to have good roads leading to them,, with commodious bridges where there was occaſion.. The width of the roads was to be 32 cubits or 48 feet at leaſh It was further required, that at all cioſs-ways direction-polls ſhould be erected, with an inſcriptiom pointing cut the road to the cities of refuge. The 15th of Adar,, which anſwers to our February moon<hi rend="sub">r </hi>was appointed for the city magiſtrates to ſee that the roads were in good condition. No perſon in any of theſe cities was allowed to make weapons, leſt the relations of the deceaſed ſhould be furniſhed with the means-of gratifying their revenge. Deut. xix. 3. iv. 41. 43.;;. Joſh. xx. 7. Three other cities of refuge were conditionally promiſed, butnever granted. See As v <hi rend="smallcaps">l u m.</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>