<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>viour’s ſoul was not to be left in hell 5 and we know that on the day of his crucifixion he went not to hea-veil : for after he had riſen from the place of the dead, he forbade one of the women to touch him, as he had not yet aſcended to the Father. Hell, therefore, and paradiſe, continue they, ſeem to be in this paſſage the very ſame thing, the place of the dead ; and our Savi-our’s intention, they add, was not to go to heaven at that time, but to ſhow his victory' over death and the grave, to whoſe power all mankind had become ſub-ject by the diſobedience of their ſirſt parents.</p><p>without pretending to enter into the merits of this difpute, the ingenious Burnet, in his Theory of the Earth, endeavours to prove, upon the authority of the ancient fathers, that paradiſe lies between the earth and the moon ; and the learned Dodwell, on the ſame authority, has made it the common receptacle of fouls till the reſurrection ; but has not told us whether or not they are to be accountable for the actions of this ſeparate exiſtence at the latter day, or are only to be judged according to the deeds that were done in their bodies.</p><p>This notion of a common receptacle has diſpleaſed many. The ſtate of purgation, obſcurely hinted in the doctrines of Pythagoras, and openly avowed by Plato and virgil, has been adopted by the Romiſh divines, who ſupport their opinion on certain obſcure paſſages of ſcripture, which are always of a yielding and a waxen nature, may caſily be twilled to any hypotheſis, and like general lovers efpouſe rather from intereſt than merit.</p><p>It has diſpleaſed others, becauſe they are anxious that the righteous ſhould have a fore-taſte of their joys, and the wicked of their torments, immediately after death, which they infer to be certainly the caſe from the parable of the rich man and Lazarus(u). But to this it is objected, that the rich man is ſuppoſed to be in hell, the place of torments, and that this puniſhment ought not to take place on their own hypotheſis till after the ſentence at the reſurrection.</p><p>Another argument uſed for the intermediate ſtate is the viſion of St John in the Apocalypſe. In this viſion the Evangeliſt faw under the altar the fouls of thoſe that were ſlain for the word of God and for the teſtimo-ny which they held. Their opponents doubt whether theſe viſible fouls were immaterial, as St John heard them cry with a loud voice, and ſaw white robes given unto every one of them. If they had bodies, that circumſtance might chance to prove a refurrection immediately after death, and ſo ſuperſede the general reſurrection at the laſt day.</p><p>while ſuch concluſions as are here drawn ſrom the parable and viſion, ſay the oppoſers of an intermediate confcious exiſtence, imply that the dead are already raifed, and are now receiving the reſpective rewards of their virtues and their crimes ; thoſe who maintain an intermediate ſeparate exiſtence, who ſpeak of the body as a prifon, and of the ſoul as receiving an increaſe of power when freed from the body, are certainly not more than conſiſtent with themſelves, when they think that this foul would derive an advantage from its after union with either a new ſyſtem of matter or the old onc, how-ever much altered. Baxter, they ſay, who ſaw the in-</p><p>conſiſtency, was diſpoſed to reaſon ſomewhat like Æ-neaβ,</p><p>O, Father ! can it be that fouls fublime</p><p>Return to viſit our terreſtrial çlime ?</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ογ that the gett’rous mind, releas’d at death,</hi></p><p>Should covet lazy limbs and mortal breath ?</p><p>In no one inſtance, they continue, have Chriſtiann perhaps more apparently than in this argument wreſted the ſcriptures to their own hurt: by thus raſhly at-temping to accommodate the ſacred doctrines of religion to a preconceived philofophical hypotheſis, they have laid themfelves open to the ridicule of deiſts, and have been obliged, for the fake of confiſtency, either to deny or to ſpeak ſlightingly of the refurrection; which is certainly the ſureſt foundation of their hope, feeing St Paul hath aſſured us, that if there be no reſurrection of the dead, then they which are fallen aſleep in Chriſt are periſhed, and thoſe who ſurvive may eat and drink, and act as they pleafe, for to-morrow they die; and die, too, never to five again.</p><p>Though this reproof may be rather ſevere, we are forry to obferve that there ſeems to havc been fome-times too much reaſon for it. A certain divine J, whoſe piety was eminent, and.whoſe memory we reſpect, having written " An Eſſay toward the proof of a ſeparate State oſ Souls between Death and the Reſurrec -tion, and the Commencement of the Rewards of virtue and vice immediately after death,” has taken this motto, " Becauſe ſentence againſt an evil work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the fons of men is fully ſet in them to do evil.” “ The doctrine, he ſays, of the reſurrection of the body and the conſc-quent ſtates of heaven and of hell, is a guard and motive of divine force, but it is renounced by the enemies of our holy Chriſtianſty ; and ſhould we give up the re-compenfes of ſeparate fouls, while the deiſt denies thc reſurrection of the body, I fear, between both we ſhould fadly enfeeble and expoſe the cauſe of virtue, and leave it too naked and defenceleſs.”</p><p>This author, who wiſhes much that the puniſhment of crimes ſhould follow immediately after death, is of opinion, that if heaven intended to check vice and impiety in the world, it has acted unwiſely, if it really has deferred the puniſhment of the wicked to fo late a pe-riod as the reſurrection. " For ſuch, he obſerves, is the weakneſs and folly of our natures, that men will not be fo much influenced and alarmed by diſtant proſpects, nor fo folicttous to prepare for an event which they ſuppoſe to be fo very far off, as they would for the ſame event if it commences as foon as ever this mortal life expires. The vicious man will indulge his ſenſualities, and lie down to ſleep in death with this comfort, I ſhall take my reſt here for too or 1000 years, and perhaps in all that fpace my offences may be forgotten ; or let the worſt come that can come, I ſhall have a long ſweet nap before my ſorrows begin : and thus the force of divine terrors is greatly enervated by this delay of puniſhment.”</p><p>Thus far our author, who thinks that his hypothe-fis, if not true, is at leaſt expedient, and that from motives of expediency it ought to be inculcated as a doc</p><p>(u) whitby ſhows that this parable was conformable to the notions of the Jews at that time; and even th<hi rend="sup">c </hi>Mahometans, who believe in the reſurrection of the dead, ſuppoſe likewiſe a ſtate ¢f rewards and puniſhments ⅛ the grave.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>