<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Sabbath. The obſervance of the Sabbath, and deteſta-tiυn of idolatrous worſhip, are frequently inculcated together ; and, again, the breach of the Sabbath, and the worſhip of idols, are uſually reprobated at the ſame time. Another good reaſon for the inſtitution of a Sabbath might be, to remind the Jews of their delive-rance from bondage, to inſpire them with humanity to ſtrangers and domeſtics, and to mitigate the rigours of ſervitude.</p><p>The purpoſes for which the other feſtivals of the Jewiſh religion were inſtituted appear alſo of ſuſſicient importance. The great miracle, which, after a ſeries of other miracles, all directed to the ſame end, finally effected the deliverance of the Jews out of Egypt ; and their actualdeparture from that land of ſervitude, might well be commemorated in the feaſt of the paffover. To recal to the minds of poſterity the hiſtory of their anceſtors, to impreſs them with an awful and grateful ſenſe of the goodnefs and greatnefs of God, and to make them think of the purpoſes for which his almighty power had been ſo ſignally exerted, were ſurely good reaions for the inſtitution of ſucſh a feſtival. The feaſt of Pentecoſt celebrated the ſirſt declaration of the law by Moſes, in the ſpace of fifty days after the feaſt of the paffover. It ferved alſo as a day of folemn thankſgiving for the bleſſings of a plenteous harveſt. Οη the feaſt of tabernacles, they remembered the wanderings of their anceſtors through the wilderneſs, and expreffed their gratitude to heaven for the more comfortable circumſtances in which they found themſelves placed. The feaſt of ncw moons ſerved to fix their kalendar, and determine the times at which the other feſtivals were to be celebrated ; on it trumpets were founded, to give public notice of the event which was the cauſe of the feſtival ; no ſervile works were performed, divine fervice was carefully attended, and the firſt fruits of the month were offered to the Lord. The Jewiſh legiila-tor limited his feſtivals to a very fmall number, while the heathens devoted a confiderable part of the year to the celebration of theirs. But we perceive the occaſions upon which the Jewiſh feſtivals were celebrated to have been of ſuitable importance ; whereas thoſe of the heathens were often celebrated on trifling or ridiculous occafions. Piety and innocent recreation ſſiared the Jewiſh feſtival ; the feſtivals'of the heathens were chiefly devoted to debauchery and idleneſs.</p><p>The Hebrews had other ſolemn ſeaſons of devotion beſides the weekly Sabbath and the£e annual feſtivals. Every ſeventh year they reſted from labour: they were then neither to plough, to low, nor to prune; and what-ever the earth produced ſpontaneouſiy that year belonged rather to ſtrangers, orphans, and the poor, than to the proprietors of the ground. Οη this year inſolvent debtors were diſcharged from all debts contracted by purchaſing the neceffaries of life : and the great end of this releaſe from debts contracted during the preceding fix years, appears to have been to prevent the Hebrew from flying to the Gentiles and forſaking his religion when embarraffed in his circumſtances. None but native Iſraelites and proſelytes of righteouſneſs were admitted to this privilege j it was refuſed to ſtrangers, and even to proſelytes of the gate. The jubilee was a feſtival to be celebrated every fiftieth year. It produced the fame effects with the ſabbatical year as to reſt from labour and the diſcharge of debts j with this addition, that on the year of the jubilee ſlaves obtained their freedom, and the lands reverted to the old pro-prietors. Οη the year of the jubilee, as on the ſabba» tical year, the lands were to reſt uncultivated, and law-ſuits were now to terminate. The chief deſign of this inſtitution appears to have been, to preſerve the order of ranks and property originally eſtabliſhed in the Hc-brew ſtate. None but iſraelites or circumciſed coq-verts could enjoy the benefit pf this inſtitution ; nor could even theſe hope to regain their eſtates on the year of the jubilee, if they fold them for any other purpoſe but to ſupply their neceſſities. The law relative to ufury was evidently founded on the ſame plan of polity with reſpect to property. To almoſt any other nation fuch a law, it muſt be confeffed, would have been unſuitable and unjuft : but as the Jews were not de-ſigned lor a trading nation, they could have little occafion to borrow, unleſs to relieve diſtreſs; and as an indulgence to people in fuch circumſtances, the Jew was foi bidden to exact uiury from his brother to whom he had lent money.</p><p>The Jewiſh legiflator, we may well think, would be diſpoſed to adopt every proper method to prevent his nation from tailing away into the idolatry of heathen nations. Probably one reaſon of the diſtinctions between <hi rend="italic">clean</hi>  beaſts which they were permitted to eat, and <hi rend="italic">unclean</hi>  beaſts, the eating of which they were tarn &gt;ſht to conſider as pollution, was to prevent them from con-viyial intercourfe with profane nations, by which they might be ſeduced to idolatry. ∖Ve do not readily ſit down at table with people who are fond of diſhes which we regard with abhorrence. And if the Jews were taught to loathe the ſleſh of ſome of thofe animals which were among the greateſt delicacies of the Gentiles, they would naturally of conſequence avoid fitting down aζ meat with them, either at their ordinary meals or at thoſe entertainments which they prepared in honour of their deities ; and this we may with good reaſon con-ſider as one happy mean to preſerve them from idolatry· Beſides, the Jews were permitted, or rather in-joined, to eat animals which the Gentiles reverenced as ſacred, and from which they religiouſly witlι-lιeld alI violence. Goats, ſheep, and oxen, were worſhipped in Egypt (ſee Polytheism and Pan) ; and ſeveral learned writers are of opinion, that Moſes directed his people to ſacriſice and eat certain of the favourite animals of the Egyptians, in order to remove from their minds any opinions which they might have otherwiſe entertained oſ the ſanctity ot thole pretended deities. Many of the obſervances which Moſes injoined with regard to food, appear to have been intended to inſpire the Iſrael-ιtes with contempt for the ſuperſtitions of the people among whom they had fo long lojourπed∙ Fhey were to kill the animal which the Egyptians worſhipped; to roaſt the ſteſh which that people ate raw j to eat the head, which they never ate ; and to drefs the entrails, which they fet apart for divination. Theſe diſtinctions concurred with the peculiarities of their drefs, language, government, cuſtoms, places, and times of worſhip, and even the natural ſituation of their country, by which they were in a manner confined and fortified on all ſides, to ſeparate them in luch a manner from neighbouring nations, that they might eſcape the infection of their idolatry. And if we reflect both on the deſign for which Providence ſeparated the Iſraelites from other</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>