<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>not to he fitting at the time, he was bound to let the enemy advance without oppoſition till he had convened his orators, diſpcrſed over 24,000 ſquare leagues, and liſtened to their metaphyſical quibbles in Paris.</p><p>On the 19th June, a very ſingular farce was acted in the Aſſembly. A Pruſſian refugee, who called himſelf Anacharſis Clouts, and who was ſtruggling hard to bring himſelf into public notice, on an evening fitting (which, it is to be obſerved, was generally ill attended by the perfons of the higheſt rank), introduced to the Aſſembly a number of perſons dreffed in the different habits of all the different .countries that could he thought of. In a formal harangue, he told the Aſſembly that lie was come, as the <hi rend="italic">orator oſ the human race,</hi>  at the head of the reprefentatives of all nations, to congratulate them upon the formation ©f their new conſtitution. He was anſwered by the Preſident with abundance of ſolemnity, and retired with his motley groupe. This fantaſtical piece of folly, which in any other country than France would ſcarcely, perhaps, have excited a ſmile, was treated by the Aſſembly in a ferions light. Alexander Lameth propoſed, that the figures of different nations exhibited in chains at the feet of Louis XIV. ſhould be dellroyed as an inſult upon mankind. M. Lamhel, a lawyer, at this moment propofed the <hi rend="italic">abolition oſ all hereditary titles.</hi>  He was iιιpported by La Fayette, St Fargeau, and the viſcount de Noailles. The decree was paffed, along with another ſuppreſſing all armorial bearings. It is our intention at preſent rather to ſtate facts than to hazard any political opinion concerning the wiſdom or folly of the tranſactions which we record. It may here, however, be remarked, that no part of the proceedings of the French National Aſſembly was received by perſons of rank upon the Continent of Europe with ſo much indignation as this.— 'I'he feudal ſyſtem had been overturned, and the property of the church wreſted from it, with little comparative notice ; but when thoſe nominal diſtinctions were attacked which antiquity had ſanctioned, and perſonal vanity rendered dear, the ſurrounding nations were inſtantly alarmed, and beheld with terror the levelling precedent, we may likewiſe add, that no part of their proceedings was more inimical to rational and practical freedom. To preferve a perfect equality of ranks is impoffible. In a commercial nation, induſtry will procure wealth, and wealth will every where procure dependents. Now nothing more contributes to keep within ſome tolerable bounds the inſolence of newly acquired wealth, than the rank attached to birth and nobility, which time and prejudice have conſpired to make reſpectable. It is not a little remarkable, that of all the King’s miniſters, Neckar alone, a plebeian, a republican, born and bred in a democracy, adviſed his Majeſty to refuſe his affent to this fooliih decree, as a violent but uſeleſs encroachment upon the prejudices of a powerful order of the ſtate.</p><p>In the mean time, the capital was entirely engroſſed by hurry and buſtle. M. Bailly had propoſed a plan for commemorating the anniverſary of the taking of the Baſtile. It was adopted, becaufe it flattered the vanity of the people, by preſenting them with a fplendid fpectacle in commemoration of their own exertions. —The army had been much diſorganized ; and it was reſolved to attempt to unite all its branches, as well as She whole departments of the ſtatc, ia onc common at-</p><p>tachment to the new order of things, by collecting into one place deputations, for the purpoſe of ſwearing· fidelity to the new conſtſtution. In the middle of the Champ de Mars an altar was erected, at which the civic oath, as it was called, was to be taken. Around the akar an amphitheatre was thrown up capable of containing 400,000 ſpectators; 2000 workmen were employed in this operation ; and the people of Paris, fearing left die plan might not be completed, affiiſted ia the labour. All ranks of perſons, thc nobles, clergy, and even ladies, with the eagerneſs for novelty ſo pe-culiar to that people, united their efforts. Crowds of foreigners as well as natives hurried to the capital to be preſent at this ſolemnſty, which was called the <hi rend="italic">Confederation.</hi>  The long-expected 14th of July at length arrived. At fix o’clock in the morning the prυceffion was aπanged on the Boulevards, and conſiſted of the electors of the city of Paris, the reprefentatives of the commons, the adminiſtrators of the municipality, a bat-talion of children, with a ſtandard, infcribed " The hopes -of the nation deputies from the troops of France wherever quartered, and of every order, along with deputies from all the departments ; to theſe were added immenfe detachments of the military, and of the na<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ional guards, along with an almoſt infinite multitude oſ drums, trumpets, and muſical inſtruments. The pro-ceffion was extremely fplendid, as every diſtrict had its peculiar decorations. The national affembly paffed through a grand triumphal arch, and the king and queen, attended by the foreign miniſters, were placed in a ſuperb box. After a ſolemn invocation to God, the King approached the altar, and, amidſt the deepeſt ſilence, took the following oath : " I the King of the French do ſwear to the nation, that I will employ the whole power delegated to me by the conſtitutional law of the ſtate, to maintain the conſtitution, and enforce the execution of the law.” The preſident of the national affembly then went up to the altar, and took the civic oath, “ I ſwear to be faithful to the nation, the law, and the king ; and to maintain with all my powers the conſtitution decreed by the national affembly, and accepted by the king.” Every member of the affembly handing up, ſaid, “ That I fwear.” La Fayette then advancing, took the oath for himfclf ; the other deputies of the national guards pronouncing after him, " That I ſwear and theſe words were ſolemnly pronounced byevery individual of this immenfe affembly.<hi rend="italic">Te Deum</hi>  was then fung. The performance was ſublime beyond the powers of defcriptiυn. Never perhaps be-fore was there hιch an orcheſtra, or ſuch an audience : their numbers baffled the eye to reckon, and their ſhouts in full chorus rent the ſkies. It is impoffible to enumerate ail the means which were employed to add fpleh-dυr to this day. It ended with a general illumination, and no accident diſturbed the public tranquillity.</p><p>The aſſembly now proceeded in the formation of the conſtitution with conſiderable tranquillity; which, however, was diſturbed by au unhappy event at Nancy. Moil of the officers of the army were unfriendly to the late revolution, and every means had been employed by them to difguſt the loldiers with it. At Nancy., in particular, neceffaries had been &lt;lenied them, and their pay was kept back, under pretence that this was the will of thc national aſſembly. Driven to deſpair, the regiments in garrifon threw off their allegiance, and de-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>