<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>plans readily : he ſhould be the beſt mounted of the whole, in caſe the enemy happen to ſcatter the cſcorte, that he may ſave his works and ideas. See war.</p><p>R.ECORD, an authentic teſtimony in writing, con-tained in rolls of parchment, and preſerved in a court of record. See Court.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Trial by Record,</hi>  a ſpectes of trial which is ufed only in one particular inſtance: and that is where a matter of record is pleaded in. any action, as a fine, a judgment, or the like ; and the oppoſite party pleads, <hi rend="italic">nul tied record,</hi>  that thefe fis no fuch matter of record exiſting.. Upon this, iſſue is tendered and joined in the following form, " and this he prays may be inquired of by the record, and the other doth the like and hereupon the party pleading the record has a day given him to bring it in, and proclamation is made in court for him to " bring forth the record by him in pleading alleged, or elſe he ſhall be condemned and, on his failure, his antagoniſt ſhall have judgment to recover. The trial, therefore, of this iſſue, is merely by the record : for, as Sir Edward Coke obſerves, a record or enrolment is a monument of ſo high· a nature, and im-porteth in itſelf ſnch abſolute verity, that if ſt be pleaded that there is no fuch record, it ſhall not receive any trial by witneſs, jury, or otherwiſe, but only by itſelf. Thus titles of nobility, as whether earl or not earl, ba-ron or not baron, ſhall be tried by the king’s writ or patent only, which is matter of record. Alſo in caſe of an alien, whether alien friend or enemy, ſhall be tried by the league or treaty between his ſovereign and ours; for every league or treaty is of record. And alſo, whether a manor be held in ancient demeſne or not, ſhall be tried by the record of domefday in. the king’s exchequer.</p><p>RECORDER, a perfon whom the mayor and ether magiſtrates of a city or corporation aſſociate to them, for their better direction in matters of juſtice and proceedings in law ; on which account this perſon is generally a counſellor, or other perfon well ſkilled in the law.</p><p>The recorder of London is choſen by the lord mayor and aldermen ; and as he is held to be the mouth of the city, delivers the judgment of the courts there-iu, and records and certifies the city-cuſtoms. See London, n<hi rend="sup">0</hi>38.</p><p>RECOVERY, or <hi rend="italic">Common </hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Recovery,</hi></hi>  in Engliſh law, a ſpecies of aſſurance by matter of record ; concerning the original of which it muſt be remarked, that com-mon recoveries were invented by the eccleſiaſtics to elude the ſtatutes of mortmain (ſee Tail) ; and after-wards encouraged by the ſineſſe of the courts of law in 12 Edward IV. in order to put an end to all fettered iα-heritances, and bar not only eſtates-tail, but alfo all re-mainders and reverſions expectant thereon, we have here, therefore, only to conſider, ſirſt, the <hi rend="italic">nature</hi>  of a common recovery ; apd, ſecondly, its <hi rend="italic">force</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">effect.</hi></p><p>I. A common recovery is a fuit or action, either ac-tual or fictitious : and in it the lands are recovered againſt the tenant of the freehold; which recovery, being a ſuppoſed abjudication of the right, binds all perſons, and veſts a free and abſolute fee-ſimple in the recoverer. To explain this as clearly and conciſely as poſſible, let us, in the ſirſt place, ſuppoſe David Edwards to be tenant of the freehold, and deſirous to fuſſer a common recovery, in order to bar, 'alj entails, remain-</p><lb/><p>ders, and reverſions, and to convey the fame in feeſſimple, to Francis Golding. To effect this, Golding is to bring an action againſt him for the lands ; and he accordingly ſues out a writ called a <hi rend="italic">prœâpe quod reddat,</hi>  becauſe theſe were its initial or moſt operative words when the law-proceedings were in Latin. In this writ the demand-ant Golding alleges, that the defendant Edwards (here called the tenant) has no legal title to the land ; but that he came into poſſeſſion of it after one Hugh Hunt had turned the demandant out of it. The ſubſequent proceedings are made up into a record or recovery roll, in which the writ and complaint of the demandant are ſiiſt recited : whereupon the tenant appears, and calls upon one Jacob Morland, who is ſuppoſed, at the ori-ginal purchaſe, to have warranted the title to the te-riant ; and thereupon he prays, that the ſaid Jacob Morland may be called in to defend the title which he ſo warranted. This is called the <hi rend="italic">voucher,</hi><hi rend="sup">&lt;¢</hi>  vocatio,” or calling of Jacob Morland to warranty ; and Morland is called the<hi rend="italic">vouchee.</hi>  Upon this Jacob Morland, the vouchee, appears, is impleaded, and. defends the title, whereupon Golding the demandant deſires leave of the court to imparl, or confer with the vouchee in private ; which is (as uſual) allowed him. And ſoon afterwards the demandant Goldirtg returns to court ; but Morland the vouchee difappears, or makes default, whereupon judgment is given for the demandant Golding, now call·· ed the <hi rend="italic">recοvεrlr,</hi>  to recover the lands in queſtion againſt the tenant Edwards, who is now the recoveree : and. Edwards has judgment to recover of Jacob Morland lands of· equal value, in recompenſe for the lands ſo warranted by him, and now loſt by his default ; which is agreeable to the doctrine of warranty mentioned in the preceding chapter. This is called the <hi rend="italic">recompenfe, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">recovery-in value.</hi>  But Jacob Morland having no lands of his own,'being uſually the crier of the cour£, who, from being frequently thus vouched, is called the <hi rend="italic">common vouchee,</hi>  it is plain that Edwards has only a nominal 'recompenſe for the lands ſo recovered againſt him by Golding ; which lands are now abſolutely veſt-ed in the ſaid recoverer by judgment of law, and feiiin thereof is delivered by the ſheriſſ of the county. So that this colluſive recovery operates merely in the nature of a conveyance in fee-ſimple, from Edwards the tenant in tail to Golding the purchafer.</p><p>The recovery here deſcribed, is with a ſingle vouch-er only;-'but ſometimes it is with a double, treble, or farther voucher, as the exigency of the cale may require. And indeed it is now uſual always to have a recovery with double voucher at the leaſt : by ſirſt conveying an eſtate of freehold to any indifferent perſon, againſt whom the <hi rend="italic">pradpe</hi>  is brought ; and then he vouches the tenant in tail, who vouches over the common vouchee. For, if a recovery be had immediately againſt tenant in tail, it bars only ſuch eſtate in the premiſes of which he 13 then actually ſeifed ; whereas if the recovery be had againſt another perſon, and the tenant in tail be vouched, it bars every latent right and intereſt which he may have in the" lands recovered. If Edwards therefore be tenant of the freehold in poſſeſſion, and John Barker be tenant in tail in remainder, here Edwards doth ſirſt vouch Barker, and then Barker vouches Jacob Morland the common vouchee ; who is always the laſt perſon vouched, and always makes default ; whereby the de-maπdant Golding recovers the land againſt the tenant</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>