<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>but ſt differs from that bird in many particulars, eſpe-cially in wanting the calloſity on the ſternum, and ſpars on the wing. AVith theſe laſt the-common oſtrich is known to defend itſelf : in defect of them, the one here treated of uſes the feet with ſuch addreſs as to become at once a furious and dangerous· antagoniſt. The fe-male calls its young ones together with a kind of whii-'tling note fomewhat ſimilar to that of a man: when young it is very tame, frequently following the ſirſt creature it meets with. The fleſh of this bird is ſaid to be very unpalatable. It is found in various parts of South America, from Patagonia to Guiana, and is known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Choique.</hi>  "AVe are happy to be able to preſent our readers with an accurate drawing of the bird. See Plate CCCCXXXVII.</p><p>RHEEDIA, in botany: A genus of the monogynia order,· belonging to tbe polyandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking with thoſe of which the order is doubtful. I he corolla is tetrapetalous; there is no-calyx ; and the fruit is a triſpermous berry.</p><p>RHEGIUM (anc. geog.), ſo very ancient a city as to be ſuppoſed to take its name from the violent burſt-ing of the coaſt of Italy from Sicily ; thought to have been formerly conjoined (Mela, Virgil). A city of the Bruttii, a colony of Chalcidians from Euhœa: a ſtrong barrier oppoſed to Sicily (Strabo) ; mentioned by Luke; ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Julium</hi>  (Ptolemy), from afreſh ſupply of inhabitants ſent thither by Auguſtus, after driving Sextus Pompeius out of Sicily (Strabo) ; and thus was in part a colony, retaining ſtill the right of a municipium (Inſcription). The city is now called <hi rend="italic">Reggio,</hi>  in the Farther Calabria.</p><p>RHE 1 MS, a city of France in Champagne, and capital of Rhemois. It is one of the moſt ancient, celebrated, and largeſt places in the kingdom, had an archbiſhop’s ſee, whoſe archbiſhop was duke and peer of. France. It is about four miles in circumference, and contains ſeveral ſine fquares, well-built houſes, and magnificent churches. It had a mint, an univerſity, and ſive abbeys, the moſt famous of which was that of St Remy. There are alſo ſeveral triumphal arches and other monuments of the Romans. It is feated on the river Velie, on a plain ſurrounded by hills, which pro-duce excellent wine. E. Long. 4. 8. N. Lat. 49. 14.</p><p>RHENISH wine, that produced on the hills about Rheims. This wine is much uſed in medicine as a ſohent of mon, for which it is well calculated on ac-count of its acidity. Dr Percival obſerves, that it is the beſt ſolvent of the Peruvian bark ; in which, how-ever, he thinks its acidity has no ſhare, becauſe an ad-dition of vinegar to water does not augment its ſolvent power.</p><p>RHETORES, amongſt the Athenians, were ten in number, elected by lot to plead public cauſes in the ſenate-houſe or affembly. For every cauſe in which they were retained, they received a drachm out of the public money. They were ſometimes called and their fee ™ Συν^ο^ικον. No man was admitted to thls office bciore ne was q o years of age, though others ſay 30. Valour in war, piety to their parents, prudence in their affairs, frugality, and temperance, were neceffary qualifications for tliis office, and every candi-date underwent an examination concerning tlieſe virtues previous to the election. The orators at Rome were not unlike the Athenian rhetores. See Ora-TOR.</p><p>- RHETORIANS, a ſect of heretics in Egypt, ſo denominated from Rhetorius tlieir leader. The di-ſtinguiſhlng tenets of this hereſiarch, as repreſented by Philaſtrius, was, that he approved of all the here-ſies before him, and taught that they were all in the right-<hi rend="sub">τ</hi></p><p>RHETORIC, the art of ſpeaking copiouſſy on any ſubject, with all the advantages of beauty and force. See Oratory.</p><p>RHEUM, a thin ſerous humor, occaſionally oozing out of the glands about the mouth and threat.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rheum, </hi><hi rend="italic">Rhubarb:</hi>  A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the enrteandria claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 12th order, <hi rend="italic">Holora-ceœ.</hi>  There is no calyx ; the corolla is ſexſid and per-ſiftent ; and there is one triquetrous ſeed. There are ſive ſpecies, viz. 1. The rhaponticum, or common rhu-barb, hath a large, thick, fleſhy, branching, deeply-ffriking root, yellowiſh within ; crowned by very large, roundiſh, heart-ſhaped ſmooth leaves, on thick, ſſightly-ſurrowed foot-ſtalks : and an upright ſtrong ſtem, two or three feet high, adorned with leaves ſingly, and terminated by thick cloſe ſpikes of white flowers. It grows » in Thrace and Scythia, but has been long in the Engliſh gardens. Its root affords a gentle purge. It is however of inferior quality to ſome of the following ſorts ; but the plant being aſtringent, its young ſtalks in ſpring, being cut and peeled, are ilfed for tarts.</p><p>2. The palmatum, palmated-leaved true Chineſe rhubarb, hath a thick fleſhy root, yellow within ; crowned with very large palmated leaves, being deeply divided into acuminated ſegments, expanded like an open hand ; upright ſtems, ſive or ſix feet high or more, terminated by large ſpſkes of flowers *. This is now pro</p><p>ved to be the true foreign rhubarb, the purgative qua-lity of which is well known. 3. The compactum, or Tartarian rhubarb, hath a large, fleſhy, branched root, yellow within ; crowned by very large, heart-ſhaped fomewhat lobated, ſharply indented, ſmooth leaves, and an upright large ſtem, five or ſix feet high, garniſhed with leaves ſingly, and branching above ; having all the branches terminated by nodding panicles of white flowers. This has been ſuppoſed to be the true rhubarb ; which, however, though of ſuperior quality to ſome ſorts, is accounted inferior to the rheum palmatum.</p><p>4. The undulatum, undulated, or waved-leaved Chineſe rhubarb, hath a thick, branchy, deep-ſtriking root, yellow within ; crowned with large, oblong, undulate, fomewhat hairy leaves, having equal foot-ſtalks, and an upright firm ſtem, four feet high ; garniſhed with leaves ſingly, and terminated by long looſe ſpikes of whlte flowers, 5. The Arabian ribes, or currant rhu-barb of Mount Libanus, hath a thick fieſhy root, very broad leaves, full of granulated protuberances, and with equal ſoot-ſtalks, and upright ſirm ſtems, three or four feet high, terminated by ſpikes of flowers, ſucceeded by berry-nke ſeeds, being ſurrounded by a purple pulp« All theſe plants are perennial in root, and the leaves and ſtalks are annual. The roots being thick, fleihy, gene-rally divided, ſtrike deep into the ground ; of a browrt-iſh colour without and yellow within : the leaves riſe in the ſpring, generally come up in a large head folded</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>