<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>But ſomething farther may be yet ſaid in defence of this <hi rend="italic">artificial</hi>  delivery, as our author calls it. Is not the movement of any thing, of whatever ſpecies, when dignified or ſolemn, in general of an <hi rend="italic">equable</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">deliberate</hi>  nature (as in the minuet, the military ſtep, &amp;c.) ? And in theatrical declamation, is not the propenſity to introduce this <hi rend="italic">equab!enefs</hi>  ſo ſtrong, that it is almoſt <hi rend="italic">ιm-poflible</hi>  to avoid it wholly, were we ever ſo determined to do it ? If thele two queries be anſwered in the affirmative (as we are perſuaded they will), while the ſirſt ſupports our argument for the <hi rend="italic">propriety</hi>  of the manner of delivery in queſtion, the ſecond diſcovers a kind of ne-<hi rend="italic">cefiity</hi>  for it. And that this manner may be carried a little <hi rend="italic">farther</hi>  in quantity on the <hi rend="italic">fiage</hi>  than is uſual in <hi rend="italic">real life,</hi>  the principle (IV.) of heightening nature will juſtify, provided faſlrion (which has ever fomething to do in theſe articles) give it a fonction ; for the <hi rend="italic">precife </hi>quantity of ſeveral heightenings may be varied by this great legiſlator almoſt at will.</p><p>II. <hi rend="italic">Emphafis.</hi>  As <hi rend="italic">emphafis</hi>  is not a thing annexed to particular words, as <hi rend="italic">accent</hi>  is to ſyllables, but owes its riſe chiefly to the <hi rend="italic">meaning</hi>  of a paffage, and muſt therefore vary its feat according as that meaning varies, it will be neceffary to explain a little farther the general idea given of it above.    ♦</p><p>Οί mart’s ſirſt diſobedience,’ and the fruit Of that forbidden tree, whoſe mortal taſte Brought death into the world, and all our woe, &amp;c. Sing heav’nly muſe, &amp;c.</p><p>Suppoſing, in reference to the above well-known lines, that originally other beings, beſides men, had diſ-obeyed the commands of the Almighty, and that the circumſtance were well known to us, there would fall an <hi rend="italic">emph ιfis</hi>  upon the word <hi rend="italic">man's</hi>  in the ſirſt line, and hence it would be read thus ;</p><p>of <hi rend="italic">man's</hi>  ſirſt diſobedience, and the fruit, &amp;e.</p><p>But if it were a notorious truth, that mankind had tranſgreffed in a peculiar manner more than once, the <hi rend="italic">emphafis</hi>  would fall on <hi rend="italic">firfi,</hi>  and the line be read,</p><p>Οί man’s <hi rend="italic">firfi</hi>  diſobedience, &amp;c.</p><p>Again, admitting death (as was really the caſe). to</p><lb/><p>have been an unheard-of and dreadful puniſhment brought upon man in conſequence of his tranſgreſſion 5 on that ſuppoſition the third line would be read,</p><p>Brought <hi rend="italic">death</hi>  into the world, &amp;c.</p><p>But if we were to ſuppoſe mankind knew there was ſuch an evil as death in other regions, though the place they inhabited had been free from it till their tranſgreſſion ; the line would run thus,</p><p>Brought death into the <hi rend="italic">world,</hi>  &amp;c.</p><p>Now from a proper delivery of the above lines, with regard to any one of the ſuppoſitions we have choſen, out of ſeveral others that might in the ſame manner havc been imagined, it will appear that the <hi rend="italic">emphafis</hi>  they illuſtrate is effected by a manifeſt <hi rend="italic">delay</hi>  in the pronunciation, and a tone ſomething <hi rend="italic">fuller</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">louder</hi>  than is uſed in ordinary ; and that its office is ſolely to determine the meaning of a ſentence with reference to ſomething foid before, preſuppofed by the author as general knowledge, or in order to remove an, ambiguity where a paffage is capable of having more ſenſes given it than one.</p><p>But, ſuppoſing in the above example, that none of the ſenſes there pointed out were preciſely the true one, and that the meaning of the lines were no other than what is obviouſiy ſuggeſted by their ſimple conſtruction; in that cafe it may be aſked, if in reading them there ſſiould be no word dignified with the emphatical accom-panyments above deſcribed ?—The anſwer is, Not one with an emphaſis of the <hi rend="italic">Jame</hi>  kind as that we have juſt been illuſtrating ; yet it is nevertheleſs true, that on hearing theſe lines well read, we ſſiall ſind ſome words, diſtinguiſſied from the reſt by a manner of delivery bordering a little upon it (a). And thefe words will in general be ſuch as ſeem the moſt important in the ſentence, or on other accounts to merit this diſtinction. But as at beſt it only <hi rend="italic">enforces, graces,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">enlivens,</hi>  and not <hi rend="italic">fixes</hi>  the meaning of any paffage, and even caprice and fofliion ( b) have often a hand in determining its place and magnitude, it cannot properly be reckoned an <hi rend="italic">ejfential</hi>  of delivery. However, it is ot too much moment to be neglected by thoſe who would wiſh to be good readers ; and, for the fake of diſtinction, we may not</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi>     The following lines will illuſtrate both theſe kinds of ſtreffes: For, to convey their right meaning, the word any is evidently to be pronounced louder and fuller than thoſe with the accents over them.</p><p>Get wealth and place, if poſſible with grace ;</p><p>If not, by any means get wealth and place. Pope.</p><p>This couplet is accented in the manner we ſind it in the <hi rend="italic">EJfay on Elocution</hi>  by <hi rend="italic">Mafion.</hi>  And if, according to the judgment of this author, the words thus diſtinguiſhed are to have an emphatical ſtrefs, it muſt be of the inferior kind above-mentioned, and which a little farther on we call <hi rend="italic">emphafis of force ;</hi>  while the word any in a different type alone poffeffes the other fort ©f energy, and which is there contradiſtinguiſhed by the term <hi rend="italic">emphafis. ojfinfi-</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi>     Among a number of people who have had proper opportunities of learning to read in the beſt manner it is now taught, it would be difficult to ſind two, who, in a given inſtance, would ufe the <hi rend="italic">emphafis oſ force</hi>  alike<hi rend="sub">ft </hi>either as to place or quantity. Nay ſome ſcarce uſe any at all : and others will not ſcruple to carry it<hi rend="italic">much</hi>  beyond any thing we have a precedent for in common diſcourſe ; and even now and then throw it upon words ſo. very trifling in themſelves, that it is evident they do it with no other view, than for the fake of the <hi rend="italic">variety</hi>  it gives to the modulation.—This practice, like the introduction of diſcords into muſic, may without doubt be indulged now and then ; but were it too frequent, the capital intent of theſe energies would manifeſtly either be deſtroyed or rendered dubious.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>