<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cſ Betignies, now advanced with fnch ſtrength upon ’ Charleroi in the eaſt that its immediate ſali was fear-ed. As this would have enabled the two French ar-mies to encircle the whole of Flanders, the prince of Cobourg advanced to its relief. Charleroi furrendered at diſcretion on the 25th. This circumſtance was not known by the prince of Cobourg when he advanced on the 26th to. attack in their entrenchments the army that covered the ſiege near Fleürus : but the covering army being by this time reinforced by the acceffion of the beſieging army, the aliies were repulſed. Jourdan then drew llis men out of their entrenchments ; and, in his turn, attacked the Auſtrians. Fie was three times re-pulſed, but was at laſt ſucceſaſul : the hffs of the van· quiſhed army is ſaid to have been prodigious ; but no regular accounts of it have been publiſhed. The French unqueſtionably exaggerated their own ſucceſs, when they ſaid that it amounted to 15,000 men.</p><p>The allies now retreated in ali quarters. Nieuport, Oſtend, and Bruges, were taken ; and Tournay, Mons, Oudenarde, and Bruſſels, opened their gates. At this .laſt place tlie French armies of Eaſt and weſt Flan-ders united. Landrecies, Valenciennes, Condé, and Queſnoy, were fruitleisly left with garriſons in them. The allied troops, evacuating Namur, formed a line from Antwerp to Liege to protect the country behind. The French advanced in full force, and attacked ge-neral Clairfait, cut to pieces half the troops that now remained under him, and broke the line. The ah lies retreated before them. The dtike of York was joined' by ſome troops under the earl of Moira that with much , difficulty had made their way to him from Oſtend ; and with thefe and the Dutch troops he retired to the neighbourhood of Bergen-op-zoom and- Breda for the protection of Holland. The prince of Cobourg eva-cuated Liege, croſſed the Mæfe, and placed a garri-ſon in Maeſtricht. He ſoon, however, ſent back a part of his troops to the neighbourhood of Tongres ; for here, to the aſtoniſhment of all Europe, the French armies made a voluntary pauſe in their career of vic-tory, and ceaſed to purſue their retiring foes. Sluys in Dutch Flanders was the only foreign poſt that they continued to attack, and it ſurrendered after a ſiege of 21 days.</p><p>On the Rhine the war was equally ſuccefsful on the part bf the French. On the lzth, 13th, and 14th of July, repeated engagements were fought ; in which the French enjoyed their uſual ſucceſs. They had nume-rous armies in every quarter.. Their mode of fighting was to make full preparation for aecompliſhing their object, and to fight in great bodiea day after day till it was obtained. The Palatinate was thus over-run, and Treves taken, by general Michaud. Flanders and the Palatinate have always been accounted the. granaries of Germany ; and both of them, at the commencement of the harveſt, now fell into the hands of the French.</p><p>During the courſe of this ſummer Corſica was ſub-dued by Great Britain and the whole of the French weſt India Iſſands, excepting a part of Gaadaulope, yielded to the Britiſh troops under the command oſ Sir Charles Grey and Sir John Jarvis. On the firſt oſ June the Britiſh fleet, under the command oſ earl Howe, gained a moſt ſplendid victory over the French fleet to the weſtward of Uſhant. The French committee of ſaſety were known to have puchaſed in America im</p><lb/><p>menſe quantities of grain and other ſtores. Thefe were embarked on board 160 fail of merchantmen, convoyed by ſix ſail oſ the line.. Lord Howe failed to intercept this valuable convoy. The French fleet failed at the fame time to protect it... On the morning oſ the 28th oſ May the fleets came in ſight of each other. The Britiſh admiral had previouſſy diſpatched ſſx ſhips of the line under admiral Montague to intercept the French convoy, while he ſhould engage and detain the grand fleet, 'ſ'he French diſpatched eight, ſail to defeat this attempt.. In the courſe oſ the 29th Lord Howe got to windward of the French fleet. His force was 25, and theirs was 2-6, ſail oſ the line. The following day he bore dôwn upon them, and broke their line. Tlie engagement was one oſ the ſevereſt' ever fought., Tlie French admiral, in leſs than an hour aſter the cloſe action commenced in the centre, crouded off with 12 oſ his ſhips.. The Britiſh fleet was ſo much diſabled, or ſeparated, that ſeveral oſ the French diſ-rnantled ſhips got away under fails raiſed on the ſtump, oſ their ſore-maſts. Seven ſail oſ the line, however, re-mained in poſſeffion· oſ the Britiſh, and two were un-queſtionably ſunk.. In the mean time, admiral Mon-. tague ſell in with the French convoy, but it- was now guarded by 14 ſail oſ the line. Äs he could not encounter ſuch a force, he returned home, and it was ſafe»-ly conveyed into port; Thus, by one oſ thoſc contradictions which ſo often occur in human affairs, the Britiſh fleet was victorious, and the French were leſt in ſome meaſure mailers oſ the ſea. As this engagement however teſtiſied that tlre Britiſh ſeamen had not loſt, their ancient ſuperiority on their own element, the nation regarded the preſent victory as a pledge oſ its independence, and very general rejoicings took place in conſequence of it.</p><p>In the mean time, the revolutionary ſyſtem of go-vernment in the hands of committees of the convention at Paris, and. of committees of the- popular ſocieties throughout the country, was arrived at its higheſt perfection, and proceeded without oppoſition in its ſevere and ſanguinary meaſures-</p><p>On .the 10th of May Madame Elizabeth, ſiſter of thc late king, was ſacriſiced by it in conſequence of a decree of the revolutionary tribunal. Multitudes of others of every rank and ſex were daily ſacrificed in a ſimſſar manner; the rich in particular were the great, objects of perſecution, becauſe the confifcation of their property added to the ſtrength of the ruling powers. But neither were the poor ſafe from the bloody vigilance of this new and ſingular government. By the different executions Robefpierre had contrived to deſtroy every avowed rival. All the conſtituted authorities conſiſted wholly of perſons nominated with his approbation ; and as the committees which conducted the buſineſs of the ſtate were at his diſpoſal, his will was irreſiſtible throughout the republic. He met witli no oppoſition in th’e conventien ; ſor that body was no longer the turbulent popular aſſembly which it had once appeared ; it was little more than a name employed to give ſome fort of reſpectability to ſuch ſchemes as were propoſed to it.</p><p>Amidſt this accumulation, however, of ſecmingly ir-reſiſtible authority, Robefpierre was at the brink of ruin. The whole of the old Girondiſt party was indeed ſubdued and ſilent ; but many members of the convention ſtill remained attached to it. The party of the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>