<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>loyalty, the national cockade, which had been adopted by fome of the gardes du corps, was thrown aſide, and white cockades were ſupplied as quickly as they could be made by the ladies of the court.</p><p>When thefe events were next day reported at Paris, accompanied by a multitude of exaggerations, they gave rife to the moſt violent alarm. The capital was at that time ſuſſering all the horrors of famine ; and in ſuch a fituation, the news of a feaſt which others have enjoyed, ſeldom gives much pleafure to hungry men. To the former report of an intended flight on the part of the royal family, it was now added, that a counter revolution was fpeedily to be attempted by force of arms ; and that thc preſent fcarcity was artificially cre-ated by the court for the purpoſe of reducing the peo-ple to fubmiſſion. Their ariſtocratic antagoniſts have fince aſſerted, that the famine was indeed artificial ; but that it was created by a portion of the violent party in the national aſſembly, which was then denominated the <hi rend="italic">Cabal,,</hi>  whoſe object was to excite commotions as the means of procuring an opportunity of ſetting the duke of orleans at the head of the ſtate, either as regent, or in ſome other form. To this laſt party Mirabeau is faid to have belonged.</p><p>For four days no notice was taken in the aſſembly of ■what had paffed at the entertainment given by the gardes du corps. Οη the 5th of october M. Petion mentioned it for the firſt time, and a violent debate enfued; during which Mirabeau rofe and exclaimed, “ Declare that the king’s perfon <hi rend="italic">alone</hi>  is ſacred, and I rnyfelf will bring forward an impeachment thereby alluding to the conduct of the queen. while this debate wa3 pro-ceeding at verſaillcs, thc city of Paris was in commotion. A vaſt multitude of women of the loweſt rank, with fome men in womens clothes, had aſſem-bled at the <hi rend="italic">Hotel de Ville,</hi>  and were ca∏ing aloud for arms and bread. They reſolved to proceed inſtantly to verfailles to demand bread from the king and from the national aſſembly. La Fayette oppυfed them in vain; for his own ſoldiers refufed to turn their bayonets againſt the women. Upon this one Staniſlaus Mail-lard, who had diſtinguiſhed himſelf at the taking of the Baſtile, offered himſelf as a leader to the inſurgents. He had the addveſs to prevail with them to lay aſide ſuch arms as they had procured; and he ſet out for ∖er-failles about noon with as much order among his fυl-Iowers as could well be expected from ſuch an aſſenp blage. Either becaufe the paſſion for going to Verfailles had ſuddenly become too infectious to be reſiſted, or becaufe the multitude already gone thither was now ac-counted dangerous, the mayor and municipality of Pa-ris thought fit to give υrdeιs to la Fayette inſtantly to ſet out for that place at the head of the national guard.</p><p>In the mean time, Maillard approached verfailles with his tumultuous troop ; he arranged them in three diviſions, and perfiiaded them to behave with tolerable decency. The king was hunting in the woods of Mendon when he was informed of the arrival of a moſt formidable band of women calling aloud for bread. " Alas ! (replied he) if I had it, I ſhould not wait to be aſked.” Maillard entered the aſſembly accompa-nied by a deputation of his followers to ſtate the ob-ject of their journey. The aſſembly, to pacify them, feat a deputation of their own number along with them to</p><p>lay their complaints before the king. His majeſty recei-ved the whole with great politeneſs, and readily agreed to go into any meaſures for the fupply of the capital that could be ſuggeſted. The report of this behaviour had fuch an effect upon the multitude collected around the palace, that they began to difperſe ; but they were ſpeedily fucceeded by another croud not lefs numerous. A ſudden refolution of flight ſeems now to have been propoſed by the court ; for the king’s carriages were brought to the gate of the palace which communicatee with the orangry : but the ħational guard of Verfailleβ refuſed to allow them to paſs, and the king himſelf refufed to remove, or to allow any blood to be ſhed in his cauſe.</p><p>La Fayette with his army at length arrived about 10 o’clock at night, and found the aſſembly in a very unpleaſant ſituation. Their hall and galleries were crowded by the Parifian fiſh-women and others of the mob, who, at eveιy inſtant, interrupted the debates. La Fayette waited upon the king, and informed him of the proceedings of the day, planted guards in every quarter ; and after a ſcanty banquet had been procured for the multitude, he prevailed with the aſſembly to clofe their fitting for the night. In this laſt part of his conduct M. la Fayette has been much cenfured, and probably not without reaſon ; for it could ſcarcely be expected that ſuch a night would be ſpent in peace by the immenſe aſſemblage of turbulent characters that were now brought together. All was quiet, however, till about fix in the morning of the 6th, when a great number of women anddefperate perſons ruſhed forward to the palace, and attempted to force their way into it. Two of the gardes du corps were killed ; the croud aſcend¢d the ſtair-caſe leading to the queen’s apartment, but were bravely reſiſted by M. Miemandre a ſentinel, who gave the alarm, and defended his poll till he fell covered with wounds, of which, however, he afterwards fortunately recovered. The ruffians, reeking with his blood, ruſhed into the chamber of the queen, and pierced with bayonets and poniards the bed whence this</p><p>perſecuted woman had but juft time to fly almoſt naked, and, through ways unknown to the murderers, had eſca-ped to ſeek refuge at the feet of the king, who w as al-ready alarmed, and had gone to feek her.</p><p>Ί he tumult became more violent every moment, and fudden death feemed to threaten the royal family ; but la Fayette was by this time at the head of his troops, whom he befecched earneſtly to ſave the gardes du corps from maffacre. In this he was ſuccefsful ; ſome that had been taken priſoners were ſurrounded by the grenadiers of the French guards who protected them, and the retreat of the whole corps was eaſily ſecured. The croud was fpeediſy driven from the different quar-ters of the palace, which they were already beginning to pillage; and the royal family ventured to ſhow them-felves at a balcony. A few voices now exclaimed* <hi rend="italic">Le Roi à Paris,</hi>  " the King to Paris.” Ιhe ſhout be-came general ; and the king, after conſulting with la Fayette, declared that he had no objection to take up his reſidence at Paris, provided he was accompanied by the queen and his children, when the propoſal was reported to the aſſembly, the popular leaders expreſſed much ſatisſaction. Ι'hey ordered a deputation of 100 members to attend the king thither; they voted the national aſſembly inſeparable from the king. His majeſty</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>