<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>will be proportional to the fquares of the velocities directly, and to the chords of curvature haviag the direc-tion of the forces inverſely.</p><p>From theſe premiſes, therefore, we deduce, jit the ſtricteſt manner, the demonſtration of the leading theo-<hi rend="sub">r</hi>em of the reſiſtance and impulfe of fluids ; namely,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">cîProp. I. The refiſtances, and (by the third law of motion), the impulſions of fluids on ſimilar bodies, are proportional to the ſurfaces of the ſolid bodies, to the denſities of the fluids, and to the fquaιes of the velocities, jointly.</hi></p><p>We muſt now obferve, that when we ſuppofe the par-ticles of the fluid to be in mutual contact, we may ei-ther fuppoſe them elaſtic or unelaſtic. The motion communicated to the collection of elaſtic particles muſt be double of what the ſame body, moving in the ſame manner, would communicate to the particles of an unelaſtic fluid. The impnlſe and reſiſtance of elaſtic fluids muſt therefore be double of thoſe of unelaſtic fluids.— But we muſt caution our readers not to judge of the elaſticity oſ fluids by their ſenfible compreffibility. A diamond is incomparably more elaſtic than the ſineſt football, though not compreſſible in any fenfible degree.— It remains to be decided, by well choſen experiments, whether water be not as elaſtic as air. If we ſuppoſe, with Boſcovich, the particles of perfect fluids to be at a diſtance from each other, we ſſiall find it difficult to conceive a fluid void of elafticity. we hope that the theory of their impulſe and reſtſtance wiſl l'uggeſt experiments which wiſl decide this queſtion, by pointing out what ought to be the abſolute impulſe or reiiſtance in either caſe. And thus the fundamental propoſttion of the impulſe and reſiſtance of fluids, taken in its pro-per meaning, is ſufceptible of a rigid demonſtration, re-lative to the only diſtinct notion that we can form of the internal conſtitution of a fluid. We lay, <hi rend="italic">taken in its proper meaning ;</hi>  namely, that the impulſe or refiſtance of fluids is a preffure, oppoſed and meaſured by another preffure, ſuch as a pound weight, the force of a ſpring, the preffure of the atmoſphere, and the like. And we apprehend that it would he very difficult to find any legitimate demonftration of this leading propoſttion different from this, which we have now borrowed from Sir lſaac Newton, Prop. 23,. B. II. <hi rend="italic">Princip. We</hi>  ac-knowledge that it is prolix and even circuitous : but in all the-attempts made by his commentators and their copyiſts to ſimplify it, we ſee great defects of logical argument, or affumption of principles, which are not only gratuitous, but inadmiſſible. we ſſiall have occa-ſion, as we proceed, to point out ſome of thefe defects ; and doubt not but the illuſtrious author of this demon-ſtration hadexercifed his uncommon patience and ſagacity in ſimilar attempts, and was diffatisſied with them aſl.</p><p>Before we proceed further, it vyill be proper to rn&gt;ke a general remark, which wiſl fave a great deal of diſcuſſion. Since it is a matter of univerfal experience, that every action of a body on others is accompanied by an equal and contrary re-action ; and ſince all that we can demonſtrate concerning the reſiſtance of bodies during their motions through fluids proceeds on this ſup-poſition, (the reſiſtance of ∣the body being <hi rend="italic">ajfumed</hi>  as equal and oppoſite to the ſum of motions communicated to the particles of the fluid, eſtimated in the direction of the bodies motion), we are intitled to proceed in the contrary ordfer, and to conſider the impulſions which each of the particles of fluid exerts on the body at reſt, as equal and oppofite to the motion which the body would communicate to that particle if the fluid were at reſt, and the body were moving equaſly ſwift in the oppoſite direction. And therefore the whole impulſion of the fluid muſt be conceived as the meaſure of the whole motion which the body would thus communicate to the fluid. It muſt therefore be alſo conſidered as themeaſurcof the reſiſtance which the body, moving wiſh the ſame velocity, would ſuſtain from the fluid, when, therefore, we ſſiall demonſtrate any thing concerning the impulſion of a fluid, eſtimated in the direction of its motion, we muſt conſider it as demonſtrated concerning the refift= ance of a quieſcent fluid to the motion of that body, having the ſame velocity in the oppoſite direction. The determination of theſe impulſions being much eaſier than the determination of the motions communicated by the body to the particles oſ the ſiuid, this method wiſl be followed in moſt of the ſubſequent diſcuſſions.</p><p>Tlie general propofition already delivered is by no means ſuſſicient for explaining the various important phenomena obſerved in the mutual actions oſ ſolids and fluids. In particular, it gives us no aſſiſtance in aſcer-tainſhg ſhe modifications of this reſtſtance or impulfe, which depend on the ſhape of ſhe body and the ineli-nation of its impelled or reſiſted ſurface to the direction of the motion. Sir Iſaac Newton found another hypothefis neceffary ; namely, that the ſtuid ſhould be ſo extremely rare that the diſtance of the particles may be incomparably greater than their diameters. This addi-tional condition is neceſſary for conſidering their actions as ſo many ſeparate codifions or impuliι&lt;ans on the ſolid body. Each particle mnſt be ſuppoſed to have abundant room to rebound, or otherwiſe eſcape, after having made its ſtroke, without ſenfibly affecting the ſituations and motions of the particles which have not yet made their ftroke : and the motion mnſt be ſo ſwiſt as not to give time for the ſenſible exertion of their mutual forces of attractions and repulſions.</p><p>Keeping theſe conditions in mind, we may proceed to determine the impuliions made by a fluid on ſurfaces of every kind : And the mo⅛ convenient method to purſue in this determination, is to compare them all either with the inιpulfε which the <hi rend="italic">fame Jurfiqce</hi>  would receive from the fluid impinging on it perpendicularly, or with the impulſe which the <hi rend="italic">fame fiream of fiuid</hi>  would, make when coming perpendicularly on a ſurface of ſuch extent as to occupy the whole ſtream.</p><p>It will greatly abbreviate-language, if we make uſe of a few terms in an appropriated ſenſe.</p><p>By <hi rend="italic">3. fiream,</hi>  we ſhall mean a quantity of ſiuid moving in one direction, that is, each particle moving in paral-lel lines ; and the <hi rend="italic">breadth</hi>  of the ſtream is a line perpen-dicular to all theſe parallels.</p><p>A <hi rend="italic">filament</hi>  means a portion of this ſtream of very ſmall breadth, and it conſiſts of an indefinite number of particles following one another in the ſame direction, and ſucceſſively impinging on, or gliding alom&gt;-, the ſurface of the ſolid body.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">baſe</hi>  of any lurface'expofed to a. ſtream of ſiuid, is that portion of a plane perpendicular to the ſtream, which is covered or protected from the action of the ſtream by the furface expofed to its impulſe. Thus the baſe of a ſphere expofed to a ſtream of fluid is its great</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>