<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>th⅛ m¾n had not the courage of Luther ∣ and was therefore on all occaſions ready to make conceſſions, and to propoſe ſchemes of accommodation. In the preſent caſe, therefore, he gave it as his opinion, that the whole of the book called <hi rend="italic">Interim</hi>  could not by any means be adopted by the Proteſtants; but at ſame time he declared, that, he ſaw no reaſon why this book might not be appproved, adopted, and received, as an authoritative rule in things that did not relate to the ciſential parts of religion, and which he accounted indifferent. But this ſcheme, inſtead of cementing tlie differences, made them much worſe than ever ; and produced a divjſion among the Proteſtants themſelves, which might have overthrown the Reformation en-tirely, if the emperor and pope had ſeized the oppoι⅛ tunity.</p><p>In the year 1549, the pope (Paul ∏I.) died; and w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as ſucceeded by Julius III. who, at the repeated fo-licitations of the emperor, conſented to the re-aſſem-bling oſ a council at Trent. A diet was again held at Augſhurg under the cannon of an imperial army, and Charles laid the matter. before the princes of the em*= pire. Moſt of theſe preſent gave their conſent to it, and among the reſt Maurice elector of Saxony $ who conſented on the following conditions ; 1, That the points of doctrine which had already been decided there, ſhould be re-examined.2. That this eχami-nation ſhould be made in preſence of the Proteſtant divines. 3. That the Saxon Proteſtants ſhould have a liberty of voting as well as of deliberating in the council. 4. That the pope ſhouid not pretend to pre-fide in that aſſembly, either in perfon or by his legates. This declaration of Maurice was read in the diet, and his deputies inſiſted upon its being entered into the regiſters which the archbiſhop of Mentz obſtinately re-fuſed. The diet was concluded in the year 1551 ; and, at its breaking up, the emperor deſired the aſſembled princes and ſtates to prepare all things for the approaching council, and promifed to uſe his ut-moſt endeavours to procure moderation and harmony, impartiality and charity, in the tranſactions of that aſ-fembly.</p><p>Οη the breaking up of the diet, the Proteſtants took fuch ſteps as they thought moſt proper for their own ſafety. The Saxons employed Melancthon, and the wurtembergers Brengius, to draw up Confeſſions of Faith to be laid before the new council. The Saxon di-vines, however, proceeded no farther than Nuremberg, having received ſecret orders from Maurice to ſtop there : For the elector, perceiving that Charles had formed deſigns againſt the liberties of the German princes, reſolved to take the moſt effectual meaſures for cruſhing his ambition at once. He therefore entered with the utmQſt fecrecy and expedition into an alliance with the king of France, and ſeveral of the German princes, for the ſecurity of the rights and liberties of the empire ; after which, aſſembling a powerful army in 1552, he marched againſt the emperor, who lay with a handful of troops at Inſpruck, and expected no ſuch thing. By thi3 ſudden and unforeſeen accident Charles was ſo much diſpirited, that he was willing to make peace almoſt on any terms, The conſequence ef this was, that he concluded a treaty at Paſſau, which by the Proteſtants is conſidered as the bafis of their religi-«us liberty. By the firſt three articles of this treaty it</p><p>was agreed, that Maurice and the eon⅛4βFStfs ſh¢ſtd lay down their arms, and lend their troops to Ferdinand to aſſiſt him againſt the Turks ↑ and that the landgrave of Heſſe ſhould be ſet at liberty. By the fourth it was agreed, that the Rule of Faith called the <hi rend="italic">Interim </hi>ſhould be confidered as null and void ; that the contending parties ſhould enjoy the free and undiſturixd exerciſe of their religion, until a diet ſhould be aſſetrw bled to determine amicably the prefent diſputes (which diet was to meet in the ſpace of ſix months) ; and. that this religious liberty ſhould continue always, in caſe it ſhould be found impoſſible to come to an uniformity in doctrine and worſhip. It was alſo determined, that all thoſe who had ſuffered baniſhment, or any other eala∙* mity, on account of their having been concerned in the league or war of Smalca!d&gt; ſhould. be iesnſtated in their privileges, poſieſſions, and employments ; that the im« pedal chamber at Spire ſhould be open to the. Prate· Hants as well as to the Catholics 5 and that there ſhould always be a certain number of Lutherans in that high court.-—To this peace Albert, marquis of Branden-burg, refufed to ſubfcribe ; and continued the war agamſt the Roman-catholics, committing ſuch ravagea in the empire, that a confederacy was at laſt formed again ſt him, At the head of this confederacy was Maurice elector of Saxony, who died of a wound he received in a battle fought on the occaſion in 155 3,</p><p>The affembling of the diet promiſed by Charles was prevented by various incidents ; however it met at Augſhurg in 1555, where it was opened by Ferdinand in name of the emperor, and terminated thoſe deplorable calamities which had ſh long deſolated the empire» After various debates, the following acts were paffed, on the 25th of September t That the Prote-ſtants who followed the Confeſſion of Augſhurg ſhould be for the future conſidered as entirely free from the ju∙ riſdiction of the Roman pontiff, and from the authority and fuperintendance of the biſhops 5 that they were left at perfect liberty to enact laws for themſelves relating to their religious ſentiments, diſcipline, and worſhip j that all the inhabitants oſ the German empire ſhould be allowed to judge for themſelves in religious matteι⅜ and to join themſelves to that church whole doctrine and worſhip they thought the moſt pure and ¢onfimant to the ſpirit of true Chriſtianity 5 and that all thoſe who ſhould injure or perſecute any perfon under reli» gious pretences, and on account of their opinions, ſhould be declared and proceeded againſt as public enemies oſ the empire, invaders of its liberty, and diſturbers of its peace.</p><p>Thus was the Reformation eſtabliſhed in many parts of the German empire, where it continues to this day j nor have the efforts of the Popiſh powers at any time been able to fupprefs it, or even to prevent it from gaining ground. It was not, however, in Germany alone that a reformation of religion took place, Ak moſt all the kingdoms of Europe began t© open their eyes to the truth about the ſame time. The reformed religion was propagated in Sweden, ſoon after Lu-ther’s rupture with the church of Rome, by onc of his diſciples named <hi rend="italic">Olaus Petri,</hi>  The zealous efforts of this miſſionary were feconded by Guſtavws Vafi⅛ whom the Swedes had raifed to the throne in place of Chriſtiern king of Denmark, whoſe horrid barbarity loſt him the crown. This priaee, however, was as</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>