<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the prcffurê may be almoſt annihilated by the <hi rend="italic">tendency </hi>to rebound of thc inner filaments.</p><p>Part (and perhaps a conſiderable part) of this appa-rent non-preſſion is undoubtedly produced by thc tenacity of the water, which licks off with it the water lying in the hole. But, at any rate, this is an important fact, and gives great value to theſe experiments. It gives a key to many curious pnenome-na in the rehſtance of fluids ; and the theory of Mr Buat deſerves a very ſerious confideration. It is all contained in the two following propoſitions.</p><p>1.    " <hi rend="italic">If by any cauſe whatever, a column of fluid, whether making part of an indefinitefiuid, or contained in ſolid canals, comes to move with a given velocity, the prejfure • which it exerted laterally before its motion, either on the adjoining fiuid or on the fides of the canal, is diminijhed by the</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">weight of a column having the height necejfary for communicating the velocity of the motion.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">2.    " The prefl'ure On the centre of a plane furface perpendicular to theJlream, and wholly immcrfed in it, is ⅜ of the weight of a column having the height necejfιry for communicating the velocity. For</hi>  33 h ⅜ ¾f 2l-r∙"</p><p>He attempted to aſcertain the medium preffure on the whole ſurface,. by opening 625 holes diſperſed all over it. with the ſame velocity of current, he found the height in the tube to be 29 lines, or 7 more than the height neceffary for producing the velocity. But he juftly concluded this to be too great a meaſure, be-cauſe the holes were ⅛ of an inch from the edge : had there been holes at the very edge, they would have ſuſ-tained a non-preſſion, which would have diminiſhed the height in the tube very conſiderably. He expofed to the ſame ftream a conical funnel, which raiſed the water to 34 lines. But this could not be conſidered as a meaſure of the preffure on a plane ſolid ſurface : for the central water was undoubtedly ſcooped out, as it were, and the filaments much more deflected than they would have been by a plane ſurface. Perhaps ſomething of this happened even in every ſmall hole in the for-mer experiments. And this ſuggeſts ſome doubt as to the accuracy of the meafurement of the preffure and of the velocity of a current by Mr Pitot’s tube. It ſurely renders ſome corrections abſolutely neceffary. It is a faſt, that when expofid to a vein of ſtuid coming through a ſhort paffage, the water in the tube Hands on a level with that in the reſervoir. Now we know that the velocity of this ſtream <hi rend="italic">does not</hi>  exceed what would be produced by a fall equal to <hi rend="sub">τ</hi><hi rend="sup">8</hi>θ⅛ of the head of water in the refirvoir. Mr Buat made many valuable ob∙ firvations and improvements on this moſt uſeful inſtrument, which will be taken notice of in the articles Rivers and<hi rend="italic">WATF.R-Wsrks.</hi></p><p>Mr Buat, by a ſcrupulous attention to all the circum-ſtances, concludes, that the medium of preffure on the</p><p>25.5</p><p>whole ſurface is equal to-of the weight of a co.</p><p>21.5</p><p>lumn, having the ſurface for its bafc, and the produc-tive fall for its height. But we think that there is an uncertainty in this conclufion ; becaufe the height of the water in the vertical tube was undoubtedly augmented by an hydroftatical preffure ariſtng from the accumulation of water above the. body which was expofed to the ftream.</p><p>Since the preffures are as the ſquares of tlie veloci-</p><p>ties, or as the heights <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  which produce the velocities,</p><p>we may expreſs this preffure by the fmybol~—<hi rend="italic">'~b,</hi>  or</p><p>t,ι86∕&gt;, or <hi rend="italic">mh,</hi>  the value of <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  being 1,186. This exceeds confιderably the reſult of the experiments of the French academy. In theſe it does not appear that <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  ſenfibly exceeds unity. Note, that in theſe experi-ments the body was moved through ſtill water ; here it is expofed to a ſtream. Thefi are generally fupρofid to be equivalent, on the authority of the third law of mo∙ tion, which makes every action depend on thc 1 elative motions. we ſhall by and by fie ſome cauſes of difference.</p><p>The writers on this ſubject ſeem to think their taſk completed when they have conſidered the action of the ſiuid on the anterior part of the body, or that part of it which is before the broadeſt fiction, and have paid little or no attention to the hinder part. Yet thofi who are moſt intereſted in the ſubject, the naval architects, ſeem convinced that it is of no leſs importance to attend to the form of the hinder part of a ſhip. And the univerſal practice of all nations has been to make the hinder part more acute than the fore-part. This has undoubtedly been deduced from experience; for it is in direct oppoſition to any notions which a perſon would naturally form on this ſubject. Mr Buat therefore thought it very neceffary to examine the action of the water on the hinder part of a body by the fame method. And, previous to this examination, in order to acquire ſome ſcientiſic notions of the ſubject, he made the following very curious and inſtruſtive experiment.</p><p>Two little conical pipes AB (fig. 22.) were inferted into the upright ſide of a priſmatic veffel. They were an inch long, and their diameters at the inner and outer ends were five and four lines. A was ς7 lines under the ſurface, and B was 73. A glaſs ſyphon was made of the ſhape repreſented in the figure, and its internal diameter was 1 £ lines. It was placed with its mouth in the axis, and even with the bafe of the conical pipe. The pipes being lhut, the veffel was ſilled with water, and it was made to ſtand on a level in the two legs of the ſyphon, the upper part being full of air. when this fyphon was applied to the pipe A, and the water running freely, it rofe 3 2 lines in the ſhort leg', and funk as much in the other, when it was applied to the pipe B, the water rofe 41 lines in the one leg of the ſyphon, and ſunk as much in the other.</p><p>He reafons in this manner ſrom the experiment. The ring comprehended between the end of the ſyphon and the ſides of the conical tube being the narroweſt part of the orifice, the water iffued with the velocity cor-reſponding to the height of the water in the veffel above the orifice, diminiſhed for the contraction. If therefore the cylindcr of water immediately before the mouth of the ſyphon iffued with the ſame velocity, the tube would be emptied through a height equal to this head of water. <hi rend="italic">(charge j.</hi>  If, on the contrary, this cylinder of water, immediately before the mouth of the ſyphon, were ſtagnant, the water in it would exert its full preffure on the mouth of the ſyphon, and the water in the ſyphon would be level with the water in the veffel. Between theſe extremes we muſt find the real ſtate of the caſe, and we muſt meafure the force of non-preffure by the riſe of the water in the fyphon.</p><p>we fie that in both experiments it bears an accurate</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>