<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Regiments were ſirſt formed in France in the year 1558, and in England in the year 1660.</p><p>REGIOMONTANUS. See Muller.</p><p>REGION, in geography, a large extent oſ land, in-habited by many people of the ſame nation, and incloſed within certain limits or bounds.</p><p>The modern aſtronomers divide the moon into ſeveral regions, or large tracts of land, to each of which they give its proper name.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Region, in phyſiology, is taken for a diviſion of our ■atmoſphere, which is divided into the upper, middle, and Iower regions.</hi></p><p>The upper region commences from the tops of the -mountains, and reaches to the utmoſt limits of the at-moſphere. In this region reign a perpetual, equable, calmneſs, clearneſs, and ſerenity. The middle region is that in which the clouds reſide, and where meteors are formed, extending from the extremity of the loweſt to the tops of the higheſt mountains. The loweſt region is that in which we breathe, which is bounded by the reflection of thc fun’s rays ; or by the height to which they rebound from the earth. See Atmosphere and Air.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Æthereal Region,</hi>  in cofmography, is the whole ex-tent of the univerſe, in which is included all the heavenly bodies, and even the orb of the fixed ſtars.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Elementary Region,</hi>  according to the Ariſtotelians, is a ſphere terminated by the concavity of the moon’s orb, comprehending the atmoſphere of the earth.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Region, in anatomy, a diviſion of the human body, otherwiſe ealled </hi><hi rend="italic">cavity,</hi>  of which anatomiſts reckon three, viz. the upper region, or that of the head ; the middle region, that of the thorax or breaſt ; and the lower, the abdomen, or belly. See Anatomy.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Region, in ancient Rome, was a part or diviſton of •the city. The regions were only four in number, till Auguſtus Cæiar’s time, who divided the city into fourteen ; over each of which he fettled two furveyors, called </hi><hi rend="italic">curatores viarum,</hi>  who were appointed annually, and took their diviſions by lot. Theſe fourteen regions contained four hundred and twenty-four ſtreets, thirty-one of which were called <hi rend="italic">greater</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">royal Jlreets,</hi>  which began at the gilt pillar that ſtood at the entry of the open place, in the middle of the city. The extent of theſe diviſions varied greatly, ſome being from 12000 or 13000 to 33000 feet or upwards in circumference. Authors, however, are not agreed as to the exact limits of each. The curatores viarum wore the purple, had each two lictors in their proper divilions, had ſlaves under them .to take care of fires, that happened to break ■out. They had alſo two officers, called <hi rend="italic">denunciatores,</hi>  in each region, to give account of any diſorders. Four <hi rend="italic">vιco-rnagijlri</hi>  alſo were appointed in each ſtreet, who took care of the ſtreets allotted them, and carried the orders of the city to each citizen.</p><p>REGIS 1ER, a public book, in which are entered and recorded memoirs, acts, and minutes, to be had recourſe to occafionally for knowing and proving matters of fact. Οί theſe there are ſeveral kinds ; as,</p><p>i. Regiſter of deeds in Yorkſhire and Middleſex, in which are regiſtered all deeds, conveyances, wills, &amp;c\ -that affect any lands or tenements in thoſe counties, which are otherwife void againſt any ſubfequent pur-■chafers or mortgagees, &amp;c. but this does not extend to any copyhold eſtate, nor to leaſes at a rack-rent, or where they do not exceed 21 years. The regiſtered memorials muſt be ingroffed on parchment, under the hand and ſcal of ſome of the granters or grantees, at-tefted by witneffes who are to prove the ſigning or ſeal· ing of them and the execution of the deed. But theſe regiſters, which are confined to two counties, are in Scotland general, by which the laws of North Britain are rendered very eaſy and regular. Οί theſe there are two kinds ; the one general, fixed at Edinburgh, under the direction of the lord-regiſter ; and the other is kept in the ſeveral ſhires, ſtewartries, and regalities, the clerks of which are obliged to tranſmit the regiſters of their reſpective courts to the general regiſter.</p><p>2. Pariſſi-regiſters are books in which are regiſtered the baptifms, marriages, and burials, of each pariſli.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Registers were kept both at Athens and Rome, in which were inferted the names of ſuch children as were to be brought up, as foon as they were born. Marcus Aurelius required all free perſons to give in accounts of their children, within 30 days after the birth, to the treaſurer of the empire, in order to their being depofited in the temple of Saturn, where the public acts were kept, officers were alſo appointed aa public regiſters in the provinces, that recourſe might be had to their lifts of names, for ſettling diſputes, or pro-ving any perſon’s freedom.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Register Ships,</hi></hi>  in commerce, are veffels which ob-tain a permiſſion either from the king of Spain, or the council of the Indies, to traffic in the ports of the Spaniſh weft Indies ; which are thus called, from their being regiſtered before they ſet ſail from Cadiz for Buenos Ayres.</p><p>REGISTERS, in chemiſtry, are holes, or chinks with ſtopplea, contrived in the fides of furnaces, to regulate the fire ; that is, to make the heat more intenſc or remifs, by opening them to let in the air, .or keeping them cloſe to exclude it. There are alſo regiſters in the ſteam-engine. See <hi rend="italic">SτκAM-Enfine.</hi></p><p>REGISTRAR, an officer in the Engliſh univerſi-ties, who has the keeping of all the public records.</p><p>REGIUM, Regi um <hi rend="italic">Lepidi, Regium Lepidum,</hi>  (anc. geog.); a town of Cifalpine Gaul, on the via Æmilia, ſo called from Æmilius Lepidus, who was conſul with C. Flaminius ; but whence it was ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Regium</hi>  is altogether uncertain. Tacitus relates, that at the battle of Bedriacum, a bird of an unuſual ſize was ſeen perching in a famous grove near Regium Lepidum. Now called <hi rend="italic">Reggio,</hi>  a city of Modena. E. Long. 11. ο. N. Lat. 44. 45. See Reggio.</p><p>REGNARD (John Francis), one of the beſt French comic writers after Moliere, was born at Paris in 1647⅛ He had ſcarcely finiſſied his ſtudies, when an ardent paſſion for travelling carried him over the greateſt part of Europe, when he fettled in his own country, he was made a treaſurer of France, and lieutenant of the waters and foreſts : he wrote a great many comedies ; and, though naturally of a gay genius, died of chagrin in the 52d year or his age. His works, conſtſting of comedies and travels, werc printed at Rouen, in 5 vola I2mo, 1732.</p><p>REGNIER (Mathurin), the firſt French poet wh© ſucceeded in ſatire, was born at Chartres in 1573. He was brought up to the church, a place for which his debaucheries rendered him very unfuitable ; and theſe by his own confeſſioh were ſo exceſſive, that at 30 he had</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>