<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>fiſtaflfce been made from within, it is probable they would have joined the royal party. But towards eight o’clock M. Roederer procured admittance to the palace, and told the king that armed multitudes were aſſembling in hoſtile array around the Thuilleries ; that the national, guard was not to be depended upon ; and that, in caſe of reſiſtance, the whole royal family would moſt certainly be maſſacred. He therefore adviſed the king to ſeek protection in the hall of the national affembly. with this advice the king, with his uſual facility of temper, was ready to comply ; but the queen oppoſed with vehemence the humiliating propoſal. Becoming gradually, however, alarmed for the ſaſety of her children, ſhe gave her conſent 5 and the king and queen, the princeſs Elizabeth, with tlie prince and princeſs royal, went on foot to the hall of the affembly. " 1 am come hither (ſaid his majeſty) to prevent a great crime. Among you, gentlemen, I believe myſelf in ſafety.” By an article of the conſtitution the aſſein-bly could not deliberate in preſence of the king. The royal family were, therefore, placed in a narrow box fe-parated from tb.e hall by a railing, where they remained ſor 14 hours without any place to which they could retire for refreſhment, excepting a very ſinall cloſet adjoining. Here they ſat liſtening to debates, in which the royal character and office were treated with every mark of inſult.</p><p>when the king left the palace of the Tliuilleiies, he unfortunately forgot to order it to be immediately ſurrendered. He recollected this as ſoon as he reached the aſſembly, and ſent orders for this purpoſe ; but it was now too late, 'ſ'he inſurgents amounted to about 20,000 effective men. They were drawn up in tolerable order by weſterman a Pruffian, and had about 30 pieces of cannon along with them. The gentlemen within the palace, who had aſſembled to protect the king’s perſon, were now diſpirited, and knew not what part to act. The commander of the Swifs, M. Aſſry, was abſent, and the captains knew not what to do; and the national guard had no leader in conſequence of the death of Mandat. About nine o’clock the outer gates were forced open ; and the inſurgents formed their line in front of the palace. A bloody combat commenced chiefly between the Marſeillois and the Swiſs. After a brave reſlſtance of about an hour, the Swiſs were overpowered by numbers, and gave way. All of them that could be ſound in tlie palace were maſſacred ; fome •even while imploring quarter on their knees. Others eſeaped into the city, and were protected by individuals. Of this brave regiment, however, only 200 furvi-ved ; but every human being, even the loweſt ſervants found in the palace, were put to death. The Swiſa taken prifonere in various quarters were conducted to the door oſ the aſſembly, and taken by a decree under the protection of the ſtate. But the ſanguinary multitude inſiſted upon putting them to inſtant death ; and the aſſembly would, in aſhprobability, have been unable to protect them, had ſmt the Marſeillois interfered in their favour.</p><p>The ſuſpenſion of the royal authority was now decreed, and the nation was invited to elect a <hi rend="italic">Convention </hi>to determine the nature of its ſuture government. On this uncommon occaſion all Frenchmen of 21 years of age were declared capable of electing, and of being elected, deputies to thc new national Convention. Coni-</p><lb/><p>miffioners were, in the mean timc, ſent 011 the fame evening to give to the armies a ſalſe and favourable account of theſe tranſactions. The royal family were ſent to the old palace of the Femple in the midſt of the city, to remain there under a ſtrict guard ; and all perſons of rank who had been attached to them were ſei-r.ed and committed to rhe different priſons.</p><p>To give an idea of the temper of the people of Paris at this time, it is proper to remark, that at the ſame inſtant when the multitude with bloody fury were maf-ſacring tile menial ſervants in the palace, and could fcarcely be reſtrained from offering violence to the Swiſs who were made priſoners, they would ſuſſer no act of pillage to paſs unpuniſhed. Several attempts of this kind were accordingly followed by the inſtant death of the criminals. The plate, the jewels, and money found in the I huilleries were brought to the national aſſembly, and thrown down in the hall. One man, whoſe dreſs and appeal ance beſpoke extreme poverty, caſt upon the table an hat full of gold.—Bu^ the minds of theſe men were elevated by enthuſiaſm ; and they conceived themſelves as at this moment the champions of freedom, and objects of terror to the kings of the earth.</p><p>In the mean time, the ſituation of France was extremely critical, and it appeared very doubtful if the new Convention would ever be ſuſſered to aſſemble. La Fayette had accidentally got ſpeedy notice of the events of the 10th of Auguſh He adviſed the magiſtrates of the town of Sedan to impriſon the commiffioners from the national aſſembly when they ſhould arrive there ; which was accordingly donc. He, at the ſame time, publiſhed an addreſs to his ärmyj calling upon them to ſupport the king and the conſtitution°; but finding that they were not to be depended upon, on the 19th Auguſt he left his camp in the night, accompanied only by his ſtaſſ and a few ſervants. They took the rout of Rochefort in Liege, which was a neutral country ; but were met by a party of the enemy, who took them prifoners, and they were detained in Pruffian and Auſtrian dungeons till autumn 1794, when it is ſaid that La Fayette himſelf made lſis efcape. The ſevere treatment of this man was probably a conſiderable error in policy 011 the part of the allies. Fiis fide-lity to his king is very generally admitted; though ſome have entertained ſtrong ſuſpicions of his having°acted a very baſe part to that unfortunate monarch ; and in the Britiſh houſe of commons he has been calied an abandoned ruffian. This expreffion is certainly too ſtrong. His errors ſeem to have been thoſe of the head rather than of the heart ; and at all events, he ſhould have been protected by the allies if ſor no othcr reaſon than to encourage ſubſequent deſertions among the officers of the republican açmy.</p><p>To return from this digreffion. The commiffioners were ſoon ſet at liberty at Sedan, and received with applauſe by the army of La Fayette. General Arthur Dillon at ſirſt entered into the ſentiments of La Fayette; but tlie politic Dumourier diverted him from his purpoſe, and by this means regained his credit with the Jacobins, and was appointed commander in chief. The other generals, Biron, Monteſquieu, Kellerman, and Cuſtine, made no oppoſition to the will of the national aſſembly.</p><p>Meanwhile, the combined armies of Auſtria and Pruffia had entered France. The duke of Brunſwickſa</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>