<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>there is nothing that ſeems to comma .fi <hi rend="italic">if</hi>  but a ſmall hill at ſome diſtance, which is undermined and may be blown up. It -was taken by Amurath ill. with the loſs of 20,000 men ; but was ſurpriſed ſoon aſter by Count Palfi, who killed all the Turks that were found therein. It is ſeated at the confluence of the rivers Rab and Rabnitz, not far from the Danube, 32 miles weſt of Gran, and 55 ſouth-eaſt of vienna. E. Long. 17. 25. N. Lat. 47. 48,</p><p>RAB AC, a ſmall port on the Arabian coaſt of the Red Sea, in N. Lat. 22<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 35' 40'' by Mr Bruce’s ac-¢ount. The entry to the harbour is from the E. N. E. and is about a quarter of a mile broad. The port extends about two miles in length to thc eaſtward. The mountains are about three leagues to the north, and the town about four miles north by eaſt from the entrance to the harbour. The water is gcod, and all ſhips may be ſupplied here from the wells which are in the neigh-bourhood of the town. The country is bare and un-¢ultivated ; but from the appearance of it, and the freſhneſs of the water, Mr Bruce ſuppoſes that it fome-times rains among the mountains here, which is the more probable as it is conſiderably within the tropic.</p><p>RABAT, a large and handfome ſea-port town of Africa, in the kingdom of Fez and province of Tremε-fen. It has fine mofques and handſome palaces, and is ſeated at the mouth of the river Burrigrig, almoſt in the mid-way between Fez and Tangier. W. Long. 5. 28. N. Lat. 34. 40.</p><p>Rabat, together with SaHee, which is oppoſite to it, was formerly famous for fitting out piratical veſſels ; but the late emperor Sidi Mahomet ſubdued them both, and annexed them to the empire ; ſince which time the harbour of Rabat has been ſo filled with the ſand waſhed in by the ſea as to render it unfit to carry on ſuch piracies in future.</p><p>The town of Rabat, whoſe walls incloſe a large ſpace of ground, is defended on the ſea-fide by three forts to-lerably well finiſhed, which were erected ſome little time ago by an Engliſh renegado, and furniſhed with guns from Gibraltar. The houſes in general are good, and many of the inhabitants are wealthy. The Jews, who are very numerous in this place, are generally in better circumſtances than thoſe of Larache or Tangier, and their women are extremely beautiful.</p><p>The caſtle, which is very extenſive, contains a ſtrong building, formerly uſed by the late emperor as his prin-cipal treaſury, and a noble terrace, which commands an extenfive proſpect oſ the town of Sallee, the ocean, and all the neighbouring country. There are alſo the ruins of another caſtle, which is ſaid to have been built by Jacob Almonzor, one of their former emperors, and of which at preſent very little remai∏3 but its walls, con-taining within them ſome very ſtrong magazines for powder and naval ſtores. Οη the outſide of theſe walls is a very high and ſquare tower, handſomely built of cut ſtone, and called the tower of <hi rend="italic">Hajfin.</hi>  From the workmanſhip of this tower, contraſted with the other buildings, a very accurate idea may be formed how great-ly the Moors have degenerated from their former ſplen-dour and taſte for aιchitecture.</p><p>RABBETTING, in carpentry, the planning or cut-ting of channels or grooves in boards, &amp;c.</p><p>In ſhip-carpentry, it figmies the letting in of the planks of the ſhip into the keel; which, in the rake aιid</p><p>run of a ſhip, is hollowed away, that the planks may join the cloſer.</p><p>RABBI, or Rabbins, a title which the Phariſees and doctors of the law among the Jews aſſumed, and literally fignifies <hi rend="italic">mqflers</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">excellents.</hi></p><p>There were ſeveral gradations before they arrived at the dignity of a rabbin ; which was not conferred till they had acquired the prcfoundeſt knowledge of the law and the traditions. It does not, however, appear that there was any fixed age or previous examination ncceſſary ; but when a man had diſtinguiſhed himſelſ by his ſkill in the written and oral law, and paſſed through the ſubordinate degrees, he was faluted a rabbin by the public voice.</p><p>Among the modern Jews, for near 700 years paſt, the learned men retain no other title than that of <hi rend="italic">rabbi, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">rabbins</hi>  ; they have great reſpect paid them, have the firſt places or ſeats in their ſynagogues, determine all matters of controverſy, and frequently pronounce upon civil affairs ; they have even power <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">f</hi>o</hi>  excommunicate the diſobedient.</p><p>RABBIN1STS, among the modern Jews, an appellation given to the doctrine of the rabbins concerning traditions, in oppofition to the Caraites ; who reject all traditions. See Car ait e.</p><p>RABELAIS (Francis), a French writer famous ſor his facetiouſneſs, was born at Chinonin Touraine about the year 1483. . He was ſirſt a Francifcan⅛ friar ; but quitting his religious hablt ſtudied phyſic at Montpelier, where he took his doctor’s degree. It is ſaid, that the chancellor du Pratt ha ing aboliſhed the privileges of the faculty of phyſic atv Montpelier by a decree of the parliament, Rabelais h ad the addreſs to make him revoke what he had don e ; and that thofe who were madc doctors of that univerſity wore Rabelais’s robe, which is there held in great veneration. Some time after, he came to Rome, in quality of phyſician in ordinary to Cardinal John du Bellay archbiſhop of Paris. Rabelais is ſaid to have uſed the freedom to jeer Pope Paul III. to his face. He had quitted his religious connections for the ſake of leading a life more agreeable to his taſte ; but renewed them on a ſecond journey to Rome, when he obtained, in 1536, a brief to qualify him for holding eccleſiaſtical benefices ; and, by the intereſt of his friend Cardinal John du Bellay, he was received as a ſecular canon in the abbey of St Maur near Paris. His profound knowledge in phyſic rendered him doubly uſeful ; he being as ready, and at leaſt as well qualified, to prefcribe for the body as for the foul : but as he was a man of wit and humour, many ridiculous things are laid to his charge, of which he was quite innocent. He publiſhed ſeveral things ; but his chief performance is a ſtrange incoherent romance, called the <hi rend="italic">IIfiory oſ Gargantua and Pantagruel,</hi>  being a ſatire upon prieſts, popes, fools, and knaves of all kinds. This work contains a wild, irregular profuſion of wit, learning, obſcenſty, low conceits, and arrant nonſenſe ; hence thc ſhrewd-neſs of his ſatire, in ſome places where he is to be underſtood, gains him credit ſor thoſe where no meaning is diſcoverable. Some alluſions may undoubtedly have been ſo temporary and local as to be now quite loſt : but it is too much to conclude thus in favour of every unintelligible rhapſody ; for we are not without Engliſh writers of great talents, whoſe ſportive geniufes have betrayed them into puerilities, no leſs incoherent at</p></body></text></TEI>