<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Rdwards,-and. Edwards recovers a recompense <hi rend="italic">ef</hi>  equal value againſt Barker the firſt vouchee ; who recovers the like againſt Morland the common vouchee, againſt whom ſuch ideal recovery in value is always ultimately awarded.</p><p>This ſuppoſed reeompenſe in value is the reaſon why the iſſue in tail is held to be barred by a common recovery. For, if the reeoveree ſhould obtain a recom-penſe in lands from the-common vouchee (which there is a poſſibility in contemplation of law, though a very improbable one, of hiε doing), theſe lands would ſup-ply the place of thoſe ſo recovered from him by co!lu-dſion, and would deſcend to the iſſue in tail. The reafon will alfo hold with equal force as to meſt remainder-mien and reverſioners, to whom the poſſibility will re-main land revert, as a full recompenfe for the reality which they were otherwiſe entitled to: but it will not always hold ; and therefore, as Pigott ſays, the judges have been even <hi rend="italic">ajluti,</hi>  in inventing other reaſons to maintain the authority of recoveries. And, in par-ticular, it hath been ſaid, that though the eſtate-tail is gone from the recoveree ; yet it is not deſtroyed, but only transferred, and ſtill ſubſiſts ; and will ever con-tin ue to ſubſiſt (by conſtruction of law) in the reco-veror, his heirs and aſſigns : and as the eſtate-tail fo continues to fubſiſt for ever, the remainders or reversions expectant on the determination of ſuch eſtate-tail can never take place.</p><p>To ∙fiιch aukward ſhifts, ſuch ſubtile refinements, and inch ſtrafige reaſoning, were our anceſtors obliged to have recourſe, in order to get the better of-that ſtub-born ſtatute <hi rend="italic">de donis.</hi>  The deſign for which theſe contrivances were ſet on foot, was certainly laudable ; the tmrivetιing the fetters of eſtatestail, which were attended with a legion of miſchiefs to the commonwealth: but, while we applaud the end, we cannot but admire the means, our modern courts of juſtice have indeed adopted a move manly way of treating the ſubject ; by eonſidering common recoveries, in no other light than as the formal mode of conveyance by which tenant in tail is enabled to aliene his lands. But, ſince the ill ■eonſequences of fettered inheritances are now generally feeai arid allowed, and of courſe the utility and expedience of fitting them at liberty are apparent, it hath often been wiſhed that the proceſs of this conveyance was ſhortened, and rendered leſs ſubject to niceties, by either totally repealing the ſtatute <hi rend="italic">de donis ;</hi>  which per-haps,- by reviving the old doctrine of conditional fees, might give birth to many litigations : or by veſting in every tenant in tail, of full age, the fame abſolute feeſſimple at once, which now he may obtain whenever •he pleafis, by the colhſſive fiction of a common recovery ; though this might poffibly bear hard upon thofe ’ir. remainder or reverſion, by abridging the chances they would otherwiſe frequently have, as no recovery can be ſuffered in the intervals between term and term,</p><p>. which ſometimes continue for -near five months toge-ther : or, laſtly, by empowering the tenant in tad.to bar the eſtate-tail by a ſolemn deed, to be made in term-time, and enrolled in ſome·court of.record ; which is liable to neither of the other objections, and is warranted not only- by .the uſage of our American colonies, but by the precedent of the ſtatute 21 Jac. I. c. ∣ 9 which, in the. cafi of !a bankrupt tenant in tail, empowers his commiſſioners tq fc4l the eſtate at any t<hi rend="sub">4</hi>iae<hi rend="sub">y </hi>  by deed indented and enrolled. Aud if, in ſo national</p><p>a concern, th¢ emoluments of the officers concerned in paſſing recoveries are thought to be worthy attention, thofe might be provided for in the fees to be paid upon each enrollment.</p><p>2. The force and effect of common recoveries may appear, from what has been ſaid, to be an abſolute bar not only of all eſtates tail, but of remaindeιs and re-verſions expectant on the determination of ſuch eſtates. So that a tenant in tail may, by this method of aſſu-rance, convey the lands held iu tail to the recoverer, his heirs and affigns, abſolutely free and diſcharged of all conditions and limitations· in tail, and of all remainders and reverſions. But, by ſtatute 34. &amp; 35 H. VIIL c. 2c. no recovery had againſt tenant in tail of the king’s gift, whereof the. remainder or reverſion is in the king, ſhall bar ſuch eſtate-tail, or the remainder or reverſion oſ the crown. And by the ſtatute 11 H. VIL· c. 2c. no woman, after her huftand<hi rend="sup">,</hi>6 death, ſhall fuffer a recovery of lands fettled on her by her huſhand, or fettled on her huſhand and her by any of his anceſtors-And by ſtatute 14 Eliz. c. 8. no tenant for life, of any fort, can fiιffer a recovery fo a3 to bind them in remainder or reverſion. For which reaſon, if there be tenant for life, with remainder in tail, and other remainders over, and the tenant for Iife is deſirous to fnffer a valid recovery, either he, or the tenant to the<hi rend="italic">precipe</hi>  by him made, muſt vouch the remainder-man in tail, otherwiſe the recovery is void : but if he does vouch ſuch remainder-man, and he appears and vouches the common vouchee, it is then good ; for if a man be vouched and appears, and ſuffers the recovery to be had, it is as effectual to ‘ bar the eſtate-tail as if he himfclf were the recoveree.</p><p>In all recoveries, it is neceſſary that the recoveree,. or tenant to the <hi rend="italic">prαcipe,</hi>  as he is ufiually called, be actually fiifid of the freehold, elfi the recovery is void. For all actions to recover the fiiſin of lands muſt be brought againſt the actual tenant of the freehold, elſe the fuit will loſe its effect ; ſince the freehold cannot be recovered of him who has it not. And, though theſe recoveries are in themfelves fabulous and fictitious, yet it is neceſſary that there be <hi rend="italic">actores 1αbui&lt;ε.</hi>  properly qualified. But the nicety thought by ſome modern practitioners to.be requiſite in conveying the legal freehold, in order to make a good tenant to the <hi rend="italic">pracipe, </hi>is removed bv the proviſions of-the ſtatute 14 Geo. IL c. 20. which enacts, with a retroſpect and conformity to tlιe ancient rul¢ of law, that, though the legal freehold be veſted in leſſees, yet thoſe who are entitled to the next freehold eſtate in remainder, or reverſion, may make a good tenant to the <hi rend="italic">rrœcipe ;</hi>  and that, though the deed or fine which creates ſuch tenant be fiιbie-quent to the judgment of recovery, yet iſ it be in the ſame term, the recovery ſhall be valid in law : and that though the recovery itfilf·do not appear to be entered, or be not regularly entered on record, yet the deed to make a tenant to the <hi rend="italic">prœàpe</hi>  and declare the uſes of the recovery, ſhall after a poſſeſſion of 20 years be ſufficient evidence on behalf of a purchaſer for valuable conſideration, that ſuch recovery was duly ſuffered.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Recover,v of perſons drowned, or apparently dead See Re-am π ation, and the articles there referred to.</hi></p><p>RECREANT, Cowardly, <hi rend="italic">Fuint-h earted;</hi>  formerly a word very reproachful. See Battel..</p><p>RECREMEN Γ, in chemiſtry, feme fμperfjupus matter fcparated from ſome other that is uſeful ; in·</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>