<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a voi&lt;L He never ſaw the wake perfectly tranfparent (and therefore completely ſilled with water) when the velocity exceeded 9 or ι o feet per ſecond. while this broken water is obferved, there can be no doubt that there is a void and an additional refiſtance. But even when the ſpace left by the body, or the ſpace behind a ſtill body expofed to a ſtream, is completely ſilled, it may not be ſilled ſuſſiciently faſt, and there may be («and certainly is, as we ſhall fee afterwards)· a quantity of water behind the body, which is moving more ſlowly away than the reſt, and therefore hangs in ſome ſhape by the body, and is dragged by it, increafing the reſiſtance. The quantity of this muſt depend partly on the velocity of the body or ſtream, and partly on the rapidity with which the ſurrounding water comes in behind. This laſt muſt depend on the preſſure of the ſurrounding water. It would appear, that when this adjoining- preſſure is very great, as muſt happen when the depth is great, the augmentation of reſiſtance now ſpoken of would be lefs. Accordingly this appears in Newton’s experiments, where the balls were leſs retarded as they were deeper under water.</p><p>Theſe experiments are ſo ſimple in their nature, and were made with fuch care, and by a perſon ſo able to detect and appreciate every circumſtance, that they de-ſerve great credit, and the concluſions <hi rend="italic">legitimately</hi>  drawn from them deſerve to be conſidered as phyfical laws, we think that the preſent deduction is unexception-able : for in the motion of balls, which hardly deſcen-ded, their preponderancy being hardly ſenſible, the effect of depth muſt have borne a very great proportion to the whole reſiſtance, and muſt have greatly influenced their motions ; yet they were obſerved to fall as if the refiſtance had no way depended on the depth.</p><p>The ſame thing appears in Borda’s experiments, where a ſphere which was deeply immerſed in the water was leſs reſiſted than one that moved with the ſame velocity near the ſurface ; and this was very conſtant and regular in a courſe of experiments. D’Ulloa, however, affirms the contrary : He ſays that the reſiſtance of a board, which was a foot broad, immerfed one foot in a ſtream moving two feet per ſecond, was 15⅜ lbs⅛ and the reſiſtance to the ſame board, when immerſed 2 ſeet in a ſtream moving if feet per ſecond (in which caſe the ſurface was 2 feet), was 264 pounds (a).</p><p>we are very ſorry that we cannot give a proper account of this theory of reſiſtance by Don George Juan D’Ul-loa, an author of great mathematical reputation, and the inlpector of the marine academies in Spain, we have not been able to procure either the original or the French tranſlation, and judge of it only by an extract by Mr Prony in his <hi rend="italic">Architecture Hydraulique, §</hi>  868. &amp;c. The theory is enveloped (according to Mr Prony’s cuſtom) in the moſt complicated expreſſions, ſo that the phyſical principles are kept almoſt out of ſight. when accommodated to the ſimpleſt poſſible caſe, it is nearly as follows.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">0</hi>  be an elementary oriſice or portion of the ſurface of the ſide of a veſſel ſilled with a heavy fluid, and let <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  be its depth under the horizontal ſurface of the fluid. Let ί be the denſity of the fluid, and ;&gt;  the ac-celerative power of gravity, =32 feet velocity acqui-red in a ſecond.</p><p>It is known, ſays he, that the water would flow out at this hole with the velocity <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  ≈ V<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  2<hi rend="italic">fh,</hi>  anda<hi rend="sup">2</hi>^3ιA</p><p><hi rend="italic">u<hi rend="sup">z</hi></hi></p><p>and <hi rend="italic">h —— ∙ </hi>It is alſo known that the preſſure <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  on</p><p>the oriſice <hi rend="italic">0 is φ 0 $ h, :=:&lt;;&gt; 0 $ <hi rend="sup">t</hi>^~, ~</hi>  ∙∣∙ ί 0 a<hi rend="sup">,</hi>.</p><p>2 <hi rend="italic">T&gt;</hi></p><p>Now let this little ſurface <hi rend="italic">0</hi>  be ſuppoſed to mov¢" with the velocity <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">t</hi>υ.</hi>  The ſiuid would meet it with the velocity <hi rend="italic">u -fi v,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">u — v,</hi>  according as it moved in the oppoſite or in the ſame direction with the efflux. In the equation <hi rend="italic">p ~ l<hi rend="sub">r</hi>  S 0 u<hi rend="sup">1</hi>,</hi>  ſubſtitute <hi rend="italic">u τ±z</hi>  &lt;u for <hi rend="italic">u,</hi>  and we have the preſſure on <hi rend="italic">0 ~ ρ ■=. -~- (u</hi>  ∑±c <hi rend="italic">v} =</hi></p><p>( V<hi rend="sup">z</hi><hi rend="italic">2d z±z</hi>  &lt;υ<hi rend="sup">1</hi>).</p><p>This preſſure is a weight, that is, a maſs of matter <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  actuated by gravity <hi rend="italic">t,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">p = f m,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">m = o</hi></p><p>r√^→<hi rend="sub">z</hi>-2L.y.</p><p>∖    √2f∕</p><p>This elementary ſurface being immerſed in a ſtag-nant ſtuid, and moved with the velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi>  will ſuſtaiiv on one ſide a preſſure <hi rend="italic">0</hi>  (<hi rend="sup">vzz,+</hi>  √rj'and on the</p><p>other ſide a preſſure &lt;-<hi rend="sup">r</hi><hi rend="italic">0 h —</hi>  ζZ~) ’ <hi rend="sup">an</hi>^<hi rend="sup">t</hi>^<hi rend="sup">ιe</hi>  ^<hi rend="sup">en</hi>' ſible reſiſtance will be the difference of theſe two preffures, which is<hi rend="italic">$ 0</hi>  4 5/ <hi rend="italic">h —— , </hi>or &lt;f <hi rend="italic">0</hi>  4 <hi rend="italic">h —</hi>, that</p><p>√2P    8</p><p>is, —--γ<hi rend="sup">r</hi>  becaufe <hi rend="italic">f2T<hi rend="sub">f</hi>&gt;= S ;</hi>  a quantity which is 2</p><p>in the ſubduplicate ratio of the depth under the ſurface of the fluid, and the ſimple ratio of the velocity of the reſiſted furface jointly.</p><p>There is nothing in experimental philoſophy more certain than that the reſiſtances are very nearly in the duplicate ratio of the velocities ; and we cannot conceive by what experiments the ingenious author has ſupported this concluſion.</p><p>But there is, beſides, what appears to us to be an eſſential defect in this inveſtigation. The equation ex-hibits no reſiſtance in the caſe of a fluid without weight. Now a theory of the reſiſtance of fluids ſhould exhibit the retardation ariſing from inertia alone, and ſhould di-ſtinguiſh it from that ariſing from any other cauſe: and. moreover, while it <hi rend="italic">ajfigns</hi>  an ultimate ſenſible reſiſtance proportional <hi rend="italic">(c&amp;teris paribus)</hi>  to the ſimple velocity, it <hi rend="italic">aj]umes</hi>  as a ſirſt principle that the preſſure <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  is as <hi rend="italic">u u±zv ∙ </hi>It alſo gives a falſe meaſure of the ſſatical preſſures ⅞ for theſe (in the caſe of bodies immerſed in our waters at leaſt) are made up of the preſſure of the incumbent water, which is meaſured by <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  and the preſſure of the atmoſphere, a conſtant quantity.</p><p>whatever 1eafon can be given for ſetting out with-the principle that the preſſure on the little furface 0, moving with the velocity <hi rend="italic">u,</hi>  is equal to ⅜ <hi rend="italic">io</hi>  (w=±&gt;u)<hi rend="sup">i</hi>, makes it indiſpenſably neceſſary to take for the velocity</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi>  There is ſomethſhg very unaccountable in theſe experiments. The·reſiſtances are much greater than any-•ther author has obſerved,</p></body></text></TEI>