<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Their genius is Cumulated to commerce, by the example of their neighbours of Glaſgow, as well as tbe convenience of the river and frith of Clyde, along the courſe of which they are ſituated.</p><p>RENNES, a town of France, in Bretagne, and capital of that province. Before the revolution it had a biſhop’s ſee, two abbeys, a parliament, and a mint. It is very populous ; the houſes are fix or feven ſtories high, and the ſuburbs of larger extent than the toιvn itfeif. The cathedral church is large, and the parlia-ment-houſe a handſome ſtructure. The great ſquare belonging to it is ſurrounded with handlome houfes. There is a tower, formerly a pagan temple, which now contains the town-clock. It is ſeated on the river VÜ-laine, which divides it into two parts, and was ancient-ly fortified, but the walls are now in ruins, and the ditch nearly ſilled up. The ſiege of the city by Ed-ward III. king of England, is very celebrated in hi-ſtory. The Engliſh and Breton army conſiſted of 40,000 men ; and nevertheleſs, after having remained before it fix months, were obliged to retire without ſucceſs. E. Long. o. 23. N. Lat. 48. 7.</p><p>RENNET. See Runnet,</p><p>RENT, in law, a ſum of money, or other conſidera-tion, iffuing yearly out oſ lands or tenements.</p><p>RENTE RING, in the manufactories, the ſame with ſine-drawing. It confiſts in ſewing two pieces of cloth edge to edge, without doubling them, ſo that the ſeam ſcaree appears ; and hence it is denominated<hi rend="italic">fine-drawing. </hi>lt is a French word meaning the ſame thing, and is derived from the Latin <hi rend="italic">reirahere,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">re, in,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">trahere, </hi>becauſe the ſeam is drawn in or covered. WC are told*, that in the Eaſt Indies, if a piece of fine muſiin be torn and afterwards mended by the ſine-drawers, it will be impoſſible to diſcover where the rent was. Irf this country the dexterity of the ſine-drawers is not ſo great as that of thoſe in the eaſt ; but it is ſtill ſuch as to enable them to defraud the revenue, by fewing a head or ſlip of Engliſh cloth on a piece of Dutch, Spaniſh, or other foreign cloth : or a ſiip of foreign cloth on a piece of Engliſh, ſo as to paſs the whole as of a piece ; and by that means avoid the duties, penalties, &amp;c. The trick was ſirſt diſcovered in France by M. Savary.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Renterino, in tapeſtry, is the working new warp into a piece of damaged tapeſtry, whether eaten by the rats or otherwife deſtroyed, and on this warp to reſtore the ancient pattern or deſign. The warp is to be of woollen, not linen. Among the titles of the French tapeſtry makers is included that of renterers. Fine-drawing is particularly uſed for a rent or hole, which happens in dreſſing or preparing a piece of cloth art-fully ſewed up or mended with lilk. All fine-drawings are reckoned defects or blemiſhes ; and ſhould be allow-</hi>¢d for in the price of the piece.</p><p>RENVERSE, inverted, in heraldry, is when any thing is ſet with the head downwards, or contrary to its natural way of ſtanding. Thus, a chevron renverfé, is a chevron with the point downwards. They uſe alſo the ſame term when a beaſt is laid on its back.</p><p>RENUNCIATION, the act of renouncing, abdi-&lt;cating, or relinquiſhing, any right, real or pretended.</p><p>REPARTEE, a fmart⅛ ready reply, eſpecially in matters of wit, humour, or raillery. See Raillery.</p><p>REPEALING, in law, the revoking or annulling of a ſtatute or the like.</p><p>No act of parliament ſhall be repealed the ſame ſeffion in which it was made. A deed or will may be repealed in part, and ſtand good ſor the reft. It is held that a pardon of felony may be repealed on diſproving the ſuggeſtion thereof.</p><p>REPELLENTS, in medicine, remedies which drive back a morbid humour into the maſs of blood, from whence it was unduly ſecreted.</p><p>REPENTANCE, in general, means ſorrow for any thing paſt. In theology it means ſuch a ſorrow for fin as produces newneſs of life, or ſuch a conviction of the evil and danger of a iinful courſe as is ſuſſicient to produce ſhame and ſorrow in the review of it, and effectual refolutions of amendment. In this ſenſe the evangelical writers uſe ^∙erα<hi rend="sub">l</hi>usλtiα <hi rend="sub">an</hi>J ∕ziτa.oιa. S<hi rend="sub">ee</hi> Penitence and Theology.</p><p>REPERCUSSION, in muſic, a frequent repetition of the fame found.</p><p>REPERTORY, a place wherein things are orderly diſpoſed, ſo as to be eaſily found when wanted. The indices of books are repertories, ſhowing where the matters fought for are treated of. Common-place books are alſo kinds of repertories.</p><p>REPETITION, the reiterating of an action.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Repetition, in muſic, denotes a reiterating or playing over again the ſame part of a compoſition, whether it be a whole ſtrain, part of a ſtrain, or double ſtrain, &amp;c.</hi></p><p>when the ſong ends with a repetition of the firſt ſtrain, or part of it, the repetition is denoted by <hi rend="italic">da</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">capo,</hi>  or D. C. <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>  " from the beginning.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Repetition, in rhetoric, a figure which gracefully and emphatically repeats either the fame word, or thc ſame ſenſe in different words. See oratory, n</hi><hi rend="sup">0</hi>  67 — 80.</p><p>The nature and defign of this figure is to make deep impreſſions on thoſe we addreſs. It expreffes anger and indignation, full aifurance of what we affirm, and a ve-hement concern for what we have eſpouſed.</p><p>REPH1DIM (anc. geog.), a ſtation of the Iſrael-ites near mount Horeb, where they murmured for want of water; when Moſes was ordered to fmite the rock Horeb, upon which it yielded water. Here Joſhua dif-comfited the Amalekites. This rock, out of which Moſes brought water, is a ſtone of a prodigious height and thickneſs, riſing out of the ground ; on two ſides of which are ſeveral holes, by which the water ran. (Thevenot.)</p><p>REPLEGIARE, in law, ſignifies to redeem a thing taken or detained by another, by putting in legal fureties.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">De homing REPLEGIANDO. See Homine.</hi></p><p>REPLEVIN, in law, a remedy granted on a diſtreſs, by which the fi ſt poffeffor has his goods reſtored to him again, on his giving ſecurity to the ſheriff that he will purſue his action againſt the party diſtraining, and return the goods or cattle if the taking them ſliall be adjudged lawful.</p><p>In a replevin the perſon diſtrained becomes plaintiff ; and the perſon diſtraining is called the <hi rend="italic">defendant</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">avowant,</hi>  and his juſtification an <hi rend="italic">avowry.</hi></p><p>At the common law replevins are by writ, either out of the king’s-bench or common-pleas ; but by ſtatute, they are by plaint in the ſheriff’s cyurt, and court-baron, for a perfon’g more ſpeedily obtaining the goods diſtrained.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>