<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to run along the ſurface. "water rails (ſays Buffon) are ſeen near the perennial fountains during the greateſt. part of the winter, yet like the land rails they haye their regular migrations. They paſs Malta in the ſpring and au-tumn. The Viſcount de Querhoent ſaw ſome 50 leagues off the coaſts of Portugal on the 17th of April. They were ſo fatigued, that they ſuffered themielves to be caught by the hand (a). Gmelin found theie birds in the countries watered, by the Don. ,Belon calls them <hi rend="italic">black rails,</hi>  and ſays they are everywhere known, and that the ſpecies is more numerous than the red rail, or land rail. * The fleſh of the water rail is not ſo delicate as that of the land rail, and has even a marſhy taſte, nearly like that of the gallinule. It continues the whole year in England.”</p><p>2. The porzana, or gallinule, is not very frequent in Great Britain, and is ſaid to be migratory. Inhabits the ſides of ſmall ſtreams, concealing itſelf among the buſhes. Its length is nine inches ; its breadth, 15 ; its weight, four ounces five drachms. d he head is brown, fpotted with black ; the neck a deep olive, fpotted with white : the feathers of the back are black next their ſhafts, then olive-coloured, and edged with white ; the ſcapulars are olive, finely marked with two ſmall white ſpots on each web : the legs of a yellowiſh green. " Its habits (fays Buffon) wild, its inſtinct ſtupid, the porzana is unſuſceptible of education, nor is even ca-pable of being tamed, we raiſed one, however, which lived a whole ſummer on crumbs of bread and hemp-feed; when by itſelf, it kept conſtantly in a large bowl of v ater ; but if a perſon entered the cloſet where it was ſhut, it ran to conceal itſelf in a ſmall dark corner, without vent-ing cries or murmurs. In the ſtate ot liberty, hυweveι, it has a ſharp piercing voice, much like the ſcieam. of a young bud of prey ; and though it has no propenſity to ſociety, as ſoon as one cries, another repeats the found, which is thus conveyed through all the ιeit in the diſtrict. Like all the rails, it is ſo obſtinately averſe to riſe, that the ſportſman often ſeizes it with his hand, or fells it with a ſtick. If it finds a buſh in its retreat, it climbs upon it, and from the top of its aſylum beholds tlie dogs bruſhing along in iault : this habit is common to it and to the water-rail. It dives, ſwims, and even fwims under water, when hard puſhed.</p><p>" Theſe birds diiappear in the depth of winter, but re-turn early in the ſpring ; and even in the month of Fe-bruary they are common in ſome provinces of 1 rance and Italy. Ί heir fleſh is delicate, and much eſteemed : thoſe, in particular, which are caught in the 1 ice-fields in Piedmont are very fat, and of an exquiſite flavour.”</p><p>3. The crex, crake, or corn-crek, has been ſuppoſed by ſome to be the ſame with the water-rail, and that it differs only by a change of colour at a certain ſeaſon of the year : this error is owing to inattention to their characters and nature, both which differ entirely. The bill of tfiis ſpecies is ſhort, ſtrong, and thick ; formed exactly like that of the water-lien, and makes a generi-cal diſtinction. It never frequents watery places ; but is always found among corn, graſs, broom, or furze. It quits the kingdom before winter; but the water-ιail en-</p><p>dures our ſharpeſt ſeaſons. They agree in their averſion to flight ; and the legs, which are remarkably long for the ſize of the bird, hang down whilſt they are on the wing ; they truſt their ſafety to their _ ſwiftneſs on foot, and ſeldom are ſprung a ſecond time but with great difficulty. The land rail lays from 12 to 20 eggs,-of a dull white colour, marked with a few yellow.ſpots; notwithſtanding this, they are very numerous in thιs-kingdom. 1 heir note is very ſingular; and like the quail, it is decoyed into a net by the imitation of its cry, <hi rend="italic">crëk crek crek,</hi>  by rubbing hard the blade of a knife on an indented bone. Moſt of the names given in different languages to this bird-rare evidently formed to imitate this ſingular cry. Hence Iurner and ſome other naturaliſts have ſuppoſed it to be the crex of the ancients ; but that term appears to have been applied by the ancients to other birds. Philus gives the crex the epithet of ∕⅛α&lt;Juτ)Efθf, or <hi rend="italic">βuggi(h∙winged,</hi>  which would indeed fuit the land-rail. Ariſtophanes repreſents it as migrating from Libya: Ariſtotle ſays that it is quand» ſome, which may have been attributed to it from the analogy to the quail ; but he adds, that the crex ιeeks to deſtroy the neſts of the blackbird, which cannot apply to the rail, ſince it never inhabits the woods. Still leſs is the crex of Herodotus a rail, for he compares its ſize to that of the ibis, which is ten times larger. The avoſet, too, and the teal, have ſometimes the cry <hi rend="italic">crex, crex :</hi>  and the bird which Belon heard repeating that cry on the banks of the Nile is, according to his account, a ſpecies of godwit. Thus the found repreſented by the word <hi rend="italic">erex,</hi>  belonging to ſeveral ſpecies, is not ſufficiently preciſe to diſtinguiſh the land-rail.</p><p>They are in greateſt plenty in Angleſea, where they appear about the 20th of April, ſuppoſed to paſs over from Ireland, where they abound ; at their firſt aπival it is common to ſhoot ſeven or eight in a morning. They are found in moſt of the Hebrides·, and the Drk-neys. Οη their arrival they are very lean, weighing only ſix ounces ; but before they leave this iſland, grow ſo fat as to weigh above eight. The feathers on the crown of the head and hind-part of the neck are black, edged with bay colour : the coverts of the wings of the ſame colour, but not ſpotted ; the tail is ſhort, and of a deep bay : the belly white ; the legs aſh-coloured.</p><p>RALPH (James), a late ingenious hiſtorical and political writer, was born, we know not when or where, being ſirſt known as a ſchoolmaſter in Philadelphia in North America. He came to England about the be-ginning of the reign of George I. and wrote ſome things in the dramatic way, which were not received with great applauſe ; but though he did not ſucceed as a poet, he was a very ingenious proſe-writer. He wrote A Hiſtory of England, commencing with the Stuarts, which is much eſteemed ; as were his political eſſays and pamphlets, ſome of which were looked upon as mafter-pιeces&gt; His laſt publication, The Caſe of Authors by Profeſſion, is an excellent and entertaining performance. He died in 1762.</p><p>RAM,, in zoology. See Ovis.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Battering RAM,</hi>  in antiquity, a military engine uſed</p><lb/><p>f<hi rend="sub">A</hi>I ‘I tried (ſays M. de Querhoent) to raiſe ſome: they thrived wonderfully at firſt, but after a fortnight’s confinement their long l¾ grew paralytic, and the birds could only crawl on their knees ; at laſt they expired.’ Gef∏er ſays, that having long fed one, he found it to be peeviſh and quarrelſome.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>