<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>died John elector of Saxony, who was ſucceeded by his ſon John Frederic, a prince of invincible fortitude and magnanimity, but whoſe reign was little better than one continued train of diſappointments and calamities. The religious truce, however, gave new vigour to the reformation. Thofe who had hitherto been only ſe-cret enemies to the Roman pontiff, now publicly threw off his yoke ; and various cities and provinces of Gcr-jnany enliſted themſelves under the religious ſtandards of Luther. Οη the other hand, as the emperor had now no other hope of terminating the religious diſputes Éut by the meeting of a general council, he repeated his requeſts to the pope for that purpoſe. The pontiff (Clement VII.), whom the hiſtory of paſtcoun-cils filled with the greateſt uneaſineſs, endeavoured to retard what he could not with decency refuſe, At laſt, in 1533, he made a propoſal by his legate to affemble a council at Mantua, Placentia, or Bologna ; but the Proteſtants refuſed their conſent to the nomination of an Italian council, and inſiſted that a controverſy which had its riſe in the heart of Germany, ſhould be deter-mined within the limits of the empire. The pope, by his uſual artifices, eluded the performance of his own promife ; and, in 1534, was cut off by death, in the midſt of his ſtratagems. His ſucceffor Paul III. feem-ed to ſhow leſs reluctance to the aſſembling a general council, and in the year 1535 expreſſed his inclination to convoke one at Mantua ; and, the year following, actually ſent circular letters for that purpoſe through all the ſtates and kingdoms under his juriſdiction. Tin’s council was ſummoned by a bull iſſued out on the 2d of June 1536, to meet at Mantua the following year but ſeveral obſtacles prevented its meeting; one of the moſt material of which was, that Frederic duke of Mantua had no inclination to receive at once ſo many gueſts, ſome of them very turbulent, into the place of his reſidence. Οη the other hand, the Proteſtants were firmly perſuaded that, as the council was aſſembled in</p><p>Italy, and by the authority of the pope alone, the lat-ter muſt have had an undue influence in that aſſembly ; of conſequence, that all things muſt have been carried by the votaries of Rome. For this reaſon they aſſem-bled at Smalcald in the year 1537, where they folemn-ly proteſted againſt this partial and corrupt council, and, at the ſame time, had a new ſummary of their doctrine drawn up by Luther, in order to preſent it to the aſſembled biſhops if it ſhould be required of them. This fummary, which had the title of <hi rend="italic">The Articles oſ Smalcald,</hi>  is commonly joined with the creeds and confeſſions of the Lutheran church.</p><p>After the meeting of the general council in Man-tua was thus prevented, many ſchemes of accommodation were propoſed both by the emperor and the Proteſtants ; but, by the artifices of the church of Rome, all of them came ≠o nothing. In 1541, the emperor appointed a conference at worms on the ſubject of religion, between perſons of piety and learning choſen from the contending parties. This conference, however, was, for certain reaſons, removed to the diet which was to be held at Ratiſhon that fame year, and in which the principal ſubject of deliberation was a me-morial preſented by a perſon unknown, containing a project of peace. But the conference produced no other effect than a mutual agreement of the contending parties to refer their matters to a general council, or, if</p><p>the meeting of ſuch a council ſhould be prevented, to the next German diet.</p><p>This refolution was rendered ineffectual by a variety of incidents, which widened the breach, and put off to a farther day the deliberations which were de-ſigned to heal it. The pope ordered his legate to declare to the diet of Spire, aſſembled in 1542, that he would, according to the promiſe he had already made, aſſemble a general council, and that Trent ſhould be the place of its meeting, if the diet had no objection to that city. Ferdinand, and the princes who adhered to the cauſe of the pope, gave their conſent to this propoſal ; but it was vehemently objected to by the Proteſtants,. both becauſe the council was ſummoned by the authority of the pope only, and al-ſo becauſe the place was within the juriſdiction of the Pope; whereas they deſired a free council, which ſhould not be biaſſed by the dictates, nor awed by the proximity, of the pontiff. But this proteſtation produced no effect. Paul III. perſiſted in his purpoſe, and iſſued. out his circular letters for the convocation of the council, with the approbation of the emperor. In juſtice to this pontiff, however, it muſt be obſerved, that he ſhowed himſelf not to be averſe to every reformation. He appointed four cardinals, and three other perſons eminent for their learning, to draw up a plan for the reformation of the church in general, and of the church of Rome in particular. The reformation propoſed in this plan was indeed extremely fuperficial and partial, yet it contained fome particulars which could ſcarcely have been expected from thoſe who compoſed it. They complained of the pride and ignorance of the biſhops, and propoſed that none ſhould receive orders but learned and pious men ; and that therefore care ſhould be taken to have proper maſters for the inſtruction of youth. They condemned tranſlations from one benefice to another, grants of reſervation, non-reſidence, and pluralities. They propoſed that ſome convents ſhould be aboliſhed ; that the liberty of the preſs ſhould be re-ſtrained and limited ; that the colloquies of Eraſmus ſhould be ſuppreffed ; that no eccleſiaſtic ſhould enjoy a benefice out of his own country ; that no cardinal fnould have a biſhopric ; that the queſtors of St Anthony and ſeveral other ſaints' ſhould be aboliſhed ; and, which was the beſt of all their propoſals, that the effects and perſonal eſtates of eccleſiaſtics ſhonld be given to the poor. They concluded with complaining of the prodigious number of indigent and ragged prieſts who frequented St Peter’s church ; and declared, that it was a great fcandal to fee the whores lodged fo magnificently at Rome, and riding through the ſtreets on . fine mules, while the cardinals and other eccleſiaſtics accompanied them in the moſt courteous manner.— This plan of reformation was turned into ridicule by Luther and Sturmius ; and indeed it left unredreffed the moſt intolerable grievances of which the Proteſtants complained.</p><p>All this time the emperor had been labouring to perfuade the Proteſtants to conſent to the meeting of the council at Trent ; but when he found them fixed in their oppoſition to this meaſure, he began to liſten to the ſanguinary meaſures of the pope, and refolved to terminate the diſputes by force of arms. The elec-tor of Saxony and landgrave of HeiΓe, who were the chief ſupporters of the Proteſtant cauſe, upon this took</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>