<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſtraiglit lines and with an accelerated motion, and at laſt darted into the orifice with great rapidity. He had obſerved a thing ſimilar to this in a horizontal ca-nal, in which he had fet up a ſmall board like a dam or bar, over wh'eh the water flowed. He had thrown a gooſtberry into the water, in order to meaſure the velo-city at the bottom, the goofet&gt;erry being a fmall matter heavier than water. It approached the dam uniformly till about three inches from it. Here it almoſt ſtood ſtill, but it continued to advance till almoſt in contact. It then roſe from the bottom along the inlide of the dam with an accelerated motion, and quickly eſcaped over the top.</p><p>Hence he concluded, that the water which covers the anterior part of the body expofed to the ſtream is not perfectly ſtag.nant, and that the filaments recede from the axis in curves, which converge to the ſurface of the body as different hyperbolas converge to the fame affymptote, and that they move with a velocity continually increafing till they eſcape round the ſides ef the body.</p><p>He had eſtabliſhed (by a pretty reaſonable theory, confirmed by experiment) a propoſition concerning the preffure which water in motion exerts on the ſurface along which it glides, viz. <hi rend="italic">that the prejfure is equal to that which it would exert if at reft</hi>  minus <hi rend="italic">the weight of the column whoſe height would produce the velocity of the paftlng (lream.</hi>  Conſequently the preffure which the ftream exerts on the ſurface perpendicularly expofed to it will depend on the velocity with which it glides along it, and will diminiſh from the centre to the circumference. This, ſays he, may be the reaſon why the impnlſe on a plane wholly immerſed is but one half of that on a plane which deflects the whole ſtream.</p><p>He contrived a very ingenious inſtrument ſor exami-ning this theory. A fquare braſs plate ABGF (fig.</p><p>20.    ) was pierced with a great number of holes, and fixed in the front of a ſhallow box repreſented edgewiſe in fig.</p><p>21.    The back of this box was pierced with a hole r, in which was inferted the tube of glaſs CDE, bent fquare at D. This inſtrument was expofed to a ſtream of water, which beat on the braſs plate. The water having ſilled the box through the holes, ſiood at an equal height in the glaſs tube when the ſurrounding water was ſtagnant ; but when it was in motion, it always ſiood in the tube above the level of the ſmooth water without, and thus indicated the preffure occaſion-ed by the action of the ſtream.</p><p>when the inſtrument was not wholly immerfed, there was always a conſiderable accumulation againſt the front of the box, and a depreſſion behind it. The water before it was by no means ſtagnant : indeed it ſhould not be, as Mr Buat obſerves ; for it conſiſts of the water which was eſcaping on all ſides, and therefore upwards from the axis of the ſtream, which meets the plate perpendi-cularly in <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  conſiderably under the ſurface. It eſcapes upwards ; and if the body were fuſſiciently immerſed, it would eſcape in this direction almoſt as eaſily as laterally. But in the preſent circumſtances, it heaps up, till the elevation occaſions it to fall off ſidewiſe as faſt as it is renewed, when the inſtrument was immerfed more than its ſemidiameter under the ſurface, the water- ſtill roſe above the level, and there was a great depreſſion immediately behind this elevation. In con-Lquence of this difficulty of eſcaping upwards, the wa-ter flows off laterally ; and if the horizontal dim¢nſions of the lurface is great, this lateral efflux becomes more difficult, and requires a greater accumulation. From this it happens, that the reſiſtance of broad ſurfaces equally immerſed is greater than in the proportion of the breadth. A plane of two feet wide and one foot deep, when it is not completely immerſed, will be more refilled than a plane two feet deep and one foot wide ; ſor there will be an accumulation againſt both : and even if theſe were equal in height, the additional fur-face will be greateſt in the wideſt body ; and- the ele-vation will be greater, becaufe the lateral eſcape is more difficult.</p><p>The circumſtances chiefly to be attended to are theſe.</p><p>The preffure on the centre was much greater than towards the border, and, in general, the height oſ the water in the tube DE was more than ∙∣ of the height ue-ceffary for producing the velocity when only the central hole was open, when various holes were opened at different diſtances from the centre, the height of the water in DH continually diminiſhed as the hole was nearer the border. At a certain diſtance from the border the water at E was level with the ſurrounding water, ſo that no preffure was exerted on that hole. But the moft unexpected and remarkable circumſtance was, that, in great velocities, the holes at the very border, and even to a ſmall diſtance from it, not only ſuſtained no preffure, but even gave out water ; for the water in the tube was lower than the ſurrounding water. Mr Buat calls this a <hi rend="italic">r.on-prejfιυn.</hi>  In a caſe in which the velocity ot the ſtream was three feet, and the preffure on the central hole cauſed the water in the vertical tube to ſtahd 33 lines or ⅜⅜ of an inch above the level of the ſuriounding ſmooth water, the action on a hole at the lower corner of the ſquare cauſed it to ſtand 12 line» lower than the furrounding water. Now the velocity of the ſtream in this experiment was 36 inches <hi rend="italic">per</hi>  ſecond. This requires 21⅜ lines for its productive fall ; whereas thc preffure on the central hole was 33. This approaches to the preffure on a ſurface which deflects it wholly. The intermediate holes gave every variation of preffure, and the diminution was more rapid as the holes were nearer the edge j but the law of diminution could not be obferved.</p><p>This is quite a new and moſt unexpected circumſtance in the action of fluids on ſolid bodies, and renders the ſubject more intricate than ever ; yet it is by no means inconliſtent with the genuine principles of hydroſtatics or hydraulics. In as far as Mr Buat’s propoſttion conccrning the preffure of moving fluids is true, it is very reaſonable to fay, that when the lateral velocity with which the fluid tends to eſcape exceeds the velocity of percuiſion, the height neceffa-ry for producing this velocity muſt exceed that which would produce the other, and a non-preffion muſt be obſerved. And if we conſider the forms of the la-teral filaments near the edge of the body, we ſee that the concavity of the curve is turned towards the body, and that the centrifugal forces tend to diminiſh. their preffure on the body. If the middle alone were ſtruck with a confiderable velocity, the water might even rebound, as is frequently obferved. This <hi rend="italic">actual </hi>rebounding is here prevented by the ſurrounding water, which is moving with the fame velocity ; but</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>