<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">a </hi><hi rend="italic">pmom,</hi>  what will be the motion of the fluid whoſe courſe is obſtructed by a body of any form. And here we cannot omit taking notice of the caſual ob-fervation of Sir Iſaac Newton when attempting to de-termine the reſiſtance of the plane ſurface or cylinder, or ſphere expofed to a ſtream moving in a canal. He fays that the form of the reſiſt ing ſurface is of leſs con-ſequence, becauſe there is always a quantity of water ſtagnant upon it, and which may therefore be conſider-ed as frozen,; and he therefore conſiders that water only whoſe motion is neceffary for the moſt expedi-tious diſcharge of the water in the veffel. He endeavours to diſcriminate that water from the reſt ; and although it muſt be acknowledged that the principle which he affumes for this purpoſe is very gratuitous, becauſe it only ſhows that <hi rend="italic">iſ certain portions oſ the water,</hi>  which he determines very ingeniouſly, were really frozen, the reſt will iffue as he ſays, and will exert the preffure which he aſſigns ; ſtill we muſt admire his fertility of reſource, and his ſagacity in thus foreſeeing what ſubſequent obſervation has completely confirmed, we are even diſpoſed to think, that in this caſual ob--ſervation Sir Iſaac Newton has pointed out the only method of arriving at a folution of the problem ; and that if we could diſcover <hi rend="italic">what motions are not neceſſary ſor the mοβ expeditious paſſage oſ the water,</hi>  and could thus determine the form and magnitude of the ſtagnant water which adheres to the body, we ſhould much more eaſily aſcertain the real motions which occaſion the obſerved reſiſtance. we are here diſpoſed to have recourſe to the economy of nature, the improper uſe of which we have ſometimes taken the liberty of reprehend-jng. Mr Maupertuis publiſhed as a great diſcovery his principle of ſmalleſt action, where he ſhowed that in all the mutual actions of bodies the quantity of action was a minimum ; and he applied this to the folution of many difficult problems with great ſucceſs, ima-gining that he was really reaſoning from a contingent law of nature, ſelected by its infinitely wiſe Author, viz. that in all occaſions there is the ſmalleſt poſſible exertion of natural powers. Mr D’Alembert has, however, ſhown <hi rend="italic">(vi&amp;. Encyclopédie Françoifi, </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Action) that this was but a whim, and that the minimum obſerved by Mau-pertuis is merely a minimum of calculus, peculiar to a formula which happens to expreſs a combination of mathematical quantities which frequently occurs in our way of conſidering the phenomena of nature, but which is no natural meaſure of action.</hi></p><p>But the chevalier D’Arcy has ſhown, that in the trains of natural operations which terminate in the pro-duction of motion in a particular direction, the interme-diate communications of motion are ſuch that the ſmall-eſt poſſible quantity of motion is produced, we ſeem obliged to conclude, that this law.will be obſerved in the preſent initance ; and it ſeems a problem not above our reach to determine the motions which reſult from it. we would recommend the problem to the eminent mathematicians in ſome ſimple caſe, ſuch as the propo-ſition already demonſtrated by Daniel Bernoulli, or the perpendicular impulſe on a cylinder included in a tubular canal ; and if they ſucceed in this, great things may be expected, we think that experience gives great encouragement, we ſee that the r£ſiſiance to a plane ſurface is a very ſmall matter greater than the weight of a column of the fluid having the fall productive of</p><p>the velocity for its height, and the ſmall exceſs is moſt probably owing to adheſion, and the meaſure of the real reſiſtance is probably preciſely this weight. The velocity oſ a ſpouting fluid was found, in fact, to be that acquired by falling from the ſurface of the fluid ; and it was by looking at this, as at a pole ſtar, that Newton, Bernoulli, and others, have with great ſagaci-ty and ingenuity diſcovered much of the laws of hy-draulics, by ſearching for principles which would give this reſult. we may hope for ſimilar ſucceſs.</p><p>In the mean time, we may receive this as a phyfical truth, that the perpendicular impulſe or reſiſtance of a plane ſurſace, wholly immerſed in the fluid, is equal to the weight of the column haring the ſurface for its baſe, and the fall producing the velocity for its height.</p><p>This is the medium reſult of all experiments made in tbeſe precife circumftances. And it is confirmed by a ſet of experiments of a kind wholly different, and which feem to point it out more certainly as an im-mediate conſequence of hydraulic principles.</p><p>If Mr Pitot’s tube be expofed to a ſtream of fluid iffuing from a reſervoir or veffel, as repreſented in ſig. 14. with the open mouth I pointed directly againſt the ftream, the fluid is obſerved to Hand at K in the upright tube, preciſely on a level with the fluid AB in the reſervoir. Here is a moſt unexceptionable experi-ment, in which the impulſe of the ſtream is actually oppoſed to the hydroſtatical preffure of the fluid on the tube. Preffure is in this caſe oppoſed to preffure, be-cauſe the iffuing fluid is deflected by what flays in the mouth of the tube, in the ſame way in which it would be deflected by a firm ſurface. we ſſiall have occafion by and by to mention ſome moſt valuable and inſtruc-tive experiments made with this tube.</p><p>It was this which ſuggeſted to the great mathema-tician Euler another theory of thé impulſe and reſiſtance of fluids, which muſt not be omitted, as it is applied in his elaborate performance Οη the Theory of the Conſtruction and working of Ships, in two vo-lumes 4to, which was afterwards abridged and uſed as a text book in ſome marine academies. He fuppoſes a ſtream of fluid ABCD (fig. 15.), moving with any ve-locity, to ſtrike the plane ËD perpendicularly, and that part of it goes through a hole EF, forming a jet EGHF. Mr Euler ſays, that the velocity of this jet will be the ſame with the velocity of the ſtream. Now compare this with an equal ſtream iffuing from a hole in the ſide of a veffel with the fame velocity. The one ftream is urged out by the preffure occaſioned by the impulſe of the fluid ; the other is urged out by the preffure of gravity. The effects are equal, and the modifying circumftances are the fame. The cauſes are therefore equal, and the preffure occaſioned by the im-pulſe of a ſtream of fluid, moving with any velocity, is equal to the weight of a column of fluid whoſe height is productive of this velocity, &amp;c. He then determines the oblique impulſe by the refolution of motion, and deduces the common rules of reſiſtance, &amp;c.</p><p>But all this is without juſt grounds. This gentle-man was always ſatisſied with the ſlighteſt analogies which would give him. an opportunity of exhibiting his great dexterity in algebraic analyſis, and was not afterwards llartled by any diſcordancy with obſervation. <hi rend="italic">Analyfit magis fidendum</hi>  is a frequent affertion with him.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>