<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>thc goδd and a hell for the wicked. In this heaven the faints dwell in the preſence of God and the unin-terrupted ſplendors- of day. Thoſe who have been wife ſhine as the firmament, and thoſe who have converted many to righteouſneſs as the ſtars. Their bodies are glorious, immortal, incorruptible, not ſubject to diſeaſe, to pain, or to death. Their minds are ſtrangers to ſor-rtrw, to crying, to diſappointment ; all their deſires are preſently ſatisſied ; while they are calling, they are aπ-ſwered ; while they are fpeaking, they are heard. Their mental faculties are alſo enlarged ; they no more ſee things obfcurely, and as through a cloud, but continu-ally beholding new wonders and beauties in creation, are conſtantly exclaiming^ " Holy, holy, holy ! is the Lord of Hoſts, worthy is he to receive glory, and honour, and th’inkſgiving ; and to him be afcribed wiſdom, and power, and might; for great and marvellous are his works, and the whole univerſe is filled with his glory.”</p><p>Their notions of hell differ conſiderably. Some un-derſtanding the Scriptures literally, have plunged the v⅛ icſked into an abyſs without any bottom ; have made this g∏lρh darker than night ; have ſilled it with rancorous and malignant ſpirits, that are worſe than furies ; and have deſcribed it as lull of ſulphur, burning for ever. This frightful gulph has by ſome been placed in the bowels of the earth ; by ſome in the fun ; by ſome in the moon ; and by ſome in a comet : but as the Scriptures have determined nothing on the ſubject, all ſuch conjectures are idle and groundless.</p><p>others imagine, that the fire and ſulphur are here to be taken in a figurative ſenfe. Thefe fuppoſe the torments of hell to be troubles of mind and remorfes of conſcience ; and ſupport their opinion by obſerving, that matter cannot act upon ſpirit ; forgetting, perlιaps, that at the reſurrection the fpirſt is to he clothed with a body, and, at any rate, that ſt is not for man vainly to preſcribe bounds to omnipotence.</p><p>what ſeems to have tortured the genius of divines much more than heaven or hell, is a middle ſtate. Οη this ſubject there being little revealed in Scripture, many have thought it incumbent upon them to lupply the defect ; which they ſeem to have done in different ways. From the Scriptures ſpeaking frequently of the dead as ſleeping in their graves, thoſe who imagine that the powers of the mind are dependent on the body, ſuppoſe that they ſleep till the reſurrection, when they are to be awakened by the trump &lt;⅛f God, reunited to their bodies, have their faculties reſtored, and their ſentence awarded.</p><p>This opinion they Γupport by what St Peter ſays in the Acts, that David is not aſcended into heaven ; and that this patriarch could not poſſibly be ſpeaking of himſelf when he ſaid, “ Thou wilt not leave my ſoul in hell, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi>  the place of the dead.” They obſerve, too, that the victory of Chriſt over death and the grave ſeems to imply, that our fouls are ſubject to their power ; that accordingly the Scripture ſpeaks frequently of the foul’s drawing near to, of its being redeemed from, and of its deſcending into, the grave ; that the Pſalmiſt, however, declares plainly, that when the breath of man goeth forth, he returneth to his earth, and that very day his thoughts pcriſh. And ſhould any one choofe to con-fult Eccleſiaſtes, he will find, that the living know that they ſhall die, but that the dead know not any thing : that their love, and their hatred, and their envy, are periſhed-; aud- that there is no work, nor device, nor</p><p>wiſdom, nor knowledge, in the grave, whether theÿ are gone.</p><p>Thoſe who believe that the foul is not for the exer-cife of its faculties dependent on the body, are upon its feparation at death obliged to diſpoſe of it ſome other way. In eſtabliſhing their theory, they uſually begin with attempting to prove, from Scripture or tradi-tion, both its active and ſeparate exiſtence ; but with proofs from tradition we intend not to meddle. Their arguments from Scripture being of more value, deſerve our ferions conſtderation ; and are nearly as follow.</p><p>Abraham, they ſay, Ifaac, and Jacob, are ſtill living, becauſe Jehovah is their God, and he, it is allowed, is not the God of the dead, but of the living. But their opponents reply, That this is the argument which our Saviour brought from the writings of Mofes to prove a future refurrection of the dead ; and that aay perfon who looks into the context, will ſee it was not meant ol a middle ſtate. From the dead living unto God, our Saviour infers nothing more than that they ihall live at the reſurrection ; and that theſe gentlemen would do well in future to make a diſtinction between limply living and living unto God : For though. Abιaham, lfaac, and Jacob, be living unto God, our Saviour~has affured us that Abraham is dead, and thé prophets dead.</p><p>A ſecond argument is that glimpfe which St PauI had oſ paradiſe about 14 years before he had written his Second Epiſtle to the Corinthians. To this argument their opponents reply, That as St Paul could not tell whether, on that occafion, he was out of the body or in the body, it is more than probable that the whole was a viſion ; and, at any rate, it is no prooſ oſ a ſeparate exiſtence.</p><p>A third argument is, St Paul’s wiſhing to be abſent from the body, and preſent with the Lord. But, fay<hi rend="sup">r </hi>their opponents, St Paul defιred not to be unclothed, but to be clothed upon r. and as ſome oſ thoſe who maintain a ſeparate exiſtencce, bring Scripture to prove that thc body ,∣ continues united to Chriſt till the reſurrec-tiυn ; in that cale, St. Paul, if he wiſhed to be preſertt with the Lord, ſhould have rather remained with his body than leſt it-</p><p>A fourth argument is, the appearance oſ Moſes and Elias upon the mount of transfiguration. To which their opponents reply, that theſe ſaint's appeared in their bodies ; that Elias was never diverted oſ his body; and that the account which we have oſ the burial of Moſes, has led fome of the ableſt critics and foundeſt divines to conclude, that he was likewiſe tranſlated to heaven without tailing death. At any rate, ſay they, he might have beeιr raifed from the dead for the very purpoſe of being preſent at the transfiguration, as the bodies of other faints certainly were, to bear teſtimony to our Lord's reſurrection and victory over the grave.</p><p>A fifth argument is, what our Saviour ſaid to the thief, “ verily I ſay unto thee, to-day thou ſhalt be with me in paradiſc.” The objection uſually made here is, that the expreſſion is evidently ambiguous, and' that the ſenſe depends entirely on the punctuation : for if the point be placed after <hi rend="italic">to-day,</hi>  the meaning will be " verily, even now, I tell thee, thou ſhalt be with me in paradiſe.” But the import of paradiſe in this place, ſay the opponents, is likewiſe doubtful, we learn from St Peter’s explanation of the 16th Pſalm, that our Sa-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>