<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>different claſs from thoſe which enthufiafm and impoſ-ture have fabricated among other nations. See Mira-cle and Prophecy.</p><p>But as the evidence of the divine origin of the prirnse-val religion reſts particularly on the authority of the firſt five books of the old Teſtament, it may be thought incumbent on us to ſupport our reaſoning on this ſubject, by proving, that the author of thoſe books was indeed inſpired by God. This we ſhall endeavour to do by one decifive argument ; for the nature of the ar-ticle, and the limits preſcribed us, admit not of our en-tering into a minute detail of all that has been written on the divine legation of Moſes.</p><p>If the miracles recorded in the book of Exodus, and the other writings of the Hebrew lawgiver, were really performed ; if the ſirſt-born of the Egyptians were all cut off in one night, as is there related ; and if the children of Iſrael paſſed through the Red fea, the waters being divided, and forming a wall on their right hand and on their left—it muſt neceffarily be granted, that Moſes was ſent by God ; becauſe nothing leſs than a divine power was ſufficient to perform ſuch wonderful works. But he who ſuppoſes that thoſe works were never performed, muſt affirm that the books recording them were<hi rend="italic">forged, </hi>either at the era in which the miracles are ſaid to have been wrought, or at ſome ſubſequent era : There is no other alternative.</p><p>That they could not be <hi rend="italic">forged</hi>  at the era in which they affirm the miracles to have been wrought, a very few reflections will make incontrovertibly evident. Theſe books inform the people forwhoſe uſe they were written, that their author, after having inflicted various plagues upon Pharaoh and his ſubjects, brought them, to the number of 600,coo, out of Egypt with a high hand ; that they were led by a pillar of cloud through the day, and by a pillar of fire through the night, to the brink of the Red fea, where they were almoſt overtaken by the Egyptians, who had purſued them with chariots and horſes ; that, to make a way for their eſcape, Mofes ſtretchcd out'his rod over the ſea, which was immediately divided, and permitted them to paſs through on dry ground, between two walls of water ; and that the E-gyptians, purfuing and going in after them to the midſt of the ſea, were all drowned by the return of the waterε to their uſual ſtate, as ſoon as the Hebrews arrived at the further ſhore. Is it poſſible now that Moſes or any other man could have perſuaded 600,000 perſons, however barbarous and illiterate we ſuppoſe them, that they had been witneffes of all theſe wonderful works, if no ſuch works had been performed ? Could any art or elo-quence perſuade all the inhabitants of Edinburgh- and Leith, that, they had ycſterday walked on dry ground through the Frith to Kinghorn, the waters being di-vided and forming a wall on their right hand and on their left ? If this queſtion muſt be anſwered in the negative, it is abſolutely impoſſible that the books of Moſes, ſup-poſing them to have been forged, could have been re-ceived by the people who were alive when thoſe won-ders are ſaid to have becn wrought.</p><p>Let us now inquire, whether, if they be forgeries, they could have been received as authentic at any ſub-ſequent period ; and we ſhall ſoon find this ſuppoſition as impoſſible as the former. The books claiming Moſes for their author fpeak of themfelves as delivered by him, and from his days kept in the ark.of the covenant *j an</p><lb/><p>ark which, upon this ſuppofition, had no exiſtence prior to the forgery. They ſpeak of themſelves likewiſe, not only as. a hiſtory of miracles wrought by their author, but as the ſtatutes or municipal law of the nation, of which a copy was to be always in the poſſeſſion of the prieſts, and another in that of the ſupreme magiſtrate J. Now, in whatever age we ſuppoſe theſe books to have been forged, they could not poffibly be received as au-thentic ; becauſe no copy of them could then be found' either with the king, with the prieſts, or in the ark, though, as they contain the ſtatute law of the land, it is not conceivable that, if they had exiſted, they could have been kept ſecret. Could any man, at this day, forge a book of ſtatutes for England or Scotland, and make it paſs upon theſe nations for the only book of ſtatutes which they had ever known ? was there ever ſince the world began a book of ſham ſtatutes, and theſe, too, multifarious and burdenſome, impoſed upon any people as the only ſtatutes by which they and their farthers had been governed for ages ? Such a forgery is evidently impoſſible.</p><p>But the books of Moſes have internal proofs of au-thenticity, which no other books of ancient ſtatutes e-ver had. They not only contain the laws, but alſo give an hiſtorical aecount of their enactment, and the reaſons upon which they were founded. Thus they tell us¢, that the rite of circumciſion was inſtituted as a mark of the covenant between God and the founder of the Jewiſh nation, and that the practice of it was enforced by the declaration of the Almighty, that every uncircumcifed man-child ſhould be cut off from his people. They in-form us that the annual ſolemnity of the paffover waβ inſtituted in commemoration of their deliverance when God flew, in one night, all the firſt-born of the Egyp-tians ; that the firſt-born of Iſrael, both of men and beaſt, were on the fame occaſion dedicated ſor ever to God, who took the Levites inſtead of the firſt-born of the men ſ; that this tribe was conſecrated as prieſts, by whoſe hands alone the ſacrifices of the people were to be offered ; that it was death for any perſon of a different tribe to approach the altar, or even to touch the ark of the covenant ; and that Aaron’s budding rod was kept in the ark in memory of the wonderful deſtruction of Korah, Dathan, and Abiram, for their rebellion a-gainſt the prieſthood.</p><p>Is it poſſible now, if all thefe things hadnot been practiſed among the Hebrews from the era of Moſes, with a retroſpect to the ſignal mercies which they are ſaid to commemorate, that any man or body of men could have perſuaded a whole nation, by means of forged books, that they had always religiouſly obſerved ſuch inſtitutions ? Could it have been poſſible, at any period poſterior to the Exodus, to perſuade the Iſraelites that they and their fathers had all been circumciſed on the eighth day from their birth, if they had been confcious themfelves that they had never been circumciſed at all? or that the paffover was kept in memory of their deliverance from Egyptian bondage, if no ſuch feſtival was known among them ?</p><p>But let us ſuppoſe that circumciſion had been practiſed, and all their ether ritcs and ceremonies obſerved from time immemorial, without their knowing any reaſon of fuch inſtitutions ; ſtill it muſt be confeſſed that the forger of theſe books, if they <hi rend="italic">were</hi>  forged, conſtructed his narrative in ſuch a manner as that no man</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>