<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the nation has the imprefcriptible right of changing its conſtitution ; and nevertheleſs conſidering that it is more conformable to the national intereſt to employ only by means provided in the conſtitution itſelf, the right of reforming thoſe articſes of it, of which experience ſhall have ſhown the inconveniencies, decrees, that the proceeding by an- aſſembly of reviſion ſhali be regulated in the form following:</p><p>“ when three ſucceſſive legiſſatures ſhall have ex-preffed au uniform wiſh for the change of any conſtitu-tional article, the reviſſon demanded ſhali take place.</p><p>" The next legiſſature, and the following, cannot propoſe the reform of any conſtitutional article.</p><p>" The fourth legiſſature, augmented with 249 members, choſen in each department, by doubling the ordinary number wliich it furniſhes in proportion to its population, ſhall form the affembly of reviſion.”</p><p>The French colonies and poffeffions in Alia, Africa, and America, " though they form part of the French empire,” are not included in the preſent conftitution.</p><p>with reſpect to the laws made by the national aſe ſembly which are not included in the act of conſtitu-tion, and thoſe anterior laws which it has not altered, they ſhall be obſerved, ſo long as they ſhall not be revoked or modified by the legiſſative power.</p><p>On the 13th of September the King announced, by a letter to the Preſident of the Affembly, his accept-ance of the conftitution. This event was ordered to be notified to all the foreign courts, and the Affembly decreed a general amneſty with reſpect to the events of the revolution. On the following day the King repaired fin perſon to rhe National Aſſembly; and being conducted to a chair of ſtate prepared for him at the ſide oſ the Preſident, he ſigned the conſtitutional act, and took an oath of fidelity to it. He then withdrew, and was attended back to the Thuilleries by the whole Affembly, with the Preſident at their head. On the 30th of September, tliis National Affembly, which has ſince been known by the name of the <hi rend="italic">ConfUtuent AJfem-bly,</hi>  diſſolved itſelf, and gave place to the ſucceeding <hi rend="italic">Leſtſtative National Affembly,</hi>  which had been elected according to the rules preſcribed by the new conſtitu-tion.</p><p>On the character and the labours of the <hi rend="italic">Conſtituent Affembly,</hi>  we ſhall only remark, that it contained many men of talents, and, in all probability, a conſiderable number of men of integrity. Towards the clofe of its ſeffion, it affumed a very ſtriking character of modera-tion, and appears to have been completely monarchical, although its jealouſy oſ tlie ancient ariſtocracy pre-vented it from ſufficiently guarding the throne againſt popular violence ; for a very ſtriking defect in the new couſtitution ſoon appeared. The King poſſeffed a <hi rend="italic">veto, </hi>or negative, upon the reſolutions of the legiſiative body: but this negative he was bound to exerciſe in <hi rend="italic">perfon,</hi>  without reſponſibility, and without the intervention of his miniſters. He had no ſenate, or upper chamber, to ſtand between him and popular violence ; and there was ſomething apparently abſurd in ſettling the vote of an individual, »1 oppoſition to the collective wifdom and will of a whole nation·. In conſequence of this, he was reduced to the hard alternative of yielding to every vote of the National Affembly, or of expoſing himſelf perſonally to public odium.</p><p>The new Aſſembly was opened by the King on the</p><lb/><p>7th of October, with much apparent union op. all ſides. His ſpeech, recommending unanimity aud conſidence between the legiſſative and executive powers, was received with unbounded applauſe. The character of the men who compoſed the new National Affembly was unauſpicions to the Court. At the commencement of the revolution, the great body of the people at a diſtance from the capital were little intereſted in thoſe projects of freedom which occupied the more enlightened or more turbulent inhabitants of Paris. They had gra-dually, however, been roufed from their lethargy. The variety of powers conferred by the new conſtitution upon the people at large, and the multiplicity of offices of which it gave them the patronage, had kindled in the minds of men a love of dominion, and a wiſh to inter-fere in public affairs. This attached them to the new order of things. The love of power, which is the leaſt difguiſed paffion in the human heart, and equally ſtrong in the breaſt of the meaneſt and of the higheſt of mankind, was thus, under the name of liberty, become a leading paffion throughout this wide empire. They who flattered it moſt, and were moſt loud in praiſe of the rights of the people, became ſpeedily the favourites of the public. The conſequence of this was, that the new National Aſſembly was chiefly compoſed oſ conn-try gentlemen, of principles highly democratic, or oſ men of letters who had publiſhed popular books, or conducted periodical publications. The members of the Conſtituent Affembly had been excluded by their own decree from holding feats in the new legiſlature.—-The members of the latter, theiefore, had little regard, for a conſtitution which they themſelves had not framed, and whieh was not protected by the venerable ſanction of antiquity.</p><p>when this Aſſembly ſirſt met, it ſhowed a very triſſmg attentlon to formalitles, and a peevlſh jealouſy of the miniſters of the crown. In the mean time, the treaty of Pilnitz, already mentioned, began to be rumoured abroad, and France was thrown into a ſtate of anxious jealoufy for the ſaſety of its newly-acquired liberties. Although the Pruffians and Germans (the Elector of Mentz alone excepted) all continued to temporize, the northern powers, Sweden and Ruffia, entered into ſtrict engagements to reſtore the old def-potiſm of France. On the 9th of November, a decree was paffed, that the emigrants who, after the ſirſt of January next, ſhould be found affembled, as at preſent, in a hoſtile manner, beyond the frontiers, ſhould be conſidered as guilty of a conſpiracy, and ſuffer death ; that the French Princes, and public functionaries, wlio ſhould not return before that period, ſhould be puniſh-able in the fame manner, and their property forfeited during their own lives. On the 18th, a ſeriesof ſevere decrees was alſo paffed againſt ſucli of the ejected clergy as ſtill refuſed to take the civic oath. To both-theſe decrees the King oppoſed his <hi rend="italic">veto,</hi>  or negative.— The moderate party,, who were attached to the conſti-tution, rejoiced at this as a proof of the freedom of their ſovereign. But, on the other ſide, it excited a moſt violent clamour, and became the means of exciting new ſufpſcion of the wiſhes of the Court. At this time. anſwers were received from thc different foreign Courts to the notification ſent them of the King’s acceptance of the new conſtitution. Theſe were generally conceived in a ſtile of caution, and avoided giving</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>