<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>more elevated form in the middle than any other rays, but grows thin towards the edges. The noſe is very ſharp pointed, but ſhort ; the mouth fmall, and filled with granulated teeth. The irides are of a gold colour: behind each eye the orifice is very large. The tail is very thick at the beginning : the ſpine is placed about a third the length of the former from the body; is about five inches long, flat on the top and bottom, very hard, ſharp pointed, and the two ſides thin, and clofely and ſharply bearded the whole Way. The tail extends four inches beyond the end of this ſpine, and grows very deader at the extremity. Theſe ſiſh are obſerved to ſhed their ſpine, and renew them annually ; ſometimes the new ſpine appears before the old one drops off ; and the Corniſh call this fpecies <hi rend="italic">cardinal trilofi,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">three-tailed, </hi>when ſo circumſtanced. The colour of the upper part of the body is a dirty yellow, the middle part of an obſcure blue : the lower fide white, the tail and ſpine duſky. The weapon with which nature has aimed this fiſh, hath ſupplied the ancients with many tremendous fables relating to it. Pliny, Ælian, and Qppian, have given it a venom that affects even the inanimate creation : trees that are ſtruck by it inſtantly loſe their verdure and periſh, and rocks themfelves are incapable of refilling the potent poiſon. The enchantreſs Circe armed her ſon with a ſpear headed with the ſpine of the trygon, as the moſt irreſiſtible weapon ſhe could furniſh him witjj, ; and with which he afterwards committed parricide, unintentionally, on his lather Ulyſſes. That fpear⅛ and darts might, in very early times, have been headed with this bone inſtead of iron, we have no kind of doubt ; that of another fpecies of this ſiſh being ſtill ufed to point the arrows of ſome of the South American Indians, and is, from its hardneſs, ſharpneſs, and beards, a moſt dreadful weapon. But in reſpect to its venomous qualities, there is not the leaſt credit to be given to the opinion, though it was believed (as far as it affected the animal world) by Rondeletius, Aldro-vand, and others, and even to this day by the fiſhermen in ſeveral parts of the kingdom. It is in fact the wea-pon of offence belonging to the fiſh, capable of giving a very bad wound, and which is attended with dangerous ſymptoms when it falls on a tendinous part or on a perfon in a bad habit of body. As to any fiſh having a ſpine charged with actual poifon, it ſeems very dubious, though the report is ſanctified by the name of Linnæus. He inſtances the <hi rend="italic">paftiηaca,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">torpedo,</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">tetrodon (meatus.</hi>  The firſt is incapable of conveying a greater injury than what reſults from the mere wound ; the ſecond, from its electric effluvia ; and the third, by imparting a pungent pain like the ſting of nettles, occaſioned by the minute ſpines on its abdomen.</p><p>RAI ΑΝΙΑ, in botany : A genus of the hexandria order, belonging to the dioecia claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the nth order, <hi rend="italic">Sa-mentaceœ.</hi>  The male calyx is fexpartite ; there is no corolla. The female calyx as in the male, without any corolla; there are three ſtyles; the fruit is roundiſh with ari oblique wing, inferior. There are three ſpecies, the haſtata, cordata, and quinquefolia.</p><p>RAIETEA, one of the South Sea iſlands, named alfo Ulieteλ.</p><p>RAIL, in ornithology. See Rallus.</p><p>RAILLERY, according to Dr Johnſon, means flight ſatire, or ſatirical merriment ; and a beautiful wri-ter of the laſt century compares it to a light which dazzles, and which does not burn. It is ſometimes i∏-noc'ent and ρleafant, and it ſhould always be ſo, but it is moſt frequently offenſive. Raillery is of various kinds ; there is a ferious, ſevere, and good-humoured raillery ; and there is a kind which perplexes, a kind which offends, and a kind which pleaſes.</p><p>To rally well, it is abſolutely neceſſary that kindneſs run through a∏ you ſay ; and you muſt ever preſerve the character of a friend to ſupport your pretenſions to be free with a man. Alluſions to paſt follies, hints to revive what a man has a mind to forget for ever, ſhould never be introduced as the ſubjects of raillery. This is not to thruſt with the ſkill of fencers, but to cut with the barbarity of butchers. But it is below the character of men of humanity and good-breeding to be capable of mirth, while there is any in the company in pain and diforder.</p><p>RAIN, the deſcent of water from the atmofphere^ in the form of drops of a conſiderable ſize. By this circumſtance it is diſtinguiſhed from dew and fog : in the former of which the drops are ſo ſmall that they are quite inviſible ; and in the latter, though their ſize is larger, they ſeem to have very little more fpecific gravity than the atmoſphere itſelf,. and may therefore be reckoned hollow ſpherules rather than drops.</p><p>It is univerſally agreed, that rain is produced by the water previouſly abſorbed by the heat of the ſun, or otherwiſe, from the terraqueous globe, into the atmoſphere ; but very great difficulties occur when we begin to explain why the water, once ſo cloſely united with the atmoſphere, begins to ſeparate from it. we cannot afcribε this ſeparation to cold, ſince rain often takes place in very warm weather ; and though we ſhould ſuppofe the condenfation owing to the ſuperior cold of the higher regions, yet there is a remarkable fact which will not allow us to have recourſe to this ſuppofition. It is certain that the drops of rain increaſe in ſize con-ſiderably as they deſcend. Οη the top of a hill, for inſtance, they will be finall and inconfiderable, forming only a drizzling ſhower ; but at the bottom of the ſame hill the drops will be exceſſively large, deſcending in an impetuous rain ; which ſhows that the atmoſphere is diſpoſed to condenſe the vapours, and actually does ſo, as well where it is warm as where it is cold.</p><p>For ſome time the ſuppoſitions concerning the cauſe of rain were exceedingly inſufficient and unſatisfactory. It was imagined, that when various conge-ries of clouds were driven together by the agitation of the winds, they mixed, and run into one body, by which means they were condenſed into water. The eoldnefs of the upper parts of the air alſo was thought to be a great means of collecting and condenſing the clouds into water ; which, being heavier than the air, muſt neceſſarily fall down through it in the form of rain. The reaſon why it falls in drops, and not in large quantities, was ſaid to be the refiſtance of the air; whereby being broken, and divided into ſmaller and ſmaller parts, it at laſt arrives to us in ſmall drops. But this hypotheſis is entirely contrary to almoſt all the phenomena : for the weather, when coldeſt, that is, in the time of ſevere fioſt, is generally the moſt ſerene ; the moſt violent rains alſo happen where there is little or no cold to condenſe the clouds ; and the drops of rain, inſtead of being divided into ſmaller and finaller ones as they approach the earth, are plainly increaſed in ſizc as they deſcend.</p></body></text></TEI>