<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of them are together, they make ſuch a horrid noiſe, that two people cannot underſtand each other’s ſpeech. They croak all together, and then ſtop for a little and begin again. It feems as if they had a captain atno∏g them : for when he begins to croak, all the others iol-low ; and when he ſtops, they alſo become filent. when this captain gives the ſignal for ſtopping, you hear a note like <hi rend="italic">poop</hi>  coming from him. In the day-time they ſeldom make any great noiſe, unleſs the ſky is covered ; but in the night-time thcy may be heard at the diſtance of a mile and an half, when they croak, they are commonly near the ſurface of the water, under the buſhes, and have their heads out of the water. By going ſlowly, therefore, one may get up almoſt quite cloſe to<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  them before they go away. As ſoon as they are quite under water, they think themſelves fate, though it be ever ſo ſhallow. Theſc creatures kill and eat young ducklings and goſlings, and ſometimes carry off chickens that come too near the water ; when beaten, they cry out almoſt like little children. As ſoon as the air begins to grow a little cool in autumn, they hide them-felves under the mud in the bottom of ſtagnant waters, and lie there torpid during the winter. As ſoon as the weather grows mild towards ſummer, they begin to get out of their holes and croak. They are ſuppoſed by the people ofvirginia to be the purifiers of waters, and are reſpected as the genii of the fountains. Some of them were brought to England alive ſcveral years ago.</p><p>4. The bufo, or toad, is the moſt deformed and hι-deous of all animals. The body is broad ; the back flat, and covered with a pimply duſky hide ; the belly large, ſwagging, and ſwelling out ; the legs ſhort, and its pace laboured and crawling ; its retreat gloomy and filthy : in ſhort, its general appearance is ſuch as to ſtrike one with diſguſt and horror. Yet it is ſaid by thofe who have refolution to view it with attention, that its eyes are fine ; to this it ſeems that Shakeſpeare alludes, when he makes his Juliet remark,</p><p>Some fay the lark and loathed toad change eyes;</p><p>As if they would have been better beſtowed on ſo charming a ſongſter than on this raucous reptile.</p><p>Çut the hideous appearance of the toad is fuch as to make this one advantageous feature overlooked, and to have rendered it in all ages an object of horror, and the origin of moſt tremendous inventions. Ælian makes its venom' ſo potent, that baſiliſk-like it conveyed death by its vcry look and breath ; but Juvenal is content with making the Roman ladies who were weary of their huſhands form a potion from its entrails, in order to get rid of the good man. This opinion begat others of a more dreadful nature ; for in after-times ſu-perſtition gave it preternatural powers, and made it a principal ingredient in the incantations of nocturnal hags.</p><p>This animal was believed by ſome old writers to have a ſtone in its head fraught with great virtues medical and magical : it was diſtinguiſhed by the name of the reptile, and called the <hi rend="italic">toadfione, lιfοηites, era· paudine, kr(<hi rend="sub">j</hi>ttenfictn ;</hi>  but all its-fancied powers, vaniſh-ed on the diſcovery· of its.being nothing but the foſſil-tooth of the ſea-wolf¢, or. of ſome other flat-toothed</p><lb/><p>fiſh, not unfrequeΛt in our iſland as well as feveral other countries.    . .</p><p>But theſe fables have been long exploded. And as to the notion of its being a poifonous animal, it is pro· bable that its exceffive deformity, joined to the faculty it has of emitting a juice from its pimples, and a duſky liquid from its hind parts, is the foundation of the report.</p><p>That it has any noxious qualities there feem to have been no proofs in the fmalleſt degree fatisfactory, tho’ we have heard many ſtrange relations on that point.—. Οη the contrary, there have been many who have taken them in their naked hands, and held them long without receiving the leaſt injury : it is alfo well known that quacks have eaten them, and have beſides ſqueezed their juices into a glaſs and drank them with impunity, we may ſay alſo, that tlieſe reptiles are a common food to many animals ; to buzzards, owls, Norfolk plovers, ducks, and ſnakes, who would not touch them were they in any degree noxious.</p><p>Go far from having venomous qualitics, they have of late been confidered as if they had beneficent ones ; particularly in the cure of the moſt terrible of diſeaſes, the <hi rend="italic">cancer,</hi>  by ſuction : (See <hi rend="italic">Britiſh Zoology,</hi>  vol. iii. Append, p. 389, <hi rend="italic">etfiq.) </hi>But, from all circumſtances, as Mr Pennant obſerves, they ſeem only to have ren« dered a horrible complaint more loathſome.</p><p>The moſt full information concerning the nature and qualities of this animal is contained in the following letters from Mr Arſcott and Mr Pittfield to Dr Milles. " It would give me great pleaſure (ſays Mr Arſcott) to be able to inform you of any particulars worthy Mr Pennant’s notice, concerning the toad who lived ſo many years with us, and was ſo great a favourite. Tlie greateſt curioſity in it was its becoming ſo remarkably tame. It had frequented ſome ſteps before the hall-door ſome years before my acquaintance commenced with it, and had been admired by my father for its ſize (which was of the largeſt I ever met with), who conſtantly paid it a viſit every evening. I knew it mylelf above 30 years ; and by conſtantly feeding it, brought it to be ſo tame, that it always came to the candle, and looked up as if expecting to be taken up and brought upon the table, where I always fed it with infects of all forts ; it was fondeſt of fleſh maggots, which I kept in bran ; it would follow them, and, when within a proper diſtance, would fix its eye, and remain motionlefs for near a quarter of a minute, as if preparing for the ſtroke, which was an inftantaneous throwing its tongue at a great diſtance upon the inſect, which ſtuck to the tip by a glutinous matter : the motion is quicker than the eye can follow (a).</p><p>" 1 always imagined that the root of its tongue was placed in the forepart of its under jaw, and the tip to-wards its throat, by which the motion muſt be a half circle ; by which, when its tongue recovered its fituation, the inſect at the tip would be brought to the place ot deglutition. I was confirmed in this by never obſerving any internal motion in its mouth, excepting one&gt; ſwallow the inſtant its tongue returned. Poſſibly I might be miſtaken ; for I never diffected one, but con-</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi>  This rapid capture of its prey might give occaſion to the report of its faſcinating powers, Linnæus ſays, <hi rend="italic">InfictΛ in fauces fafiiηο revocat.</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>