<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to the 29th natural order, <hi rend="italic">Camtanacea.</hi>  The capfule is bilocular, the corolla cylindrical, and villous without; the iligma bifid.</p><p>REUd I.INGEN, a handſome, free, and imperial town oſ Germany, in the circle oſ Suabia, and duchy of wirtemberg ; ſeated in a plain on the river Eſchez, near the Neckar, adorned with handſome public build-ings, and has a well frequented college. E. Long. 9. 10. N. Lat. 48. 31.</p><p>REVE, Reeve, or <hi rend="italic">Grew,</hi>  the bailiff of a franchife, or manor, thus called, eſpecially in the weft of Eng-land. Hence ſhire-reeve, iheriff, port-greve, &amp;c.</p><p>REVEILLE, a beat of drum about break of day, to give notice that it is time for the ſoldiers to ariſe, and that the ſentries are to forbear challenging.</p><p>RE∙vEL, a port town of Livonia, ſituated at the ſouth entrance of the gulph of Finland, partly in a plain and partly on a mountain ; 133 miles ſouth-weft of Pe-terſhurg, and 85 ſonth-eaſt of Abo. It is a place of great trade, and holds two Υtrirs yearly, which are vi-ſited by merchants from all countries, but particularly by thoſe oſ England and Holland. It is a ſtrong and a rich place, with a capital harbour. It is ſurrounded with high walls and deep ditches, and defended by a caſtle and ſtout baſtions. It was confirmed to the Swedes at the peace of oliva, conquered by Peter the Great in 1710, and ceded to Ruſſia in 1721. The conqueſt of it was again attempted by the Swedes in 1790. The duke of Sudermania, with the Swediih fleet, attempted to carry the harbour ; but after an ob-ſtinate engagement with the Ruffian fleet, he was obliged to give it up ; but it was but for a very ſhort while. He retired about 10 leagues from the harbour, to repair the damage his fleet had fuſtained, and to prepare for a ſecond attack before any relief could be afforded to the Ruſſian fleet. As ſoon as he had refitted, he failed for the harbour, at a league diſtant from which the Ruſſian fleet was diſcovered, ready to dispute with the Swedes the entrance. Upon a council being held by the Duke, it was reſolved to attack the Ruffians ; and the ſignals being given, the fleet bore down for the attack, which was maintained for near fix hours with the utmoſt fury : at length the Swedes broke the Ruſſian line, which threw them into much confuſion ; when the Swedes, taking the advantage of the general confuſion into which the Ruffians were thrown, followed them with their whole force into the harbour, where the conflict and carnage were dreadful on both ſides, though the Swedes certainly had the worſt of it ; at the fame time that their ſkill and bravery is indiſputable.</p><p>This valuable place was again confirmed to Ruſſia by the peace. The government of Revel or Eſt-honia is one of the diviſions of the Ruffian empire, containing five diſtricts. 1. Revel, on the Baltic ſea.</p><p>2.    Baltic-port, about 40 verſts weſtward ſrom Revel.</p><p>3.    Habſal, or Hapſal, a maritime town. 4. weiffen-ſtein, on the rivulet Saida, about 80 verſts from Revel. 5. weſenberg, about 100 verſts from Revel, at about an equal diſtance from that town and Naιva.</p><p>REVELATION, the act of revealing, or making a thing public that was before unknown ; it is alſo uſtd for the diſcoveries made by God to his prophets, and by them to the world ; and more particularly for the books of the Qld and New Teſtament. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bible<hi rend="sub">;</hi></hi></p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chrtstianitv, Miracle, Religion,</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Theolo-</hi></p><p>GY.</p><p>The principal teſts of the truth of any revelation, are the tendency of its practical doctrines ; its conliſten-cy with itſelf, and with the known attributes of God ; and ſome fatisfactory evidence that it cannot have been derived from a human ſouree.</p><p>Before any man can receive a written book as a re-velation from God, he muſt be convinced that God ex-iſts, and that he is poffeffed oſ almighty power, infinite wildom, and perfect jnſtice Now ſhould a book teaching abſurd or immoral doctrines (as many chapters of the Koran do, and as all the traditionary fyſtems of Paganiſm did), pretend to be revealed by a God of wiſdom and juſtice, we may ſafely reject its pretenfions without farther examination than what is neceffary to ſatisfy us that we have not mifunderſtood its doctrine. Should a book claiming this high origin, enjoin in one part oſ it, and forbid in another, the ſame thing to be done under the ſame circumſtances, we may reject it with contempt and indignation ; becauſe a being of infinite wiſdom can never act capriciouſly or abſurdlv. Still, however, as it is impoſſible for us to know how far the powers of men may reach in the inveſtigation or diſcovery of uſeful truth, ſome farther evidence is neceſ-ſary to prove a doctrine of divine origin, than its mere confiſtency with itſelf', and with the principles of morality ; and this evidence can be nothing but the power of working miracles exhibited by him by whom it was originally revealed. Tn every revelation confirmed by this evidence, many doctrines are to be looked for which human reaſon cannot fully comprehend ; and theſe are to be believed on the teſtimony oſ God, and ſuffered to produce their practical conſequences. At this kind of belief the ſhallow infidel may ſmile con-temptuouſiy ; but it has place in arts and ſciences as</p><p>well as in religion, whoever avails himfelf of the demon-ſtrations of Newton, Bernoulli, and others, refpectinœ the refiſtance of fluids, and applies their conclu lions to the art of flιip-h&gt;uilding, is as implicit a believer, if he underſtand not the principles of fluxions, as any Chri-ſtian ; and yet no man will fay that his faith is not pro-ductive of important practical confequences. He believes, however, in man, while the Chriſtian believes in God ; and therefore he cannot pretend that his faith reſts on a ſurer foundation.</p><p>Mr Locke, in laying down the diſtinct provinces of reaſon and faith, obſerves, 1. That the fame truths may be diſcovered by revelation which are discoverable to us by reaſon. 2. That no revelation can bc admitted againſt the clear evidence of reafon. 3. That there are many things of which we have but imper-fect notions, or none at all ; and ethers, of whoſe paſt, prefent, or future exiſtence, by the natural uſe of our faculties we cannot have the leaſt knowledge: and theſe, being beyond the diſcovery of our faculties, and above reafon, when revealed, become the proper object of our faith. He then adds, that our reafon is not injured or diſturbed, but aſſiſted and improved, by new diſcoveries of truth coming from the fountain of knowledge, whatever Gβd has revealed is certainly true ; but whether it be a divine re velation. or not, rea-fon muſt judge, which can never permit the mind to reject a greater evidence to embrace what is leſs evi-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>