<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>V∏ιen the velocity is three feet per ſecond, requiring the productive Height 2 ι ,5 lines, the heights correſponding to the non-preffure on the poop of a thin plane is 14,41 lines (taking in ſeveral circumſtances of judicious correction, which we have not mentioned), that of a foot cube is 5,83, and that of a box of triple length is 3,-31.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  expreſs the variable ratio of theſe to the height producing the velocity, ſo that <hi rend="italic">q h</hi>  may expreſs the non-preffnre in every cafe ; we have,</p><p>For a thin plane    -    -    <hi rend="italic">q ~</hi>  0,67</p><p>a cube    -    0,271</p><p>a box ~ 3 cubes -    -    o, 153</p><p>It is evident that the value of <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  has a dependence on the proportion of the length, and the tranſverſe fiction of the body. A firies oſ experiments oil priſmatic bo-dies ſhowed Mr de Bπat that the deviation of the ſila-meπts was ſimilar in ſimilar bodies, and that this ob-tained even in diſſimilar priſms, when the lengths were as the ſquare-roots of the tranfverſe fictions. Although therefore the experiments were not ſufficiently numerous for deducing the precifi law, it ſeemed not impoſ-ſible to derive from them a very ufeful approximation. By a dexterous compariſon he found, that if Z expreffes the length of the priſm, and r the area of the tranſverſe fiction, and ∑<hi rend="sub">j</hi>  expreffes the common logarithm of the quantity to which it is prefixed, we ſhall expreſs the non-preffure pretty accurately by the formula <hi rend="sup">1</hi>~-</p><p>Hence arifis an important remark, that when the height correſponding to the non-preſſion is greater than <hi rend="italic">»,/s,</hi>  and the body is little immerfid in the fluid, there will be a void behind it.. Thus a ſurface of a ſquare inch, juſt immerfid in a current of three feet per ſe--cond, will have a void behind it. A foot ſquare will be in a fimilar condition when the velocity is 12 feet.</p><p>we muſt be careful to diſtinguiſh this non-preffure from the other caufis of reſtſtance, which are always neceffarily combined with it. It is fuperadditive to the active impreffion on the prow, to the ftatical preſ-ffure of the accumulation a-head of the body, the llaticaî preffure ariſing from the depreſſion behind it, the effects of friction, and the effects of tenacity. It is indeed next to impoſſible to eſtimate them feparately, and many of them are actually combined in the meafures now given. Nothing can determine the pure nou-preffures till we can aſcertain the motions of the filaments.</p><p>Mr de Buat here takes occaſion to controvert the univerſally adopted maxim, that the preffure &lt;3ccaf1oned by a ſtream of ſtuid on a fixed body is the ſame with that on a body moving with equal velocity in a qui-efcent fluid. He repeated all theſe experiments with the perforated box in ſtill water. The general diſtinc-tipn was, that both the preffures and the non-preffure in this caſe was leſs, and that the odds was chiefly to be obfirved near the edges of the ſurface. The gene-ral factor of the preffure of a ftream on the anterior fur-face was <hi rend="italic">m </hi>~ 1,186; but that on a body moving through a ſtill ſtuid is only <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  — 1. Fie obſerved no non-preffure even at the very edge of the prow, but even a finſible preffure. The preffure, therefore, or re-ſiſtance, is more equably diffufid over the ſurface of the prow than the impulſe is.— He alfo found that the reſiſtances diminiſhed in a leſs ratio than the ſquares of the velocities, eſpecially in ſmall velocities.</p><p>The non-preſſures increaſed in a greater ratio than the ſquares of the velocities. The ratio of the velocities to a ſmall velocity of <hi rend="italic">2(</hi>  inches <hi rend="italic">per</hi>  ſecond increaſed geome-trically, the value of <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  increafid arithmetically ; and we may determine <hi rend="italic">q for any</hi>  velocity V by this proportion</p><p><hi rend="sub">l</hi> V,</p><p>L — :    L ~    = 0,5 :y, and    <hi rend="italic">q    -</hi>  ---<hi rend="sup">2</hi>&gt;,.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.    That is,</p><p>2,2    22    <hi rend="sup">y,</hi>    ■*    <hi rend="sub">2</hi>,8 ∙</p><p>let the common logarithm of the velocity, divided by 2ſ, be conſidered as a common number ; divide this common number by 2<hi rend="sub">1</hi>⅞∙, the quotient is y, which muſt be multiplied by the productive height. The pro-duct is the preffure.</p><p>when Pitot’s tube was expofid to the ſtream, we had <hi rend="italic">m —</hi>  1 ; but rvhen it is carried through ſtill water, <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  is = 1,22. when it was turned from the ſtream, we had <hi rend="italic">q —</hi>  0,157 ; but when carried through ſtili water, <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  is =0,138. A remarkable experiment.</p><p>when the tube was moved laterally through the wa-ter, ſo that the motion was in the direction of the plane of its mouth, the non-preffure was — 1. This is one of his chief arguments for his theory of non-preſſion. Fie does not give the detail of the experiment, and only infirts the reſult in his table.</p><p>As a body expofid to a ftream deflects the ſtuid, heaps it up, and increaſes its velocity; fo a body moved through a ſtill fluid turns it aſide, caufis it to ſwell up before it, and gives it a real motion alongiide of it in the oppoſite direction. And as the body expofid to a ſtream has a quantity of fluid almoſt ſtagnant both before and behind; ſo a body moved through a ſtill fluid carries before it and drags after it a quantity of fluid, which accompanies it with nearly an equal velocity. This addition to the quantity of matter in motion muſt make a diminution of its velocity ; and this forms a very conſiderable part of the obfirved reſiſtauce.</p><p>we cannot, however, help remarking that it would require very diſtinct and ſtrong proof indeed to overturn the common opinion, which is founded on our moſt certain and ſxmple conceptions of motion, and on a law of nature to which we have never obferved an exception. Mr de Buat’s experiments, tho’ moſt judiciouſiy contrived, and executed with ſcrupulous care, are by no means of this kind. They were, of abſolute neceſſity, veιy complicated ; and many circumſtances, impoſſible to avoid or to appreciate, rendered the obfirvatiυn, or at leaſt the compariſon, of the velocities, veιy uncertain.</p><p>we can fie but two circumſtances which do not admit of an· eaſy or immediate compariſon in the two ſtates of the problem, when a body is expofid to a ftream <hi rend="italic">in </hi><hi rend="italic">our experiments,</hi>  in order to have an impulſe made on it, there is a force tending to move the body backwards, independent of the real impulſe or preffure occaſtoned by the deflection of the ftream. we cannot have a ſtream except in eonfiquence of a Hoping ſurface. Suppofe a body floating on this ſtrearti. It will not only fail down <hi rend="italic">along with the flream,</hi>  but it will fail <hi rend="italic">down the flream,</hi>  and will therefore go faſter along the canal than the ſtream does : for it is floating on an inclined plane ; and if we examine it by the laws of hydroſtatics, we ſliall find, that befides its own tendency to<hi rend="italic">flide</hi>  down this inclined plane, there is an odds of hydroſtatical preffure, which <hi rend="italic">pujhes</hi>  it down this plane. It will therefore go along the canal faſter than</p><p>the ſtream For this acceleration depends on the différence of preffure at the two ends, and will be more re-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>