<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to be received jo years hence, and the rate of intereſt Ç <hi rend="italic">per cent,</hi>  is equal to .6 ! 39×10,0000 = 6i39.00c0l. or 6139k Again, thc preſent value oſ 10,000 1. due in ten years, the rate of intereſt being 3 <hi rend="italic">per cent,</hi>  is .7441 × 10,000 = 7441.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Reversion oſ Series,</hi></hi>  in algebra, <hi rend="sup">-</hi>a kind oſ reverſed operation of an infinite ſeries. See Series.</p><p>REVIVIFICATION, in chemiſtry, a term ge-ηerally applied to the diſtillation of quickſilver from cinnabar.    #</p><p>C0M⅛rtssι0N <hi rend="smallcaps">of REVIEW, is a commiſſion ſome-times granted, in extraordinary cafes, to revile the ſentence of the court of delegates, when it is appre-hended they have been lcd into a material error. This commiſſion the king may grant, although the ſtatutes 24 and 25 Hen. VIII. declare the ſentence of the de-legates definitive : becaufe the pope, as ſupreme head by the canon law, ufed to grant ſuch commiſſion of review; and ſuch authority as the pope heretofore exerted is now annexed to the crown by ſtatutes 26 Hen. VIII, c. </hi>I. and 1 Eliz. c. I. But it is not matter of right, which the fubject may demand <hi rend="italic">ex debito jufiiti&lt;e ;</hi>  but merely a matter of favour, and which therefore is often denied.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Review, is the drawing out ail or part of the army in line of battle, to be viewed by the king,«or a general, that they may know the condition of the troops.</hi></p><p>At all reviews, the officers ſhould be properly arm-ed, ready in their exerciſe, ſalute well, in good time, and with a good air ; their uniform genteel, &amp;c. The men ſhould be clean and well dreſſed ; their accoutrements well put on ; very well fized in their ranks ; the ſerjeants expert in their duty, drummers perfect in their beatings, and the fifers play correct. The manual ex-erciſe muſt be performed in good time, and with life ; and the men carry their arms well ; march, wheel, and form with exactneſs. All manœuvres muſt be performed with the utmoſt regularity, both in quick and flow -time. The firings are generally 36 rounds; viz. by companies ; by grand diviſions ; by ſubdiviſions ; ob-liquely, advancing, retreating ; by files ; in the ſquare ; ſtreet firings, advancing and retreating ; and laſtly, a volley. The intention of a review is, to know the condition of the troops, ſee that they are complete and perform their exerciſe and evolutions well.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Review is alſo applied to Literary Journals, which give a periodical view of the ſtate of literature j as the Monthly Review, the Critical Review, the Britiſh Critic, and Analytical Review, &amp;c.</hi></p><p>RE-UN10N island, an iſland in the South Sea, diſcovered by the French on the 16th December 1773; lying, according to M. de Pages, in latitude 48<hi rend="sup">0</hi> 21", and longitude 66<hi rend="sup">3</hi> 47", the variation of the needle being 30<hi rend="sup">0</hi> always towards north-weſt. The road and harbour are extremely good, and the latter from 16 to 8 fathoms deep at the very ſhore. The coaſt on each ſide is lofty, but gteen, with an abrupt deſcent, and ſwarms with a ſpecies of buſtards. The penguins and ſea-lions, which ſwarmed on the ſands, were nowiſe alarmed at the approach of thoſe who landed; from whence M. de Pages concluded that the country was wholly uninhabited. The foil produces a kind of grafs, about live .inches long, with a broad black leaf, and ſeemingly of <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">ά</hi></hi>  rich quality—but there was no veſtige of a tree or</p><p>human habitation, See <hi rend="italic">Travels round the Wοrld∖yy</hi>  M<hi rend="sub">t </hi>  de Pages, V0I, III. chap. viii. and ix.</p><p>REVOLUTION, in politics, ſigniſies a change in the conſtitution of a ſtate ; and is a word of different import from <hi rend="italic">revolt,</hi>  with which it is ſometimes confound-ed, when a people withdraw their obedience ſrom their governors for any particular reaſon, without overturning the government, or waging an offenſive war againſt it, they are in a ſtate of revolt; when they over-turn the government and foιm a new one for themſelves, they effect a <hi rend="italic">revolution.</hi></p><p>That which is termed <hi rend="italic">the revolution</hi>  in Britain is the change which, in 1688, took place in conſequence of the forced abdication of king James II. when the Pro-teſtant ſucceflion was eſtabliſhed, and the conſtitution reſtored to its primitive purity. 01 this important tranſaction, which confirmed the rights and liberties of Britons, we have endeavoured to give an impartial account under another article (ſee Britain, n<hi rend="sup">o</hi>  281, &amp;c). Οί the riſe and progreſs of the American revolution, which is ſtill freſh in the memory of our readers, a large detail is given under the article America : But there are two other revolutions yet depending, of which ſome account will be expected in this place.</p><p>The Poli(h revolution, which, in all its circumſtances, was perhaps the leaſt exceptionable of any in the records of hiſtory, we have already traced to the period when the amiable king, over-awed by the arms of Ruſ-ſia, was obliged to undo his patriotic work, and give his fonction to the reſtoration of the old and wretched government (fee Poland). Since that period, Koſ-ciuſko’s army has been completely defeated, himſelf made a priſoner, warfow taken, and the whole king-dom ſubdued by the powers combined againſt it. what will be the conſequence of this ſucceſs may perhaps be conceived, bur the rumours of the day are various. At one time we are told, that Poland is to be no longer an independent ſtate, but to be divided among the three great powers which formerly wreſted from it ſome of its moſt valuable provinces. At another time, we hear of the diſintereſted intention of the Emprefs, to reſtore the king to his original authority ; although ſhe has, in the mean time, driven him from his capital, where ſhe herfelf exerciſes fovereign power. And a third report fays, that Staniſlaus is to retire with a large penlion, and a Ruffian prince to ſtep into his throne. The ſirſt ot theſe rumours we think much more probable than the other two : eſpecially as it ſeems confirmed by the following letter fent from Grod-no, on the 18th of January, by the unfortunate king to the Britiſh ambaſſador.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">" My dear Gardiner—Tlιe characters with which you and I have been inveſted ſeem to be now almoſt at an end. I do not expect to fee you again, but it is of importance to me to bid you farewell ; and this I do from the bottom of my heart. You will preſerve a place in my heart till death ; and I hope that at laſt we ſhall meet again, in a place where upright minds, ac-cording to my opinion, will be for ever united.</hi></p><p>“ Every thing belonging to the uſual etiquette has been ſo much deranged and interrupted by my fod fate, that moſt probably neither you nor I will be able to fulfil the diplomatic cuſtoms.</p><p>“ But be aſſured, that I love and honour your king</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>