<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>circle, whoſe plane is perpendicular to th¢ ftτeam. If BC (fig. I.) be a plane ſurface expofed to the action of a ſtream of ſtuid, moving in thc direction DC, then BR, or SE, perpendicular to DC, is its baſe.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Direct impulſe</hi>  ſhall expreſs the energy or action of the particle or filament, or ſtream of fluid, when meeting the ſurface perpendicularly, or when tlie furface is perpendicular to the direction of the ſtream.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Abſolute impu/ſe</hi>  means the actual preffure on the impelled ſurface, arifing from the action of the fluid, whether ſtriking the ſurface perpendicularly or obliquely ; or it is the force impreffed on the ſurface, or tendency to motion which it acquires, and which muſt be oppoled by an equal force in the oppoſite direction, in order that the ſurface may be maintained in its place. It is of importance to keep in mind, that this preffure is always perpendicular to the ſurfacc. It is a propoſttion found-ed on univerſal and uncontradicted experience, that the mutual actions of bodies on each other are always exerted in a direction perpendicular to the touching fur-faces. Thus, it is obferved, that when a billiard ball A is ſtruck by another B, moving in any direction what-ever, the ball A always moves off in the direction perpendicular to the plane which touches the two balls in the point of mutual contact, or point of impulſe. This inductive propoſition is fupported by every argument which can be drawn from what we know concerning the forces which connect the particles of matter together, and are the immediate cauſes of the communication of motion. It would employ much time and room to ſtate them here ; and we apprehend that it is unneceffary : for no reaſon can be aſſigned why the preffure ſhould be in <hi rend="italic">any particular</hi>  oblique direction. If any one ſhould ſay that the impulſe will be in the direction of the ſtream, we have only to deſire him to take notice of the effect of the rudder of a ſhip. This ſhows that the impulſe <hi rend="italic">is not in the direction of the fir earn,</hi>  and is therefore in ſome direction tranſverſe to the ftream.— He will alſo find, that when a plane ſurface is impelled obliquely by a fluid, there is no direction in which it can be ſupported but the direction perpendicular to it-ſelf. It is quite ſafe, in the mean time, to take it as an experimental truth, we may, perhaps, in ſome other part of this work, give what will be received as a rigorous demonſtration.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Relative or effective impulſe</hi>  means the preffure on the ſurface eſtimated in ſome particular direction. Thus BC (fig. i.) may repreſent the ſail of a ſhip, impelled by the wind blowing in the direction DC. G Ο may be the direction of the ſhip’s keel, or the line of her courſe. The wind ſtrikes the ſail in the direction GH parallel to DC ; the ſail is urged or preffed in the di-rection GI, perpendicular to BC. But we are intereſted to know what tendency this will give the ſhip to move in the direction GO. This is the effective or relative impulſe. Ογ BC may be the tranſverfe ſection of the ſail of a common wind-mill. This, by the conſtruction of the machine, can move only in the direction GP, perpendicular to the direction of the wind ; and it is only in this direction that the impulſe produces the deſired effect. Ογ BC may be half of the prow of a punt or lighter, riding at anchor by means of the cable ' DC, attached to the prow C. In this caſe, GfiL. pa-rallel to DC, is that part of the abſolute impulfe which <hi rend="italic">is</hi>  employed in ſtraining the cable.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">angle of incidence</hi>  is the angle F G C contained between the direction of the ſtream FG and the plane BC.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">angle oſ obliquity</hi>  is the angle OGC contained between the plane and the direction GO, in which we wiſh to eſtimate the impulſe.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop. II. The direct impulfe of a fluid on a plane ſurface, is to its abſolute oblique impulſe on the ſame furface, as the ſquare of the radius to the ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence.</hi></p><p>Let a ſtream of fluid, moving in the direction DC,</p><p>(fig. ι.), act on the plane BC. with the radius CB deſcribe the quadrant ABE ; draw CA perpendicular to CE, and draw MN BS parallel to CE. Let t,he particle E, moving in the direction FG, meet the plane in G, and in F G produced take GH to reprefent the magnitude of the direct impulſe, or the impulſe which the particle would exert on the plane AC, by meeting it in V. Draw GI and HR perpendicular to BC, and HI perpendicular to G I. Alſo draw BR perpendicular to DC.</p><p>The force GH is equivalent to the two forces GI and GK ; and GK being in the direction of the plane has no ſhare in the impnlſe. The abſolute impulſe, therefore, is reprefeπted by GI ; the angle GHI is equal to FGC, the angle of incidence; and there·» fore GH is to GI as radius - to the fine of the angle of incidence : Therefore the direct impulſe of each particle or filament is to its abſolute ob-lique impulſe as radius to the fine of the angle of inci-dence. But further, the number of particles or filaments which ſtrike the ſurface AC, is to the number of thoſe which ſtrike the ſurſhce B C as A C to NC : for all the filaments between LA and MB go paſt the ob-lique furface BC without ſtriking it. But BC : NC≈ rad. : fin. NBC, = rad. : fin. FGC, = rad. : fin. incidence. Now the whole impulſe is as the impulſe of each filament, and as the number of filaments exerting equal impulſes jointly ; therefore the whole direct im-pulſe on AC is to the whole abſolute impulſe on BC, as the ſquare of radius to the ſquare of the fine of the angle of incidence.</p><p>Let S expreſs the extent of the ſurface, <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  the angle of incidence, <hi rend="italic">o</hi>  the angle of obliquity, <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  the velocity of the fluid, and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  its denfity. Let F repreſent the direct impulſe, <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  the abſolute oblique impulſe, and <hi rend="italic">φ </hi>the relative or effective impulſe : And let the tabular fines and coſines be coniidered as decimal fractions of the radius unity.</p><p>This propofition gives us F : ∕ = R<hi rend="sup">z</hi> : Sin.’<hi rend="italic">i, =</hi>  ι : Sin.’ <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  and therefore <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  = F × Sin.’ z. Alſo, becauſe impulſes are in the proportion of the extent of ſurface fimilarly impelled, we have, in general, ∕= F S X Sind, <hi rend="italic">i.</hi></p><p>The firſt who publiſhed this theorem was Pardies, in his <hi rend="italic">Oeuvres de Mathématique,</hi>  in 1673. we., know that Newton had inveſtigated the chief propoſitions of the Principia before 1670.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prop. III. The direct impulſe on any ſurſace is to the effective oblique impulſe on the ſame ſurface, as the cube of radius to the ſolid, which has for its baſe the ſquare of the fine of incidence, and the fine of obliquity for its height.</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>