<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>then the ordinary theory will furniſh maxims of con· ftruction which will be very ſerviceable. This will be attempted in its proper place ; and we ſhall endeavour, in our treatment of all the practical queſtions, to derive uſeful information from all that has been delivered on the preſent occaſion.</p><p>RESOLUTION √Ιdeδs. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Logic,</hi>  Parti, ch. 3,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution, in muſic. To </hi><hi rend="italic">reſolve</hi>  a diſcord or diſ-ſonauce, fays Rouffeau, is to carry it according to rule into a conſonance in the ſubſequent chord. There is for that purpofe a procedure preſcribed, both for the fundamental baſs of the diffonant chord, and for the part by which the diffonance is formed.</p><p>There is no poſſible manner of reſolving a diffo-nance which is not derived from an operation of cadence: it is then by the kind of cadence which we wiſh to form, that the motion of the fundamental baſs is de-termined, (ſee Cadence), with reſpect to the part by which the diſibnance is formed, it ought neither to continue in its place, nor to move by disjointed gra-dations ; but to riſe or deſcend diatonically, accord-ing to the nature of the diffonance. Theoriſts ſay, that major diffonances ought to riſe, and minor to de-ſcend ; which is not however without exception, ſince in particular chords of harmony, a ſeventh, although major, ought not to riſe, but to deſcend, unleſs in that chord which is, very incorrectly, called <hi rend="italic">the chord of the ſeventh redundant.</hi>  It is better then to ſay, that the ſeventh and all its derivative diffonanees ought to deſcend ; and that the ſixth ſnperadded, and all its de-rivative diffonances, ſhould riſe. This is a rule truly general, and without any exception. It is the ſame cafe with the rule of reſolving diffonances. There are ſome diffonances which cannot be prepared ; but there is by no means one which ought not to be reſolved.</p><p>with reſpect to the ſenſible note, improperly called a <hi rend="italic">major diſfonance,</hi>  if it ought to aſcend, this is leſs on account of the rule for reſolving diffonanees, than on account of that which preſcribes a diatonic procedure, and prefers the ſhorteſt road ; and in reality, there are caſes, as that of the interrupted cadence, in which this fenſible note does not aſcend.</p><p>In chords by ſuppoſition, one ſingle chord often produces two diffonances ; as the ſeventh and ninth, the ninth and fourth, &amp;c.· Then theſe two diffonances ought to have been prepared, and both muff iikewiſe be reſolved ; it is becauſe regard ſhould be paid to every thing which is diſcordant, not only in the fun-damental, but even in the continued baſs.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution, in chemiſtry, the reduction of a mixed body into its component parts or ſirſt principles, as far as can be done by a proper analyſis.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Resolution,</hi>  in medicine, the diſappearſhg of any tumor without coming to fuppuration or forming an abſceſs.</p><p>RESOLVENTS, in medicine, ſuch as are proper for diſſipating tumors, without allowing them to come to fuppuration.</p><p>RESONANCE, Resounding, in muſic, &amp;c. a found returned by the air incloſed in the bodies of ſtringed inſtruments, ſuch as lutes, &amp;c or even in the bodies of wind-ſhſtruments, as flutes, &amp;c.</p><p>RESPIRATION, the act of refpiring or breathing the air. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy, n</hi><hi rend="sup">θ</hi>  118. Blood, n 29. Medicine,  n' 104. <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology,</hi>  Sect. I.and<hi rend="smallcaps">Pvtrefac∙&gt;</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">tion </hi><hi rend="italic">pajfim,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Respirationo/</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">F'ι∕hes.</hi>  See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ichthyology, n</hi><hi rend="sup">0</hi>7, 8, 9.</p><p>RESPITE, in law, ſignifies a delay, forbearance, cr prolongation of time, granted to any one ſor the pay-ment of a debt or the like. See Reprieve.</p><p>RESPONDENT,, in the ſchools, one who main-tains a thelis in any art or ſeience ; who is thus called from his being to anſwer all the objections propoſed by the opponent.</p><p>RESPONDENTIA. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bottomry.</hi></p><p>RESPONSE, an anſwer or reply. A word chiefly uſed in ſpeaking of the anſwers made by the people to the prieſt, in the litany, the pſalms, &amp;c.</p><p>RESSORT, a Ftench word, ſometimes uſed by En-gliſh authors to ſignify the juriſdiction of a court, and particularly one from which there is no appeal. — Thus it is ſaid, that the houſe of lords judge <hi rend="italic">en dernier reffort, </hi>or in the laſt reffυrt.</p><p>REST, the continuance of a body in the ſame place, or its continual application or contiguity to the ſame parts of the ambient or contiguous bodies ; and therefore is oppoſed to motion. See the article Mo-TION.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rest, in poetry, is a ſhort pauſe of the voice in reading, being the ſame with the cæfura, which, in Alexandrine verſes, falls on the ſixth ſyllable ; but in verſes of 10 or 11 ſyllables, on the fourth. See Poetry, Part III.</hi></p><p>REST-HARROW, or Cammock, <hi rend="italic">the Ononis Λr-venfis.</hi>  A decoction of this plant has been much re-commended to horſes labouring under a ſtoppage of urine. It is the peſt of ſome corn-fields ; but in its-younger ſtate, before the plant has acquired its thorns, it is a moſt acceptable food to ſhccp.</p><p>RESTAURA ΓΙΟΝ, the act of re-eſtabliſhſhg βr fetting a thing or perſon in its former good ſtate.</p><p>REST 10, in botany ; a genus of the triandria or-der, belonging to the diœcia claſs of plants. The male calyx is an ovate ſpike of membranaceous ſcales ; the corolla is proper, hexapetalous, and perſiſtent. The fe-male calyx and corolla are as in the male ; the germen is roundiſh, and lex∙fulcated ; there are three erect and perſiſtent ſtyles ; the capſule is roundiſh, with fix plaits, and is roſtrated and trilocular; the feeds are oblong and cylindrical.</p><p>RESTITUTI0N, in a moral and legal ſenſe, is reſtoring a perſon to his right, or returning ſomething unjuſtly taken or detained from him.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Restitution of Medals,</hi></hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Refiitυted Medals,</hi>  is a term uſed by antiquaries for ſuch medals· as were ſtruck by the emperors, to retrieve the memory of their pre-dect’ffors.</p><p>Hence, in ſeveral medals, we find the letters rest.. This practice was ſirſt begun by Claudius, by his ſtri-king afreſh ſeveral medals of Auguſtus. Nero did the ſame ; and Titus, after his father’s example, ſtruck re-ſtitutions of moſt of his predeceffors. Gallienus ſtruck a general reſtitution of all the preceding emperors on two medals ; the one bearing an altar, the other an eagle, without the rest.</p><p>RESTIVE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Re sty,</hi>  in the manege, a ſtubborn<hi rend="sub">? </hi>unruly, ill-broken hoiſſe, that ſtops, or runs back, inſtead of advancing forward.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>