<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>not unaptly denominate both the kinds of energies in queſtion, by the terms <hi rend="italic">emphafis of fenſe,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">tmphafis of forte(c}.</hi></p><p>Now from the above account of tbeſe two ſpecies of emphaſis it will appear, " that in reading, as in ſpeak-ing, tlie ſirſt of them muſt be determined entirely by the <hi rend="italic">ſenſe</hi>  of the paffage, and always made <hi rend="italic">alike :</hi>  But as to the other, <hi rend="italic">tafle</hi>  alone ſeems to have a right of fixing its ſituation and quantity.”—Farther : Since the more effential of theſe two energies is ſolely the work of <hi rend="italic">na-tore</hi>  (as appears by its being <hi rend="italic">coηfiaηtly</hi>  found in the common converſation of people of all kinds ot capacities and degrees of knowledge), and the moft ignorant perfon never fails of ufing it <hi rend="italic">rightly</hi>  in the effuſions of his own heart, it happens very luckily, and ought always to be remembered, that provided we underſtand what we read, and give way io the dictates of our own feeling, the <hi rend="italic">emphafis of ſenfe</hi>  can fearce ever avoid falling ſpontaneouſly upon its proper place.</p><p>Here it will be neceffary to ſay ſomething by way of reply to a queſtion which will naturally occur to the mind of every one. As the rule for the <hi rend="italic">emphafis</hi>  of <hi rend="italic">ſenſe </hi>requires we ſhould underſtand what we read before it can be properly uſed, it is incumbent upon us never to attempt to read what we have not previouſly ſtudied for that purpoſe ? In anfwer to this, it muſt be obſer-ved, that though ſuch a ſtep will not be without its advantages ; yet, as ſrom the fairnefs of printed types, the well-known pauſes of punctuation, and a long ac-quaintance with the phraſeology and conſtruction of our language, &amp;c. experience tells us it is <hi rend="italic">pojfible</hi>  to comprehend the fenſe at the firſt reading, a previous peruſal of what is to be read does not ſeem <hi rend="italic">neceffary</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">all, </hi>though, if they would wiſſi to appear to advantage, it may be <hi rend="italic">expedient</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">many ;</hi>  and it is this circumſtance</p><p>which makes us venture upon extemporary reading, and give it a place among our arouſements.—Similar re-marks might be made with regard to <hi rend="italic">modulation, expreſfion,</hi>  &amp;c. did not what is here obſerved naturally anticipate them.</p><p>III. <hi rend="italic">Modulation </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(d). Every perſon muſt have obſerved, that, in ſpeaking,. the voice is ſnbject to an alteration of found, which in ſome meafure reſembles the movement of a tune. Theſe founds, however, are evidently nothing like ſo much varied as thoſe that are ſtrictly mufical ; and we have attempted to ſliow in the preceding chapter, that, befides this, they have an effential difference in themfelves. Nevertheleſs, from the general fimilitude of theſe two articles, they poſiels feveral terms in common; and the particular we have now to examine is in both of them called </hi><hi rend="italic">modulation. </hi>This affection of the voice, being totally <hi rend="italic">arbitrary,</hi>  is differently characterized in different parts of the world; and, through the power of cuſtom,,every place is in-cliπed to think their own the only one natural and agreeable, and the reſt affected with ſome barbarous twang or ungainly variation ( e ). It maybe obſerved, however, that though there is a general uniform caſt or faſlrion of modulation peculiar to every country, yet it by no means follows, that there is or can be any thing fixed in its application to particular paffages ; and therefore we find different people will, in any given inſtance, ufe modulations fomething different, and nevertheleſs be each of them equally agreeable.</p><p>But, quitting thefe general remarks, we ſhall (as our purpoſe requires it) confider the properties of modula -tion a little more minutely.</p><p>Firſt, then, we may obſerve, that, in ſpeaking, there is a particular found (or <hi rend="italic">key-note,</hi>  as it is often called) in which the modulation for the moſt part runs, and to</p><p>(c)    The firſt of thefe terms anſwers to the <hi rend="italic">fimple emphafis</hi>  deſcribed in the <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Elocution,</hi>  and the ſecond <hi rend="italic">nearly</hi>  to what is there called <hi rend="italic">complex.</hi>  The difference lies in this. Under <hi rend="italic">complex emphafis</hi>  the author ſeems (for he is far from being clear in this article) to include the <hi rend="italic">tones</hi>  fimply confidered of all the eft&gt;otions of the mind ; as well the <hi rend="italic">tender</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">languid,</hi>  as the <hi rend="italic">forcible</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">exulting,</hi>  our term is intended to be confined to ſuch modes of expreſſion alone as are marked with an apparent <hi rend="italic">firefis</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">increaſe</hi>  of the voice.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(d)</hi>     The author of the <hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Art oſ Reading,</hi>  not allowing that there is any variation of tone, as to <hi rend="italic">high</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">low,</hi>  in the delivery of a complete period or ſentence, places modulation ſolely in the diverfification of the key-note and the variety of ſyllables, as to <hi rend="italic">long</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">ſhorl, ſwiſt</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">flow, Jtivng</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">weak,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">loud</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Joft.</hi>  As we are of a different opinion, our idea of modulation is confined purely to <hi rend="italic">harmonious inflexions oſ voice.</hi>  Thefe qualities of words, it is true, add greatly both to the force and beauty of delivery ; yet, ſince ſome of them are fixed and not arbitrary (as <hi rend="italic">long</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ſhort),</hi>  and the others (of <hi rend="italic">ſwiſt</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">fiοw,firong</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">weak, loud</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">ſſt), </hi>may be conſidered as modes of expreſſion which do not affect the modulation as to <hi rend="italic">tone,</hi>  it will agree belt with our plan to eſteem theſe properties as refpectively belonging to the eſtabliſlied laws of <hi rend="italic">pronunciation</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">imitative</hi>  branch of expreſſion mentioned in the end of the enſuing head.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(e)</hi>     From what accounts we have remaining of the modulation of the ancients, it appears to have been highly ornamented, and apparently ſomething not unlike our modern <hi rend="italic">recitative ;</hi>  particularly that of their theatric declamation was muſic in its ſtricteſt ſenſe, and accompanied with inſtruments. In the courſe of time and the progreſs of refinement, this modulation became gradually more and more ſimple, till it has now loſt the genius of muſic, and is entirely regulated by taſte. At home here, every one has heard the <hi rend="italic">fing-fong</hi>  cant, as it is called, of</p><p>Ti ti dum dum, ti ti dum ti dum de,</p><p>Ti dum ti dum, ti dum ti dum dum de ;</p><p>which, though difguſtful now to all but mere rqſtics on account of its being out of ſaſhion, was very probably the favourite modulation in which heroic verſes were recited by our anceſtors. So fluctuating are the taſte and practices of mankind ! But whether the power of language over the paſſions has received any advantage from the change juſt mentioned, will appear at leaſt very doubtful, when w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>e recollect the ſtories of its former triumphs-, and the inherent charms of muſical founds.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>