<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Mountain, by the aſſiſtance of the Jacobin club, had now acquired a complete aſcendancy over the city of Paris. The Girondiſts or Briſſotines propoſed therefore to remove the convention from the capital ; and to prevent this, rhe <hi rend="italic">Mountain</hi>  reſolved to make the ſame uſe of the people of the capital -againſt the Girondiſt party that they had formerly done againſt the monarch on the I oth of Auguſt. It is unneceſſary to ſtate in detail all the tumults that occurred either in Paris or in the convention during the remaining part of the month of May. On the 31ft, at four o’clock in the morning, the tociin was founded, the generale was beat, and the alarm guns fired. All was commotion and terror. The citizens flew to arms, and aſſembled round tbe convention. Some deputations demanded a decree of accuſation againſt 35 of its members. The day, however, was ſpent without deciſion. On the afternoon of the iſt of June an armed force made the ſame demand. On the 2d of June this was repeated, the tocſin again founded, and an hundred pieces of cannon ſurrounded the national hall. At laſt Barfere mounted the tribune. He was confidered as a moderate man, and reſpected by both parties ; but he now artfully deſerted the Girondiſts. He invited the denounced members voluntarily to reſign their character of repreſentatives. Some of them complied, and the preſident attempted to diſſolve the ſitting ; but the members were now imprifoned in their own hall. Henriot, commander of the armed force, compelled them to remain ; and the obnoxious deputies, amounting to upwards of 90 in number, were put under arreſt, and a decree of denunciation againſt them ſigned.</p><p>It is obvious, that on this' occaſion the liberties of France were trodden under foot. The minority of the national repreſentatives, by the aſſlſtance of an armed force raiſed in the capital, compelled the majority to ſubmit to their meaſures, and took the leading members prifoners. Thus the city of Paris aſſumed to itſelf the whole powers of the French republic ; and the nation was no longer governed by repreſentatives freely cliofen, but by a minority of their members, whoſe ſentiments the city of Paris and the Jacobin club had thought ſit to approve of. Human hiſtory is a maſs of contradictions. The <hi rend="italic">Mountain</hi>  party came into power by preaching liberty, and by violating its fundamental principles. How ſar the plea of political neceffity may excuſe their con-duct, we ſhall not venture to decide explicitly. Certain it is, however, that they ſoon commenced a career of the moſt terrible energy both at home and abroad that is to be found in the annals of nations.</p><p>The ſirſt refult of their victory in the capital was ca-lamitous to the republic at large. Briſſot and ſome other deputies eſcaped, and endeavoured to kindle the flames of civil war. In general, however, the influence of the Jacobin club, and of its various branches, was ſuch, that the north of France adhered to the convention as it ſtood ; but the ſouthern departments were ſpeedily in a ſtate of rebellion. Tlie department of Lyons declared the <hi rend="italic">Mountain</hi>  party outlawed. Marfeilles and Toulon followed tlie example of Lyons, and entered into a confederacy, which has ſince been known by the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Faderaliſm.</hi>  The departments of La Gironde and Calvades broke out into open revolt. In ſhort, the whole of France was in a ſtate of violent convulſion. Still, however, the enthuſiaſtic garriſons of Mentz and Valenciennes protected it againſt the ſm« mediate entrance of a foreign force, and allowed leiſure for one of its internal factions to gain an aſcendancy, and thereafter to protect its independence. In the mean time, the political entliuſiaſm of all orders of per-fons was ſuch, that even tlie female ſex did not eſcape its contagion. A young woman of the name of Charlotte Cordé, in tlie beginning of July, came from the department of Calvades to devote her life for what ſhe thought the cauſe of freedom and of her country. She requeſted an interview with <hi rend="italic">Marat,</hi>  the moſt obnoxious of the Mountain party. Having obtained it, and con-verſed with him calmly for ſome time, ſhe ſuddenly plunged a dagger in his breaſt, and walked careleſsly out of the houſe. She was immediately ſeized and condemned. At the place of execution ſhe behaved with infinite conſtancy, ſhouting <hi rend="italic">Vive la république.</hi>  The remains of Marat were interred with great ſplendor, and the convention attended his funeral. His party perhaps derived advantage from the manner of his death, as it ſeemed to fatten the odious charge of affaſ-ſination upon their antagoniſts, and gave them the appearance of ſuffering in the cauſe of liberty. The truth is, that aſſaffination was ſanctioned by both parties under pretence of defending the liberties of the republic.</p><p>One of the ſirſt acts of the Mountain junto after their triumph was to ſiniſh the republican conftitution. Previous to tlieir fall, the Girondiſts liad brought forward tlie plan of a conſtitution, chiefly the work of Condorcet; but it never was ſanctioned by the convention, and was too intricate to be practically uſeful. The new conſtitution now framed, which was afterwards ſanctioned by the nation, but has never yet been put in practice, aboliſhes the former mode of electing the repreſeutatives of the people through the medium of <hi rend="italic">electoral</hi>  aſtemblies, and appoints them to be choſen immediately by the <hi rend="italic">primary</hi>  aſſemblies, which are made to conſiſt of from 200 to 600 citizens, each man vo-ting by ballot or open vote at his option. There is·· one deputy for every 40,000 individuals, and population is the ſole baſis of repreſentation. The elections take place every year on the iſt of May. Electoral aſtemblies are ſtill retained ſor one purpoſe. Every 200 citizens in the primary aſſemblies name one elector ; and an aſſembly of all the electors of the department is afterwards held, which elects candidates ſor the <hi rend="italic">executive council,</hi>  or miniſtry of the republic. The legiſſative body choofes out of this liſt of candidates the members of the executive council. One half of this council is renewed by each legiſſature in the laſt month of the ſeſc ſlon. Every law, after it is paſſed by the legiſſative body, is ſent to the department. Iſ in more than half of the departments the tenth of the primary aſſemblies of each have not objected to it, it becomes effectual.. Trial by jury is eſtabliſhed. National conventions may be called for altering the conſtitution, and <hi rend="italic">muß</hi>  be call-ed, if · required by the tenth of the primary affemblies of eacll department in a majority of the departments.</p><p>The publication of tliis conſtitution procured no ſmall degree of applauſe to the convention and the Mountain party. The rapidity with which it was formed (being only a fortnight) ſeemed to caſt a juſt reproach upon the ſſowneſs of their antagoniſts, and it was regarded as a proof of their being decidedly ſe-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>