<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>foreſt trees were unable to vvithſtand thc fury of the tempeſt. The hail was compofed of enormous, iolid, and angular pieces office, ſome of them weighing from eight to ten ounces. The conntry people, beaten down in the fields on their way to church, amidſt this concuf-ſion of the elements, concluded that the laſt day was arrived ; and ſcarcely attempting to extricate themfelves, lay defpairing and half ſuffocated amidſt the water and the mud, expecting the immediate diffolution of all things. The ſtorm was irregular in its devaſtations. while ſeveral rich diſtricts were laid entirely waſte, ſome intermediate portions of country were comparatively little injured. Οηε of 6o ſquare leagues had not a fingle ear of corn or a fruit of any kind left, of the 66 pariſhes in the diſtrict of Pontoiſe, 43 were entirely defolated, and of the remaining 23 ſome loſt two-thirds and others half their harveſt. The iſle of France, be-ing the diſtrict in which Paris is ſituated, and the Ογ-leannois, appear to have ſuffered chiefly. The damage there, upon a moderate eſtimate, amounted to 80,000,000 of livres, or between three and four millions Sterling. Such a calamity muſt at any period have been ſeverely felt ; but occurring on the eve of a great political revolution, and amidſt a general ſcarcity throughout Europe, it was peculiarly unfortunate, and gave more embarraſſment to the government than per-haps any other event whatever. Numbers of families found it neceſſary to contract their mode of living for a time, and to diſmifs their ſervants, who were thus left deſtitute of bread. Added to the public difcontent and political diſſenſions, it produced ſuch an effect upon the people in general, that the nation ſeemed to have changed its character ; and inſtead of that levity by which it had ever been diſtinguiſhed, a fettled gloom now feemed fixed on every countenance.</p><p>The ſpring of the year 1789 was a period of much political anxiety in France. The ſuperior orders wiſhed to reduce the power of the crown, but were jealous oſ their own privileges, and determined to retain them; while the popular philoſophers and others were endeavouring to render them odious, and to rouſe the people to a love of freedom. Still, however, the great body of the common people remained careleſs fpectators of the ſtruggle and unconſcious of the approaching commotion. Such was their indifference, that few of them took the trouble even to attend and vote at the elections of the deputies to the ſtates-general. In many places, where a thouſand voters were expected, not fifty came forward ; but ſuch of them as did appear ſhowed that a feed was fown which might one day rife into important fruits. In the inſtructions which they gave to their deputies, the Britiſh conſtitution was in general the model of what they wiſhed their government to be. They demanded equal taxation, the abolition of <hi rend="italic">lettres de cachet</hi>  or arbitrary impriſonment, the refponſibility of miniſters, and the extinction of the feudal privileges of the nobles ; but they wiſhed that the whole three orders of the ſtate ſhould fit and vote in one houſe, well knowing that their nobility were not prepared to act the moderate part of a Britiſh houſe of lords. The nobles, on the contrary, although willing to renounce ſome of their pecuniary privileges, and to ſacrifice the power of the crown, were moſt deciſively reſolved neither to ſurrender their feudal prerogatives nor the right of fitting in three feparate affemblies; by means of which each of the orders could eaſily reſiſt the encroachments of the other two. Mr Neckar has been improperly cen-fured for not deciding this laſt important queſtion pre-vious to the meeting of the ſtates-gencral : but it muſt be obſerved, that the very purpoſe of calling that aſſembly vzas to overturn the unjuſt privileges of the higher orders through its medium, and without any di-rect interpoſition on the part of the miniſters. Had the king poſitively decided in favour of three chambers, the nobles and the clergy would have retained all thoſe ancient abuſes eſtabliſhed in their own favour, of which it was his wiſh to deprive them, and the crown and its prerogatives would have been the only objects of ſacri-fice. It w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>as therefore thought ſafer to leave the<hi rend="italic">tiers etat</hi>  to fight its own battle : nor was it yet imagined that the commons of France, depreſſed and poor, and diſperſed by ſituation over a multitude of provinces, could ever unite in enterpriſes dangerous to tire ſove-reign.</p><p>The ſtates had been ſummoned to meet at verfailles on the 27th of April, and moſt of the deputies arrived at that time ; but the elections for the city of Paris not. being concluded, the king deferred the commencement of their ſeffions till the 4th of May. During this period, the members, left in idleneſs, began to find out and form acquaintance with each other. Among others, a few members from Brittany (Bretagne) form-ed themſelves into a club, into which they gradually ad-mitted many other deputies that were found to be zea-lous for the popular cauſe, and alſo many perſons who were not deputies. This ſociety, thus originally eſta-bliſhed at verfailles, was called the <hi rend="italic">Comité Breton;</hi>  and was one day deſtined, under the appellation of the <hi rend="italic">(fa-cobin Club,</hi>  to give laws to France, and to diſſuſe terror and alarm throughout Europe. Οη the other fide, the ariſtocratic party eſtabliſhed conferences at the houſe of Madame Polignac, for the purpoſe, it is ſaid, of uniting the nobles and the clergy.</p><p>An event occurred at this time which all parties aſcri-bed to ſome malicious motive. In the populous ſuburb of St Antoine, a M. Reveillon carried on a great paper manufactory. A falſe report was ſpread that he intended to lower the wages of his workmen, and that he had declared bread was too good for them, and that they might ſubſiſt very well on potato-flour. A corn-motion was raifed, he was burnt in effigy, and his houſe was thereafter burnt and pillaged by the mob, who were not diſperſed till the military had been called in, and much carnage enſued. The popular party aſſerted that the commotion had been artfully excited by the party of the queen and the Count D’Artois, to afford a pretence for bringing great bodies of the military to the neighbourhood to overawe the ſtates-general, or induce the king more decifively to reſolve on affembling that body at verfailles, in preference to Paris, where they and the popular miniſter M. Neckar wiſhed it to be held.</p><p>Ο11 the 4th of May the ſtates-general aſſembled at verfailles. They commenced bufineſs by going in a folemn proceſſion, preceded by the clergy, and foliow-ed by the king, according to ancient cnſtom, to church, to perform an act of devotion. The nobles were ar-rayed in a ſplendid robe, and they and the higher cler-gy glittered in gold and jewels. The commons ap-peared in black, the drefs belonging to the law. The</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>