<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the troops, offering to be reſponſible for the public peace, and to proceed in a body to Paris to encoun-ter perſonally every danger that might occur. But they were coolly told, that the king was the beſt judge of the mode of employing the troops, and that the pre-fence of the aſſembly was neceſſary at Verfailles. From a fovereign wh® doubtleſs recollected the proceedings of the long parliament of England, a different reply could not in reafon be expected. Οη receiving it, however, it was inſtantly decreed, on the motion of the marquis de la Fayette, that the late miniſtry had <hi rend="italic">carried with them</hi>  the confidence of the aſſembly ; that the troops <hi rend="italic">ought</hi>  to be <hi rend="italic">removed ;</hi>  that the miniſtry are and ſhall be reſponſible to the people for their conduct ; that the aſſembly perſiſted in all its former decrees ; and that as it had taken the public debt under the protec-tion of the nation, no power in France was entitled to pronounce the infamous word <hi rend="italic">bankruptcy.</hi></p><p>The city of Paris was thrown into deep conſterna-tion by the news of M. Neckar’s retreat. His bull and that of the Duke dOrleans were dreſſed in mourning, and carried through the ſtreets. The royal Alle-mand, a German regiment, broke in pieces the buſts, and diſperſed the populace. The prince De Lambeſq, grand ecuyer of France, was ordered to advance with his regiment of cavalry, and take poſt at the Tlιuilleries. Being a man of a violent temper, and enraged by the appearances of diſapprobation which were viſible around him, he furiouſly cut down with his ſword a poor old man who was walking peaceably in the gardens. The conſequences of this act of inhumanity were ſuch as might have been expected ; a ſhout of execration instantly aroſe ; the cry <hi rend="italic">to arms</hi>  was heard ; the military were aſſaulted on all ſides ; the French guards joined their countrymen, and compelled the Germans, over-powered by numbers, and unſupported by the reſt of the army, to retire.</p><p>All order was now at an end, and as night approached an univerſal terror diſſuſed itſelf through the city. Bands of robbers were collecting ; and from them or from the foreign ſoldiery a general pillage was expected. The night paſſed away in conſternation and tumult. It was found in thc morning that the hoſpital of St Lazare was already plundered. The alarm bells were rung ; the citizens aſſembled at the Hotel de ville, and adopted a propoſal that was there made, of enrolling themſelves as a militia for general defence, under the appellation of the <hi rend="italic">national guard.</hi>  This day and the ſucceed-ing night were ſpent in tolerable quietneſs, without any attempt on the part of the army. Οη the morning of the memorable 14th of July, it was diſcovered that the troops encamped in the Champs Eliſees had moved off, and an immediate aſſault was expected. The national guard now amounted to 150,000 men ; but they were in general deſtitute of arms. They had aſſumed a green cockade ; but on recollecting that this was the livery of the Count d’Artois, they adopted one of red, blue, and white. M. de la Salle was named commander in chief, officers were choſen, and detachments ſent around in queſt of arms. In the Hotel des Invalides upwards of 30,000 ſtand of arms were found, along with 20 pieces of cannon ; a variety of weapons was alfo procured from the <hi rend="italic">garde meuble de la couronne,</hi>  and from the ſhops of armourers, cutlers, &amp;c.    »</p><p>The celebrated fortreſs of the Baſtile was an object</p><p>of much jealouſy to the Pariſians. At 11 o'clock in the morning, M. de la Roſiere, at the head of a numerous deputation, waited upon M. de Launay the go-vernor, who promifed, ∙ along with the officers of his garrifon, that they would not ſire upon the city unleſs they ſhould be attacked. But a report was foon ſpread through Paris, that M. de Launay had, in a ſhort time thereafter, admitted into the fortreſs a multitude of perſons, and then treacherouſly maſſacred them. The cauſe of this piece of perfidy has never been explained. The fact itſelf has been denied ; but it was atteſted at the time by the duke of Dorſet, the Britiſh ambaſſa-dor at the court of France. The effect of the report was, that a ſudden refolution was adopted of aſſaulting the Baſtile ; an immenſe and furious multitude ruſhed into its outer, and ſoon forced their way into its inner, courts, where they received and returned a ſevere fire for the fpace of an hour. The French guards, who were now embodied into the national guard, conducted the attack with ſkill and coolneſs : they dragged three waggons loaded with ſtraw to the foot of the walls, and there ſet them on fire ; the ſmoke of thcſe broke the aim of the garrifon, while it gave no diſturbance to the more diſtant a(Γailants. The beſieging multitude preſſed the attack with incredible obſtinacy and vigour for the ſpace of four hours ; the garrifon was in confuſion ; the officers ſerved the cannon in perfon, and fired their muſkets in the ranks ; the governor, in deſpair, thrice attempted to blow up the fortrefs. A capitulation, when at laſt fought, was refuſed to the garrifon, and an unconditional ſurrender took place. The governor, and M. de Loſme Salbrai his major, a gentleman of diſtinguiſhed humanity and honour, be-came victims of popular fury in ſpite of every effort that could be made for their protection ; but the French guards ſucceeded in procuring the ſafety of the garrifon. only feven priſoners were found in the Baſtile.</p><p>A guard was placed in it, and the keys were ſent to the celebrated M. Briffot de warville, who a few years before had inhabited one of its caverns.</p><p>The remaining part of this eventful day was fpent at Paris in a mixture of triumph and alarm. In the pocket of the governor of the Baſtile a letter was found, encouraging him to reſiſtance by the promiſe of ſpeedy ſuccours, written by M. de Fleffelles, the prevot de marchands, or chief city magiſtrate, who had pretended to be a moſt zealous patriot. This piece of trea-chery was puniſhed by inſtant death ; and his bloody head was carried through the city on a pole, along with, that of M. de Launay. At the approach of night a body of troops advanced towards the city, at the Bar-riere d<hi rend="sup">,</hi>Enfer. The new national guard hurried thither, preceded by a train of artillery, and the troops withdrew upon the firſt fire : barricadoes were everywhere formed, the alarm-bells were rung, and a general illumination continued during the whole of this night of confuſion.</p><p>In the mean time, it was obvious that the new mini-ſtry were entering upon a difficult ſcene of action, where one falſe ſtep might lead to ruin, and where their own plan of conduct ought to be maturely digeſt-ed. Marſhall Broglio was made miniſter of war, the baron de Breteuil preſident of finance, M. de la Gale-ziere comptroller-general, M. de la Porte intendant of the war department, and M. Foulon intendant of the</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>