<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The difference between raiſins dried in the fun and thoſc dried in ovens, is very obvious : the former are ſweat and pleaſant, but the latter have a latent acidity with the ſweetneſs that renders them much leſs agreeable.</p><p>The cpmmon way of drying grapes for raiſins, is to tie two or three bunches of them together while yet on the vine, aud dip them into a hot lixivium of wood-aſhes, with a little of the oil of olives in it. This diſ-poſes them to ſhrink and wrinkle ; and after this they are left on the vine three or four days ſeparated on ſticks in an horizontal ſituation, and then dried in the fun at leiſure, after being cut from the tree. The ſineſt aud beſt raiſins are thoſe called in ſome places <hi rend="italic">Damaſ-tus</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Tube roifins ;</hi>  which are diſtinguiſhed from the others by their ſize and figure : they are flat and wrinkled on the ſurface, foft and juicy within, and near an inch long ; and, when freſh and growing on the bunch, are of the ſize and ſhape of a large olive.</p><p>The raiſins of the ſun, and jar-raiſins, are all dried by the heat of the ſun ; and theſe are the ſorts uſed in medicine. However, all the kinds have much the ſame virtues : they are all nutritive and balſamic ; they are allowed to be attenuant, are ſaid to be good in nephritic complaints, and are an ingredient in pectoral decoc-tions : in which caſes, as alſo in all others where aſtrin-gency is not required of them, they ſhould have the ſtones carefully taken oκt.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RA is </hi><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">in</hi></hi><hi rend="italic">-Wine.</hi>  SeewiNE.</p><p>RAKKATH (anc. geog.), a town of Upper Galilee, thought to be Tiberias, (Talmud) : but this is denied by Reland, who fays that Rakkath was a town cf the tribe of Naphthali.</p><p>RAKE is a well known inſtrument with teeth, by which the ground is divided. See Agriculture, j&gt;. 3 i 8.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rake alſo means a looſe, diſorderly, vicious, and thoughtleſs fellow.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RAKe oſ a Ship,</hi>  is all that part of her hull which hangs over both ends of her keel. That which is be-fore is called the <hi rend="italic">fore rake,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">rake forward,</hi>  and that part which is at tlie ſetting on of the ſtern-poſt is call-cd the <hi rend="italic">rake-aji,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">afterward.</hi></p><p>RALEIGH (Sir walter), fourth fon of walter Raleigh, Eſq; of Fardel, in the pariſh of Cornwood in Devonſhire, was born in 1552 at Hayes, in the pariſh of Budley, a farm belonging to his father. About the year 1568, he was ſent to Οπεί college in oxford, where he continued but a ſhort time ; for in the following year he embarked for France, being one of the hundred volunteers, commanded by Henry Champer-non, who, with other Engliſh troops, were ſent by queen Eliſabeth to aſſiſt the queen of Navarre in defending the Proteſtants. In this ſervice he continued for five or ſix years ; after which he returned to Lon-don, and probably reſided in the Middle Temple. But his entcrpriſing genius would not ſuffer him to remain long in a ſtate of inactivity In 1577 or 1578, he embarked for the Low Countries with the troops ſent. by the queen to aſſiſt the Dutch againſt the Spaniards, and probably ſhared the glory of the deciſive victory over Don John of Auſtria in 1578. Οη his return to England, a new enterprife engaged his attention. His half-brother, Sir Humphrey Gilbert, having obtained a patent to plant and inhabit ſome parts of North America, Mr Raleigh embarked in this adventure ; but, meeting with a Spaniſh fleet, after a fraart engagement they returned, without ſucceſs, in 1579.</p><p>The following year, the king of Spain, in conjunc-tion with the pope, having projected a total couqneſt of the Engliſh dominions, ſent troops to Ireland to aſſiſt the Deſmonds in the Munſter rebellion. Raleigh obtained a captain’s commiſſion under Lord Grey of wilton, then deputy of Ireland, and embarked ſor that kingdom ; where, by his conduct and refolution, he was principally inſtrumental in putting an end to the rebellious attempt. He returned to England ; and attract-ed the notice of queen Eliſabeth, owing, as we are told in Naunton’s <hi rend="italic">Fragmenta Regalia,</hi>  to the following accidental piece of gallantry. The queen, as ſhe was one day taking a walk, being ſtopped by a <hi rend="italic">plajhy</hi>  place in the road, our gallant young ſoldier took off his new pluſh mantle, and ſpread it on the ground. Her ma∙ jeſty trod gently over the fair foot-cloth, ſurpriſed and pleaſed with the adventure. He was a handſome man, and remarkable for his gentility of addreſs.</p><p>The queen admitted him to her court, and employed him firſt as an attendant on the French ambaſſador Si-mier on his return home, and afterward to cſcort the duke of Anjou to Antwerp. During this excurſion he became perſonally known to the prince of orange ; from whom, at his return, he brought ſpecial acknowledgments to the queen, who now frequently converſed with him. But the inactive life of a courtier did not fuit the enterpriſing ſpirit of Mr Raleigh In the ycar 1583, he embarked with h.is brother, Sir Humphrey Gilbert, on a ſecond expedition to Newfoundland, in a ſhip called the <hi rend="italic">Rat'eigh,</hi>  which he built at his own ex-pence ; but was obliged to return on account of an in-fectiυus diſtemper on board. He was, however, ſo little affected by this diſappointment, that he now laid before the queen and council a propoſal for exploring the continent of North America; and in 1584 obtained a patent empowering him to poſſeſs ſnch countries as hc ſhould diſcover in that part of the globe. Accordingly Mr Raleigh fitted out two ſhips at his own expence, which ſailed ip the month of April, and returned to England about the middle of September, reporting that they had diſcovered and taken poſſeſſion of a fine country called <hi rend="italic">Windangocoa,</hi>  to which the queen gave the name of <hi rend="italic">Virginia.</hi>  About this time he was elected knight of the ſhire for the county of Devon, and ſoon aſter received the honour of knighthood ; and to enable him t® carry on his deſigns abroad, the queen granted him a patent for licenſing the venders of wine throughout the kingdom. In 1 ,85 he ſent a fleet of ſeven ſhips to virginia, commanded by his relation Sir Richard Greenville, who left a colony at Roanah of 107 perſons, under the government of Mr Lane; and by the eſtabliſhment of this colony he firſt imported tobacco into England. See Nicotiana. In the ſame year Sir walter Raleigh obtained a grant of 12,000 acres bf the forfeited lands in the county of Corke in Ireland.— About the ſame time he was made ſeneſchal of the duchy of Cornwall, and warden of the {tanneries ; and grew into fuch favour w.th the queen, that even Lei-ccſter was jealous of his influence.</p><p>In 1587, he ſent another colony of 150 men to vir-ginia, with a governor, Mr John white, and 12 aſſiſtants. About this time we find our knight diſtinguiſh-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>