<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>immediately deſerted and went borne to France. Dumou-rier continued to retreat, and on the 2 2d he was again attacked near Louvain. He now, through the medium of Colonel Mack, came to an agreement with the Im-perialiſts that his retreat ſhould not be ſeriouſſy inter-fupted. It was now fully agreed between him and the Imperialiſts, that while the latter took poffeffion of Condé and Valenciennes, he ſhould march to Paris, diffolve the convention, and place the ſon of the late king upon the throne.</p><p>The rapid retreat and ſucceffive defeats of General Dumourier rendered his conduct ſuſpicious. Commiſ-ſioners were ſent from the executive power for the purpoſe of diſeovering his deſigns. They diffembled, and pretended to communicate to him a ſeheme of a coun-ter-revolution. He confeffed his intention of diffolving the convention and the Jacobin club by force, which he ſaid would not exiſt three weeks longer, and of re-ſtoring monarchy. On the report of theſe commiſe fioners the convention ſent Bournonville the miniſter of war to ſuperſede and arreſt Dumourier, along with Camus, Blancal, La Marque, and Quinette, as commiffioners.' The attempt on the part of theſe men was at leaſt hazardous, to ſay no more of it ; and the reſult was, that on the ſirſt of April Dumourier ſent them priſoners to General Clairfait’s head quarters at Tournay as hoſtages for the ſaſety of the royal family. He next attempted to feduce his army from their fidelity to the convention ; but he ſpeedily found that he had much miſtaken the character of his troops. Upon the report that their general was to be carried as a criminal to Paris, they were ſeized with ſudden indignation; but when they found that an attempt was making to pre-vail with them to turn their arms againſt their country, their ſentiments altered. On the 5th of April two proclamations were iffued ; one by General Dumourier, and the other by the prince of Saxe Cobourg, declaring that their only pnrpoſe was to reſtore the conſtitution of 1789, 1790» and 1791. Prince Cobourg announ-ced that the allied powers wiſhed merely to co-operate with General Dumourier in giving to France her con-ſtitutſcnal king and the conſtitution ſhe had formed for herſelf, declaring, on his word of honour, that he came not to the French territory for the purpoſe of making conqueſts. O11 the ſame day Dumourier went to the advanced guard of his own camp at Maulde. He there learned that the corps of artillery had riſen upon their general, and were marching to Valenciennes ; and he ſoon found that the whole army had determined to ſtand by their country. Seven hundred cavalry and 800 infantry was the whole amount of thoſe that deſerted with Dumourier to the Auftrians, and many oſ them afterwards returned.</p><p>By the defection of Dumourier, however, the whole army of the north was diffolved, and in part diſhanded, in preſence of a numerous, well-diſciplined, and victorious enemy. The Pruffians were at the ſame time advancing on the Rhine with an immenſe force, and about to commence the ſiege of Mentz. In the interior of the republic more ſerious evils if poſſible were ariſing. In the departments of La Vendée and La Loire, or the Provinces of Brittany and Poitou, immenſe multitudes of emigrants and other royaliſts had gradually aſſembled in the courſe of the winter. They proſeſſed to act in the name oſ Monſieur, as regent oſ France.</p><p>About the middle oſ March they advanced againſt Nantz to the amount of 40,000. In the beginning oſ April they defeated the republicans in two pitched battles, and poſſeſſed themſelves oſ 50 leagues oſ country. They even threatened by their own efforts to ſhake the new republic to its foundation. On the 8th oſ April a congreſs of the combined powers aſſembled at Antwerp. It was attended by the prince of Orange and his two ſons, with his excellency Vander Spiegel, on the part of Holland ; by the duke of York and Lord Auckland on the part of Great Britain ; by the prince of Saxe Cobourg, Counts Metterinch, Staren-berg, and Mercy Dargenteau, with the Pruffian, Spa-niſh, and Neapolitan envoys. It was here determined to commence active operations againſt France. The prince of Cobourgſa proclamation was recalled, and a ſcheme of conqueſt announced.</p><p>Commiffioners from the convention now ſet up the ſtandard of the republic anew, and tlie ſeattered battalions flocked around it. General Dampierre was appointed commander, andon the 13th lie was able to reſiſt a general attack upon his advanced poſts. On tlie 14th, his advanced guard yielded to ſuperior numbers, but on tlie 15th was victorious in a long and well-fought battle. On the ' 23d tlie Auſtrians were again repulſed, and on thc iſt of May General Dampierre was himſelf repulſed in an attack upon tlic enemy. On the 8th another engagement took place, in which tlie French general was killed by a cannon ball. On the 23d a very determined attack was madc by the allies upon the French fortified camp of Famars, which covered the town of Valenciennes. I'he French were overcome, and in the night abandoned their camp. In confeqnence of this the allies were enabled to commence the ſiege of Valenciennes ; for Condé had been blockaded from the lſt of April.</p><p>About the ſame time General Cuſtine on the Rhine made a violent but unſucceſsful attack upon the Pruſc ſians, in conſequence of which they were ſoon enabled to lay ſiege to Mentz. The Corſican General Paoli revolted at this period ; and tlie new republic, affaulted ſrom without by the whole ſtrength oſ Europe, was un-dermined by treachery and faction within.</p><p>while the country was in a ſtate verging upon utter ruin, parties in the convention were gradually waxing more fierce in their animoſity ; and regardleſs oſ what was paffing at a diſtance, they ſeemed only anxious ſor the extermination oſ each other. In the month oſ March, the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Revolutionary Tribunal</hi>  was eſta-bliſhed ſor the purpoſe oſ trying crimes committed a-gainſt the ſtate; and the Girondiſt party, the mildneſs oſ whoſe adminiſtration had contributed not a little to increaſe the evils oſ their country, began to ſee the neceffity oſ adopting meaſures oſ ſeverity. But the pub-lic calamities, which now rapidly followed each other in fucceffion, were aſeribed by their countrymen to their imbecillity or perfidy. This gave to the party oſ tlie <hi rend="italic">Mountain</hi>  a fatal advantage. On the 15th oſ April tlie communes of the 48 ſections oſ Paris preſented a petition, requiring that the chiefs oſ the Girondiſts therein named ſhould be impeached and expelled from the convention. This was followed up on the lit of May by another petition from the ſuburb of St Antoine. The Girondiſt party in the mean time impeached Marat, but he was acquitted by the jury at his trial. '1 he</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>