<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of common ſenſe could receive it as authentic. He ſays it was death to touch the ark ! As ſuch an aſſertion was never heard oſ before, and as the ritual he was endeavouring to make them eſteem ſacred was opprcſſively multifarious ; ſurely ſome daring ſpirit would have ventured to put his veracity to the teſt by moving the ark and even offering ſacrifices ; and ſuch a teſt would at once have expofed the impoſture. The budding rod, too, and the hat of manna, which, though long preferved, were never before heard of', muſt have produced inquiries that could not fail to end in detection. Thefe books ſpeak likewiſe of weekly ſabbaths, daily ſacrifices, a yearly expiation, and monthly feſtivals, all to be kept in remembrance of great things particularly fpecified as done for the nation at an early period of its exiſtence. If this was not the caſe, could the forger of the books have perſuaded the people that it really was fo ? The enlightened reaſoners of this nation would be offended were we to compare them with the ancient Iſraelites ; but ſurely they will not ſay that we are partial to that people, if we bring them to a level with the moſt ſavage tribes of the Ruſſian empire, who profeſs Chriſtianity ? Now, were a book to be forged containing an account of many ſtrange things done a thouſand years ago in Siberia by an <hi rend="italic">Apollonius,</hi>  or any other philoſopher or hero, numbers of the barbarians inhabiting that country would, we doubt not, give implicit credit to the <hi rend="italic">legend</hi>  : But were the author, in confirmation of his narrative, to affirm, that all the Siberians had from that day to this kept ſacred the ſirſt day of the week in memory of his hero ; that they had all been baptized or circumciſed in his name ; that in their public judicatories they had fworn by his name, and upon that very book which they had never feen before ; and that the very ſame book was their law and their goſpel, by which for a thouſand years back the actions of the whole people had been regulated—ſurely the groffeſt favage among them would reject with contempt and indignation a forgery ſo palpable.</p><p>If this reaſoning be concluſive, the books of Moſes muſt indubitably be authentic, and he himſelf muſt have been inſpired by the ſpirit of God. But this point being eſtabliſhed, the queſtion reſpecting the origin of the primaeval religion is completely anfwered. The writer of the book of Genelis informs us, that Adam and Noah received many revelations from the Author of their being, and that their religion was founded on the principles of the pureſt theiſm. How it degenerated among the greater part of their defcendants into the groſſeſt idolatry, has been ſhown at large in another place. See Polytheism.</p><p>II. Having thus anſwered the firſt queſtion propofed ſor diſcuſſion in the preſent article, we now proceed to conſider the ſecond, and to inquire whether and how far religious ſentiments have a tendency to injure or to pro-mote the welfare of fociety ? This is a ſubject of the utmoſt importance ; and if we prove ſucceſsful in our inquiries, we ſhall be enabled to determine whether the governors of mankind ought carefully to ſupport religious eſtabliſhments, or whether the philoſopher who calls himſelf a citizen of the world, and profeſſes to feel the moſt eager deſire to promote the intereſts of his ſpecies, acts conſiſtently when he labours to exterminate religion from among men.</p><p>A celebrated French financier *, a man of abilities and virtue, who has publiihed a book on the importance of religious opinions, labours to ſhow that religious eſta-bliſhrnents are indiſpenſably neceſſary for the maintenance of civil order., and demonſtrates how weak the influence of political inſtitutions is on the morals of mankind ; but he refuſes to review the hiſtory of paſt ages in order to diſcover how far religious opinions have actually been injurious or beneficial to the welfare of ſociety ; choo-ſing rather to content himſelf with the refult of a ſe« ries of metaphyfical diſquifitions.</p><p>we admire the ſpirit which induced a man who had ſpent a confiderable part of his life -amid the hurry of public bufinefs, to become the ſtrenuous advocate of re-ligion ; but we cannot help thinking that, notwithſtanding the eloquence, the acuteneſs, and the knowledge of mankind which he has diſplayed, his refuſing to admit the evidence of facts concerning the influence of reli-gion on ſociety may poſſibly be regarded by its enemies as a tacit acknowledgment that the evidence of facts would be unfavourable to the cauſe which he wiſhes to defend. The fallacy of general reaſonſhgs, and the inutility of metaphyfics for the purpoſes of life, are ſo uni-verſally acknowledged, that they have long been the theme of declamation. Though the abuſes oſ religion, as well as the abuſes of reaſon, the perverſion oi any of the principles of the human mind, and the miſap-plication of the gifts of providence, may have often produced effects hurtful to the virtue and the happineſs of mankind ; yet, after tracing religion to a divine ori-gin, we cannot, for a moment, allow ourſelves to think that the primary tendency of religion muſt be hoſtile to the intereſts of ſocicty, or that it is neceſſary to view it abſtractly in order that we may not behold it in an odious light, often has the fceptic attacked religion with artful malice ; but perhaps none of his attacks has been ſo ſkilfully directed as that which has firſt ridiculed the abſurdity of the moſt abſurd ſuperſtitions, and afterwards laboured to prove that the moſt abfurd ſyſtem of polytheiſm is more favourable to the intereſts of ſociety than the pureſt and moſt ſublime theiſm. In-ftances in which the abuſe of religion had tended to deprave the human heart, and had led to the moſt ſhocking crimes, have been aſſiduouſly collected, and diſplayed in all the aggravating colours in which elo-quence could array them, till at length even the friends of true religion have been abaſhed ; and it has become a faſhionable opinion, that nothing but ſelf-intereſt or bigotry can prompt men to repreſent religion as the friend of civil order. But let us try if, by a candid conſideration of what effects have reſulted to ſociety from religious principles, in general, without compa-ring theſe with regard to truth or falſehood, we can</p><p>advance any thing to vindicate the character of religion.</p><p>Notions of Deity in general, of various orders of divinities, of their moral character, of their influence on human life, of a future ſtate, and of the immortality of the human foul, conſtitute the leading articles of religion. Let us view thefe together with the rites to which they have given jiſe ; and we may perhaps be enabled to form fome well-grounded notions on this important point.</p><p>I. Having proved that the firſt religious principles entertained by men were derived from revelation, it is impoffible to ſuppoſe that they could produce effects in-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>