<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>It was ſoon diſcovered that the leading.republicans had divided into two oppoſite factions. The one of theſe was called <hi rend="italic">Girondßs</hi>, becaufe V'ergniaud, Gen-ſoene, Guadet, and ſome others of its leaders, were members from the department of La Gironde. The celebrated Condorcet belonged to this party; and they were ſometimes denominated <hi rend="italic">Bofſfihnes,</hi>  from M. Briſſot de warville their principal leader. They ſupported the miniſtry now in officc, at the head of which was Roland ; and the majority of the convention was obviouſly attachetſ to them. In oppoſition to theſc was the ſmaller party of the <hi rend="italic">M untrnn ;</hi>  fo called from its members uſually ſitting in the convention on the upper feats of the hall. They were men poſſeſſed of lefs perfonal reſpectability, and fewer literary accompliſhments, but oſ daring and ſanguinary characters, whom the revolu-t ion had brought into public notice. At the head of this party were Danton and Robefpierre ; and ſubor-dinate to theſe were Couthon, Bazire, Thuriot, Mer-hn de Thionville, St Andre, Camille Demoulins, Chabot, Collot D’Herbois, Sergent, Legendre, Fabre D’Eglantine, Panis, and Marat.</p><p>ſ heſc two parties ſhowed the diverſity of their characters in the manner in which they treated the maſſacres of the 2d and 3d of September. The Briſſotines, with the majority of the convention, wiſhed to bring the murderers to trial ; but the queſtion was always eluded by the other party, with the aſſiſtance of the Jacobin cſub and of the populace.</p><p>On the 9th oſ October it was decreed, that all emigrants, when taken, ſhould ſuſſer death; and on the 15th oſ November, in confeqnence of an infurrection in the duchy of Deux Ponts, and an application on the part of the inſurgents to thc convention ſor aid,the following decree was paſſed : " The national convention declare, in the name of the French nation, that they will grant fraternity and affiſtance to ali thoſe people who wiſh to procure liberty ; and they clſarge the executive power to ſend orders to the generals to give aſſlſtance to ſuch people as liave ſuffered, or are now ſuſfering, in the cauſe oſ liberty.” Of this decree foreign nations, with great reaſon, complained much, as will ſhortly appear.</p><p>To return to the military affairs of the new republic. On the 12th of October General Dumourier came to Paris, and was ſpeedily ſent to commence a winter campaign in the Netherlands. He ſuddenly attacked the Auſtrians at the village of Boffu, and drove them from their ground. On the 5th oſ November he came in ſight of the enemy upon the heights of <hi rend="italic">Je-mappe.</hi>  .Three rows of fortifications aroſe above each other defended by 100 pieces of cannon. Their right was covered by the village and a river, and thcir left by thick woods. The French were by their ovzn account 30,000, whilſt others with great probability of truth compute them at double that number, and the number of the Auſtrians was at leaſt 20,000. At ſeven in the morning of the following day a heavy cannonade com-menced on both ſides, and at noon a cloſe attack was determined on by the French, whoſe right wing was commanded by Generals Bournonville and Dampierre, and the centre by Generals Egalité (ſon to the duke of Orleans who had affumed that name), Stetenboffe, Deſporets, and Drouet. The muſic played thepopu-Iar march of the Marſeillois, and the ſoldiers ruſhed on with enthuſiaſm, ſhouting " Vive la nation.” The en-'</p><lb/><p>gagement was warm and bloody ; the French were twice repulſed ; but their impetuoſity was at laſt irreſiſtible, and about two o’clock the enemy fled from their laſt entrenchments. The loſs on both ſides was very great, that of the Auſtrians amounting to 400c. This victory was deciſive of the fate of the Netherlands. Mons and Bruſſels ſurrendered to Dumourier ; 'ſmurnay, Malines, Ghent, and Antwerp, were taken poſſeſſion of by General Labourdonnaye ; Louvain and Namur were taken by General Valence ; and the whole Auſtrian Netherlands, Luxembourg pnly excepted, fell into the hands of the French : Liege was taken on the 28th of November after a ſuccefsful engagement, in which thc Auſtrians loſt 5 or 600 men and an immenſe train of artillery.</p><p>France was now in a ſituation not unuſual in.the hiſtory of thoſe nations that either are free, or are at-tempting to become ſo; ſucceſsful in all quarters abroad, but diſtracted by factions at home. Ί he two parties in the convention were engaged in a ſtruggle, which daily became more implacable. The party called the <hi rend="italic">Mountain</hi>  did not hêfitate about the nature of the means they were to employ to bring about the ruin of their antagoniſts. 1 hey are even ſuſpected of having, through the medium of Fache the war-miniſter, retarded the ſupply of the armies, to render the ruling party odious by want of ſucceſs. They were for fome time, however, unfortunate in this reſpect ; and the daily news· of victories ſupported with the public the credit of the Girondiſts. A new ſubject was therefore fallen upon, which was the queſtion, how the dethroned king was to be diſpoſcd of? The moderate patty wiſhed to ſave him ; and this was a ſufficient reaſon for their antago-nill s to reſolve upon his ruin. A committee was ap-poiuted to give in a report upon his conduct. A variety of accuſations were brought againſt him ; and the convention inſamouſly refolved co act the part of ac-cufers and of judges.</p><p>It was on the 1 1 th of December when the ill-fated monarch was ordered to the bar of the convention : the act of accuſation was read, and the king was ſummon-ed by the preſident, Barrere, to anſwer to each ſcparate chargç.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prof. “</hi>  Louis, the French nation accnſes you of having committed a multitude of crimes to eſtabliſh your tyranny, in deſtroying her freedom. You, on the 20th of June 1789, attempted the ſovereignty of the people, by ſuſpending the aſſemblies of their repreſen-tatives, and expelling them with violence from the places of their ſittings. This is proved in the procefs verbal entered at the Tennis-court of Verſailles by the members of the conſtſtuent aſſembly. On the 23d of June you wanted to dictate laws to the nation ; you ſurrounded their repreſentatives with troops ; you prcſented to them two royal declarations, ſubverſive of all liberty, and ordered them to ſeparate. Your own declarations, and the minutes of the aſſembly, prove theſe attempts, what have you to anſwer ?”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Louis.</hi>  " No laws were then exiſting to prevent me from it.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Prof</hi>  " You ordered an army to march againſt the citizens of Paris. Your ſatellites have ſhed the blood of ſeveral of them, and you would not remove this army till the taking of the Baſtile and a general infurrection. announced to you that the people were victorious. The</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>