<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſpectes, that we can recollect, a greater, than to that which is ſeen in a perfon who pretends to mimicry and courtly geſture, without poffeffing the advantages and talents they require ; and of which not many people, comparatively fpeaking, have any remarkable ſſiare.</p><p>The inference of this is too obvious to need drawing out, aud we would particularly recommend it to tlie conſideration of thofe readers who think the common occuπ∙mces of a newſpaper, &amp;c. cannot be properly delivered without a good deal of elbow-room</p><p>Although it is impoſſible to come to particulars in any directions of this kind, yet there is one article of our preſent ſnbject on which a ſerviceable remark may be made. Iu ordinary difcourſe, when we are parti-cularly preſſing and earneſt in what we ſay, the eye is naturally thrown upon thoſe to whom we addreſs our-ſelves : And in reading, a turn of this organ now and then upon the hearers, when any thing-very remark-able or intereſting falls in the way, has a good effect in gaining it a proper attention, &amp;c. But this ſſiould not be too frequently uſed ; for iffo, befides its having a tendency to confound the natural importance of different paffages, it may not be altogether agreeable to ſome to have their own reflections broken in upon by a ſignal, which might be interpreted to hint at their wanting regulation.</p><p>o∏e obſervation more, and then we ſſiall attempt to recapitulate the ſubſtance of this ſection in the form of a precept. Though it is, when ſtrictly examined, inconfiſtent, both in ſpeaking and reading, to imitate with action what we are deſcribing, yet as in any thing <hi rend="italic">comic</hi>  ſuch a practice may ſuggeſt ideas that will <hi rend="italic">accord</hi>  with thofe oſ the ſubject, it may there be now and then indulged in either of theſe articles.</p><p>“ In a manner ſimilar to that directed with regard to tones, moderate your bodily expreſſions of the ſigns of the emotions. And in order to fupply, as it were, this deficiency, introduce into your carriage ſuch an eaſy gracefulnefs, as may be confiſtent with your acquirements in thefe particulars, and the neceffary dread which ſſiould ever be preſent of falling into any kind of affectation or grimace.”</p><p>V. <hi rend="italic">Paufes.</hi>  Speech conſiſting of a ſucceſſion oſ di-ſtinct words, muſt naturally be liable (both from a kind of accident, and a difficulty there may be in be-g’fining certain founds or portions of phraſes immediately on the ending of certain others) to feveral fmalΓ intermiſſions of voice ; of which, as they can have no meaning, nothing farther need here be ſaid. There are, however, ſome pauſes, which the ſenſe neceffarily de-mands ; and to theſe the ſubſtance of this ſection is di-τected.</p><p>The panics are in part to diſtinguiſſi the members of ſentences from one another, the terminations of complete periods, and to afford an opportunity for taking breath. Beſides this, they have a very graceful effect in the modulation, on the fame account they are ſo effential in muſic.—In both articles, like blank fpaces in pictures, they ſet off and render more conſpicuous what-foever they disjoin or terminate.</p><p>were language made up of nothing but ſſiort collo-quial ſentences, theſe paufes, though they might do no harm, and would generally be graceful, would however be ſuperſeded as to uſe by the completeneſs and <hi rend="italic">nar-rownefs,</hi>  as we may ſay, of the meaning. But in more diffuſe language, compofed of ſeveral detached ſentences, and which require fome degree of attention in order to take in the ſenfe, the intermiſſions of voice under conſideration are of the greateſt ſervice, by ſig-nifying to the mind the progrefs and completion of the whole paffage. Now, though in extenſive and differently formed periods there may be members whoſe completeneſs of fenſe might be conceived of various degrees, aud hence might ſeem to require a ſet of pauſes equally numerous ; yet, ſince the ſenſe does not altogether depend upon theſe intermiſſions, and their ratios to one another, if capable of being properly defined, could 'not be accurately obſerved, grammarians have ventured to conceive the whole claſs of pauſes as reducible to the four or five kinds now in ufe, and whoſe marks and ratios are well known (g) ; prefu-∙ ming that under the eye of taſte ; and with the aſſiſt-ance of a particular to be next mentioned, they would not fail in all cafes to ſuggeſt intermiſſions of voice ſuitable to the ſenfe. But in many of theſe extenfive and complex periods, rounded with a kind of redundancy of matter, where the full ſenſe is long ſuſpended, and the final words are not very important, there would be fome hazard of a miſapprehenfion of the termina-tion, had we not more evident and infallible notice of it than that which is given by the paufe. This notice is the <hi rend="italic">cadence,</hi>  referred to in the ſection on <hi rend="italic">Modulation ;</hi>  which, as is there obſerved, befides the orna-mental variety it affords, appears from theſe remarks to be a very neceffary and ſerviceable article in perſpi-cuous delivery.</p><p>As this cadence naturally accompanies the end of every entire ſenfe, circumftanced as above-mentioned, it may ſometimes fall hefo∙re the <hi rend="italic">ſemicolon,</hi>  but morè generally before the <hi rend="italic">colon,</hi>  as well as the period : For theſe marks are often found to terminate a complete ſenſe ; and in theſe cafes, the relation what follows has to what went before, is lignified to the mind by the relative ſſiortnefs of the ſtop, and the form of introducing the additional matter. Nor can any bad conſe-</p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(g)</hi>  Suppoſing the <hi rend="italic">comma</hi>  (,) one <hi rend="italic">time,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">ſemicolon</hi>  (;) will be two ; the <hi rend="italic">colon</hi>  (:) three, and the <hi rend="italic">period (.) </hi>&gt;2S alſo the marks of <hi rend="italic">interrogation</hi>  (?) and <hi rend="italic">admiration</hi>  (!) four of theſe times. The blank line ( — or —), and the <hi rend="italic">breaks</hi>  between <hi rend="italic">paragraphs,</hi>  intimate ſtill greater times ; and by the ſame analogy may be reckoned a double and quadruple period refpectively. Now and then theſe blank lines are placed immediately <hi rend="italic">after</hi>  the ordinary points, and then they are conceived only as ſeparating ſor the ¢y? the different.natures of the matter ;—as .a queſtion from an anſwer,—precept from example,—premiſes from inferences, &amp;c. in which caſe their import is evident. Bπt of late ſome authors have not fcrupled to confound theſe diſtinctions ; and to make a blank ſerve for all the pauſes univerſally, or the mark of an indefinite reſt, the quantity of which is left to the determination of the reader’s taſte. A practice, it. is imagined, too deſtructive of the intended preciſion of thefe typical notices to be much longer adopted.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>