<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rtf level exiſts, whatever Ptolemy’s cngineers might have pretended to him; becauſe, to ſuppoſe it fact, is to ſup-poſe the violation of one very material law of nature.”</p><p>The next thing conſidered by our author is the paſſage of the Iſraelites through the Red Sea. At the place where he ſuppoſes the paffage to have been, the ſea is not quite four leagues broad, ſo that it might ea-fily have been croſſed in one night without any miracle. There is about 14 fathom water in the channel, and 9 at the ſides, with good anchorage everywhere ; the far-theſt ſide is a low fandy coaſt, and a very eaſy landing place. " The draught of the bottom of the gulph (fays he) given by Dr Pococke, is very erroneous in every part of it. It was propoſed to Mr Niebuhr, when in Egypt, to inquire upon the fpot, whether there were not fome ridges of rocks where the water was ſhallow, fo that an army at particular times might paſs over ? Secondly, whether the Eteſian winds, which blow ſtrongly all ſummer from the north-weſt, could not blow ſo violently againſt the fea, as to keep it back on a heap, ſo that the Iſraelites might have paſſed with-⅛&gt;ut a miracle ? And a copy of theſe queries was left for me to join my inquiries likewiſe. But I muſt con-feſs, however learned the gentlemen were who propoſed theſe doubts, I did not think they merited any attention to ſolve them. If the Eteſian winds, blowing from the north-weſt in ſummer, could heap up the fea as a wall on the right or to the ſouth, of 50 feet high, ſtill the difficulty would remain of building the wall on the left hand or to the north. Beſides, water ſtanding in that poſition for a day, muſt have loſt the nature of a fluid, whence came that coheſion of particles that hindered that wall to efcape at the ſides ? This is as great a miracle as that of Moſes. If the Eteſian winds had done this once, they muſt have repeated it many a time before and ſince, from the ſame caufes. Yet Dio-dorus Siculus ſays, the Troglodytes, the indigenous inhabitants of that very ſpot, had a tradition from father to ſon, from their very earlieſt and remoteſt ages, that once this diviſion of the ſea did happen there ; and that, after leaving the bottom ſome time dry, the ſea again came back and covered it with great fury. I he words of this author are of the moſt remarkable kind, we cannot think this heathen is writing in favour of reve-lation. He knew not Mofes, nor ſays a word about Pharaoh and his hoſt ; but records the miracle of the diviſion of the ſea in words nearly as ſtrong as thoſe of Moſes, from the mouths of unbiaſſed undeſigning pagans.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">R ED-Shank,</hi>  in ornithology. See Scolopax.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RED-Stari,</hi>  a ſpecies of Motacilla.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RKD-Wing.</hi>  SeeTuRDus.</p><p>REDANS, in field fortification. See the article Redens.</p><p>REDDENDUM, in law, is uſed ſubſtantively for the clauſe in a leaſe wherein the rent is reſerved to the leſſor. Tlre proper place ſor it is next aſter the limita-tion of eſtate.</p><p>REDDI ΓΙΟ, was the third part of the ſacrifice of the heathens, and conſiſted of the ſolemn act of putting in again the entrails of the victims, after they had been religiouſly inſpectcd. See Sacrifice.</p><p>REDDLE, a ſoft, heavy, red marle, of great uſe an colouring ; and being waſhed and freed from ſand, is often fold by our druggiſts under the name of <hi rend="italic">lole armeηic.</hi></p><p>REDEMPTION, in law, a faculty or right of reentering upon lands, &amp;c. that have been fold and aſſigned, upon reimburſing the purchaſe-money with le-gal coſts.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Redemption, in theology, denotes the recoveιy of mankind from ſin and death, by the obedience and ſacrifice of Chriſt, who on this account is called the </hi><hi rend="italic">Redeemer oſ the world.</hi>  See Theology.</p><p>REDENS, Redans, or <hi rend="italic">Redant,</hi>  in fortification, a kind of work indented in form of the teeth of a ſaw, with ſaliant and re-entering angles ; to the end that one part may flank or defend another. It is likewiſe called <hi rend="italic">ſaw-work</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">indented work.</hi>  The lines or faces in this flank one another.</p><p>Redens are uſed in fortifying walls, where it is not neceſſary to be at the expence of building baſtions ; as when they ſtand on the ſide of a river running through a garrifon town, a marſh, the ſea, &amp;c. But the fault of ſuch fortification is, that the befiegers from one battery may ruin both the ſides of the tenaille or front of a place, and make an aſſault without fear of being enfiladed, ſince the defences are mined. The parapet of the corridor is likewiſe often redented or carried oa by the way of redens. The redens was ufed before baſtions were invented, and fome people think them preferable.</p><p>RED I (Francis), an Italian phyſician and polite ſcholar, was born at Arezzo in Tuſcany in 1626. Hie ingenuity and learning recommended him to the office of firſt phyſician to Ferdinand II. duke of Tuſcany ; and he contributed not a little toward the compiling of the Dictionary of La Crufca. He wrote upon vipers, upon the generation of infects, and compoſed a good deal of poetry. All his writings are in Italian ; and his language is fo fine and pure, that the authors of the Dictionary of La Crufca have often cited them as ſtan-dards of perfection. He died in 1697.</p><p>REDOUBT, in fortification, a ſmall ſquare fort, without any defence but in front ; uſed in trenches, lines of circumvallation, contravallation, and approach ; as alfo for the lodgings of corps-de-gard, and to defend paſſages.</p><p>RE DUC ΓΙΟΝ, in the fchools, a manner of bring-ing a term or propoſition, which was before oppoſite to ſome other, to be equivalent to it.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reduction, in arithmetic, that rule whereby numbers of different denominations are brought into one de-nomination. See Arithmetic.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Reduction of Equations,</hi></hi>  in algebra, is the clearing them from all ſuperfluous quantities, bringing them to their loweſt terms, and ſeparating the known from the unknown, tiff at length only the unknown quantity is found on one ſide, and known ones on the other. The reduction of an equation is the laſt part of the refolu-tion of the problem. See Algebra.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Reduction of a figure, deſign, or draught, is the making a copy thereof, either larger or ſmaller than the original ; ſtill preſerving the form and proportion. The great uſe of the proportional compaffes is the reduction oſ figures, &amp;c. whence they are called </hi><hi rend="italic">co∣npafies oſ reduction.</hi>  See the article Compass.</p><p>There are various methods of reducing figures, &amp;c.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>