<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>navy ; but theſe were onIy meant to act as official men, &gt;under the Count d’ Artois, and the other leaders of the ariſtocracy. To theſe leaders there did not even remain a choice of difficulties ; no refource was left but that of -overawing by military power the national aſſembly and the capital, and of riſking the deſperate meaſure of a national bankruptcy, which the court had not formerly dared to encounter, and to avoid which it had convo-ked the ſtates-general. No trace remains, however, of any attempt to put this criminal, but laſt refource, in execution. The evening after the departure of M. Neckar was ſpent by the court of verfailles in feaſting and joy, as if a victory had been gained. The courtiers of both fexes went round among the foldiery, ſtriving to fecure their fidelity by careſſes, largeſſes, and every fpecies of flattering attention. The miniſtry not only failed to fupport the Prince de Lambeſq in the poſt which he had been ſent to occupy, but they ſuſſered the whole of the 13th to paſs in indeciſion, while the capital was in a ſtate of rebellion, while an army was formally muſtering within its walls, and the names of the principal nobility were put up in lifts of proſcrip-tions. They received the news of the capture of the Baſtile with confuſion and diſmay, which were increa-fed, if poffible, by information given by Marſhal Broglio, that the troops refuſed to act againſt Paris or the national aſſembly. In this perplexity they adopted the miſerable device of concealing from the king the ſtate of public affairs ; and that unfortunate prince was thus perhaps the only perſon out of millions around him who remained ignorant of the convulſions in which his country was involved.</p><p>At length, at midnight, the Duke de Liancourt forced his way into the king’s apartment, and told him of the revolt of his capital, of his army, and of the ſurrender of the fortreſs of the Baſtile. The Count d’ Artois, who was preſent, ſtill attempted to retain the monarch under his fatal deluſion ; but the Duke de Liancourt turning round, exclaimed, " As for you, Sir, yoHr life can only be ſaved by inſtant flight ; I have ſeen with horror your name in the bloody liſt of the profcribed.” Accordingly the Count, with the members of his ſhort-lived adminiſtration and their adhe-rents, fled to the frontiers. And thus an emigration commenced, the fource of that terrible conte It which has covered Europe with bloodſhed and mourning. This miniſtry had, no doubt, many difficulties to contend againſt ; but an accurate attention to their conduct ex-cſtes a ſufpicion which, while it exculpates them from many intended crimes that have been laid to their charge, at the ſame time does little honour to their ta-lents. It is this, that they had come into office without having formed any clear plan of conduct ; that they were men acting without deciſion and at random, and conſequently became the ſport of thoſe events which they wanted ſkill and vigour to direct or controul. By their introduction into office, and their miſconduct while in it, the royal authority fell proſtrate before the popular party in the national aſſenſhly. The nobles and the clergy ſtill remained, but confounded in one aſſembly with the more numerous order of the <hi rend="italic">tiers état;</hi>  and no longer rallying round a throne that was too feeble to afford protection, they foon yielded to that fierce and levelling ſpirit of democracy that now roſe around them.</p><lb/><p>But the perſon of the monarch was ſtill beloved.— Early next morning the king went to the aſſembly, but with none of the uſual folemr&gt;ities. He " regretted the commotions of the capital, dtfavowed any knowledge of an intention againſt the perfons of the deputies, and intimated that he had commanded the removal of the troops.” A deep and expreſſive ſilence prevailed for a few moments ; this was ſucceeded by vehement and uni-verſal ſhouts of applaufc. The king aroſe to depart, and inſtantly the whole affembly crowded around, and attended him to his palace. The queen appeared at a balcony with the dauphin in ker arms ; the muſic play-ed the pathetic air of <hi rend="italic">Où peut-on dt<hi rend="sub">re</hi>  mieux qu’au fin de ſa ſarndle.</hi>  The enthuſiaſm of loyalty communicated itſelf to the ſuriounding multitudes, and nothin"· was heard but acclamations of joy.</p><p>Οη the following day, the king declared his refolu-tion to. viſit the city of Paris in perſon. Accordingly that prince, who never wanted perſonal courage, however deficient he might be in political ſtedfaſtneſs, ſet out, attended by ſome members of the aſſembly and by the militia of verfailles. He was met by the celebrated M. de la Fayette, at the head of a body of the na-tional guard, of which he had now been choſen com-mander in chief. M. Bailly, in whofe perfon the an-cient office of mayor of Paris had been revived, received the king at the gates, and delivered to him the keys. All this while no ſhout was heard from the crowd of innumerable ſpectators but that of <hi rend="italic">Vive la nation. </hi>The king advanced to the Hotel de ville, where the new cockade was preſented to him, which he put on<hi rend="sub">F </hi>and preſented himſelf with it at a window. At the light of this badge of patriotiſm an univerſal ſhout of <hi rend="italic">Vive le Roi</hi>  burſt forth from every quarter ; and he returned to verfailles amidſt general triumph and applauſe.</p><p>Much confuſion ſtill prevailed in the capital; but there was more appearance of regularity than could have been expected at the conclufion of ſuch important events. I his aroſe from a caſual concurrence of circumſtances. <hi rend="sup">r</hi>L o conduct with eaſe the elections to the ſtates-general, Paris had been divided into 60 diſtricts, each of which had a feparate place of meeting. The people did not elect the members to the ſtates-general ; but they choſe delegates, who, under the name of elec-toιs, voted for the members. A,t the commencement of the diſturbances, the electors, at the requeſt of their fellow-citizens, aſſumed a temporary authority ; of which, however, they were foon weary, and as foon as poffible procured the public election of 120 perfons as municipal officers for the government of the city. The citizens having got the habit of aſſembling in their diſtricts, grew fond of it : they aſſembled frequently, made rules-for their own government, and ſent commiſſioners to communicate with other diſtricts. The tumultuous nature of theſe meetings, and the vehemence of debate which prevailed in them, will belt be conceived from the ludicrous contrivance of one of their prefidεnts, who ſtationed a drummer at the back of his chair, and when the confuſion and noiſe became altogether ungovernable, gave the ſignal for beating the drum, which ſpeedily overpowered every other noiſe. Theſe meetings, however, gradually ripened into clubs, in which much dexterity and intrigue were exerted.</p><p>The whole of the late miniſtry eſcaped excepting M.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>