<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>jurions to ſociety. If religion oſ any kind has ever Ieſſened the virtue or diſturbed the peace oſ men, it muſt have been that religion which ſprings from a belief in a multitude of ſuperior powers actuated by paf-fιons, and of whom fome were conceived as benevolent and others as malicious beings. That fuch ſentiments ſhould have produced vices unknown in ſocieties where pure theiſm is profeſſed, will be readily admitted. Even the few <hi rend="italic">atheifis</hi>  who live in Chriſtian or Mahometan countries are reſtrained by the laws, by a deſire to promote the honour of the ſect, and by many other confiderations, from indulging in practices which the ex-ample of the falſe gods of antiquity ſanctioned in their votaries. But in determining the preſent queſtion, we muſt not compare the virtues of the pagan world with thoſe of individual atheiſts in modern Europe, but with thoſe of <hi rend="italic">nations</hi>  profeſſing atheiſm ; and ſuch nations are nowhere to be found. We can however eaſily conceive, that in a ſociety unawed by any notions of God or a future ſtate, no ſuch laws would be enacted as thoſe which reſtrain the ſenſual appetites ; of which the criminal indulgence was one of the greateſt ſtigmas on the pagan worſhip of antiquity. In ſuch ſocieties, therefore, thoſe vices would be practiſed conſtantly to which paganiſm gave only an occaſional ſanction ; and many others, in ſpite of the utmoſt vigilance of human Iaws, would be perpetrated in ſecret, which the moſt profligate pagans viewed with horror. Conſcience, though acting with all her energy, would not be able to command any regard to the laws of morality : No virtue would be known ; focial order would be nowhere obſerved; the midnight aſſaffin would every where be found ; and in the general ſcramble mankind would be exterminated from the face of the earth.</p><p>The worſt ſpecies of paganifm, even that which pre-vails among ſavages who worſhip evil ſpirits, affords greater ſecurity than this. It is indeed ſhocking to think that demons ſhould be Worſhipped, while deities, who are regarded as being all benevolence, are treated with contempt: And it has been aſked, If the influence of ſuch religious ſentiments on the moral practice of the idolaters muſt not naturally be, to cauſe them to treat their friends and benefactors with ingratitude, and to humble themſelves with mean ſubmiſſion before a powerful enemy ?</p><p>They do not appear to have produced ſuch effects on the morality of the ſavages by whom they were entertained. The benevolent deities were neglected, only becauſe their benevolence was neceſſary. A voluntary iavour merits a grateful return : a deſigned injury provokes reſentment. But when you become, by accident, the inſtrument of any man’s good fortune, the world will ſcarce conſider him as owing you any obligation : the ſtone which bruiſes your foot excites only a momentary emotion of reſentment. Thoſe gods who could not avoid doing good to men might not receive a pro-fuſion of thanks for their ſervices ; and yet a favohr conferred by an human benefactor commands the warm-eft gratitude. But thoſe rude tribes appear to have had fo much wiſdom âs to confer a lefs abſolute malice on their malcvolent deities, than the benevolence which -they attributed to their more amiable order of ſuperior beings : though the latter could not poffibly do them any thing but good, and that conſtantly ; yet the former were not under an equally indifpenſable neceffity of perſevering in depreſſing them under calamities. On their malevoIent deities they conferred a freedom of agency which they denied to the benevolent. No won-der, then, that they were more afliduous in paying their court to the one than to the other. They might with as much propriety have thought of being grateful to the boar or ſtag whoſe fleſh fupported them, as to deities who were always benevolent, becaufe they could not poſſibly be otherwiſe. Though negligent of ſuch. deitiete, this can ſcarce be thought to have had any ten» dency to render them ungrateful to benefactors like themfelves. And yet, it muſt not be diſſembled, thafc the American Indians, among whom ſuch religion» ſentiments have been found to prevail, are ſaid to be very little ſenſible to the emotions of gratitude. Ait Indian receives a preſent without thinking of making any grateful acknowledgments to the beſtower. He pleaſes his fancy or gratifies his appetite with what you have givcn, without feeming to conſider himſeif as under the ſmalleſt obligation to you for the gift.</p><p>Tt may be doubted, however, whether this ſpirit of ingratitude originates from, or is only collateral with, that indifference which refuſes adoration and worſhip to the benevolent divinities. If the former be actually the cafe, we muſt acknowledge that thoſe religious notion's which we now conſider, though preferable to general atheiſm, are in this reſpect unfriendly to virtue. But if the Indians may be thought to owe the ingratitude for which they are diſtinguiſhed to the opinion which they entertain of the exiſtence of a benevolent order of deities, whofe benevolence is neceffary and involuntary, their ideas of the nature of their malevolent demons do not appear to have produced equal effects on their moral ſentiments. However ſubmiffive to thoſe dreaded beings, they are far from ſhowing the fame tame and cowardly fubmiſſion to their human enemies : towards them they ſeem rather to adopt the ſentiments of their demons. Inveterate rancour and brutal fury, inhuman cruelty and inconceivable cunning, are diſplayed in the hoſtilities of tribes at war ; and we know not, after all, if even theſe ſentiments do not owe ſomewhat of their force to the influence of religion.</p><p>Yet let us remember that thefe fame Indians have not been always repreſented in ſo unamiable a light ; or, at leaſt, other qualities have been aſcribed to them which ſeem to be inconſiſtent with thoſe barbarous diſpoſitions. They have been deſcribed as peculiarly ſuſceptible of conjugal and parental love; and he who is ſo cannot be deſtitute of virtue.</p><p>2. But leaving the religion of ſavages, of which very little is known with certainty, let us proceed to examine what is the natural influence of that mixed ſyſtem of theology which repreſents to the imagination of men a number of fuperior and inferior divinities, actuated by the fame paſſions and feelings with themſelves, and often making uſe of their ſuperior power and knowledge for no other purpoſe but to enable them to violate the laws of moral order with impunity. This is the cele-brated polytheiſm of the Greeks and Romans, and moſt other nations of antiquity (ſee Polytheisλm). Could its influence be favourable to virtue ?</p><p>At a firil view every perſon will readily declare, that ſuch a ſyſtem muſt have been friendly to profligacy. If you commit the government of the univerſe, and the inſpection of human ſociety, to a ſct of beings who are</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>