<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The reſults of theſe experiments were as-conformable to the theory as could be wiſhed. The reſiſtance was always a little leſs than wſhat the theory required, but greatly exceeded its half ; the reſult of the generally re-ceived theories. This defcct ſhould be expected ; for the demonſtration ſuppoſes· the plane MN to be infinitely extended, fo that the film of water which iffues through the chink may be accurately parallel to the plane. This never can be completely effected. Alſo it was ſuppoſed, that the velocity was juſtly meaſured by the amplitude of the parabola EGK. But it is well known that the. very putting the plane MN in the way of the jet, though at the diſtance of an inch from the orifice, will diminiſh the velocity, of the efflux through this orifice. This is eaſily verified by experiment, 05-ferve the time in which the veſſel will be emptied when there is no plane in the way. Repeat the experiment .with the plane in its place ; and more time will be ne-ceſſary. The following is a note of a courſe of ex-periments, taken as they ſtand, without any ſelection.</p><p>N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> i »    3    4    5    <hi rend="sup">6</hi></p><p>Refill, by theory    1701    1720    165 r    ι6oa    1528    107»</p><p>&lt;Refiih by experiment <hi rend="underline">1403    1463    1486    140t    1403    ιo¾ι</hi></p><p>Difference    ay 8    45 7    165    201    ιaj 51</p><p>In order to demonſtrate this propofition in ſuch a manner as to furniſh the means of inveſtigating the jwhole mechaniſm and action of moving fluids, it is neceffary to premife an elementary theorem of curvilineal motions.</p><p>If .a particle of matter deſcribes a curve line ABCE (fig. 13∙) by the continual action of deflecting forces, which vary in any manner, both with reſpect to inten-fity and direction, and if the action of thfeſe forces, in .every point of the curve, be reſolved into two directions, perpendicular and parallel to the initial direction AK; then,</p><p>i. The accumulated effect of the deflecting forces, eſtimated in a direction AD perpendicular to AK, is to the final quantity of motion as the fine of the final change of direction is to radius.</p><p>Let us ſirſt fuppofe that the accelerating forces act by ſtarts, at equal intervals of time, when the body is in the points A, B, C, E. And let AN be the de-flecting force, which, acting at A, changes the origi-nal direction AK to AB. Produce AB till BH= AB, and complete the parallelogram BFCH. Then FB is the force which, by acting at B, changed the motion BH (the continuation of AB) to BC. In like manner make <hi rend="italic">Ch</hi>  (in BC produced) equal to BC, and complete the parallelogram C/EÂ <hi rend="italic">Cſ</hi>  is the deflecting force at C, &amp;c. Draw BO parallel to AN, and GBK perpendicular to AK. Alſo draw lines through C and E perpendicular to AK, and draw through B and C lines parallel to AK. Draw alſo HL, <hi rend="italic">h∕</hi>per-pendicular, and FG, HI, <hi rend="italic">hi,</hi>  parallel to AK.</p><p>It is plain that BK is BO or AN eſtimated in the direction perpendicular to AK, and that BG is BF eſtimated in the ſame way. And fince BH = AB, HL or IM is equal to BK. Alſo CI is equal to BG. Therefore CM is equal to AP+BG. By ſimilar rea-ſcning it appears that E∕w = Ez-f-Z&gt;∕,=∑C⅛<hi rend="sup">r</hi>4-CM, = C^~f-BG, ſt-AP.</p><p>Therefore if CE be taken for the meaſure of the final velocity or quantity of motion, Em will be the accumulated effect of the deflecting forces eſtimated in the direction AD perpendicular to AK. But Em is</p><lb/><p>to CE as the fine of mCE is to radius; and the angle wCE is the angle contained between the initial and final directions, becauſe <hi rend="italic">Cm</hi>  is parallel to AK. Now let the intervals of time diminiſh continually and the frequency of the impulſes increaſe. The deflection be-eomes ultimately continuous, and the motion curvili* iieal, and the propofition is demonfl rated.</p><p>we ſee that the initial velocity and its ſubſequent changes do not affect the conclufion, which depends entirely on the final quantity of motion.</p><p><hi rend="italic">2.</hi>  The accumulated effect of the accelerating forces, when eſtimated in the direction AK of the original motion, or in the oppofite direction, is equal to the difference between the initial quantity of motion and the product of the final quantity of motion by the cofine of the change of direction.</p><p>For Cmr=C <hi rend="italic">I— rn l,</hi>  =BM—<hi rend="italic">-ſq </hi>BM=BL-ML,=AK- FG <hi rend="smallcaps">AK=Ao-oK,~Ao-</hi>PN.</p><p>Therefore PN+FG+∕Qj(the accumulated impulfe in the direction ΟΑ)~ ΑΟ—CM, —AO—CE× coi fine of ECM.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor.</hi>  I. The ſame action, in the direction oppofite to that of the original motion, is neceffary for caufing a body to move at right angles to its former direction as for ſtopping its motion. For in this caſe, the co-fine of the change of direction is <hi rend="italic">— 0,</hi>  and A Ο—CE ×cofine ECM=Ao—ο, “ΑΟ, = the original motion.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Cor. 2.</hi>  If the initial and final velocities are the ſame, the accumulated action of the accelerating forces, eſti-mated in the direction OA, is equal to the product of the original quantity of motion by the verſed fine of the change of direction.</p><p>The application of theſe theorems, particularly the ſecond, to our preſent purpoſe is very obvious. All the filaments of the jet were originally moving in the direction of its axis, and they are finally moving along the reſiſting plane, or perpendicular to their former motion. Therefore their tranſverſe forces in the direction of th&lt;s axis are <hi rend="italic">(in cumulo)</hi>  equal to the force which would ſtop the motion. For the aggregate of the ſimulta-neous forces of every particle in the whole filament is the ſame with that of the ſucceſſive forces of one particle, as it arrives at different points of its curvineal path. All the tranſverſe forces, eſtimated in a direction per-pendicular to the axis of the vein, preciſely balance and ſuſtain each other; and the only forces which can pro-duce a ſenſtble effect are thoſe in a direction parallel to the axis. By theſe all the inner filaments are preſſed towards the plane MN, and muſt be withſtood by it. It is highly probable, nay certain, that there is a quantity of ſtagnant water in the middle of the vein which ſuſtains the preffures of the moving filaments without it, and tranſmits it to the ſolid plane. But this does not alter the caſe. And, fortunately^ it is of no conſequence what changes happen in the velocities of the particles while each is deſcribing its own curve. And it is from this circumſtance, peculiar to this particular caſe of per-peudicular impulſe, that we are able to draw the con-clufion. It is by no means difficult to demonſtrate that the velocity of the external ſurface of this jet is con-ſtant, and indeed of every jet which is not acted on by external forces after it has quitted the orifice : but this diſcuſſion is quite unneceffary here. It is however extremely difficult to aſcertain, even in this moſt fimp<hi rend="sup">,</hi>e</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>