<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title></title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſpect can be obſerved in the actions of air and water ; and this had always appeared a great defect in Newton’s theory : but it was only a defect of the theory attributed to him. But it is alſo true, that the obſerved action is but one-half of what is juft now deduced ſrom this improved view of the ſubject. whence arifes this difference ? The reafon is this : we have given a very erroneous account of the motions of the filaments. A filament Έ F does not move as repreſented in ſig. 6. with two rectangular inflexions at I and at H, and a path IH between them parallel to C B. The proceſs of na-ture is more like what is repreſented in ſig. io. <hi rend="italic">It is obfirved,</hi>  that at the anterior part of the body A B, there remains a quantity of fluid AD B, almoft, if not alto-gether, ftagnant, of a ſingular ſhape, having two curved concave ſides A <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  D, B <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  D, along which the middle filaments glide. This fluid is very {lowly changed.— The late Sir Charles Knowles, an officer of the Britiſh navy, equally eminent for his fcientiſic profeſſional knowledge and for his military talents, made many beautiful experiments for aſceitaining the paths of the filaments of water. At a diftance up the ftream, he allowed ſmall jets of à coloured ſiuid, which did not mix with water, to make part of the ftream ; and the experiments were made in troughs with ſides and bottom of plate-glaſs. A ſmall taper was placed at a conſider-able height above, by which the ſhadows of the colour-ed filaments were moft diſtinctly projected on a white plane held below the trough, fo that they were accu-rately drawn with a pencil. A few important parti-eulars may be here mentioned.</p><p>The ftill water ADC lafted for a long while be-fore it was renewed ; and it ſeemed to be gradually wafted by abraſion, by the adheſion of the ſurrounding water, which gradually licked away the outer parts from D to A and B ; and it ſeemed to renew itſelf in the direction CD, oppoſite to the motion of the ftream. There was, however, a conſiderable intricacy and eddy in this motion. Some (ſeemingly ſuperſicial) water was continually, but ſiowly, flowing outward from the line DC, while other water was feen within and below it, coming inwards and going backwards.</p><p>The coloured lateral filaments were moft conftant in their form, while the body was the fame, although the ve-locity was in idrne caſes quadrupled. Any change which this produced ſeemed confined to the ſuperſicial filaments.</p><p>As the filaments were deflected, they were alſo con-ftipated, that is, the curved parts of the filaments were nearer each other than the parallel ftraight filaments up the ftream ; and this conftipation was more conſiderable as the. prow was more obtuſe and the deflexion greater.</p><p>The inner filaments were ultimately more deflected than thoſe without them.; that is, if a line be drawn touching the curve EFIH in the point H of contrary flexure, wherc the concavity begins to be on the ſide next the body, the angle HKC, contained between the axis and this tangent line, is ſo much the greater as the filament is nearer the axis.</p><p>when the body expofed to the ftream was a box of upright ſides, flat bottom, and angular prow, like a wedge, having its edge alfo upright, the filaments were not all deflected laterally, as theory would make us expect ; but the filaments near the bottom were alſo deflected downwards as well as laterally, and glided alon^</p><p>at ſome diftance under the bottom, forming lines of double curvature.</p><p>1 he breadth of the ftream that was deflected was much greater than that of the body ; and the ſenſible deflection begun at a conſiderable diftance up the ftream, eſpecially in the outer filaments.</p><p>Laſily, the form of the curves was greatly influenced by the proportion between the width of the trough and that of the body. The curvature was always leſs when the trough was very wide in proportion to the body.</p><p>Great varieties were alſo obferved in the motion or velocity of the filaments. In general, the filaments increaſed in velocity outwards from the body to a certain ſmall diftance, which was nearly the ſame in all caſes, and then diminiſhed all the way outward. This was obferved by inequalities in the colour of the filaments, <hi rend="italic">hγ</hi>  which one could be obſerved to outftrip an-other. I he retardation of thoſe next the body ſeemed to proceed from friction; and it was imagined that without this the velocity there would always have been greateft.</p><p>I heſe obſervations give us conſiderable information reſpectſhg the mechaniſm of theſe motions, and the action of fluids upon ſolids. The preffure in the duplicate ratio of the velocities comes here agqin into view, we found, that although the velocities were very different, the curves were preciſely the ſame. Now the obferved preffures arife from the tranſverſe forces by which each particle of a filament is retained in its curvilineal path ; and we know that the force by which a body is retain-ed in any curve is directly as the fquare of the velocity, and inverſely as the radius of curvature. The curvature, therefore, remaining the ſame, the tranſverſe forces, and conſequently the preffure on the body, muft be as the ſquare of the velocity : and, on the other hand, we can ſee pretty clearly (indeed it is rigorouſly demonſtrated by D Alembert), that whatever be the velocities, the curves <hi rend="italic">wit/</hi>  be the ſame. For it is known in hydraulics, that it requires a fourfold or ninefold preffure to pro-duce a double or triple velocity. And as all preffures are propagated through a perfect fluid without diminution, this fourfold preffure, while it produces a double velocity,. produces alio fourfold tranſverſe preffures, which wiſl retain the particles, moving twice as faſt, in the ſame curvilineal paths. And thus we ſee that the impulſes, as they are called, and reſiſtances of fluids, haye a certain relation to the weight of a column of fluid, whofe height is the height neceſlary for producing the velocity. . How it happens that a plane ſurface, im-merſed in an extended fluid, ſuſtains juſt half the pref-ſure which it would have ſuſtained had the motions been ſuch as are ſketched in figure 6th, is a matter of more curious and difficult inveſtigation. But we fee evidently that the preffure muſt be leſs than what is there affigned; for the ſtagnant water a-head of the body greatly di-mimſhes the ultimate deflections of the filaments : And it may be demonſtrated, that when the part BE of the</p><p>canal, ſig. 9. is inclined to the part AB in an angle leſs than 90<hi rend="sup">0</hi>, the preffures B G along the whole canal are as the verſed fine of the ultimate angle oſ deflection, or the verſed fine of the angle which the part BE makes with the part AB. Therefore, ſince the deflexions re-ſemble more the ſketch given in ſig. 1 o. the accumulated ſum of all theſe forces BG of ſig. 9. muſt be lefs than the ſimilar ſum correſponding to ſig. 6. that is, leſs than</p><p>O 2</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>