<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>of runaway slaves, outlaws, brigands, and impoverished peasants. By the'end of 73 he
                had 70,000 men under his command, had twice defeated the Roman troops, and was
                master of southern Italy. In 72 he advanced on Rome, but, though he again routed the
                legions led against him by the consuls in person, he abandoned his scheme and
                established himself in the now desolate country near Thurii, already the natural
                home of brigandage. At length in 71 the prætor Crassus, who had been sent against
                him with no less than six legions, ended the war. Spartacus was defeated and slain
                in Apulia. In Rome itself the various classes and parties hostile to the Sullan
                system had, ever since Sulla’s death in 78, been incessantly agitating for the
                repeal of his most obnoxious laws, and needed only a leader in order successfully
                to attack a government discredited by failure at home and abroad. With the return of
                Pompey from Spain their opportunity came. Pompey, who understood politics as little
                as Marius, was anxious to obtain—what the senate was more than likely to refuse to
                give him, and what he was not legally entitled to—a triumph, the consulship for the
                next year (70), and as the natural consequence of this an important command in the
                East. The opposition wanted his name and support, and a bargain was soon struck.
                Pompey and with him AIarcus Crassus, the conqueror of Spartacus, were elected
                consuls, almost in the presence of their troops, which lay encamped outside
                the gates in readiness to assist at the triumph and ovation granted to their
                respective leaders. Pompey lost no time in performing his part of the agreement. The
                tribunes regained their prerogatives.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The “ perpetual
                courts” were taken out of the hands of the senatorial judices, who had outdone the
                equestrian order in scandalous corruption,@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and finally the
                censors, the first since 86<hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> purged the senate of the
                more worthless and disreputable of Sulla’s partisans.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The
                victory was complete ; but for the future its chief significance lay in the
                clearness with which it showed that the final decision in matters political lay
                with neither of the two great parties in Rome, but with the holder of the military
                authority. The recognition of this fact was fatal to the dignity of politics in the
                city. In proportion as the mass of the Roman community in Italy, and able aspirants
                to power, like Cæsar, became conscious of the unreality of the old constitutional
                controversies, they became indifferent to the questions which agitated the forum and
                the curia and contemptuously ready to alter or disregard the constitution itself,
                when it stood in the way of interests nearer to their hearts. Of this growing
                indifference to the traditional politics of the republic, against which Cicero
                struggled in vain, Pompey is an excellent example. He was absolutely without
                interest in them, except in so far as they led up to important military commands,
                and, though he was never revolutionary in intention, his own career, in its quiet
                defiance of all the established rules of the constitution, did almost more than the
                direct attacks of others to render the republic impossible.</p>
            <p>AVhen his consulship ended, Pompey impatiently awaited at the hands of the
                politicians he had befriended the further gift of a foreign command. He declined an
                ordinary</p>
            <p>province, and from the end of 70 to 67 he remained at Rome in a somewhat affectedly
                dignified seclusion.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> But in 67 and 66 the laws of Gabiuius
                and Alanilius gave him all and more than all that he expected. The ravages of the
                pirates, encouraged in the first instance by the inactivity which had marked Roman
                policy in the East after 167, and by the absence of any effective Roman navy in
                the Alediterranean, had now risen to an intolerable height, and the spasmodic
                efforts made since 81 had done little to check them. The trade of the AIediterranean
                was paralysed, and even the coasts of Italy were not safe from their raids.@@<hi
                    rend="sup">5</hi> Aulus Gabinius, a tribune, and a follower of Pompey, now
                proposed to the people to entrust Pompey with the sole command against the
                    pirates.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> His command was to last for three years. He was
                to have supreme authority over all Roman magistrates in the provinces throughout the
                Alediterranean and over the coasts for 50 miles inland. Fifteen Iegati, all of
                prætorian rank, were assigned to him, with two hundred ships, and as many troops as
                he thought desirable. These powers were still further enlarged in the next year by
                the Alanilian law, which transferred from Lucullus and Glabrio to Pompey the conduct
                of the Alithradatic war in Asia, and with it the entire control of Roman policy and
                interests in the East.@@<hi rend="sup">7 </hi>The unrepublican character of the
                position thus granted to Pompey, and the dangers of the precedent established, were
                clearly enough pointed out by such moderate men as Q. Lutatius Catulus, the “ father
                of the senate,” and by the orator Hortensius—but in vain. Both laws were supported,
                not only by the tribunes and the populace, but by the whole influence of the “
                ρublicani ” and “ nego-tiatores,” whose interests in the East were at stake.</p>
            <p>Pompey left Rome in 67, and did not return to Italy till towards the end of 62. The
                interval was marked in Rome by the rise to political importance of Cæsar and Cicero,
                and by Catiline’s attempt at revolution. AVhen in 7O the removal of the restrictions
                placed upon the tribunate restored to the popular party their old weapons of
                attack, Cæsar was already a marked man. In addition to his patrician birth, and his
                reputation for daring and ability, he possessed, as the nephew of AIarius and the
                son-in-law of Cinna, a strong hereditary claim to the leadership of the popular and
                AIarian party. He had already taken part in the agitation for the restoration of the
                tribunate ; he had supported the AIanilian law ; and, when Pompey’s withdrawal left
                the field clear for other competitors, he stepped at once into the front rank on the
                popular side.@@<hi rend="sup">8 </hi>He took upon himself, as their nearest
                representative, the task of clearing the memory and avenging the wrongs of the great
                popular leaders, AIarius, Cinna, and Saturninus. He publicly reminded the people of
                Alarius’s services, and set up again upon the Capitol the trophies of the Cimbric
                AVar. He endeavoured to bring to justice, not only the ringleaders in Sulla’s bloody
                work of proscription, but even the murderers of Saturninus, and vehemently pleaded
                the cause of the children of the proscribed. AVhile thus carrying on in genuine
                Roman fashion the feud of his family, he attracted the sympathies of the Italians
                by his efforts to procure the Roman franchise for the Latin communities beyond the
                Po, and won the affections of the populace in Rome and its immediate
                neighbourhood by the splendour of the games which he gave as curule ædile (65), and
                by his lavish expenditure upon the improve-</p>
            <p>@@@    The exact provisions of Pompey’s law are nowhere given ; Livy, <hi
                    rend="italic">Epit.,</hi> xcvii., “ tribuniciam potestatem restitueront. ” <hi
                    rend="italic">Cf.</hi> Velleius, ii. 30. A “lex Aurelia,” in 75, had already
                repealed the law disqualifying a tribune for further office ; Cic., <hi
                    rend="italic">Com.,</hi> fr. 78.</p>
            <p>@@@    This was the work of L. Aurelius Cotta, prætor in this year. The “judices ”
                were to be taken in equal proportions from senators, equites, and “ tribuni aerarii.
                ” For the latter and for the law generally, see Madvig,<hi rend="italic">Verf.,</hi>
                i. 182, ii. 222; Lange, <hi rend="italic">R. AU.,</hi> iii. 193. Compare also
                Cicero’s language, <hi rend="italic">In Verr.,</hi> i. 1, 15. The prosecution
                of Verres shortly preceded the lex Aurelia.</p>
            <p>@@@    Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.,</hi> xcviii. Sixty-four senators were expelled.
                    <hi rend="italic">Cf. </hi>Pint., <hi rend="italic">Pomp.,</hi> 22 ; Cic. <hi
                    rend="italic">In Verr.,</hi> i. 1, 15.</p>
            <p>@@@    Velleius, ii. 31 ; Plut.,<hi rend="italic">Pomp.,</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>@@@    See the brilliant sketch by Mommsen,<hi rend="italic">R. G.,</hi> iii. 39 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq. </hi></p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">β</hi> Plut.,<hi rend="italic">Pomp.,</hi> 25 ; Dio, xxxvi. 6 ;
                Livy, <hi rend="italic">Epit.,</hi> c.</p>
            <p>@@@    Cic.<hi rend="italic">Pro Lege Manilia</hi> ; Dio, xxxvi. 25.; Plut., <hi
                    rend="italic">Pomp.,</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>@@@    Prof. Beesly, in his essay on Catiline, has vainly endeavoured to show that
                Catiline and not Cæsar was the popular leader from 67 to 63. That this is the
                inference intentionally conveyed by Sallust, in order to screen Cæsar, is true, but
                the inference is a false one.</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
