<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The revolutionary movement of 1848 extended from the Roumans of Hungary and Transylvania to their kinsmen of the Transalpine regions. In Moldavia the agitation was mostly confined to the boiars, and the Iiospodar Michael Sturdza succeeded in arresting the ringleaders. In Walachia, however, the outbreak took a more violent form. The people assembled at Bucharest, and demanded a constitution. The prince Bibescu, after setting his signature to the constitution submitted to him, fled to Transylvania, and a provisional government was formed. The Turks, however, urged thereto by Russian diplomacy, crossed the Danube, and a joint Russo-Turkish dictatorship restored the “ Organic Law.” Bythe Balta-Liman convention of 1849 the two Governments agreed to the appointment of Barbu Stirbeiu as prince of Walachia, and Gregoriu Ghika for Moldavia.</p><p>On the entry of the Russian troops into the principalities in 1853, the hospodars fled to Vienna, leaving the government in . the hands of their ministers. During the Danubian campaign that now ensued great suffering was inflicted on the inhabitants, but in 1854 the cabinet of Vienna induced the Russians to withdraw.</p><p>. Austrian troops occupied the principalities, and the hospodars</p><p>returned to their posts.</p><p>f By the treaty of Paris in 1856 the principalities with their existing privileges were placed under the collective guarantee of the contracting powers, while remaining under the suzerainty of the Porte,—the Porte on its part engaging to respect the complete independence of their internal administration. A strip of southern Bessarabia was restored to Moldavia, so as to push back the Russian frontier from the Danube mouth. The existing laws and statutes of both principalities were to be revised by a European commission sitting at Bucharest, and their work was to be assisted by a Divan or national council which the Porte was to convoke <hi rend="italic">ad hoc</hi>  in each of the two provinces, and in which all classes of AValachian and Moldavian society were to be represented. The European commission, in arriving at its conclusions, was to take into consideration the opinion expressed by the representative councils ; the Powers were to come to terms with the Porte as to the recommendations of the commission ; and the final result was to be embodied in a Iiattisherif of the sultan, which was to lay down the definitive organization of the two principalities. In 1857 the commission arrived, and the representative councils of the two peoples were con-</p><p>’ voked. On their meeting in September they at once proceeded to vote with unanimity the union of the two principalities into a single state under the name of Romania (Roumania), to be governed by a foreign prince elected from one of the reigning dynasties of Europe, and having a single representative assembly. The Powers decided to undo the work of national union. By the convention concluded by the European congress at Paris in 1858, it was decided that the principalities should continue as heretofore to be governed each by its own prince. AValachia and Moldavia were to have separate assemblies, but a central commission was to be established at Fokshaiii for the preparation of laws of common interest, which were afterwards to be submitted to the respective assemblies. In accordance with this convention the deputies of Moldavia aud AValachia met in separate assemblies at Bucharest and Jassy, but the choice of both fell unanimously on Prince Alexander John Cuza, thus ensuring the personal union of the two principalities (January 1859). A new conference was now summoned to Paris to discuss the affairs of the principalities, and the election of Prince Cuza finally ratified by the Powers and the Porte. The two assemblies and the central commission were preserved till 1862, when a single assembly met at Bucharest and a single ministry was formed for the two countries. The central commission was at the same time abolished, and a council of state charged with preparing bills substituted for it. In May 1864, owing to difficulties between the Government and the general assembly, the latter was dissolved, and a statute was submitted to universal suffrage giving greater authority to the prince, and creating two chambers (of senators and of deputies). The franchise was now extended to all citizens, a cumulative voting power being reserved, however, for property, and the peasantry were emancipated from forced labour.</p><p>In 1865 a conflict broke out between the Government and the people in Bucharest, and in February 1866 Prince Cuza, whose personal vices had rendered him detestable, was forced to abdicate. The chambers chose first as his successor the count of Flanders, but on his declining the office proceeded to elect Prince Charles of Hohenzollern-Sigmaringen, who was proclaimed hospodar or <hi rend="italic">Domnu</hi>  of Roumania April 29, 1866. A new constitution was at the same time introduced. Its provisions secure the universal suffrage of tax-paying citizens, ministerial responsibility, trial by jury, freedom of meeting and petition, of speech and of the press (except as regards breaches of the criminal code), gratuitous and compulsory primary education, and the right of asylum for political exiles. Legislative power is shared between the prince and chambers, but bills relating to the budget and army must originate with the chamber of deputies. There are two chambers— the senate and the chamber of deputies. Both houses are elective, and the election is carried out by means of electoral colleges classified</p><p>according to property and professional qualifications. For the house of deputies each constituency is divided in this way into four colleges, each of which elects a member. The two highest of these colleges also elect the senators, each senator being elected for a term of eight years. The senate also includes <hi rend="italic">ex officio</hi>  certain high officials and ecclesiastics, and members for the universities. The senate consists at present of 120 members, the chamber of deputies of 178. The sovereign has a right of veto reserved to him on all measures. The judicial system is based on the <hi rend="italic">Code Napoléon, </hi>with some modifications.</p><p>On the outbreak of the Russo-Turkish war in 1877 Roumania found herself once more between hammer and anvil. Yielding to <hi rend="italic">force majeure</hi>  the Government of Prince Charles consented to the passage of Russian troops across Roumanian territory, on the understanding that the scene of hostilities was as far as possible to be removed outside the limits of the principality. The Porte, however, refusing to recognize that Roumania had acted under constraint, proclaimed the Roumanians rebels, and the prince’s Government accordingly resolved to offer active assistance to the Russians. A Roumanian division of 32,000 men under General Cernat, took part in the siege of Plevna, and the Roumanian soldiers distinguished themselves in the opinion of the most competent j udges alike for their heroism and endurance. The successful assault by the Roumanian troops on the “indomitable redoubt ” of Grivitza formed in fact the turning point of the siege and of the war. In the peace of StStefano, however, Russia insisted on the retrocession of the strip of Bessarabia that had been restored to Moldavia by the treaty of Paris, giving Roumania “ in exchange ” the islands of the Danubian delta, and the Dobrudja, which had been ceded by the sultan. This territorial readjustment w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as ratified by the treaty of Berlin (1878). The high contracting powers at the same time consented by Art. xliii. to recognize the independence of the principality subject to the provision (Art. xliv.) that all the inhabitants should enjoy complete religious freedom, a clause inserted on account of the Jewish persecutions that had previously taken place, and that foreigners in the country should be treated on a footing of perfect equality. All Danubian fortresses were to be razed, and the jurisdiction of the European commission to regulate the Danubian navigation, on which Roumania now acquired the right of representation, was extended from the mouth to the Iron Gates. The coping-stone to Roumanian independence was set by the proclamation on March 26, 1881, of Prince Charles as king of Roumania, and on May 22 of the same year his coronation took place with the European sanction. The crown placed on King Carol’s head was made from the captured cannon of the Plevna redoubts.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi>As the questions regarding the first appearance of the Rouinans north of the Danube are reserved for the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Vlachs,</hi>  it tray be sufficient Iiere to refer the reader to the works of Roesler, especially <hi rend="italic">Romanische Studien; </hi>J. Jung, <hi rend="italic">Anfänge der Romanen,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Roemer und Romanen</hi>  ; Lad. Pii, <hi rend="italic">Abstammung der Rumänen</hi>  ; A. D. Xenopol, <hi rend="italic">Les Roumains au Moyen Âge.</hi>  For the history of the principalities down to the end of the last century J. C. Engel’s works, <hi rend="italic">Die Geschichte der Walachei</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Moldau,</hi>  are still the most trustworthy authorities. J. A. Vaillant, <hi rend="italic">La Romainie: Histoire, Langue,</hi>  Ac., and A. T. Laurianu, <hi rend="italic">Istoria Romaniloru,</hi>  Ac., may be consulted for the later history, but a really critical history of the principalities has yet to be written. The materials for it are, however, being rapidly amassed—thanks to the publications of the Roumanian Academy and the documents collected by native scholars ; <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi>  especially Hurmuzaki, <hi rend="italic">Documente ρrivitore la Istoria Romanitor, </hi>and Hasdeu, <hi rend="italic">Publicationi istorico-filologice,</hi>  Ac. For a useful account of the present state of Roumania, see James Samuelson, <hi rend="italic">Roumania Past and Present, </hi>1882. For views of Walachia and Moldavia, as they existed from the 15th century onwards, reference has already been made to the works of Verantius and Del Cliiaro, and Cantemir’s <hi rend="italic">Descriptio Moldavise.</hi>    (A. J. E.)</p><p>ROUMANIAN LITERATURE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Vlachs.</hi></p><p>ROUMELIA. The name of Roumili, “ the land of the Romans,” was applied from the 15th century downwards to all that portion of the Balkan peninsula westwards from the Black Sea which was subject to Turkey. More precisely it was the country bounded N. by Bulgaria, W. by Albania, and S. by the Morea, or in other words the ancient provinces, including Constantinople and Salonica, of Thrace, Thessaly, and Macedonia. The name was ultimately applied more especially to an eyalet or province composed of Central Albania and Western Macedonia, having Monastir for its chief town and including Kesrie (Castoria), Ocri (Ochrida), and Scodra (Scutari) ; and at length it disappeared altogether in the administrative alterations effected between 1870 and 1875. Eastern Roumelia was constituted an autonomous province of the Turkish empire by the Berlin treaty of 1878, to be governed by a Christian governor-general appointed by the sultan for a term of five years. In 1879, in obedience to an international commission, it was divided into six departments and twenty-eight cantons, the departments being Philippopolis (187,095), Tatarbazarjik (117,063),</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>