<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>dreaming that, as he is about to inscribe in all modesty his name upon the threshold of the temple of glory, the goddess or fiend of Envy obstructs him, and a long interchange of reciprocal objurgations ensues. Here occurs the highly-charged portrait of the chief Roman detractor of Salvator (we are not aware that he has ever been identified by name) ; and the painter protests that he would never condescend to do any of the lascivious work in painting so shamefully in vogue.</p><p>As authorities for the life of Salvator Rosa, Passeri, <hi rend="italic">Vite drPitlori,</hi>  may he consulted, and Salvini, <hi rend="italic">Safire e Vila di Salrator Rosa;</hi>  also Baldinucei and Dominiei. The <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>  by Lady Morgan is a romantic treatment, mingling tradition or mere Action with fact.    (W. M. R.)</p><p>ROSAMOND, <hi rend="smallcaps">Fair.</hi>  Rosamond Clifford, mistress of Henry IL, was the daughter of Sir Walter Clifford, a Berkshire knight (Dugdale, <hi rend="italic">Monasticon,</hi>  iv. 366). She appears to have died in or about the year 1177, and was buried in the nunnery at Godstow. At the command of St Hugh, bishop of Lincoln, her body was removed from the church in which it had been buried, and was interred again outside the church. Such are all the facts that are known about Fair Rosamond. She is said to have been the mother of William Longsword, and of Geoffrey, archbishop of York. But this is impossible, for both William and Geoffrey -were born before 1155, and Rosamond was still a girl at the time of her death. The story of the labyrinth or maze built by Henry to conceal her from Queen Eleanor occurs first in Brompton (end of 12th century). The legend of her death at Queen Eleanor’s hand is variously related, but does not appear to be traceable beyond the first half of the 14th century. It can hardly be true in any form, for Eleanor was in confinement during the last fifteen years of Henry’s reign.</p><p>ROSARIO, a river-port on the Paranâ, and the chief town of a department in the province of Santa Fé in the Argentine Republic, 186 miles by river from Buenos Ayres. In 1853 an insignificant village, with less than four thousand inhabitants, it now ranks in commercial importance as the second city in the republic, being the centre of almost the entire trade of the eleven provinces lying between the Paranâ and the Andes and the terminus of the great railways which since 1863 have gradually been pushed further north and west to Cordoba (1870), Tucuman (1876), Mendoza (1884), and San Juan (1885). The population had increased to 21,000 by 1870 and to 45,000 in 1883, while the imports in the latter year reached the value of £4,560,000 and the exports £3,780,000.</p><p>Rosario stands about 65 feet above the level of the river. It is laid out chess-board fashion ; and the streets are paved, and lighted with gas (introduced in 1869). The area, 145 acres in 1870, is now about 2000 acres. Brick is the principal building material, and the houses are mostly of one story. There are no suburbs, the city terminating abruptly on the great plain. The industrial establishments are extensive foundries, a large number of brick kilns, a jam and fruit-preserving factory, breweries, tanneries, soap-works, saw-mills, and flour-mills.</p><p>Rosario was founded in 1725 by Don Francisco Godoy as a settlement of “reduced” CalChaqui Indians, and the parish was established in 1731 and dedicated to Our Lady of the Rosary, whose colours, blue and white, were adopted in 1813 as those of the national flag. The prosperity of the town dates from 1854, when it was made a port of entry by General Urquiza. In 1867 and 1868 it suffered from a severe cholera plague. The proposal to make Rosario the capital of the republic instead of Buenos Ayres has more than once been nearly carried in the legislature.</p><p>ROSARY <hi rend="italic">(Rosarium,</hi>  Germ. Rosenkranz) is defined in the Roman <hi rend="italic">Rreviary</hi>  as a series of one hundred and fifty repetitions of the “ Ave Maria,” with a “ Pater Noster ” interpolated after each decade, the whole exercise being accompanied with pious meditation on the mysteries of redemption. This particular method of devotion, though said to have been not altogether unknown previously, first became extensively popular through St Dominic, who was admonished by the Virgin Mary to preach the rosary as</p><p>a special defence against heresy and vice. The Feast of the Rosary of the Blessed Virgin (Duplex Majus—first Sunday in October) was instituted by Clement XI. to commemorate the successes of the Christian arms against the Turks in 1716 ; it has reference also to the battle of Lepanto (Oct. 7, 1571). The word “ rosary ” or “ chaplet ” (capellina) is also employed to denote the string of beads of larger and smaller size by the use of which in repeating the rosary the faithful secure the due alternation of Ave Marias with Pater Nosters. In strict language the word chaplet is applied only to the “ lesser ” rosary, consisting of but fifty Aves and five Pater Nosters. Similar expedients to assist the memory in complex repetitions occur among Mohammedans and Buddhists : in the former case the so-called sobha has ninety-nine beads, and is used for the pious repetition of the ninety-nine names which express the attributes of God.</p><p>ROSAS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jüan Manuel de,</hi>  born at Buenos Ayres March 30, 1793, died in England March 14, 1877 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Argentine Republic,</hi>  vol. ii. p. 491).</p><p>ROSCELLINUS (also written <hi rend="smallcaps">Rousselin</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Ruce-linus),</hi>  often called the founder of nominalism (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Scholasticism),</hi>  was born in Armorica or Lower Brittany somewhere about the middle of the llth century. Our information about his life is scanty, and, as he appears to have written nothing, we are dependent for a knowledge of his doctrine upon the statements of his opponents and the cursory statements of later writers. He studied at Soissons and Rheims, was afterwards attached to the cathedral of Chartres, and became canon of Compiègne. It seems most probable that Roscellinus was not strictly the first to promulgate nominalistic doctrines; but in his exposition they received more definite expression, and, being applied to the dogma of the Trinity, attracted universal attention. The chief opponent of Roscellinus was Anselm of Canterbury, w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ho defended at once the realistic doctrine of universals and the orthodox tradition of the church. It appears from the polemic of Anselm that “ the heretics in dialectic ” whom he combats denied the substantial reality of universals, asserting, for example, that colour has no real existence except as coloured body. There is no reason, however, to suppose that Roscellinus meant thereby to deny the real existence of attributive differences in things, though Anselm endeavours to involve him in that consequence. But we may conclude from the censure of his pupil Abelard that his reaction against realism had led Roscellinus into rashness of expression. In conformity with his general nominalistic position, Roscellinus taught that whatever exists as a real thing or substance exists as one self-identical whole, and is not susceptible of division into parts. This was the part of his teaching which created so much scandal when applied to the doctrine of the Trinity. Roscellinus maintained that it is merely a habit of speech which prevents outspeaking of the three persons as three substances or three Gods. If it were otherwise, and the three persons were really one substance or thing<hi rend="italic">(fitηa res),</hi>  we should be forced to admit that the Father and the Holy Spirit became incarnate along with the Son. Roscellinus seems to have put forward this doctrine in perfect good faith, and to have claimed for it at first the authority of Lanfranc and Anselm. In 1092, however, a council convoked by the archbishop of Rheims condemned his interpretation, and Roscellinus, who was in danger of being lynched by the orthodox populace, recanted his error. As his enforced penitence did not prove lasting, his opinions were condemned by a second council (1094), and he himself fled to England. Forced by a fresh persecution to return to France at a later date, he taught at Tours and Loc-menach in Brittany (where he had Abelard as a pupil), and resided</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>