<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>under the Albergo di Catena near the Piazza Montanara. This temple was begun by Augustus in 36 ιs.c.,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> after his Sicilian victory over Sextus Pompeius, and finished in 28 B. c.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> A glowing account of the splendours of these buildings is given by Propertius <hi rend="italic">{El.,</hi>  ii. 3). Inside the cella were statues of Apollo between Latona and Diana by Scopas, Praxiteles, and Timotheus respectively (Plin., <hi rend="italic">H.N^.,</hi>  xxxvi. 4) ; round the walls were statues of the nine Muses (Juv., vii. 37). The pediment had sculpture by Bupalus and Arehermus of Chios (Plin., <hi rend="italic">H.N.,</hi>  xxxvi. 4), and on the apex was Apollo in a quadriga of gilt bronze. The double door was covered with ivory reliefs of the death of the Niobids and the defeat of the Gauls at Delphi. The Ancyra inscription records that Augustus sold eighty silver statues of himself and with the money “ offered golden gifts” to this temple, dedicating them both in his own name and in the names of the original donors of the statues.@@<hi rend="sup">3 </hi>The Sibylline books were preserved under the statue of Apollo (Suet.,<hi rend="italic">Axιg.,</hi>  31); and within the cella were vases, tripods, and statues of gold and silver, with a collection of engraved gems dedicated by Marcellus (see Plin., <hi rend="italic">H.N.,</hi>  xxxvii. 5). On each side of the porticus was a large library, one Latin and the other Greek ;@@<hi rend="sup">4 </hi>and a third side of the great enclosure was occupied by a large hall where the Senate Occasionallymet (Tac.,<hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi>  ii. 37), in the centre</p><p>@@@1    <hi rend="smallcaps">Templvm . Apollinis . in . solo . magnam . partem . </hi>EMPTO . FECI (<hi rend="italic">Mon. Ancyr.).</hi></p><p>@@@    See Dion Cass., xlix. 15, liιi. 1, and C.LL., i. p. 403.</p><p>@@@    See also Suet.,<hi rend="italic">Aug.,</hi>  52, whose account is rather different.</p><p>@@@4 Schol. to Juv., i. 128, and Suet., <hi rend="italic">Αug.,</hi>  29.</p></body></text></TEI>