<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>the people backed by a written recommendation from the dictator, which was equivalent
                to a command.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Finally, the senate itself was transformed out
                of all likeness to its former self by the raising of its numbers to 900, and by the
                admission of old soldiers, sons of freedmen, and even “semi-barbarous Gauls.”@@<hi
                    rend="sup">2</hi> But, though Cæsar’s highhanded conduct in this respect was not
                imitated by his immediate successors, yet the main lines of their policy were laid
                down by him. These were (1) the municipalization of the old republican constitution,
                and (2) its subordination to the paramount authority of the master of the legions
                and the provinces. In the first case he only carried further a change already in
                progress. Of late years the senate had been rapidly losing its hold over the empire
                at large. Even the ordinary proconsuls were virtually independent potentates, ruling
                their provinces as they chose, and disposing absolutely of legions which recognized
                no authority but theirs. The consuls and prætors of each year had since 81 been
                stationed in Rome, and immersed in purely municipal business; and, lastly, since the
                enfranchisement of Italy, the comitia, though still recognized as the ultimate
                source of all authority, had become little more than assemblies of the city
                populace, and their claim to represent the true Roman people was indignantly
                questioned, even by republicans like Cicero. The concentration in Cæsar’s hands of
                all authority outside Rome completely and finally severed all real connection
                between the old institutions of the republic of Rome and the government of the Roman
                empire. And, though Augustus and Tiberius elevated the senate to a place beside
                themselves in this government, its share of the work was a subordinate one, and it
                never again directed the policy of the state ; while, from the time of Cæsar
                onwards, the old magistracies are merely municipal offices, with a steadily
                diminishing authority, even in the city, and the comitia retain no other prerogative
                of imperial importance but that of formally confirming the ruler of the empire in
                the possession of an authority which is already his. But the institutions of the
                republic not merely became, what they had originally been, the local institutions of
                the city of Rome ; they were also subordinated even within these narrow limits to
                the paramount authority of the man who held in his hands the army and the provinces.
                And here Cæsar’s policy was closely followed by his successors. Autocratic abroad,
                at home he was the chief magistrate of the commonwealth ; and this position was
                marked, in his case as in that of those who followed him, by a combination in his
                person of various powers, and by a general right of precedence which left no limits
                to his authority but such as he chose to impose upon himself. During the greater
                part of his reign he was consul as well as dictator.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> In 48,
                after his victory at Pharsalia, he was given the “tribunicia potestas ” for
                    life,@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> and after his second success at Thapsus the “
                praefectura morum ” for three years.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> As chief magistrate he
                convenes and presides in the senate, nominates candidates, conducts elections,
                carries laws in the assembly, and administers justice in court.@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >6</hi> Finally, as a reminder that the chief magistrate of Rome was also the
                autocratic ruler of the empire, he wore even in Rome the laurel wreath and triumphal
                dress, and carried the sceptre of the victorious imperator.@@<hi rend="sup"
                >7</hi></p>
            <p>Nor are we without some clue as to the policy which</p>
            <p>Cæsar had sketched out for himself in the administration of the empire, the
                government of which he had centralized in his own hands. The much-needed work of
                rectifying the frontiers ho was forced, by his premature death, to leave to other
                hands, but our authorities agree in attributing to him the design of extending the
                rule of Rome to its natural geographical limits @@<hi rend="sup">8</hi>—to the
                Euphrates and the Caucasus on the east, to the Danube and the Rhine or possibly the
                Elbe on the north, and to the ocean on the west. Within the frontiers he anticipated
                Augustus in lightening the financial burdens of the provincials,@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >9 </hi>and in establishing a stricter control over the
                    provincial governors,@@<hi rend="sup">10</hi> while he went beyond him in his
                desire to consolidate the empire by extending the Roman franchise@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >11 </hi>and admitting provincials to a share in the government.@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >12 </hi>He completed the Romanization of Italy by his enfranchisement of the
                Transpadane Gauls,@@<hi rend="sup">13</hi> and by establishing throughout the
                peninsula a uniform system of municipal government, which under his successors was
                gradually extended to the provinces.@@<hi rend="sup">14</hi></p>
            <p>On the eve of his departure for the East, to avenge the death of Crassus and humble
                the power of Parthia, Cæsar fell a victim to the wounded pride of the republican
                nobles ; and between the day of his death (March 15, 44) and that on which Octavian
                defeated Antonyat Actium (September 2, 31) lies a dreary period of anarchy and
                    bloodshed.@@<hi rend="sup">15</hi></p>
            <p>For a moment, in spite of the menacing attitude of Cæsar’s self-constituted
                representative Antony, it seemed to one man at least as if the restoration of
                republican government was possible. With indefatigable energy Cicero strove to
                enlist the senate, the people, and above all the provincial governors in support of
                the old constitution. But, though his eloquence now and again carried all before it
                in senate house and forum, it was powerless to alter the course of events. By the
                beginning of 43 civil war had recommenced ; in the autumn Antony was
                already threatening an invasion of Italy at the head of seventeen legions. Towards
                the end of October Antony and his ally Lepidus coalesced with the young Octavian,
                who had been recently elected consul at the age of twenty, in spite of senatorial
                opposition ; and the coalition was legalized by the creation of the extraordinary
                commission for the “ reorganization of the commonwealth ” known as the “second
                    triumvirate.”@@<hi rend="sup">16</hi> It was appointed for a period of five
                years, and was continued in 37 for five years more.@@<hi rend="sup">17 </hi>The rule
                of the triumvirs was inaugurated in the Sullan fashion, and, in marked contrast to
                the lenity shown by Cæsar, by a proscription, foremost among the victims of which
                was Cicero himself.@@<hi rend="sup">18</hi> In the next year the defeat of Brutus
                and Cassius at Philippi, by the combined forces of Octavian and Antony, destroyed
                the last hopes of the republican party.@@<hi rend="sup">19</hi> In 40 a threatened
                rupture between the two victors was avoided by the treaty concluded at Brundusium.
                Antony married Octavian’s sister Octavia,</p>
            <p>@@@    Suet., 41, “Caesar dictator . . . commendo vobis ilium et ilium, ut vestro
                suffragio suam dignitatem teneant.”</p>
            <p>@@@    Suet., 41, 76 ; Dio, xliii. 47.</p>
            <p>@@@    Watson,<hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> App. x.; Zumpt, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Stud. Rom., loe. eit.,</hi> Suet., 76, “ tertium et quartum consulatuιη titulo
                tenus gessit.”</p>
            <p>@@@    Dio, xlii. 20.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> Dio, xliii. 14 ; Suet., 76.</p>
            <p>@@@ Suet., 43, “jus Iaboriosissime ac severissime dixit.”</p>
            <p>@@@ App., ii. 106 ; Dio, xliii. 43.</p>
            <p>@@@ Plut., 58, “<hi rend="italic">trυvdψaι τbv κυκ</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">οv τηs fjyepovias” ;</hi> Suet., 44; Dio, xliii. 51.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi> Plut., 48 ; App., v. 4.</p>
            <p>@@@ He limited the term of command to two years in consular and one year in prætorian
                provinces; Cicero,<hi rend="italic">Phil.,</hi> i. 8 ; Dio, xliii. 25.</p>
            <p>@@@    Suet., 42; Cic.<hi rend="italic">Ad Att.,</hi> xiv. 12.</p>
            <p>@@@    Suet., 76.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">13</hi> Dio, xli. 36; Tac., <hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi> xi.
                24.</p>
            <p>@@@ LexJulia municipalis ; Wordsworth,<hi rend="italic">Fragments of Early
                    Latin, </hi>pp. 213, 464 ; Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">R. G.,</hi> iii. 524. Lex
                Rubria; Wordsworth, pp. 212, 463.</p>
            <p>@@@ For this period see Merivale,<hi rend="italic">Romans under the Empire,</hi> vol
                iii.; Lange, <hi rend="italic">R&lt;5m. Alterth.,</hi> iii. 476 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi> ; Ranke, <hi rend="italic">Weltgeschichte,</hi> ii. 336 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.</hi> ; Watson, <hi rend="italic">Cicero's Letters,</hi>
                Introd. to Part v.</p>
            <p>@@@ The triumvirate was formally constituted in Rome (Nov. 27) by a plebiscitum ;
                App., iv. 7 ; Dio, xlvi. 50-56, xlvii. 2 ; Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit., </hi>cxx.
                “ut ιπviri reipublicae Constituendae per quinquennium essent.”</p>
            <p>@@@    Dio, xlviii. 54 ; App., v. 93. For the date,<hi rend="italic">cf.</hi>
                Fischer, <hi rend="italic">R&lt;im. Zeittafeln,</hi> 352, 353.</p>
            <p>@@@    Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.,</hi> cxx. ; App., iv. 7 ; and art. Cicero.</p>
            <p>@@@    Dio, xlvii. 35-49 ; App., iv. 87-138.</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
