<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>side was occupied by the Basilica Ulpia (Jordan, <hi rend="italic">For. Ur. Rom.'), </hi>part of which, with the column of Trajan, is now visible ; none of the columns, which are of grey granite, are <hi rend="italic">in situ,</hi>  and the whole restoration is misleading. Part of the rich paving in Oriental marble is genuine. This basilica contained two large libraries (Dion Cass., Ixviii. 16 ; Aul. Gell., xi. 17).</p><p>The Columna Cochlis (so called from its spiral stairs) is, including capital and base, 97 feet 9 inches high,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi><hi rend="italic">ix.,</hi>  IOO Roman feet ; its pedestal has reliefs of trophies of Dacian arms, and winged Victories, with an inscription recording the enormous mass of Iiill which was removed to form the site (comp. Dion Cass., Ixviii. 16). On the shaft are reliefs arranged spirally in twenty-three tiers, scenes of Trajan’s victories, containing about 2500 figures. Trajan’s ashes were buried in a gold urn under this column (Dion Cass., Ixviii. 16) ; and on the summit was a colossal gilt bronze statue of the emperor, now replaced by a poor figure of St Peter, set there by Sixtus V.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  Beyond the column stood the temple of Trajan . completed by Hadrian ; its foundations exist under the buildings at the north-east side of the modern piazza, and many of its granite columns have been found. This temple is shown on coins of Hadrian.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  The architect of this magnificent group of buildings was Apollodorus of Damascus (Dion Cass., Ixix. 4), who also designed many buildings in Rome during Hadrian’s reign.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  In addition to the five imperial fora, and the Forum AIagnum, Olitorium, and Boarium, mentioned above, there were also smaller markets for pigs (Forum Suarium), bread (Forum Pistorium), and fish (Forum Piscarium), all of which, with some others, popularly but</p><p>wrongly called fora, are given in the regionary catalogues.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Other Temples, Ac.</hi></p><p>Besides the temples mentioned in previous sections remains of many others still exist in Rome. The circular temple by the Tiber in the Forum Boarium, formerly thought to be that of Vesta, may be the temple of Hercules mentioned by AIacrobius <hi rend="italic">{Saturn., </hi>iii. 6), Solinus <hi rend="italic">{Colled.,</hi>  i. 11), and Livy (x. 23). Its design is similar to that of the temple of Vesta in the Forum (fig. 15), and, except the entablature and upper part of the cella, which are gone, it is well preserved (see Piale, <hi rend="italic">Tempiodi Vesta,</hi>  1817). The neighbouring Ionic temple, popularly called of Fortuna Virilis, is of special interest from its early date, probably the end of the 2d century b.c. The complete absence of marble and the very sparing use of travertine, combined with the simple purity of its design, are all proofs of its great antiquity. It has a prostyle tetrastyle portico of travertine, and a short cella of tufa with engaged columns ; the bases of these and of the angle columns are of travertine. The frieze has reliefs of ox skulls and garlands. The whole was originally stuccoed and painted so that the different stones used</p><p>would    not</p><p>show. Fig. 21</p><p>gives the plan,</p><p>showing the hard travertine used at the points of greatest pressure, while the main walls with the half columns are of the weaker and</p><p>softer tufa. The dedication of this temple is doubtful ; on the whole it appears most probable that it is the temple to Fortuna (without any affix) founded by Servius Tullius (Dionys., iv. 27) in the Forum Boarium, not the one to <hi rend="italic">Τύχη <hi rend="sup">,</hi>λv5ρeια</hi>  (Fors Fortuna ?) mentioned as being by the river (comp. Plut., <hi rend="italic">De Fork Rom.,</hi>  5). Ten columns of what is probably the temple of Ceres, Liber, and Libera exist wι∙ <hi rend="italic">situ,</hi>  built up in the end and side walls of the church of S. AIaria in Cosmedin. These have well sculptured composite capitals and wide Intercolumniation,—probably a survival of the original design of this temple, which was Tuscan in style (Vitr., iii. 3, 5 ; Plin., <hi rend="italic">H.N.,</hi>  XXXV. 45). Itwas founded by Aulus Postumius, dictator in 497 b.c., and dedicated by Spurius Cassius, consul in 494 B. C.</p><p>(Dionys,, vi. 17, 94). In 31 B.C. it was burnt (Dion Cass., 1. 10), and was rebuilt by Augustus and Tiberius (Tac., <hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi>  ii. 49); but the existing columns belong to a still later restoration. The temple stands close to the carceres of the Circus AIaximus, in the Forum Boarium. Within the walls of S. Niccolo in Carcere (see fig. 22) in the Forum Olitorium are preserved remains of the tufa cellæ and travertine columns of three small hexastyle peripteral temples, two Ionic and one Tuscan, set close side by side.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  A fragment of the</p><p>marble plan in</p><p>cludes part of this</p><p>group, as is indi</p><p>cated on fig. 22.</p><p>Two of these</p><p>temples were pro</p><p>bably those to</p><p>Spes and Juno</p><p>Sospita (Liv.,xxi.</p><p>62, xxxii. 30) ; the</p><p>third may be that</p><p>of Apollo AIedicus</p><p>(Liv., xl. 51), as</p><p>suggested by</p><p>Burn <hi rend="italic">{Rome mid</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Campagna,</hi>  1871,</p><p>note i. p. 306).</p><p>Near the Fomm</p><p>Olitorium, in the ]</p><p>modern Ghetto,</p><p>are extensive re</p><p>mains of the large</p><p>group of buildings included in the Porticus Octaviæ, two of which, dedicated to Juno Regina and Jupiter Stator, with part of the enclosing porticus and the adjoining temple of Hercules AIusarum, are shown on a fragment of the marble plan. The Porticus Octaviæ, a large rectangular space enclosed by a double line of columns, was built in honour of Octavia by her brother Augustus on the site of the Porticus AIetelli, founded in 146 b.c. This must not be confounded with the neighbouring Porticus Octavia founded by Cn. Octavius, the conqueror of Perseus (Liv., xlv. 6, 42), in 168 B.c., and rebuilt under the same name by Augustus, as is recorded in the Ancyræan inscription. The whole group was one of the most magnificent in Rome, and contained a large number of works of art by Phidias and other Greek sculptors. The existing portico, which was the main entrance into the porticus, is a restoration of the time of Severus in 203. The church of S. AIichele and the houses behind it conceal extensive remains of the porticus and its temples (see <hi rend="italic">Ann. Inst.,</hi>  1868, p. 108 ; and Contigliozzi, <hi rend="italic">I Portixidi Ottavia, </hi>1861).@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi></p><p>Remains of a large peripteral Corinthian temple are built into the side of the “ Dogana di Terra,” near AIonteCitorio. Eleven marble columns and their rich entablature are still <hi rend="italic">in situ,</hi>  with the corresponding part of the cella wall of peperino ; in 1878 a piece of the end wall of the cella was discovered, and, under the houses near, part of a large peribolus wall, also of peperino, forming an enclosure with columns all round the temple nearly 330 feet square (see <hi rend="italic">Bull. Comm. Arch. Rom.,</hi>  vL, pi. iv., 1878). The dedication of this temple is not known ; it has commonly been identified with the temple of Neptune (Dion Cass., Ixvi. 24), built by Agrippa, and surrounded by the Porticus Argonautarum (Dion Cass., Iiii. 27 ; AIart. iii. 20, 11) ; but its details appear to be later than the reign of Augustus.@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi>  Another not improbable theory is that it was the temple of Hadrian, mentioned in the<hi rend="italic">Mirabilia</hi>  (Uhlrichs, <hi rend="italic">Codex Topogr.,</hi>  Wiirtzburg, 1871, p. 107) as being near this spot.</p><p>The temple of Venus Felix and Roma Æterna on the Velia (see fig. 23) was the largest in Rome ; it was pseudo-dipteral with ten Corinthian columns of Greek marble at the ends, and probably twenty at the sides ; it had an outer colonnade round the peribolus of about 180 columns of polished granite and porphyry. Of these only a few fragments now exist ; for several centuries the whole area of this building was used as a quarry, while the residue of the marble was burnt into lime on the spot in kilns built of broken fragments of the porphyry columns. A considerable part of the two cellæ with their apses, set back to back, still exists ; in each apse was a colossal seated figure of the deity, and along the side walls of the cellæ were rows of porphyry columns and statues in niches. The vault is deeply coffered with stucco enrichments once painted and gilt. The roof was covered with tiles of gilt bronze, which were taken by Pope Honorius I. (625-638) to cover the basilica of St Peter’s. These were stolen by the Saracens during their sack of the Leonine city in 846. The emperor Hadrian himself designed this magnificent temple, which was partially completed</p><p>@@@    Its pedestal is inscribed, “ Senatus Populusque Romanus Imp. Csesari Divi Nervse F. Nervæ Trajano Aug. Germ. Dacico Pontif. Maximo Trib. Pot. XVII. [i.e., 114 A.D.1 Imp. VI. P. P. ad declarandum quantæ altitudinis nions et locus tant(is operi)bus sit egestus.” This cannot be taken literally, as the ridge which was cut away never approached IOO feet in height, but possibly means that the cliff of the Quirinal was cut back to a slope reaching to a point IOO feet high (see Brocchi,<hi rend="italic">Suοlο di Roma,</hi>  p. 133 ; Becker, <hi rend="italic">Ηandb.,</hi>  note 737).</p><p>@@@2    See Fabretti, <hi rend="italic">Columna Trajana</hi>  (1683), who gives drawings of all the reliefs'; also De Rossi, <hi rend="italic">Cok Traj. designata.</hi>  The reliefs, from their lofty position, are now difficult to see, but originally must have been very fairly visible from the galleries on the colonnades which once surrounded the column.</p><p>@@@    See Aul. Gell., xi. 17, 1 ; Spart.,<hi rend="italic">Hist. Aug. : Hadr.,</hi>  19 ; and compare Pau-sanias(v. 12, 6 ; x. 5,11), who mentions the gilt bronze roofs of Trajan’s forum.</p><p>@@@4    See Fea, <hi rend="italic">Foro Trajano,</hi>  1832 ; Richter, <hi rend="italic">Ristauro del Foro Trajano,</hi>  1839 ; Bartoli, <hi rend="italic">Cok Trajana,</hi>  1704 ; Pistolesi, <hi rend="italic">Cok Trajana,</hi>  1846 ; Froehner, <hi rend="italic">La Colonne Trajane,</hi>  Paris, 1865.</p><p>@@@ For drawings of them see<hi rend="italic">Ann. Inst.,</hi>  1850, p. 347, and <hi rend="italic">Μon. Inst.,</hi>  v. 24; also Labacco, <hi rend="italic">Architettura,</hi>  1557.</p><p>@@@6 The remains of the Porticus Octaviæ are now being more completely exposed by the demolition of the Ghetto.</p><p>@@@7 This, however, is not conclusive, as the temple of Neptune may have been completely rebuilt after the fire which injured it in 80.</p></body></text></TEI>