<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>this symbolic worſhip began among the Magi, who were the ſons of Chus ; and by them they were propagated in various parts Wherever the Amonians founded any places of worſhip, and introduced their rites, there was generally some ſtory of a ſerpent. There was a legend about a ſerpent at Colchis, at Thebes, and at Delphi ; and likewiſe in other places. The Greeks  called Apollo himſelf Python, which is the ſame as Opis, Oupis, and Oub.</p><p>In Egypt there was a ſerpent named Thermuthis, which was looked upon as very sacred ; and the natives are said to have made uſe of it as a royal tiara, with which they ornamented the ſtatues of Iſis. The kings of Egypt wore high bonnets, terminating in a round ball, and ſurrounded with figures of alps ; and the prieſts likewiſe had the representation of serpents upon their bonnets.</p><p>Abadon, or Abaddon, mentioned in the Revelations XX. 2 is ſuppoſed by Mr Bryant to have been the name of the Ophite god, with whole worſhip the world had been ſo long infected. This worſhip began among the people of Chaldea, who built the city ot Ophis upon the Tigris, and were greatly addicted to divination, and to the worſhip of the ſerpent. From Chaldea the worſhip paſſed into Egypt, where the ſerpent deity was called Canoph, Caneph, and C’neph. It had also the name of Ob or Oub, and was the ſame as the Baſiliſcus or royal ſerpent, the ſame as the Thermuthis, and made uſe of by way of ornament to the ſtatues ol their gods. The chief deity of Egypt is ſaid to have been Vulcan, who was ſtyled Opas. He was the ſame as Oſiris, the Sun, and hence was often called Ob'el, or Pythoſol; and there were pillars ſacred to him, with curious hieroglyphical inſcriptions bearing the same name; whence,  among the Greeks, who copied from the Egyptians, every thing gradually tapering to a point was ſtyled  Obelos, or obeliſcus.</p><p>As the worſhip of the ſerpent began among the ſons  of Chus, Mr Bryant conjectures, that from thence they were denominated Ethiopians and Aithiopians, from Athope or Athopes, the god whom they worſhipped, and not from their complexion : the Ethiopes brought theſe rites into Greece, and called the iſland where they  firſt eſtabliſhed them <hi rend="italic">Ellopia, Solis Serpentis insulα,</hi> the ſame with <hi rend="italic">Eubaea,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Oubaia,</hi> i. e. “ the ſerpent iſland.” The ſame learned writer diſcovers traces of the ſerpent worſhip among the Hyperboreans, at Rhodes, named Ophiuſa, in Phrygia, and upon the Helleſpont, in the iſland Cyprus, in Crete, among the Athenians, in the name of Cecrops, among the natives of Thebes in Boeotia, among the Lacedemonians, in Italy, in Syria, &amp;c. and in the names of many places, as well as of the people where the Ophites ſettled. One of the most early hereſies introduced into the Chriſtian church was that of the Ophitæ. Bryant’s Analyſis of Ancient Mythology, vol. i. p. 43, &amp;c. p. 473, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Serpent</hi><hi rend="italic"> Stones.</hi> See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Cornu</hi><hi rend="italic"> Ammonis.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Sea-SERPENT.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">SEA-Serpent.</hi></p><p>SERPENTARIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">snake-root ; </hi>a ſpecies of <hi rend="smallcaps">Aristolochia.</hi></p><p>SERPENTA RIUS, in astronomy, a conſtellation of the northern hemiſphere, called also Ophiuchus, and anciently Æsculapius The ſtars in the conſtellation Serpentairius, in Ptolemy's catalogue, are 29 ; in Tycho’s</p><p>15 ; in Hevelius's 40 ; in the Britannic catalogue they are 74.</p><p>SERPENTINE, in general, denotes any thing that reſembles a ſerpent ; hence the worm or pipe of a ſtill, twilled in a spiral manner, is termed a <hi rend="italic">terpentine worm.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Serpentine</hi><hi rend="italic"> Stony</hi> a genus of magnesian earths, of which there are different ſpecies : 1. The fibroſus, compoſed of fibrous and coherent particles. This reſembles the aſbeſtos ſo much that it might be confounded with it, were not the fibres of the ſerpentine ſo cloſely coherent, that they cannot be diſtinguished when the ſtone is cut or poliſhed. The fibres themſelves are large, and ſeem to be twilled, There are two varieties, a dark green and a light one ; the former ſrom Germany, the latter from Sweden. 2. The zoeblitz ſerpentine, found near that place, of many different colours, as black, deep green, light green, red, bluish-grey, and white ; but the green colour is most predominant.</p><p>3.	Porcelain earth mixed with iron. It is met with either diffusible in water or indurated. The former is found of a red colour from China and Montmartre. The water-clinkers, imported from ſome places in Germany, ſeem to be made of this kind of earth. There are two varieties of the indurated kind, viz. the martial ſoap-earth, of a red colour, from Jaſherg and oilier places in Norway, or black from ſome parts of Sweden.</p><p>4.	The telgſton of the Swedes, the ſame with the lapis ollaris.. It is found in various places of Norway, as light grey, dark grey, whitiſh-yellow, and dark green. It is employed with great advantage for building fire-places, furnaces, &amp;c. the extremities of the ſtrata being turned towards the fire when it is ſlaty.</p><p>M. Magellan obſerves, that there is a great variety of colour as well as compoſition in this kind of ſtones ; it being found either white, green, brown, yellow, light- blue, black, ſpotted, or ſtreaked with veins of different colours. Its texture is either indistinct, obscurely laminar, or fibrous. The ſpecific gravity is from 2400 to 2650; and it is harder than ſoap-rock or steatites ; though not hard enough to strike fire with ſteel; being less ſmooth to the touch than ſteatites, but ſuſceptible of a good poliſh, looking like marble ; and is often met with in thin semitranſparent plates. It melts in a ſtrong heat without addition, and corrodes the crucibles, but hardens in a lower degree of heat. It is ilowly and partially soluble in acids, but does not efferveſce with them. According to Bayon’s analyſis, 100 parts of it contain about 41 or ſilex, or rattier mica; 33 of magnesia; 10 of argillaceous earth ; 12 of water, and about 3 of iron. That brought from Corsica contains a greater proportion of argil, and a ſmaller one of ſilex. The ſerpentine commonly ſo called, according to Fabroni, is a true lapis ollaris ; but has its name from being variegated with green, yellowiſh, and brown ſpots, like the ſkin of ſome ſerpents ; great quantities of it are found in Italy and Switzerland, where it is frequently worked into diſhes and other veſſels.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Serpentine</hi> verses, are ſuch as begin and end with the ſame word. As,</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ambo florentes aetatibus·, Arcades ambo.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Serpentine,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Manege.</hi> A horse is ſaid to&gt; have a ſerpentine tongue, if it is always friſking and moving, and ſometimes paſſing over the bit, inſtead of</p></body></text></TEI>