<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>occaſioned clamours that overpowered the lamb’s bleat and the linnet’s ſong, and his groves were haunted by beings very different from fawns and fairies. He ſpent his eſtate in adorning it, and his death was probably haſtened by his anxieties. He was a lamp that ſpent its oil in blazing. It is ſaid, that if he had lived a little longer, he would have been aſſiſted by a penſion ; such bounty could not have been more properly beſtowed, but that it was ever aſked is not certain ; it is too certain that it never was enjoyed.— He died at the Leaſowes, of a putrid fever, about five on Friday morning, Feb. II. 1763 ; and was buried by the side of his brother, in the churchyard of Hales- Owen.</p><p>In his private opinions, our author adhered to no particular ſect, and hated all religious diſputes. Tenderneſs, in every ſenſe of the word, was his peculiar characteriſtic ; and his friends, domeſtics, and poor neighbours, daily experienced the effects of his benevolence. This virtue he carried to an exceſs that ſeemed to border upon weakneſs ; yet if any of his friends treated him ungenerouſly, he was not eaſily reconciled. On such occaſions, however, he uſed to say, “ I never will be a revengeful enemy ; but I cannot, it is not in my nature, to be half a friend.” He was no economiſt ; for the generoſity of his temper prevented his paying a proper regard to the uſe of money : he exceeded therefore the bounds of his paternal fortune. But, if we conſider the perfect paradiſe into which he had converted his eſtate, the hospitality with which he lived, his charities to the indigent, and all out of an eſtate that did not exceed 300 l. a-year, one ſhould rather wonder that he left any thing behind him, than blame his want of economy : he yet left more than ſufficient to pay all his debts, and by his will appropriated his whole eſtate to that purpoſe. Though he had a high opinion of many of the fair ſex, he forbore to marry. A paſſion he entertained in his youth was with difficulty ſumounted. The lady was the ſubject of that admirable paſtoral, in four parts, which has been ſo univerſally and ſo juſtly admired, and which, one would have thought, muſt have ſoftened the proudeſt and moſt obdurate heart. His works have been publiſhed by Mr Dodſley, in 3 vols 8vo. The firſt volume contains his poetical works, which are particularly diſtinguiſhed by an amiable elegance and beautiful simplicity ; the second volume contains his proſe works ; the third his letters, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary.</hi></p><p>SHEPPEY, an iſland at the mouth of the river Medway, about 20 miles in circumference. It is ſeparated from the main land by a narrow channel, and has a fertile soil, which feeds great flocks of ſheep. The borough-town of Queenborough is ſeated thereon ; beſides which it has several villages.</p><p>SHERARDIA, in botany : A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 47th order, <hi rend="italic">Stellütœ.</hi> The calyx is ſmall, quadridentate ; the corolla monopetalous, long, and funnel-ſhaped. The two feeds are naked, and crowned with the calyx. There are three ſpecies, viz. 1. Arvensis ; 2. Muralis ; 3. Fruticoſa.</p><p>SHERBET, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sherbit,</hi> a compound drink, firſt Brought into England from Turkey and Periia, conſiſtng of water, lemon juice, and ſugar, in which are dissolved perfumed cakes made of excellent Damaſcus fruit, containing an infuſion of some drops of rose water. Another kind of it is made of violets, honey, juice of raiſins, &amp;c,</p><p>SHERIDAN (Thomas), D. D. the intimate friend of Dean Swift, is ſaid by Shield, in Cibber’s “ Lives of the Poets,” to have been born about 1684, in the county of Cavan, where, according to the ſame authority, his parents lived in no very elevated ſtate. They are deſcribed as being unable to afford their ſon the advantages of a liberal education; but he, being obſerved to give early indications of genius, attracted the notice of a friend to his family, who font him to the college of Dublin, and contributed towards his ſupport while he remained there. He aftewards entered into orders, and ſet up a ſchool in Dublin, which long maintained a very high degree of reputation, as well for the attention beſtowed on the morals of the ſcholars as for their proficiency in literature. So great was the eſtimation in which this ſeminary was held, that it is aſſerted to have produced in some years the ſum of L. 1000. It does not appear that he had any conſiderable preferment ; but his intimacy with Swift, in 1725, procured for him a living in the south of Ireland worth about L. 150 a-year, which he went to take poſſeſſion of, and, by an act of inadvertence, deſtroyed all his future expectations of riling in the church ; for being at Corke on the 1st of Auguſt, the anniverſary of King George’s birth-day, he preached a ſermon, which had for its text, “ Sufficient for the day is the evil thereof.” On this being known, he was ſtruck out of the list of chaplains to the lord lieutenant, and forbidden the castle.</p><p>This living Dr Sheridan afterwards changed for that of Dunboyne, which, by the knavery of the farmers, and power of the gentlemen in the neighbourhood, fell so low as L. 80 <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi> He gave it up for the free ſchool of Cavan, where he might have lived well in so cheap a country on L. 80 a-year ſalary, beſides his ſcholars ; but the air being, as he ſaid, too moiſt and unwholesome, and being diſguſted with some perſons who lived there, he fold the ſchool for about L. 400 ; and having ſoon ſpent the money, he fell into bad health, and died Sept. 10. 1738, in his 55th year.</p><p>Lord Corke has given the following character of him : “ Dr Sheridan was a ſchool-maſter, and in many inſtances perfectly well adapted for that ſtation. He was deeply verſed in the Greek and Roman languages, and in their cuſtoms and antiquities. He had that kind of good nature which abſence of mind, indolence of body, and careleſſneſs of fortune, produce ; and although not over ſtrict in his own conduct, yet he took care of the morality of his ſcholars, whom he font to the university remarkably well founded in all kinds of claſſical learning, and not ill inſtructed in the ſocial duties of life. He was ſlovenly, indigent, and cheerful. He knew books much better than men ; and he knew the value of money leaſt of all. In this ſituation, and with this diſpoſition, Swift faſtened upon him as upon a prey with which he intended to regale himſelf whenever his appetite ſhould prompt him.” His Lordſhip then mentions the event of the unlucky ſermon, and adds : “ This ill-ſtarred, good-natured, improvident man, returned to Dublin, unhinged from all favour at court, and even baniſhed from the castle. But still he remained a punſter, a quibbler, a fiddler, and a wit. Not a</p></body></text></TEI>