<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:05:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Management of </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Ships</hi><hi rend="italic"> at single anchor,</hi> is the method of taking care of a ship while riding at ſingle anchor in a tide-way, by preventing her from fouling her anchor, &amp;c<hi rend="italic">.</hi> The following rules for this purpoſe, with which we have been favoured by Mr Henry Taylor@@* of North Shields, will be found of the utmoſt conſequence.</p><p>Riding in a tide-way, with a freſh-of-wind, the ſhip ſhould have what is called <hi rend="italic">a short</hi> or w<hi rend="italic">indward ſervice, s</hi>ay 45 or 50 fathoms of cable, and always ſheered to windward @@( <hi rend="smallcaps">a),</hi> not always with the helm hard down, but more or leſs ſo according to the ſtrength or weak- neſs of the tide. It is a known fact, that many ſhips ſheer their anchors home, drive on board of other ſhips, and on the ſands near which they rode, before it has been diſcovered that the anchor had been moved from the place where it was let go.</p><p>When the wind is croſs, or nearly croſs, off ſhore, or in the oppoſite direction, ſhips will always back. This is done by the mizen-topſail, aſſiſted, if needful, by the mizen-stayſail ; ſuch as have no mizen-topſail commonly uſe the main-topſail, or if it blows freſh, a top- gallant-ſail, or any ſuch ſail at the gaff.</p><p>In backing, a ſhip ſhould always wind with a taught cable, that it may be certain the anchor is drawn round. In case there is not a ſufficiency of wind for that purpoſe, the ſhip ſhould be hove apeak.</p><p>Riding with the wind afore the beam, the yards ſhould be braced forward ; if abaft the beam, they are to be braced all aback.</p><p>If the wind is ſo far aft that the ſhip will net back (which ſhould not be attempted if, when the tide eaſes, the ſhip forges ahead, and brings the buoy on the lee quarter), ſhe muſt be ſet ahead : if the wind is far aft, and blows freſh, the utmoſt care and attention is neceſsary, as ſhips riding in this ſituation often break their ſheer, and come to windward of their anchors again. It ſhould be obſerved, that when the ſhip lies in this tickliſh ſituation, the after-yards muſt be braced forward, and the fore-yards the contrary way : ſhe will lay ſafe, as the buoy can be kept on the lee quarter, or ſuppoſe the helm is aport, as long as the buoy is on the larboard quarter. With the helm thus, and the wind right aft, or neatly ſo, the ſtarboard main and fore braces ſhould be hauled in. This ſuppoſes the main braces to lead forward.</p><p>When the ſhip begins to tend to leeward, and the buoy comes on the weather-quarter, the firſt thing to be done is to brace about the fore-yard ; and when the wind comes near the beam, ſet the fore-ſtayſail, and</p><p>keep it ſtanding until it ſhakes; then brace all the yards ſharp forward, eſpecially if it is likely to blow strong.</p><p>If laying in the aforeſaid poſition, and ſhe breaks her ſheer, brace about the main-yard immediately; if ſhe recovers and brings the buoy on the lee or larboard quarter, let the main-yard be again braced about; but if ſhe come to a ſheer the other way, by bringing the buoy on the other quarter, change the helm and brace the fore-yard to.</p><p>Riding leeward tide with more cable than the windward ſervice, and expecting the ſhip will go to windward of her anchor, begin as ſoon as the tide eaſes to ſhorten in the cable. This is often hard work ; but it is neceffary to be done, otherwiſe the anchor may be fouled by the great length of cable the ſhip has to draw round ; but even if that could be done, the cable would be damaged againſt the bows or cut-water. It is to be obſerved, that when a ſhip rides windward tide the cable ſhould be cackled from the ſhort ſervice towards the anchor, as far as will prevent the bare part touching the ſhip.</p><p>When the ſhip tends to windward and muſt be ſet a- head, hoiſt the fore-ſtayſail as ſoon as it will ſtand, and when the buoy comes on the leequarter, haul down the fore-ſtayſail, brace to the fore-yard, and put the helm a-lee ; for till then the helm muſt be kept a-weather and the yards full.</p><p>When the ſhip rides leeward tide, and the wind increaſes, care ſhould be taken to give her more cable in time, otherwiſe the anchor may ſtart, and probably it will be troubleſome to get her brought up a- gain ; and this care is the more necessary when the ſhip rides in the hauſe of another ship. Previous to giving a long ſervice it is uſual to take a weather-bit, that is, a turn of the cable over the windlaſs end, ſo that in veering away the ſhip will be under commend. I he ſervice ought to be greaſed, which will prevent its chafing in the hauſe.</p><p>If the gale continues to increaſe, the topmaſts ſhould be ſtruck in time ; but the fore-yard ſhould ſeldom, if ever, be lowered down, that in cafe of parting the fore-ſail may be ready to be ſet. At ſuch times there ſhould be more on deck than the common anchor-watch, that no accident may happen from inattention or falling aſleep.</p><p>In a tide-way a second anchor ſhould never be let go but when abſolutely necessary ; for a ſhip will ſome- times ride eaſier and ſafer, eſpecially if the ſea runs high, with a very long ſcope of cable and one anchor, than with</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@[m]* </hi>Taylor's Instructions to Young Mariners Riding at Anchor in moderate Weather.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> It has been thought by ſome theoriſts, that ſhips ſhould be ſheered to leeward of their anchors ; but experience and the common practice of the beſt informed ſeamen are againſt that opinion : for it is found, that when a ſhip rides leeward tide and ſheered to windward, with the wind two or three points upon the bow, and blowing hard in the interval between the ſqualls, the ſheer will draw her towards the wind’s eye ; ſo that when the next squall comes, before ſhe be preſſed aſtream of her anchor, it is probable there will be a lull again, and the ſpring which the cable got by the ſheer will greatly eaſe it during the ſquall.</p><p>Every ſeaman knows that no ſhip without a rudder, or the helm left looſe, will wear ; they always in ſuch ſituations fly to : this proves that the wind preſſing upon the quarter and the helm alee, a ſhip will be less liable to break her ſheer than when the helm is a-weather. Beſides, if the helm is a-lee when ſhe breaks her ſheer, it will be a-weather when the wind comes on the other quarter, as it ought to be until ſhe either ſwing to leeward, or bring the buoy on the other quarter. Now if the ſhip breaks her ſheer with the helm a-weather, it throws her head to the wind ſo ſuddenly as ſcarce to give time to brace the yards about, and very probably ſhe will fall over? her anchor before the fore-ſtayſail can be got up.</p></body></text></TEI>