<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:07:02Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>for the diſtance and ſwiftneſs of the pace. Another thing to be attended to is, that the ſhooter ought not involuntarily to ſtop the motion of the arms at the moment of pulling the trigger ; for the inſtant the hand  stops in order to fire, however inconſiderable the time be, the bird gets beyond the line of aim, and the ſhot will miss it. A ſportſman ought therefore to accustom his hand while he is taking aim to follow the object. When a hare runs in a straight line from the ſhooter, he ſhould take his aim between the ears, otherwiſe he will run the hazard either of missing, or at leaſt not of killing dead, or as it is ſometimes called <hi rend="italic">clean.</hi></p><p>A fowling-piece ſhould not be fired more than 20 or 25 times without being waſhed ; a barrel when foul neither ſhoots ſo ready, nor carries the ſhot ſo far as when clean. The flint, pan, and hammer, ſhould be well wiped after each ſhot ; this contributes greatly to make the piece go off quick, but then it ſhould be done with ſuch expedition, that the barrel may be reloaded whilſt warm, for the reaſons we have before advanced. The flint ſhould be frequently changed, without waiting until it miſſes fire, before a new one is put in. Fifteen or eighteen ſhots, therefore, ſhould only be fired with the same flint ; the expence is too trifling to be regarded, and by changing it thus often much vexation will be prevented.</p><p>A gun alſo ſhould never be fired with the prime of the preceding day ; it may happen that an old priming will ſometimes go off well, but it will more frequently contract moiſture and fuze in the firing ; then the object will moſt probably be missed, and that becauſe the piece was not freſh primed.</p><p>For the information of the young ſportſman we ſhall add a few more general directions. In warm weather he ought to ſeek for game in plains and open grounds, and in cold weather he may ſearch little hills expoſed to the ſun, along hedges among heath, in stubbles, and in paſtures where there is much furze and fern. The morning is the beſt time of the day, before the dew is exhaled, and before the game has been disturbed. The colour of the ſhooters dreſs ought to be the same with that of the fields and trees ; in summer it ought to be green, in winter a dark grey. He ought to hunt as much as poſſible with the wind, not only to prevent the game from perceiving the approach of him and his dog, but alſo to enable the dog to ſcent the game at a greater diſtance.</p><p>He ſhould never be diſcouraged from hunting and ranging the same ground over and over again, eſpecially in places covered with heath, brambles, high graſs, or yoiιng coppide wood. A hare or rabbit will frequently ſuffer him to paſs ſeveral times within a few yards of its form without getting up. He ſhould be still more patient when he has marked partridges into ſuch places, for it often happens, that after the birds have been ſprung many times, they lie ſo dead that they will ſuffer him almoſt to tread upon them before they will rise. Pheaſants, quails, and woodcocks do the ſame.</p><p>He ought to look carefully about him, never paſſing a buſh or tuft of graſs without examination ; but he ought never to strike them with the muzzle of his gun for it will looſen his wadding. He who patiently beats and ranges his ground over again, without being diſ</p><p>courages, will always kill the greateſt quantity of game ; and if he is ſhooting in company, he will find game where others have passed without diſcovering any.</p><p>When he has fired he ſhould call in his dog, that he may not have the mortification to ſee game rise which he cannot ſhoot. When he has killed a bird, inſtead of being anxious about picking it up, he ought to follow the rest of the covey with his eye till he ſee them  settle.</p><p>Three ſpecies of dogs are capable of receiving the proper inſtruction, and of being trained. Theſe are the ſmooth pointer, the ſpaniel, and the rough pointer. The laſt is a dog with long curled hair, and ſeems to be a mixed breed of the water-dog and the ſpaniel. The ſmooth pointer is active and lively enough in his range, but in general is proper only for an open country.</p><p>The greateſt part of theſe dogs are afraid of water, brambles, and thickets ; but the ſpaniel and the rough pointer are eaſily taught to take the water, even in cold weather, and to range the woods and rough places as well as the plain. Greater dependence may therefore be had on theſe two laſt ſpecies of dogs than on the ſmooth pointer.</p><p>The education of a pointer may commence when he is only five or six months old. The only leſſons which he can be taught at this time are to <hi rend="italic">fetch</hi> and <hi rend="italic">carry</hi> any thing when deſired ; to come in when he runs far off, and to go behind when he returns ; uſing, in the one caſe, the words <hi rend="italic">here, come in,</hi> and in the other <hi rend="italic">back</hi> or <hi rend="italic">behind.</hi> It is alſo neceſſary at this period to accuſtom him to be tied up in the kennel or stable ; but he ought not at first to be tied too long. He ſhould be let looſe in the morning, and faſtened again in the evening. When a dog is not early accuſtomed to be chained, he diſturbs every perſon in the neighbourhood by howling. It is alſo of importance that the perſon who is to train him ſhould give him his food.</p><p>When the dog has attained the age of 10 or 12 months, he may be carried into the field to be regularly trained. At firſt he may be allowed to follow his own inclination, and to run after every animal he fees. His indiſcriminating eagerneſs will ſoon abate, and he will purſue only partridges and hares. He will ſoon become tired of following partridges in vain, and will content himſelf after having fluſhed them to follow them with his eyes. It will be more difficult to prevent him from following hares.</p><p>All young dogs are apt to <hi rend="italic">rake ;</hi> that is, to hunt with their noſes cloſe to the ground, to follow birds rather by the track than by the wind. But partridges lie much better to dogs that <hi rend="italic">wind</hi> them, than to thoſe that follow them by the track. The dog that winds the ſcent approaches the birds by degrees and without diſturbing them ; but they are immediately alarmed when they ſee a dog tracing their footſteps. When you perceive that your dog is committing this fault, call to him in an angry tone <hi rend="italic">hold up:</hi> he will then grow uneaſy and agitated, going firſt to the one side and then to the other, until the wind brings him the ſcent of the birds. After finding the <hi rend="italic">game</hi> four or five times in this way, he will take the wind of himſelf, and hunt with his noſe high. If it be difficult to correct this fault, it will be neceſſary to put the <hi rend="italic">puzzle peg</hi> upon him. This is of very ſimple conſtruction, conſisting</p></body></text></TEI>