<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Livery in <hi rend="italic">deed</hi> is thus performed. The feoffor, leſſor, or his attorney, together with the feoffee, leſſee, or his attorney, (for this may as effectually be done by deputy or attorney as by the principals themſelves in person), come to the land or to the houſe ; and there, in the preſence of witneſſes, declare the contents of the feoffment or leaſe on which livery is to be made. And then the feoffor, if it be of land, doth deliver to thc feoffee, all other perſons being out of the ground, a clod or turf, or a twig or bough there growing, with words to this effect : “ I deliver theſe to you in the name of ſeisin of all the lands and tenements contained in this deed.” But, if it be of a houſe, the feoffor must take the ring or latch of the door, the houſe being quite empty, and deliver it to the feoffee in the same form ; and then the feoffee muſt enter alone, and ſhut the door, and then open it, and let in the others. If the conveyance or feoffment be of divers lands, lying ſcattered in one and the same county, then in the feoffor’s poſſession, livery of ſeisin of any parcel, in the name of the rest, ſufficeth for all ; but if they be in ſeveral counties, there muſt be as many liveries as there are counties. For, if the title to theſe lands comes to be diſputed, there muſt be as many trials as there are counties, and the jury of one county are no judges of the notoriety of a fact in another. Beſides, anciently, this ſeisin was obliged to be delivered <hi rend="italic">coram paribus de vicineto,</hi> before the peers or freeholders of the neighbourhood, who atteſted ſuch delivery in the body or on the back of the deed ; according to the rule of the ſeodal law, <hi rend="italic">Pares debent interesse inveſliturae feudi, et non alii :</hi> for which this reason is expressly given ; becauſe the peers or vaſſals of the lord, being bound by their oath of fealty, will take care that no fraud be committed to his prejudice, which  strangers might be apt to connive at. And though afterwards the ocular atteſtation of the <hi rend="italic">pares</hi> was held unneccſſary, and livery might be made before any credible witneſſes, yet the trial, in caſe it was diſputed, (like that of all other atteſtations), was ſtill reſerved to the <hi rend="italic">pares</hi> or jury of the county. Alſo, if the lands be out on leaſe, though all lie in the same county, there  muſt be as many liveries as there are tenants : becauſe no livery can be made in this caſe, but by the conſent of the particular tenant ; and the conſent of one will not hind the rest. And in all theſe caſes it is prudent, and usual, to endorſe the livery of ſeisin on the back of the deed, ſpecifying the manner, place, and time of making it ; together with the names of the witneſſes. And thus</p><p>much for livery in deed.</p><p>Livery in <hi rend="italic">law</hi> is where the ſame is not made <hi rend="italic">on </hi>the land, but <hi rend="italic">in sight of it</hi> only ; the feoffor ſaying to the feoffee, “ I give you yonder land, enter and take poſſeſſion.” Here, if the feoffee enters during the life of the feoffor, it is a good lively, but not otherwise ; unleſs he dares not enter through fear of his life or bodily harm ; and then his continual claim; made yearly in due form of law, as near as poſſible to the lands, will ſuffice without an entry. This livery in law cannot, however, be given or received by attorney, but only by the parties themſelves.</p><p>SEIZE, in the ſea-language, is to make faſt or bind, particularly to faſten two ropes together with rope-yarn. The ſeizing of a boat is a rope tied to a ring or little chain in the fore-ſhip of the boat, by which means it is faſtened to the side of the ſhip.</p><p>SEIZURE, in commerce, an arreſt of ſome merchandiſe, moveable, or other matter, either in conſequence of ſome law or of ſome express order of the sovereign. Contraband goods, thoſe fraudulently entered, or landed without entering at all, or at wrong places, are ſubject to ſeizure. In ſeizures among us, one half goes to the informer, and the other half to the king.</p><p>SELAGO, in botany : A genus of the angioſpermia order, belonging to the didynamia claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 48th order,  Aggregatae. The calyx is quinquefid : the tube of the corolla capillary, with the limb nearly equal, and a  single ſeed. There are 22 ſpecies.</p><p>SELDEN (John), called by Grotius <hi rend="italic">the glory of England,</hi> was born at Salvington in Suſſex in 1584. He was educated at the free-ſchool at Chicheſter; whence he was sent to Hart-Hall in the univerſity of Oxford, where he ſtaid four years. In 1612, he entered himſelf in Clifford’s Inn, in order to ſtudy the law ; and about two years after removed to the Inner Temple, where he soon acquired great reputation by his learning. He had already publiſhed ſeveral of his works ; and this year wrote verſes in Latin, Greek, and Engliſh, upon Mr William Browne’s Britannia’s Paſtorals. In 1614, he publiſhed his Titles of Honour; and in 1616, his Notes on Sir John Forteſcue’s book <hi rend="italic">De Laudibus Legum Angliae.</hi> In 1618,he publiſhed his Hiſtory of Tythes ; which gave great offence to the clergy, and was animadverted upon by ſeveral writers ; and for that book he was called before the high commiſſion court, and obliged to make a public acknowledgment of his sorrow for having publiſhed it. In 1621, being sent for by the parliament, though he was not then a member of that houſe, and giving his opinion very ſtrongly in favour of their privileges in oppoſition to the court, he was committed to the cuſtody of the ſheriff of London, but was ſet at liberty after five weeks confinement. In 1623, he was choſen burgeſs for Lancaſter ; but, arnidſt all the diviſions of the nation, kept himſelf neuter, proſecuting his ſtudies with ſuch application, that though he was the next year choſen reader of Lyon’s Inn, he refilled to perform that office. In 1625, he was choſen burgeſs for Great Bedwin in Wiltſhire, to ſerve in the firſt parliament of king Charles I. in which he declared himſelf warmly againſt the duke of Buckingham ; and on his Grace’s being impeached by the Houſe of Commons, was appointed one of the managers of the articles againſt him. In 1627 and 1628, he oppoſed the court party with great vigour. The parliament being prorogued to January 20. 1629, Mr Selden retired to the earl of Kent’s houſe at Wreſt, irr Bedfordſhire, where he finiſhed his <hi rend="italic">Marmora Arundeliana.</hi> The parliament being met, he, among others, again diſtinguiſhed himſelf by his zeal againſt the court; when the king diſſolving the parliament, ordered ſeveral of the members to be brought before the King’s-Bench bar, and committed to the Tower. Among theſe was Mr Selden, who insisting on the benefit of the laws, and refuſing to make his submiſſion, was removed to the King’s Bench priſon. Being here in danger of his life on account of the plague then raging in Southwark, he petitioned the lord high treaſurer, at the end of Trinity-term, to intercede with his Majeſty that he might be removed to the Gate-Houſe, Weſtminſter, which was granted : but in Michaelmas term following, the judges objecting to the lord treaſurer’s warrant, by which he</p></body></text></TEI>