<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:07:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is under the juriſdiction and viſitation of the archdeacon of Shrewſbury or Salop, and is divided into ſeveral deanries.</p><p>The Oxford circuit includes in it this county, which sends 12 members to parliament, viz. two for the ſhire, and two for each of the following towns, Shrewſbury, Ludlow, Wenlock, and Biſhop’s Caſtle.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SHROVE-Tuesday,</hi> is the Tueſday after Quinquageſima Sunday, or the day immediately preceding the firſt of Lent ; being ſo called from the Saxon word  s<hi rend="italic">hrive,</hi> which ſignifies “ to confeſs.” Hence Shrove* Tueſday ſignifies Confeſſion-Tueſday ; on which day all the people in every pariſh throughout England (during the Romiſh times) were obliged to confeſs their ſins, one by one, to their own pariſh-prieſts, in their own pariſhchurches ; and, that this might be done the more regularly, the great bell in every pariſh was rung at ten o’clock (or perhaps ſooner), that it might be heard by all, and that they might attend, according to the custom then in uſe. And though the Romiſh religion has now given way to the Proteſtant religion, the cuſtom of ringing the great bell in our ancient pariſh-churches, at leaſt in ſome of them, ſtill remains, and obtains in and about London the name of Pancake bell ; perhaps, becauſe after the confeſſion it was cuſtomary for the ſeveral perſons to dine on pancakes or fritters. Moſt churches, indeed, have rejected that cuſtom of ringing the bell on Shrove-Tueſday ; but the uſage of dining on pancakes or fritters, and ſuch like proviſion, ſtill continues.</p><p>SHROUDS <hi rend="italic">(ſcrud</hi> Sax.), a range of large ropes extending from the maſt-heads to the right and left side of the ſhip, to ſupport the masts, and enable them to carry sail, &amp;c.</p><p>The ſhrouds as well as the ſails are denominated from the masts to which they belong. Thus they are the main, fore, and mizen ſhrouds ; the main-top-maſt, fore-top-maſt, or mizen -top-maſt ſhrouds ; and the main-top-gallant, fore-top-gallant, or mizen-top-gallant ſhrouds. The number of ſhrouds by which a mast is ſuſtained, as well as the ſize of rope of which they are formed, is always in proportion to the ſize of the mast and the weight of the sail it is intended to carry.</p><p>Bowſprit ſhrouds are thoſe which ſupport the bow- ſprit. Bumkin ſhrouds are thoſe which ſupport the bumkins. Futtock ſhrouds are ſhrouds which connect the efforts of the topmaſt ſhrouds to the lower ſhrouds. Bentinck-ſhrouds are additional ſhrouds to ſupport the maſts in heavy gales. Preventer ſhrouds are ſimilar to bentinck-ſhrouds, and are uſed in bad weather to eaſe the lower rigging. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mast</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Sail.</hi></p><p>SHRUB, fru<hi rend="italic">tex,</hi> a little, low, dwarf tree, or a woody vegetable, of a ſize leſs than a tree ; and which, inſtead of one ſingle stem, frequently from the ſame root puts forth ſeveral ſets or ſtems. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Plant</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Tree.</hi> Such are privet, phillyrea, holly, box, honey- ſuckle, &amp;c. Shrubs and trees put forth in autumn a kind of buttons, or gems, in the axis of the leaves ; theſe buttons are as ſo many little ova, which, coming to expand by the warmth of the following ſpring, open into leaves and flowers. By this, together with the height, ſome diſtinguiſh ſhrubs from s<hi rend="italic">uffrutices, </hi>or under ſhrubs, which are low buſhes, that do not put forth any of theſe buttons, as ſage, thyme, &amp;c.</p><p>The two hardſeſt ſhrubs we are poſſessed of are the ivy and box ; theſe ſtand the ſeverity of our ſharpeſt winters unhurt, while other ſhrubs periſh, and trees have their ſolid bodies ſplit and torn to pieces. In the hard winter of the year 1683, theſe two ſhrubs ſuffered no injury any where ; though the yews and hollies, which are generally ſuppoſed very hardy, were that winter in ſome places killed, and in others ſtripped of their leaves, and damaged in their bark. Furze-buſhes were found to be ſomewhat hardier than theſe, but they ſometimes periſhed, at leaſt down to the root. The broom ſeemed to occupy the next ſtep of hardineſs beyond theſe. This lived where the others died, and where even this died, the juniper ſhrubs were ſometimes found unhurt. This laſt is the only ſhrub that approaches to the hardineſs of the box and ivy, but even it does not quite come up to them ; for while they ſuffer nothing in whatever manner they are exposed, the juniper, though it bears cold well under the ſhelter of other trees, yet cannot bear the viciſſitudes of heat and cold ; inſomuch that ſome juniper ſhrubs were found half dead and half vigorous ; that side which faced the mid-day fun having periſhed by the ſucceſſive thawings and freezings of its ſap ; while that which was not expoſed to the viciſſitudes of heat had born the cold perfectly well. Such ſhrubs as are not hardy enough to defy the winter, but appear half dead in the ſpring, may often be recovered by Mr Evelyn’s method of beating their branches with a ſlender hazel-wand, to ſtrike off the withered leaves and buds, and give a free paſſage to the air to the internal parts. Where this fails, the method is to cut them down to the quick, and if no part of the trunk appears in a growing condition, they muſt be taken off down to the level of the ground. Philoſophical Tranſactions, n⁰ 165.</p><p>SHUCKFORD (Samuel), curate of Shelthon in Norfolk, prebendary of Canterbury, and chaplain in ordinary to the king, was a learned Engliſhman. His manners were thoſe of a philoſopher,  uncorrupted by the manners of the world. He wrote a hiſtory of the world, ſacred and profane, to ſerve as an introduction to Prideaux, in 3 vols 8vo. It is heavily written, but diſplays a great deal of erudition. His death, which happened in 1756, prevented him from carrying it down to the year 747 before Chriſt, where Prideaux begins. He wrote alſo a treatiſe on the Creation and Fall of Man, to ſerve as a ſupplement to the preface to his hiſtory.</p><p>SHUTTLE, in the manufactures, an inſtrument uſed by the weavers, which guides the thread it contains, either of woollen, ſilk, flax, or other matter, ſo as to make it form the woofs of fluffs, cloths, linens, ribbands, &amp;c. by throwing the ſhuttle alternately from left to right, and from right to left, acroſs between the threads of the warp, which are ſtretched out lengthwiſe on the loom.</p><p>In the middle of the ſhuttle is a kind of cavity, called the <hi rend="italic">eye</hi> or <hi rend="italic">chamber</hi> of the ſhuttle ; wherein is incloſed the ſpoul, which is a part of the thread deſtined for the woof ; and this is wound on a little tube of paper, ruſh, or other matter.</p><p>The ribband-weaver’s ſhuttle is very different from that of moſt other weavers, though it serves for the ſame purpoſe : it is of box, six or ſeven inches long, one broad, and as much deep ; ſhod with iron at both</p></body></text></TEI>