<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ther we consider the degree of fatneſs, or their natural propenſity to a ſtate of fatneſs, even at as early age, the improved breed of Leiceſterſhire ſheep appear with many superior advantages.</p><p>The degree of fatneſs to which the individuals of this breed are capable of being raised, will perhaps appear incredible to thoſe who have not had an opportunity of being convinced by their own obſervation. “ I have ſeen wedders (ſays Mr Marſhall) of only two ſhear (two to three years old) ſo loaded with fat as to be ſcarcely  able to make a run ; and whoſe fat lay ſo much without the bone, it ſeemed ready to be ſhaken from the ribs on the ſmalleſt agitation.</p><p>" It is common for the ſheep of this breed to have ſuch a projection of fat upon the ribs, immediately behind the shoulder, that it may be eaſily gathered up in the hand, as the flank of a fat bullock. Hence it has gained, in technical language, the name of the fore-flank { a point which a modern breeder never fails to touch in judging of the quality of this breed of ſheep.</p><p>“ What is, perhaps, ſtill more extraordinary, it is not rare for the rams, at leaſt of this breed, to be ‘ cracked on the back ; that is, to be cloven along the top of the chine, in the manner fat ſheep generally are upon the rump. This mark is considered as an evidence of the beſt blood.</p><p>" Extraordinary, however, as are theſe appearances while the animals are living, the facts are ſtill more ſtriking after they arc ſlaughtered. At Litchfield, in February 1785, I law a fore quarter of mutton, fatted by Mr Rrincep of Croxall, and which meaſured upon the ribs four inches of fat. It muſt be acknowledged, however, that the Leiceſterſhire breed do not produce ſo much wool as most other long-woolled ſheep.”</p><p>As the practice of letting rams by the ſeason is now become profitable, it may be uſeful to mention the method of rearing them.</p><p>“ The principal ram-breeders save annually twenty, thirty, or perhaps forty ram lambs ; caſtration being ſeldom applied, in the firſt inſtance, to the produce of a valuable ram, for in the choice of theſe lambs they are led more by blood, or parentage, than by form ; on which, at an early age, little dependence can be placed. Their treatment from the time they are weaned, in July or Auguſt, until the time of ſhearing, the firſt week in June, consiſts in giving them every indulgence of keep, in order to puſh them forward for the ſhow ; it being the common practice to let ſuch as are fit to be let the firſt ſeason, while they are yet yearlings—provincially ‘ ſharhogs.’</p><p>“ Their firſt paſture, after weaning, is pretty generally,</p><p>I believe, clover that has been mown early, and has got a second time into head ; the heads of clover being conſidered as a moſt forcing food of ſheep. After this goes off, turnips, cabbages, colewort, with hay, and (report ſays) with corn. But the uſe of this, the breeders ſeverally deny, though collectively they may be liable to the charge.</p><p>“ Be this as it may, ſomething conſiderable depends on the art of making up, not lambs only, but rams of all ages. Fat, like charity, covers a multitude of faults ; and beſides, is the beſt evidence of their fatting quality wſhich their owners can produce (i. e their natural propenſity to a ſtate of fatneſs), while in the fatneſs of the</p><p>ſharhogs is ſeen theſe degree of inclination to fat at an early age.</p><p>“ Fatting quality being the one thing needful in grazing ſtock, and being found, in ſome conſiderable degree at leaſt, to be hereditary, the ſattest rams are of courte the beſt ; though other attachments, well or ill placed, as to form or faſhionable points, will perhaps, have equal or greater weight in the minds of ſome men, even in this enlightened age. Such ſhearlings as will not make up ſufficiently as to form and fatneſs, are either kept on to another year to give them a fair chance, or are caſtrated, or butchered while ſharhogs.”</p><p>From the firſt letting, about 40 years ago, to the year 1780, the prices kept gradually rising from fifteen ſhillings to a guinea, and from one to ten. In 1780 Mr Bakewell let ſeveral at ten guineas each ; and, what is rather inexplicable, Mr Parkinſon of Quarndon let one the ſame year for twenty-five guineas; a price which then aſtoniſhed the whole country.</p><p>From that time to 1786 Mr Bakewell’s ſtock roſe rapidly from ten to a hundred guineas ; and that year he let two thirds of one ram (reſerving one third of the uſual number of ewes to himſelf) to two principal breeders, for a hundred guineas each, the entire ſervices of the ram being rated at three hundred guineas ! Mr Bakewell making that year, by letting twenty rams only, more than a thouſand pounds !</p><p>Since that time the prices have been ſtill riſing. Four hundred guineas have been repeatedly given. Mr Bake- well, this year (1789) makes, ſays Mr Marſhall, twelve hundred guineas by three rams (brothers, we believe); two thouſand of ſeven ; and of his whole letting, full three thouſand guineas !</p><p>Beſide this extraordinary ſum made by Mr Bakewell, there are six or ſeven other breeders who make from five hundred to a thouſand guineas each. The whole amount of monies produced that year in the Midland Counties, by letting rams of the modern breed for one ſeason only, is eſtimated, by thoſe who are adequate to the ſubject, at the almoſt incredible ſum of ten thouſand pounds.</p><p>Rams previous to the ſeaſon are reduced from the cumbrous fat ſtate in which they are ſhown. The uſual time of ſending them out is the middle of September. They are conveyed in carriages of two wheels with ſprings, or hung in flings, 20 or 30 miles a-day, ſometimes to the diſtance of 200 or 300 miles. They are not turned loose among the ewes, but kept apart in a ſmall incloſure, where a couple of ewes only are admitted at once. When the ſeaſon is over every care is taken to make the rams look as fat and handſome as poſſible.</p><p>In the choice of ewes the breeder is led by the ſame criterions as in the choice of rams. Breed is the firſt object of conſideration. Excellency, in any ſpecies or variety of live-ſtock, cannot be attained with any degree of certainty, let the male be ever ſo excellent, unleſs the females employed likewiſe inherit a large proportion of the genuine blood, be the ſpecies or variety what it may. Hence no prudent naan ventures to give the higher prices for the Diſhley rams, unless his ewes are deeply tinctured with the Diſhley blood. Next to breed is fleſh, fat, form, and wool.</p><p>After the lambs are weaned, the ewes are kept in common feeding places, without any alteration of paſ-</p></body></text></TEI>