<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:07:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>heads are concealed ; and in this way they will ſometimes ſuffer themſelves to be killed with a ſtick. They love low and moiſt places, and haunt the edges of thoſe pools which are found in woods, as well as the high grass of marſhes that are near at hand ; and above all, places where there are clumps of alders.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Grouſe,</hi> or muir-game, are found in Wales, in the northern counties of England, and in great abundance in Scotland. They chiefly inhabit thoſe mountains and muirs which are covered with heath, and ſeldom deſcend to the low grounds. They fly in companies of four or five braces, and love to frequent moſſy places, particularly in the middle of the day or when the weather is warm. In purſuing this game, when the pointer ſets, and the ſportſman perceives the birds running with their heads erect, he muſt run after them as fall as he can, in the hope that he may get near enough to  ſhoot when they rise upon the wing ; for he may be pretty certain they will not lie well that day. As theſe birds are apt to grow ſoon putrid, they ought to be drawn carefully the inſtant they are ſhot and stuffed with any heath, and if the feathers happen to be wetted they muſt be wiped dry.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">woodcock</hi> is a bird of paſſage ; it commonly arrives about the end of October, and remains until the middle of March. Woodcocks are fatteſt in December and January, but from the end of February they are lean. At their arrival they drop anywhere, but afterwards take up their residence in copſes of nine or ten years growth. They ſeldom, however, ſtay in one place longer than 12 or 15 days. During the day they remain in thoſe parts of the woods where there are void ſpaces or glades, picking up earth-worms and grubs from the fallen leaves. In the evening they go to drink and waſh their bills at pools and ſprings, after which they repair to the open fields and meadows for the night. It is remarkable, that when a woodcock ſprings from a wood to go into the open country, he always endeavours to find ſome glade or opening, which he follows to the boundaries of the wood. At his return he purſues the ſame path a good way, and then turns to the right or left oppoſite to ſome glade, in order to drop into a thick part of the wood, where he may be ſheltered from the wind. He may therefore be watched with advantage in theſe narrow passes and little alleys on the edges of woods which lead to a pool or ſpring, or he may be watched in the dusk of the evening near the pools which he frequents.</p><p>The snip<hi rend="italic">e</hi> is a bird of paſſage as well as the woodcock. This bird is ſcarcely worth ſhooting till the froſt commences. In the month of November they begin to grow fat. Snipes, like woodcocks, frequent ſprings, bogs, and marſhy places, and generally fly against the wind. The ſlant and croſs ſhots are rather difficult, as the birds are ſmall and fly very quickly. The ſportſman ought to look for them in the direction of the wind ; becauſe then they will fly towards him, and preſent a fairer mark.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">wild duck</hi> is alſo a bird of paſſage, and arrives " here in great flocks from the northern countries in the beginning of winter. Still, however, a great many remain in our marſhes and fens during the whole year,</p><p>and breed.</p><p>The wild duck differs little in plumage from the tame duck, but is eaſily diſtinguiſhed by its ſize, which is leſs ; by the neck, which is more ſlender ; by the foot,</p><p>which is ſmaller ; by the nails, which are more black ; and above all, by the web of the foot, which is much finer and ſofter to the touch.</p><p>In tire ſummer ſeaſon, when it is known that a team of young ducks are in a particular piece of water, and juſt beginning to fly, the ſportſman is ſure to find them early in the morning dabbling at the edges of the pool, and amongſt the long graſs, and then he may get very near to them : it is uſual alſo to find them in thoſe places at noon.</p><p>In the beginning of autumn almoſt every pool is frequented by teams of wild ducks, which remain there during the day, concealed in the ruſhes. If theſe pools are of ſmall extent, two ſhooters, by going one on each ſide, making a noiſe and throwing ſtones into the ruſhes, will make them fly up ; and they will in this way frequently get ſhots, eſpecially if the pool is not broad, and contracts at one end. But the ſureſt and most ſucceſsful way, is to launch a ſmall boat or trow on the pool, and to traverſe the ruſhes by the openings which are found ; at the same time making as little noiſe as poſſible. In this manner the ducks will ſuffer the ſportſmen to come ſufficiently near them to ſhoot flying ; and it often happens that the ducks, after having flown up, only make a circuit, return in a little time, and again alight upon the pool. Then the ſportſmen endeavour a second time to come near them. If ſeveral ſhooters are in company, they ſhould divide, two ſhould go in the boat, whilſt the others ſpread themſelves about the edge of the pool, in order to ſhoot the ducks in their flight. In pools which will not admit a trow, water-ſpaniels are abſolutely neceſſary for this ſport.</p><p>In winter they may be found on the margins of little pools ; and when pools and rivers are frozen up, they muſt be watched for in places where there are ſprings and waters which do not freeze. The ſport is then much more certain, becauſe the ducks are confined to theſe places in order to procure aquatic herbs, which are almoſt their only food at this period.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SHOP-lifters,</hi> are thoſe that steal goods privately out of ſhops ; which, being to the value of 5s. though no perſon be in the ſhop, is felony without the benefit of clergy by the 10 and I 1 W. III. c. 23.</p><p>SHORE, a place waſhed by the ſea, or by ſome large river.</p><p>Count Marſigli divides the ſea-ſhore into three portions : the firſt of which is that track of land which the ſea juſt reaches in ſtorms and high tides, but which it never covers ; the second part of the ſhore is that which is covered in high tides and ſtorms, but is dry at other times ; and the third is the deſcent from this, which is always covered with water.</p><p>The firſt part is only a continuation of the continent, and ſuffers no alteration from the neighbourhood of the ſea, except that it is rendered fit for the growth of ſome plants, and wholly unfit for that of others, by the ſaline steams and impregnations : and it is ſcarce to be conceived by any, but thoſe who have obſerved it, how far on land the effects of the ſea reach, ſo as to make the earth proper for plants which will not grow without this influence ; there being ſeveral plants frequently found on high hills and dry places, at three, four, and more miles from the ſea, which yet would not grow unleſs in the neighbourhood of it, nor will ever be found elſewhere.</p></body></text></TEI>