<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to render women learned ; yet ſurely it is neceſſary they ſhould be raiſed above ignorance. Such a general tincture of the most useful ſciences as may ſerve to free the mind from vulgar prejudices, and give it a reliſh for the rational exerciſe of its powers, might very juſtly enter into a plan of female erudition. That ſex might be taught to turn the courſe of their reflections into a proper and advantageous channel, without any danger of rendering them too elevated for the feminine duties of life. In a word, they ought to be conſidered as deſigned by Providence for uſe as well as ſhow, and trained up, not only as women, but as rational creatures.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sex</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Bees.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bee.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sex</hi><hi rend="italic"> of Plants.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany,</hi> p. 448. SEXAGENARY, ſomething relating to the number ſixty : thus ſexagenary or ſexageſimal arithmetic is a method of computation proceeding by ſixties ; ſuch is that uſed in the diviſion of a degree into ſixty minutes, of the minute into ſixty ſeconds, of the ſecond into ſixty thirds, &amp;c. Alſo ſexagenary tables are tables of proportional parts, ſhowing the product of two ſexagenaries that are to be multiplied, or the quotient of the two that are to be divided.</p><p>SEXAGESIMA, the second Sunday before Lent, or the next to Shrove-Sunday, ſo called as being about the 60th day before Eaſter.</p><p>SEXAGESIMALS, or  S<hi rend="italic smallcaps">exagesimal</hi> <hi rend="italic">Fractions,</hi> fractions whoſe denominators proceed in a ſexagecuple ratio ; that is, a prime, or the firſt minute, <hi rend="italic">—</hi> a ſecond = 1/3600; a third = 1/216000. Anciently, there were no other than ſexageſimals uſed in aſtronomy ; and they are ſtill retained in many caſes, though decimal arithmetic begins to grow in uſe now in aſtronomical calculations. In theſe fractions, which ſome call a<hi rend="italic">ſtronomicαl fractions,</hi> the denominator being always 60, or a multiple thereof, is uſually omitted, and the numerator only written down : thus, 4⁰, 59', 32", 50'", 16"", is to be read, 4 degrees, 59 minutes, 32 ſeconds, 50 thirds, 16 fourths, &amp;c.</p><p>SEXTANS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sextant,</hi> a ſixth part of certain things. The Romans having divided their <hi rend="italic">as</hi> into 12 ounces or uncia, the ſixth part of that, or two ounces, was the ſextans.—<hi rend="italic">Sextans</hi> was alſo a meaſure which contained two ounces of liquor, or two cyathi.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sextans,</hi> in astronomy, a conſtellation of the ſouthern hemiſphere, made by Hevelius out of unformed  stars. In Hevelius’s catalogue it contains 11, but in the Britannic catalogue 41 ſtars.</p><p>SEXTANT, in mathematics, denotes the ſixth part of a circle, or an arch comprehending 60 degrees.</p><p>The word <hi rend="italic">ſextant</hi> is more particularly uſed for an aſtronomical inſtrument made like a quadrant, excepting that its limb only comprehends 60 degrees. The uſe and application of the ſextant is the same with that of the quadrant. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Quadrant</hi>; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Navigation, </hi>P∙ 737, &amp;c.</p><p>SEXTILE, <hi rend="italic">ſexiills,</hi> the poſition or aſpect of two planets when at 60 degrees diſtance, or at the diſtance of two ſigns from one another. It is marked thus (*). See <hi rend="smallcaps">Aspect.</hi></p><p>SEXTIUS (Quintus), a Pythagorean philoſopher, flouriſhed in the time of Auguſtus. He ſeemed formed to rise in the republic; but he ſhrunk from civil honours, and declined accepting the rank of ſenator when it was offered him by Julius Cæsar, that he might have time to apply to philoſophy. It appears that he wiſh. ed to eſtabliſh a ſchool at Rome, and that his tenets, though chiefly drawn from the doctrines of Pythagoras, in ſome particulars reſembled thoſe of the Stoics.</p><p>He ſoon found himſelf involved in many difficulties. His laws were tinctured with great ſeverity ; and in an early period of his eſtabliſhment, he found his mind ſo haraſſed, and the harſhneſs of the doctrines which he wiſhed to eſtabliſh ſo repulſive to his feelings, that he had nearly worked himſelf up to ſuch an height of deſperation as to reſolve on putting a period to his exiſtence.</p><p> Of the ſchool of Sextius were Fabianus, Sotion, Flavianus, Craſſitius, and Celſus. Of his works only a few fragments remain ; and whether any of them formed a part of the work which Seneca admired ſo much, cannot now be determined. Some of his maxims are valuable. He recommended an examination of the actions of the day to his ſcholars when they retired to rest ; he taught, that the road to Heaven (ad astra) was by frugality, temperance, and fortitude. He uſed to recommend holding a looking-glaſs before perſons diſordered with paſſion. He enjoined his scholars to abstain from animal food.</p><p>SEXTON, a church-officer, thus called by corruption of the Latin <hi rend="italic">ſacrista,</hi> or Saxon segerst<hi rend="italic">one,</hi> which denotes the same. His office is to take care of the veſſels, veſtments, &amp;c. belonging to the church ; and to attend the miniſter, church-warden, &amp;c. at church. He is uſually choſen by the parſon only. Sextons, as well as parish-clerks, are regarded by the common law as perſons who have freehold in their offices ; and, therefore, though they may be puniſhed, yet they cannot be deprived, by eccleſiaſtical censures.</p><p>The office of ſexton in the pope’s chapel is appropriated to the order of the hermits of St Augustine. He is generally a biſhop, though ſometimes the pope only gives a biſhopric, <hi rend="italic">in partibus,</hi> to him on whom he confers the poſt. He takes the title of <hi rend="italic">Preβa oſ the Pope's Sacristy,</hi> and has the keeping the veſſels of gold and ſilver, the relics, &amp;c. When the pope says mass, the ſexton always taſtes the bread and wine firſt. If it be in private he fays mass, his holineſs, of two wafers, gives him one to eat ; and, if in public, the cardinal, who aſſiſts the pope in quality of deacon, of three wafers, gives him two to eat. When the pope is desperately sick, he adminiſters to him the ſacrament of extreme unction, &amp;c. and enters the conclave in quality of firſt conclaviſt.</p><p>The office of a ſexton in Sweden is ſomewhat Angular. During M. Outhier’s ſtay at Stockholm in 1736 he viſited the church of St Clara, and during divine ſervice he obſerved a ſexton going about with a long rod, waking thoſe perſons who had fallen aſleep.</p><p>SEXTUPLE, in muſic, denotes a mixed fort of triple, which is beaten in double time.</p><p>SEXTUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Empiricus,</hi> a famous Pyrrhonian philoſopher, lived in the ſecond century, under the reign of Antoninus the Debonair. He was a physician of the ſect of the Empirics, and is Paid to have been one of the preceptors of Antoninus the philoſopher. There are ſtill extant his Pyrrhonian Inſtitutions, and a large work againſt the mathematicians, &amp;c. The beſt edition of Sextus Empiricus is that of Fabricius in Greek and Latin, printed at Leipſicin 1718, folio.</p></body></text></TEI>