<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:06:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">scuppers,</hi> or leaden tubes, that carry the water off from the
                decks, are then placed in holes cut through the ſhip’s ſides ; and the <hi
                    rend="italic">ſtandards</hi> repreſented in the <hi rend="smallcaps">Midship
                    Frame,</hi> Plate CCCXIV. bolted to the beams and ſides above the decks to which
                they belong. The poop lanthorns are laſt fixed upon their cranes over the stern, and
                the <hi rend="italic">bilge-ways</hi> or <hi rend="italic">cradles</hi> placed under
                the bottom to conduct the ſhip ſteadily into the water whilſt launching.</p>
            <p>As the various pieces which have been mentioned above are explained at large in their
                proper places, it is therefore ſuperfluous to enter into a more particular
                deſcription of them here.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> VII, <hi rend="italic">Of Improvements in the Masts
                    and Rudder.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Since</hi> the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Mast</hi> was
                printed, an account of a method for reſtoring maſts of ſhips when wounded, or
                otherwiſe injured, in an eaſy, cheap, and expeditious manner, by Captain Edward
                Pakenham of the royal navy, has been publiſhed in the tenth volume of the
                Tranſactions of the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, &amp;c. Captain Pakenham
                introduces his invention with the following obſervations:@@</p>
            <p>“ Among the various accidents which ſhips are liable to at ſea, none call more for
                the attention and exertion of the officer than the ſpeedy refitting of the maſts ;
                and having obſerved, in the courſe of laſt war, the very great deſtruction made
                among the lower maſts of our ſhips from the enemy’s mode of fighting, as well as the
                very great expence and delay in refitting a fleet after an action, particularly
                acroſs the Atlantic—a very ſimple expedient has ſuggeſted itſelf to me as a reſource
                in part ; which appears ſo very ſpeedy and ſecure, that the capacity of the meaneſt
                ſailor will at once conceive it. I therefore think it my duty to ſtate my ideas of
                the advantages likely to reſult from it ; and I ſhall feel myſelf exceedingly happy
                ſhould they in anywiſe contribute to remedy the evil.</p>
            <p>“ My plan, therefore, is, to have the heels of all lower maſts ſo formed as to become
                the heads : but it is not the intention of the above plan to have the ſmalleſt
                alteration made in the heels of the preſent lower maſts ; for as all line-of-battle
                ſhips maſts are nine inches in diameter larger at the heel than at the head, it will
                follow, that by letting in the treſſel-trees to their proper depth, the maſt will
                form its own cheeks or hounds ; and I flatter myſelf the following advantages will
                reſult from the above alteration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I must beg to obſerve, that all line-of-battle ſhips bury one-third of their
                lower maſts, particularly three-deckers ; it therefore follows, that if the wounds
                are in the upper third, by turning the maſt ſo as to make the heel the head, it will
                be as good as new ; for, in eight actions I was preſent in laſt war, I made the
                following obſervations:</p>
            <p>“ That in the ſaid actions fifty-eight lower maſts were wounded, and obliged to be
                ſhifted, thirty-two of which had their wounds in the upper third, and of courſe the
                ſhips detained until new maſts were made. And when it is conſidered that a lower
                maſt for a 90 or 74 ſtands government in a ſum not leſs, I am informed, than 2000 l.
                to 2300 l. the advantages acroſs the Atlantic reſulting from the aforeſaid plan will
                be particularly obvious ; not to mention the probability of there being no fit ſpars
                in the country, which was the caſe in</p>
            <p>the inſtances of the Iſis and Princeſs Royal; and as I was one of the lieutenants of
                the Iſis at that time, I am more particular in the circumſtance of that, ſhip. The
                Iſis had both her lower maſts wounded above the cathar pins in her action with the
                Cæſar, a French 74 ; and as there were no ſpars at New York, the Iſis was detained
                five weeks at that place.— Now, if her maſts had been fitted on the plan I have
                propoſed, I am confident ſhe would have been ready for ſea in 48 hours ; and as a
                further proof, I beg leave to add, that the whole fleet, on the glorious 12th of
                April, had not the leaſt accident of any conſequence except what befel their lower
                maſts, which detained them between eight and ten weeks at Jamaica.</p>
            <p>“ The delay of a ſhip while a new maſt is making, and probably the fleet being
                detained for want of that ſhip, which frequently occurred in the courſe of laſt war,
                the taking of ſhipwrights from other work, with a variety of inconveniences not
                neceſſary to mention here, muſt be obvious to every officer that has made the
                ſmalleſt obſervations on ſea actions.</p>
            <p>“ You will further obſerve, that this ſubſtſtute is formed on the most ſimple
                principle, fitted to the meaneſt capacity, and calculated to benefit all ſhips, from
                a firſt-rate down to the ſmalleſt merchantman, in caſes of an accident by ſhot, a
                ſpring, a rottenneſs, particularly as theſe accidents generally happen in the upper
                third of the maſt and above the cheeks.</p>
            <p>“ It might probably be objected, that a difficulty and ſome danger might ariſe from
                the wounded part of the maſt being below ; but this will at once be obviated, when
                it is remembered, that as the wounded part is below the wedges, it may with eaſe be
                both fiſhed, caſed, and ſecured, to any ſize or degree you pleaſe, with the addition
                of its being wedged on each deck.”</p>
            <p>Fig. 41. repreſents a maſt of a firſt-rate in its proper ſtate, the figures
                repreſenting its thickneſs at the different divisions.</p>
            <p>Fig. 42. the ſame maſt inverted, the heel forming the head, and the tressel-trees let
                into their proper depth, the additional thickneſs of the maſt forming its own
                cheeks.</p>
            <p>Fig. 43. the propoſed maſt, the figures repreſenting the thickneſs of the maſt in the
                propoſed alterations ; <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> the heel made ſquare ; <hi
                    rend="italic">b,</hi> the letting in of the treſſel- trees ; <hi rend="italic"
                    >c,</hi> the third proportion of thickneſs continued up to where the fourth is
                in the preſent maſt, or at leaſt ſome little diſtance above the lower part of the
                cheeks, which is always looked upon as the weakest part of the maſt ; and by its
                being ſo proportioned, the maſt, when turned, will be nearly as ſtrong in the
                partners as before.</p>
            <p>As the expence of a maſt is much greater than is generally imagined, it is therefore
                thought proper to ſubjoin the following ſtatement of the ſeveral articles uſed in
                making a 74 gun ſhip’s mainmaſt.@@</p>
            <table cols="5">
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2"> </cell>
                    <cell cols="3"><hi rend="italic">Value.</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">Fishes for a spindle, 21 inches, 2 nails of two maſts,</cell>
                    <cell>L. 101 </cell>
                    <cell> 3</cell>
                    <cell> 11</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">Two side fiſhes, 22 inches, 2 ditto, </cell>
                    <cell>133</cell>
                    <cell> 10</cell>
                    <cell> 9</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">Fore and aft fiſhes, 22 inches, 2 nails of one maſt,</cell>
                    <cell>66</cell>
                    <cell> 13</cell>
                    <cell> 10</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Fish</cell>
                    <cell>21½ inches, 1 nail of half a maſt,</cell>
                    <cell> 29</cell>
                    <cell> 8</cell>
                    <cell> 5</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Iron</cell>
                    <cell>On the fore part. 3 qrs 19 lbs</cell>
                    <cell> 1</cell>
                    <cell> 5</cell>
                    <cell> 9</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">Aries load baulk, 2 loads 22 feet,</cell>
                    <cell> 12</cell>
                    <cell> 2</cell>
                    <cell> 5</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Carried over </cell>
                    <cell>L. 344</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell> 1</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>@@@[mu] Page 209.</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Papers on Naval Architecture, Part 2.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
