<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of literature, he reſolved to devote a certain number of hours every day to his ſtudies ; and thereby improved himſelf to the degree of learning he afterwards attained. Though poſſeſſed of a good eſtate, he did not abandon himſelf to pleaſure and indolence, but entered a volunteer in the ſecond Dutch war ; and accordingly was in that famous naval engagement where the duke of York commanded as admiral : on which occaſion his lordſhip behaved ſo gallantly, that he was appointed commander of the Royal Catharine. He afterward made a campaign in the French ſervice under M. de Turenne. As Tangier was in danger of being taken by the Moors, he offered to head the forces which were ſent to defend it ; and accordingly was appointed to command them. He was then earl of Mulgrave, and one of the lords of the bed-chamber to king Charles II. The Moors retired on the approach of his majeſty’s forces ; and the reſult of the expedition was the blowing up of Tangier. He continued in ſeveral great poſts during the ſhort reign of king James II. till that unfortunate prince was dethroned. Lord Mulgrave, though he paid his reſpects to king William before he was advanced to the throne, yet did not accept of any poſt in the government till ſome years after. In the ſixth year of William and Mary he was created marquis of Normanby in the county of Lincoln. He was one of the moſt active and zealous oppoſers of the bill which took away Sir John Fenwick’s life ; and exerted the utmoſt vigour in carrying through the Treaſon Bill, and the bill for Triennial Parliaments. He enjoyed ſome conſiderable poſts under king William, and enjoyed much of his favour and confidence. In 1702 he was ſworn lord privy-ſeal ; and in the ſame year was appointed one of the commiſſioners to treat of an union between England and Scotland. In 1703 he was created duke of Normanby, and ſoon after duke of Buckinghamſhire. In 1711 he was made ſteward of her majeſty’s houſehold, and preſident of the council. During queen Anne’s reign he was but once out of employment ; and then he voluntarily reſigned, being attached to what were called the <hi rend="italic">Tory principles.</hi> Her majeſty offered to make him lord-chancellor ; but he declined the office. He was inſtrumental in the change of the miniſtry in 1710. A circumſtance that reflects the higheſt honour on him is, the vigour with which he acted in favour of the unhappy Catalans, who afterward were ſo inhumanly ſacrificed. He was furvived by only one legitimate son (who died at Rome in 1735) ; but left ſeveral natural children. His worst enemies allow that he lived on very good terms with his laſt wife, natural daughter to king James II. the late ducheſs of Buckingham, a lady who always behaved with a dignity suitable to the daughter of a king. He died in 1721. He was admired by the poets of his age ; by Dryden, Prior, and Garth. His Eſſay on Poetry was applauded by Addiſon, and his Rehearſal is ſtill read with pleaſure. His writings were ſplendidly printed in 1723, in two volumes 4t0 ; and have ſince been reprinted in 1729, in two vols 8vo. The firſt contains his poems on various ſubjects : the ſecond, his proſe works ; which conſiſt of hiſtorical memoirs, ſpeeches in parliament, characters, dialogues, critical obſervations, eſſays, and letters. It may be proper to obſerve, that the edition of 1729 is eaſtrated ; ſome particulars relating to the revolution in that of 1723 having given offence.</p><p>SHEFFIELDIA, in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the class of pentandria, and to the order of monogynia. The corolla is bell-ſhaped ; the filaments are 10, of which every ſecond is barren. The capſule consists of one cell, which has four valves. There is only one ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">repens.</hi></p><p>SHEIK, in the oriental cuſtoms, the perſon who has the care of the moſques in Egypt ; his duty is the ſame as that of the imams at Conſtantinople. There are more or fewer of theſe to every moſque, according to its ſize or revenue. One of theſe is head over the rest, and anſwers to a pariſh-prieſt with us ; and has under him, in large moſques, the readers, and people who cry out to go to prayers ; but in ſmall moſques the ſheik is obliged to do all this himſelf. In ſuch it is their buſineſs to open the moſque, to cry to prayers, and to begin their ſhort devotions at the head of the congregation, who ſtand rank and file in great order, and make all their motions together. Every Friday the ſheik makes an harangue to his congregation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SHEIK-Bellet,</hi> the name of an officer in the Oriental nations. In Egypt the ſheik-bellet is the head of a city, and is appointed by the pacha. The buſineſs of this officer is to take care that no innovations be made which may be prejudicial to the Porte, and that they ſend no orders which may hurt the liberties of the people. But all his authority depends on his credit and intereſt, not his office : for the government of Egypt is of ſuch a kind, that often the people of the leaſt power by their poſts have the greateſt influence ; and a caia of the janizaries or Arabs, and ſometimes one of their meaneſt officers, an oda-baſha, finds means, by his parts and abilities, to govern all things.</p><p>SHEILDS. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Shields.</hi></p><p>SHEKEL, the name of a weight and coin current among the ancient Jews. Dr Arbuthnot makes the weight of the ſhekel equal to 9 pennyweights 2<hi rend="superscript">4</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">7</hi> grains Troy weight ; and the value equal to 2 s. 3<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">8</hi>d. Sterling. The golden ſhekel was worth L. 1 : 16 : 6.</p><p>SHELDRAKE, in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anas.</hi></p><p>SHELF, among miners, the ſame with what they otherwiſe call fast <hi rend="italic">ground</hi> or fast <hi rend="italic">country ;</hi> being that part of the internal ſtructure of the earth which they find lying even and in an orderly manner, and evidently retaining its primitive form and ſituation.</p><p>SHELL, in natural hiſtory, a hard, and, as it were, ſtony covering, with which certain animals are defended, and thence called sh<hi rend="italic">ell-fish.</hi></p><p>The Angular regularity, beauty, and delicacy in the ſtructure of the ſhells of animals, and the variety and brilliancy in the colouring of many of them, at the ſame time that they ſtrike the attention of the moſt incurious obſervers, have at all times excited philoſophers to inquire into and detect, if poſſible, the cauſes and manner of their formation. But the attempts of naturaliſts, ancient and modern, to diſcover this proceſs, have conſtantly proved unſucceſsful. M. de Reaumur hitherto appears alone to have given a plauſible account, at leaſt, of the formation of the ſhell of the garden-ſnail in particular, founded on a courſe of very ingenious experiments, related in the Paris Memoirs @@*. He there endeavours to ſhow, that this ſubſtance is produced merely by the perſpirable matter of the animal condenſing and afterwards hardening on its ſurface, and accordingly taking the figure of its body, which has performed the office of a mould to it ; in ſhort, that the ſhell of a ſnail, and, as he ſuppoſed, of all other animals poſe</p><p>@@@[m]* See Mem. de l'Acad. annee 1709. p. 475. Edit de Hollande, in 12mo.</p></body></text></TEI>