<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>It has been much diſputed whether theſe games were held every hundred, or every hundred and ten years. Valerius Antius, Varro, and Livy, are quoted in ſupport of the former opinion: In favour of the latter may be produced the quindecemviral regiſters, the edicts of Auguſtus, and the words of Horace in the Secular poem,</p><p><hi rend="italic">Catus undenos decies per annos.</hi></p><p>It was a general belief, that the girls who bore a part in the ſong ſhould be ſooneſt married; and that the children who did not dance and fing at the coming of Apollo, ſhould die unmarried, and at an early period of life.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Secular</hi><hi rend="italic"> Poem,</hi> a poem ſung or rehearſed at the ſecular games; of which kind we have a very fine piece among the works of Horace, being a ſapphic ode at the end of his epodes.</p><p>SECULLARIZATION, the act of converting a regular perſon, place, or benefice, into a ſecular one. Almoſt all the cathedral churches were anciently regular, that is, the canons were to be religious; but they have been ſince ſecularized. For the ſecularization of a regular church, there is required the authority of the pope, that of the prince, the biſhop of the place, the patron, and even the confient of the pople. Religious that want to be releaſed from their vow, obtain briefs of ſecularization from the pope.</p><p>SECUNDINES, in anatomy, the ſeveral coats or membranes wherein the foetus is wrapped up in the mother’s womb; as the chorion and amnios, with the placenta, &amp;c.</p><p>SECUNDUS (Joannes Nicolaius), an elegant writer of Latin poetry, was born at the Hague in the year 1511. His deſcent was from an ancient and honourable family in the Netherlands; and his father Nicolaus Everardus, who was born in the neighbourhood of Middleburg, ſeems to have been high in the favour of the emperor Charles V. as he was employed by that monarch in ſeveral ſtations of conſiderable importance. We find him firſt a member of the grand parliament or council of Mechelen, afterwards preſident of the ſtates of Holland and Zealand at the Hague, and laſtly holding a ſimilar office at Mechelen, where he died, Auguſt 5. 1532, aged 70.</p><p>Theſe various employments did not occupy the whole of Everardus’s time. Notwithſtanding the multiplicity of his buſineſs, he found leiſure to cultivate letters with great ſucceſs, and even to act as preceptor to his own children, who were five ſons and three daughters. They all took the name of Nicolaii from their father; but on what account, our author was called <hi rend="italic">Secundus</hi> is not known. It could not be from the order of his birth, for he was the youngeſt ſon. Perhaps the name was not given him till he became eminent; and then, according to the faſhion of the age, it might have its riſe from ſome pun, ſuch as his being <hi rend="italic">Poetarum nemini Secundus.</hi> Poetry, however, was by no means the profeſſion which his father wiſhed him to follow. He intended him for the law, and when he could no longer direct his ſtudies himſelf, placed him under the care of J<hi rend="italic">acobus Valeardus.</hi> This man is ſaid to have been everyway well qualified to diſcharge the important truſt which was committed to him; and he certainly gained the affection of his pupil, who, in one of his poems,</p><p>mentions the death of Valeardus with every appearance of unfeigned ſorrow. Another tutor was ſoon provided; but it does not appear that Secundus devoted much of his time to legal purſuits. Poetry and the ſiſter arts of painting and ſculpture had engaged his mind at a very early period; and the imagination, on which theſe have laid hold, can with difficulty ſubmit to the dry ſtudy of muſty civilians. Secundus is ſaid to have written verſes when but ten years old; and from the vaſt quantity which he left behind him, we have reaſon to conclude that ſuch writing was his principal employment. He found time, however, to carve figures of all his own family, of his miſtreſſes, of the emperor Charles V. of ſeveral eminent perſonages of thoſe times, and of many of his intimate friends; and in the laſt edition of his works publiſhed by Scirverius at Leyden, 1631, there is a print of one of his miſtreſſes with this inſcription round it; <hi rend="smallcaps">Vatis amatoris Julia sculpta </hi>MANU.</p><p>Secundus having nearly attained the age of twenty one, and being determined, as it would ſeem, to comply as far as poſſible with the wiſhes of his father, quitted Mechelen, and went to France, where at <hi rend="italic">Bourges,</hi> a city in the <hi rend="italic">Orleanois,</hi> he ſtudied the civil law under the Celebrated <hi rend="italic">Andreas Alciatus.</hi> Alciatus was one of the moſt learned civilians of that age; but what undoubtedly endeared him much more to our author was his general acquaintance with polite literature, and more particularly his taſte in poetry. Having ſtudied a year under this eminent profeſſor, and taken his degrees, Secundus returned to Mechelen, where he remained only a very few months. In 1533 he went into Spain with warm recommendations to the count of Naſſau and other perſons of high rank; and ſoon afterwards became ſecretary to the cardinal archbiſhop of Toledo in a department of buſineſs which required no other qualifications than what he poſſeſſed in a very eminent degree, a facility in writing with elegance the Latin language. It was during his reſidence with this cardinal that he wrote his <hi rend="italic">Basia,</hi> a ſeries of wanton poems, of which the fifth, ſeventh, and ninth <hi rend="italic">carmina</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Catullus</hi> ſeem to have given the hint. Secundus was not, however, a ſervile imitator of Catullus. His expreſſions ſeem to be borrowed rather from <hi rend="italic">Tibullus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Propertius;</hi> and in the warmth of his deſcriptions he ſurpaſſes every thing that has been written on ſimilar ſubjects by <hi rend="italic">Catullus, Tibullus, Propertius, C. Gallus, Ovid,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Horace.</hi></p><p>In 1335 he accompanied the emperor Charles V. to the ſiege of Tunis, but gained no laurels as a ſoldier. The hardſhips which were endured at that memorable ſiege were but little ſuited to the ſoft diſpoſition of a votary of Venus and the muſes; and upon an enterpriſe which might have furniſhed ample matter for an epic poem, it is remarkable that Secundus wrote nothing which has been deemed worthy of preſervation. Having returned from his martial expedition, he was ſent by the cardinal to Rome to congratulate the pope upon the ſucceſs of the emperor’s arms; but was taken ſo ill on the road, that he was not able to complete his journey. He was adviſed to ſeek, without a moment’s delay, the benefit of his native air; and that happily recovered him.</p><p>Having now quitted the ſervice of the archbiſhop of Toledo, Secundus was employed in the ſame office of ſecretary by the biſhop of Utrecht; and ſo much had</p></body></text></TEI>