<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:01:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>they were not many years formed into a diſtinct ſociety, when they expelled from their communion a Mr Thomas Nairn miniſter at Kirkcaldy, who had taught doctrines inimical to the civil governmcnt of the nation. In 1745 there was not one of their number who joined the then pretender to the Britiſh crown. They are ſtill of the  ſame ſentiments; and in their public aſſemblies they always pray for our ſovereign King George, with the royal family, and for all who are in authority under them. They are ſo far from wiſhing the overthrow of the preſent civil government, that when the nation was lately in danger of being thrown into a fermentation by the circulation of inflammatory and ſeditious writings, they warmly recommended peace and order in ſociety @@(c). No legal diſqualifications, as in the caſe of the diſſenters in England, exclude them from any place of public truſt in the municipal government of the country; and ſome of them are frequently in the magiſtracy of the royal boroughs. They are not, however, legally tolerated, but are ſupported by the mildneſs of adminiſtration and the liberal ſpirit of the times. Avowing their adherence to the doctrines contained in the public ſtandards of the church of Scotland, together with the preſbyterian form of government, from which they never intended to ſecede, they deny that they are either ſchiſmatics or ſectaries, as they have been frequently called: and when they withdrew from the eccleſiaſtical courts, they did not, they ſay, conſtitute a church of their own, different from the national church, but profeſs to be a part of that church, endeavouring to hold by her reformed principles, in oppoſition to thoſe deviations from them which they have ſpecified in their</p><p><hi rend="italic">Act and Testimony.</hi> Moſt of them live in habits of friendſhip and intimacy with their brethren of the eſtabliſhment, and they profeſs an affectionate regard for all thoſe of every denomination who love Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity and truth. In the late re-exhibition of their teſtimony, they have declared to the world, that, were the grounds of their ſeceſſion happily removed, they would account it one of the moſt ſingular felicities of their time to return with pleaſure to the communion of the eſtabliſhed church.</p><p>SECHIUM, in botany: A genus of the ſyngeneſia order, belonging to the monœcia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 34th order, <hi rend="italic">Cucurbitaceœ.</hi> The male calyx is quinquedentate and monophyllous; the corolla monopetalous; the five filaments are united in an erect tube. In the female flower the piſtillum is cylindrical and erect; the ſtigma large, peltated, and reflected; the pericarpium large, oval, unequal, fleſhy, and unilocular, containing one feed, which is ſmooth, compreſſed, and fleſhy. Of this there is only one ſpecies, viz. the <hi rend="italic">Edulis,</hi> or Chocho vine.— This is cultivated and grows very luxuriantly in many places in Jamaica. The vines run and ſpread very much. The fruit is boiled, and ſerved up at table by way of greens; and the root of the old vine is ſomewhat like a yam <hi rend="italic">(Dioſcorea)</hi> and on being boiled or roaſted taſtes farinaceous and wholeſome.</p><p>SECKENDORF (Guy Lewis de), a very learned German, deſcended from an ancient and noble family, was born at Aurach in Franconia in 1626. He was a good linguiſt, learned in law, hiſtory, and divinity and is ſaid to have been a tolerable painter and engraver. He was honourably employed by ſeveral of the German princes; and died counſellor of ſtate to Frederic III. elector of Brandenburg, and chancellor of the university of Halle, in 1692. He wrote many books, particularly “A hiſtory and defence of the Lutheran religion,” 2 vols folio, Frankfort, 1602, in Latin.</p><p>SECKER (Thomas), a learned and reſpectable prelate of the church of England, was born, in 1693, at a village called <hi rend="italic">Sibthorp,</hi> in the vale of Belvoir, Nottinghamſhire. His father was a Proteſtant diſſenter, a pious, virtuous, and ſenſible man; who having a small  paternal fortune, followed no profession. His mother was the daughter of Mr George Brough, a ſubſtantial gentleman farmer of Shelton in the ſame county. He received his education at ſeveral private ſchools and academies in the country, being obliged, by various accidents, to change his maſters frequently.</p><p>Notwithſtanding this diſadvantage, he had at the age of 19 not only made a conſiderable progreſs in Greek and Latin, and read the beſt writers in both languages, but had acquired a knowledge of French, Hebrew, Chaldee, and Syriac; had learned geography, logic, algebra, geometry, conic ſections, and gone through a courſe of lectures on Jewiſh antiquities and other points, preparatory to the critical ſtudy of the Bible. He had been deſtined by his father for orders among the Diſſenters. With this view, during the latter years of his education, his ſtudies were chiefly turned towards divinity, in which he had made ſuch quick advances, that by the time he was 23 he had carefully read over a great part of the Scriptures, particularly the New Teſtament, in the original, and the beſt comments upon it; Euſebius’s Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, The Apoſtolical Fathers, Whiſton’s Primitive Chriſtianity, and the principal writers for and againſt Miniſterial and Lay Conformity—- But though the reſult of theſe inquiries was a well- grounded belief of the Chriſtian revelation, yet not being at that time able to decide on ſome abſtruſe ſpeculative doctrines, nor to determine abſolutely what communion he ſhould embrace; he reſolved, like a wiſe and honeſt man, to purſue ſome profeſſion, which ſhould leave him at liberty to weigh thoſe things more maturely in his thoughts, and not oblige him to declare or teach publicly opinions which were not yet thoroughly ſettled in his own mind.</p><p>In 1716, therefore, he applied himſelf to the ſtudy of phyſic, and after gaining all the medical knowledge he</p><p>@@@( c ) All this is ſaid of the Burgher Seceders; but we hope it is equally true of thoſe who are ſtyled. Antiburghers. There are indeed ſome clauſes in the Covenant which they ſwear to maintain, that ſeem not, at firſt view, very friendly to civil ſubordination; but let not thoſe who entertain any apprehenſion on this account, forget that one of the moſt uſeful defences of the Britiſh conſtitution, occaſioned by the late factious ſpirit of democratic innovation, came from the pen of Dr Young the Antiburgher miniſter at Hawick. See Young's Essays.</p></body></text></TEI>