<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ſource of wild conjecture, and not of sound philosophy. We view the contraction and
                expanſion of the ſenſitive plant in the ſame light as we do gravitation, chemical
                attraction, electricity, and magnetiſm, as a singular fact, the circumſtances of
                which we may be fully acquainted with, but muſt deſpair of underſtanding its
                cauſe.</p>
            <p>What has been ſaid under this article chiefly refers to the <hi rend="italic">mimoſa
                    ſenfitiva</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pudica.</hi> For a full account of the
                motions of vegetables in general, ſee <hi rend="italic">Vegetable Motion,</hi> under
                the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Motion.</hi></p>
            <p>SENTENCE, in law, a judgment paſſed in court by the judge in ſome process, either
                civil or criminal. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Judgment.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sentence,</hi> in grammar, denotes a period ; or a ſet of words
                comprehending ſome perfect ſenſe or ſentiment of the mind. The buſineſs of pointing
                is to diſtinguiſh the ſeveral parts and members of ſentences, ſo as to render the
                ſenſe thereof as clear, diſtinct, and full as poſſible. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Punctuation.</hi></p>
            <p>In every ſentence there are two parts neceſſarily required ; a noun for the ſubject,
                and a definite verb : whatever is found more than theſe two, affects one of them,
                either immediately, or by the intervention of ſome other, whereby the firſt is
                affected.</p>
            <p>Again, every ſentence is either simple or compound: a simple ſentence is that
                conſiſting of one ſingle ſubject, and one finite verb.—A compound ſentence contains
                ſeveral ſubjects and finite verbs, either expreſsly or implicitly.</p>
            <p>A simple ſentence needs no point or diſtinction ; only a period to cloſe it : as, “ A
                good man loves virtue for itſelf.”— In ſuch a ſentence, the ſeveral adjuncts affect
                either the ſubject or the verb in a different manner. Thus the word <hi
                    rend="italic">good</hi> expresses the quality of the ſubject, <hi rend="italic"
                    >virtue</hi> the object of the action, and <hi rend="italic">for itſelf </hi>the
                end thereof.—Now none of theſe adjuncts can be ſeparated from the reft of the
                ſentence : for if one be, why ſhould not all the reſt ? and if all be, the ſentence
                will be minced into almoſt as many parts as there are words.</p>
            <p>But if ſeveral adjuncts be attributed in the ſame manner either to the ſubject or the
                verb, the ſentence becomes compound, and is to be divided into parts.</p>
            <p>In every compound ſentence, as many ſubjects, or as many finite verbs as there are,
                either expreſsly or implied, ſo many diſtinctions may there be. Thus, “ My hopes,
                fears, joys, pains, all centre in you.” And thus <hi rend="italic">Catilina abiit,
                    exceſfit, evasit, erupit.</hi> The reason of which pointing is obvious ; for as
                many ſubjects or finite verbs as there are in a ſentence, ſo many members does it
                really contain. Whenever, therefore, there occur. more nouns than verbs, or
                contrariwiſe, they are to be conceived as equal. Since, as every ſubject requires
                its verbs, ſo every verb requires its ſubject, wherewith it may agree : excepting,
                perhaps, in ſome figurative expreſſions.</p>
            <p>SENTICOSÆ (from <hi rend="italic">ſentis,</hi> a “ briar or bramble) ;” the name of
                the 35th order in Linnaeus’s fragments of a natural method, conſiſting of roſe,
                bramble, and other plants, which reſemble them in port and external ſtructure. See
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany,</hi> page 465.</p>
            <p>SENTIMENT, according to Lord Karnes, is a term appropriated to ſuch thoughts as are
                prompted by paſſion. It differs from a perception ; for a perception ſigniſies the
                add by which we become conscious of external objects. It differs from conſciouſnefs
                of an internal action, ſuch as thinking, ſuſpending thought, inclining, reſolving,
                willing, &amp;c. And it differs from the conception of a relation among objects ; a
                conception of that kind being termed <hi rend="italic">opinion.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sentiments,</hi> in poetry. To talk in the language of muſic,
                each paſſion hath a certain tone, to which every ſentiment proceeding from it ought
                to be tuned with the greateſt accuracy : which is no eaſy work, eſpecially where
                ſuch harmony ought to be ſupported during the courſe of a long theatrical
                repreſentation. In order to reach ſuch delicacy of execution, it is neceſſary that a
                writer aſſume the preciſe character and paſſion of the personage repreſented ; which
                requires an uncommon genius. But it is the only difficulty ; for the writer, who,
                annihilating himſelf, can thus become another perſon, need be in no pain about the
                ſentiments that belong to the aſſumed character : theſe will flow without the leaſt
                ſtudy, or even preconception ; and will frequently be as delightfully new to himſelſ
                as to his reader. But if a lively picture even of a ſingle emotion require an effort
                of genius, how much greater the effort to compoſe a passionate dialogue with as many
                different tones of paſſion as there are ſpeakers ? With what ductility of feeling
                muſt that writer be endued, who approaches perfection in ſuch a work ; when it is
                neceſſary to aſſume different and even oppoſite characters and paſſions in the
                quickeſt ſucceſſion ? Yet this work, difficult as it is, yields to that of compoſing
                a dialogue in genteel comedy, exhibiting characters without paſſion. The reason is,
                that the different tones of character are more delicate, and leſs in fight, than
                thoſe of paſſion ; and, accordingly, many writers, who have no genius for drawing
                characters, make a ſhift to represent, tolerably well, an ordinary paſſion in its
                ſimple movements. But of all works of this kind, what is truly the moſt difficult,
                is a characteriſtical dialogue upon any philofophical ſubject ; to interweave
                characters with reaſoning, by ſuiting to the character of each ſpeaker a peculiarity
                not only of thought but of expreſſion, requires the perfection of genius, taſte, and
                judgment.</p>
            <p>How difficult dialogue-writing is, will be evident, even without reaſoning, from the
                miſerable compoſitions of that kind found without number in all languages. The art
                of mimicking any ſingularity in geſture or in voice, is a rare talent, though
                directed by sight and hearing, the acuteſt and moſt lively of our external ſenſes :
                how much more rare muſt that talent be, of imitating characters and internal
                emotions, tracing all their different tints, and repreſenting them in a lively
                manner by natural ſentiments properly expressed ? The truth is, ſuch execution is
                too delicate for an ordinary genius; and for that reason the bulk of writers,
                inſtead of expressing a paſſion as one does who feels it, content themſelves with
                deſcribing it in the language of a ſpectator. To awake passion by an internal effort
                merely, without any external cauſe, requires great ſenſibility ; and yet that
                operation is necessary, not leſs to the writer than to the actor ; becauſe none but
                thoſe who actually feel a paſſion can repreſent it to the life. The writer’s part is
                the more complicated : he muſt add compoſition to paſſion : and muſt, in the
                quickeſt ſucceſſion, adopt every different character. But a very humble flight of
                imagination may ſerve to convert a</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
