<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:05:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>vation, and in the body plan, at equal diſtances from the upper edge of the keel.
                Then the diſtances between the middle line of the body plan, and the ſeveral points
                of interſection of theſe lines with the frames, are to belaid off from the middle
                line in the floor plan upon the correſponding frames ; and if the line drawn through
                theſe points form a fair curve, the frames are truly drawn in the body plan.</p>
            <p>In figs. 30. and 32. there are drawn four water lines at any equal diſtances from the
                keel, and from each other. Theſe lines are then transferred from fig. 32. to fig.
                31; and the lines paſſing through theſe points make fair curves.</p>
            <p>The tranſoms are deſcribed by Problem VIII. it is therefore unnecessary to repeat the
                proceſs. A riſing line of the floor timbers is commonly drawn in the plane of
                elevation.</p>
            <p>As this is intended only as an introductory example, ſeveral particulars have
                therefore been omitted ; which, however, will be exemplified in the following
                ſection.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> IV. <hi rend="italic">To describe the ſeveral Plans
                    of a Ship of War propoſed to carry</hi> 80 <hi rend="italic">Guns upon two
                    Decks.</hi></p>
            <p>As it is propoſed in this place to ſhow the method of deſcribing the plans of a ſhip
                of a very conſiderable ſize, it therefore ſeems proper to give the dimenſions of
                every particular part neceſſary in the delineation of theſe plans. The ſeveral plans
                of this ſhip are contained in Plate CCCCLXI. figs 33, and 34. But as it would very
                much confuſe the figures to have a reference to every operation, and as the former
                example is deemed a ſufficient illuſtration, the letters of reference are upon theſe
                accounts omitted in the figures.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Principal Dimensions.</hi></cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Lengths.—</hi> Length on the gun or lower deck from the
                        aft part of the rabbet of the ſtem to the aft part of the rabbet of the
                        poſt</cell>
                    <cell><p><hi rend="italic">F.</hi></p><p>182</p></cell>
                    <cell><p><hi rend="italic">In.</hi></p><p>0</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Length from the foremoſt perpendicular to dead flat</cell>
                    <cell>63</cell>
                    <cell>11 ¾</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Length from the foremoſt perpendicular to timber Y</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Length from after perpendicular to timber 37 -</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Room and ſpace of the timbers</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>8 ¾</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Length of the quarter-deck from the aft part of the ſtern</cell>
                    <cell>95</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Length of the forecaſtle from the fore part of the beak-head</cell>
                    <cell>49</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Length of round-houſe deck from the aft part of the ſtern</cell>
                    <cell>51</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Heights.—</hi>Height of the gun or lower deck from the
                        upper edge of the keel to the under fide of the plank at dead flat</cell>
                    <cell>24</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the gun or lower deck from the upper edge of the keel to the
                        under side of the plank at foremoſt perpendicular</cell>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the gun or lower deck from the upper edge of the keel to the
                        under side of the plank at after perpendicular</cell>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height from the upper fide of the gun-deck plank to the under fide of the
                        upper deck plank, all fore and aft</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height from the upper fide of the upper deck plank to the under side of
                        the greater deck plank</cell><cell> </cell><cell> </cell></row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>afore</cell> <cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell>
                 </row> 
                <row>
                    <cell>abaft</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell>
                </row>
                 <row>
                    <cell>Height to the under fide of forecaſtle plank, afore and abaft</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height from the upper fide of the ashore quarter-deck plank to the under
                        ſide of the round-houſe plank</cell><cell> </cell><cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>afore</cell> <cell>6</cell><cell>9</cell>
                </row> 
                <row>
                    <cell>abaft</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>10</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the lower edge of the main wales at foremoſt
                        perpendicular</cell>
                    <cell>24</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the lower edge of the main wales at dead flat</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the lower edge of the main wales at after perpendicular</cell>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the lower edge oſ the channel wales at foremoſt
                        perpendicular</cell>
                    <cell>32</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the lower edge oſ the channel wales at dead flat</cell>
                    <cell>29</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the lower edge of the channel wales at after
                        perpendicular</cell>
                    <cell>34</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the upper fide of the wing tranſom -</cell>
                    <cell>28</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the touch of the lower counter at the middle line</cell>
                    <cell>33</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the touch of the upper counter at the middle line</cell>
                    <cell>36</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of the top-timber line at the after part of the ſtern timber</cell>
                    <cell>44</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Breadths.—</hi>Main wales in breadth from lower to upper
                        edge</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Channel wales in breadth from lower to upper edge -</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Waiſt rail in breadth</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Diſtance between the upper edge of the channel wales and the under edge of
                        the waiſt rail - - -</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Sheer rail in breadth</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Diſtance between the ſheer rail and the rail above from timber 13 to the
                        ſtern</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Diſtance between the ſheer rail and the rail above from timber 7 to timber
                        11</cell>
                    <cell>I</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Diſtance between the ſheer rail and the rail above from timber C to the
                        forepart of beak-head</cell>
                    <cell>I</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>And the ſaid rail to be in breadth</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Plank ſheer to be in thickneſs</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>2 ⅛</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Gentres of the masts.—</hi> From the foremoſt
                        perpendicular to the centre oſ the mainmaſt on the gun-deck</cell>
                    <cell>103</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>From the foremoſt perpendicular to the centre of the foremaſt on the
                        gun-deck</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>From the after perpendicular to the centre of the mizenmaſt on the
                        gun-deck</cell>
                    <cell>28</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Stem.—</hi>The centre of the ſweep of the ſtem abaft
                        timber P -</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of ditto from the upper edge of the keel</cell>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                    <cell>I</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Stem moulded</cell>
                    <cell>I</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Foremoſt part of the head afore the perpendicular</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Height of ditto from the upper edge of the keel</cell>
                    <cell>38</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Stern-post. Aft</hi> part of the rabbet afore the</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
            </table>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
