<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:48Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>wiſe free citizens. Mr Bruce, who paſſed through this country in his return from Abyſſinia, gives a list of 20 kings who have reigned in it ſince the conqueſt of the Shillook.</p><p>This country is inhabited by a people ſo barbarous and brutiſh, that no hiſtory of them can be expected. One of the most remarkable of their cuſtoms is, that the king ascends the throne with the expectation of being murdered whenever the general council of the nation thinks proper. The dreadful office of executioner belongs to one ſingle officer, ſtyled, in the language of the country, <hi rend="italic">Sid el Coom ;</hi> and who is always a relation of the monarch himſelf. It was from his regiſters that Mr Bruce took the list of the kings already mentioned, with the number of years they reigned, and which may therefore be received as authentic. The Sid el Coom in office at the time that Mr Bruce viſited this country was named Achmet, and was one of his beſt friends. He had murdered the late king, with three of his ſons, one of whom was an infant at its mother’s breaſt ; he was alſo in daily expectation of performing the same office to the reigning sovereign. He was by no means reierved concerning the nature of his office, but anſwered freely every queſtion that was put to him. When aſked by Mr Bruce why he murdered the king’s young ſon in his father’s preſence? he anſwered, that he did it from a principle of duty to the king himſelf, who had a right to see his ſon killed in a lawful and regular manner, which was by cutting his throat with a ſword, and not in a more painful or ignominious way, which the malice of his enemies might possibly have inflicted.</p><p>The king, he ſaid, was very little concerned at the sight of his Ion’s death, but he was so very unwilling to die himſelf, that he often preſſed the executioner to let him eſcape; but finding his intreaties ineffectual, he submitted at last without reſiſtance. On being aſked, whether he was not afraid of coming into the preſence of the king, conſidering the office he might poſſibly have to perform? he replied, that he was not in the leaſt afraid on this account ; that it was his duty to be with the king every morning, and very late in the evening ; that the king knew he would have no hand in promoting his death ; but that, when the matter was abſolutely determined, the rest was only an affair of decency; and it would undoubtedly be his own choice, rather to fall by the hand of his own relation in private than by a hired aſſaſſin, an Arab, or a Chriſtian ſlave, in the light of the populace. Baady the king’s father, having the misfortune to be taken priſoner, was ſent to Atbara to Welled Haſſan the governor of that province to be put to death there. But the king, who was a ſtrong man, and always armed, kept ſo much upon his guard, that Welled could find no opportunity of killing him but by running him through the back with a lance as he was waſhing his hands. For this Welled himſelf was afterwards put to death ; not on account of the murder itſelf, but becauſe, in the first place, he, who was not the proper executioner, had preſumed to put the king to death; and, in the next, becauſe he had done it with a lance, whereas the only lawful inſtrument was a ſword.</p><p>On the death of any of the ſovereigns of this country, his eldeſt ſon ſucceeds to the throne of courſe ; on which as many of his brothers as can be found are ap</p><p>prehended, and put to death by the Sid el Coom in the manner already related. Women are excluded from the ſovereignty here as well as in Abyſſinia. The princeſſes of Sennaar, however, are worſe off than thoſe of Abyſſinia, having no settled income, nor being treated in any degree better than the daughters or private perſons. The king is obliged, once in his lifetime, to plough and ſow a piece of ground ; whence he is named <hi rend="italic">Baady,</hi> the “ countryman or peasant ;’’ a title as common among the monarchs of Sennaar as Cæsar was among the Romans. The royal family were originally negroes; but as the kings frequently marry Arab women, the white colour of the mother is communicated to the child. This, we are told by Mr Bruce, is invariably the caſe when a negro man of Sennaar marries an Arab woman ; and it holds equally good when an Arab man marries a negro woman; and he likewiſe informs us, that he never ſaw one black Arab all the time he was at Sennaar.</p><p>The soil and climate of this country is extremely unfavourable both to man and beast. The men are ſtrong· and remarkable for their size,but ſhortlived; and there is ſuch a mortality among the children, that were it not for a constant importation of slaves, the metropolis would be depopulated. The shortneſs of their lives, however, may perhaps be accounted for, from their indulging themſelves from their infancy in every kind of exceſs. No horſe, mule, nor aſs, will live at Sennaar or for many miles round it. The caſe is the ſame with bullocks, ſheep, dogs, cats, and poultry ; all of them muſt go to the ſands every half-year. It is difficult to account for this mortality ; though Mr Bruce aſſures us it is the caſe everywhere about the metropolis of this country, where the ſoil is a fat earth during the first leaſon of the rains. Two greyhounds which he brought along with him from Atbara, and the mules he brought from Abyssinia, lived only a few weeks after their arrival at Sennaar. Several of the kings of Sennaar have tried to keep lions, but it was always found impoſſible to preſerve them alive after the rains. They will live, however, as well as other quadrupeds, in the ſands, at no great diſtance from the capital. - No ſpecies of tree except the lemon flowers near this city ; the cultivation of the roſe has often been attempted, but always without ſucceſs. In other reſpects, however, the ſoil of Sennaar is exceedingly fertile, being ſaid to yield 300 fold ; but this is thought by Mr Bruce to be a great exaggeration. It is all ſown with dora or millet, which is the principal food of the people ; wheat and rice are alſo produced here, which are ſold by the pound, even in years of plenty. The ſoil all round is ſtrongly impregnated with ſalt, ſo that a ſufficient quantity to ſerve the inhabitants is extracted from it.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sennaar,</hi> a city of Africa, the capital of the kingdom of that name. It stands, according to Mr Bruce’s observations, in N. Lat. 13⁰ 34' 36" E. Long. 33⁰ 30' 30" on the western side of the Nile, and cloſe upon the banks of it ; the ground on which it stands being just high enough to prevent the inundation. The town is very populous, and contains a great many houſes. In Poncet’s time they were all of one ſtory ; but now most of the officers have houſes of two stories high. They are built of clay mixed with a very little ſtraw, and have all flat roofs ; which ſhows that the rains here</p></body></text></TEI>