<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:03:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>keeping in the void ſpace, called the liberty of the tongue.</p><p>SERPICULA, in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the class of monœcia, and to the order of tetrandia. The male calyx is quadridentate, and the corolla consiſts of four petals : The female calyx is divided into four parts, and the pericarpium is a tomentoſe nut. There are two ſpecies, the verticillata and repens.</p><p>SERPIGO, in ſurgery, a kind of herpes, popularly called a <hi rend="italic">tetter</hi> or ringworm. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Surgery.</hi></p><p>SERPULA, in natural hiſtory ; a genus belonging to the claſs of vermes, and to the order of teſtacea. The ſhell is ſingle, tubular, and adhering to other bodies. The animal which inhabits it is the terebella.</p><p>SERRANUS (Joannes), or John de Serres, a learned French Proteſtant, was born about the middle of the ſixteenth century. He acquired the Greek and Latin languages at Lauſanne, and grew very fond of the philoſophy of Ariſtotle and Plato. On his return to France he ſtudied divinity. He began to diſtinguiſh himſelf in 1572 by his writings, but was obliged to forſake his country after the dreadful maſſacre of St Bartholomew. He became miniſter of Niſmes in 1582, but was never regarded as a very zealous Calviniſt : he has even been ſuſpected, though without reaſon, of having actually abjured the Proteſtant religion. He was one of the four clergymen whom Henry IV. conſulted about the Romiſh religion, and who returned for anſwer, <hi rend="italic">that Catholics might be ſaved.</hi> He wrote afterwards a treatiſe in order to reconcile the two communions, entitled <hi rend="italic">De fide Catholica, five de principiis religionis Christianœ, Communi omnium Chriſtianorum conſenſu, ſemper et ubique ratis.</hi> This work was diſliked by the Catholics, and received with ſuch indignation by the Calviniſts of Geneva, that many writers have affirmed that they poiſoned the author. It is certain at leaſt that he died at Geneva in 1598, at the age of 50. His principal works are, 1. A Latin tranſlation of Plato, publiſhed by Henry Stephens, which owes much of its reputation to the elegance of the Greek copy which accompanies it. 2. A Treatiſe on the Immortality of the Soul. 3 <hi rend="italic">De statu religionis et republicae in Francia.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Memoire de la me guerre civile et derniers troubles de France fous Charles IX. &amp;c. 5. Inventaire general de l'Histoire de France, illustre par la conference de l'Eglise et de l'Empire, idle.</hi> 6. <hi rend="italic">Recueil de chose memorable avenue en France sous Henri II François IL Charles IX. Henri III.</hi> Theſe three hiſtorical treatiſes have been juſtly accuſed of partiality and paſſion ; faults which it is next to impoſſible for a contemporary writer to avoid, eſpecially if he bore any part in the tranſactions which he deſcribes. His ſtyle is exceedingly incorrect and inelegant ; his miſtakes too and misſtatements of facts are very numerous.</p><p>SERRATED, in general, ſomething indented or notched in the manner of a ſaw ; a term much uſed in the deſcription of the leaves of plants. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany. </hi>SERRATULA, <hi rend="smallcaps">saw-wort,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of ſyngeneſia, and to the order of polygamia æqualis. In the natural ſyſtem it is ranged under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Compositœ.</hi> The calyx is ſubcylindrical, imbricated ; the ſcales of it pointed, but not spinous. There are 15 ſpecies : The tinctoria, alpina, arvenſis, coronata, japonica, ſalicifolia, multiflora, noveboracenſis, præalta, glauca, ſquarroſa, ſcarioſa, ſpicata, amara, and centauroidcs. The three firſt ſpecies</p><p>arc Britiſh. I. The <hi rend="italic">tintoria</hi> is diſtinguiſhed by a  stem erect and ſlender, branched at the top, and three feet high. The leaves are ſmooth, pinnatifid, and ſerrated ; The flowers are purple, in umbels, and terminal. The down of the seed is gloſſy, with a brown or gold tinge. It grows in woods and wet paſtures. It dyes cloth of an exceeding fine yellow colour, which ſtands well when, fixed with alum. Goats eat this plant ; horſes are not fond of it ; cattle, ſwine, and ſheep, leave it untouched. 2. The <hi rend="italic">alρina,</hi> or mountain ſaw-wort, The root and stem are woody ; the latter being from one to two feet high. The leaves are numerous, triangular, long, pointed, ſubſtantial, dark green above, white beneath, and ſerrated, with round intervals between the teeth, on footſtalks. The flowers are purple. The ſcales of the calyx are very ſhort and downy. It grows on high mountains, and flowers commonly in July or Auguſt. 3. The <hi rend="italic">arvenſis,</hi> corn ſaw-wort, or way-thiſtle. The stem is generally erect, branched, and two or three feet high. The leaves are ſinuated, ſerrated, and ſpinous ; thoſe above being almoſt entire. The flowers are of a pale purple ; the down is very long·. This plant grows in cultivated grounds and by way- ſides, and flowers in July or Auguſt. When burned it yields good aſhes for making glaſs or fixed alkali.</p><p>SERRATUS, in anatomy, a name given to ſeveral muſcles, from their reſemblance to a ſaw. See ANATOMY, <hi rend="italic">Table of the Muſcles.</hi></p><p>SERTORIUS.(Quintus), an eminent Roman general ; (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Spain),</hi> under the hiſtory of which his exploits are related.</p><p>SERTULARIA , in natural hiſtory, a genus belonging to the class of vermes, and to the order of zoophyta. The ſtem is radicated, fibrous, naked, and jointed ; the florets are hydræ, and there is one at each joint. This genus comprehends 42 ſpecies of corallines.</p><p>SERVAL, mountain cat. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Feus,</hi> xvi.</p><p>SERVANDONI (John Nicolas), was born at Florence in 1695. He rendered himſelf famous by his exquiſite taste in architecture, and by his genius for decorations, fetes, and buildings. He was employed and rewarded by most of the princes in Europe. He was honoured in Portugal with the order of Chriſt : In France he was architect and painter to the king, and member of the different academies establiſhed for the advancement of theſe arts. He received the ſame titles from the kings of Britain, Spain, Poland, and from the duke of Wirtemberg. Notwithſtanding theſe advantages, his want of economy was ſo great, that he left nothing behind him. He died at Paris in 1766. Paris is indebted to him for many of its ornaments. He made decorations for the theatres of London and Dreſden. The French king’s theatre, called <hi rend="italic">la falle des Machines,</hi> was under his management for ſome time. He was permitted to exhibiti ſhows conſiſting of simple decorations : Some of theſe were aſtoniſhingly ſublime ; his “ Deſcent of Æneas into Hell” in particular, and his “ Enchanted Foreſt,” are well known. He built and embelliſhed a theatre at Chambor for Mareſchal Saxe ; and furniſhed the plan and the model of the theatre royal at Dreſden. His genius for fetes was remarkable ; he had the management of a great number in Paris, and even in London. He conducted one at Liſbon given on account of a victory gained by the duke of Cumberland. He was employed frequently by the king of</p></body></text></TEI>