<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:05:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>of the poſt, and CF equal to half that of the ſtem, and from the points A, E, F, B,
                draw lines parallel to CD. Make AG, BG each equal to 14 feet, the height at the main
                frame, and draw the line GG parallel to AB. Make GH, GH each equal to half a foot,
                the difference between the main and top timber half breadths. From A and B ſet up
                the heights of the lower and upper breadth lines to I and K, and draw the ſtraight
                lines IK, IK. Let CL be the rising at the main frame, and ⊕, ⊕ the extremities of
                the floor timber. Henca, as there are now five points determined in each half of the
                main frame, it may be very eaſily deſcribed.</p>
            <p>Make CM equal to L⊕, join M⊕, and draw the other ribbands NO, PQ. In order, however,
                to simplify this operation, the rectilineal diſtance ⊕I was triſected, and through
                the points of diviſion the lines NO, PQ were drawn parallel to the floor ribband
                M⊕.</p>
            <p>Take the diſtance <hi rend="italic">bc</hi> (fig. 30.), and lay it off from F to
                (fig. 32.); alſo make Fb (fig. 32.) equal to Fu (fig. 30.) ; through <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> draw <hi rend="italic">b c</hi> parallel to AB, and equal
                to FR (fig. 31). In like manner take the heights of each top-timber from fig. 30.
                and lay them off from C towards D (fig. 32) ; through theſe points draw lines
                parallel to AB, and make them equal each to each, to the correſponding half breadth
                lines taken from the floor plan: Then through the ſeveral points <hi rend="italic"
                    >a, c,</hi> &amp;c thus found, draw a line a <hi rend="italic">c</hi> H, which
                will be the projection of the top-timber line of the fore body in the body plan.
                Proceed in the ſame manner to find the top-timber line in the after body.</p>
            <p>Transfer the height of the main breadth line on the ſtem bl (fig. 30.) from F to d
                (fig. 32). Transfer alſo the heights of the lower and upper breadth lines at timber
                F (fig. 30. ), namely, FW, FX, from F to <hi rend="italic">e and f</hi> (fig. 32.) ;
                through which draw the parallels <hi rend="italic">eg, fh</hi> ; make them equal to
                FS (fig. 31.), and draw the ſtraight line <hi rend="italic">g h.</hi> In this manner
                proceed to lay down the portions of the extreme breadth at each frame, both in the
                fore and in the after body in the body plan, and draw the upper and lower breadth
                lines <hi rend="italic">dh</hi> K, <hi rend="italic">dg</hi> I in the fore body and
                K i, I <hi rend="italic">i</hi> in the after body. Hence the portions of the ſeveral
                top-timbers contained between the top-timber and main breadth lines may be eaſily
                deſcribed. It was before remarked that their forms were partly arbitrary. The
                midſhip top-timber has generally a hollow, the form of which is left entirely to the
                artiſt, though in ſome ſhips, eſpecially ſmall ones, it has none. It is the common
                practice to make a mould for this hollow, either by a ſweep or ſome other
                contrivance, which is produced considerably above the top-timber line, in a ſtraight
                line or very near one; The midſhip top-timber is formed by this mould, which is ſo
                placed that it breaks in four with the back of the upper breadth ſweep. The other
                top-timbers are formed by the ſame mould, obſerving to place it ſo that the ſtraight
                part of it may be parallel to the ſtraight part of the midſhip timber, and moved up
                or down, ſtill keeping it in that direction till it juſt touches the back of the
                upper breadth ſweep. Some conſtructors begin at the after timber, after the mould is
                made for the mid- ſhip top-timber, becauſe they think it easier to keep the ſtraight
                part of the mould parallel to this than to the midſhip timber ; and by this means
                the top side is kept from winding. Others, again, make a mark upon</p>
            <p>the mould where the breadth line of the midſhip timber croſſes it, and with the ſame
                mould they form the after timber ; this will occasion the mark that was made on the
                mould when at the main frame to fall below the breadth line of the after timber, and
                therefore another mark is made at the height of the breadth line at the after timber
                ; the ſtraight part of the mould is then laid obliquely acroſs the breadth lines of
                the top-timbers, in ſuch a manner that it may interſect the breadth line of the
                midſhip timber at one of theſe marks and the breadth line of the after timber at the
                other mark ; then the ſeveral interſections of the breadth lines of the timbers are
                marked upon the mould ; which muſt now be ſo placed in forming each timber, that the
                proper mark may be applied to its proper breadth, and it muſt be turned about ſo as
                juſt to touch the upper breadth ſweep. Any of theſe methods may make a fair side,
                and they may be eaſily proved by forming another intermediate half breadth line.</p>
            <p>The remaining parts of the frames may be deſcribed by either of the methods laid down
                in Problems IX. and X. In order, however, to illuſtrate this ſtill farther, it is
                thought proper to ſubjoin another method of forming the intermediate frames, the
                facility of which will recommend it.</p>
            <p>Take FZ (fig. 30.), and lay it from F to <hi rend="italic">k</hi> (fig. 32.) ; then
                deſeribe the lower part of the foremost frame, making it more or lets full according
                as propoſed ; and interſecting the ribbands in the points l, m, n. Deſcribe alſo the
                aftermoſt frame o, p, q, Make αβ (fig. 30.) equal to F <hi rend="italic">r</hi>
                (fig. 32.), and produce it to <hi rend="italic">a</hi> (fig. 31.) ; alſo draw γδ and
                ες (fig. 30.) equal to E <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and E J (fig. 32.) reſpectively ;
                and produce them to <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and <hi rend="italic">c :</hi> Make F
                e, Ff, FR (fig. 31.) equal to Ml, Nm<hi rend="italic">,</hi> Pn (fig. 32.) each to
                each. Let alſo ⊕h, ⊕i, ⊕k, and 9l, 9 m, 9n (fig. 31,) be made equal to M⊕, NO, and
                Mo, N <hi rend="italic">q, Pp </hi>(fig. 32 ) ; then through theſe points trace the
                curves aenhlb<hi rend="italic">, rfimc,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">r</hi> R <hi
                    rend="italic">k n p,</hi> and they will be the projections of the ribbands in
                the floor plane. Now transfer the ſeveral intervals of the frames contained between
                the middle line and the ribbands (fig. 31.) to the correſponding ribbands in the
                body plan (fig. 32). Hence there will be five points given in each frame, namely,
                one at the lower breadth line, one at each ribband, and one at the keel ; and
                conſequently theſe frames may be eaſily deſcribed. In order to exemplify this, let
                it be required to lay down the frame E in the plane of projection. Take the interval
                En (fig. 31.), and lay it from M to <hi rend="italic">u</hi> (fig. 32). Lay off alſo
                E <hi rend="italic">v, </hi>Ee (fig. 31.) from N to <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and
                ſrom P to n (fig. 32 ); then through the points F, <hi rend="italic">u, v, n</hi>
                and the lower breadth line deſcribe a curve, and it will be the repreſentation of
                the frame E in the body plan. In like manner the other frames may be deſcribed.</p>
            <p>The ribbands may now be transferred from the body plan to the plane of elevation, by
                taking the ſeveral heights of the interſection of each ribband with the frames, and
                laying them off on the correſponding frames in the floor plan ; and if the line
                drawn through theſe points make a fair curve, it is preſumed that the curves of the
                frames are rightly laid down in the body plan. Only one of theſe ribbands, namely,
                the firſt, is laid down in fig. 30. Theſe curves may alſo be farther proved, by
                drawing water lines in the plane of ele-</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
