<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tion for promoting the diſcovery of the Interior Parts of Africa, which, as far as we know, is the lateſt and most authentic.</p><p>The river known to Europeans by the name of <hi rend="italic">Niger</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Senegal</hi> runs on the ſouth of the kingdom of Casina, in its courſe towards Tombuctou ; and if the report which Ben Alli heard in that town may be credited, it is afterwards loſt in the ſands on the ſouth of the country of Tombuctou. In the map @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a),</hi> only the known part of its courſe is marked by a line ; and the ſuppoſitious part by dots. It may be proper to observe, that the Africans have two names for this river; that is, <hi rend="italic">Neel il Abeed,</hi> or river of the Negroes ; and <hi rend="italic">Neel il Kibeer,</hi> or the great river. They also term the Nile (that is the Egyptian river) <hi rend="italic">Neel Shem</hi> ; ſo that the term <hi rend="italic">Neel,</hi> from whence our Nile, is nothing more than the appellative of river ; like Ganges, or Sinde.</p><p>Of this river the rise and termination are unknown, but the courſe is from eaſt to west. So great is its rapidity, that no veſſel can aſcend its ſtream ; and ſuch is the want of skill, or ſuch the abſence of commercial inducements among the nations who inhabit its borders, that even with the current, neither veſſels nor boats are ſeen to navigate. In one place, indeed, the traveller finds accommodations for the paſſage of himſelf and of  his goods ; but even there, tho’ the ferrymen, by the indulgence of the sultan of Caſhna, are exempted from all taxes, the boat which conveys the merchandiſe is nothing more than an ill-conſtructed raft ; for the planks are faſtened to the timbers with ropes, and the ſeams are doled both within and without by a plaſter of tough day, of which a large provision is always carried on the raft, for the purpoſe of excluding the ſtream wherever its entrance is obſerved.</p><p>The depth of the river at the place of paſſage, which is more than a hundred miles to the ſouth of the city of Caſhna, the capital of the empire of that name, is eſtimated at 23 or 24 feet Engliſh. Its depth is from 10 to 12 peeks, each of which is 27 inches.</p><p>Its width is ſuch, that even at the iſland of Gongoo, where the ferrymen reſide, the sound of the loudeſt voice from the northern ſhore is ſcarcely heard ; and at Tombuctou, where the name of <hi rend="italic">Gnewa,</hi> or black, is given to the ſtream, the width is deſcribed as being that of the Thames at Weſtminſter. In the rainy season it ſwells above its banks, and not only floods the adjacent lands, but often ſweeps before it the cattle and cottages of the ſhort-ſighted or too confident inhabitants.</p><p>That the people who live in the neighbourhood of the Niger ſhould refuſe to profit by its navigation, may juſtly furpriſe the traveller: but much greater is his aſtoniſh.ment, when he finds that even the food which the bounty of the ſtream would give, is uſeleſsly offered to their acceptance ; for ſuch is the want of ſkill, or ſuch the settled diſlike of the people to this sort of proviſion, that the fiſh with which the river abounds are left in undiſturbed poſſeſſion of its waters.</p><p>SENE'KA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Senega, </hi><hi rend="italic">Rattteſnake-root, Milk-wort, a</hi> medicinal plant. See <hi rend="smallcaps">PolYGala.</hi></p><p>SENESCHAL, <hi rend="italic">( Seneſchallus),</hi> derived from the German <hi rend="italic">ſein</hi> “ a houſe or place,” and <hi rend="italic">ſcale “ </hi>an officer,” is a ſteward, and ſignifies one who has the dispenſing of juſtice in some particular cases : As the high ſeneſchal or ſteward of England ; <hi rend="italic">ſeneſchal de la hotel de roi,</hi> “ ſteward of the king’s houſehold, ſeneſchal, or ſteward of courts, &amp;c.” <hi rend="italic">Co. Lit.</hi> 61. <hi rend="italic">Crοke's Jurisd.</hi> 102. <hi rend="italic">Kiich.</hi> 83. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Steward.</hi></p><p>SENNA, the leaf of the caſſia ſenna of Linnæus. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cassia.</hi></p><p>Senna appears to have been cultivated in England in the time of Parkinſon (1640) ; and Miller tells us, that by keeping theſe plants in a hot-bed all the ſummer, he frequently had them in flower ; but adds, it is very rarely that they perfect their feeds in England. There can be little doubt, however, but that ſome of the Britiſh poſſeſſions may be found well enough adapted to the growth of this vegetable, and that the patriotic views of the Society for encouraging Arts, &amp;c. which has offered a reward to thoſe who ſucceed in the attempt, will be ultimately accompliſhed.</p><p>Senna, which is in common uſe as a purgative, was  firſt known to the Arabian phyſicians Serapion and Meſue : the firſt among the Greeks who takes any notice of it is Actuarius, but he only ſpeaks of the fruit, and not of the leaves. To remove the diſagreeable taſte of this medicine, Dr Cullen recommends coriander feeds; and, for preventing the gripings with which it is sometimes attended, he thinks the warmer aromatics, as cardamoms or ginger, would be more effectual.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Senna Italica,</hi> or blunt-leaved ſenna, is a variety of the Alexandrian ſpecies; which, by its cultivation in the ſouth of France (Provence), has been found to asſume this change. It is leſs purgative than the pointed-leaved ſenna, and is therefore to be given in larger doses. It was employed as a cathartic by Dr Wright at Jamaica, where it grows on the ſand-banks near the sea.</p><p>SENNAAR, a country of Africa, bordering upon Abyſtinia, with the title of a kingdom ; the preſent government of which was eſtabliſhed in the 16th century by a race of negroes named, in their own language, <hi rend="italic">Shillοok.</hi> This country, together with all the northern parts of Africa, had been over-run by the Saracens during the rapid conqueſts of the khalifs ; but inſtead of erecting any diſtinct principalities here, as in other parts, they had incorporated themſelves with the old inhabitants called <hi rend="italic">Shepherds,</hi> whom they found at their arrival; had converted them to their religion, and become one people with them. In 1504 the Shillook, a people before unknown, came from the western banks of the river Bahiar el Abiad, which empties itſelf into the Nile, and conquered the country; allowing the Arabs, however, to retain their poſſeſſions on condition of paying them a certain tribute, Theſe founded the city of Sennaar, and have ever ſince continued to carry on an intercourſe with Egypt in the way of merchandiſe. At the eſtabliſhment of their monarchy the whole nation were Pagans, but soon after became converts to Mohammedaniſm, and took the name of <hi rend="italic">Funge,</hi> an appellation ſignifying “lords or conquerors,” and like-</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> The map alluded to is that which accompanies the volume which contains the proceedings of the Associations. This work was printed in 1791 .</p></body></text></TEI>