<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ture, previous to their taking the ram. In winter they are kept on graſs, hay, turnips, and cabbages. As the heads of the modern breed are much finer than moſt others, the ewes lamb with leſs difficulty.</p><p>The female lambs, on being weaned, are put to good keep, but have not ſuch high indulgence ſhown them as the males, the prevailing practice being to keep them from the ram the firſt autumn.</p><p>At weaning time, or previouſly to the admiſſion of the ram, the ewes are culled, to make room for the thaves or ſhearlings, whoſe ſuperior blood and faſhion intitle them to a place in the breeding flock. In the work of culling, the ram-breeder and the mere grazier go by ſomewhat different guides. The grazier’s guide is principally age, ſeldom giving his ewes the ram after they are four shear. The ram-breeder, on the contrary, goes chiefly by merit ; an ewe that has brought him a good ram or two is continued in the flock ſo long as ſhe will breed. There are inſtances of ewes having been prolific to the tenth or twelfth year ; but in general the ewes of this breed go off at six or ſeven ſhear.</p><p>In the practice of ſome of the principal ram-breeders, the culling ewes are never ſuffered to go out of their hands until after they are ſlaughtered, the breeders not only fatting them, but having them butchered, on their premiſes. There are others, however, who ſell them ; and ſometimes at extraordinary prices. Three, four, and even ſo high as ten, guineas each have been given for theſe outcaſts.</p><p>There are in the flocks of ſeveral breeders ewes that would fetch at auction twenty guineas each. Mr Bakewell is in poſſeſſion of ewes which, if they were now put up to be fold to the beſt bidder, would, it is eſtimated, fetch no leſs than fifty each, and perhaps, through the preſent ſpirit of contention, much higher prices.</p><p>The following inſtructions for purchaſing ſheep, we hope, will be acceptable to our country readers.— The farmer ſhould always buy his ſheep from a worſe land than his own, and they ſhould be big-boned, and have a long greaſy wool, curling cloſe and well. Theſe ſheep always breed the fineſt wool, and are alſo the moſt approved of by the butcher ſor ſale in the market. For the choice of ſheep to breed, the ram muſt be young, and his skin of the ſame colour with his wool, for the lambs will be of the ſame colour with his ſkin. He ſhould have a large long body ; a broad forehead, round, and well riſing ; large eyes ; and ſtraight and ſhort noſtrils. The polled ſheep, that is, thoſe which have no horns, are found to be the best breeders. The ewe ſhould have a broad back ; a large bending neck ; ſmall, but ſhort, clean, and nimble legs ; and a thick, deep wool covering her all over.</p><p>To know whether they be found or not, the farmer ſhould examine the wool that none of it ſhe wanting, and ſee that the gums be red, the teeth white and even, and the briſket ſkin red, the wool firm, the breath ſweet, and the feet not hot. Two years old is the beſt time for beginning to breed; and their firſt lambs ſhould not be kept too long, to weaken them by ſuckling, but be fold as soon as conveniently may be. They will breed advantageouſly till they are ſeven years old. The farmers have a method, of knowing the age of a ſheep, as a horſe’s is known, by the mouth. When a ſheep</p><p>is one ſhear, as they expreſs it, it has two broad teeth before ; when it is two ſhear, it will have four ; when three, six ; and when four, eight. After this .their mouths begin to break.</p><p>The difference of land makes a very great difference in the ſheep. The fat paſtures breed ſtraight tall ſheep, and the barren hills and downs breed ſquare ſhort ones ; woods and mountains breed tall and ſlender ſheep ; but the beſt of all are thoſe bred upon new-ploughed land and dry grounds. On the contrary, all wet and moist lands are bad for ſheep, eſpecially ſuch as are ſubject to be overflowed, and to have sand and dirt left on them. The ſalt marſhes are, however, an exception to this general rule, for their ſaltneſs makes amends for their moiſture ; ſalt, by reaſon of its drying quality, being of great advantage to ſheep.</p><p>As to the time of putting the rams to the ewes, the farmer muſt consider at what time of the ſpring his graſs will be fit to maintain them and their lambs, and whether he has turnips to do it till the graſs comes ; for very often both the ewes and lambs are deſtroyed by the want of food ; or if this does not happen, it the lambs are only ſtinted in their growth by it, it is an accident that they never recover. The ewe goes 20 weeks with lamb, and according to this it is eaſy to calculate the proper time. The beſt time for them to yean is in April, unleſs the owner has very forward graſs or turnips, or the ſheep are field ſheep. Where you have not incloſures to keep them in, then it may be proper they ſhould yean in January, that the lambs may be ſtrong by May-day, and be able to follow the dam over the fallows and water-furrows ; but then the lambs that come ſo early muſt have a great deal of care taken of them, and ſo indeed ſhould all other lambs at their firſt falling, elſe while they are weak the crows and magpies will pick their eyes out.</p><p>When the ſheep are turned into fields of wheat or rye to feed, it muſt not be too rank at firſt, for if it be, it generally throws them into ſcourings. Ewes that are big ſhould be kept but bare, for it is very dangerous to them to be fat at the time of their bringing forth their young. They may be well fed, indeed, like cows, a fortnight beforehand, to put them in. heart- Mortimer’s Huſhandry, p. 243.</p><p>The feeding ſheep with turnips is one great advantage to the farmers. When they are made to eat turnips they soon fatten, but there is some difficulty in bringing this about. The old ones always refuſe them at firſt, and will ſometimes faſt three or four days, till almoſt famiſhed ; but the young lambs fall to at oncs. The common way, in ſome places, of turning a flock of ſheep at large into a field of turnips, is very diſadvantageous, for they will thus deſtroy as many in a fortnight as would keep them a whole winter. There are three other ways of feeding them on this food, all of which have their ſeveral advantages.</p><p>The firſt way is to divide the land by hurdles, and allow the ſheep to come upon ſuch a portion only at a time as they can eat in one day, and ſo advance the hurdles farther into the ground daily till all be eaten. This is infinitely better than the former random method; but they never eat them clean even this way, but leave the bottoms and outsides ſcooped in the ground : the people pull up theſe indeed with iron crooks, and lay them before the ſheep again, but they are common-</p></body></text></TEI>