<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and in leſs than two years after the compiling of King Edward’s liturgy, a formula was compoſed, which continues, with ſcarce any variation, to be the rule for choral ſervice even at this day. The author of this work was John Marbecke, or Marbeike ; and it was printed by Richard Grafton, in 1550, under the title of the Book of Common Prayer, noted. Queen Mary laboured to re-eſtabliſh the Romiſh choral ſervice ; but the acceſſion of Elizabeth was followed by the act of uniformity ; in conſequence of which, and of the queen’s injunctions, the Book of Common Prayer, noted by Marbecke, was conſidered as the general formula of choral ſervice. In 1560, another muſical ſervice, with ſome additions and improvements, was printed by John Day; and in 1565<hi rend="italic">,</hi> another collection of offices, with muſical notes. Many objections were urged by Cartwright and other Puritans againſt the form and manner of cathedral ſervice, to which Hooker replied in his Eccleſiaſtical Polity. In 1664, the ſtatutes of Edward VI. and Elizabeth, for uniformity in the Common Prayer, were repealed ; and the Directory for Public Worſhip, which allows only of the ſinging of pſalms, eſtabliſhed. But upon the reſtoration of Charles II. choral ſervice was again revived, and has ſince uniformly continued. See on this ſubject Hawkins’s Hiſtory of Muſic, vol. i. p. 404. vol. ii. p. 264. vol. iii. p. 58—468, &amp;c. vol. iv. p. 44—347.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SERVICE-Tree.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sorbus.</hi></p><p>SERVITES, a religious order in the church of Rome, founded about the year 1233, by ſeven Florentine merchants, who, with the approbation of the biſhop of Florence, renounced the world, and lived together in a religious community on mount Senar, two leagues from that city.</p><p>SERVITOR, in the univerſity of Oxford, a ſtudent who attends on another for his maintenance and learning. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sizar.</hi></p><p>SERVITUDE, the condition of a servant, or rather ſlave.</p><p>Under the declenſion of the Roman empire, a new kind of ſervitude was introduced, different from that of the ancient Romans : it conſiſted in leaving the lands of ſubjugated nations to the firſt owners, upon condition of certain rents, and ſervile offices, to be paid in acknowledgment. Hence the names of <hi rend="italic">ſervi censiti, ascriptitii,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">addicti gleba ;</hi> ſome whereof were taxable  at the reaſonable diſcretion of the lord ; others at a certain rate agreed on ; and others were mainmortable, who, having no legitimate children, could not make a will to above the value of five pence, the lord being heir of all the rest ; and others were prohibited marrying, or going to live out of the lordſhip. Moſt of theſe ſervices exiſted lately in France ; but they were long ago aboliſhed in England. Such, however, was the original oſ our tenures, &amp;c. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Slave.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Servitude,</hi> in Scots law. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Law,</hi> Part III. Sect. ix.</p><p>SERVIUS (Maurus Honoratus), a celebrated grammarian and critic of antiquity, who flouriſhed about the time of Arcadius and Honorius ; now chiefly known by his Commentaries on Virgil. There is alſo extant a piece of Servius upon the feet of verſes and the quantity of ſyllables, called <hi rend="italic">Centimetrum.</hi></p><p>SERUM, a thin, tranſparent, ſaltiſh liquor, which makes a considerable part of the maſs of blood. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy,</hi> n<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 126. and <hi rend="smallcaps">Blood.</hi></p><p>SESAMOIDEA <hi rend="smallcaps">ossa,</hi> certain ſmall bones ſomewhat reſembling the seeds of ſeſamum, whence their name. They are placed at the under part of the bones of the laſt joints of the fingers and toes.</p><p>SESAMUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">oily grain,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of didynamia, and to the order of angioſpermia ; and in the natural ſystem ranging under the 20th order, <hi rend="italic">Lurida.</hi> The calyx is divided into five parts. The corolla is campanulated, the tube of which is nearly the length of the calyx ; the throat is inflated, and very large ; the border is divided into five parts, four of which are ſpreading and nearly equal ; the fifth is the loweſt and largeſt. There are four filaments, and the rudiments of a fifth. The ſtigma is lanceolated, and the capſule has four cells. There are only two ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">orientale </hi>and <hi rend="italic">indicum.</hi> 1. The orientale has ovate, oblong, entire leaves. It is an annual, and grows naturally on the coaſt of Malabar and in the iſland of Ceylon ; riſing with an herbaceous four-cornered ſtalk, two feet high, ſending out a few ſhort ſide-branches ; the leaves are oblong, oval, a little hairy, and ſtand oppoſite. The flowers terminate the ſtalks in looſe ſpikes ; they are ſmall, of a dirty white colour, ſhaped ſomewhat like thoſe of the fox-glove. After the flowers are paid, the germen turns to an oval acute-pointed capſule with four cells, filled with oval compreſſed ſeeds, which ripen in autumn. 2. The indicum, with trifid lower leaves, grows naturally in India : this is alſo an annual plant ; the ſtalk riſes taller than that of the former ; the lower leaves are cut into three parts, which is the only difference between them.</p><p>The firſt fort is frequently cultivated in all the eaſtern countries, and alſo in Africa, as a pulſe ; and of late years the ſeeds have been introduced into Carolina by the African negroes, where they ſucceed extremely well. The inhabitants of that country make an oil from the ſeed, which will keep good many years, without having any rancid ſmell or taſte, but in two years become quite mild ; ſo that when the warm taſte of the feed, which is in the oil when firſt drawn, is worn off, they uſe it as a ſalad-oil, and for all the purpoſes of ſweet oil. The ſeeds oſ this plant are alſo uſed by the negroes for food ; which ſeeds they parch over the fire, and then mix them with water, and ſtew other ingredients with them, which makes an hearty food. Sometimes a fort of pudding is made of theſe ſeeds, in the ſame manner ,as with millet or rice, and is by ſome perſons eſteemed, but is rarely uſed for theſe purpoſes in Europe. This is called <hi rend="italic">benny</hi> or <hi rend="italic">bonny</hi> in Carolina. In England theſe plants are preſerved in botanic gardens as curiosities. Their ſeeds must be ſown in the ſpring upon a hot bed ; and when the plants are come up, they muſt be tranſplanted into a freſh hot-bed to bring them forward. After they have acquired a tolerable degree of ſtrength, they ſhould be planted into pots, and plunged into another hot-bed, managing them as hath been directed for amaranths ; for if theſe plants are not thus brought forward in the former part of the ſummer, they will not produce good ſeeds in this Country.</p><p>From nine pounds of this ſeed which came from Ca-</p></body></text></TEI>