<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:05:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſome of hardened clay, and others of lead. The floors of the temple of Venus were inlaid with agates and other precious ſtones ; the inſide lined with cypreſs wood ; the windows adorned with ivory paintings and ſmall ſtatues. There was likewiſe a library. This veſſel was adorned on all ſides with fine paintings. It had 20 benches of oars, and was encompaſſed with an iron rampart, eight towers, with walls and bulwarks, furniſhed with machines of war, particularly one which threw a ſtone of 300 pounds, or a dart 12 cubits long, the space of half a mile, with many other particulars related by Athenæus. Caligula likewiſe built a veſl’el adorned with jewels in the poop, with ſails of many colours, and furniſhed with large porticoes, bagnios, and banquet- ing-rooms, beſides rows of vines, and fruit-trees of various kinds. But these, and all ſuch monſtrous fabrics, ſerved only for ſhow and oſtentation, being rendered by their vaſt bulk unwieldy and unfit for ſervice. Athenæus informs us, the common names they were known by, were <hi rend="italic">Cyclades,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ætna,</hi> i. e. “ iſlands, or mountains,” to which they ſeemed nearly equal in bigneſs ; conſiſting, as ſome report, of as many materials as would have compoſed 50 triremes, or ſhips of three banks.</p><p>The veſſels employed by the northern nations appear to have been ſtill more imperfect than thoſe of the Romans ; for a law was enacted in the reign of the emperor Honorius, 24th September, A. D 418, inflicting capital puniſhment on any who ſhould inſtruct the barbarians in the art of ſhip-building ; a proof at once of the great eſtimation in which this ſcience was then held, and of the ignorance of the barbarians with regard to it.</p><p>The fleet of Richard I. of England, when he weighed anchor for the holy war from Meſſina, in Sicily, where he had paſſed the winter, A. D. 1190-1, is ſaid to have conſiſted of 150 great ſhips and 53 galleys, beſides barks, tartans, &amp;c. What kinds of ſhips theſe were is not mentioned. To the cruſades, however pernicious in other reſpects, this ſcience ſeems to owe ſome improvements ; and to this particular one we are indebted for Richard’s marine code, commonly called the <hi rend="italic">Laws of Oleron,</hi> from the name of a ſmall iſland on the coaſt of France, where he compoſed them, and which moſt of the nations in Europe have made the baſis of their maritime regulations. Thoſe ſhips, if they merited the name of ſhips, were probably very ſmall, as we find that ſo long after as the time of Edward I. <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1304, 40 men were deemed ſufficient to man the beſt and largeſt veſſels in England ; and that Edward the Third, <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1335, ordained the mayor and ſheriffs of London to “ take up all ſhips in their port, and all other ports in the kingdom, of the burden of 40 tons and upwards, and to furniſh the ſame with armed men and other neceſſaries of war, against the Scots his enemies, conſederated with certain perſons of foreign nations.” Edward the Third’s fleet before Calais, <hi rend="italic">anno </hi>1347, conſiſted of 738 Engliſh ſhips, carrying 14,956 mariners, being on an average but 20 men to each ſhip ; 15 ſhips and 459 mariners, from Bayonne in Guienne, being 30 men to each ſhip ; 7 ſhips and 184 men from Spain, which is 26 men to each ſhip ; one from Ireland, carrying 25 men ; 14 from Flanders, with 133 men,</p><p>being ſcarcely 10 men to each ſhip ; and one from Guelderland, with 24 mariners. Fifteen of theſe were called the king’s own ſhips, manned with 419 mariners, being ſomewhat under 17 to each ſhip.</p><p>Hiſtorians repreſent the veſsels of Venice and Genoa as the largeſt and the beſt about this time, but they were loon exceeded in ſize by the Spaniſh veſſels called c<hi rend="italic">arricks,</hi> ſome of which carried cannon ; and theſe again were exceeded by the veſſels built by the northern people, particularly thoſe belonging to the Hanſe-towns.— In the 14th century, the Hanſiatics were the ſovereigns of the northern ſeas, as well without as within the Baltic ; and their ſhips were ſo large, that foreign princes often hired them in their wars. According to Hakluyt, an Engliſh ſhip from Newcaſtle, of 200 tons burden, was ſeized in the Baltic by thoſe of Wiſmar and Roſtock, <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1394 ; and another Engliſh veſſel of the ſame burden was violently ſeized in the port of Liſhon, <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1412.</p><p>Soon after ſhips of a much larger ſize were conducted. It is mentioned that a very large ſhip was built, <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1449, by John Taverner of Hull ; and in the year 1455, king Henry IV. at the requeſt of Charles king of Sweden, granted a licence for a Swediſh ſhip of the burden of a thouſand tons or under, laden with merchandize, and having 120 perſons on board, to come to the ports of England, there to diſpoſe of their lading, and to relade back with Engliſh merchandize, paying the uſual cuſtoms The inſcription on the tomb of William Canning, an eminent merchant, who had been five times mayor of Briſtol, in Ratcliff-church at Briſtol, <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1474, mentions his having forfeited the king’s peace, for which he was condemned to pay 300 merks ; in lieu of which ſum, king Edward IV. took of him 247⁰ tons of ſhipping, amongſt which there was one ſhip of 900 tons burden, another of 500 tons, and one of 400 tons, the rest being ſmaller.</p><p>In the year 1506, king James IV. of Scotland built the largeſt ſhip which had hitherto been ſeen, but which was lost in her way to France in the year 1512, owing probably to a defective conſtruction, and the unskilfulneſs of the crew in managing ſo large a ſhip.	</p><p>About this time a very large ſhip was likewiſe built in France. In the fleet fitted out by Henry VIII, <hi rend="italic">anno</hi> 1512, there was one ſhip, the Regent, of 1000 tons burden, one of 500, and three of 400 each. A ſhip ſtill larger than the Regent was built ſoon after, called <hi rend="italic">Henri Grace Dieu l</hi> In the year 1522 the ſirſt voyage round the globe was finiſhed.</p><p>The Engliſh naval hiſtorians think that ſhips carried cannon on their upper decks only, and had not gun- ports before the year 1545 ; and it is certain that many of the largeſt ſhips in former times were fitted out from harbours, where ſhips of a moderate ſize now would not have water enough to float them. In 1575 the whole of the royal navy did not exceed 24 ſhips, and the number of merchant-ſhips belonging to England amounted to no more than 135 veſſels above 100 tons, and 656 between 40 and 100 tons. At queen Elizabeth’s death, anno 1603, there were not above four</p><p>merchant-ſhips in England of 400 tons burden each.	</p><p>I he largeſt of queen Elizabeth’s ſhips of war was 1000 tons burden, carrying but 340 men, and 40 guns, and</p></body></text></TEI>