<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:06:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>vertical ſection paſſing through the keel, and dividing the ſhip into two equal and
                similar parts, at a certain diſtance from the ſtern, and altitude above the
                heel.</p>
            <p>ln order to determine the centre of gravity of the immerſed part of a (hip’s bottom,
                we muſt begin with determining the centre of gravity of a ſection of the ſhip
                parallel to the keel, as ANDFPB (fig. 56.), bounded by the parallel lines AB, DF,
                and by the equal and ſimilar curves AND, BPF.</p>
            <p>If the equation of this curve were known, its centre of gravity would be eaſily found
                : but as this is not the case, let therefore the line CE be drawn through the middle
                C, E, of the lines AB, DF, and let this line CE be divided into ſo great a number of
                equal parts by the perpendiculars TH, KM, &amp;c. that the arches of the curves
                contained between the extremities of any two adjacent perpendiculars may be
                conſidered as ſtraight lines. The momentums of the trapeziums DTHF, TKMH, &amp;c.
                relative to the point E, are then to be found, and the ſum of theſe momentums is to
                be divided by the ſum of the trapeziums, that is, by the ſurface ANDFPB.</p>
            <p>The diſtance of the centre of gravity of the trapezium THFD from the point E is = <hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi> IE x DF+2TH DF+TH @@*. For
                the ſame reaſon, and becauſe of the equality of the lines IE, IL, the diſtance of
                the centre of gravity of the trapezium TKMH from the ſame point E will be <hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>IE×(TH+2 KM) <hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3</hi>IE ×(4TH+5KM)</p>
            <p>TH + KM +IE, or = TH+KM^∙ In like manner, the diſtance of the centre of gravity of
                the trapezium NKMP from the point E will be <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">3</hi>IE×(KM+2NP) + 2IE×(<hi rend="subscript">7</hi>KM<hi
                    rend="subscript">+</hi>8NP) KM+NP KM+NP &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now, if each diſtance be multiplied by the ſurface of the correſponding trapezium,
                that is, by the product of half the ſum of the two oppoſite ſides of the trapezium
                into the common altitude IE, we ſhall have the momentums of theſe trapeziums,
                namely, <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">6</hi> IE<hi
                    rend="superscript">2</hi>×(DF+2TH), <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">6</hi> IE<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> × (4 TH + 5KM) <hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">6</hi> IE<hi rend="superscript"
                    >2</hi> X (7 KM + 8NP), &amp;c. Hence the ſum of theſe momentums will be <hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">6</hi> IE<hi rend="superscript"
                    >2</hi>× (DF+6TH+12 KM + 18 NP+24QS+14 AB). Whence it may be remarked, that if
                the line CE be divided into a great number of equal parts, the factor or coefficient
                of the laſt term, which is here 14, will be = 2 + 3 (n—2) or 3 <hi rend="italic"
                    >n—</hi>4, <hi rend="italic">n</hi> being the number of perpendiculars. Thus the
                general expreſſion of the ſum of the momentums is reduced to IE x (<hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">6</hi> DF + TH + 2 KM + 3 NP + 4
                QS +, &amp;c. —+ 3n-4 × AB).</p>
            <p>The area of the figure ANDFPB is equal to IE × (4 DF + TH + KM + N P +, &amp;c... .+
                4AB) ; hence the diſtance EG of the centre of gravity G from one of the extreme
                ordinates DF is equal to IE × (<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                    >6</hi>DF+TH+2 KM+3 NP+, &amp;c.+3n-4 AB)</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">6</hi></p>
            <p> 4 DF + IH+KM + NP+, &amp;c. + <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript"
                    >2</hi> AB </p>
            <p>Whence the following rule to find the diſtance of the centre of gravity G from one of
                the extreme ordinates DF. To the ſixth of the firſt ordinate add the sixth of the
                laſt ordinate multiplied by three times the number of ordinates minus four ; then
                the ſecond ordinate, twice the third, three times the fourth, &amp;c. the ſum will
                be a firſt term. Then to half the ſum oſ the extreme ordinates add all the
                intermediate ones, and the ſum will be a second term. Now the firſt term divided by
                the second, and the quotient multiplied by the interval between two adjacent
                perpendiculars, will be the diſtance ſought.</p>
            <p>Thus, let there be seven perpendiculars, whoſe values are 18, 23, 28, 30, 30, 21, 0,
                feet respectively, and the common interval between theſe perpendiculars. 20 feet.
                Now the ſixth of the firſt term 18 is 3 ; and as the laſt term is 0, therefore to 3
                add 23, twice 28 or 56, thrice 30 or 90, four times 30 or 120, five times 21 or <hi
                    rend="italic">105</hi> ; and the ſum is 397. Then to the half of 18 + 0, or 9,
                add the intermediate ordinates, and the ſum will be 141. Now 397 x 20, or 7940, = 59
                feet</p>
            <p><hi rend="subscript"> 141 or</hi> 141</p>
            <p>4 inches nearly, the diſtance of the centre of gravity from the firſt ordinate.</p>
            <p>Now, when the centre of gravity of any ſection is. determined, it is easy from thence
                to find the centre of gravity of the ſolid, and conſequently that of the bottom of a
                ſhip.</p>
            <p>The next ſtep is to find the height of the centre of gravity of the bottom above the
                keel. For this purpoſe the bottom muſt be imagined to be divided into ſections by
                planes parallel to the keel or water-line, (figs. 37, 58.) Then the solidity of each
                portion contained between two parallel planes will be equal to half the ſum of the
                two oppoſed ſurfaces multiplied by the diſtance between them ; and its centre of
                gravity will be at the ſame altitude as that of the trapezium <hi rend="italic"
                    >abcd,</hi> (fig. 58.), which is in the vertical ſection paſſing through the
                keel. It is hence obvious, that the ſame rule as before is to be applied to find the
                altitude of the centre of gravity, with this difference only, that the word
                perpendicular or ordinate is to be changed into ſection. Hence the rule is, to the
                ſixth part of the loweſt ſection add the product of the ſixth part of the uppermoſt
                ſection by three times the number of ſections minus four ; the second ſection in
                aſcending twice the third, three times the fourth, &amp;c. the ſum will be a firſt
                term. To half the ſum of upper and lower ſections add the intermediate ones, the ſum
                will be a second term. Divide the firſt term by the second, and the quotient
                multiplied by the diſtance between the ſections will give the altitude of the centre
                of gravity above the keel.</p>
            <p>With regard to the centre of gravity of a ſhip, whether it is conſidered as loaded or
                light, the operation becomes more difficult. The momentum of every different part of
                the ſhip and cargo muſt be found ſeparately with reſpect to a horizontal and alſo a
                vertical: plane. Now the ſums of theſe two momentums being divided by the weight of
                the ſhip, will give the altitude of the centre of gravity, and its diſtance from the
                vertical plane ; and as this centre is in a vertical plane paſſing through the axis
                of the keel, its place is therefore determined. In the calculation of the momentums,
                it muſt be obſerved to multiply the weight, and not the magnitude of each piece, by
                the diſtance of its centre of gravity.</p>
            <p>A more eaſy method of finding the centre of gravity of a ſhip is by a mechanical
                operation, as follows; Conſtruct</p>
            <p>***[m] <hi rend="italic">Brand's Mechanique,</hi> ar. 279.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
