<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:05:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ducks, teal, whaps, foists, lyres, kittiwaiks, maws, plovers, cormorants, &amp;c. There is likewiſe the ember-gooſe, which is ſaid to hatch her egg under her wing. Eagles and hawks, as alſo ravens, crows, mews,&amp;c. abound here.</p><p>All theſe iſlands are well watered ; for there are everywhere excellent ſprings, ſome of them mineral and medicinal. They have indeed no rivers ; but many pleaſant rills or rivulets, which they call <hi rend="italic">burns,</hi> of different ſizes ; in ſome of the largeſt they have admirable trouts, ſome of which are of 15 and even of 20 pounds weight. They have likewiſe many freſh-water lakes, well ſtored with trout and eels, and in most of them there are alſo large and fine flounders ; in ſome very excellent cod. Theſe freſh water lakes, if the country was better peopled, and the common people more at their eaſe, are certainly capable of great improvements. The ſea- coaſts of the main land of Shetland, in a ſtraight line, are 55 leagues ; and therefore there cannot be a country conceived more proper for eſtabliſhing an extenſive  fiſhery. What the inhabitants have been hitherto able to do, their natural advantages conſidered, does not deserve that name, notwithſtanding they export large quantities of cod, tuſk, ling, and slate, inſomuch that the bounty allowed by acts of parliament amounts from L. 1400 to L. 2000 annually. They have, beſides, haddocks, whitings, turbot, and a variety of other  fish. In many of the inlets there are prodigious quantities of excellent oyſters, lobſters, muſcles, cockles, and other ſhell-fiſh. As to amphibious creatures, they have multitudes of otters and ſeals ; add to theſe, that amber, ambergris, and other ſpoils of the ocean, are frequently found upon the coaſts.</p><p>The inhabitants are a ſtout, well-made, comely people ; the lower sort of a ſwarthy complexion. The gentry are allowed, by all who have converſed, with them, to be moſt of them polite, ſhrewd, ſenſible, lively, active, and intelligent perſons ; and theſe, to the number of 100 families, have very handſome, ſtrong, well-built houſes, neatly furniſhed ; their tables well ſerved, poliſhed in their manners, and exceedingly hoſpitable and civil to ſtrangers. Thoſe of an inferior rank are a hardy, rebuff, and laborious people, who, generally ſpeaking, get their bread by fiſhing in all weathers in their yawls, which are little bigger than Graveſend wherries ; live hardily, and in the ſummer seaſon moſtly on fiſh ; their drink, which, in reference to the British dominions, is peculiar to the country, is called <hi rend="italic">bland,</hi> apd is a sort of butter-milk, long kept, and very sour. Many live to great ages, though not ſo long as in former times. In reſpect, however, to the bulk of the inhabitants, from the poorneſs of living, from the nature of it, and from the drinking great quantities of corn-ſpirits of the very worſt sort, multitudes are afflicted with an inveterate ſcurvy ; from which thoſe in better circumſtances are entirely free, and enjoy as good health as in any other country in Europe. As they have no great turn to agriculture, and are perſuaded that their country is not fit for it, they do not (though probably they might) raiſe corn enough to ſupport them for more than two-thirds of the year. But they are much more ſucceſsful in their paſture-grounds, which are kept well incloſed, in good order, and, together with their commons, supply them plentifully with beef and mutton. They pay their</p><p>rents generally in butter at Lammas, and in money at Martinmas. As to manufactures, they make a strong coarſe cloth for their own uſe, as alſo linen. They make likewiſe of their own wool very fine ſtockings. They export, beſides the different kinds of fiſh already mentioned, ſome herrings, a conſiderable quantity of butter and train-oil, otter and ſeal ſkins,and no inconſiderable quantity of the fine ſtockings just mentioned. Their chief trade is to Leith, London, Hamburgh, Spain, and to the Straits. They import timbers, deals, and ſome of their beſt oats, from Norway ; corn and flour from the Orkneys, and from North Britain ; ſpirits and ſome other things from Hamburgh ; cloths and better sort of linen from Leith ; grocery, houſehold furniture, and other neceſſaries, from London. The ſuperior-duties to the earl of Morton are generally let in farm ; and are paid by the people in butter, oil, and money. The remains of the old Norwegian conſtitution are ſtill viſible in the diviſion of their lands ; and they have ſome udalmen or freeholders amongſt them. But the Scots laws, cuſtoms, manners, dreſs, and language, prevail ; and they have a ſheriff, and other magiſtrates for the adminiſtration of juſtice, as well as a cuſtomhouſe, with a proper number of officers. In reference to their eccleſiaſtical concerns, they have a preſbytery, 12 miniſters, and an itinerant for Foula, Fair Island, and the Skerries. Each of theſe miniſters has a ſtipend of between 40 and 50 pounds, beſides a houſe and a glebe free from taxes·. The number of ſouls in theſe iſlands may be about 20,0c0.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SHEW-bread,</hi> the loaves of bread which the prieſt of the week put every Sabbath-day upon the golden- table in the ſanctuary, before the Lord, in the temple of the Jews. They were twelve in number, and were offered to God in the name of the twelve tribes of Iſrael. They were ſhaped like a brick, were ten palms long and five broad, weighing about eight pounds each. They were unleavened, and made of fine flour by the Levites. The prieſts ſet them on. the table in two rows, six in a row, and put frankincenſe upon them to preſerve them from moulding. They were changed every Sabbath, and the old ones belonged to the prieſt upon duty. Of this bread none but the prieſts might eat, except in caſes of neceſſity. It was called the <hi rend="italic">bread of faces, </hi>becauſe the table of the ſhew-bread, being almoſt over- againſt the ark of the covenant, the loaves might be ſaid to be ſet before the face of God. The original table was carried away to Babylon, but a new one was made for the second temple. It was of wood overlaid with gold. This, with the candleſtick and ſome other ſpoils, was carried by Titus to Rome.</p><p>SHIELD, an ancient weapon of defence, in form of a light buckler, borne on the arm to fend off lances, darts, &amp;c. The form of the ſhield is repreſented by the eſcutcheon in coats of arms. The ſhield was that part of the ancient armour on which the perſons of diſtinction in the field of battle always had their arms painted ; and moſt of the words uſed at this time to expreſs the ſpace that holds the arms of families are derived from the Latin name for a s<hi rend="italic">hield, scutum.</hi> The French <hi rend="italic">eſcu and escussion,</hi> and the Engliſh word <hi rend="italic">eſcutcheon, </hi>or, as we commonly ſpeak it, sc<hi rend="italic">utcheon,</hi> are evidently from this origin ; and the Italian <hi rend="italic">ſcudo</hi> signifies both the ſhield of arms and that uſed in war. The Latin name <hi rend="italic">clypeus,</hi> for the ſame thing, ſeems alſo to be derived from</p></body></text></TEI>