<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:04:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>or laſt ſtate, feed on the liver of the animal, and occasion this diſorder.</p><p>It is a ſingular fact, “ that no ewe ever has the rot while ſhe has a lamb by her ſide.” The reaſon of this may be, that the impregnated ovum passes into the milk, and never arrives at the liver. The rot is fatal to ſheep, hares, and rabbits, and ſometimes to calves ; but never infeſts animals of a larger ſize.</p><p>Miller says that parſley is a good remedy for the rot in ſheep. Perhaps a ſtrong decoction of this plant, or the oil extracted from its ſeeds, might be of ſervice. Salt is alſo a uſeful remedy. It ſeems to be an acknowledged fact that ſalt marſhes never produce the rot. Salt indeed is pernicious to most infects. Common ſalt and water expel worms from the human body; and ſea-weed, if laid in a garden, will drive away infects ; but if the ſalt is ſeparated by ſteeping it in the pureſt ſpring-water for a few days, it abounds with animalcule of various ſpecies.</p><p>Liſle, in his book of huſbandry, informs us of a farmer who cured his whole flock of the rot by giving each ſheep a handful of Spaniſh ſalt for five or six mornings ſucceſſively. The hint was probably taken from the Spaniards, who frequently give their ſheep ſalt to keep them healthy. On ſome farms perhaps the utmoſt caution cannot always prevent this diſorder. In wet and warm ſeaſons the prudent farmer will remove his ſheep from the lands liable to rot. Thoſe who have it not in their power to do this may give each ſheep a ſpoonful of common ſalt, with the ſame quantity of flour, in a quarter of a pint of water, once or twice a-week. When the rot is recently taken, the ſame remedy given four or five mornings ſucceſſively will in all probability effect a cure. The addition of the flour and water (in the opinion of Mr Price of Saliſhury, to whole excellent paper in the Bath Society’s Tranſactions we own ourſelves much indebted) will not only abate the pungency of the ſalt, but diſpoſe it to mix with the chyle in a more gentle and efficacious manner.</p><p>A farmer of a conſiderable lordſhip in Bohemia visiting the hot-wells of Carlſhad, related how he preſerved his flocks of ſheep from the mortal diſtemper which raged in the wet year 1769, of which ſo many periſhed. His preſervative was very simple and very cheap : “ He ſed them every night, when turned under a ſhed, cover, or ſtables, with haſhed fodder ſtraw ; and, by eating it greedily, they all eſcaped.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">" Red-water</hi> is a diſorder moſt prevalent on wet grounds. I have heard (says Mr Arthur Young) that it has ſomctimes been cured by tapping, as for a dropſy. This operation is done on one side of the belly towards the flank, just below the wool.</p><p><hi rend="italic">“ The foot-rot</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hoving,</hi> which is very common on low fenny grounds, is cured by keeping the part clean, and lying at rest in a dry paſture.”</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">ſcab</hi> is a cutaneous diſeaſe owing to an impurity of the blood, and is moſt prevalent in wet lands or in rainy ſeaſons. It is cured by tobacco-water, brimſtone, and alum, boiled together, and then rubbed ever the ſheep. If only partial, tar and greaſe may be sufficient. But the ſimpleſt and moſt efficacious remedy for this diſeaſe was communicated to the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, &amp;c, by Sir Joſeph Banks. " Take one pound of quickſilver, half a pound of Venice turpentine, half a pint of oil of turpentine, and four pounds of hogs lard @@(c). Let them be rubbed in a mortar till the quickſilver is thoroughly incorporated with the other ingredients ; for the proper mode of doing which, it may be proper to take the advice, or even the aſſiſtance, of ſome apothecary or other perſon uſed to make ſuch mixtures.</p><p>“ The method of uſing the ointment is this : Beginning at the head of the ſheep, and proceeding from between the ears along the back to the end of the tail, the wool is to be divided in a furrow till the ſkin can be touched ; and as the furrow is made, the finger ſlightly dipped in the ointment is to be drawn along the bottom of it, where it will leave a blue ſtain on the ſkin and adjoining wool : from this furrow similar ones must be drawn down the ſhoulders and thighs to the legs, as far as they are woolly ; and if the animal is much infected, two more ſhould be drawn along each ſide parallel to that on the back, and one down each ſide between the fore and hind legs.</p><p>“ Immediately after being dreſſed, it is uſual to turn the ſheep among other ſtock, without any fear of the infection being communicated ; and there is ſearcely an inſtance of a ſheep ſuffering any injury from the application in a few days the blotches dry up, the itching ceaſes, and the animal is completely cured : it is generally, however, thought proper not to delay the operation beyond Michaelmas.</p><p>“ The <hi rend="italic">hippoboſca ovina,</hi>called in Lincolnshire sheep f<hi rend="italic">agg, </hi>an animal well known to all ſhepherds, which lives among the wool, and is hurtful to the thriving of ſheep both by the pain its bite occaſions and the blood it  sucks, is deſtroyed by this application, and the wool is not at all injured. Our wool-buyers purchaſe the fleeces on which the ſtain of the ointment is viſible, rather in preference to others, from an opinion that the uſe of it having preſerved the animal from being vexed either with the ſcab or faggs, the wool is leſs liable to the defects of joints or knots; a fault obſerved to proceed from every ſudden flop in the thriving of the animal, either from want of food or from diſeaſe.</p><p>“ This mode of curing was brought into that part of Lincolnſhire where my property is ſituated about 13 years ago, by Mr Stephenſon of Mareham, and is now ſo generally received, that the ſcab, which uſed to be the terror of the farmers, and which frequently deterred the more careful of them from taking the advantage of paſturing their ſheep in the fertile and extenſive commons with which that diſtrict abounds, is no longer regarded with any apprehenſion : by far the moſt of them have their flock anointed in autumn, when they return from the common, whether they ſhow any ſymptons of ſcab or not ; and having done ſo, conclude</p><p>@@@(c) By ſome unaccountable miſtake the laſt ingredient, the four pounds of hogs lard, is omitted in the receipt publiſhed in the Tranſactions of the Society ; a circumſtance that might be productive of bad effects.--· The leaf which contained the receipt has since been cancelled, and a new one printed.</p></body></text></TEI>