<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:02:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>he hitherto diſtinguiſhed himſelſ by the claſſical elegance of his compoſitions, that he was ſoon called upon to fill the important poſt of private Latin ſecretary to the emperor, who was then in Italy. This was the moſt honourable office to which our author was ever appointed; but before he could enter upon it death put a ſtop to his career of glory. Having arrived at <hi rend="italic">Saint Amand</hi> in the diſtrict of <hi rend="italic">Tournαy,</hi> in order to meet, upon buſineſs, with the biſhop of Utrecht, he was on the 8th of October 1536 cut off by a violent fever, in the very flower of his age, not having quite completed his twenty-fifth year. He was interred in the church of the Benedictines, of which his patron, the biſhop, was <hi rend="italic">abbot</hi> or <hi rend="italic">pro-abbot; </hi>and his near relations erected to his memory a marble monument, with a plain Latin inſcription.</p><p>The works of Secundus have gone through ſeveral editions, of which the beſt and moſt copious is that of Scriverius already mentioned. It conſiſts of <hi rend="smallcaps">Julia, </hi><hi rend="italic">Eleg. Lib.</hi> I.; <hi rend="smallcaps">Amores, </hi><hi rend="italic">Eleg. Lib.</hi> 2.; <hi rend="smallcaps">ad Diversos </hi><hi rend="italic">Eleg. Lib.</hi> 3.; <hi rend="smallcaps">Basia,</hi> ſtyled by the editor <hi rend="italic">incomparabilis et divinus prorſus liber; </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Epigrammata; Odarum </hi><hi rend="italic">liber unus; </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Epistolarum </hi><hi rend="italic">liber unus Elegiaca; </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Epistolarum </hi><hi rend="italic">liber alter, heroico carmine ſcriptus; </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Funerum </hi><hi rend="italic">liber unus; </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Sylvæ </hi><hi rend="italic">et </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Carminum </hi><hi rend="italic">fragmenta; </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Poemata </hi><hi rend="italic">nonnulla ſratrum; </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Itineraria </hi><hi rend="italic">Secundi tria,</hi> &amp;c.; <hi rend="smallcaps">EpisTolæ </hi><hi rend="italic">totidem, ſoluta oratione.</hi> Of theſe works it would be ſuperfluous in us to give any character after the ample teſtimonies prefixed to them of <hi rend="italic">Lelius Greg. Gyraldus,</hi> the elder <hi rend="italic">Sea liger, Theodore Beza,</hi> and others equally celebrated in the republic of letters, who all ſpeak of them with rapture. A French critic, indeed, after having affirmed that the genius of Secundus never produced any thing which was not excellent in its kind, adds, with too much truth, <hi rend="italic">Mais sa muſe est un peu trop laſcive.</hi> For this fault our author makes the following apology in an epigram addreſſed to the grammarians;</p><p>Carmina cur ſpargam cunctis laſciva libellis,</p><p>Queritis? Inſulſos arceo grammaticos.</p><p>Fortia magnanimi canerem ſi Cæſaris arma,</p><p>Factave <hi rend="smallcaps">Divorum</hi> religioſa <hi rend="smallcaps">virum:</hi></p><p>Quot miser exciperemque notas, patererque lituras? Quot fierem teneris ſupplicium pueris?</p><p>At nunc uda mihi dictant cum <hi rend="smallcaps">Basia</hi> carmen,</p><p>Pruriet et verſu mentula multa meo;</p><p>Me leget innuptæ juvenis placiturus amicae,</p><p>Et placitura nova blanda puella viro:</p><p>Et quemcunque juvat lepidorum de grege vatum</p><p>Otia feſtivis ludere deliciis.</p><p>Luſibus et laetis procul hinc abſiſtite, <hi rend="smallcaps">sævi</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Grammatici,</hi> injuſtas et cohibite manus.</p><p>Ne puer, ab malleis cæſus lacrymanſque leporis;</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Duram forte meis ossibus optet humum.</hi></p><p>SECURIDACA, a plant belonging to the claſs of diadelphia, and to the order of octandria The calyx has three leaves, which are ſmall, deciduous, and coloured. The corolla is papilionaceous. The vexillum, conſiſting of two petals, is oblong, ſtraight, and conjoined to the carina at the baſe. The carina is of the ſame length with the alæ. The legumen is ovated, unilocular, monoſpermous, and ending in a ligulated ala. There are two ſpecies, the <hi rend="italic">erecta</hi> and <hi rend="italic">volubilis.</hi> The erecta has an upright item: the volubilis or ſcandens is a climbing plant, and is a native of the Weſt Indies.</p><p>SECUTORES, a ſpecies of gladiators among the Romans, whoſe arms were a helmet, a ſhield, and a ſword or a leaden bullet. They were armed in this manner, becauſe they had to contend with the retiarii, who were dreſſed in a ſhort tunic, bore a three-pointed lance in their left hand, and a net in their right. The retiarius attempted to caſt his net over the head of the ſecutor; and <hi rend="italic">if</hi> he ſucceeded, he drew it together and flew him with his trident: but if he miſſed his aim, he immediately betook himſelſ to flight till he could find a ſecond opportunity of intangling his adverſary with his net. He was purſued by the ſecutor, who endeavoured to diſpatch him in his flight.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Secutores</hi> was alſo a name given to ſuch gladiators who took the place of thoſe killed in the combat, or who engaged the conqueror. This poſt was uſually taken by lot.</p><p>SEDAN is a town of Champagne in France, in E. Long. 4. 45. N. Lat. 49. 46. This is the capital of a principality of the ſame name, ſituated on the Maeſe,  ſix miles from Bouillon, and fifteen from Charleville. Its ſituation on the frontiers of the territory of Liege, Namur, and Limburg, formerly rendered it one of the keys of the kingdom. It is extremely well fortified, and defended by a ſtrong citadel. The caſtle is ſituated on a rock, ſurrounded with large towers and ſtrong walls: here you ſee a moſt beautiful magazine of ancient arms. The governor’s palace is oppoſite the caſtle. From the ramparts you have a moſt agreeable proſpect of the Maeſe and the neighbouring country. Though the town is but ſmall, yet it is full of tradeſmen, as tanners, weavers, dyers, &amp;c. the manufacture of fine cloth in this city employing a great number of hands. The principality of Sedan formerly belonged to the duke of Bouillon, who was obliged in the beginning of the laſt century to reſign it to the crown.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SEDAN-chAir</hi> is a covered vehicle for carrying a ſingle perſon, ſuſpended by two poles, and borne by two men, hence denominated <hi rend="italic">chairmen.</hi> They were firſt introduced in London in 1634, when Sir Sanders Duncomb obtained the ſole privilege to uſe, let, and hire a number of the ſaid covered chairs for fourteen years.</p><p>SEDITION, among civilians, is uſed for a factious commotion of the people, or an aſſembly of a number of citizens without lawful authority, tending to diſturb the peace and order of the ſociety. This offence is of different kinds: ſome ſeditions more immediately threatening the ſupreme power, and the ſubverſion of the preſent conſtitution of the ſtate; others tending only towards the redreſs of private grievances. Among the Romans, therefore, it was variouſly puniſhed, according as its end and tendency threatened greater miſchieſ. See lib. i. <hi rend="italic">Cod. de Seditiosis,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mat. de Crimin. lib.</hi> ii. n. 5. <hi rend="italic">de Loeſa Majestate.</hi> In the puniſhment, the authors and ringleaders were justly diſtinguished from thoſe who, with leſs wicked intention, joined and made part of the multitude.</p><p>The ſame diſtinction holds in the law of England and in that of Scotland. Some kinds of Edition in England amount to high treaſon, and come within the flat. 25 Edw. III. as levying war againſt the king. And ſeveral ſeditions are mentioned in the Scotch acts of parliament as treaſonable. <hi rend="italic">Bayne’s Grim. Law of Scotland,</hi> p. 33, 34. The law of Scotland makes riotous and tumultuous aſſemblies a ſpecies of ſedition. But the law there, as well as in England, is now chiefly</p></body></text></TEI>