<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb07-19-r01-0164-05" facs="eb07_19_Page_175.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RESIDUAL</label>
Analysis, a calculus invented by Mr Landen, and proposed as a substitute for the method of fluxions. The design of it was to avoid introducing the idea of motion, and of quantities infinitely small, into mathematical investigation. The residual analysis accordingly proceeds by taking the difference of the same function of a variable quantity in two different states of the said variable quantity, and denoting the relation of this difference to the difference between the two states of the said variable quantity. This relation being first generally expressed, is next considered in the case when the difference of the two states of the variable quantity is = 0 ; and by that means it is obvious that the same thing is done as when the function cf a variable quantity is assigned by the ordinary methods.</p><p>The evolutions of the functions, considered in this very general view, require the aid of a new theorem, discovered by Mr Landen, and remarkable for its simplicity and great extent. It is, that if <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">v</hi> are any two variable quantities</p><p>A→ <hi rend="sup">1</hi> +^ + g + <hi rend="underline">g+......( <hi rend="sup">w</hi> )</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">-</hi> — <hi rend="italic">χ <hi rend="sup">n</hi></hi> y-</p><p><hi rend="italic">X- V m</hi> 2m 3m</p><p>-+er÷e)'÷er......&lt;∙&gt;</p><p>where <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and <hi rend="italic">n</hi> are any integer numbers.</p><p>This theorem is the basis of tile calculus, and from the <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup"> m</hi> m</hi></p><p>expressions <hi rend="italic">x <hi rend="sup">n</hi> — v",</hi> and <hi rend="italic">x — v</hi> having the form of what algebraists denominate <hi rend="italic">residuals,</hi> the inventor gave to his method the name of the <hi rend="italic">residual analysis.</hi></p><p>Mr Landen published the first account of this method in 1758, which he denominated a Discourse concerning the Residual Analysis. The first book of the analysis appeared in 1764, and contained an explanation of the principles of the new calculus, with its application to problems of the direct method of fluxions ; the second book, which solved several problems of the inverse method, was never published.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Residual</hi> <hi rend="italic">Figure,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> the figure remaining after the subtraction of the less from the greater.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Residual</hi> <hi rend="italic">Root</hi> is a root composed of two members only connected by the sign — or minus. Thus, β— <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> or 5 — 3, is a residual root ; and is so called, because its true value is no more than the residue or difference between the parts <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> or 5 and 3, which in this case is 2.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>