<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb07-19-r01-0075-03" facs="eb07_19_Page_086.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RATIO</label>
in <hi rend="italic">Arithmetic</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Geometry,</hi> is that relation of homogeneous things which determines the quantity of one from the quantity of another, without the intervention of a third.</p><p>The numbers, lines, or quantities, A and B, being proposed, their relation one to another may be considered under one or other of these two heads : 1. How much A exceeds B, or B exceeds A ; which is found by taking A from B, or B from A, and is called <hi rend="italic">arithmetical reason</hi> or <hi rend="italic">rαtia.</hi> 2. How many times, or parts of a time, A contains B, or B contains A ; which is called <hi rend="italic">geometrical reason</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ratio,</hi> or, as Euclid defines it, the <hi rend="italic">mutual habitude,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">respect,</hi> of two magnitudes of the same kind, according to quantity, that is, llow often the one contains or is contained in the other ; and this is found by dividing A by B, or B by A. But observe, that that quantity which is referred to another quantity is called the <hi rend="italic">antecedent e&gt;f the ratio ;</hi> and that to which the other is referred is called the <hi rend="italic">consequent of the ratio.</hi> In the ratio of A to B, A is the antecedent, and B the consequent. Therefore any quantity as antecedent, divided by any quantity as a consequent, gives the ratio of that antecedent to the consequent.</p><p>Thus the ratio of A to B is <hi rend="italic">∙q <hi rend="sub">r</hi> ,</hi> but the ratio of B to A is B</p><p>B 12</p><p>— ; and, in numbers, the ratio of 12 to 4 is — = 3, or tri-A ⅛</p><p>4 1</p><p>ple ; but the ratio of 4 to 12 is — = -, or subtriple.</p><p>1 &lt;~ «5</p><p>And here observe, that the quantities thus compared must be of the same kind ; that is, such as by multiplication may be made the one to exceed the other, or as these quantities are said to have a ratio between them, which, being multiplied, may be made to exceed one another. Thus a line, how short soever, may be multiplied, that is, produced so as to exceed any given right line ; and consequently these may be compared together, and the ratio expressed. But as a line can never, by any multiplication whatever, be made to have breadth, that is, to be equal to a superficies, however small, so these can never be compared together, and consequently have no ratio or respect to one another, according to quantity ; that is, how often the one contains or is contained in the other.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>