<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0673.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0592-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SECT</label>
. IΠ. ON THE MATHEMATICAL LAW WHICH CON</p><p>NECTS THE ELASTIC FORCE OP VAPOUR WITH ITS</p><p>TEMPERATURE.</p><p>*35. An inference which may be drawn from all these experiments is, that Nature seems to affect a certain law in the dilatation of aeriform fluids by heat. They seem to be dilatable nearly in the proportion of their present dilatation. For, if we suppose the vapours to resemble air in having their elasticity in any given temperature proportional to their density, we must suppose that if steam of the elasticity 60, that is, under a pressure of 60 inches of mercury, were subjected to a pressure of 30 inches, it would expand into twice its present bulk. The augmentation of elasticity, therefore, is the measure of the bulk into which it would expand, in order to acquire its former elasticity. Taking the increase of elasticity, as a measure of the bulk into which it would expand under one constant pressure, we see that equal increments of temperature produce nearly equal multi plications of bulk. Thus, if a certain diminution of temperature, diminishes the bulk of steam ½, another equal diminution will very nearly diminish this new bulk ½. Thus, in our experiments (Art. 25), <hi rend="italic">the temperatures being in arithmetical progression, having equal differences, we see that the corresponding elasticities are very nearly in the continued proportion of</hi> 1 to 2, <hi rend="italic">thus :</hi></p><p>Temperatures 110° 140° 170° 200° 230°</p><p>Corresponding Elasticities } <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 25 5</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 15 11.05 22</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 62 44.7</hi> ∙</p><p>Now, although extreme temperatures differ considerably from this law, still we see that there is a considerable approximation to it ; and it will frequently assist us, to recollect that within these limits an increase of 30° of temperature nearly doubles the elasticity and bulk of watery vapour.</p><p>This law obtains exactly in air and other gases, all of which are subject to the Boylean law, or law of Marriotte, as it is called, and have their elasticity proportional to their bulk inversely. If the bulk were always augmented in the same proportion by equal augmentations of temperature, the elasticities would be accurately represented by the ordinates of a logarithmic curve, of which the temperatures are the corresponding abscissæ ; and we might contrive such a scale for our thermometer, that the temperatures would be the common logarithms of the elasticities, or of the bulks having equal elasticity ; or, with our present scale, we may find such a multiplier <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> for the number <hi rend="italic">t</hi> degrees of our thermometer (above the temperature where the elasticity is equal to unity), that this multiple shall be the common logarithm of the elasticity F ; so that</p><p>Log. F = <hi rend="italic">m t</hi> A.</p><p>36. As Dr Dalton was one of the earliest to investigate the properties of steam by well-contrived experiment, he has likewise been the most successful in obtaining pro found and accurate views of those general relations which connect this with coordinate branches of physical know ledge. His experimental researches have been the model of imitation to all subsequent investigators. His apparatus was simple, his artifices were highly refined, and his processes elegant and precise; and, consequently, the results of his labour were immediately transferred to the works of highest philosophical character on the Contiuent and at home, and became part of the staple of accurate science. But his philosophical views were not so readily and widely received, and the fault lay, in part, with their author himself. He had overreached the ex<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0674.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0593"/>
isting condition of the other branches of contemporaneous science ; and in taking for granted the accuracy of the existing state of knowledge, he proceeded to raise a theoretical structure on ground not yet sufficiently ascertained and determined. The result has been, as might have been anticipated, that now, when the progress of accurate knowledge has altered the conditions on which his system was based, his theory, becoming inapplicable to the facts, has been thrown aside, and, instead of having been modi fied, as it ought to have been, in conformity with the ad vancement of science, it has been hastily abandoned or undeservedly neglected.</p><p>From an extensive and laborious review of all that has since been added to the stores of our experimental facts on the properties of vapour, we have been conducted to this conclusion, that of all the views that have been taken of the constitution and laws of vapour, Dr Dalton’s are those from which we may gain the clearest and most adequate conceptions ; and therefore we have undertaken the task of reviewing the subject, and of making those changes and modifications which are now required to represent with fidelity and precision the advanced state of our know ledge.</p><p>If we examine any series of even the earlier experiments on the vapour of water (such as those in Art. 27), we cannot fail to recognise a certain d2gree of regularity in the progress of the increasing force of the vapour as the temperature is successively augmented. At the temperature of freezing water, the force of its vapour being taken at two-tenths of an inch, we see that it becomes more than <hi rend="italic">doubled</hi> by raising the temperature 22½°: this again is rather more than <hi rend="italic">doubled</hi> at 22½ <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> of additional heat ; and this is again exactly <hi rend="italic">doubled</hi> by a third addition of 22½°. But another addition of 22½° of heat scarcely doubles the pressure ; and 22½° more fall still further short of producing that effect ; so that, while the increase of the force of the steam takes place rapidly, with equal additions of heat, the rapidity of the increase does not maintain a constant proportion, but slowly diminishes as the temperature ascends. This will be plainer in the following table</p><table> <row> <cell>Temperature of the Vapour.</cell> <cell>Pressure on Mercury.</cell> <cell>Proportion of Increase.</cell> <cell>Decrease of Proportion.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>32°</cell> <cell>0∙200</cell> <cell/> <cell>8</cell> </row> <row> <cell>54½</cell> <cell>0∙445</cell> <cell>2 + <hi rend="superscript"> 17</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi></cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>77</cell> <cell>0∙910</cell> <cell>2 + <hi rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi></cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>99½</cell> <cell>1∙820</cell> <cell>2+ <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi></cell> <cell>9∙</cell> </row> <row> <cell>122</cell> <cell>3∙500</cell> <cell>2 — <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi></cell> <cell>8∙</cell> </row> <row> <cell>144½</cell> <cell>6∙450</cell> <cell>2 — <hi rend="superscript"> 16</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi></cell> <cell>8∙</cell> </row> <row> <cell>167</cell> <cell>11∙250</cell> <cell>2— <hi rend="superscript"> 25</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi></cell> <cell>9∙</cell> </row> <row> <cell>189½</cell> <cell>18∙800</cell> <cell>2— <hi rend="superscript"> 23</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi></cell> <cell>8∙</cell> </row> <row> <cell>212</cell> <cell>30000</cell> <cell>2— <hi rend="superscript"> 41</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi></cell> <cell>8∙</cell> </row> </table><p>From this simple collocation of results, a principle of progression is manifested. The number of degrees in the first column increases at each step by 22½ degrees, and the number in the second column on the same line is nearly doubled every step. At first, as the third column shows, it is more than doubled by <hi rend="superscript"> 17</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi> next time it is more than doubled by <hi rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi>, and next it is doubled exactly ; after this, however, it falls <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi> short of being doubled, next time by twice that quantity, and so on, till we find at last that it falls short of doubling every time by about 8 or 9 hundredths for every 11½ degrees. Although, therefore, we may at first be disappointed in finding that the reduplication does not proceed with the regularity of a law of na ture, still it is satisfactory to know that the deviation from this progression is itself the subject of a tolerably simple law, so as to enable us to predict, with some measure of</p><p>accuracy, what would take place if we were to add another increment of 22½ degrees. We should then diminish the number in the third column by <hi rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi>, and by doubling the pressure, and having regard to this diminution from the preceding numbers, 2— <hi rend="superscript"> 41</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 100</hi> we should have at</p><p>234½° 45.00 2.— <hi rend="superscript"> 50</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 200</hi> —9</p><p>And again at</p><p>257 63.90 2.——8</p><p>It was in this way that Dr Dalton examined his experiments, and proceeded to form his tables, so as to include not only those points which he had already examined by experiment, but to fill up the vacancies, and extend them beyond the range which his actual observation had reach ed. He thus completed the table which we have already given. This was much more accurate than any previous table, and, being more extensive, formed a valuable addition to our knowledge.</p><p>This simple method of interpolation by which Dr Dalton constructed his table, although it suited perfectly, the limited object which he at that time had in view, and coincided with the limited range of his observations, was not of a sufficiently general description to stretch far beyond that sphere. It is obvious, that if his progression were continued much further, it would come to an end of itself ; because the constant diminution of the proportion in the third column would bring it down to nothing, and so the march of the method would close and retrograde, and would thus bring the method of the formation into opposition with the march of the fact, for the force of the vapour continues to increase. Dr Dalton was himself the first to recognise the limited applicability of his method of interpolation to wide ranges of temperature ; and, accordingly, in his lectures on heat, delivered at Edinburgh and Glasgow in 1807, and in his <hi rend="italic">New System of Chemistry,</hi> published 1808, he developed those larger and more matured views which had grown up in his mind during a longer and more thorough investigation of the subject.</p><p>It does not belong to this article to consider the nature, and decide on the merits of Dr Dalton’s theory of temperature ; nor is a perfect acquaintance with that theory of any further use in understanding his views of the constitution of vapour, than to enable us to perceive how he was led from the former to the latter. For the validity of his views regarding steam, it is indeed of no consequence whether the theory of temperature from which it was originally deduced, be true or erroneous. The general laws which he has determined for elastic vapours, form the well-settled foundation on which any theory of temperature, true or false, must in some measure ultimately rest.</p><p>The only circumstances in regard to temperature which it is proper to keep in view, are these : that the present thermometer used to indicate temperature is not to be regarded as an exact measure of the <hi rend="italic">quantity</hi> of heat producing that temperature. This is shown from the circumstance, that the same quantity of fuel which heats water 10° from 180° to 190°, will not heat it from 80° to 90°, an equal interval. From considerations of this nature it was evident that the divisions of the common scale were too large near the bottom, and too small in the higher portions ; and Dr Dalton evinced this difference to be so great, that 72° of the common scale below the freezing point of water down to the freezing point of mercury, were to be reckoned as equivalent to as many as 207° of Dalton’s scale. Proceeding on this view, it was necessary to find the ratio of these two series of indications, the indications of Dalton’s and of Fahrenheit’s scale ; and he accordingly found that the progression of Fahrenheit’s scale was in a high geometrical proportion to the increments of true temperature of the new one. On this principle he proceeded to construct his new scale of temperature—of which the following is a specimen.<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0675.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0594"/>
Fahrenheit’s Scale. Dalton’s Scale.</p><p>—40° (Freezing point of Mercury), —175°</p><p>32 (Freezing point of water), + 32</p><p>110 (Middle of scale), 122</p><p>212 (Boiling point of water), 212</p><p>296 272</p><p>342.7 302</p><p>409∙8 342</p><p>520.3 402</p><p>600.7 422</p><p>By this new scale of temperature it was found that many of the apparent anomalies in the effects of heat were resolved, and the complex relations of its phenomena rendered very simple. Amongst others, the most important were the phenomena of vapours, as it was found that, on the new scale of temperature, the elastic force of different vapours increased almost exactly in a uniform ratio to equal increments of heat.</p><p>But the further progress of experimental science soon raised up serious grounds of objection to this view. It was found that Dr Dalton had rated the inaccuracies of the present scale somewhat too high. His results were thus rendered inapplicable to the advanced state of some branches of thermal science ; and his theory, instead of being modified and improved, was first hastily discredited and then summarily dismissed. Unable to follow the theory to its whole extent, it was abandoned even when it had furnished a safe guide thoroughly to explicate the intricacies of obscure truth.</p><p>It is now, therefore, necessary to examine the views of those who have endeavoured to form adequate representations of the mathematical law which connects the clastic force of vapour with its temperature. We shall first of all examine the methods and views which they have adopted, and then consider whether there may not be deduced from the clear theoretical views of Dr Dalton, tested and modified by the results of modern experiment, mathematical expressions of a character, at once less empirical, and more closely in accordance with observed phenomena.</p><p>37. M. de Prony was the first to represent, by a purely empirical formula, the law which governs the relation between the temperature and the elasticity of aqueous vapour. It was derived by him, in 1796, from the experiments of M. de Betancourt, and constructed according to a method of interpolation, which he afterwards presented to the Academy of Sciences, and which they have placed among the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires des Savans Etrangers.</hi></p><p>The Formula which he has thus obtained is y=ef <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> + <hi rend="superscript"> λ</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> <hi rend="italic">—e</hi> <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> '+ <hi rend="superscript"> λ</hi> '∙ <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> _e <hi rend="italic">&lt;</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi> <hi rend="italic">∙</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi> <hi rend="italic">~f +</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> e</hi> <hi rend="italic">°</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi> <hi rend="italic">*(' ;</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">y</hi> being the height of the mercurial column of pressure, <hi rend="italic">x</hi> the temperature.</p><p><hi rend="italic">e</hi> the base of the common log. . . =10.</p><p><hi rend="italic">p</hi> an empirical coefficient, . . . = 0.068831</p><p>λ = 0.019438</p><p>λ' 0.013490</p><p>0.058576</p><p><hi rend="italic">&lt;r</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi> 0.049157</p><p><hi rend="italic">t</hi> = 4.686080</p><p><hi rend="italic">f .......</hi> = 3.932560</p><p>The same formula holds in the case of alcoholic vapour, the numerical coefficients being changed, and a constant quantity A=1.126447 subtracted from the result.</p><p><hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi> <hi rend="italic">c=</hi> —0.04853, λ=0.02393, r=0.0467, p=2.60249 <hi rend="italic">p =</hi> —0.63414, λ'=0.09653, <hi rend="italic">&lt;r</hi> =0.0294, <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi> <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> = 1.64909 This formula was afterwards improved by its author,</p><p>and presented in the following more elegant and convenient shape.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript"> z</hi> <hi rend="italic">~f</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi> <hi rend="italic">V+f</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi> f'+i“ f <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> B.</p><p><hi rend="italic">II PH III III</hi></p><p>Where <hi rend="italic">z</hi> is the mercurial column of pressure, <hi rend="italic">x</hi> the temperature centigrade, and <hi rend="italic">g, (t</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> ll</hi> <hi rend="italic">p</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> ω</hi> <hi rend="italic">p</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> p,, <hi rend="subscript"> fu</hi> equidistant constants derived from experiment.—For water, these values are :—</p><p><hi rend="subscript"> ft</hi> = —0.0000000196 <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi> = 1.136006</p><p>I ∕</p><p><hi rend="subscript"> j</hi> u= +0.023403 ,= 1.038037</p><p><hi rend="italic">It H</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">p=z</hi> —0.023403 <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi> = 1.022490</p><p><hi rend="italic">m m</hi></p><p>and hence he has formed the numbers which we have united in a subsequent table.</p><p>M. de Prony’s formula for the vapour of alcohol is— *=f* r'+f <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">f</hi> <hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> j</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">+∕*!</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">∕ H H PI Pl ∙lll</hi></p><p>the constants being</p><p>,*=—0.000058 <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi> =L090391</p><p>i ∕</p><p><hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi> <hi rend="italic">c=</hi> +0.024669 <hi rend="subscript"> p</hi> = 1.045453</p><p>ff »</p><p><hi rend="italic">μ=</hi> +0.005677 p=0.836030</p><p><hi rend="italic">Pl III</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">P= iP+P+Μ∖ r"</hi> If ∏ <hi rend="italic">!r I</hi></p><p>= —0.030288</p><p>These numbers refer to the centigrade thermometer, and to an atmosphere of 0.7577 metres in height.</p><p>These formulæ indicate some singular phenomena at high temperatures, which have not been observed in re cent experiments, and may therefore be deemed anomalies of the formulæ themselves rather than the legitimate results of the experiments they were intended to represent. The formulæ are, besides, much too operose to be useful.</p><p>38. The experiments of Dr Dalton are adopted by La place in the fourth volume of the <hi rend="italic">Méchanique Céleste,</hi> where we find him applying them to the calculation of the influence of the aqueous vapour of the atmosphere upon astronomical refractions. As an empirical formula agreeing sufficiently with Dr Dalton’s experiments, he adopted the following approximation :—</p><p><hi rend="italic">f</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> n</hi> <hi rend="italic">~ p.</hi> (10) <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi> 0∙0144S4T««.0.0000625526 Q</p><p><hi rend="italic">f</hi> being the force at any temperature <hi rend="italic">n</hi> of the centesimal scale, reckoned from the point of ebullition, and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> the pressure of the atmosphere =0.76 metres ; or that we have only to add to the log. of 0.76 the quantity n.0.0154547 — <hi rend="italic">n</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>.0.0000625826 and we have the log. of the common tabular logarithm of the corresponding elasticity at <hi rend="italic">n</hi> centisimal degrees of temperature.— <hi rend="italic">Meeh. Cel.</hi> iv. 273.</p><p>These numbers agree very well with the observations they were intended to represent, from 0° to 100° centigrade, but are found inaccurate above and below these points.</p><p>39. M. Biot, adopting still the methods and experiments of Dr Dalton, found it necessary to modify the formula in order to obtain a closer approximation to truth. Using the notation in which we hare expressed Dr Dalton’s method of calculation, Biot considers</p><p><hi rend="italic">fn</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> =</hi> <hi rend="italic">P</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> a</hi> <hi rend="italic">n</hi></p><p>as a first approximation ; of which the Iogarithmic form is Log.y = log. 30. + <hi rend="italic">n</hi> log. α ; which would always give the logarithm of the elastic force, provided the ratio were accurately constant ; but, as it is variable in Dr Dalton’s observed numbers, it would be convenient to represent the variation of the logarithm</p><p>of the elastic force thus :—</p><p>Log·./« = log. 30. J <hi rend="italic">» n + β n* +</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> y</hi> <hi rend="italic">n</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> <hi rend="italic">,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">«, ß, V,</hi> being constants derived from experiments thus— and setting out from 100° cent. as the zero—</p><p>If <hi rend="italic">n =</hi> 0° the number given by exp. is F <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> = 30. in.</p><p><hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 25 F <hi rend="subscript"> ii</hi> = 11.250</p><p>n = 50 FJ <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi> = 3.500</p><p>« = 75 <hi rend="superscript"> p</hi> <hi rend="subscript"> 7f</hi> = 0.910</p><p>By substituting successively these values in the formula we get<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0676.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0595"/>
— 0.4259687 = 25« + 6253 + 15625. <hi rend="subscript"> y</hi>.</p><p>— 0.9330519 = 50» + 2500g + 125000∙ <hi rend="subscript"> y</hi>.</p><p>— 10.5180799 = 75« + .5625,8 + 4∙21875∙y. From these three equations we can readily obtain the</p><p>three values wanted of », S, and y, and which we find to be = — 0.01537419550 <hi rend="italic">β =</hi> — 0.00006742735 y = + 0.00000003381</p><p>and hence the whole equation</p><p>Log. 30.∕. = log. 30. + <hi rend="italic">» n ∣ β n</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi> <hi rend="italic">+ γ n</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi></p><p>is now determined in English inches for the centigrade thermometer ; and in order to compare it with the French observations, it is only necessary to remember that 30. in. = 0∙7679 French metres, and to transform it thus : Log. F» = log. 0“ .76199 — 0.00112919957 — 0.01537278757.„N.</p><p>— 0.00006731995N’ + 0.00000003374N <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> and in the common table of logarithms</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">F</hi> <hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> n</hi> = 0 <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> ∙76.10 AN + BNt + cκ&lt; or,</p><p>Log. <hi rend="smallcaps">F</hi> <hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> n</hi> = T∙880820I + AN + BN <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> + CN <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> which are almost identical with Laplace’s formula (C), the degrees being reckoned positively from 100° cent. downwards, and negatively upwards.</p><p>In degrees Fahrenheit and English inches, the formula in this shape becomes—</p><p>Log. F <hi rend="subscript"> z</hi> = 1.4771213T 0.00854121972/</p><p>— 0.00002081091∕ <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> + 0.00000000580∕&lt;.D.</p><p>These formulæ are far from representing the results of late experiments at high temperatures, although, within the limits of one atmosphere, they accord pretty closely with Dr Dalton’s early observations.</p><p>40. In the first volume of the new series of the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Magazine,</hi> Mr Ivory has given a formula constructed to represent empirically the experiments of Dr Ure. It is—</p><p>Log.^ = .0087466&lt;000015178t <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> +000000024825f E.</p><p>The application of this formula is laborious. It is of exactly tne same nature with that of Laplace and Biot, and only represents the observations of Dr Ure within their narrow limits ; extended to higher temperatures, it seems to deviate considerably from the truth, as may be seen from our table (Art. 57∙)</p><p>41. Schmidt and Soldner, reviewing Dr Dalton’s experiments, have each constructed a formula to represent them :</p><p>Schmidt’s is—F = i <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 363</hi> + ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 0θilt</hi> F.</p><p>Soldner’s formula is—</p><p>r = Ix¾30.13— <hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> ι952</hi> <hi rend="strikethrough">j</hi> <hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> a</hi> <hi rend="strikethrough">⅞</hi> <hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> 12,</hi> <hi rend="strikethrough">&gt;</hi> G.</p><p>42. In the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Journal Of Science</hi> for 1829, Mr Tregaskis has given a theorem, which furnishes a rough approximation to experiment. It is this : that <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> of the temperature above 32°, added to vapour, will double its elasticity.</p><p>43. M. Roche, Professor of Mathematics at Toulon, sent to the Academy of Sciences, in 1828, a memoir on this subject, in which he proposes a formula, deduced from general principles. This formula is—</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> F</hi> =’“ + <hi rend="superscript"> ,0</hi> π⅛5i ,∙∙∙∙ <hi rend="superscript"> h</hi> ∙</p><p>This formula agrees closely with the French experiments.</p><p>44. Dr Thomas Young invented a species of formula entirely new. Abandoning altogether the formula in which one of the variables is involved as an exponent, and abandoning altogether the views from which formulæ of this kind had been derived, he assumed an expression which is apparently perfectly arbitrary, and which has been adapted empirically to the experiments of Dr Dalton. It is this :</p><p>F = (1 + 0.0029.1) <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> 1.</p><p><hi rend="italic">t</hi> being reckoned above 212 Fahr, and F being the force in inches of mercury. Hence we get inversely ;</p><p>,_ <hi rend="underline">F)l</hi></p><p>.0029</p><p>For very small changes of temperature, Dr Young’s formula becomes</p><p>t = 1.642e</p><p><hi rend="italic">e</hi> being the corresponding slight variation of pressure from 30 inches, which corresponds, within three-thousandth parts, with the mean between Deluc’s correction 1.598, and Shuckburg's 1.70, or 1.645 <hi rend="italic">e</hi>.</p><p>Notwithstanding the simplicity of the form of this expression, and the facilities which it presents for ready calculation, it is impossible to adopt it, as it deviates widely and rapidly from the results of observation when extended to high temperatures. Induced, however, by the simplicity of the expression, and not a little influenced, it may be, by the high authority of a name that will ever be distinguished among the most distinguished of those who have contributed immortal truths to the treasures of physical science, the example of Dr Young has drawn after it many followers. Southern, Creighton, Coriolis, Tredgold, Arago, and Dulong, have successively attempted to modify the formula of Young, so as to twist it into some measure of conformity with observed phenomena—we shall see with how little success.</p><p>45. Mr Creighton adopted a similar formula to repre sent Ure’s experiments, only changing the constant expon ent from 7 to 6 ; so that, making F the force of steam in inches of mercury—0.09, and the temperature of Fahrenheit (85° = <hi rend="italic">t</hi>, we have</p><p>F=f√V K.</p><p>∖168.878∕</p><p>Log. F = (Log. <hi rend="italic">t —</hi> —2.22679)«</p><p>46. Mr Southern represented his experiments by the formula</p><p>p_(£+5L3)^_ <hi rend="subscript"> + Oi</hi> i L.</p><p>87344.000000.</p><p>Or,</p><p>Log. (1.1 F) = 5.13 Log. (Z+51.3)10.94123</p><p>And,</p><p>Log. (f+5l3) <hi rend="superscript underline"> L</hi> <hi rend="underline">°g (</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline"> F</hi> <hi rend="underline">+ O∙1)+I⅛94</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline"> 12</hi> <hi rend="underline">3</hi></p><p>5.13</p><p>47. Mr Tredgold simply reinstated Creighton’s expo nent, altering the coefficient to bring it nearer to those experiments with which he was acquainted when his work was written ; but it is inaccurate at high temperatures, and like that of Creighton.</p><p>κw «·</p><p>48. To adapt the formula to more recent experiments, M. Coriolis (in his work <hi rend="italic">Du Calcul de l'Effet des Machines,</hi> 4to, 1829) changed the exponent to 5.355, making it in French measures,</p><p><hi rend="subscript"> p</hi> ∕ <hi rend="underline">l+0DI87</hi> 8A <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∙^</p><p>∖, 2.878 <hi rend="italic">I</hi></p><p>reckoning from 0° cent. in atmospheres of 0.76 metres of mercury.</p><p>49. The French Academy of Sciences have finally reduced the index to 5. ; finding that number represent their experiments at high temperatures, they adopted the following expression :</p><p>F = (l + 0.7l53f) <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> O.</p><p>to give the elasticity in atmospheres of 0.76 metres, the temperature being in centesimal degrees, of course FI ι</p><p><hi rend="italic">t =</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi> <hi rend="strikethrough">t</hi></p><p>0.7153</p><p>50. In conclusion, the committee of the Franklin Insti<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0677.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0596"/>
tute have found it necessary to reinstate the index 6, of Creighton, only modifying Dr Young’s constant multiplier, so as to obtain</p><p>F= (0.00333i+1) <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> P.</p><p>51. It may be useful to collate these formulæ, and for this purpose they are assimilated in notation as follows— F being the elastic force due to a certain temperature <hi rend="italic">t</hi>.</p><p>Robison’s Formula.</p><p>Log. F <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> = <hi rend="italic">m t</hi> A.</p><p>Prony’s Formula.</p><p>F <hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> = <hi rend="italic">μ ft + fi f</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi> 4 <hi rend="italic">fl f</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi> + &amp;c B.</p><p><hi rend="italic">I r n n mm</hi></p><p>Laplace's Formula.</p><p>Ft = 0. <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> 76. (10) <hi rend="superscript"> , 0</hi> ∙° <hi rend="superscript"> l54547</hi> — &lt; <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> ∙0,000°6258I6 <hi rend="subscript"> ιt</hi>.C.</p><p>Biot’s Formula.</p><p>F, = O’".76. <hi rend="smallcaps">(10)** + b&lt;∙+c&lt;∙</hi> D.</p><p>Ivory’s Formula.</p><p>F, = 30. (0.0087466f — 0.000015178f <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi></p><p>+ 0.0000002483i <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>) E.</p><p>Schmidt’s Formula.</p><p>F, = fl.ιw + oosιr <hi rend="subscript"> f</hi>.</p><p>Soldner’s Formula.</p><p>F, = log. 30.13 <hi rend="underline">(</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline"> 66a</hi> <hi rend="underline">~</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline"> f</hi> <hi rend="underline">) &lt;</hi> <hi rend="superscript underline"> 212ι</hi> λ..C.</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> 52042.</p><p>Roche’s Formula.</p><p>F, = 760. 10 H.</p><p>11+0.03f</p><p>Dr Thomas Young’s Formula,.</p><p>F, = (0.00291 + 1) <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> 1</p><p>Creighton’s Formula.</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> f</hi> ' <hi rend="superscript"> =</hi> (l⅛) <hi rend="superscript"> κ</hi> ∙</p><p>Southern’s Formula.</p><p>F,=^±⅛iil <hi rend="subscript"> +0</hi>.1 L.</p><p>87344,000,000</p><p>Tredgold’s Formula.</p><p>MST «</p><p>Coriolis’ Formula.</p><p>F _ Z <hi rend="underline">001878&lt;+1</hi> ∖ <hi rend="superscript"> 3 333</hi> <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi></p><p>∖ 2.878 )</p><p>Commission of the French Academy.</p><p>F j =(0.7153Z+l) <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> O.</p><p>Committee of the Franklin Institute.</p><p>F&lt; = (0.00333&lt;+1) <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> P.</p><p>52. From his earlier experiments Dr Dalton constructed a scale of true temperature, in which the point of freezing mercury is placed at 175°, and in the method he there adopts, the increments of the scale of true temperature are as the square roots of the corresponding expansions of the mercury from its point of maximum density. This scale was soon made the subject of a close experimental scrutiny by Messrs Dulong and Petit, and afterwards of less accurate, though more acrimonious, strictures by Dr Ure.</p><p>This scale was, in fact, slightly inaccurate, because it was founded on the comparatively incorrect data of the experimental physics of that date. It is, however, scarcely fair to institute a comparison between the results of a theory based on certain phenomena and the results of experiments which the improvement of our knowledge has entirely altered. It were less unjust to the theory, and more wise as regards the interest of philosophy, first to examine how far it would have been modified by recent discoveries and then to compare its</p><p>results with the legitimate consequences of the data on which it rests. It ought also to be recorded, that Dr Dalton published, in the third part of his <hi rend="italic">Chemical Philosophy</hi> in 1827, the corrected experimental results to which he had been conducted by the improved methods of observation, and the increased experience of thirty years which had elapsed from his first experiments, while modern writers continue to use the old numbers which should have been altogether discarded.</p><p>Adopting, then, Dr Dalton’s recent experiments below the point of ebullition of water, and the experiments of the French and American Institutes above that point to 24. atmospheres, let us see what theory the views of Dr Dalton would conduct us to, setting out from these improved data.</p><p>Now, Dr Dalton found that, in his experiments, a certain progression of temperatures was accompanied by a certain progression of elastic force ; but his range of experiment being too small, he adopted an erroneous progression, by which, reckoning this progression as rising from the freezing point of mercury, and proceeding as the square roots of the equal expansions of mercury above that point, gave 175° as the point corresponding to the zero of the scale and the origin of his progression.</p><p>53. In examining this subject again, I have found that this gradation of temperatures, though not exact in truth, is analogous to one which may be deduced from the best experiments—and equally from Dr Dalton's and those of the French Academy. The law at which I have arrived is this—that if we reckon the temperatures from the point of congelation of mercury in a logarithmic series, the elastic force of steam forms a similar <hi rend="italic">geometric</hi> series to these intervals of temperature. This would indicate that equal intervals of temperature are those which expand the substance of the thermometer through equal fractional parts of its bulk, instead of equi-differential parts as at present, so that, instead of tne common arithmetical series as at present, viz.,</p><p>C + rf+2 rf+3 rf+4 rf+ <hi rend="italic">nd «</hi></p><p>we should have the temperatures represented by the geo metrical series</p><p>(C + rf) . (1+dβ <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> d <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> +rf <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> + .....∕") <hi rend="italic">β</hi></p><p>and then the corresponding elasticities would be the geometrical series</p><p>(F+Λ) . (1 }Λ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + A <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> JΛ <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> J A") y</p><p>54. Let us, therefore, endeavour to obtain the values of two such series, so as to coincide with the best experi ments. For this purpose we put the series y into the form</p><p><hi rend="italic">α m</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> n</hi> <hi rend="italic">f</hi> 3</p><p>and the series representing the progression of tempera tures into the form</p><p><hi rend="italic">÷=p</hi></p><p>r <hi rend="superscript"> ,r</hi></p><p>then since (?)</p><p>Log. <hi rend="italic">a</hi> f log. tn.n = log·/" or making <hi rend="italic">a</hi> the unit of pressure, for simplicity, we get</p><p>n= <hi rend="underline">⅛∕</hi> 1og. <hi rend="italic">m</hi></p><p>whence by substitution in ε when <hi rend="italic">q=n,</hi> that is, when the elastic force is that which corresponds to the temperature <hi rend="italic">q</hi>, we get</p><p>_ <hi rend="superscript underline"> 1</hi> <hi rend="underline">°K∙∕</hi></p><p>r <hi rend="italic">P</hi> log. <hi rend="italic">m.......................ζ</hi></p><p>therefore</p><p>Log. t = ,° <hi rend="superscript"> g</hi> ' <hi rend="superscript"> P</hi>. log. <hi rend="italic">f+</hi> log. <hi rend="italic">V «</hi></p><p>and <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> °S∙ <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi><pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0678.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0597"/>
Log∙∕= (<hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> °g∙ &lt;— <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> °g∙ «) ■ <hi rend="superscript strikethrough"> 1</hi> <hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> 1</hi> <hi rend="strikethrough">°</hi> <hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> o</hi> <hi rend="strikethrough">g.^ ■·</hi></p><p>When, therefore, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> and <hi rend="italic">r</hi> are determined for a given vaIue of <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> the relative is obtained. If we take the value <hi rend="italic">m</hi> = 2, and if we take from the experiments of the French Academy and Franklin Institute, values of <hi rend="italic">t</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f</hi> above and below 30 inches, or unity, which is the value of <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> and let these values be <hi rend="italic">t'</hi>, <hi rend="italic">t”, t', t'';</hi> then from <hi rend="italic">(ξ) we</hi> have</p><p>_ι . _I</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> f</hi> ' J log·/' <hi rend="italic">Ç</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi> <hi rend="italic">"</hi> J log·/" _Q</p><p>and</p><p><hi rend="superscript"> lθ</hi> g∙ (7) lθg√' l°ff∙ (γ∙) ⅛∙∕ <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> = 0 <hi rend="italic">i</hi></p><p>We have only, therefore, to assume <hi rend="italic">r</hi> so as to satisfy these conditions. Now,</p><p><hi rend="subscript"> t</hi> _ &lt;Fahr∙ + c 7 212 + c</p><p>that is to say, if we reckon temperature from some given point <hi rend="italic">c</hi> above or below the usual zero, viz. at the freezing point of mercury, like Dr Dalton’s scale of temperature, and use the elastic force at 212° as our unit of pressure, we have then only to take <hi rend="italic">f'</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f"</hi> from the tables of experiment, and give such a value to <hi rend="italic">c</hi> as will satisfy the conditions. But as Dr Dalton places that zero at 175° we get</p><p>&lt; _ i <hi rend="superscript"> F4hr</hi> +175 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> r “ 387</p><p>We have still to find <hi rend="italic">p</hi> the index of progression, cor responding to the values of <hi rend="italic">f and f"</hi> in the experiments.</p><p>If we take the value of <hi rend="italic">m</hi> = 2, then since by <hi rend="italic">ζ</hi></p><p>(. y <hi rend="underline">log, m</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">—)</hi> <hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> w</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">∙'=f</hi></p><p>From the French experiments we <hi rend="italic">get p—</hi> 1.103, whence by substitution, <hi rend="italic">r</hi> being=387 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">jb=1.102,</hi> m=2, we have</p><p>&lt; <hi rend="underline">+175°</hi> ⅛</p><p>387° = (1.103) R.</p><p>From Dr Dalton’s experiments we get <hi rend="italic">r =</hi> 387°, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 1.1320, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> = 2.602,</p><p>l <hi rend="underline">og f∙</hi></p><p>whence ι&lt;,g 2.602</p><p>f+175 <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> = (1.1320) .S.</p><p>387*</p><p>From the combination of Dr Dalton’s experiments below 30 inches, with the mean between those of the French Academy and the Franklin Institute, we get</p><p>r= 330 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> =1.11401, <hi rend="italic">m</hi> =2.0,</p><p>whence</p><p><hi rend="underline">log F.</hi> log. 2</p><p>&lt;+121 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> = (1.11401) T.</p><p>333°</p><p>It is from equation S and equation T that we have constructed the large table (Art. 56) in which the results of these formulæ are compared with experiment ; the formula for high-pressure steam being compared with the mean of the French and American experiments ; but, as they do not extend below 212°, that part is compared with Dr Dalton’s table. The coincidence of these formulæ with experiment turns out to be much closer than could possibly have been expected where the discrepancies of experiments from each other are so great. The experiments of Dr Ure deviate from those of Dr Dalton, below</p><p>the pressure of the atmosphere, as much as .33, and the greatest deviation of the formulæ is .08. At pressures above the atmosphere the maximum deviation in the first ten atmospheres between the French and American experiments amounts to 6.4°, while the maximum deviation of the formulæ is only 1.1°.—</p><p>It is, however, remarkable, that in all the experiments hitherto made, the law of elasticity below the atmospheric pressure appears to deviate considerably from that above the atmosphere—perhaps it may arise from the circum stance that the experiments below atmospheric pressure have been made with different apparatus, having errors of a different kind from those made at high pressures above the atmosphere.</p><p>From these equations we easily deduce the following formulæ in a shape convenient for calculation.</p><p>o. <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> ( Log. F = 7.71307 (log. — 2.587711) A</p><p>S∏ ) Log. i = 0.12965.log. F + 2.587711 (<hi rend="subscript"> oa</hi></p><p>I!« ) i <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi></p><p>«S <hi rend="superscript"> s b</hi> ( when i=f <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> ' <hi rend="superscript"> 4hl</hi> '∙f175. <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> J</p><p>Finally</p><p>o . ∙ I Log. F=6.42 (log. <hi rend="italic">t</hi> —2.5224442) 1</p><p>J Log. f=0.1557634. log. F+52244422. f . <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi>,</p><p>4 <hi rend="superscript"> fe</hi> S ( when Z=i <hi rend="superscript"> F</hi> * <hi rend="superscript"> hr</hi> ·J121. <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>)</p><p>These formulæ converted into rules are as follows :</p><p>To find the pressure corresponding to any given temperature of steam above 212°—</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rule.</hi> To the temperature add 121°, find the logarithm of that sum, subtract from this logarithm the number 2.5224442, and multiply the remaining number by 6.42, the product is the logarithm of the pressure in atmospheres of 30 inches of mercury.</p><p>To find the temperature of steam, having any given pressure greater than that of the atmosphere—</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rxde.</hi> Find the logarithm of the pressure in atmospheres, multiply it by 0.1557634, add to the product 2.5224442 ; the sum is the logarithm of the temperature, from which, if 121° be subtracted, the remainder will be the temperature on the common scale.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi> To find the temperature at which high pres sure steam will exert a force greater than the atmosphere by 195 lbs. on the inch—</p><p>195. lbs. = 390. inches of mercury,</p><p>390. inches of mercury =13. atmospheres,</p><p>.∙. 14 atmospheres s= total elastic force of the steam. Logarithm of 14 1.1461280</p><p>.1557634</p><p>11461280</p><p>5730640</p><p>573064</p><p>80227</p><p>6876</p><p>342</p><p>44</p><p>.17852473 Add <hi rend="underline">2.5224442</hi></p><p>502.306 is the number of which 2.7009689 is the log. 121. being subtracted</p><p>381.306° is the temperature on Fahrenheit’s scale at which the elastic force of steam has a pressure of 14 atmospheres; an elastic force of 13.×15. lb. excess of pressure above the atmosphere on each square inch, = 195. lbs.</p><p>To find the pressure corresponding to any given temperature of steam below 212°—</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rule.</hi> To the temperature add 175°, find the logarithm of that sum, subtract from this logarithm the number<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0679.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0598"/>
2.587711, and multiply the remainder by 771307; the product is the logarithm of the pressure in decimal parts of an atmosphere ; which, if multiplied by 15. will give pounds on the square inch, and by 30. inches of mercury.</p><p>To find the temperature at which steam will have a given elastic force less than that of the atmosphere—</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rule.</hi> Find the logarithm of the pressure in decimal parts of an atmosphere, multiply it by 0.12965, add to the product 2.5877110 ; the sum is the logarithm of the temperature which will be expressed in degrees of Fahrenheit’s scale, if 175. be subtracted from it.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi> To find the pressure of steam at 175°.</p><p>To 170°</p><p>Add <hi rend="underline">175°</hi></p><p>The sum is 345°, of which the log. 2.5378191 subtract 2.5877110</p><p>the remainder 1.9501081 multiplied by 7∙7l307</p><p>6.6507567</p><p>6650756</p><p>95010</p><p>28503</p><p>6650</p><p><hi rend="underline">—(771307)</hi></p><p>The next No. is 0.412837, its log. 1.6157786 <hi rend="underline">30</hi></p><p>12.384 inches of mercury is the pressure ; being 17.616 inches of mer. below the atmos.</p><p>30.000</p><p>By these rules the following table is calculated.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Table of the Elastic Force of Vapour in inches of Mercury, at different temperatures, according to our Formulæ</hi> S <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> <hi rend="italic">below</hi> 212° <hi rend="italic">and</hi> T <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> <hi rend="italic">above it.</hi></p><table> <row> <cell>0° 0.07</cell> <cell>62° 0.68</cell> <cell>1 96° 1.89</cell> <cell>130° 4.78</cell> </row> <row> <cell>10 0.10</cell> <cell>63 0.70</cell> <cell>97 196</cell> <cell>131 4.91</cell> </row> <row> <cell>20 0.15</cell> <cell>64 0.72</cell> <cell>98 2.01</cell> <cell>132 5 03</cell> </row> <row> <cell>30 0.22</cell> <cell>65 0.74</cell> <cell>99 2.08</cell> <cell>133 5.15</cell> </row> <row> <cell>‘32 0.24</cell> <cell>66 0.77</cell> <cell>100 2.15</cell> <cell>134 5.28</cell> </row> <row> <cell>33 0.25</cell> <cell>67 0.80</cell> <cell>101 2.21</cell> <cell>135 5.41</cell> </row> <row> <cell>34 0.26</cell> <cell>68 0.82</cell> <cell>102 2.28</cell> <cell>136 5.55</cell> </row> <row> <cell>35 0 27</cell> <cell>69 0.85</cell> <cell>103 2.34</cell> <cell>137 5.70</cell> </row> <row> <cell>36 0.28</cell> <cell>70 0.88</cell> <cell>104 2.41</cell> <cell>138 5.84</cell> </row> <row> <cell>37 0.29</cell> <cell>71 0.91</cell> <cell>105 2.48</cell> <cell>139 5.98</cell> </row> <row> <cell>38 0.30</cell> <cell>72 0.94</cell> <cell>106 2.55</cell> <cell>140 6.13</cell> </row> <row> <cell>39 0.31</cell> <cell>73 0.97</cell> <cell>107 2.62</cell> <cell>141 6.29</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40 0.32</cell> <cell>74 1.00</cell> <cell>108 2.69</cell> <cell>142 6.45</cell> </row> <row> <cell>41 0.33</cell> <cell>75 1.03</cell> <cell>109 2.76</cell> <cell>143 6.61</cell> </row> <row> <cell>42 0.34</cell> <cell>76 1.06</cell> <cell>110 2.83</cell> <cell>144 6.76</cell> </row> <row> <cell>43 0.35</cell> <cell>77 1.09</cell> <cell>111 2.91</cell> <cell>145 6.92</cell> </row> <row> <cell>44 0.37</cell> <cell>78 1.12</cell> <cell>112 2.98</cell> <cell>146 7.08</cell> </row> <row> <cell>4.5 0.38</cell> <cell>79 1.16</cell> <cell>113 3.08</cell> <cell>147 725</cell> </row> <row> <cell>46 0.39</cell> <cell>80 1.20</cell> <cell>114 3.16</cell> <cell>148 7.41</cell> </row> <row> <cell>47 0.40</cell> <cell>81 1.24</cell> <cell>115 3.25</cell> <cell>149 7.61</cell> </row> <row> <cell>48 0.42</cell> <cell>82 1.28</cell> <cell>116 3.33</cell> <cell>150 7.80</cell> </row> <row> <cell>49 0.43</cell> <cell>83 1.31</cell> <cell>117 3.42</cell> <cell>151 8.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>50 0.45</cell> <cell>84 1.36</cell> <cell>118 3.51</cell> <cell>152 8.20</cell> </row> <row> <cell>51 0.47</cell> <cell>85 1.39</cell> <cell>119 3.60</cell> <cell>153 8.40</cell> </row> <row> <cell>52 0 19</cell> <cell>86 1.44</cell> <cell>120 3.69</cell> <cell>154 8.59</cell> </row> <row> <cell>53 0.51</cell> <cell>87 147</cell> <cell>121 3.79</cell> <cell>155 8.79</cell> </row> <row> <cell>54 0.53</cell> <cell>88 1.51</cell> <cell>122 3.88</cell> <cell>156 8.99</cell> </row> <row> <cell>55 0.55</cell> <cell>89 1.56</cell> <cell>123 398</cell> <cell>157 9∙20</cell> </row> <row> <cell>56 0.57</cell> <cell>90 1.61</cell> <cell>124 4.08</cell> <cell>158 9.41</cell> </row> <row> <cell>57 0∙59</cell> <cell>91 1.65</cell> <cell>123 4.19</cell> <cell>159 9.62</cell> </row> <row> <cell>58 0.61</cell> <cell>92 1.69</cell> <cell>126 4.30</cell> <cell>160 9.84</cell> </row> <row> <cell>59 0.62</cell> <cell>93 1.74</cell> <cell>127 4.42</cell> <cell>161 10.06</cell> </row> <row> <cell>60 0.64</cell> <cell>94 1.79</cell> <cell>128 4.53</cell> <cell>162 10.28</cell> </row> <row> <cell>61 0.66</cell> <cell>95 1.84</cell> <cell>129 4.66</cell> <cell>163 10.51</cell> </row> </table> <table> <row> <cell>164°</cell> <cell>10.75</cell> <cell>192°</cell> <cell>19.86</cell> <cell>220°</cell> <cell>35.35</cell> <cell>248°</cell> <cell>58.48</cell> </row> <row> <cell>165</cell> <cell>11.01</cell> <cell>193</cell> <cell>20.30</cell> <cell>221</cell> <cell>36.08</cell> <cell>249</cell> <cell>59∙37</cell> </row> <row> <cell>166</cell> <cell>11.28</cell> <cell>194</cell> <cell>20.74</cell> <cell>222</cell> <cell>36.80</cell> <cell>294.7</cell> <cell>60.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>167</cell> <cell>11.56</cell> <cell>195</cell> <cell>21.19</cell> <cell>223</cell> <cell>37.54</cell> <cell>250.</cell> <cell>60.27</cell> </row> <row> <cell>168</cell> <cell>11.85</cell> <cell>196</cell> <cell>21.64</cell> <cell>224</cell> <cell>38.31</cell> <cell>274.1</cell> <cell>90.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>169</cell> <cell>12.05</cell> <cell>197</cell> <cell>22.11</cell> <cell>225</cell> <cell>39.11</cell> <cell>291.9</cell> <cell>120.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>170</cell> <cell>12.36</cell> <cell>198</cell> <cell>22.57</cell> <cell>226</cell> <cell>39.94</cell> <cell>306.8</cell> <cell>150.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>171</cell> <cell>12.66</cell> <cell>199</cell> <cell>23.04</cell> <cell>227</cell> <cell>40.70</cell> <cell>319.2</cell> <cell>180.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>172</cell> <cell>12.96</cell> <cell>200</cell> <cell>23.52</cell> <cell>228</cell> <cell>41.66</cell> <cell>329.9</cell> <cell>210.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>173</cell> <cell>13.26</cell> <cell>201</cell> <cell>24.00</cell> <cell>229</cell> <cell>42.55</cell> <cell>339∙3</cell> <cell>240.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>174</cell> <cell>13.56</cell> <cell>202</cell> <cell>24.50</cell> <cell>230</cell> <cell>43.46</cell> <cell>348.8</cell> <cell>270.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>175</cell> <cell>13.86</cell> <cell>203</cell> <cell>25.00</cell> <cell>231</cell> <cell>44.29</cell> <cell>355.6</cell> <cell>300.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>176</cell> <cell>14.16</cell> <cell>204</cell> <cell>25.52</cell> <cell>232</cell> <cell>45.14</cell> <cell>363.0</cell> <cell>330.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>177</cell> <cell>14.47</cell> <cell>205</cell> <cell>26.05</cell> <cell>233</cell> <cell>45.95</cell> <cell>369.4</cell> <cell>360.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>178</cell> <cell>14.78</cell> <cell>206</cell> <cell>26.59</cell> <cell>234</cell> <cell>46.78</cell> <cell>375.5</cell> <cell>390.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>179</cell> <cell>15.09</cell> <cell>207</cell> <cell>27.14</cell> <cell>235</cell> <cell>47.58</cell> <cell>381.3</cell> <cell>420.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>180</cell> <cell>15.41</cell> <cell>208</cell> <cell>27.69</cell> <cell>236</cell> <cell>48.39</cell> <cell>387.0</cell> <cell>450.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>181</cell> <cell>15.73</cell> <cell>209</cell> <cell>28.25</cell> <cell>337</cell> <cell>49.21</cell> <cell>391.9</cell> <cell>480.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>182</cell> <cell>16.06</cell> <cell>210</cell> <cell>28.83</cell> <cell>238</cell> <cell>50.04</cell> <cell>396.7</cell> <cell>510.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>183</cell> <cell>16.40</cell> <cell>211</cell> <cell>29.40</cell> <cell>239</cell> <cell>50.86</cell> <cell>401.3</cell> <cell>540.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>184</cell> <cell>16.75</cell> <cell>•212</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>240</cell> <cell>51.70</cell> <cell>405.8</cell> <cell>570.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>185</cell> <cell>17.10</cell> <cell>213</cell> <cell>30.61</cell> <cell>241</cell> <cell>52.53</cell> <cell>410.0</cell> <cell>600.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>186</cell> <cell>17.46</cell> <cell>214</cell> <cell>31.24</cell> <cell>242</cell> <cell>53.37</cell> <cell>444.6</cell> <cell>900.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>187</cell> <cell>17.83</cell> <cell>215</cell> <cell>31.89</cell> <cell>243</cell> <cell>54.22</cell> <cell>470.5</cell> <cell>1200.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>188</cell> <cell>18.21</cell> <cell>216</cell> <cell>32.56</cell> <cell>244</cell> <cell>55.07</cell> <cell>491.4</cell> <cell>1500.00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>189</cell> <cell>18.60</cell> <cell>217</cell> <cell>33.24</cell> <cell>245</cell> <cell>55.93</cell> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>190</cell> <cell>19.00</cell> <cell>218</cell> <cell>33.93</cell> <cell>246</cell> <cell>56.73</cell> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>191</cell> <cell>19.42</cell> <cell>219</cell> <cell>34.63</cell> <cell>247</cell> <cell>57.60</cell> <cell/> <cell/> </row> </table><p>55. The formulæ thus given are in such perfect accor dance with our best experimental knowledge, that we can not withhold our assent from the correctness of the principles from which they have been deduced. At the same time, we desiderate very much a better series of experiments than we yet possess, as the range of doubtful temperature above 212° is far wider than the present perfect state of experimental science, and our improved means of observing, can at all warrant. The discrepancies between the experiments above and below 212° show, that the two series should if possible be performed with identical apparatus.</p><p>The formulæ we have obtained have been founded on the <hi rend="italic">hypothesis, that bodies expand nearly equal proportions of bulk in equal intervals Of true temperature ; and we have found that the elastic force of steam increases in equal proportions, from equal increments of temperature, reckoned in true intervals from the bottom of the scale.</hi></p><p>Our formula should, however, be capable of being reduced into a form closely resembling those which have preceded it, in so far as these have represented approximately the experiments they were made to represent ; thus the formula of Laplace and his followers is of the form F <hi rend="italic">— Q m t</hi> f <hi rend="italic">m t</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> 8</hi> <hi rend="italic">+^ m</hi> ∕ <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ½ 4 <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> c. <hi rend="italic">ad infinit»</hi></p><p>So, in like manner, we should obtain from Equation T the following ;</p><p><hi rend="italic">( ∕ t c t</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> 6</hi> <hi rend="italic">. )</hi></p><p>Log. 2 × ■ 21og.c—Iog.(cf <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>)λ (+1 f&amp;c.]) &gt;</p><p><hi rend="italic">I</hi> ' c* 2c <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> 3c <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi> ' )</p><p>— log. C — log. (1.11401) log. F = 0 which is easily presented in a form absolutely the same.</p><p>In like manner, it may be presented at once in the form adopted by Dr Thomas Young and all his followers, viz.</p><p>for, if we take our formula S <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi></p><p>Log. F=7.71307 (log. <hi rend="italic">t—</hi> 2.587711) we get, resuming the natural number,</p><p>F <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> √i±W <hi rend="superscript"> n,</hi> <hi rend="subscript"> Ss</hi>.</p><p>∖ 387 <hi rend="italic">J</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> s</hi></p><p>Or, if we take formula T <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, we get</p><p><hi rend="subscript"> F =</hi> /£±W*’ T <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi>.</p><p>V 333 <hi rend="italic">J</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> 3</hi></p><p>We thus find, that the old formulæ have all approximated in a greater or less degree to the representation of<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0680.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0599"/>
the very hypothesis on which ours has now been formed. They thus add greatly to the probability of its truth.</p><p>We do not, however, mean to assert, that the zero of the mercurial thermometer is absolutely at 175° or 121° below the present 0. or that the progression of the temperatures has been fixed accurately for mercury or for vapour. On the contrary, we have seen that the discrepancies of the results obtained by different physical experimenters are great, and do not admit of obtaining un</p><p>changeable numerical indices of progression, either of the temperatures or the corresponding elastic force. The existence of these two progressions, and their character, has, we think, been established, and our research has the effect of confirming, the profound views of Dr Dalton, which have, we think, been ill understood and insufficiently appreciated.</p><p>56. The following table exhibits some formulæ and experiments collated :</p><p><hi rend="italic">Table of the force of Steam at different temperatures from</hi> 0° <hi rend="italic">to</hi> 500°.</p><table> <row> <cell><p>I.</p><p>Tempera</p><p>ture.</p><p>Fahrenheit.</p></cell> <cell><p>IL</p><p>Dalton.</p></cell> <cell><p>III</p><p>Ure.</p></cell> <cell><p>IV.</p><p>Young.</p></cell> <cell><p>V.</p><p>Ivory.</p></cell> <cell><p>VI.</p><p>Tred</p><p>gold.</p></cell> <cell><p>VII.</p><p>South</p><p>ern</p></cell> <cell><p>VIII</p><p>Robison.</p></cell> <cell><p>IX.</p><p>Watt.</p></cell> <cell><p>X.</p><p>Frank.</p><p>Inst.</p></cell> <cell><p>XI.</p><p>New</p><p>For</p><p>mula.</p></cell> <cell><p>XII.</p><p>Diff. Dolt. so Ure's Expts.</p></cell> <cell><p>XIII.</p><p>Diff</p><p>Acad.</p><p>Inst.</p></cell> <cell cols="2">XIV. Diff. Tred. &amp; Dalton</cell> <cell cols="2"><p>XV.</p><p>Diff. New Formula ⅜ Dalton.</p></cell> <cell><p>XVI.</p><p>Tempera</p><p>ture.</p><p>Fahrenheit</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell>0º</cell> <cell>0.08</cell> <cell/> <cell>,</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.07</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>— .01</cell> <cell>0°</cell> </row> <row> <cell>10</cell> <cell>0.12</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.10</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>..</cell> <cell/> <cell>— .02</cell> <cell>10</cell> </row> <row> <cell>20</cell> <cell>0.17</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.11</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.15</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.09</cell> <cell/> <cell>.02</cell> <cell>20</cell> </row> <row> <cell>»2</cell> <cell>0.26</cell> <cell>0.20</cell> <cell>0.18</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.17</cell> <cell>0.16</cell> <cell>0.00</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.24</cell> <cell>— .06</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.10</cell> <cell/> <cell>.02</cell> <cell>32</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>0.34</cell> <cell>0.25</cell> <cell>0.20</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.24</cell> <cell>0.22</cell> <cell>0.10</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.32</cell> <cell>— .09</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.11</cell> <cell/> <cell>— .02</cell> <cell>40</cell> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>0.49</cell> <cell>0.36</cell> <cell>0.36</cell> <cell>0.36</cell> <cell>0.37</cell> <cell>0.33</cell> <cell>0.20</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.45</cell> <cell>— .13</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>.10</cell> <cell/> <cell>— .04</cell> <cell>50</cell> </row> <row> <cell>60</cell> <cell>0.65</cell> <cell>0.52</cell> <cell>0.53</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.55</cell> <cell>0.48</cell> <cell>0.35</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.64</cell> <cell>— .13</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.09</cell> <cell/> <cell>— .01</cell> <cell>60</cell> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>0.87</cell> <cell>0.73</cell> <cell>0.75</cell> <cell>0.73</cell> <cell>0.78</cell> <cell>0.68</cell> <cell>0.55</cell> <cell>0.77</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>0.88</cell> <cell>— .14</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.05</cell> <cell/> <cell>.01</cell> <cell>70</cell> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>1.19</cell> <cell>1.01</cell> <cell>1.05</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>1.11</cell> <cell>0.95</cell> <cell>0.82</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>1.20</cell> <cell>— .16</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.06</cell> <cell/> <cell>.04</cell> <cell>80</cell> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>1.59</cell> <cell>1.36</cell> <cell>1.44</cell> <cell>1.36</cell> <cell>1.53</cell> <cell>0.34</cell> <cell>1.18</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>1.61</cell> <cell>— .23</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>.04</cell> <cell/> <cell>.02</cell> <cell>90</cell> </row> <row> <cell>100</cell> <cell>2.12</cell> <cell>1.86</cell> <cell>1.95</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>2.08</cell> <cell>1.84</cell> <cell>1.60</cell> <cell>1.55</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>2.15</cell> <cell>— .24</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>.00</cell> <cell/> <cell>.03</cell> <cell>100</cell> </row> <row> <cell>110</cell> <cell>2.79</cell> <cell>2.45</cell> <cell>2.62</cell> <cell>2.46</cell> <cell>2.79</cell> <cell>2.56</cell> <cell>2.25</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>2.83</cell> <cell>— .34</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.05</cell> <cell/> <cell>.04</cell> <cell>110</cell> </row> <row> <cell>120</cell> <cell>3.63</cell> <cell>3.30</cell> <cell>3.46</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>3.68</cell> <cell>3.46</cell> <cell>3.00</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>3.69</cell> <cell>— .33</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.10</cell> <cell/> <cell>.06</cell> <cell>120</cell> </row> <row> <cell>130</cell> <cell>4.71</cell> <cell>4.37</cell> <cell>4.54</cell> <cell>4.41</cell> <cell>4.81</cell> <cell>4.43</cell> <cell>3.95</cell> <cell>.∙∙</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>4.78</cell> <cell>— .34</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...16</cell> <cell/> <cell>.07</cell> <cell>130</cell> </row> <row> <cell>140</cell> <cell>6.05</cell> <cell>5.78</cell> <cell>5.88</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>6.21</cell> <cell>5.75</cell> <cell>5.15</cell> <cell>5.14</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>6.15</cell> <cell>— .27</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.08</cell> <cell>140</cell> </row> <row> <cell>150</cell> <cell>7.73</cell> <cell>7.53</cell> <cell>7.55</cell> <cell>7.42</cell> <cell>7.94</cell> <cell>7.46</cell> <cell>0.72</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>7.80</cell> <cell>— .20</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.21</cell> <cell/> <cell>.07</cell> <cell>150</cell> </row> <row> <cell>160</cell> <cell>9.79</cell> <cell>9.60</cell> <cell>9.62</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>10.05</cell> <cell>9.52</cell> <cell>8.65</cell> <cell>8.92</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>9.85</cell> <cell>— .19</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>.26</cell> <cell/> <cell>.08</cell> <cell>100</cell> </row> <row> <cell>170</cell> <cell>12.31</cell> <cell>12.05</cell> <cell>12.14</cell> <cell>12.05</cell> <cell>12.60</cell> <cell>12.14</cell> <cell>11.05</cell> <cell>11.37</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>12.38</cell> <cell>— .26</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.29</cell> <cell/> <cell>.t∣7</cell> <cell>170</cell> </row> <row> <cell>180</cell> <cell>15.38</cell> <cell>15.16</cell> <cell>15.23</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>15.67</cell> <cell>15.20</cell> <cell>14.05</cell> <cell>14.73</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>15.41</cell> <cell>— .28</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>.29</cell> <cell/> <cell>.03</cell> <cell>180</cell> </row> <row> <cell>190</cell> <cell>18.98</cell> <cell>19.00</cell> <cell>18.96</cell> <cell>18.93</cell> <cell>19.00</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>17.85</cell> <cell>19.00</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>18.90</cell> <cell>+ .12</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.02</cell> <cell/> <cell>.02</cell> <cell>190</cell> </row> <row> <cell>200</cell> <cell>23.51</cell> <cell>23.60</cell> <cell>23.44</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>23.71</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>22.62</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>23.52</cell> <cell>+ .09</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>.20</cell> <cell/> <cell>.01</cell> <cell>200</cell> </row> <row> <cell>210</cell> <cell>28.82</cell> <cell>2.8.88</cell> <cell>28.81</cell> <cell>28.81</cell> <cell>28.86</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>28.65</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>28.82</cell> <cell>4.07</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>.04</cell> <cell/> <cell>.00</cell> <cell>210</cell> </row> <row> <cell>212</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>.30.00</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>29.40</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>30.00</cell> <cell>0.00</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.00</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.00</cell> <cell>212</cell> </row> <row> <cell>220</cell> <cell>35.18</cell> <cell>35.54</cell> <cell>35.19</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>34.92</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>35.8</cell> <cell>33.65</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>35.10</cell> <cell>— 0.36</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>— .26</cell> <cell/> <cell>— .15</cell> <cell>220</cell> </row> <row> <cell>230</cell> <cell>44.60</cell> <cell>43.10</cell> <cell>42.47</cell> <cell>42.63</cell> <cell>42.00</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>44.5</cell> <cell>40.+</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>42.60</cell> <cell>— 1.50</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>2.13</cell> <cell/> <cell>2.00</cell> <cell>230</cell> </row> <row> <cell>240</cell> <cell>53.45</cell> <cell>51.70</cell> <cell>51.66</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>50.24</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>54.9</cell> <cell>49.0</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>51.42</cell> <cell>— 1.75</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>3.21</cell> <cell/> <cell>2.03</cell> <cell>240</cell> </row> </table><p><hi rend="italic">Table of the Force of Steam at different Temperatures (continued).</hi></p><table> <row> <cell>I.</cell> <cell>II.</cell> <cell>III.</cell> <cell>IV.</cell> <cell>V.</cell> <cell cols="2">VI</cell> <cell>VII.</cell> <cell>VIII.</cell> <cell>IX.</cell> <cell>X.</cell> <cell>XI</cell> <cell>XII</cell> <cell>XIII.</cell> <cell cols="2">XIV.</cell> <cell cols="2">XV.</cell> <cell>XVI</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Pressure in</cell> <cell><p>French</p><p>Acad.</p></cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>Franklin Institut.</cell> <cell><p>New</p><p>Form.</p></cell> <cell>Din; Dr</cell> <cell>Diff</cell> <cell/> <cell>Diff.</cell> <cell cols="2">Diff New</cell> <cell>Pressure in</cell> </row> <row> <cell><p>Atmos</p><p>pheres.</p></cell> <cell/> <cell>Dr Ure.</cell> <cell>Young.</cell> <cell>Ivory.</cell> <cell cols="2">Tredg∙.</cell> <cell>South.</cell> <cell>Robinson.</cell> <cell>Watt.</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>Ure's Expedient.</cell> <cell><p>Arad.</p><p>Inst.</p></cell> <cell cols="2">Tred. &amp;Dalton</cell> <cell cols="2">Form &amp; Ac. Inst.</cell> <cell>Atmospheres.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>1st At.</cell> <cell>212.0°</cell> <cell>212°</cell> <cell>212"</cell> <cell>212»</cell> <cell>212°</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>212°</cell> <cell>212°</cell> <cell>212°</cell> <cell>212°</cell> <cell>0.00</cell> <cell>000.2</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.00°</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.00o</cell> <cell>1st At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>2d At.</cell> <cell>250.5</cell> <cell>2000</cell> <cell>240.3</cell> <cell>249</cell> <cell>250</cell> <cell/> <cell>250.3+</cell> <cell/> <cell>2525</cell> <cell>250.0</cell> <cell><p>249.7</p><p>274.1</p></cell> <cell/> <cell>— 0.5</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.+</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>2d At. 3&lt;l At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>3d At.</cell> <cell>27δ.2</cell> <cell>2750</cell> <cell>271</cell> <cell/> <cell>274</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>267</cell> <cell/> <cell>275.2</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>— 0.2</cell> <cell/> <cell>1.+</cell> <cell/> <cell>1.0</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>4th At.</cell> <cell>293.7</cell> <cell>201.5</cell> <cell>288</cell> <cell>290</cell> <cell>294</cell> <cell/> <cell>293.4+</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>201.5</cell> <cell>201.9</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>— 2.2</cell> <cell/> <cell>1.4</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.7</cell> <cell>4th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>5th At.</cell> <cell>308.8</cell> <cell>304.5</cell> <cell>302</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>309</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>304.5</cell> <cell>306.8</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>— 4.3</cell> <cell/> <cell>3.7</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.1</cell> <cell>5th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>6th At.</cell> <cell>320.4</cell> <cell>315.5</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>322.</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>315.5</cell> <cell>319.2</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>— 4.9</cell> <cell/> <cell>—4.0</cell> <cell/> <cell>1.2</cell> <cell>6th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>7th At.</cell> <cell>.331.7</cell> <cell>325.5</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>326.5</cell> <cell>329.9</cell> <cell/> <cell>— 6.7</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>1.1</cell> <cell>7th Λt.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>8th At.</cell> <cell>362.0</cell> <cell>336.0</cell> <cell/> <cell>337</cell> <cell cols="2">342.+</cell> <cell>343.6+</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>336.0</cell> <cell>339.3</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>— 6.0</cell> <cell cols="2">+3.3</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.3</cell> <cell>8th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>9tb At.</cell> <cell>374.8</cell> <cell>345</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>.345.0</cell> <cell>348.8</cell> <cell/> <cell>— 5.0</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>0.9</cell> <cell>9th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>10th At.</cell> <cell>358.9</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>352.5</cell> <cell><p>355.6</p><p>363.0</p></cell> <cell/> <cell>— 6.4</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>0.1</cell> <cell>loth At. 11th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>11th At.</cell> <cell>366.8</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>12th At.</cell> <cell>374.0</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>372.</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>309.4</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell cols="2">—3.0</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>12th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>13th At.</cell> <cell>380.6</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>..</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>375.5</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>13th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>14th At.</cell> <cell>38S.9</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>381.3</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>l4th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>15th At.</cell> <cell>392.8</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>383.8</cell> <cell>387.0</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>— 9.0</cell> <cell/> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>0.3</cell> <cell>15th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>16th At.</cell> <cell>398.5</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>391.9</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>16th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>l7th At.</cell> <cell>403.8</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>396.7</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>«··</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>17th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>18th At.</cell> <cell>408.9</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>401.3</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>18th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>19th At.</cell> <cell>413.9</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>405.8</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>19th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>20th At.</cell> <cell>418.5</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>·■·</cell> <cell>414</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>405</cell> <cell>410.</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>— 13.5</cell> <cell cols="2">+2.3</cell> <cell/> <cell>1.7</cell> <cell>20th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>30th At.</cell> <cell>457.2</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>444.0</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>30th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40th At.</cell> <cell>466.0</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>∙∙∙</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>470.5</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>40th At.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>50th At.</cell> <cell>510.6</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>491.4</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell/> <cell>...</cell> <cell>50th At.</cell> </row> </table><p>The first and last columns contain the successive temperatures, as far as 240°, and after that the number of atmospheres of pressure ; and their reference extends wholly across the table.</p><p>Col. II. contains the later experiments of Dr Dalton, interpolated, where necessary, down to 240° ; the remainder of that column is from the experiments of the French Academy.</p><p>Col. III. contains the experiments of Dr Ure.</p><p>Cols. IV. V. and VI. contain the formulæ of Dr Young,</p><p>Mr Ivory, and Mr Tredgold.</p><p>Cols. VIL VIII. IX. and X. contain the experiments of</p><p>Southern, Robison, Watt, and the Franklin Institute. Col. XI contains the numbers given by our formulæ. Col. XII. exhibits the differences between the experi</p><p>ments of Drs Dalton and Ure.<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0681.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0600"/>
Col. XIII. exhibits the differences between the experiments of the French Academy and the Franklin Institute.</p><p>Col. XIV. exhibits the deviations of Tredgold’s formula from Dalton's experiments, down to 240° ; and be low that point, from the mean of the experiments of the French Academy and the Franklin Institute, in terpolated where required.</p><p>Col. XV. exhibits the difference between our formulæ and the best experiments, Dr Dalton’s being taken down to 240° ; and the mean between those of the French Academy and the Franklin Institute from that point to the end of the table—interpolations being used when necessary.</p></div></body></text></TEI>