<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0502.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0435-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOCRATES</label>
. The name of Socrates is familiar to every one among his earliest classical recollections. Who has not heard of the Athenian sage, the great moralist of heathenism, and his persecution and constancy even to death ? There is no name indeed which stands forth more conspicuously in the history of the philosophy, or of the religion, or of the <hi rend="italic">general</hi> civilization of the ancient world. It marks a distinct era in the progress of the human race. The character of a great period in the history of man is concentrated, in fact, in the life and teaching of this extraordinary individual ; and his name accordingly has descended to us with all the importance of the crisis itself at which he flourished; recom- mended as it is to our affection and admiration, not so much by the characteristics of his personality, as by the tradition of his influence and authority.</p><p>For when we come to consider his particular biography, we find our attention arrested by little that belongs merely to the individual. We read of a long life passed for the most part in uniform tenour within the walls of his native Athens ; and until we come to its tragical close, scarcely distinguished in point of incident from that of the mass of his contemporaries. When, again, we ask for writings from which, as from the proper mirror of the philosopher’s mind, we may collect some express lineaments of his character and teaching, we find nothing even on this ground on which our curiosity can fasten ; so little have we derived that interest, which the mention of Socrates now awakens, from himself immediately ; and so much, on the other hand, are we indebted for our acquaintance with this philosopher to a popular feeling preserving and handing down to us the name which represents the thought and character of an age.</p><p>The conjuncture of events at the time of Socrates was<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0503.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0436"/>
peculiarly favourable to the development of such a character. Socrates, born at Λthens in the year 469 or 470 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> grew up to manhood during those years when Athens, standing on the proud eminence of her victories of Marathon and Salamis, was consolidating her power as a sovereign state and seat of empire. In the course of the fifty years which intervened between her triumphant resistance to the Persian invasion and the commencement of the Peloponnesian war, Athens, like Rome in her struggle with her Italian neighbours, had gradually converted her allies in the islands and on the coasts of Asia Minor and Thrace into dependent subjects and tributaries. But Athens had not, like Rome, the prudence to combine these scattered members of her empire, elements of discord and trouble as much as of strength to the sovereign state, by the free communication of the rights of citizenship. Nor indeed could this wise expedient have availed in the case of Athens as in that of Rome. For the states over which the empire of Athens extended were either independent governments reluctantly submitting to her yoke, or the weak dependencies of a rival power, and indisposed to acknowledge the sovereignty of Athens but so long as that power wanted the vigour and the enterprize to head a coalition against the common oppressor. There were thus in the very constitution of the Athenian empire, materials of jealousy and disunion, which no line of conduct but the impolitic one of surrendering an arbitrary rule into the hands of the people who had groaned under it, could long have kept from explosion. And, in fact, it was not the policy of Athens (masterly as that policy was under the hands of her great leaders) which sustained her empire for more than fifty years, so much as the inertness of her great rival, Lacedemon, and the difficulty of bringing the several grievances of the subject-states to bear on some decisive point, capable of influencing the movement of the whole in a strenuous concerted effort of resistance. At length we see this effort in the outbreak of the Peloponnesian war, as well as the difficulty of it in the complicated diplomacy by which that great movement was preceded, and in the reluctance of Lacedemon to bring home to herself the necessity of exertion.</p><p>But, whilst Athens was thus aggrandizing herself against a day of retribution from the insulted states of Greece, she enjoyed the sunshine of her day of empire, in the brilliant assemblage, which she then witnessed within her walls, of the great, and the learned, and the eloquent, from all parts of Greece.<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Isocrat. Panegyr. Καί τό a <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> λ⅞⅛r <hi rend="italic">των άφικνονμίνων i&gt;t ημas τoσovτov i&lt;rτιv, κ.τ∙λ.</hi> p. 59.</p></note> While her arms and her enterprize were setting foot on every sea and land, her attractiveness as a home of genius and civilization, was evidenced in the number of strangers frequenting her porticoes, and groves, and theatres, and temples, and the houses of her nobles. During thirty years of this period of glory, the philosopher Anaxagoras was employed in propagating there the doctrines of the Ionic school, honoured by the patronage of her great men, and the revered master of her choicest spirits in the newly-acquired taste for philosophical inquiry. During, also, a considerable portion of the same period, the sophist Prodicus was domesticated within her walls, surrounded by crowds of admiring pupils from the highest ranks of her citizens, eagerly catching the inspiration of that rhetorical ability for which he was famed. Occasionally, too, amongst the distinguished visitors of the city, might be seen other illustrious professors of the day, also familiarly known by the name of sophists, then a complimentary designation,—Protagoras of Abdera, Gorgias of Leontium, Hippias of Elis,—drawn there by the demand for that literary merchandize, of which they claimed the monopoly. There also were now collected, as in a school of all arts, the great masters of the drama, of sculpture, and painting, and music, and the gymnastic exercises. So that Athens, at this time, contained within her own bosom abundant resources for the enlargement of the mind, whether in the eminent men who formed her society, in the lectures and conversation of the professors of science, or in noble works, the specimens and examples of what genius could effect. Athens contained, also, doubtless, much to enervate and corrupt the moral judgment, whilst she presented every thing to exalt the imagination and refine the taste. Her political institutions, well-balanced as they had been left by Solon, were now violently disturbed. In the course of these years of imperial greatness and prosperity, they received a large infusion of that licentious spirit, which the naval successes of the Athenians had engendered in the lower order of the citizens,<note anchored="true" n="2" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Aristot. Polit, ii. 9, τ⅞r <hi rend="italic">vmapχiat γάρ lv</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> tôiî</hi> <hi rend="italic">Mηδικ0ιs</hi> à <hi rend="italic">δf∣μot aιτιos γtvoμtvos iφpovημaτiσt)η,</hi> κ.r∙λ.</p></note> and the flattery of successive demagogues had fostered and diffused through the whole of the state. Now, also, faction divided the ties of family and kindred, and formed associations of the people for every lawless purpose of private ambition and cupidity. Their highest and purest court,—one principal anchor of the state, according to the intention of their great legislator,<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>PlutarΛ∙ Solon, 19, <hi rend="italic">oωμtvot</hi> ⅛i δv&lt;ri 0ovλa&lt;r <hi rend="italic">ωσπtρ ayκvp&lt;ut 6ρμ5vσav, πττov iv</hi> &lt;rdλv <hi rend="italic">τηv ιro∖ιv tσ.σJaι,</hi> e.r.λ. Tom. i. p∙ 35⅛ ed. Reiste.</p></note> —the Areopagus, was mutilated in its powers. And whilst numerous courts of law, thronged by their hundreds of judges, chosen by lot from the whole body of citizens, were constantly open,<note anchored="true" n="4" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Aristoph. Nub. ‘208, arèv <hi rend="italic">μiv A0ηvat.</hi> Στ. ri <hi rend="italic">trv</hi> Xéyerr ; ou <hi rend="italic">ιτtιθoμm</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> t</hi> <hi rend="italic">tιrtt 9ικaστas ovχ oρω κaθημivovς.</hi></p></note> * and an idle populace were encouraged, by pay from the public treasury, to attend on the business of these courts, the functions of the legislative and deliberative bodies were virtually suspended. The peremptory power of these judicial committees, in which the people at large felt and exercised a despotic authority, became the real executive of the state. Then came into intense activity the vile system of sycophancy,—a system, under which the life and property of the wealthy were at the mercy of every needy adventurer who could speak to the passions of the people, and earn a livelihood for himself by a career of successful prosecutions.</p><p>Nor was public corruption unattended by its usual evils of private luxury and debauchery. At this time too, there might be observed in the heart of a city which prided itself on its pious feeling,<note anchored="true" n="5" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Soph. (Ed. Col. 1006, « τir <hi rend="italic">γη θtoi&gt;ς iπiστaτ&lt;u τιμaιs σ.βiζeιv, fiδt τoυff imtpφeρtι.</hi></p></note> and amidst the frequency and splendour of festivals and external rituals of religion,<note anchored="true" n="6" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> β</hi> Xenophon, in his <hi rend="italic">Menorahilia,</hi> i. c. 4, gives an instance in Aristodemus of one who not only had a contempt for all religion, but even derided those who concerned themselves with it.</p></note> ® a profane scepticism with regard to the fundamental principles of religion and morality. A spirit of self-conceit and of presumption of knowledge, already natural to the Athenians, bad now widely spread among the people ; and every one was by turns dogmatist or sceptic,—according as it was his own opinion that he asserted,—or as he might display his ingenuity in questioning some received principle, or disputing some opinion proposed by another.</p><p>Add to these circumstances, the effect of a large slave population, the degraded ministers to the wants and the wealth of an insolent body of citizens, and of a number of resident foreigners engaged in carrying on the manufactures and trade of the city, paying a tax for their protection, and contributing to the military strength of the state, though excluded from its franchise. The slave, indeed, and the<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0504.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0437"/>
foreigner, lived more happily at Athens than at Lacedemon, or perhaps any other city of Greece, especially during a time of war, when their services were needful to the state.<note anchored="true" n="7" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Ari∙topb. Nub. 5, απ&lt;fλoιo i⅞τ <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ω πoλ&lt;μe,</hi> πολλών <hi rend="italic">oυv.κa ότι oυft κόλάσαι tξtστi μoι rois obuτas.</hi></p></note> Slavery, therefore, acted probably less injuriously on the character of the Athenian master, than it did elsewhere in Greece. It was tempered by the social humour of the people. But the facility thus afforded to the citizens of living in indolence and ease, and abandoning all domestic employment for the excitement of the public assemblies, and the courts, and the spectacles, naturally induced a neglect of the private and domestic duties. There is reason to believe, that whilst the Athenians appeared in the face of the world the most light-hearted of men, they were secretly unhappy in their homes ; living in listlessness from day to day on the alms of their public pay ; many of them reduced from affluence to poverty through the loss of lands and property by the ravages and pressure of war, and yet unable or unwilling to use the necessary exertions to relieve themselves from their distress. It is evidently no singular instance which Xenophon has given of this state of things at Athens, when he tells us of Aristarchus complaining to Socrates of the number of poor female relatives who, from losses in the course of the Peloponnesian war, were thrown on him for support. The difficulty which Aristarchus felt, was, that he could not expect persons who were free-born and his own kindred, to undertake any manual labour, so as to assist in maintaining themselves. Happily, however, he adopts the friendly suggestion of Socrates, and makes the experiment of setting them actively to work. The experiment succeeds; and thus contentment and cheerfulness are introduced to a home where before all was gloom and mutual suspicion.<note anchored="true" n="8" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> The story is beautifully told by Xenophon in his simple manner in the <hi rend="italic">Memorabilia,</hi> book ii. chapter 7. See also Mem. ii. 8.</p></note></p><p>In the meantime, a great number of mechanics and tradesmen had risen to wealth and importance, in consequence of the demand for every species of labour and trade, resulting from the multiplied population of the city and its numerous foreign dependencies and connexions, and, in particular, from the magnificent public works carried on during the administration of Pericles. All this while, Athens was becoming more and more a mercantile community, in the midst of strong aristocratic prejudices, still surviving, and rendered, indeed, more intense by the opposition growing up around them. In many instances, the older families would be declining in wealth, exhausted by the burthens of the state or the extravagance of individual expenditure ; whilst new families, the creations of successful trade and enterprize, would be obtaining influence by the force of their wealth, and encroaching on the privileged ground hitherto occupied only by right of birth. It may be easily conceived, therefore, that the mass of the society of the city would be now all fermentation and restlessness ; the one class pushing their interests and their claims to equality founded on their personal title, whilst the other obstinately clung to the exclusiveness and the pride of hereditary right.</p><p>But we shall best judge of the distempered state of the social atmosphere of Athens, by adverting to the character of female society as it existed there. It has often been remarked, as the glory of modern and Christian civilization, that it has restored woman to her due place in the scale of social importance, and thus most effectually chastened and elevated the general intercourse of human life. In a country so essentially social as Greece, and especially at Athens, it was practically impossible to impose on the women the absolute</p><p>seclusion of eastern despotism. Still it was even at Athens considered the rule of propriety, that the wives and daughters of citizens should live in the strict privacy of their homes, and be known and noticed as little as possible among the other sex, even for their virtues.<note anchored="true" n="9" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Thucyd, ii. 45, τ⅞r <hi rend="italic">re yàp vπapχov&lt;rηs φvσta&gt;s μr∣ χtlpoσι γtviιrθaι vμiv μeyaλη ή δ&lt;i(a,</hi> κα&gt; <hi rend="italic">ljt ar in iλaχιστor aptτηs nipι ⅞ ψόγου ir</hi> τo⅞ <hi rend="italic">Sprtσι κλ&lt;oc η∙</hi></p></note> But whilst the virtuous matron was excluded from the social circles, the place which she should have held in Athenian society was filled by other females, strangers to family ties, and attracted to Athens by the licentiousness and wealth of an imperial city. The union of high intellectual endowments, and a masculine dignity of understanding, in some distinguished individuals of this class, with the graces of female loveliness, appealed with a powerful interest to the sensual elegance of Grecian taste. We find, accordingly, at Athens, at this time, forming, as it were, the female court of the sovereign people, the Milesian Aspasia, and others of less name, living in the profession of a scandalous course of life, not only without shame, but even in the enjoyment of public respect. It was not the general of the commonwealth only that felt the spell of the charms of Aspasia, but grave philosophers resorted to her house ; and even the ladies of private families, in violation of the restrictions of custom, were taken there by their friends ; all eager to hear those interesting conversations, and lectures in political and rhetorical science for which she was famed.<note anchored="true" n="10" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Plato, Menez.—Xenoph. Mem. ii. 6.—Plutarch. Pericles. 24. Καί <hi rend="italic">yap ∑ωκpaτηs iστu&gt;</hi> 5τe <hi rend="italic">μtτa ri&gt;r γvopiμen&gt; iφoiτa.</hi> ml <hi rend="italic">rat γυvaικat aκpoaσoμtv&lt;κ ol &lt;rvvi∣iιιs iγγov ωs mτηv,</hi> κ.τ.λ. Tom. i. p. 638, Reiske.</p></note> We may judge how deeply corrupted must have been the standard of public opinion in Greece, when female profligacy could thus veil itself from the eye of moral observation, under the graces of splendid accomplishments of mind and person. So thoroughly had refinement of intellectual taste and of manners, together with the grossest impurity of morals, pervaded the whole society of Athens, that even those who were elevated above the world around them in talents, and strength of character, and kindliness of disposition, as Socrates was, imbibed in some measure the poison of the infected atmosphere which they breathed.</p><p>Such, then, was that state of things in which Socrates was trained, and which will greatly account to us for that peculiar form which the character of his philosophical teaching exhibits. For he was ever an Athenian instructing Athenians. He spoke as one fully conversant with the habits of thought and action of his countrymen ; as knowing what kind of instruction they most needed, and by what mode of address he might best win their attention. We might expect, therefore, to see in him some leading traits of the Athenian civilization of his time ; a teaching, admirable indeed in its main features, but bearing, at the same time, some marks of that corrupt state of society which called it forth, and to which it was immediately addressed.</p><p>The son of Sophroniscus a sculptor, and Phænareté a midwife, and himself brought up in his father’s art, he yet enjoyed those advantages of mental culture and social refinement which were common to every citizen of the democratic Athens. The meanness of his birth and his poverty, much as high birth and wealth were esteemed there, would not exclude him from familiar intercourse with persons of the highest rank and consideration in the state. Nor, indeed, could the advantages of education be restricted to a privileged few, where every one lived in public, and where knowledge was for the most part acquired and communicated by conversation and oral discussion.</p><p>If, in the general relaxation of discipline at Athens, the citizen was no longer obliged to submit himself to a prescribed course of education under the eye of the state, and it was<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0505.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0438"/>
left to each person to avail himself, or not, of the sources of instruction presented in the intellectual society of the city, Socrates was not a person to neglect the advantages placed in his way. Money he had not, to pay to the Sophists, the great masters of his day. But he had from childhood an inquisitive mind. He felt that he was thrown on his own resources of thought, and that he must be his own master in the art of education. And to this great object he appears to have bent, from the earliest time, all the powers of his energetic mind, making it his constant employment to inquire from every one,<note anchored="true" n="11" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Laches, p. 186, c., <hi rend="italic">iyω μiv nvv,</hi> κ.τ.λ. p. 176, Bip. ed.</p></note> and collect on every occasion, some hint towards the right prosecution of it. We may picture to ourselves the young Socrates, resembling the Socrates of mature life, freely entering into conversation with all to whom he had access ; feeling and acknowledging his own ignorance ; listening attentively to all that he heard ; weighing and discussing it in his own mind with patience and acuteness ; and not resting until he had traced it out in all its bearings to the utmost of his power. Thus would he gradually form and strengthen that faculty of observation, and that analytical acumen for which he was afterwards so eminently distinguished.</p><p>Nor has Plato improbably put a prophecy of his future eminence in the mouth of one of the great masters of the day, when he makes Protagoras say of him, with the self- complacency of the man of established reputation : “ For my part, Socrates, I commend your spirit, and the method of your reasoning ; for whilst in other points I am no bad sort of person, as I think, I am the farthest from being an envious one. For concerning you in particular, I have already observed to many, that of all I meet, I admire you by far the most; of those of your own age, even to the extreme; and I say too, I should not be astonished if you were to turn out a man of celebrity for philosophy.”<note anchored="true" n="12" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Plato, Protag. Op. iii. p∙ 193.</p></note> ’ To the same effect is the story, that his father, being at a loss how to educate him, consulted the Delphic oracle, and was advised to leave him entirely to his own bent, inasmuch as he had a director in himself superior to a thousand teachers.<note anchored="true" n="13" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Plutarch, de Gen. Socr.</p></note> The simple interpretation of what is here thrown into the form of marvel probably is, that he gave, even when a child, striking indications of a devotedness to those studies which became the business of his manhood.</p><p>The notice of a wealthy individual of Athens, the excellent Crito, appears to have been early attracted to Socrates. Crito was of about the same age as Socrates;<note anchored="true" n="14" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Apo∣. p. 78, <hi rend="italic">lμοs ηλuu0τηs.</hi></p></note> and an attachment to the pursuit of philosophy, and an admiration of the character of Socrates, naturally led to that intimacy which he now commenced with the young philosopher, and steadily maintained through his subsequent life. Through him Socrates was relieved from the necessity of earning his livelihood by the profession of a sculptor; or, as Laertius expresses it, “was raised from the workshop.”<note anchored="true" n="15" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>» Diog. Laert. in vit. ii. 4.</p></note> Sculpture, indeed, was in high honour at Athens, especially at this time. For Phidias, enjoying the protection of Pericles, was now adorning the city with the immortal productions of his own chisel, as well as other noble works of art executed under his taste and direction. But to follow up the profession with success, required a devotion of mind and hand that must preclude the opportunities indispensable for the moral student. And though, for a time, Socrates worked at the art,—and with success, if a statue of the Graces in the citadel of Athens, attributed to him, were really his workmanship ;<note anchored="true" n="16" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Xenoρh. Mem i. 2, ouδi n∙ωrroτ&lt; <hi rend="italic">vτriσχerο διδάσκαλος .ιvαι τόντον.</hi></p></note> —we may imagine how distasteful the occupation, however intellectual in itself, must have been to a mind, so eager for observation on living man, so intent on mental and moral phenomena, as that of Socrates ; and how gladly he would exchange the labour of his paternal art for that philosophic leisure which tl&gt;e friendship of Crito held out to him.</p><p>The world of that day reproached the philosophers with servility, taunting them with being ever seen at the “ gates of the rich.” In some instances, the reproach may have been just. But in general, the fact was the reverse. Their society rather was courted by the great and wealthy, who were proud of the reputation of being patrons of philosophy. To Socrates, indeed, the patronage of a man of wealth would be peculiarly acceptable, not so much for the means of subsistence, about which he was absolutely thoughtless and indifferent, as for the society itself to which he would thus be introduced, and the opportunity of carrying on his researches into philosophy, both by books and by the oral instructions of its living professors. To him it would be the very means by which he would enlarge his field of moral observation. The social evenings of Athens were the natural sequences of the mornings of the agora, and the courts, and the council, and the assembly. They prolonged in festive conversation that strife of words and competition of argument, which had been begun in the busy and serious discussions of the morning, and of which the last murmurs had scarcely died away on the ear of the assembled guests. For Athenian life was a life of constant excitement. What Demosthenes observed an hundred years afterwards, and an apostle four hundred years later still, —that the Athenians did nothing but go about and ask the news of the day,—was a characteristic of the people already strongly developed at this period of their history. Socrates, who, in his own person, gave a philosophical cast to this inquisitive spirit, would be peculiarly interested by such opportunities of exercising it as were presented in the animated encounters of the symposium. There he would see human nature displayed in some of its most striking forms. There he would meet the citizen full of years and honours, experienced in the arts of government and diplomacy, and in the service of the state by land and sea ; the poet flushed with his victories in the dramatic contest ; the sophist armed at all points for the display ; the philosopher expounding his theories; the orator, the idol of the people in his day; the courtly patron of literature ; and a circle of young men, the flower of the highest rank in the state ; each bearing his part in the free and lively interchange of thought, emulously provoking one another to discussion, and contending for the mastery in the conflict of debate.</p><p>By such society Socrates would be effectually prepared for that active enterprize of philosophy, which formed the whole engagement of his life. In the meagre information handed down to us respecting the details of his history, we are not able to ascertain at what precise period of life he began his career of public teaching, or at least attracted notice as the philosopher of Athens. The transition would probably be gradual, from the youthful inquirer, to the mature and expert teacher of others. This transition would be the less perceptible in the case of Socrates, from the circumstance, that he never professed to <hi rend="italic">teach,</hi> even when he was most actively employed in teaching ; but still, at the last, as he had done from the first, merely to <hi rend="italic">inquire.</hi><note anchored="true" n="17" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Diog. Laert. ii. 5. Pausanias, i. 22; ix 3ö.</p></note> For his part, he disdained the <hi rend="italic">profession</hi> of philosophy. He was disgusted with the vain pretension advanced by the Sophists, of being masters of every science, and capable of imparting instruction on any given subject. He accordingly set out with the antagonist position, that he <hi rend="italic">knew nothing:</hi> that his only wisdom, if he possessed any beyond other men, consisted in his being <hi rend="italic">aware of</hi> his real ignorance, whilst others ignorantly presumed on the possession of a knowledge which they had not. His teaching, therefore, was only a continuation of the process of educa-<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0506.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0439"/>
tion of his own mind, by extending it to the minds of others. He was fond of describing it as an <hi rend="italic">examination</hi> or <hi rend="italic">scrutiny</hi> of the mind ; a method of finding out the real condition of each mind, and so of preparing it for the due exercise of its powers in the practical emergencies of human life. He saw that, the evils of life arose, in great part, from the wrong judgments of men,—from their mistaking their own powers, presuming on their knowledge, and ability, and the truth of opinions adopted without inquiry. He endeavoured then to effect the cure of human error and unhappiness by a reformation of the intellect. The first step towards this would be taken, if men could be only divested of this vain self-confidence ; if they could be brought to <hi rend="italic">suspect</hi> that they might be mistaken in their judgments, and so to <hi rend="italic">question</hi> themselves. This preliminary labour was employment enough for any one man’s life, especially in a society such as that of Athens, so entirely infected with the sophistical leaven. Socrates wisely confined his exertions to this simple object. He is content to excite inquiry,—to provoke discussion,—and thus to suggest the necessity of self-discipline in order to right judgment. He does not, like other philosophers, quit the seclusion of a study, or the field of foreign travel, to come forth to the world the accomplished teacher of the accumulated wisdom of years of solitary thought and reflection. Whilst philosophizing in the agora and the streets of Athens, in the workshops of the artizan, or at the banquets of the rich, he is still employed in the work of <hi rend="italic">disciplining</hi> the mind. Thus he passes on insensibly from the education of himself to the education of others, and it is difficult consequently, or rather impossible, to say in his case, where the character of the learner ends, or where that of the philosopher and teacher begins.</p><p>Yet, entirely as Socrates disregarded all positive knowledge, and threw himself on the resources of a shrewd and extensive observation of human nature, we must not suppose that he neglected to inform himself in the existing systems of philosophy, and the particular sciences as they were then understood and taught. There is reason to believe, that he had accurately studied the systems of the early physical philosophers of the Ionic school, as well as the moral and mathematical theories of the Pythagoreans, and the dialectics of the school of Elea. Without supposing him so deeply versed in the doctrines of the several schools, as would be inferred from his exact discussions in the dialogues of Plato, there is still ample evidence, from the more direct account of Xenophon, that he was by no means ignorant of them. He had doubtless read much,<note anchored="true" n="18" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Xenoph. Mem, i. 6.</p></note> as well as observed much, when he commenced his philosophic mission. Xenophon indeed tells us that Socrates considered the physical and dialectical theories of his predecessors as unprofitable. But he takes care to add, that Socrates was not unacquainted with these theories. And in particular, as to the sciences of astronomy and geometry, he thought the attention of the student wasted in investigating their more abstruse theorems. But he was able (as Xenophon further observes), to speak on the subjects of these sciences also from his own knowledge of them.<note anchored="true" n="19" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Xenoph∙ Mem. iv. 7.</p></note></p><p>Nor are we to suppose that, whilst he had properly no master in that line of philosophical study which he had marked out for himself,<note anchored="true" n="20" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ He reckons himself in Xenoph. Conviv. i. 5. among the <hi rend="italic">alτοvpγ&gt;ι</hi> τ⅞s ⅛ιλoσoφιαr.</p></note> he had no aid in the cultivation of his mind, from the living masters of philosophy in his day. The long residence of Anaxagoras at Athens, probably coincides in time with part of the early life of Socrates.<note anchored="true" n="21" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• It must be admitted, however, that the chronology of the life of Anaxagoras is very doubtful.</p></note> To him, therefore, Socrates would naturally have access, as well as to Archelaus,<note anchored="true" n="22" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Archelaus is called both a Milesian and an Athenian. The probability is that he was a Milesian, since philosophy bad scarcely yet found a home at Athens.</p></note> <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> his disciple, and the inheritor of his doctrines. If he had no personal intercourse with Anaxagoras, it is at least highly probable, from the testimony of Plato, that he was acquainted with the famous treatise of Anaxagoras, which contained his theory of the universe.<note anchored="true" n="23" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• See the Phædo, p. 97. The writings of Anaxagoras appear to have been extensively circulated. Socrates is made in Plato’s <hi rend="italic">Apοlοgy</hi></p><p>to say to Melitus, o ιn <hi rend="italic">avrovς aκ.ιpovt γραμμάτων</hi> eιvαt, <hi rend="italic">ωστe ovκ iιδivaι oτι τ Αναζαγόρον βιβλία rôv</hi> Kλofoμevtou <hi rend="italic">γiμsι</hi> rwrwv τών λόγων.</p></note> · And perhaps we may distinctly trace the early and abiding influence of the lessons of this great philosopher throughout the teaching of Socrates, in his uniform maintenance of the principle of an all-disposing mind, the glory of the system of Anaxagoras.</p><p>To the writings of Heraclitus, his attention appears to have been drawn by the poet Euripides ; if the anecdote be true, as related by Laertius, that on being asked by Euripides, who had put them into his hand, what he thought of them, he replied, alluding to the studied obscurity of that philosopher ; “ What I understand is excellent ; so also, I suppose, is what I do not understand ; only there is need of some Delian diver to reach the sense.”<note anchored="true" n="24" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Diog. Laert. in vit. ii. 7.</p></note> He had also opportunities of conversing with Zeno the Eleatic, and Theodorus of Cyrene ; the former eminent for his dialectical skill, the latter the most distinguished geometrician of the time. And though his scanty means precluded his attendance on the professional lectures of Prodicus, the fashionable teacher of rhetoric at that day at Athens, it cannot be doubted that he would on several occasions have been among the company assembled at the house of some wealthy citizen, and there heard from the lips of that accomplished master of language those elaborate oratorical displays which made his name proverbial for wisdom.<note anchored="true" n="25" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Plato, Meno. p. 96. <hi rend="italic">Kιvδvvtυoμtv, J</hi> Mc'vωv, <hi rend="italic">tγω τt</hi> καl &lt;rv, <hi rend="italic">φαύλοι τιv.t tιvaι 5vδptr, και σt τt Γoργιat ivχ lκavωs πtιraΛevκtvaι,</hi></p><p>xαl <hi rend="italic">iμi Πρόδικοί.</hi> P. 382. Bipont.</p></note> With the poet Euripides, indeed, the disciple of Anaxagoras and Prodicus, and who was his senior only by a few years, he appears to have lived in habits of intimacy. With Euripides he would probably often have discussed those ethical topics which the poet so greatly delighted to transfuse into his tragic scenes, and associate with the interest of dramatic incident. They were in fact brother-labourers in the same cause, though in different ways. For whilst Euripides endeavoured to work a reformation of his countrymen, by didactic addresses insinuated through their feelings, amidst the interest of tragic story, Socrates appealed at once to their understandings, and amidst the business or pastime of real life. The envy of contemporaries was prone to attribute the excellence of the poet in some of his dramatic efforts, to the aid of his philosopher-friend.<note anchored="true" n="26" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>∙ Aristoph. Nub. Diog. Laert. in vit. ii. 5.</p></note> ® The truth probably is, that the benefit of their intercourse was mutual ; that, whilst the poet’s imagination was informed and chastened by the shrewd and severe wisdom of the philosopher, the philosopher also, ever intent on his calling, would enlarge his mind with riches drawn from the genius, and taste, and learning of the poet.</p><p>The co-existence of literary and philosophic elegance with the most disgusting coarseness of moral feeling and conduct, in the character of the Athenian courtesan, has been already noticed. To Aspasia, the heroine of her class, as we may call her, when we refer to her influence over Pericles, and the encomiums of her by Plato and others, Socrates is expressly stated to have been indebt-<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0507.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0440"/>
ed for instruction in rhetoric, as also in other subjects.<note anchored="true" n="27" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Xenophon, Mem. ii. 6. Mà Δ*, <hi rend="italic">ουχ,</hi> ωr <hi rend="italic">ποτ. tγω</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> f</hi> <hi rend="italic">Ασπασίας ήκουσα. .φη γάρ, τaς aγa∂iις προμvηστρiδaς, κ.τ.λ.</hi> P. 101.</p></note> Whilst Xenophon also introduces him familiarly conversing with Theodota, whom he describes as living in great splendour at Athens, the object of general admiration for her personal charms, and inviting her to become his disciple,<note anchored="true" n="28" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Xenophon, Mem. iii. 12. Ælian. Var. Hist. xiii. 31.</p></note> ’— Plato leads us to believe that Socrates was himself the disciple of another of the same class, the Mantinean Diotimè, who, among her other accomplishments, was distinguished in particular for her skill in the art of divination.<note anchored="true" n="29" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Plato, Conviv. p. 201. op. t. 10. p. 227. Bipont.</p></note></p><p>Instruction in music formed an important part of Athenian education. Socrates, it seems, did not neglect the opportunities which the presence of the great masters of the art in Athene afforded him of learning its principles. Connus accordingly is claimed for him, as his master in music.<note anchored="true" n="30" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Menexenus.</p></note> Damon, another celebrated musician, though not more eminent in the science which he professed, than as a politician and sophist, was resident at Athens during part of the administration of Pericles, the intimate and counsellor of that great statesman, as well as his instructor in music.<note anchored="true" n="31" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plutarch in Pericl. op. t. i. p. 594. Reiske.</p></note> ® From him also, we are told, Socrates received instruction in the art. By these accounts, however, we may probably understand, not that he became a proficient in the musical art, but that he had listened to Damon as well as to Connus, discoursing on the subject, and studied its theories under them, so far, at least, as music entered into the general pursuit of philosophy.<note anchored="true" n="32" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Diog. Laert. in vit. ii. 5, 15. Laertius says that Socrates learned to play on the lyre.</p></note></p><p>It should be observed, indeed, that though Socrates strongly discouraged the <hi rend="italic">presumption</hi> of knowledge in all with whom he conversed, he did not disapprove of the acquisition of particular kinds of knowledge. He communicated whatever he knew to every one that came in his way ; and where he was himself unacquainted with any subject, he referred his hearers to those who possessed the information.<note anchored="true" n="33" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Xenoph. Mem. iv. 7.</p></note> He was not in fact opposed to knowledge in itself. He was glad to embrace it wherever it could be found. But he was an enemy to the substitution of mere intellectual acquisitions,—and those often superficial and unreal,—for <hi rend="italic">education</hi> of the mind and character. He felt, and justly felt, that knowledge by itself was vanity. The tendency of the age was to ascribe value exclusively to mental acuteness and dexterity. Ingenuity and cleverness obtained the merit and the prize of wisdom. His labour was to draw his countrymen from thinking too highly of their boasted knowledge. He wished them to see how greatly they overrated intellectual acquirements,—how much they had yet to learn if they would be real proficients in wisdom.</p><p>Socrates indeed appears to have regarded philosophy in the light of a sacred mission, to which he was specially called, rather than of a study and exercise of the mind. This notion of philosophy had already been exemplified by Pythagoras and his followers. But they had realized it by forming themselves into distinct communities or colleges ; separating themselves from the world around, by a solemn initiation, and the practice of an ascetic discipline. Socrates, however, had no thought of changing the outward form of society. He did not propose, like Pythagoras, to institute a refuge from the pollutions and misery of the world, or to educate a peculiar brotherhood, who should afterwards act on the social mass. He did not address himself to the few. His school was all Athens, or rather indeed all Greece. Leaving society as it was, he sought to infuse a new spirit into it, by carrying his philosophy into every department of it. He therefore went about among all classes of people, preferring none, despising none, but adapting his instructions to every variety of condition and character. Thus did he in truth, according to the observation commonly applied to him from the time of Cicero, bring down philosophy from heaven to earth ; but not so much by being the first to give a moral tone to philosophy, as by the universality and philanthropy of his teaching. Philosophy in his hands was no longer an exclusive and privileged profession. It no longer spoke as from an oracular shrine, and in the language of mystery. It now conversed with every man at his own home,—submitted to be familiarly approached and viewed without reserve,—and, instead of waiting to be formally consulted by its votaries only, volunteered to mingle in the business, and interests, and pleasures of every-day life.</p><p>His manner of life and of teaching is thus described by Xenophon.<note anchored="true" n="34" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Mem. i. I. 10 ; also Plutarch, <hi rend="italic">Utrum seni ger.. Resp.</hi></p><p>Plato. Menexenus, p. 235. Kαl <hi rend="italic">lμοi μiv y.,</hi> ω Mrvc^eve, <hi rend="italic">οvδiv 0avμaςov oιω</hi> τ' <hi rend="italic">.ivaι .ιπ.ιv, &lt;p τνγχάν.ι διδάσκαλον oυσa</hi> δυ rravυ <hi rend="italic">φαύλη π.ρ'ι ρητορικής, άλλ' ήπ.ρ</hi> καί άλλονν <hi rend="italic">πολλούς</hi> καί <hi rend="italic">αγαθούς Ιποίησ. ρήτορας, .να</hi> δ« καί <hi rend="italic">διαφίροντα τών 'Ελλήνων, Π.ρικλ.α τον Savθiππoυ,</hi> Μ. <hi rend="italic">τις αυτή ; ή δηλονότι 'Ασπασίαν λty.ις</hi>; Σ. <hi rend="italic">λίγω γάρ</hi>; κα* <hi rend="italic">Κόννον γ. τον Μητροβίου. οΰτοι γάρ μοι</hi> δυο c«rl διδάσκαλο,· ό <hi rend="italic">μ.ν μουσικής, ή δ. ρητορικής.</hi> Ρ. 277. Bipont.</p></note> ’</p><p>“ He was constantly in public. For early in the morning he would go to the walks and the gymnasia ; and when the agora was full, he was to be seen there ; and constantly during the remainder of the day, he would be wherever he was likely to meet with the most persons ; and for the most part he would talk, and all that would might hear him.”</p><p>The nature of his conversations is thus further reported by the same faithful authority :</p><p>“ No one ever saw Socrates doing, or heard him saying, any thing impious or profane. For not only did he not discourse about the nature of all things, as most others, inquiring how, what by the sophists is called the universe, consists, and by what laws each heavenly thing is produced ; but he would point out the folly of those who studied such matters. And the first inquiry he would make of them was, whether they proceeded to such studies from thinking themselves already sufficiently acquainted with human things ; or whether they thought they were acting becomingly in passing by human things, and giving their attention to divine. He would wonder, too, it was not evident to them, that it was not possible for men to find out these matters ; since even those who most prided themselves on discoursing of them, did not agree in opinion with each other, but were affected like madmen in relation to one another. For of madmen, whilst some did not fear even the fearful, others were terrified at things not terrible ; whilst some were not ashamed to say or do any thing even before the multitude, others objected even to going out into the world ; whilst some paid no honour to sacred things, or altars, or any other religious object, others worshipped even stones, and common stocks, and brutes. So of those who speculated on the nature of the universe, whilst some thought that Being was one only, others thought it was infinite in number; whilst some thought that all things were in perpetual motion, others thought it impossible for any thing to be moved ; whilst some thought that all things were in a course of generation and destruction, others thought that nothing could possibly be generated or destroyed. He would further consider respecting them thus : whether, as the learners of human things think they shall be able to make practical use of their knowledge for themselves and any one else at pleasure, so also the searchers into divine things hold, that having ascertained by what laws each thing<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0508.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0441"/>
is generated, they shall be able to produce at pleasure winds, and waters, and seasons, and whatever else of the kind they may want ; or whether they have no such expectation, but it suffices them only to know how every thing of this kind is generated. Such, then, was his manner of speaking about those who busied themselves with these matters. But, for his part, he was ever discoursing about human things, inquiring what was pious, what impious, what honourable, what base, what just, what unjust, what sobriety, what madness, what courage, what cowardice, what a state, what a statesman, what a government of men, what the character of a governor ; and about other subjects, which, by being known, would make men honourable and virtuous, whilst those who were ignorant of them, would justly be called slavish.”</p><p>Xenophon has thus fully touched the character of the teaching of Socrates in its leading points, and the nature of his constant occupation at Athens. The intermissions of military service appear to have been the only occasions of any variation in this uniform course of life. No other country had any charms for him, as no other afforded such rich opportunities of conversing with men, and studying human nature.<note anchored="true" n="35" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Laches, 187, e. *Ov <hi rend="italic">μ∩ι δoκιιs ιlbιvaι ôri ôs dv ιyγυτdτω ∑ωκpaτoυs ∏</hi> λoγω, <hi rend="italic">ω&lt;rπtρ γivtι, κai πλη&lt;rιoζr∣ Dιdλιy0μcvos, ανάγκη aυτω .... πιριαγόμινον</hi> τω λόγω, <hi rend="italic">μη πavσa&lt;τ∂aι υπό τούτον πριν ίμπίπη ils το δώόναι πιρι αυτόν</hi> λόγον, <hi rend="italic">οντινα τρόπον</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">νυν τι ζη, και οντινα τον παριληλνθύτα</hi> fi&lt;ov <hi rend="italic">βιβιώκιν,</hi> κ. τ. λ. Ρ. 180.</p></note> His activity was essentially different from that either of his predecessors or successors in the path of philosophy. They travelled from place to place searching for knowledge, storing their minds with various observations, and making philosophy their formal business. Socrates, as he had no stated school or place of audience, so he had no design of framing any system of philosophy, or of enlarging the researches and discoveries of former philosophers, or of pursuing knowledge as an ultimate object. He regarded himself as called by the voice of Deity, to undertake the reformation of men, and especially of his fellow-citizens, as constituting his proper sphere of duty, from their corruptions of sentiment and conduct. He stood, therefore, by the great stream of human life which was ever flowing at Athens, and watched its course. He is said once to have visited Samos in company with Archelaus, the disciple of Anaxagoras, and also to have gone to the Pythian and the Isthmian games. With these exceptions, and those of the occasions of military service abroad, he appears to have constantly remained at home, unattracted from the town, the seat of his philosophic mission, by invitations even to the courts of princes. In vain did Scopas of Cranon, and Eurylochus of Larissa, offer him money, and invite him to visit them.<note anchored="true" n="36" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Diog. Laert. in vit.</p></note> He could refuse also the hospitality of Archelaus, king of Macedonia, the same with whom the poet Euripides found a kind and honourable refuge in his old age, from the envy of his countrymen, and domestic grievance. His refusal of the invitation of Archelaus is said indeed to have been accompanied with the declaration of his feeling, that he could not brook the acceptance of a favour which it was entirely out of his power to return.<note anchored="true" n="37" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Aristot. Rhet. ii. 23.</p><p>p. 120.</p></note> Nay, so entirely engrossed was he in the work to which he had devoted himself, that he was a stranger, as Plato represents him, even to the immediate neighbourhood of the city. The banks of the Ilyssus, even then classic ground, rich with legendary associations, could not seduce him from the agora and the crowd; so that he seemed scarcely at home beyond the walls of Athens.<note anchored="true" n="38" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Conviv. 220, a. ρ. 266 ; also Charmides.</p></note></p><p>No Athenian, however, could decline the military service of the state. And this service, at the time of Socrates, often engaged the citizen in hazardous enterprizes and long absences far from his home. The first occasion on which Socrates is related to have served, was in the Chersonese at Potidæa, just before the opening of the Peloponnesian war. The service in which the Athenian soldiers were engaged here was one of great hardship. It was in the winter season, and the climate in those parts was most severe. Amongst those who distinguished themselves by their resoluteness and gallantry, none was so conspicuous as the philosopher. Whilst others were clothing themselves with additional garments, and wrapping their feet in wool, he was observed in his usual dress, and walking barefoot on the ice, with more ease than others with their shoes. Nor even amidst these circumstances, did he merge the character of the philosopher in that of the soldier. He was seen one morning at sun-rise fixed in contemplation. At noon he was in the some position, and still in the evening, and so continued through the night, until the sun-rise of the following day. Such, too, was his bravery in the engagements at Potidæa, that he earned for himself the prize of distinction, but readily sacrificed his claim to the wishes of the generals, in favour of a more illustrious candidate in the person of Alcibiades. Alcibiades himself would have refused the honour as due rather to Socrates ; for to the unwillingness of Socrates to leave him wounded on the field, he had been even indebted for his own life, and the preservation of his arms, after the battle. But the philosopher, with a true magnanimity, insisted on the award of the generals.<note anchored="true" n="39" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Phædr. *230. Συ δr <hi rend="italic">yi</hi> ω <hi rend="italic">θανμάσιι, dτoπωτaτos τιs φaιvη' aτιχvωs yàp o λiγhs, ξtvayovμivω</hi> τιvi καί <hi rend="italic">ουκ ιπιχωρίω loικat' oυτωs ίκ του d(ττιos ουτ ils την ΰπιρορίαν aπoδημtis, όυτ ΐζω τiιχovs ιμoιyι 6oκiιs τοπαράπαν ιζιϊναι.</hi> ΣΩ. <hi rend="italic">∑vγyivωσκt δή μοι, ω apιsι, φιλoμaJηs yàp tιμι' τα μiv ονν χωρία και τα Hvipa oiιht. μι θιλιι ίιίάσκιιν, öi H ΐν τω άστιι άνθρωποι.</hi> Ρ. 287 ; also Crito,</p></note></p><p>The next occasion of military service, in which he was scarcely less distinguished than at Potidæa, was in the eighth year of the Peloponnesian war, at the battle of Delium in Boeotia. The battle was an unsuccessful one to the Athenians, and they were forced to retreat in disorder. Alcibiades was also present on this occasion, and overtook Socrates in company with Laches, one of the generals, on the way. He was on horseback, and comparatively therefore out of danger, whilst they were on foot. He had opportunity, therefore, of admiring the presence of mind which Socrates displayed on the occasion, even beyond Laches, and the steadiness and vigilance with which he kept the enemy from pressing upon them, and so secured their retreat.<note anchored="true" n="40" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Conviv. p. 270. The story is again alluded to by Plato, in the dialogue, <hi rend="italic">Laches.</hi> Laches is made to say that he bad had experience of the <hi rend="italic">actions</hi> of Socrates, and reminds Socrates of the day of their common danger, <hi rend="italic">r) μtτ tμoυ σvvftιικιvδvvtvσas, κ. τ.</hi> λ. P. 182. Laertius says that Socrates saved Xenophon, who had fallen from his horse in the battle of Delium, (in vit. Soc. ii. 5-7.) But this cannot be true, as Xenophon would be much too young at that time for military service. In the Deipnosophists of Athenaeus, (v. 55), doubt is thrown on these accounts of the military service of Socrates, and instances are given of the historical inaccuracy of Plato. The objections, however, as there given, are evidently thrown out in the wav of discussion, and not with perfect seriousness, as if the speaker re illy thought them of weight.</p></note></p><p>These incidents seem to rest on indisputable evidence. The account of them is put into the mouth of Alcibiades by Plato, in that most ingenious of his dialogues, the <hi rend="italic">Banquet.</hi> The very form in which they are introduced, related as they are by an eye-witness, and that witness Alcibiades, the person, next to Socrates himself, most interested in them, may justly be regarded as giving a sanction to their history, independent of the fictitious circumstances of the dialogue.</p><p>The third occasion on which Socrates served as a soldier<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0509.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0442"/>
was again in Thrace, at Amphipolis,<note anchored="true" n="41" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Plato, Apolog. 28. c. op. i. p. 67. Diog. Laert. in vit. Ælian, Var. Hist. iii. 17.</p></note> in the same year as that of the unfortunate expedition to Delium. No particulars are mentioned of this adventure. But the fact itself is sufficiently attested. Nor, though it follows immediately on the affair of Delium, is it improbable on that account. For at this busy period of the war, when the Athenians were making demonstrations of their power, by the presence of their forces in different places at once, and when Brasilias was pushing his successes against them in Thrace, no individual of the military age, (and Socrates was not more than forty-six or forty-seven years of age at this time), would enjoy any long interval of relaxation from foreign service.</p><p>With these exceptions, Socrates appears then to have constantly resided at Athens. All this time, throughout his whole life indeed, he lived in great poverty, content with the least that might suffice for mere sustenance and clothing from day to day.</p><p>Yet it was no artificial, and melancholy, and fanatical life that he led. He accustomed himself to a strict moderation, not with any view to the mortification of the body, or as thinking that abstinence was in itself a virtue, but in order to self-command ; by rendering himself as independent as possible of the circumstances of the body, to disencumber the soul of every burthen and obstruction to its free operation. There was nothing, indeed, of austerity in his life or manner. He might be seen walking barefoot, but it was not for the pain that it might inflict. It was only that he might bear cold and privations of every kind the better, and suffer the less inconvenience when exposed to necessary hardships, and require the less for his ordinary subsistence. So far was he from studying a discipline of bodily severity for its own sake, that he was observed at times mingling in the social festivities of his fellow-citizens with the full freedom of Athenian conviviality, and shewing that he could bear excesses which mastered others, without losing his self-command.<note anchored="true" n="42" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Plato, Conviv. Ælian, Var. Hist. iv. 11.</p></note></p><p>One account, indeed, but not a very credible one, as it rests on the authority of Aristoxenus, an invidious writer, states that he was supported by the alms of friends, contributed from time to time for his relief. With his very limited wants, and his ready access to the house of Crito and other liberal patrons of philosophy at Athens, he would not have to depend on this precarious charity. The pittance which sufficed for the humblest citizen would suffice for him. He is said to have inherited a patrimony of seventy or eighty minæ.<note anchored="true" n="43" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> About L.400 of our money. Plutarch (in his life of Aristides) finds fault with Demetrius Phalereus for having endeavoured to remove the imputation of poverty from Socrates, by stating that Socrates had land of his own and seventy minæ put out to intereat by Crito. Demetrius, however, seems only to have stated what he believed to be the truth. The idea of bis extreme indigence originated probably with the caricatures of bis profession of poverty by the comic poets ; and true as it was substantially, was afterwards, it seems, maintained by bis friends and admirers, as the evidence of the consistency of his life with his avowed contempt for worldly possessions.</p></note> But this sum, it is added, he lost (though the time is not stated when the loss occurred) by the failure of the person with whom it had been placed at interest. He possessed also a house in Athens ; and he was able, however scantily, to support a family. So that we cannot suppose he was absolutely destitute of all resources of subsistence. He appears then rather to have voluntarily renounced every kind of worldly possession, so far as his own personal comfort was concerned, than to have been absolutely reduced to want by the pressure of circumstances. Poverty, in fact, was his profession, and not the mere necessity of his case. If he prided himself in any thing, it was in his avowal of his contempt for riches, and disregard of domestic interests and comforts, in contrast with the general habits of an age of selfish activity and profusion. The means of enriching himself, at least</p><p>of extricating himself from want, were often placed in his power, and he as often rejected them. Alcibiades offered him land on which he might build a house, but he refused it pointedly, observing, “ Had I wanted shoes, would you have offered me leather to make shoes for myself?—and ridiculous should I have been in taking it.” Charmides would have given him slaves, as a source of revenue by their labour. This offer also he refused.<note anchored="true" n="44" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Diog. Laert. in vit.</p></note> In the same spirit, he would often cast a look at the number of things that were sold, and say to himself, “ Of how many things I have no need !<note anchored="true" n="45" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>&gt; Ibid.</p></note> <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> Thus was his whole plan of life studiously opposed to the acceptance of any provision for his comfort or ease. It was a service of the Deity in which he felt himself engaged, and in the prosecution of that, solemnly devoted to a course of hardy poverty.<note anchored="true" n="46" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Plato, Apolog. Άλλ’ <hi rend="italic">lv πtvia μvpla tl∣u</hi> ôià <hi rend="italic">τ&gt;'∣v</hi> row <hi rend="italic">Θt5v λarptiav.</hi> Op. i. p. 5.</p></note> ®</p><p>In the domestic relations of life, he lived an Athenian among Athenians. He differed from other heads of families at Athens in this respect, that in his dedication of himself to his philosophic mission, he took no thought about the management of his private affairs. His home was abroad ; his household the people of Athens. Still he discharged the duties of a husband, and the father of a family ; and that under trying circumstances, unless the proverbial severity of temper of his wife Xanthippe be esteemed an idle scandal of the day. No Athenian, indeed, was truly domestic, in the sense of making his home the scene of his highest interest and enjoyment. Nor was Socrates domestic in this sense. Still less was he so than other Athenians ; inasmuch as his very profession of life was a call from the bosom of his family. But in the midst of these avocations from his immediate home, and the vexations to which he was subjected there, he was not estranged from the ties of domestic affection. Xenophon has recorded a simple and touching trait of the character of Socrates under this particular point of view—a trait the more interesting, as almost every thing else that we know of the philosopher is drawn from his life in public. It occurs in the course of a conversation between Socrates and bis son Lamprocles, who had complained of the insufferable temper of his mother Xanthippe. “ What,” said he to the youth, “ do you think it more annoying to you to hear what she says, than it is to the actors, when in the tragedies they say every thing bad of one another ?” “ But they, I conceive,” re</p><p>plied the son, “ bear it easily, because they do not suppose that the speaker, in contradicting them, intends to hurt them, or that, in threatening, he intends to do them any ill.” “ Then are you,” resumed Socrates, “ vexed, when you well know that what your mother says to you, she says, not only intending no evil, but even wishing more good to you than to any one else ; or do you regard your mother as unkindly affected towards you ?” Lamprocles disclaiming this latter supposition ; “ Do you, then,” he added, “ say of her, who is both kind to you, and takes every possible care of you when you are sick, that you may recover, and want nothing proper for you, and who, moreover, prays to the gods in your behalf for many a good, and pays vows,—that she is vexatious ? For my part, I think, if you cannot bear such a mother, you cannot bear what is good for you.”<note anchored="true" n="47" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>' Xeιιopb. Mem. ii. 2.</p></note></p><p>From the description given by Plato of the family of Socrates in the prison-scene, it would appear, that Socrates had other three children besides Lamprocles,—for Lampro-<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0510.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0443"/>
cles died at an early age, before his father,<note anchored="true" n="48" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Plutarch, De Gen. Socr. p. 331.</p></note> —who were yet children, one of them a boy, another a child in the arms, at the time of their father’s death.<note anchored="true" n="49" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Plato, Phœdo, pp. 135, 262.</p></note> We learn from other authorities,<note anchored="true" n="50" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Aristotle, cited by Laertius in vit. Socr.</p></note> that two of his children were named Sophroniscus and Menexenus; but they are said to have been the children, not of Xanthippe, but of another wife, Myrto, the grand-daughter of Aristides the just.<note anchored="true" n="51" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>« Diog Laert. in vit.</p></note> To account for this, it has been stated, that after their disasters in Sicily, the Athenians made a decree authorizing double marriages, with the view of recruiting their exhausted population. But this statement does not appear to be borne out by the earlier authorities on the subject of Athenian legislation. Nor is it probable that a law should have been enacted, directly sanctioning a form of polygamy. It appears, that during the pressure and confusion of the Peloponnesian war, persons obtained the freedom of the city of Athens, whose title was objectionable on the constitutional ground of their not being bom of citizen-parents on both sides. Thus had Pericles, after the death of his two legitimate sons, obtained the admission of his son, Pericles, by Aspasia, to the privilege of citizenship ;<note anchored="true" n="52" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• The same who was among the generals at the battle of Arginusæ, and who were cruelly and iniquitously sacrificed to party spirit after their great victory.</p></note> though he had himself carried, some time before, a law of strict limitation, under which, nearly four thousand were deprived of the franchise.<note anchored="true" n="53" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Plutarch in Pericl. Op. i. p 667.</p></note> Such extension of the privilege to the offspring of illegal unions, possibly gave a pretext to the supposition, that a decree passed at Athens sanctioning bigamy.</p><p>Some difficulty, however, arises on the subject of the marriage of Socrates, from the conflict of authorities. Whilst it is asserted on the one hand, that he was married to Myrto and Xanthippe at the same time; on the other hand, others assign them both as his wives, but in succession, and also differ as to the order of succession. But the silence of Plato and Xenophon respecting any other wife of Socrates butXan- thippe, and their coincidence in speaking of her only as the mother of his children, may be regarded as sufficiently decisive of the point against every subsequent authority. Indeed, the reference to Aristotle, given by Laertius, which is the chief ground for believing that Socrates was married also to Myrto, is very questionable. Plutarch doubts whether the treatise to which Laertius appeals for the fact, is the genuine work of Aristotle. From the manner, too, in which the name of Myrto appears to have been introduced in the account, nothing more may have been intended, than that Socrates found her in a state of widowhood and distress from poverty, and took care of her at his own home.<note anchored="true" n="54" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ The poverty of the family of Aristides appears from Ælian, Var. Hist. x. 15.</p></note> Aristides belonged to the same tribe and the same demus or borough, as Socrates; and a reverence for the virtues of the grandfather, may have combined with these almost domestic ties, to call forth such an act of friendliness to the disconsolate Myrto. And, if this be the case, as is probable, it would only add an interesting instance of that liberal benevolence which characterized the whole conduct of Socrates.<note anchored="true" n="55" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Plutarch in Aristides, Op∙ ii. p. 542. Plutarch adds, that Panætius bad sufficiently refuted the story of the double marriage in his observations on Socrates. The story is also questioned by Athenæus. Deipnosoph. xiii. <hi rend="italic">2.</hi></p></note></p><p>It is a confirmation of this conclusion, that all the anecdotes of the private life of Socrates, with one exception, and that evidently a fabricated instance,<note anchored="true" n="56" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Porphyry in Theodolit. Therapeut, xii. tells of altercations, even to blows, between Xanthippe and Myrto, whilst Socrates stands by and laughs, amidst their joint attacks on himself.</p></note> bring Xanthippe on the scene. On his inviting some wealthy persons to supper, it is Xanthippe who is distressed by their deficient means of hospitality, and to whom he replies, “Takecourage; if they are worthy people, they will be satisfied; if they are worthless, we shall care nothing about them.”<note anchored="true" n="57" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Diog. Laert. in vit</p></note> It is Xanthippe whom he reproves for her particularity about her dress on the occasion of some public spectacle, as more desirous of “ being seen than to see.”<note anchored="true" n="58" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,1</hi> Ælian, Var. Hist. vii. 10.</p></note> It is of her again that Alcibiades expressed his wonder how he could bear with her, when he simply, but pointedly referred him to her just claims on his affection as the mother of his children.<note anchored="true" n="59" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Diog. Laert. in Vit.</p></note> * On another occasion, his disciple, Antisthenes, is said to have asked him, with reference to Xanthippe, why he did not study to improve the disposition of his wife, whose violence of temper (he observed) was unexampled in the history of domestic life. Instead of confirming the censorious remark, he turned it, according to his usual method, to a practical illustration of his philosophy. “ If Xanthippe was hard to be controlled,” was the tenour of his answer, “ it was only a proper discipline to him for the management of men ; as those who would be masters in horsemanship, began with managing the most spirited horse, after which, every other would be tractable.”<note anchored="true" n="60" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>” Xenoph Conviv. ii.</p></note> ’ These stories, and the like, handed down or invented by the humour of the times, may be merely exaggerations of the fact of the inconvenience and dissatisfaction occasionally felt at the philosopher’s home, by his habitual neglect of his domestic concerns, and the duty of exertion consequently imposed on Xanthippe beyond Athenian women in general. She appears indeed to have tenderly loved her husband, if Plato has faithfully traced the picture of her visit to his prison, and her extreme anguish at that trying hour. And he also knew her value, if his affection may be judged of, as surely it may, by the kind and gentle considerateness of his manner in committing her to the care of his friends at parting, and his absolute reserve of his feelings on that occasion.<note anchored="true" n="61" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“Plato, Phædo p. 135.</p></note> The picture indeed is drawn by the hand of a consummate master ; and Plato, it is true, was not present on the occasion. But we must believe, that in painting a scene that must have been impressed on the mind of the disciples of the philosopher, above every other incident of his life, and of which persons then living must have retained a lively recollection, he took his outlines at least of these interesting particulars from the real state of the case.</p><p>But the allusion to these circumstances brings us prematurely to the solemn tragedy which closed his intrepid and energetic career. We have yet to contemplate him pursuing tor many a year his unwearied labour of awakening his countrymen from their dreams of knowledge and happiness to the realities of their condition in the world. Great indeed must have been the address, which could recommend the severe and wholesome truths inculcated by him, to the hearing of the vain and volatile Athenians. To none is the practical application of a principle, so condemnatory of human folly and impertinence, as the maxim, “ know thyself,” truly welcome. And yet this was the burthen of the teaching of Socrates for a series of years, among a people, whom it was far easier to please by praising to excess, than not to displease by censuring ever so slightly. They would listen, indeed, patiently to general invectives on their publicconduct, conveyed in the impassioned eloquence of their orators ; as persons will even now sympathize with general descriptions of the depravity of human nature, or of whole classes of men. But all refuse the pain of direct self-appli-<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0511.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0444"/>
cation of the truth; and Athenians, especially, regarded with invidiousness every attempt to impart to them moral instruction. Every Athenian, they thought, was capable of communicating this kind of knowledge, at least every educated Athenian, every individual of the higher order of citizens.<note anchored="true" n="62" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Xenoph. Mem. iv. 2. 24. Kαri∕tαit{ ου» &lt;rf⅛{ <hi rend="italic">r⅛ νaιf&gt;</hi> &lt;roυ <hi rend="italic">γeγgaμμ,seον ri Γ.ωt)ι aaun. ; "Eγωγt.</hi> Πόπαο» ου» oùès» <hi rend="italic">ttι</hi> raù <hi rend="italic">ygaμ,μaτος</hi> έμέληίί», η <hi rend="italic">re xai iτeχeigηβa{ ιaυr'οe ιnt×ο∙τreA 5βrις eiης ;</hi> Μα ∆ι', où <hi rend="italic">δηra</hi> ê®»|. <hi rend="italic">xai yàg δή τά.υ roùrô ye</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">ωμ∙rl&gt; eiôéeac βχολχ yàg</hi> &lt;z» άλλο <hi rend="italic">n r</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> <hi rend="italic">δeo, tiyt μ,ηtf</hi> i <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> aaυriv <hi rend="italic">sγiγ&gt;ωβxο.,</hi> x,r.λ∙</p></note> They wanted no one to teach them virtue. Hence the allusion made on so many occasions by Socrates to the question, whether virtue could be taught or not. It was, indeed, part of the profession of the Sophists to teach virtue ;<note anchored="true" n="63" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Isocratee speaks of them as <hi rend="italic">αύμ,ταβαν ageri∣e xai eυδaιμΛ.ia&gt; ∙rωλονereς,</hi> and, again, as r»î» <hi rend="italic">eυδaιμΛ&gt;ia&gt; τagaδri6traς</hi> Or. c. Soph. 3. 4.</p></note> but it was as an accomplishment or art. and not as a <hi rend="italic">discipline of life,</hi> that it entered into the system of the Sophists. Socrates uprooted this vain notion. He laboured to impress on the Athenians, that so far from their being able to teach virtue, there were none who knew what virtue was. They had yet to learn <hi rend="italic">themselves</hi> in order to that purpose. This, then, was his great difficulty. It was not the difficulty of communicating <hi rend="italic">new</hi> knowledge, but that of leading men to unlearn their presumptions and conceits, and to <hi rend="italic">feel the necessity</hi> of moral instruction.<note anchored="true" n="64" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato. Euthyphro, 3. c. <hi rend="italic">Ahηtaiοις yàg</hi> ro&lt;, ώς <hi rend="italic">iμΛi iοxeι, ον βpiiga</hi> μiλs∕, <hi rend="italic">ä. rι&gt;a δeι&gt;i&gt; οiωeraι eiMi, fj,i) μ</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> <hi rend="italic">νιrtι διδaβxaλnit rrς αΐιτοΰ βοφ!aς∙</hi> S» δ’ a» <hi rend="italic">xai</hi> άλλους <hi rend="italic">οiωeraι rnieiï rοιο∙jrους,</hi> ⅛υ,&lt;∆oυtτar <hi rend="italic">tir'</hi> ou» <hi rend="italic">φΰό&gt;ψ, ü; eù λίγιις, lire lu'</hi> άλλδ <hi rend="italic">n.</hi> Op. 1. 6.</p><p>See the same indicated at the opening of the Protagoras, where Socrates ironically throws out his opinion, that virtue cannot be taught ; founding it on the fact of the indiscriminate admission of all persons to advise on political affairs in the Assembly, whilst on particular subjects, as in a question of building, those only were consulted who were proficients in the art. <hi rend="italic">'Eτreιha. he τι</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> t</hi> <hi rend="italic">τeξi rrς</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> ι</hi> <hi rend="italic">zοktως hιοexi∣σtως hit∣ βο∙j&gt;jυβaa6aι, &lt;n&gt;μJ3&lt;Λ)λei)tι</hi> αυro⅞ <hi rend="italic">aM&gt;raμ,eκ&gt;ς τegi rο∙irω∙ iμΛiως μit rixrω., i∕ιaως hi χgλxeiς, Uxνrοrομ,&lt;∣ς, ιμ,ποgος. taνxλr</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> <hi rend="italic">gος, &lt;rij,∙jσκς,</hi> win;;, <hi rend="italic">yenaaς, aγtnης.</hi> Plato, Op. iii. p. 105 ; also Meno. Op. iv p. 375.</p></note> That he should have succeeded then in any degree in such an attempt,—that he should have been able to carry on the effort for so many years, in the very centre of Greek civilization,—that, proceeding on so broad and fundamental a principle of reformation, presenting no definite system on which a sect might fasten, no specific lure to the zeal of party, he should have drawn around him so many followers and admirers,—this is the extraordinary effect in the case of Socrates, which shows the powerful charm of his address. To persons offering any particular instruction, or professing to qualify them for the office of statesmen and orators, the Athenians were most ready to attend ; and many doubtless did attend to the conversations of Socrates with this view. They could not but admire the skill which he displayed in arguing with every one that came in his way ; not with the vulgar only, but with those who had the highest reputation for talent in reasoning, and for the extent of their knowledge. They saw his superiority to the Sophists, on the very ground on which the Sophists set up their pretensions. Many, accordingly, flocked to him as the best master in political science and dialectical skill, particularly as he was always accessible, and his instructions were perfectly gratuitous. Some, too, of a better nature than the rest, were won by the honest and manly purpose which shone through his teaching and manner on all occasions ; whatever disguise of irony, or humour, or sophistry, he might assume. There were even some of the young men, whose habits of life were reproved, and principles condemned, by his searching interrogatories, but who yet were won to attention by the charm of his instruction, and patiently heard from him truths which they would not have listened to from any other lips. For who else could stay, even for a moment, the wild impetuosity of Alcibiades, or the ferocious arrogance of Critias ? Their motives in resorting to Socrates were chiefly selfish and political. It was in pursuit of their schemes of ambition that they sought his society. Still he was able to retain them for a time at least, though they found his instructions very different from what they calculated on receiving; and so long as they continued to associate with him, they exercised a degree of self-restraint which strikingly contrasted with the habitual profligacy of their lives.<note anchored="true" n="65" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Xenoph. Mem. i. 2. 24.</p></note> Alcibiades is represented by Plato, as confessing that he, to whom the feeling of shame was scarcely known, yet felt abashed before Socrates ; that he was enchanted by him as by the flute of Marsyas, and constrained to acknowledge his own deficiences and neglect of private duty in the midst of his officious zeal for the public service. And this feeling, Alcibiades says, was general; for that there was no one, woman, or man, or boy, that could hear him, or even his words repeated by the most indifferent speaker, but felt taken by surprize, and riveted in attention.<note anchored="true" n="66" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Plato, Conviv. 215, Op. x. p. 257.</p></note></p><p>This attention, too, it should be observed, was excited by the address of Socrates, amidst much in his outward form and mien, that, by exciting ridicule, might have repelled the sentiment of respect. The comparison of him to the satyr Marsyas, with all allowance made for comic exaggeration, was true in more respects than that of the enchantment of his conversation. His countenance, strongly marked by that arch intelligence, which half-concealed, half-betrayed, the earnest deep thought, under the light veil of irony and humour, presented features resembling those of the grotesque images of the Sileni. There were the prominent dilated eyes, scarcely parted by the low ridge of the nose, the broad expanded nostrils, the wide mouth with its thick lips, such as the sculptors delighted to represent in those rude but poetic forms.<note anchored="true" n="67" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Xenoph. Conviv. v. Plato, Theætet. 143 e.</p></note> Then his manner of looking about him, his head fixed, whilst his eyes traversed the space around, glancing from side to side, excited the smile of wonder in the spectator, as to what this strange solemnity of aspect might portend. Add to this, the clumsy protuberance of his figure, so repugnant to Grecian notions of the symmetry of form, and the awkwardness of his movement<note anchored="true" n="68" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ The idea of his attempting to dance excites a laugh in the guests in Xenophon's Banquet. Xenoph. Sympos. He says there that be practised dancing for the sake of exercise.</p></note> before the eyes of a people who had a lively perception of elegance in every gesture and motion.<note anchored="true" n="69" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Xenoph. Conviv. ii. 19.</p></note> These were circumstances which, to the fastidious taste of the Greeks, would appear more important than we, in these times, can well conceive. They judged of intellectual character more from physiognomy<note anchored="true" n="70" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Aristotle introduces in his Analytics (Anal. Prior, ii. c. ult.) a notice of the subject, as affording matter of consideration to the dialectician.</p></note> (physiognomy, that is, considered as a science, of mental indications from bodily forms in general) than we are apt to do. Thus in regard to Socrates, the physiognomist, Zopyrus, who, as Cicero informs us,<note anchored="true" n="71" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Cicero, De Fato, c. 5.</p></note> professed to discern the manners and natures of men from their body and features, pronounced that Socrates was stupid and heavy, because the outline of his throat was not con-<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0512.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0445"/>
cave, but full and obtuse. Prejudices accordingly drawn from the personal appearance of Socrates may reasonably be believed to have tended to render his teaching unwelcome in its first impressions. But soon this fastidiousness would give way as he proceeded ; and those who began to listen with a smile at the uncouthness of his form, and the quaintness of his manner, would be attracted to admiration of the intelligent and kindly expression which lighted up those rude features, and would find themselves lingering in his presence in spite of themselves.</p><p>The story of Euthydemus “ the handsome," as he was called, may be taken as a specimen of such an effect. Euthydemus, proud of his personal accomplishments, and not wishing to be thought indebted to any one for his learning and eloquence, had studiously avoided the society of Socrates. Socrates, however, with his usual dexterity, contrives to excite his attention, and gradually interests him in conversation. Euthydemus shrinks back at first on his self-conceit, but at length is so won upon by the persuasive reason of the philosopher, as freely to acknowledge his own ignorance and need of instruction ; and, ever afterwards, he is found by the side of Socrates, his devoted admirer and follower.<note anchored="true" n="72" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• Xenoph. Mem. iv. 2.</p></note></p><p>Some, indeed, took offence at the plain truths which Socrates brought home to them, and no longer frequented his society.<note anchored="true" n="73" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Ibid. 40.</p></note> But these were the inferior sluggish minds, which no arts of address could rouse to a sense of their intellectual poverty. Generous, susceptible minds overcame their first reluctance, and yielded themselves fully to his guidance. The faithful attachment of many was evidenced, to the last moment of the philosoper's life. He might have commanded the use of Crito’s wealth, bad he desired it. Such, indeed, was the confidence which Crito reposed in his sincerity of purpose, and so highly did he value his instructions, that to no other would he commit the education of his sons, but made them fellow disciples with himself of his own revered master and friend. And this friendship was warmly requitted by Socrates. For it was by his counsel that Crito was saved from the malicious arts of the sycophants. These pests of Athenian society were not to be encountered by the simple testimony of a life contradicting their mercenary calumnies ; and Crito was one of those who would rather pay their money, and compromise the attack, than take the trouble of defending themselves. They were only to be foiled by turning their own weapons against themselves. By the suggestion of Socrates, accordingly, Crito enlisted in his service a clever individual of this class, Archedemus, who effectually checked the iniquities of which his patron was the object, by counter-prosecutions of the sycophants, and exposure of their conduct; acting as a watch-dog, according to Xenophon’s description, against those rapacious wolves.<note anchored="true" n="74" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>∙ Ibid. ii. 9.</p></note></p><p>The devotedness of Plato and Xenophon to their master, speaks from every line of their writings. These writings are, in fact, as much monuments of the influence of Socrates over their minds, as of their own genius. And what human teacher has ever had such glorious trophies erected of the conquests of his philosophy as the extant works of these master minds? Entirely different as they are in character,—the one flowing with the full stream of impassioned feeling, and lively elegant imagination, and the abundant treasures of literary and traditionary wisdom,—the other sensible and acute and practical, forcible by his very simplicity and the terseness of his unaffected eloquence,—they bear distinct yet conspiring evidence of the ascendancy of that mind which could impart its own tone and character to such disciples. Both of them, indeed, lead us to think that they felt his society as a kind of spell on them. For,</p><p>when Plato speaks of the charm of the discourses of the Sophists, he seems to speak in irony of them what he thought in truth of Socrates himself. So too, when Xenophon introduces Socrates describing himself as skilled in “ philters and incantations,” he is evidently presenting that idea which the conversations of Socrates impressed on his own mind. He seems almost to confess this of himself when he informs us, how Socrates triumphantly appealed to the marked devotedness of his followers, in saying, “ Why think you that this Apollodorus and Antisthenes never quit me ? Why too, that Cebes and Simmias come here from Thebes? Be assured, that this is not without many philters, and incantations, and spells.”<note anchored="true" n="75" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Ibid. iii. 2.</p></note></p><p>To the same honourable band of attached disciples might be added many other names afterwards renowned in the annals of Grecian history and literature. Isocrates, Aristippus, Antisthenes, each of whom became afterwards masters themselves, were content to follow in his train. Antisthenes especially, who, by perverting the Socratic simplicity of life into a profession of austerity, became the founder of the Cynic school, was never from his side. He would walk from the Piræus to Athens, a distance of about four miles, every day, in order to be with Socrates. And whilst Cebes and Simmias came from Thebes, Euclid, the founder of the Megaric sect, was not deterred by the bitter hostility between Athens and his own city of Megara, from seeking the society of Socrates at the hazard of his life. Even during the war, when the Megareans were excluded by a rigid decree, he continued his visits to Athens, adopting, it is said, the disguise of female attire, and so passing unobserved into the city at nightfall, and returning at daybreak.<note anchored="true" n="76" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* Aul. Gell. vi 10.</p></note> The same individual gave still more conclusive evidence of his zealous attachment to Socrates afterwards ; when he opened his house and his heart to receive, at Megara, his brother disciples, in their panic on the death of their master. So strong was the tie of reverence and affection which subsisted between the philosopher and those whom he drew around him. They formed, indeed, a sort of select family, each of whom was engaged in the pursuit of his own peculiar employments and tastes in the world, whilst all looked up to Socrates as their father and head, and ever recurred to his society as to their common home.</p><p>This domestic intercourse subsisted in the midst of a city harassed with jealousies and dissensions, and with severe afflictions of war and pestilence. Socrates remained unmoved through all these convulsions of the city, preserving a constant evenness of temper, so that Xanthippe could testify of him, that she never saw him returning at evening with a countenance changed from that with which he left home in the morning.<note anchored="true" n="77" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>« Ælian, Var. Hist. ix. 7.</p></note> ® Nor could even the merriment of which he was sometimes the object, discompose his settled gravity and good humour. On one occasion, returning from supper late in the evening, he was assaulted by a riotous party of young men, personating the Furies, in masks, and with lighted torches.<note anchored="true" n="78" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Ibid. c. 29.</p></note> ' The philosopher, however, without being irritated by the interruption, suffered them to indulge their mirth ; only he required them to pay that tribute which he exacted from every one that came in his way, to stop and answer his questions, as if he had met them in the Lyceum, or any other accustomed place of his daily conversations. Himself sound in mind and body, (for his habitual temperance saved him from the infection of the plague which so obstinately ravaged Athens,) he was enabled to give advice and assistance to all of his country in the midst of the physical and moral desolation, in which every one else seems, more or less, to have participated.</p><p>Thus were the years of a long life quietly and usefully spent ; and he had nearly reached that limit at which<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0513.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0446"/>
nature herself would have gently closed the scene of his philanthropic exertions, when the hand of human violence interposed to hasten the approaching end.</p><p>The annals of party spirit at Athens had already recorded many a deed of dark and wanton cruelty. But they were yet to be stained with the iniquity of a persecution even to death, of him, who had been the greatest benefactor and ornament, not only of Athens, but of the whole community of the Grecian name.</p><p>The banishment by ostracism had this redeeming merit, that it was an avowal in the face of Greece, of the envious and factious spirit, which drove from the state the individual whose talents or virtues too greatly distinguished him from among his fellow-citizens. The enmity to which Socrates fell a sacrifice, exhibits a deeper character of malignity ; inasmuch as it masked itself under a hypocritical zeal for religion and virtue, and thus courted public sympathy for proceedings, against which every voice in Athens and in all Greece should have indignantly protested. Ostracism, again, was content to remove the obnoxious great man from the eyes of his fellow-citizens. The attack on Socrates was satisfied with nothing short of the destruction of its victim.</p><p>It was in the midst of the tranquil, but busy course of his daily engagement, that Socrates was suddenly arrested, and without, it seems, any previous intimation of the intended attack, summoned to the portico of the king-Archon, to answer a charge of impiety.<note anchored="true" n="79" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Plato, Thætet. ad fin. Euthyphro, et alib. The king Archon was a sort of minister of state for the department of religion—tbe representative, under the democracy, of the priestly office of the king during the monarchy at Athens. See Demosthenes, c. Neær. p. 1370, ed. Reiske.</p></note></p><p>The accusation was in this form : “ Socrates is guilty of the crime of not acknowledging the gods whom the state acknowledges, but introducing other new divinities : he is guilty also of the crime of corrupting the young.” The penalty proposed was death. It has been commonly supposed that the charge was laid before the court of Areopagus. But it would appear rather, from the course of the trial, to have been before one of the popular courts, and probably, from the great number of dicasts or jurors who voted on the cause, before the principal court, the Heliæa.</p><p>The circumstances connected with the accusation remain, after the utmost inquiry now possible, involved in considerable mystery. We are told that Melitus was the accuser, and that he was supported in the prosecution by Anytus and Lycon. These three individuals are also said to have represented distinct classes of persons interested in the proceedings ; Melitus, who was himself a poet, appearing in behalf of the offended poets ; Anytus, a wealthy tradesman and demagogue, resenting the affronts of his brother-tradesmen ; Lycon, an orator, or politician by profession, standing up as the assertor of the pretensions of his factious order. But these particulars, though they may account to us in a great measure for the success of the prosecution, do not exhibit the secret agency by which it was effected. The accusers themselves were men of no note or importance in the state. Melitus was a young man ; a vain and weak person, it seems, of whom nothing more is known than that the accusation was made in his name. Nor of Anytus and Lycon have we anything to mark the importance, beyond the fact, that the former was included, together with Alcibiades and Thrasybulus, among the persons exiled by the Thirty, and the notice taken of him by Plato, where he represents him the inexorable foe of every thing in the shape of a philosopher, and as parting from a conversation with Socrates in anger.<note anchored="true" n="80" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Xen. Hell. ii. 8. 42, 44.—Plato, Meno.</p></note> ’ Merely personal offence, however, could not have given sufficient pretext or weight to so grave an accusation. Nor can we suppose that it was even the combined interest of the three classes represented by the three accusers—the poets, the tradesmen, and the orators—which carried the condemnation of so respected a person. The ground of the attack must lie deeper ; and the men whose names appear so prominently in this fatal conspiracy against the life of the venerable old philosopher, could only have been the puppets moved by some secret and more commanding force. The trial would seem to have been only a solemn pageant, exhibited before the public, as a prelude and justification of a deed of murder already resolved on by its real though invisible perpetrators. Whilst the charges themselves, as set forth by the nominal accusers, were but feebly sustained, it is evident that no defence, however just and able, could have availed to avert the sentence of condemnation. The body of jurors before whom the cause was heard, appear to have been disposed to acquit the accused, if we may judge from the number of votes which were given in his favour ; and yet the majority were overruled. This in itself would lead us to think that some secret influence had been exercised, to obviate the chance of failure of the ordinary ostensible means of judicial assault. And so Socrates himself appears to have felt ; if Plato and Xenophon have faithfully reported the substance of his reply to the accusation in their Apologies. His defence, as there represented, is that of one who retires, on his own consciousness of right, from a bootless conflict with adversaries who are not to be appeased by argument and persuasion. It does not set forth the strength of his cause as against an opponent, but simply asserts the truth and merit of the course of life which he had been pursuing.<note anchored="true" n="81" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ See the same exemplified in what Socrates is made to reply to Callicles in the Gorgias of Plato, p. 162, <hi rend="italic">nβ&lt;Zrm μirreι xal lγω &lt;&gt;Tιa in τaioς</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript"> ι</hi> <hi rend="italic">raQoιμι ά. ιΐβιλΰύ. ι∕ς iιxaffrηξ∣oι, x.τ.λ,</hi></p></note> The sentence accordingly excites no surprize in him. He yields himself up as to the sweeping of a tempest, with which it is vain to parley. Would we then explore the circumstances of the trial and condemnation of Socrates, we must obtain a deeper insight into the moving power of Grecian politics, —the spirit of the heathen religion, and the mode of its action on the conduct of states and individuals. This appears to be the proper solution of the case of Socrates. The circumstances of the case evidently point to this. And though, from the want of information, we cannot very distinctly trace the working of the religion of the times in the particular instance before us, we may, from a closer consideration of the facts, not unreasonably suspect its active operation and instrumentality.</p><p>Speculators have sometimes spoken of the mild and tolerant spirit of paganism. The observation, however, is superficial and untrue. The facility with which the polytheistic worshipper transferred his offerings and prayers to every new idol, has been mistaken for a readiness to admit any variation from the established worship, or any freedom o. opinion respecting divine things, without offence. The contrary is the fact. The heathen, resting his religion on ancient tradition<note anchored="true" n="82" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Demosthenes, in bis Oration against Neæra, p. 1370, speaks of a column erected in the temple at Limnæ, r» <hi rend="italic">rf άξχαΜτάτφ, ιsgω nü ∆u&gt;.umυ xai aγιuraru,</hi> <hi rend="subscript"> nn</hi> d standing in his time, which stated, among other things, <hi rend="italic">ira ×aπc rà mirgia ¾0r∣τaι rà ltφfra</hi> fcfi ⅛∏e rîji T6λ4aιf, <hi rend="italic">×ai rà κιμιβμί.α γιγfηrou nui Θ10Ϊ; ιύβι&amp;ως, xal μηhi&gt; ×araλιιr∣rou, μηhi xnnen&gt;μηraι</hi>: and he sums up the account with sft⅞rr, <hi rend="italic">ύς βtμm xai aγιa,</hi> xα∕ <hi rend="italic">t⅛χuιa rà viμ&lt;μa iβr∣t.</hi></p></note> * and the authority of the priests, and not on any intrinsic evidences of its truth, could not but feel a jealousy of any departure from what he had thus received,<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0514.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0447"/>
or any attempt to bring the subject into discussion. It was not only the primitive Christians that were stigmatized by heathens as atheists, because they renounced the divinities of the heathen creed, but the same reproach was long before cast upon those among the heathens themselves, who, with however pious disposition, ventured to speculate on religion. A traditionary religion will tolerate any laxity of thought or conduct which professedly admits its authority, whilst it peremptorily puts down every thing which impugns the principle of absolute deference to its authority. Thus we shall find, that, where that principle is carried to the utmost, there co-exists with it a scarcely concealed infidelity, and an unrestrained licentiousness of conduct ; and, at the same time, also an extreme sensitiveness in regard to deviation from the orthodox profession and language. We have unhappily seen this in those Christian countries, where the true faith, the principle of devout submission to the word of God, has been transformed and perverted into a doctrine of implicit deference to the authority of the ministers themselves of that word. There,—as, for example, in Spain and Italy,—where the authority of the church is bowed to most submissively, practical infidelity and immorality shew their front with impunity, whilst the expression of opinion or argument on questions of theology is discouraged and silenced, if no longer now, as once, crushed at its outbreak by the dark terrors of an Inquisition. The same fact was intensely exemplified in heathen Athens. At no place was piety, as piety was understood by heathens, more in honour. No state boasted such a tradition of sacred associations as Athens. In none were there so many festivals and solemnities of religious observance, as in Athens.<note anchored="true" n="83" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Arutoph. Nub. 298. ou &lt;J⅜3αcς <hi rend="italic">dtfηr&lt;w itgω&gt;, oa</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">μuβroδixoς δ6μo{ b nλsraii aγlaii ataδtixsυτa∣, c,υm&gt;ιalς</hi> n iso7{ <hi rend="italic">δωgημara, ta6ι i'</hi> u∙ψeotpe⅞ <hi rend="italic">xal αγάλματα, tiιβτiφatti τι eiω&gt; ΰυβίαι 6aλiaι</hi> rs <hi rend="italic">τawoiarrcuς b ägatf, κ.r.λ∙</hi></p><p>Also Thucyd, ii. 38; and De Repub. Athen, attributed to Xenophon.</p></note> In none did the priests of religion hold such sway. Witness their power over Alcibiades, at the moment of his political triumph, and amidst the caresses and admiration of his fellow-citizens, when he felt himself obliged to relinquish his command in Sicily, and desert his country, rather than encounter at home the threatened prosecution for his profanation of sacred things. Witness their power again in the instance of the same Alcibiades, at his restoration to the command of the army, when, to conciliate their favour, he delays the urgent expedition, and keeps the soldiers under arms along the road by which the sacred procession passed from Athens to Eleusis. Witness further, the frequent prosecutions at Athens on charges of impiety of which we read, and of which we have monuments in extant orations. But, amidst this strictness of external profession, in no place was there a more entire license as to practical irreligion. Their festivals abounded with rude and obscene mirth. Their drama, whilst it inculcated in direct precept the belief and worship of the gods, indulged in the most profane ribaldry and ludicrous representation of sacred things. Yet were these follies and excesses tolerated, because under them a regard was still maintained to the authority which upheld the religion, as in the “ mysteries ” and “ moralities ” enacted with the connivance of the papal power in modern times ; and the people at large were satisfied with a religious system, which was exhibited to them as so good-humoured and humane. They were tolerated, indeed, but not without the like injury to the religious feelings, as in the parallel</p><p>cases, where a corrupted secular Christianity has ventured on the like palliations of its despotism. For all the while the people were losing their hold of the popular religion. Those who thought at all on the subject, either rejected it altogether, or accounted it a mere matter of opinion and external ordinance ; whilst those, on the other hand, who were content to receive every thing traditionary as divine on the mere principle of deference to the priests, readily engrafted every new superstition on the received religion. Thus, whilst infidelity and superstition grew up at Athens, and flourished together, and often perhaps in the same mind, the connexion between religion and morality was altogether lost sight of and dissolved. Men began to regard themselves as devout, and friends of the gods, whilst they were committing deeds of violence and lust, and blindly and wickedly endeavoured to support the cause of religion by forcible suppression of the truth, and persecution of those who subjected their tenets or their rites to the test of inquiry. Thus, whilst Aristophanes was amusing the people, not of Athens only, but from all parts of Greece, at the public festivals, with ludicrous representations of the popular theology, and loosening more and more any existing associations of reverence towards the objects of their worship, severe prosecutions were carried on from time to time against all who in any way made religion a matter of debate, or seriously brought it into question with the people. The same persons can take part in the vulgar low jest, and shew their real contempt of religion by their carelessness about oaths and the practical duties of religion, and yet join zealously in the prosecution of offenders against established notions of religion. It is the same habit of mind in both cases ; a habit of looking at religion as a general rule of orthodox profession,—as a rule binding on a community, and a test of its soundness of doctrine,—rather than as a personal concern, and a trial of the spirit of a man. “ He has brought Gentiles into the temple, he has abolished circumcision, he has profaned our religion,” was the outcry against St. Paul ; and yet these same persons thus clamorous against the apostle, were minding earthly things all the while, sticklers for externals, yet idolaters in their personal religion, as men of covetousness, and slaves to the appetites of the body.</p><p>At Athens, accordingly, though there was no freedom of religious opinion, the religion might be employed to excite festive mirth, and gτatify the levity and licentiousness of a dissolute yet intellectual populace, amidst the charms of poetry and music and the solemn graceful dance. For then the associations of deference to the mysterious agency which held together the traditions of the popular creed were not violently broken asunder. There still remained in the minds of the people an awe at the indefinite mystic truth, hidden under the embroidered veil held before their eyes. They knew that the splendid drama of religion, which at once gratified their refined intellectual taste and their sensibility, was not the whole of their religion. They had also the Eleusinian mysteries ; rites of religion performed in secrecy, and fenced round with the terror of death to him that should divulge them ; delegated to a few, the initiated only, and incommunicable to the vulgar ; of which the popular rites were but the rude symbols.<note anchored="true" n="84" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>* J30crat. Panepyr. p. 54. <hi rend="italic">'hi o'γr</hi> oEw’ <hi rend="italic">άλλοΐζ</hi> η ro⅝ <hi rend="italic">μιμυr∣μboιi a×t&gt;ικn . . . xai</hi> τή» rsλtn)r, r; <hi rend="italic">oι μsriχr</hi> <hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> <hi rend="italic">tτt{ τ∣ξi τt rijf τou βiov τtλtυτης, xal rtü βυμτa&gt;τe{ aiω&gt;oς,</hi> ⅛∂∕ouς <hi rend="italic">τaf ιλπ!δa{ iχβuβn.</hi></p></note> The popular wor-<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0515.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0448"/>
ship might wear the form of caricature, the grotesque, the farcical, and even the profane, as being merely the pantomime in which some recondite interior religion was dimly and wildly shadowed. The people laughed at what they saw and heard at their festivals. But amidst their laugh there was evidently a feeling of awe, which subdued the luxury of their mirth ; a consciousness that, whilst they sportively shook the chain of their superstition, its iron entered into their soul. We see, on the other hand, Aspasia, the favourite of Pericles, at the time of the greatest popularity of that most popular leader, summoned before the courts, to answer a charge of impiety, and scarcely defended by the eloquence and the tears of Pericles himself, from the inexorable power, whose vengeance she had provoked by her philosophical speculations. Protagoras, admired as he was and courted at Athens for his talents in his profession of a Sophist, was expelled from the city and borders of Attica by the Athenians, and his books were collected by proclamation and burnt in their agora, for his avowed scepticism as to the existence of the gods.<note anchored="true" n="85" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Diog. Laer. ix. c. 8. Cic. De Nat. Deor. i. 23. See the story of the daughter of Neæra, as told by Demosthenes, in his oration against Neæra, p. 1369. She had been married under the pretence of being an Athenian citizen, to an Athenian who served the office of the king-archon. As the wife of this officer of the state, she was admittcd to the rites of religion, and solemnly inducted into the mystic temple of Bacchus at Limns. But it was unlawful for any but a true-born citizen to enter into the temple, or to witness the rites ; and her husband consequently was tried before the court of Areopagus for the impiety, and only escaped on the plea of his ignorance of the fact, and on the condition of his dismissing her from his house.</p></note> Æschylus, whose very poetry is instinctive with religion, was accused before the Areopagus of divulging the mysteries in one of his tragedies.<note anchored="true" n="86" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>‘ Ælian, Var. Hist. v. 19.</p></note> The philosopher Anaxagoras, like Galileo under his papal inquisitors, suffered imprisonment at the hands of Athenian persecutors, for having asserted the material nature of the heavenly bodies, and only escaped death by the intervention of Pericles, and by exile from his adopted home. The extent again, to which prosecutions for offences against the popular religion could be carried at Athens, is shewn in the number of persons who were imprisoned on suspicion of being implicated in the impieties charged on Alcibiades, and the execution of so many, on that occasion of panic, on the unsupported evidence of secret informers. Lastly, not many years before the accusation of Socrates, Diagoras the Melian, and Theodorus of Cyrene, were branded with the epithets of atheists ; and the former was forced to fly from Athens on a charge of profanation of the rites, with the price of a talent set on his head for any one who should kill him. And long after the time of Socrates, the same spirit subsisted to drive Aristotle from the Lyceum, and later still, to intimidate the speculations of Epicurus. So strictly was the <hi rend="italic">authority</hi> of the established worship guarded by a jealous and watchful inquisitorial power, in a state which boasted of its perfect liberty of speech, its <hi rend="italic">παρρησiα,</hi> above all others.</p><p>In fact, there was no liberty of speech on this subject in Greece. Every thing relating to religion was to be received as handed down from former ages ; as the wisdom of an immemorial antiquity, home along on the lips of the priest and the prophet, or impressed on mystic rituals, the hereditary trust of sacred families, or symbolized in the pomp and pageant of festivals and games, in the graceful majesty of temples, and the solemn shadows of sacred groves. The inward devotion of such a religion naturally took the form of silence, and reserve, and awe. It was concentrated in the simple dread of profanation. The more superstitious indeed a people is, the more necessary is it that the rites of their religion should be strictly shut up from all inquiry, and a feeling of reserve should be inculcated as essential to the religious character. It is the indefiniteness of superstition that holds together the system. Let any one part of the vaguely-floating system be touched too palpably, and the whole crumbles. Thus it has been found, that superstition and infidelity have always gone hand in hand. Diagoras was made an atheist from being at first superstitious. The Athenian people, in like manner, from their superstitious character, were peculiarly exposed to a reaction of impiety. And it was but a wise policy, therefore, that the religion of Athens should be jealously guarded with an awe forbidding all inquiry into its truth.</p><p>The colloquial and lively spirit of the Athenians mitigated the intensity of this feeling in the minds of the people at large ; and the managers of the system were fain to relieve it, by blending recreation, and mirth, and interesting spectacles, with its public celebration. Grecian superstition accordingly, whilst it bore the essential marks of its oriental origin, in the submissiveness exacted of its votaries, and its mystic reserve, assumed also the mask of cheerful expression characteristic of the genius of the people. Still we see that submissiveness and that reserve strongly marked in the stern denial of the right, not only of private judgment on questions of religion, but even of bringing such questions at all into discussion.</p><p>Now, though, as we have already observed, we cannot distinctly trace the steps by which this spiritual despotism was brought to bear on Socrates, we cannot doubt that his was a case which must have attracted its notice. During more than forty years, Socrates had been seen at Athens, going about among all classes of the people, exciting among them a spirit of moral inquiry, urging on them the importance and the duty of self-knowledge, of taking no opinion on mere hearsay, or indolent and self-satisfied trust, but of bringing every thing to the test of discussion and learning, of acquainting themselves, as their first step to knowledge, with the depth and extent of their ignorance. Observers saw in this extraordinary teacher, one of their own citizens, educated in their own institutions, familiar with the habits of Athenian life, ever at home among themselves, recommending himself alike to the young and the old, by the honest though quaint dignity of his manner, and the interest and charm of his conversation. He was not, like Anaxagoras, or Protagoras, or Prodicus, a stranger sojourning among them ; a philosopher or rhetorician by profession, or one pursuing philosophy as a trade and a source of subsistence, waiting to be resorted to and courted by the affluent and noble, and reserving himself for occasions of display or profit ; but he was found, an Athenian among Athenians, in the market place, in the streets, in the work-shops, at the tables of the wealthy, himself seeking out persons to instruct, asking questions of all around him, and engaging them, even in spite of themselves, in conversation with him.<note anchored="true" n="87" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Plato, Euthyphro. 3 d. <hi rend="italic">"Eγω δ's ροβοϋμαι, μη M f&gt;ιλavδgu&gt;rias δοxω aυrο'.</hi> ô, <hi rend="italic">ri mg</hi> sχω fxxιχι⅞u{κω(<hi rend="italic">m.ri àvdçi λiγtm,</hi> où 'xéror, <hi rend="italic">âvfu μισύοΰ,</hi> αλλά <hi rend="italic">xai</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">tjoλ√Λ⅞</hi> ar <hi rend="italic">ήδιως lîrri μου ίίίλοι άχούιιν.</hi> Op. t. i. p. 6. Xenoph. Mem. i. 2. ’Αλλά rivβi <hi rend="italic">rοι βl Mχ,βiaι, if&gt;η, διηsu, ω Σύχςαπ;, riιι fxυrian</hi> xαι <hi rend="italic">ran nxr6van xai ran χaλx'εan, xai γag olμaι</hi> (Critias is speaking) <hi rend="italic">avroi∣ς ηδr xararεrξ!φ6aι διal)oυλλoυμinυ( wri mυ.</hi> P. 21.</p></note> In other teachers, philosophy had spoken, according to the observation already made, as from an oracular shrine, to those only who came to inquire of it as votaries and disciples. With Socrates, philosophy walked abroad, insinuating itself into the scenes and business of daily life, and drawing forth the secret treasures of men’s minds with its own hands. According to that homely but apt illustration of his mode of teaching, which he was so fond of employing, from midwifery,<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0516.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0449"/>
his method freely offered its services in assisting at the birth of the thought with which the pregnant mind was labouring. He busied himself, he used to say, with the officiousness of his maternal art, in exploring the genuineness of the fruit of the intellectual womb, which his dexterous questions had brought to light.<note anchored="true" n="88" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See especially Plato's Theætetus in illustration of this.</p></note> Such a person then could not but fix on himself the eyes of every attentive observer of the state of society in Athens. Such teaching evidently could not but have a very considerable influence on public opinion. Particularly when he was seen to be acceptable to men of all parties in the state, to the leaders of the aristocratic faction as well as the humblest citizen, it could not but be inferred that his influence was not a transitory one, dependent on the predominance of any party, but that it would reach to the fundamental constitution of the society at large of the city, and be a leaven of fermentation to the whole mass. What, then, it would naturally be asked, must be the effect of such a teacher on existing opinions in religion ? He taught, indeed, that men should acquiesce in what was established in religion ; that they should inquire no further here than what simply was the law of the state. He treated, too, the popular imagery of religion with respect. For he would often clothe his instructions in the language of the legends and traditions of their mythology. Nor did he attempt to explain them away, though he waived all discussion of them. He was seen, too, on all stated occasions, sacrificing at the altars of the gods, and joining in the rites.<note anchored="true" n="89" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> Plato, Eιιthyphr. <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> pp. 11-13, and Phædrus.</p></note> But, it would be asked, if the citizens were taught to examine into received opinions generally, would they abstain from carrying this principle into the subject of religion ? Would they continue still blindly and submissively to follow the voice of authority ? Would they not rather, so far as they were disciples of Socrates, begin to speculate on divine things, abandoning that reverence which they had hitherto maintained for the objects of public worship, disputing and discussing without reserve, and exposing to the vulgar gaze what had been all along venerated in mystic silence, and under the veil of symbol ? The mercurial temperament of the Athenian was just the soil in which the seeds now scattered by the hand of Socrates might be exacted to vegetate. The excessive prosperity, too, of Athens, during the fifty years immediately following the Persian war, and then its condition of struggle against internal faction and tl&gt;e confederate arms of Peloponnesus, were circumstances calculated to foster the profane irreligious spirit in a light-hearted people. Then, instances were not wanting of young men, tne intimates of Socrates, and whose minds had been especially cultivated by conversation with him, who proved in the end traitors to the religion, as well as to the civil liberties of their country. Critias,<note anchored="true" n="90" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Critias is placed by Sextus Empiricus among the atheists. He is said to have resolved all religion into the enactments of legislators providing against the secret commission of crimes, by inculcating the all-seeing power of the gods. He gives also several lines from a poem of Critias to this effect. Adv. Math. lib. viii. p. 318.</p></note> afterwards one of the thirty tyrants, and Alcibiades, at once the pride and the pest of his fellow-citizens, whom they loved and hated, and banished and longed for by turns, were striking evidences to the superficial observation of the evil apprehended from the teaching of Socrates. For here were young men of genius, susceptible by nature of the fullest influence of the lessons of the philosopher. And yet these had failed under his hands. What, therefore, might not be expected of minds of inferior order ? How would not the religion and the institutions of the city fall into profane neglect and contempt, should the Socratic spirit of inquiry be</p><p>imbibed by the next generation of citizens ? The observation, indeed, was only a very superficial one, which would infer from such instances the evil of the teaching which these individuals misapplied. Still it is plain, that such cases were pointed at with invidious reference to Socrates and philosophy in general. We find the orator Æschines attributing the death of Socrates to the circumstance of his having educated Critias ;<note anchored="true" n="91" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Æscbin. con. Timarch.</p></note> * not that he must be supposed to have believed this to have been the whole account of the trial and condemnation of Socrates ; but as an orator, he states for the purposes of his argument, what he conceives would be readily believed as part of the account of that event. Plato also studiously addresses himself to the defence of philosophy, from objection on this ground, with evident allusion to Alcibiades and the like cases ; arguing that the same individuals who were most susceptible of the good of philosophy, were also such as would be the most apt to abuse it. And probably he had the same design, and refers to the degenerate sons of Pericles himself, as an instance in point to those who cherished the memory of that great man, and of the times in which he flourished, to show that the philosopher was not to be held responsible for the extravagances and vices of the disciple.<note anchored="true" n="92" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>• See the Protagoras and Repub. vi—Xenophon adverts in like manner to the charge of corruption as supported by the instances of Critias and Alcibiades. Memor, i. 2. See also the conversation which Xenophon reports between Socrates and Hippias. Isocrates, in <hi rend="italic">Busir.</hi> p. 222, c. with the like feeling, <hi rend="italic">denies</hi> that Alcibiade« was educated by Socrates; meaning, it seems, that Alcibiades was too short a time with Socrates to be benefited by the instructions of the philosopher</p></note></p><p>The exhibition of the comedy of “ The Clouds,” appears to have been designed to bring before the people the supposed evil tendency of the teaching of Socrates, as exemplified in such distinguished instances. It was produced in the year <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> 423, when the philosopher had attained his forty-seventh year, and was at the height of his reputation throughout Greece, and about twenty-three years before his death. There we have Socrates introduced by name under broad caricature, as the representative of the class of sophists, and a consummate master of the arrogant pretension, and sordid cunning, and impiety of the class. The clouds are his only divinities. A profligate spendthrift youth, and a dotard father, are his dupes. The inquisitive method which Socrates practised, is also held up to ridicule and contempt, by identifying it with the frivolous questionings of the grammarians, and dialecticians, and rhetoricians of the day, and with the perverse sophistry which held truth a matter of indifference, or, which amountcd to the same thing, called every man’s opinion truth, and boasted of its skill to make the worse appear the better cause. It was but too evident to Athenian spectators at least, that the Socrates of Aristophanes was not the Socrates whom they had been accustomed to see and converse with in real life. And the play accordingly failed at the first exhibition. Not all its charms of poetry, and humour, and skilful composition, could obtain for it a favourable reception. Though Aristophanes was aware that the portrait which he had drawn, was not a portrait of the individual, but of the class, there can be little doubt, that he calculated on the sympathy of the people, in giving the name of Socrates to his personification of the sophistical spirit ; and that he felt it necessary to depreciate the influence of Socrates as the commanding influence of the day, by attributing to his method all the vices of the schools of the sophists. Socrates is honoured and complimented in the very attempt to weaken the respect for his instructions, and to awaken a clamour against him. The failure of “ The Clouds,” at the first representation, and one account adds, even at the second, (for the play is said to have been retouched for the third time), has<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0517.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0450"/>
been attributed to the influence of Alcibiades. Alcibiades indeed has been supposed by some commentators to have been no less the object of attack in the play than Socrates himself, and to have been designated under the name of Phidippides, the youthful and accomplished victim of the sophist. There are certainly some traits in the character of Phidippides, which would seem to point at Alcibiades, whom perhaps the poet, bold as he was, could hardly venture to bring on the stage by name or closer description at this particular time. And we may perhaps justly allow some weight to party influence in neutralizing the effect of “ The Clouds” at its first exhibition. Still, when we observe in other instances the great power which the comic muse could wield against a political opponent, as in the attack on Cleon in “ The Knights,” we cannot but think that there was some strong countervailing feeling in the estimation of Socrates himself. If the account of Ælian be true, Socrates could join in the laugh raised against him ; for he was present in the theatre during the acting of the play, and finding that he was the object of attraction, placed himself where all could command a view of him.<note anchored="true" n="93" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Ælian, Var. Hist.</p></note> He knew, and every one in Athens knew, that he was a very different person from the sophists with whom the play identified him. They indeed were corrupters of the young; for they unsettled every established principle in the minds of the young, and gave no substitute for what they profligately swept away. They left the young to be drifted away by the tide of their passions, with no criterion of truth or of right beyond the present opinion or the present interest. But Socrates, whilst he taught the young to inquire into the truth of their opinions, lessened their presumption and self-confidence, by shewing them how apt they were to mistake mere assumptions for knowledge, and to be conceited of their ignorance. His object was truth, and accurate knowledge. He stated difficulties and objections, but not in the spirit of a sceptic, but in order to awaken curiosity, to clear away confusion of thought, and inculcate sound principles of judgment and conduct. He could well then laugh at the jest which glanced from him to its proper objects, the sophists themselves, the very persons against whom his whole teaching was directed. He felt doubtless that he had a hold on the people at large, which the sophists had not. They were for the most part known only to the great and wealthy ; those who could receive them into their houses, as they went from city to city through Greece ; who sought their society as patrons of literature, or aspirants after political distinction, and who could pay for their instructions.<note anchored="true" n="94" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>’ Plutarch well characterises the teaching of Socrates, in speaking of him, as <hi rend="italic">ashpit aτvφ!a</hi> rat aψ&lt;λria μziλ&lt;ra δ⅛ <hi rend="italic">φιλοσοφία* iζavθpvnησa&gt;τot.</hi> De Socr. Gen. p. 301.</p></note> He on the contrary was accessible to all. He would receive no money from any one. He was the frequent guest of the rich ; but he was no less the associate of the artizan and the poor. And too many must have been present in the theatre, when the Socrates of “ The Clouds” was amusing the audience by his sleight-of- hand philosophy, who would remember the real Socrates as a man of honesty, and truth, and disinterested benevolence, from whom they had received much useful counsel from time to time, and whom they had ever found affable, and at leisure to enter into their feelings and views with patience and kindness. If we compare the Socrates of the Memorabilia of Xenophon with the Socrates of “ The Clouds,” we may judge how great was the contrast to those who compared the well-known philosopher of the agora with his portrait as drawn by Aristophanes. If we can smile at the caricature of “ The Clouds,” and yet love the excellent moralist of the Memorabilia, we may also conceive how harmless the satire of Aristophanes would really be against the object of it ; whilst the jokes of the poet, true as to the personal peculiarities of the philosopher, amused a volatile and clever people. For them to have confounded Socrates with the class of sophists, would have been in them the like palpable mistake, as it would be to confound the philosopher Bacon, on account of some points of resemblance, with the alchemist and empiric of the preceding ages.</p><p>It might seem matter of reproach against Aristophanes, that, in selecting the name of Socrates to represent the sophistical spirit which had then so largely corrupted the education and the government of Athens, he pointed the shafts of the comic muse against the very person who was in truth its most successful antagonist. In such a view of the case, however, sufficient justice would not be done to the discernment of the poet. He shrewdly observed in Socrates the master genius which would ultimately cast into the shade all those busy professors of the art of education, who, under the name of sophists, or professors of all knowledge, were then attracting the notice of the world to themselves and their doctines. Socrates, in himself, Aristophanes could not but admire and recommend to the imitation of his country. He doubtless knew Socrates to be a true patriot no less than himself,—to be steadily aiming to bring back the Athenians to the purity of their institutions, from which they had so sadly degenerated, by his instructive conversations, as he was by the satirical strokes of the drama. Socrates, too, appears to have been his personal friend ; for Plato introduces them in his Banquet as meeting on terms of intimacy, about the very time of the exhibition of “ The Clouds.” But with that freedom which the state of manners, under an absolute democracy, sanctioned and encouraged, Aristophanes did not scruple to bring even the revered name of Socrates on the stage, to give the due point to his satire. He overlooked the individual, the Socrates with whom he familiarly conversed, and presented before the spectators what he saw in Socrates, the living speaking impersonation of the influence of education on the character of a people, for good or for evil. Anaxagoras, or Protagoras, or Prodicus, or any other of the well-known philosophers or sophists of the day, might have occupied the foreground in the comedy of “ The Clouds ;” had the poet sought to give merely a fugitive sketch of the sophistical spirit of his times, or to single out for ridicule some of its external superficial features. This is what Plato has done on many occasions, and especially in that most animated picture in the dialogue entitled Protagoras, where he groups together the figures of the leading sophists in such admirable relief with each other, and such happy contrast with the unpretending but dignified form of his own loved master and friend. Such a view, however, could not have answered the design of Aristophanes in his play of “ The Clouds.” His object was to seize the deep, influential characters of the system of education which was then extending itself throughout Greece, and especially as it was manifested at Athens, the great sch∞l of all Greece. Naturally, therefore, and wisely, he fixed his eye on an Athenian—and that Athenian, Socrates,—not only as the first Athenian who had appeared in the office of a philosophical instructor, but who, as an Athenian, gave to his lessons the character of Athenian civilization, and fitly exemplified the influence of philosophical education in the hands of an Athenian, and as operating on Athenians.</p><p>The poet, indeed, as addressing the eye and the ear of the ordinary observer, and not Athenians only, but strangers of the Grecian name from all parts, mingles with his colouring some playful lights borrowed from the forms of the well-known professional sophists of the day. But neither are these representations, nor the allusions which he</p></div></body></text></TEI>