<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0357.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0298-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHIRT</label>,
a loose garment, commonly of linen or cotton, worn next the body. Shirts were not worn by the Jews, <hi rend="italic">G</hi> reeks, or Romans, but their place was supplied by thin <hi rend="italic">tunicae</hi> of wool. The want of linen among the ancients made frequent washings and ablutions necessary.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SHIRVAN,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Schirvan,</hi> a province in the north of Persia, now claimed by Russia. It is the largest and most imp <hi rend="italic">o</hi> rtant division of the Southern Caucasus. It ex<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0358.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s03-0299"/>
tends along the Caspian, 200 miles from the mouth of the Cyrus, to the little river Rubas ; and forms a large triangular peninsula, the point of which stretches into the Cas- pian. From its form it varies extremely in breadth, which, at the extremity of the peninsula on the Rubas, is scarcely sixteen miles ; near Kuba it amounts to forty ; from the mouth of the Ata it is above fifty ; while in the in- terior part it amounts to 160. It has the Caspian to the east ; Daghestan to the north ; the Kur and the plains of Mogam to the south and south-west, being separated by the river Kur from the provinces of Ghilan and Azerbijan ; and the kingdom of Georgia to the north-west. The north- ern part of this province consists of a plain, which is formed by the mountains that extend toward the sea near Derbend, and which, gradually receding behind that city, approach again in a circular form near the sea at the mouth of the river Ata. Numerous streams, issuing from the mountains, greatly contribute to fertilize this plain, and, at the same time, to secure it against the access of an invading army. They branch off in various directions, and being generally mountain-streams, are uncommonly rapid, though they are shallow, with a wide channel, and a rough and sandy bed. The plain is interspersed with small woods and clumps of bushes, and the villages are surrounded with orchards, vineyards, and plantations of mulberries. The second division of Schirvan extends on one side along the coast from the Ata to the plains watered by the Kur; and on the other it is bounded by the higher range of mountains, which run in a south-east course through the province. The length of this district is about eighty miles ; but as the coast projects considerably, the breadth varies. The higher portions of the country are here the most fertile ; the part towards the sea is barren, being devoid of water ; and to the north of Baku is a desert tract of about fifty miles. The plain along the left of the Kur is about 140 miles in length, and from forty to fifty in breadth. The district is in a great degree surrounded with mountains, and, being exposed to frequent inundations, is overgrown with rushes to a considerable distance. The most elevated division of Schirvan is that which extends from the Rubas to Lesges- tan. This tract varies much in breadth, and is intersected by narrow valleys, in many of which are small lakes, which continue filled even in the greatest heat of summer. This province is abundantly watered by streams, which fall, some into the Caspian, and others into the Kur. The most considerable are the Samur, Deli, Sagaite, and Persagat. This province was annexed to Persia in the year 1500, and con- tinued subject to that empire till the decline of the Sefi dynasty, when the native princes, taking advantage of the weakness of Persia, re-established their independence. Of late, however, the Russians have obtained possession of the sea-coast, though the interior is still in the hands of the native chiefs. The principal towns are Schamachi, the ca- pital, and Baku.</p></div></body></text></TEI>