<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>iu the structure of all languages, and therefore must be common to all men who speak with understanding ” (Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">Reid,</hi>  pp. 229 and 454).</p><p>The principles which Reid insists upon as everywhere present in experience evidently correspond pretty closely to the Kantian Categoriesandthe unity of apperception. Similarly, Reid’s assertion of the essential distinction between space or extension and feeling or any succession of feelings may be compared with Kant’s doctrine in the <hi rend="italic">Aesthetic.</hi>  “ Space/’ he says, “ whether tangible or visible, is not so properly an object [Kant’s “ matter ”] as a necessary concomitant of the objects both of sight and touch.” . Like Kant, too, Reid finds in space the source of a necessity which sense, as sense, cannot give (Hamilton’s <hi rend="italic">Reid,</hi>  p. 323). In the substance of their answer to Hume, the two philosophers have therefore much in common. But Reid lacked the art to give due impressiveness to the important advance which his positions really contain. Although at times he states his principles with a wonderful degree of breadth and insight, he mars the effect by looseness of statement, and by the incorporation of irrelevant psychological matter. And, if Kant was overridden by a love of symmetry, Reid’s indifference to form and system is an even more dangerous defect. Further, Reid is inclined to state his principles dogmatically rather than as logical deductions. The transcendental deduction, or proof from the possibility of experience in general, which forms the vital centre of the Kantian scheme, is wanting in Reid; or, at all events, if the spirit of the proof is occasionally present, it is nowhere adequately developed. Nevertheless, Reid s insistence on judgment as the unit of knowledge and his sharp distinction between sensation and perception must still</p><p>be recognized as of the highest importance.</p><p>The relativism or phenomenalism which Hamilton afterwards adopted from Kant and sought to engraft upon Scottish philosophy is wholly absent from the original Scottish doctrine. .One or two passages may certainly be quoted from Reid in which he asserts that we know only properties of things and are ignorant of their essence. But the exact meaning which he attaches to such expressions is not quite clear; and they occur, moreover, only incidentally and with the air of current phrases mechanically repeated. Dugald Stewart, however, deliberately emphasizes the merely qualitative nature of our knowledge as the foundation of philosophical argument, and thus paves the way for the thoroughgoing philosophy of nescience elaborated by Hamilton. But since Hamilton’s time the most typical Scottish thinkers have repudiated his relativistic doctrine, and returned to the original</p><p>tradition of the school. For Reid’s ethical theory, see Ethics.</p><p>The complete edition of the works by Sir William Hamilton, published in two volumes with notes and supplementary dissertations by the editor (6th ed. 1863), has superseded all others. For Reid’s life see D. Stewart’s <hi rend="italic">Memoir</hi>  prefixed to Hamilton’s edition of Reid's works. See also McCosh, <hi rend="italic">Scottish Philosophers</hi>  (1875); Rait, <hi rend="italic">Universities of Aberdeen,</hi>  pp. 199-203, 223; A. C. Fraser, <hi rend="italic">Monograph</hi>  (1898); A. Bain, <hi rend="italic">Mental Science,</hi>  p. 207, p. 422 (for his theory of free will), and Appendix, pp. 29, 63, 88, 89.</p><p>(A. S. P.-P.; X.)</p><p>REID, THOMAS MAYNE (1818-1883), better known as Mayne Reid, British novelist, the son of a Presbyterian minister, was born at Ballyroney, Co. Down, Ireland, on the 4th of April 1818. His own early life was as adventurous as any boy reader of his novels could desire. He was educated for the church, but did not take orders, and when twenty years old went to America in search of excitement and fortune. He made trading excursions on the Red river, studying the ways of the red man and the white pioneer. He made acquaintance with the Missouri in the same manner, and roved through all the states of the Union. In Philadelphia, where he was engaged in journalism from 1843 to 1846, he made the acquaintance of Edgar Allan Poe. When the war with Mexico broke out in 1846 he obtained a captain’s commission, was present at the siege and capture of Vera Cruz, and led a forlorn hope at ChapuIte-pec, where he sustained such severe injuries that his life was despaired of. In one of his novels he says that he believed theoretically in the military value of untrained troops, and that he had found his theories confirmed in actual warfare. An enthusiastic republican, he offered his services to the Hungarian insurgents in 1849, raised a body of volunteers, and sailed for Europe, but arrived too late. He then settled in England, and began his career of a novelist with the publication, in 1850, of the <hi rend="italic">Rifle Rangers.</hi>  This was followed next year by the <hi rend="italic">Scalp Hunters.</hi>  He never surpassed his first productions, except perhaps in <hi rend="italic">The White Chief</hi>  (1859) and <hi rend="italic">The Quadroon </hi>(1856); but he continued to produce tales of self-reliant enterprise and exciting adventure with great fertility. Simplicity of plot and easy variety of exciting incident are among the merits that contribute to his popularity with boys. His reflections are not profound, but are frequently more sensible than might be presumed at first from his aggressive manner of expressing them. He died in London on the 22nd of October 1883.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Memoir</hi>  (1890) by his widow, Elizabeth Mayne Reid.</p><p>REID, WHITELAW (1837-    ), American journalist and</p><p>diplomatist, was bom of Scotch parentage, near Xenia, Ohio, on the 27th of October 1837. He graduated at Miami University in 1856, and spoke frequently in behalf of John C. Fremont, the Republican candidate for the presidency in that year; was superintendent of schools of South Charleston, Ohio, in 1856-58, and in 1858-59 was editor of the Xenia <hi rend="italic">News.</hi>  In i860 he became legislative correspondent at Columbus for several Ohio newspapers, including the Cincinnati <hi rend="italic">Gazette,</hi>  of which he was made city editor in 1861. He was war correspondent for the <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi>  in 1861-62, serving also as volunteer aide-de-camp (with the rank of captain) to General Thomas A. Morris (1811-1904) and General William S. Rosecrans in West Virginia. He was Washington correspondent of the <hi rend="italic">Gazette</hi>  in 1862-68, acting incidentally as clerk of the military committee of Congress (1862-63) and as librarian of the House of Representatives (1863-66). In 1868 he became a leading editorial writer for the New York <hi rend="italic">Tribune,</hi>  in the following year was made managing editor, and in 1872, upon the death of Horace Greeley, became the principal proprietor and editor-in-chief. In 1905 Reid relinquished his active editorship of the <hi rend="italic">Tribune,</hi>  but retained financial control. He declined an appointment as United States minister to Germany in 1877 and again in 1881, but served as minister to France in 1889-92, and in 1892 was the unsuccessful Republican candidate for vice-president on the ticket with Benjamin Harrison. In 1897 he was special ambassador of the United States on the occasion of Queen Victoria’s jubilee; in 1898 was a member of the commission which arranged the terms of peace between the United States and Spain; in 1902 was special ambassador of the United States at the coronation of King Edward VII., and in 1905 became ambassador to Great Britain. He was elected a life member of the New York State Board of Regents in 1878; and in 1902 he became vice-chancellor and, in 1904, chancellor of the university of the state of New York. In 1881 he married a daughter of Darius Ogden Mills (1825-1910), a prominent financier.</p><p>His publications include <hi rend="italic">After the War</hi>  (1867), in which he gives his observations during a journey through the Southern States in 1866; <hi rend="italic">Ohio in the War</hi>  (2 vols., 1868); <hi rend="italic">Some Consequences of the Last Treaty of Paris</hi>  (1899); <hi rend="italic">Our New Duties</hi>  (1899); <hi rend="italic">Later Aspects of Our New Duties</hi>  (1899); <hi rend="italic">Problems of Expansion</hi>  (1900); <hi rend="italic">The Greatest Fact in Modern History</hi>  (1906), and <hi rend="italic">How America faced its Educational Problem</hi>  (1906).</p><p>REID, SIR WILLIAM (1791-1858), Scottish administrator and man of science, was born on the 25th of April 1791 at the manse of Kinglassie, Fifeshire, and entered the Royal Engineers in 1809. He saw active service in the Peninsula under Wellington, and took part in the bombardment of Algiers in 1816. In 1835 and 1836 he again saw active service, in Spain against Don Carlos. In 1838 he published his <hi rend="italic">Attempt to develop the Law of Storms,</hi>  which obtained wide popularity. In 1839 he was appointed governor of the Bermudas, where he did much to develop the agricultural resources of the islands, and in 1846 he was transferred to Barbados. In 1850-51 he was chairman of the executive committee of the Great Exhibition; on the completion of the work he was made a K.C.B. and appointed governor of Malta. He died in London on the 31st of October 1858.</p><p>REIGATE, a market town and municipaI borough in the Reigate parliamentary division of Surrey, England, 24 m. S. by W. of London by the South-Eastern &amp; Chatham railway. Pop. (1901) 25,993. Il is situated at the head of the long valley of Holmsdale Hollow, beneath the North Downs. A very fine prospect over a great part of Surrey and Sussex, and extending to Hampshire and Kent, is obtained from the neighbouring Reigate Hill. Of the old castle, supposed to</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>