<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>liable to be seized. The French law is in force in Mauritius, and has been reproduced in substance in the Civil Codes of Quebec (arts. 2005 et seq.) and St Lucia (arts. 1888 et seq.). There are analogous provisions in the Spanish Civil Code (art. 1922). The subject of privileges and hypothecs is regulated in Belgium by a special law of the 16th Dec. 1851; and in Germany by ss. 1113 et seq. of the Civil Code. The law of British India as to rent (Transfer and Property Act 1882) and distress (cf., <hi rend="italic">e.g..</hi>  Act 15 of 1882) is similar to English law. The British dominions generally tend in the same direction. See, <hi rend="italic">e.g..</hi>  New South Wales (the consolidating Landlord and Tenant Act 1899); Newfoundland (Act 4 of 1899); Ontario (Act 1 of 1902, s. 22, giving a tenant five days for tender of rent and expenses after distress); Jamaica (Law 17 of 1900, certification of landlord’s bailiffs) ; Queensland (Act 15 of 1904).</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Authorities.—English Law: Woodfall, </hi><hi rend="italic">Landlord and Tenant </hi>(18th ed., London, 1907) ; Foa, <hi rend="italic">Landlord and Tenant</hi>  (4th ed., London, 1907); Fawcett, <hi rend="italic">Landlord and Tenant</hi>  (3rd ed., London, 1905); Gilbert on <hi rend="italic">Distress and Replevin</hi>  (London, 1823); Bullen, <hi rend="italic">Law of Distress</hi>  (2nd ed., London, 1899) ; Oldham and Foster, <hi rend="italic">Law of Distress </hi>(2nd ed., London, 1889). Scots Law: Hunter on <hi rend="italic">Landlord and Tenant</hi>  (4th ed., Edin., 1876) ; Erskine’s <hi rend="italic">Principles</hi>  (20th ed., by Rankine, Edin., 1903); Rankine’s <hi rend="italic">Law</hi>  of <hi rend="italic">Landownership in Scotland</hi>  (3rd ed., Edin., 1891); Rankine’s <hi rend="italic">Law of Leases in Scotland </hi>(2nd ed., Edin., 1893). American Law: McAdam, <hi rend="italic">Law of Landlord and Tenant</hi>  (New York, 1900); Bouvier’s <hi rend="italic">Law Dictionary</hi>  (ed. G. Rawle) (London and Boston, 1897), tit. “ Distress ” in “ Ruling Cases”; <hi rend="italic">Landlord and Tenant</hi>  (American Notes) (London and Boston, 1894-1901).    (A. W. R.)</p><p>RENTON, a manufacturing town of Dumbartonshire, Scotland. Pop. (1901) 5067. It is situated on the Leven, 2 m. N.N.W. of Dumbarton by the North British and Caledonian railways. The leading industry is Turkey red dyeing, and calico-printing and bleaching are also carried on.. A parish church stands on the site of Dalquhurn House, the birthplace of Tobias Smollett the novelist, to whose memory a. Tuscan column was erected in 1774, the inscription for which was revised by Dr Johnson when he visited Bonhill in that year with Boswell. The town was founded in Î782 by Mrs Smollett—previously Mrs Telfer— of BonhiIl (sister of Tobias Smollett), who resumed her maiden name when she succeeded to the Smollett estates; it was named after Cecilia Renton, daughter of John Renton of Blackadder, who had married Mrs Smollett’s son, Alexander Telfer.</p><p>RENWICK, JAMES (1662-1688), Scottish covenanting leader, was bom at Moniaive in Dumfriesshire on the 15th of February 1662, being the son of a weaver, Andrew Renwick. Educated at Edinburgh University, he joined the section of the Covenanters known as the Cameronians about 1681 and soon became prominent among them. Afterwards he studied theology at the university of Groningen and was ordained a minister in 1683. Returning to Scotland “ full of zeal and breathing forth threats of organized assassination,” says Mr Andrew Lang, he became one'of the field-preachers and was declared a rebel by the privy council. He was largely responsible for the “ apologetical declaration ” of 1684 by which he and his followers disowned the authority of Charles II.; the privy council replied by ordering every one to abjure this declaration on pain of death. Unlike some of his associates, Renwick refused to join the rising under the earl of Argyll in 1685; in 1687, when the declarations of indulgence allowed some liberty of worship to the Presbyterians, he and his followers, often called Renwickites, continued to hold meetings in the fields, which were still illegal. A reward was offered for his capture, and early in 1688 he was seized in Edinburgh. Tried and found guilty of disowning the royal authority and other offences, he refused to apply for a pardon and was hanged on the 17th of February 1688. Renwick was the last of the convenanting martyrs.</p><p>See R. Wodrow, <hi rend="italic">History of the Sufferings of the Church of Scotland,</hi>  vol. iv. (Glasgow, 1838); and A. Smellie, <hi rend="italic">Men of the Covenant </hi>(1904); also Renwick’s life by Alexander Shields in the <hi rend="italic">Biographia Presbyteriana</hi>  (1827).</p><p>REP, <hi rend="smallcaps">Repp,</hi>  or <hi rend="smallcaps">Reps,</hi>  a cloth made of silk, wool or cotton. The name is said to have been adapted from the French <hi rend="italic">reps, </hi>a word of unknown origin; it has also been suggested that it is a corruption of “ rib.” It is woven in fine cords or ribs across the width of the piece. In silk it is used for dresses, and to some extent for ecclesiastical vestments, &amp;c. In wool and cotton it is used for various upholstery purposes.</p><p>REPAIRS (from Lat. <hi rend="italic">reparare,</hi>  to make ready again), acts necessary to restore things to a sound state after damage; the question of repairs is important in the relations between landlord and tenant. (See the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Flat; Landlord and Tenant.)</hi></p><p>REPEAL (O.F. <hi rend="italic">rapel,</hi>  modern <hi rend="italic">rappel,</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">rapeler, rappeler, </hi>revoke, <hi rend="italic">re</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">appeler,</hi>  appeal), the abrogation, revocation or annulling of a law (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Abrogation</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Statute).</hi>  The word is particularly used in English history of the movement led by Daniel O’Connell <hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi>  for the repeal of the act of Union between Great Britain and Ireland in 1830 and 1841-46, which in its later development became known as the Nationalist or Home Rule movement (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Ireland, </hi><hi rend="italic">History).</hi></p><p>REPIN, ILJA JEFIMOVICH (1844-    ), Russian painter,</p><p>was born in 1844 at Tschuguev in the department of Charkov, the son of parents in straitened circumstances. He learned the rudiments of art under a painter of saints named Bunakov, for three years gaining his living at this humble craft. In 1863 he obtained a studentship at the Academy of Fine Arts of St Petersburg, where he remained for six years, winning the gold medal and a travelling scholarship which enabled him to visit France and Italy. He returned to Russia after a short absence, and devoted himself exclusively to subjects having strong nationaI characteristics. In 1894 he became professor of historical painting at the St Petersburg Academy. Repin’s paintings are powerfully drawn, with not a little imagination and with strong dramatic force and characterization. A brilliant colourist, and a port rail-painter of the first rank, he also became known as a sculptor and etcher of ability. His chief pictures are “ Procession in the Government of Kiev,” “ Home-coming,” “ The Arrest,” “ Ivan the Terrible’s murder of his Son,” and, best known of all, “ The Reply of the Cossacks to Sultan Mahmoud IV.” The portraits of the Baroness V. I. Ülskül, of Anton Rubinstein and of Count Leo Tolstoy are among his best achievements in this class. The Tretiakov gallery at Moscow contains a very large collection of his work.</p><p>See “ Professor Repin,’’ by Prince Bojidar Karageorgevich, in the <hi rend="italic">Magazine of Art,</hi>  xxiii. p. 783 (1899) ; “ Russian Art,” a paper by E. Brayley Hodgetts in the <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Anglo-Russian Literary-Society</hi>  (5th of May 1896); “ Ilja Jefimovieh Repin,” by Julius Norden, in Velhagen and Klasing’s <hi rend="italic">Monatshefte,</hi>  xx. p. r (!905); also R. Muther, <hi rend="italic">History of Modern Painting</hi>  (ed. 1907), iv. 272.    (E. F. S.)</p><p>REPINGTON (or <hi rend="smallcaps">Repyngdon),</hi>  PHILIP (d. 1424), English bishop and cardinal, was educated at Oxford and became an Augustinian canon at Leicester before 1382. A man of some learning, he came to the front as a defender of the doctrines taught by John Wycliffe; for this he Was suspended and afterwards excommunicated, but in a short time he was pardoned and restored by Archbishop William Courtenay, and he appears to have completely abandoned his unorthodox opinions. In 1394 he was made abbot of St Mary de Pré at Leicester, and after the accession of Henry IV. to the English throne in 1399 he became chaplain and confessor to this king, being described as “ clericus Specialissimus domini régis Henrici. ” In 1404 he was chosen bishop of Lincoln, and in 1408 Pope Gregory XII. made him a cardinal. He resigned his bishopric in 1419. Some of Repington’s sermons are in manuscript at Oxford and at Cambridge.</p><p>REPLEVIN, an Anglo-French law term (derived from <hi rend="italic">replevin </hi>to replevy; see <hi rend="smallcaps">Pledge</hi>  for further etymology) signifying the recovery by a person of goods unlawfully taken out of his possession by means of a special form of legal process; this falls into two divisions—(1) the “ replevy,” the steps which the owner takes to secure the physical possession of the goods, by giving security for prosecuting the action and for the return of the goods if the case goes against him, and (2) the “ action of replevin ” itself. The jurisdiction in the first case is in the County Court; in the second case the Supreme Court has also jurisdiction in certain circumstances. The proceedings are now regulated by the County Courts Act 1888. At common Iaw, the ordinary action for the recovery of goods wrongfully taken would be one of detinue; but no means of immediate recovery</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>