<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>said Motowori (18th century), “ the Mikado is the child of the Sun-goddess.” (5) The
                dead hero (historical or mythic) signalizes his power by gracious saving acts;
                and Heracles, Asclepius, Amphiaraus, and others pass into the ranks of the gods,
                which are thus continually recruited from below.</p>
            <p>HI. A third great group rises out of the sentiments and affections of man, or the
                moral energies which he secs working in human life. (1) The Vedic <hi rend="italic"
                    >Craddhä,</hi> “ faith,” the Greek <hi rend="italic">Metameleia,</hi>
                    “repentance,”@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> the Latin<hi rend="italic">Spes,</hi> and a
                band of other figures, represent the dispositions of the heart; Nemesis and Nike and
                Concordia and their kin belong to a somewhat different sphere, the divine powers
                avenging, conquering, harmonizing the counterparts of the “ departmental ” gods in
                the field of moral agencies. (2) Over these theological speculation erects a few
                lofty and impressive forms; sometimes below the highest, like Vohu Mano, “ the Good
                Mind ” of Ahura Mazda; or the Bodhisattva Avalokitccvara, who vowed not to enter
                into final peace till every creature had received the saving truth; sometimes
                supreme, like Brahma or Prajapati (“ lord of creatures ”) in the early Brahmanic
                theology; or Adi Buddha, or the Zervan Akarana, “ boundless time,” of a kind of
                Persian gnosticism; or the Geôs <hi rend="italic">νψιστος</hi> whose worship appears
                among other syncretistic cults of the Roman empire.</p>
            <p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Order of Nature.—</hi>Polytheism is here on the way to
                monotheism, and this tendency receives significant support from the recognition of
                an order in nature which is the ground and framework of social ethics. Not only does
                a sky-god like Varuna, or a sun-god like the Babylonian Shamash, survey all human
                things, and take cognizance of the evil-doer, but the daily course of the world is
                itself the expression of an intellectual and moral power. In the Chinese combination
                of Heaven and Earth as the parents and nourishers of all things, the energy
                and action lie with Tien, Earth being docile and receptive. Tien is intelligent and
                all-observing, and its “ sincerity ” or steadfastness, displayed in the courses of
                the sun and moon and the succession of the seasons, becomes the basis of right
                human conduct, personal and social. The “ way ” of Heaven, the “ course ” of Heaven,
                the “ lessons ” of Heaven, the law or “ decree ” <hi rend="italic">(ming)</hi> of
                Heaven, are constantly cited as the pattern for the emperor and his subjects. This
                conception is even reflected in human nature: “ Heaven in giving birth to
                the multitude of the people, to every faculty and relationship affixed its laws ”
                    <hi rend="italic">(Shi King,</hi> III. iii. 6; cf. IV. iii. <hi rend="italic"
                    >2,</hi> tr. Legge), and the “ Grand Unity ” forms the source of all moral order
                    <hi rend="italic">(Li Ki,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Sacred Books of lhe
                    East,</hi> xxvii. p. 387). Indian thought presented this Order in a
                semi-personal form. The great elemental gods imposed their laws <hi rend="italic"
                    >(dhaman, dharman, vrata)</hi> on the visible objects of nature, the flow of
                rivers, the march of the heavenly bodies across the sky. But the idea of Law
                was generalized in the figure of <hi rend="italic">Rita</hi> (what is “ fitted ” or
                “ fixed or the “ course ” or “ path ” which is traversed), whose Zend equivalent <hi
                    rend="italic">asha</hi> shows that the conception had been reached before the
                separation of the Eastern Aryans produced the migrations into India and Iran.@@<hi
                    rend="sup">2</hi> In the<hi rend="italic">Rig Veda</hi> the gods (even those of
                storm) are again and again described as “born from the Rita,” or born in it,
                according to it, or of it. Even Heaven and Earth rejoice in the womb or lap of the
                Rita. In virtue of the mystic identity between the cosmic phenomena and sacrifice,
                Rita may be also viewed as the principle of the cultus; and from that sphere it
                passes into conduct and acquires the meaning of morality and is equated with what
                is “ true.” The fundamental idea remains the same in the Zend Asha, its philological
                counterpart, but it is applied with a difference. Its form is more personal, for
                Asha is one of the six Holy Immortals round the throne of Ahura Mazda
                (Auramazda). In the primeval conflict between the powers of good and evil, the
                Bounteous Spirit chose Asha, the Righteous Order which</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>knit the world together and maintained the stars.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> The
                immediacy of the relation between Ahura and Asha is implied in the statements that
                Ahura created Asha and that he dwells in the paths which proceed from Asha; and when
                he created the inspired word of Reason, Asha consented with him in his deed. In its
                ritual form Asha becomes the principle of sacrifice, and hence of holiness, first
                ritual and then moral. Like Rita, it rises into an object of worship, and in its
                most exalted aspect <hi rend="italic">(Asha vahisia,</hi> the “ best ” Asha, most
                excellent righteousness) it is identified with Ahura himself, being fourth among
                his sacred names <hi rend="italic">(Orrnazd Yasht,</hi> § 7; <hi rend="italic"
                    >S.B.E.</hi> xxiii. p. 25). Egyptian speculation, in like manner, impersonated
                the conceptions of physical and moral order as two sides of a fundamental unity in
                the goddess Maât. Derived from the verb <hi rend="italic">mä, </hi>“ to stretch
                out,” her name denoted the ideas of right and rule, and covered the notions of
                order, law, justice and truth, which remained steadfast and unalterable.
                Mythologically she was the daughter (or the eye) of the sun-god Re; but she
                bçcame Lady of Heaven and Queen of Earth, and even Lady of the land of the West, the
                mysterious habitation of the dead. Each of the great gods was said to be lord or
                master of Maât; but from another point of view she “ knew no lord or master,”
                and the particular quality of deity was expressed in the phrase <hi rend="italic"
                    >anx em maät,</hi> “ living by Maât,” which was applied to the gods of the
                physical world, the sun and moon, the days and hours, as well as to the divine king.
                She was solemnly offered by the sovereign to his god; and the deity replied by
                laying her within the heart of his worshipper “to manifest her everlastingly before
                the gods.” So in the famous scene of the weighing of the soul, which first appears
                pictorially under the New Empire, she introduces the deceased before the forty-two
                assessors of the heavenly judge, Osiris, and presides over the scale in which
                his actions and life are weighed. From the zenith to the realm of the departed she
                is the “queen of all gods and goddesses.”@@<hi rend="sup">4 </hi>The Hellenic
                polytheism of Homer and Hesiod is already at work upon similar ideas, and a whole
                group of mythic personifications slowly rises into view representing different
                phases of the same fundamental conception. Themis (root 0e=Sanskr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >dha,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">dhäman)</hi> appears in Homer as the
                embodiment of what is fit or right;@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> she convenes or dismisses
                assemblies, she even keeps order at the banquet of the gods. Next, Hesiod supplies a
                significant biography. She is the daughter of Ouranos and Gaia; and after Metis she
                becomes the bride of Zeus.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Pindar describes her as born in a
                golden car from the primeval Oceanus, source of all things, to the sacred height of
                Olympus to be the consort of Zeus the saviour; and she bears the same august
                epithet, as the symbol of social justice and the refuge for the oppressed.@@<hi
                    rend="sup">7</hi> Law was thus the spouse of the sovereign of the sky, but
                Aeschylus identified her with the Earth (worshipped at Athens as Ge-Themis), not
                only the kindly Mother, but the goddess who bound herself by fixed rules or laws of
                nature and life.@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi> For the cultus of the earth as the source of
                fertility was associated with the maintenance of the family, with the operations of
                agricuiture and the social order of marriage. So Themis became the mother of the
                seasons; the regular sequence of blossom and fruit was her work; and Good Order,
                Justice and Peace were her offspring.@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi> By such conceptions the
                Hellenic polytheism was moralized; the physical character of the greater gods fell
                into the background, and the sculptor’s art came to the aid of the poet by
                completely enduing them with personality.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>    Worshipped at Argos. Usener,<hi rend="italic"
                    >Gotternarnen,</hi> p. 366.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>    Cf. Max Müller,<hi rend="italic">Lectures on the Origin
                    and Growth of Religion </hi>(Hibbert Lect., 1878), v., and the Vedic treatises
                of Ludwig, Ber-gaigne and Wallis.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi><hi rend="italic"> Yasna<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> xxx. 5;
                    <hi rend="italic">Sacred Books of the East,</hi> xxxi. p. 30; cf. pp. 44, 5b
                248.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>    Cf. Renouf,<hi rend="italic">Hibbert Lectures,</hi> p.
                119; Brugsch, <hi rend="italic">Rel. und Mythol., </hi>p. 477; Wiedemann, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ann. du Musée Guirnet<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> x. p. 561;
                    Budge, <hi rend="italic">Gods of Egypt,</hi> i. p. 416.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>    Cf. AMs UijLttares<hi rend="sub">1</hi> Od. xvi. 403 ;
                cf. Apollo,<hi rend="italic">Horn. Hymn.</hi> 394.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic"/>@@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi><hi rend="italic"> Theog.</hi> 135,
                901.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic"/>@@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi><hi rend="italic">    Fr.</hi> 6, 7 ; <hi
                    rend="italic">Ol.</hi> viii. 29.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi>    Farnell, however, supposes that Ge acquired the
                cult-appellative through her prophetic character<hi rend="italic">(Cults of the
                    Greek States,</hi> iii. p. 12). The union of Zeus and Themis is, then, a later
                equivalent of the marriage of Zeus and Earth (ibid. p. 14).</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi>    Paus. v. 17; Hes.<hi rend="italic">Theog.</hi> 901 ;
                Pindar, <hi rend="italic">Ol.</hi> xiii. 6; ix. 26.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
