<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>age, world-wide distribution and with exceptional facilities of distribution.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Australian Region.—</hi>Of crocodiles only <hi rend="italic">C. johnstoni</hi>  in N.</p><p>Australia and Queensland; <hi rend="italic">C. porosus</hi>  on the N. coast, and occurring on various Pacific islands, as far E. as thc Fiji Islands. Tortoises are represented only by the pleurodirous CheIydidae, <hi rend="italic">e.g. Chelodina;</hi>  they are absent in Tasmania and on the Pacific islands. New Guinea possesses the aquatic <hi rend="italic">Carellochelys,</hi>  sole type of a family.</p><p>The bulk of the Lacertilian fauna is composed of skinks, geckos, agamoids and. Varanidae, .with the addition of a small family which is peculiar to the region, the Pygopodidae. A peculiar type, <hi rend="italic">Dibamus,</hi>  inhabits the borderlands, namely, New Guinea, the Moluccas, Celebes and the Nicobar Islands; and, finally, a single iguanoid, <hi rend="italic">Brachylophus,</hi>  is common in the Fiji Islands; how it came there, or how it survived its severance from the American stock, is a mystery. The skinks are in this region more highly developed and more specialized than in any other part of the world ; they exceed in numbers thc geckos, which generally accompany the skinks in their range over the smaller islands of the Pacific; in these islands members of these two families represent the whole of the Lacertilian fauna. The Australian agamoids are chiefly peculiar and partly much 'differentiated forms <hi rend="italic">(e.g. Moloch</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Chlamy-dosaurus),</hi>  but some have distinct affinities to, or are even identical with, Indian genera. The Varanidae are also closely allied to Indian species.</p><p>Of snakes, amounting to about one hundred species only, we note about one dozen Typhlopidae, and of Pythoninae simply <hi rend="italic">Python, </hi>and the Boine <hi rend="italic">Enygrus</hi>  on the islands from New Guinea to Fiji. There arc but surprisingly few innocuous colubrine snakes, scarcely a dozen, and all belonging to Indian genera. The bulk of the snakes belong to the poisonous Elapinae, all of genera peculiar to the region, <hi rend="italic">e.g. Acanthophis, Pseudechis, Notechis.</hi>  Such a preponderance of poisonous over harmless snakes is found nowhere else in the world. Tasmania is tenanted by poisonous snakes only. In Australia we meet, therefore, with ‘the interesting fact that, whilst it is closély allied to S. America, but totally distinct from India by its Chelonians, its lizards and colubrine snakes connect it with this latter region. With regard to the other Ophidians, they have their nearest allies partly in India, partly in Madagascar, partly in S. America; and the character of the Australian snake fauna consists chiefly in its peculiar composition, differing thereby more from the other equatorial regions than those do among themselves. Wallace’s line marks the boundary between India and Australia only as far as Chelonians are concerned, but it is quite effaced by the distribution of lizards and snakes. Thus in New Guinea lizards of the Indian region are mixed with Pygopodidae, and an island as far E. as TimorIaut is inhabited by snakes, some of which are peculiarly Indian, whilst the others are as decidedly Australian. The islands N. of New Guinea and of Melanesia are not yet occupied by the Ophidian type, and only species of <hi rend="italic">Enygrus </hi>have penetrated eastwards as far as the Low Archipelago, whilst the Fiji Islands and the larger islands of Melanesia have sufficiently long been raised above the level of the sea to develop quite peculiar genera of snakes.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Indian Region.</hi>—Of Crocodilia <hi rend="italic">C. palustris,</hi>  the <hi rend="sup">41</hi>  mugger ” or marsh crocodile, and<hi rend="italic">C. porosus·, Gavialis gangeticus; Tomistorna schlegeli</hi>  in Borneo, Malacca and Sumatra. Of tortoises <hi rend="italic">Platy-sternum megacephalum,</hi>  type of a family from Siam to S. China; many Trionychidae and Testudinidae, mostly aquatic; whilst the terrestrial <hi rend="italic">Testudo</hi>  is very scantily represented. One species which is common in the Indian peninsula <hi rend="italic">(T. stellate)</hi>  is so similar to an African species as.to have been considered identical with it; the Burmese tortoise is also closely allied to it, and the two others •extend far into western-central Asia. Thus this type is to be considered rather an immigrant from its. present headquarters, Africa, than a survivor of the Indian Tertiary fauna, which com-</p><p>{jrised the most extraordinary forms of land tortoises. Wallace’s ine marks the E. boundary of <hi rend="italic">Trionyx;</hi>  species of this genus are common in Java and Borneo, and occur likewise in the Philippine Islands, but are not found in Celebes, Amboyna or any of the other islands E. of Wallace’s line. Agamidae are exceedingly numerous, and are represented chiefly by arboreal forms, <hi rend="italic">e.g. Draco (q-v.)</hi>  is peculiar to the region, <hi rend="italic">Ceratophora</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Lyriocephalus</hi>  exclusively Ceylonese; terrestrial forms, like <hi rend="italic">Agama</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Uromastix,</hi>  inhabit the hot and sandy plains in the N.W., and pass uninterruptedly into the fauna of western-central Asia and Africa. The Geckonidae, Scincidae and Varanidae are likewise well represented, but without giving a characteristic feature to the region by special modification of the leading forms except the gecko <hi rend="italic">Ptychozoon homalocephalum </hi>in Malaya. The Lacertidae are represented by one characteristic genus, <hi rend="italic">Tachydromus—Ophiops</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Cabrite</hi>  being more developed beyond the limits assigned to this region. Finally, the Euble-pharidae and Anguidae, families whose living representatives are probably the scattered remains of once widely and more generally distributed types, have retained respectively two species in W. India, and one in the Khasi Hills, whilst the presence of a single species of chameleon in S. India and Ceylon reminds us again of the relations of this part of the fauna to that of Africa.</p><p>The Indian region excels all the other tropical countries in thc great variety of genuine types and numbers of species of snakes. Boulenger@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>recognizes 267 species,<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>  about one-nfth of the total number of snakes known, fndia is thc only country in thc world possessing vipérine, crotaline and elapine poisonous snakes (their proportion to harmless snakes being about 1 : 10), <hi rend="italic">e.g. Vipera russetli,</hi>  the “ daboia ” (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Viper); </hi><hi rend="italic">Lachesis, e.g. gramincus,</hi>  an arboreal pit viper; <hi rend="italic">Nafa tripudians,</hi>  the cobra; <hi rend="italic">Bungarus coeruleus,</hi>  the ‘ krait "; <hi rend="italic">Callophis;</hi>  and Hydrophinae along the coasts of the whole region. Several sub-families and families arc peculiar to thc region: the Uropeltidae with <hi rend="italic">Rhinophis</hi>  in southern India, and <hi rend="italic">Uropeltis</hi>  confined to Ceylon; Hysiidae in Ceylon and Malay Islands, elsewhere only in S. America; the Opisthoglyphous <hi rend="italic">Etechis-todon Westermanni</hi>  of Bengal; the Homalopsmae, with many species from Bengal to N. Australia; further the Amblycenhalidae; <hi rend="italic">Xenopeltis unicolor,</hi>  sole type of a family; and the Acrocnordinae, a sub-family of aglyphous Colubridae, ranging from the Khasi Hills to New Guinea. Of other Colubridac, wc notice numerous <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus, Coronella</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Zamenis,</hi>  the latter one of the most characteristic types of the warmer parts of Eurasia. Tree-snakes, <hi rend="italic">e.g. Dipsas</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Dendrophis,</hi>  are common. Of other families we note a great number of Typhlopidae, of which <hi rend="italic">T. braminus</hi>  occurs even on Christmas Island. Lastly various species of <hi rend="italic">Python,</hi>  but no Glauconiidae, the only family not represented in thc Indian region, which claims the UropeItidae, Xenopeltidae and AmbIyccphaTidae as peculiar to itself.</p><p>Gflpthcr remarks that to this region Japan has to be referred. This is clearly shown by the presence of species <hi rend="italic">QiOphites<hi rend="sub">t</hi>Callophis, Trimeresurus</hi>  s. <hi rend="italic">Lachesis, Tachydromus,</hi>  characteristically Indian forms, with which species of <hi rend="italic">Clemmys, Trionyx, Gecko, Halys, </hi>and some Colubrines closely allied to Chinese and Central Asiatic species are associated. <hi rend="italic">Halys</hi>  is a central Asiatic pit viper. The few reptiles inhabiting the northern part of Japan are probably of palaearctic origin.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The African Continent.</hi>—Of crocodiles, <hi rend="italic">C. vulgaris</hi>  in the E.,</p><p><hi rend="italic">C. Cataphroctus</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Osteolaemus tetraspis</hi>  in the W. There are many Chelonians, especially small land tortoises of <hi rend="italic">Testudo,</hi>  and with <hi rend="italic">Cinyxis</hi>  which is peculiar to this continent; the freshwater <hi rend="italic">Clemrnys </hi>only in the N.W. corner; several genera of the pleurodirous Pclo-medusidae, <hi rend="italic">Pelomedusa galeate,</hi>  which is equatorial and southern, with an outlying occurrence in the Sinai peninsula, and <hi rend="italic">Sternothaerus </hi>with several tropical and southern species; of Trionychidae the tropical <hi rend="italic">Cycloderma</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Cyclanorbis</hi>  peculiar to the country, and the large <hi rend="italic">Trionyx triunguis</hi>  which ranges from the Senegal and Congo into the Nile system with its big lakes, but occurring also in Syria.</p><p>Of Lacertilia the geckos and skinks, and thc typically old world families of Lacertidae and Varanidae are well represented; also Amphisbaenidae; Gerrhosauridae and Zonuridae, peculiar to Africa and Madagascar; a few Eublepharinae and a few of the so-called Anelytrqpidae in West Africa. But the most important feature of this Lacertilian fauna is the almost universal distribution of chameleons in numerous and some highly specialized forms, <hi rend="italic">Chameleon</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Rhampholeon.</hi>  We note the entire absence of Iguanidae and of Anguidae, the latter represented by <hi rend="italic">Ophisaurus</hi>  only in the north-western corner. ,</p><p>Of snakes only one sub-family is peculiar, the Rhachiodontinae with the sole species <hi rend="italic">Dasypeltis scabra,</hi>  the egg-swallowing snake. Many Typhlopidae and Glauconiidae, but no Ilysiidae; large pythons, <hi rend="italic">Eryx</hi>  in the N., and a boa, <hi rend="italic">Pelophilus fordi</hi>  in the W. of Africa. Of poisonous snakes there is an abundance, notably the Viperinae have their centre in this continent ; besides <hi rend="italic">Echis,</hi>  which is also Indian, there are peculiar to the continent <hi rend="italic">Bitis,</hi>  the puff-adder, <hi rend="italic">Causus, Atractespis, Cerastes,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Atheris</hi>  which is an arboreal genus, allIof which see under <hi rend="smallcaps">Viper.</hi>  The pit vipers are entirely absent. Elapinae are numerous, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  hooded cobras like <hi rend="italic">Naja haje</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Sepedon</hi>  the “ ringhals.’’ Many OpisthogIyphous tree snakes and a considerable number of innocuous colubrines, <hi rend="italic">e.g. Lycodon, Psammophis</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Coronella</hi>  or closely allied genera all also in India, but <hi rend="italic">Coluber-Yfoe</hi>  forms and <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus</hi>  are very scantily represented, chiefly in the N.</p><p>On the whole the reptilian fauna of Africa is not rich, considering thc huge size of the continent, but this may be accounted for by thc great expanse of desert in the N. half and of veld in thc S. Lastly, the enormous central forests are still scarcely explored.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Madagascar</hi>  and certain other islands have a fauna which is as remarkable for its deficiencies as it is for its present forms. The following well-defined groups are absent: Trionychidae and Chely-didae ; Agamidae, Lacertidae, Anguidae, Amphisbaenidae, Varanidae and Eublepharinae; all the Viperidae and Elapinae, so that this large island enjoys perfect absence of poisonous snakes, not counting the practically harmless Opisthoglyphous tree snakes; there are further no pythons and no ilysias.</p><p>The actual fauna consists of: <hi rend="italic">Crocodilus vulgaris,</hi>  which is said <hi rend="underline">to be extremely abundant; of Chelonians, </hi>Pelomedusa galeate<hi rend="underline">  and</hi></p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>The same authority enumerates 536 species of reptiles for' British India,<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>  about one-sixth of all the recent species of reptiles <hi rend="italic">(Fauna of British India,</hi>  edit. W. T. Blanford, London, 1890).</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>