<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the free importation of corn from abroad, and the abolition of the mischievous monopoly of the Iceland trade.</p><p>But the financial distress of Denmark, the jealousy of the duchies, the ruinous political complications of the Napoleonic period, and, above all, the Crown Prince Frederick’s growing jealousy of his official advisers, which led him to rule, or rather misrule, for years without the co-operation of his Council of State—all these calamities were at last too much even for Reventlow. On 7th December 1813 he received his dismissal and retired to his estates, where, after working cheerfully among his peasantry to the last, he died on the nth of October 1827.</p><p>See Adolph Frederik Bcrgsoe, <hi rend="italic">Grev. C. D. F. Reventlows Virksomhed</hi>  (Copenhagen, 1837); Louis Theodor Alfred Bobe, <hi rend="italic">Efterl. Papirer fra den Reventlowske Farniliekreds</hi>  (Copenhagen, 1895-97)·</p><p>REVENUE (O. Fr. <hi rend="italic">revenu,</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">revenir,</hi>  to return), income, return, or profit; more particularly the receipts from all sources of a government or state. The revenue of a state is largely made up of taxation, and the general principles of taxes are discussed in <hi rend="smallcaps">Taxation</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Finance.</hi>  In some countries the public or state domain may contribute substantially to the revenue, as do the crown forests in Russia, while in other countries important contributions are made from the state railways, post and telegraph services, &amp;c. For the historical development of the English revenue see <hi rend="smallcaps">English Finance, </hi>and for other countries see the sections on finance in the articles dealing with the various countries. In the United Kingdom the term inland revenue is used to denote that part of thc revenue which is derived from death duties, stamps and other taxes, such as income tax, land tax, inhabited house duty, &amp;c. The Board of Inland Revenue is a special department of the English civil service, with headquarters at Somerset House. The Board consists of a chairman, deputy chairman, and two commissioners, with joint secretaries, assistant secretaries and a staff of officials. The other important department engaged in the collection of the English revenue is the Board of . Customs and Excise. The excise department was formerly a branch of the inland revenue, but was amalgamated with the customs department on the ist of April 1909. The Board of Customs and Excise is constituted as is the Board of Inland Revenue.</p><p>In the United States the greater proportion of the national revenue ($547,086,992 out of $663,217,677 in 1909) is derived from customs and internal revenue. The internal revenue consists for the most part of receipts from taxes on spirits, tobaccos and fermented liquors. In 1909 the amount derived from customs revenue was $300,977,438, and internal revenue, $246,109,554.</p><p>REVERE, PAUL (1735-1818), American engraver and patriot, was born in Boston, Massachusetts, on the ist of January 1735. He had a meagre schooling, and in his father’s shop learned the trade of a gold- and silversmith. In 1756 he was second lieutenant of artillery in the expedition against Crown Point, and for several months was stationed at Fort Edward, in New York.*- He became a proficient copper engraver, and.engraved several anti-British caricatures in the years before the War of Independence. He was one of the Boston grand jurors who refused to serve in 1774 because parliament had made the justices independent of the people for their salaries; was a leader in the Boston Tea Party; was one of the thirty North End mechanics who patrolled the streets to watch the movements of the British troops and Tories; and in December 1774 was sent to Portsmouth, New Hampshire, to urge the seizure of military stores there, and induced the colonists to attack and capture Fort William and Mary—one of the first acts of military force in the war. His midnight ride from Charlestown to Lexington on the i8th-i9th of April 1775, to give warning of thc approach of British troops from Boston, is Revere’s most famous exploit; it is commemorated by Longfellow, who, however, has " paid little attention to exactness of fact ” (Justin Winsor). In 1775 Revere was sent by the Massachusetts provincial congress to Philadelphia to study the working of the only powder mill in the colonies, and although he was allowed only to pass through the building, obtained sufficient information to enable him to set up a powder mill at Canton. He w as commissioned a major of infantry in the Massachusetts militia in April 1776; was promoted to the rank of lieutenant-colonel of artillery in November; was stationed at Castle William, defending Boston harbour, and finally received command of this fort. He served in an expedition to Rhode Island in 1778, and in the following year participated in the unsuccessful Penobscot expedition. After his return he was accused of having disobeyed the orders of the commanding officer, was tried by court-martial, and was acquitted. After the war he engaged in the manufacture of gold and silver ware, and became a pioneer in the production in America of copper plating and copper spikes for ships. In 1795, as grandmaster of the Masonic fraternity, he laid the cornerstone of the new State House in Boston, and in this year also founded the Massachusetts Charitable Mechanic Association, becoming its first president. He died in Boston on the 10th of May 1818.</p><p>See Charles F. Gettemy, <hi rend="italic">The True Story of Paul Revere</hi>  (Boston, Ι9θ5)·</p><p>REVERE, a township and a coast resort of Suffolk county, Massachusetts, U.S.A., immediately N.E. of Boston on Massachusetts Bay. Pop. (1910, U.S. census), 18,219. Area, 4-56 sq. m. The township is served by the Boston &amp; Maine and the Boston, Revere Beach &amp; Lynn railways, and by several electric railways connecting (with Boston, ‘Chelsea, Lynn, Malden, and Medford. Revere Beach, a crescent-shaped beach of white sand extending from the promontory of Winthrop on the S. to the Point of Pines on the N., is a popular bathing resort, and has been called the Coney Island of Boston. The township has a Carnegie library and a handsome town hall. The first settlement here w<hi rend="sup">f</hi>as made about 1626, and, under the name of Rumney Marsh, it was a part of Boston until 1739, when it became a part of the new township of Chelsea. The northern part of Chelsea was organized as the township of North Chelsea in 1846; part of it was separated as Winthrop in 1852; and in 1871 the name North Chelsea was changed to Revere, in honour of Paul Revere.</p><p>REVEREND (Lat. <hi rend="italic">reverendus,</hi>  gerundive of <hi rend="italic">revereri,</hi>  to revere, pay respect to), a term of respect or courtesy, now especially used as the ordinary prefix of address to the names of ministers of religion of all denominations. The uses of Med. Lat. <hi rend="italic">reverendus</hi>  do not confine the term to those in orders; Du Cange <hi rend="italic">(Gloss, s.v.)</hi>  defines it as <hi rend="italic">titulus honorarius, etiam mulieribus potioris dignitatie Concessiis,</hi>  and in the 15th century in English it is found as a general term of respectful address. The usual prefix of address of a parson was “ sir,” representing Lat. <hi rend="italic">dominus</hi>  (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir),</hi>  or “ master.” It has been habitually used of the parochial clergy of the Church of England since the end of the 17th century. It is not, however, a title of honour or dignity, and no denomination has any exclusive right to use it. A faculty was ordered to be issued for the erection of a tombstone, the inscription on which contained the name of a Wesleyan minister prefixed by “ reverend ”; this the incumbent had refused <hi rend="italic">(Keat</hi>  v. <hi rend="italic">Smith,</hi>  1876, 1 P.D. 73). In the Church of England deans are addressed as “ very reverend,” bishops as “ right reverend,” archbishops as “ most reverend.” The Moderator of the Church of Scotland is also styled “ right reverend.”</p><p>REVERIE, a condition of mental abstraction, a fit of musing, a “brown study” (“brown” in the sense of “gloomy,” and not to be referred to Germ. <hi rend="italic">Braune,</hi>  brow). The word appears in the 14th or 15th centuries in its original meaning in Old French, of joy, delight, also wildness, anger. The French <hi rend="italic">rever, </hi>later <hi rend="italic">resver,</hi>  modem <hi rend="italic">réver,</hi>  to dream, meant originally to wander in speech or thought, and is derived from the Lat. <hi rend="italic">rabiare, </hi>cf. “ rabies,” “ rage ” and “ rave.” The French <hi rend="italic">rêverie (resverie) </hi>was adopted again in the 17th and 18th centuries as meaning a state of dreaminess; thus Locke <hi rend="italic">(Essay on the Human Understanding,</hi>  1695, ii. xix.) says: “ When ideas float in our minds</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>