<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>product is not a single cell, but a fructification termed <hi rend="italic">cystocarp </hi>(Red Algae), or <hi rend="italic">ascocarp</hi>  (Ascomycetes) or <hi rend="italic">aecidium</hi>  (Uredincae), containing many spores <hi rend="italic">(carpospores).</hi></p><p>As a consequence of the diversity in the sexual organs and cells, in the details of the sexual act, and in the product of it, several modes of the sexual process have to be distinguished, which may be conveniently summarized as follows:—</p><p>I.    <hi rend="italic">Isogamy:</hi>  the sexual process consists in the fusion of either two similar sexual cells <hi rend="italic">(isogametes),</hi>  or two similar sexual organs <hi rend="italic">(gametangia) : </hi>it is termed conjugation, and the product is a .zygoj/we. Itsvarietiesare:—-</p><p><hi rend="italic">(a)</hi>     Gametes ciliated and free-swimming <hi rend="italic">(planogametes),</hi>  set</p><p>free into the water where they meet and fuse: lower Green Algae (Protococcaceae, Pandorineae, most Siphonaceae and Confervaceae) ; some Brown Algae (Phaeo-sporeae) :</p><p><hi rend="italic">(b)</hi>     Gametangia fuse in pairs, and a gamete is differentiated in</p><p>each: the gametes of each pair fuse, but are not set free and are not ciliated (the Conjugate Green Algae): or, no gametes are differentiated, the undifferentiated contents of the gametangia fusing (Mucorinae among the Fungi).</p><p>II.    <hi rend="italic">Oogamy:</hi>  male and female organs distinct: thc protoplasm •of the female organ is differentiated into one or (rarely) more oospheres which usually remain enclosed in the female organ : the contents of the male organ are usually differentiated into one or more male cells: the process is fertilization, the product is an <hi rend="italic">oospore.</hi></p><p>(A)    The sexual organs are unicellular (or coenocytic as in certain Siphonaceous Green Algae and in the Oomycetous Fungi); the female organ is an <hi rend="italic">oogonium.</hi></p><p>(a) The male organ is an <hi rend="italic">antheridium</hi>  giving rise to one or more free-swimming ciliated Spermatozoids:</p><p>(1)    The oogonium contains a single oosphere which is fertilized</p><p><hi rend="italic">in situ:</hi>  higher Green Algae <hi rend="italic">(Volvox, Vaucheria, Oedogonium, Coleochaete,</hi>  Characeae) ; some Brown Algae <hi rend="italic">(Tiiopteris)*,</hi>  among the Fungi, <hi rend="italic">Monoblepharis, </hi>the only fungus known to have Spermatozoids:</p><p><hi rend="italic">(2)</hi>     The oogonium produces a single oosphere which is extruded</p><p>and is IertilizedJn the water: <hi rend="italic">Dictyota</hi>  and some Fucaceae (Brown Algae) f</p><p>(3)    The oogonium contains several oospheres which are fertilized</p><p><hi rend="italic">in situ : SPhaeroplea</hi>  (Siphonaceous Green Alga) :</p><p>(4)    The oogonium produces more than one oosphere (2-8) which</p><p>are extruded and are fertilized in the water: certain Brown Algae <hi rend="italic">(Pelvetia, Ascophyllum, Fucus) :</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">(ß)</hi>  The male organ is a <hi rend="italic">pollinodium</hi>  which applies itself closely to the oogonium : the amorphous male cell is not ciliated and is not set free :</p><p>(1)    The oogonium contains a single oosphere which is fertilized</p><p><hi rend="italic">in situ :</hi>  Peronosporaceae (Oomycetes) :</p><p>(2)    The oogonium contains several oospheres; Saprolegnia-</p><p>ceae: but it is debated whether or not fertilization actually takes place.</p><p>(B)    The male and female organs are (as a rule) multicellular; the male organ is an <hi rend="italic">antheridium,</hi>  the female an <hi rend="italic">archegonium:</hi>  the archegonium always contains a single oosphere which is fertilized <hi rend="italic">in situ.</hi></p><p>(a) Thc male cell is a free-swimming ciliated Spermatozoid: the antheridium produces more than one (usually very many) spermatozoïde, each of which is developed in a single cell: all Bryophyta (mosses, &amp;c.) and Pterido-phyta (ferns, &amp;c.) : thc only Phanerogams in which Spcrmatozoids have been observed are the gymno-Spermous species <hi rend="italic">Ginkgo biloba, Cycas revoluta, Zamia integrifolia.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">(ß)</hi>  The male cell is amorphous and passes directly from the pollen-tube into the oosphere <hi rend="italic">(siphonogamy)</hi>  : all Phanerogams except the species just mentioned.</p><p>It must be explained that in the angiospermous Phanerogams, thc male and female organs are so'reduced that each is represented by only a single cell : the male, by the <hi rend="italic">generative celt,</hi>  formed in the pollen-grain, which usually divides into two male cells : the female, by the oosphere. The gradual reduction can be traced through the Gymnosperms.</p><p>Attention may here be drawn to the fact (see Angiosperms) that, in several cases, the second male cell has been seen to enter the cmbryo-sac from the pollen-tube, and its nucleus to fuse with thc definitive nucleus (endosperm-nucleus) or with one of the polar nuclei.. The significance of this remarkable observation is discussed in the section on the <hi rend="italic">Physiology of Reproduction.</hi></p><p>III.    <hi rend="italic">Carpogamy:</hi>  the sexual organs are (as a rule) differentiated into male and female: the protoplasm of the unicellular or multicellular female organ (archicarp, procarp) is never differentiated into an oosphere: in many cases definite male cells, <hi rend="italic">spermatia, </hi>are produced and are set free, but they are not ciliated, and frequently have a cell-wall: the process is <hi rend="italic">fertilization:</hi>  the product is a fructification derived essentially from the female organ containing several (sometimes very many) spores <hi rend="italic">(carpospores) : </hi>characteristic of the Red Algae and of the Ascomycetous Fungi.</p><p>(A)    There are definite male cells <hi rend="italic">(spermatia) :</hi></p><p>(a) Thc female organ is a <hi rend="italic">procarp,</hi>  consisting of an elongated, closed, receptive filament, the <hi rend="italic">trichogyne,</hi>  and of a basal</p><p>•    fertile portion, the <hi rend="italic">Carpogonium:</hi>  on fertilization the</p><p>latter grows and gives rise directly or indirectly to a <hi rend="italic">cysto-</hi>carp: the spermatia are each formed in a unicellular antheridium and have no cell-wall at first: they fuse with the tip of the trichogyne: Red Algae (Rhodophyceae or Florideae) :</p><p>G8) The female organ <hi rend="italic">(archicarp)</hi>  resembles the preceding: in fertilization the fertile portion <hi rend="italic">(ascogonium)</hi>  develops into an <hi rend="italic">ascocarp</hi>  containing one or more asci (sporangia) each containing usually eight <hi rend="italic">ascospores:</hi>  the spermatia are formed by abstriction from the filaments <hi rend="italic">(sterigmata) </hi>lining special receptacles, the <hi rend="italic">Spermogonia</hi>, which are the male organs: certain Ascomycetous Fungi <hi rend="italic">(e.g.</hi>  Laboul-beniaceae, some Lichen-Fungi, <hi rend="italic">Polystigma).</hi>  For the Uredineae, see <hi rend="italic">Abnormalities of Reproduction,</hi>  below).</p><p>(B)    There are no definite male cells : the more or less distinct male and female organs come into contact, and their undifferentiated contents fuse: the product is an <hi rend="italic">ascocarp:</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">(a)</hi>  The male and Jemale organs are obviously different : the female organ is an <hi rend="italic">ascogonium,</hi>  the male a <hi rend="italic">pollinodium: e.g. Pyronema, Sphaerotheca</hi>  (Ascomycetes) :</p><p>(3) The male and female organs are quite similar: <hi rend="italic">e.g. Eremas-cus, Dipodascus</hi>  (Ascomycetes).</p><p>It may be explained that carpogamy is the expression of sexual degeneration. In the cases last mentioned, when the sexual organs are quite similar, they have reverted to the condition of gametangia. Still further reduction is observable in other Ascomycetes in which one of the. sexual organs, presumably the male, is either much reduced or is altogether wanting. Again in the Tusts (Uredineae), there are spermatia, but they are functionless (see section on <hi rend="italic">Abnormalities of Reproduction).</hi>  In the highest Fungi, the Auto-basidiomycetes, no sexual organs have been discovered.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Details of the Sexual Act.—</hi>It has been already stated that the sexual act consists in the fusion of two masses of protoplasm, commonly cells, derived from two organs of opposite sex? but this is only the first stage in the process. The second stage is the fusion of the nuclei, which usually follows quickly upon the fusion of the cells; but nuclear fusion may be postponed so that the two sexual nuclei may be observed in the zygote, as “ conjugate ” nuclei, and even in the cells of the organism developed from the zygote <hi rend="italic">(e.g.</hi>  Uredineae). The result of nuclear fusion is that the nucleus of the zygote contains the double number of chromosomes—that is, if the number of chromosomes in each of the fusing sexual nuclei be <hi rend="italic">x,</hi>  the number in the nucleus of the zygote will be <hi rend="italic">2x.</hi>  Moreover, this double number persists in aU the cells of the organism developed from the zygote, until it is reduced to one-balf by meiosis preceding either the development of the spores, or, less commonly, the development of the sexual cells. But there is yet a third stage, which consists in thc temporary fusion of the chromosomes belonging to the two sexual nuclei. This always takes place as a preliminary to meiosis; it may be in the germinating zygote, or after many generations of cells have been formed from it. At the onset of meiosis the (2x) chromosomes are seen to be double, one of each pair having been derived from the male and the female cell respectively: the chromosomes of each pair then fuse so that their chromomeres unite along their length, constituting the <hi rend="italic">pseudo-chromosomes.</hi>  The paired chromosomes separate and eventually go to form tbe two daughter-nuclei, one to each, which thus have half <hi rend="italic">(x)</hi>  the original number of chromosomes. The daughter-nuclei at once divide homotypically, retaining the reduced <hi rend="italic">(x)</hi>  number of chromosomes to form the four nuclei of a tetrad of spores (more rarely, <hi rend="italic">e.g. Fucus,</hi>  of sexual cells).</p><p>III. <hi rend="italic">Lifc-history.</hi></p><p>It will have been gathered from the foregoing sections that plants generally arc capable of both sexual and asexual reproduction; and, further, that in different stages of their life-history they possess the diploid <hi rend="italic">(ix)</hi>  number of chromosomes in their nuclei, or the haploid (x) number. It may be at once stated that, in all plants in which sexual reproduction and true meiotic spore-formation exist, these two modes of reproduction are restricted to distinct forms of thc plant; the sexual form bears only thc sexual organs and is haploid; the asexual form only</p></body></text></TEI>