<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the prostate the urethra runs more forward for about three-quarters of an inch, lying between the two layers of the triangular</p><lb/><p>ligament, both of which it pierces. This is known as the <hi rend="italic">membranous urethra,</hi>  and is very narrow, being gripped by the compressor urethrae muscle.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">spongy urethra</hi>  is that part which is enclosed in the penis after piercing the anterior layer of the triangular ligament. At first it lies in the substance of the bulb and, later, of the corpus spongiosum, while finally it passes through the glans. In the greater part of its course it is a transverse slit, but in traversing the glans it enlarges considerably to form the <hi rend="italic">fossa navicularis,</hi>  and here, in transverse section, it looks like an inverted T (1), then an inverted Y (A), and finally at its opening</p><lb/><p>(external meatus) a vertical slit. Into the whole length of the urethra mucous glands <hi rend="italic">(glands of Littré)</hi>  open, and in thc roof of</p><lb/><p>the fossa navicularis the mouth of one of these is sometimes so large that it may engage the point of a small catheter and is known as the <hi rend="italic">lacuna magna.</hi>  As a rule the meatus is the narrowest part of thc whole canal.</p><p>Opening into the spongy urethra where it passes through the bulb are the ducts of two small glands known as Cowper’s glands, which lie on each side of the membranous urethra and are best seen in childhood.</p><p>Tho <hi rend="italic">penis</hi>  is the intromittent organ of generation, and is made up of three cylinders of erectile tissue, covered by skin and subcutaneous tissue without fat. In a transverse section two of these cylinders (the <hi rend="italic">corpora cavernosa) axe</hi>  placed above, side by side, while one, thc <hi rend="italic">corpus spongiosum,</hi>  is below. Posteriorly, at what is known as the root of the penis, the two corpora cavernosa diverge, become more and more fibrous in structure, and are attached on each side to the rami of the ischium, while the corpus spongiösum becomes more vascular and enlarges to form the bulb. It has already been pointed out that the whole length of the corpus spongiosum is traversed by the urethra. The anterior part of the penis is formed by the <hi rend="italic">glans,</hi>  a bell-shaped structure, apparently continuous with the corpus spongiosum, and having the conical ends of the corpora cavernosa fitted into depressions on its posterior surface. On the dorsum of the penis the rim of the bell-shaped glans projects beyond the level of the corpora cavernosa, and is</p><lb/><p>known as the <hi rend="italic">corona glandis.</hi>  The skin of the penis forms a fold which covers the glans and is known as the <hi rend="italic">prepuce</hi>  or foreskin; when this is drawn back a median fold, the <hi rend="italic">frenulum praeputn,</hi>  is seen running to just below the meatus. After forming the prepuce the skin is reflected over the glans and here looks like mucous membrane. The structure of the corpora cavernosa consists of a strong fibrous coat, the <hi rend="italic">tunica albuginea,</hi>  from the deep surface of which numerous fibrous trabeculae penetrate the interior and divide it into a number of spaces which are lined with endothelium and communicate with the veins. Between the two corpora cavernosa the sheath is not complete and, having a comb-hke appearance, is known as the <hi rend="italic">septum pectinatum.</hi>  The structure of the corpus spongiosum and glans resembles that of thc corpora cavernosa, but the trabeculae are finer and the network closer.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Female Reproductive Organs.</hi></p><p>The <hi rend="italic">ovary</hi>  is an organ which in shape and size somewhat resembles a large almond, though its appearance varies considerably in different individuals, and at different times of life. It lies in the side wall of the pelvis with its long axis nearly vertical and having its blunt end (tubal pole) upward. Its more pointed lower end is attached to the uterus by the ligament of the ovary, while its anterior border has a short reflection of peritoneum, known as the <hi rend="italic">mesovarium,</hi>  running forward to the broad ligament of the uterus. It is through this anterior border that the vessels and nerves enter and leave the gland.</p><p>Under the microscope the ovary is seen to bc covered by a</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>