<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ducts, or vestigial representatives of the vasa efferentia, are often of considerable length, persistent in chameleon and <hi rend="italic">Uromastix, </hi>much reduced in geckos, or disappearing with age as in <hi rend="italic">Lacerta. </hi>The urine of most lizards contains much solid uric acid, which is retained in the urodaeum and voided as a rather solid, white mass, not united with the faeces. Those which have a greater amount of fluid urine have a bladder which receives the fluid portion. The opening of this bladder is on the ventral side of the cloaca, not in direct connexion with the ureters. The bladder is very rarely absent, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  in Varanidae and Amphisbaenidae.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Crocodilia</hi>  have the kidneys placed below the pelvis; their surface shows meandering convolutions separated by furrows. The ureters are for the greater part of their length deeply sunk into the substance of the kidneys, which they leave near the hinder ends, to run freely for a short distance along the dorsal sides of the cloaca, and they open, each separately, and away from the vasa deferentia, into the dorsal side of the urodaeum, which, together with the coprodaeum, forms a large oval chamber, and this being filled with the very fluid urine, functionizes instead of the absent bladder.</p><p>In <hi rend="italic">Chelonia</hi>  the kidneys lie in the pelvis, short and thick, more or less trihedral; the surface is marked with many shallow meandering grooves and fewer deeper furrows. Each ureter, composed of several large successive canals, leaves its kidney near the inner hinder end, and then runs free for a short space, crossing the gut to open into the neck of the urinary bladder, which arises ventrally out of the urodaeum, which itself has become a recess of the cloaca. The bladder is large, often more or less two-horned, attached to the pelvic wall by a peritoneal fold, and it contains very fluid urine.</p><p>The kidneys of <hi rend="italic">Sphenodon</hi>  are very small and far removed from the generative organs. The ureters open, each close to the vas deferens of its side, beneath a little papilla, on the dorsal side, rather near the midline of the urodaeum, whence arises a long-necked bladder.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Reproductive System.</hi></p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Ovaries</hi>  are always in pairs, placed headwards at a distance from the kidneys in <hi rend="italic">Sphenadon,</hi>  lizards and snakes; in the latter the right ovary lies farther forward. In tortoises, and especially in the crocodiles, where they arc very long and much twisted or Iobated, they are situated close to the kidneys and even accompany them. The ovaries of lizards and snakes contain many and large lymph spaces; those of the other reptiles are much denser in structure. The ripening eggs always cause them to assume the shape of a bunch of grapes. The <hi rend="italic">oviducts</hi>  are each held by a peritoneal fold which arises from near the dorsal midline. The abdominal ostia are long slits and are turned towards the side, away from the ovaries. The walls of the ducts gradually become thicker, glandular and much folded. Whilst the ripe eggs, often in considerable numbers, receive their shell, each egg lies in a separate chamber; in the geckos, which lay only one pair of eggs, the two respective chambers have become permanent features. In <hi rend="italic">Sphenodon</hi>  each oviduct opens together with the ureter of its side near the dorsomedian line of the urodaeum. In most lizards the two oviducts and the two ureters have four separate openings in the dorsal wall of the rather deep dorsal recess of the urodaeum. But in <hi rend="italic">Lophura </hi>both oviducts unite (like the ureters) and have only one opening, which is placed a little nearer towards the pelvis than the urinary opening, but they are divided by a longitudinal septum which extends almost to their common orifice. In the snakes the oviducts likewise open into the dorsal recess, sometimes by a common ostium, which is provided with a strong sphincter. The whole recess acts like a vagina for the reception of one of-the copulatory organs. The oviducts of the crocodiles open in a decidedly ventral position, on either side close to the base of the clitoris, a considerable distance from the openings of the ureters. In the tortoises the oviducts open separately into a wide ventral urino-genital sinus, at the base of the neck of the bladder.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Testes</hi>  correspond in position with the ovaries; in snakes and Amphisbaenids the right is placed farther headwards than the left. The usual shape is elongated, sometimes pointed forwards. The <hi rend="italic">Epididymis</hi>  is sometimes of the same size as the testis and then consists of many meandering convolutions of the vas defercns which is composed of several canals from thc testis. The convolutions are held together by a peritoneal lamella. Towards thc cloaca they become much smaller and shorter, and the vas deferens passes along the median side of the ureter. In <hi rend="italic">Sphenodon</hi>  these open separately, each near and below the same papilla near which opens the ureter of the same side. In most lizards the vas deferens unites with its ureter into one short canal which opens beneath or upon a small papilla in the upper corner of the urodaeal recess, far away from the penis. In snakes vas deferens and ureter of each side are likewise commonly united. In the crocodiles each vas dcferens passes from the dorsal side of the cloaca to the ventral side, not accompanied by the ureter, and opens into the blind sac which forms the basal continuation of the deep groove on the dorsal side of the penis. In the tortoises the epididymis is very large and the vas deferens is also much convoluted; each opens separately near the neck of the large urinary bladder close to the backward continuation of the deep longitudinal groove of the copulatory organ.</p><p>Remnants of the Mullerian ducts run paralleI with the vasa deferentia, and similar remnants of the Wolffian ducts accompany the oviducts in crocodiles and tortoises, least degenerated of course in young specimens. Such reciprocal vestiges occur most likely also in lizards, and in female snakes a.vestige of the male duct joins its ureter. In a nearly adult male <hi rend="italic">Sphenodon</hi>  the present writer missed the female remnants.</p><p>The copulatory organs show’ very important modifications. <hi rend="italic">Sphenodon</hi>  is the only recent reptile which is devoid of such an organ; its imperfect substitute is an unpaired, thin, but high membranous fold which arises from the dorsal middle of the circular fold between urodaeum and coprodaeum. During copulation this part of the cloaca is probably everted to secure conception, a striking resemblance to the arrangement found in the Caecilia. The organs of all lizards and snakes are paired, in their quiescent state withdrawn into deep pockets which open on the right and left posterior comers of the proctodaeum or outer chamber of the</p><p>cloaca, which for this reason</p><p>has assumed the shape of</p><p>a transverse slit in all</p><p>lizards and snakes. Hence</p><p>these have sometimes been</p><p>called <hi rend="italic">Plagiotremota.</hi>  Each</p><p>organ can be everted and</p><p>tucked in like the finger</p><p>of a glove, a muscle being</p><p>attached, to the inside of</p><p>the apex; when everted, the</p><p>muscle extends through the</p><p>length of the organ; each</p><p>muscle arises from the ven</p><p>tral side of several trans</p><p>verse processes of the tail</p><p>vertebrae, at a consider</p><p>able distance from the</p><p>cloaca. In the embryo each</p><p>organ arises as a conical protuberance, or papilla, which projects out of the vent. Later it becomes inverted. Probably this ontogenetic feature recapitulates the phylogeny of these organs, which have to be looked upon as swelling flaps or portions of the walls of the cloaca which were protruded during copulation, and which in time borrowed, and specialized, muscular fibres from the ventral tail muscles. On the outer everted side of each organ is a furrow for the reception of the semen. The apex is either single or more or lcss deeply bifurcated, each arm being followed by the likewise divided furrow.. The outer investing membrane of these.very muscular erectile bodies is epidermal; often, especially in snakes, provided with numerous papillae, folds or other excrescences. In</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>