<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>road constructed and worked by a Russian company and opened to traffic in 1899 connects Resht with Teheran via Kazvin.    r</p><p>The value of trade probably exceeds £2,000,000, principal exports being rice, raw silk, dry fruit, fish, sheep and cattle, wool and cotton, and cocoons, the principal imports sugar, cotton goods, silkworm “ seed ” or eggs (£70,160 worth in 1906-7), petroleum, glass and china. The trade in dried silkworm cocoons has increased remarkably since 1893, when only 76,150 Ib valued at £6475 were exported; during the year 1906-7 ending 20th March, 2,717,540 ft) valued at £238,000 were exported. There are telegraph and post offices and branches of the Imperial Bank of Persia and Banque d’Escompte.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Enzeli,</hi>  thc port of Resht in the S.E. corner of the Caspian, is 14 m. N. of Resht, in 37° 29' N., 49° 28' E. Pop. 4000. Between it and other ports in the Caspian communication is maintained by the mail-steamers of the Caucasus and Mercury Steam Navigation Company and many vessels of commercial firms with head offices chiefly at Baku.    (A. H.-S.)</p><p>RESIDENCE (Latin <hi rend="italic">residere,</hi>  to remain behind, to dwell, reside), in general, a place of abode. In law, it usually means continuance in a place. The ordinary meaning of the word has been defined as “ the place where an individual eats, drinks and sleeps, or where his family or his servants eat, drink and sleep ” (R. v. <hi rend="italic">North Curry,</hi>  1825, 4 B. &amp; C. 959). For certain purposes, however, a man may be said to have his residence not only where he sleeps, but also at his place of business. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Abode ; Domicile.</hi>  In ecclesiastical law residence is the continuance of a spiritual person upon his benefice. As a general rule, it is necessary for every rector or vicar to reside within his parish, even though there may be no house of residence annexed to the benefice. But under certain circumstances the bishop of the diocese may grant a licence of non-residence (Pluralities Act 1836).</p><p>RESIDENT, a political agent or officer representing the Indian government in certain native states in India. He resides in the state and advises on all matters of government, legislative or executive. Residents are divided into three classes or ranks. In certain other dependencies or protectorates of the British Empire the representative of the government is termed a resident or political agent, notably in Nepaul, Aden, Sarawak, British North Borneo, &amp;c. In general, where the state to which a resident is attached is not an independent one, he exercises consular and magisterial functions.</p><p>For “ Resident ” as the title of a diplomatic agent see <hi rend="smallcaps">Diplomacy.</hi></p><p>■ RESIDUE (through the French, from thc Lat. <hi rend="italic">residuum,</hi>  a remainder, from <hi rend="italic">residere,</hi>  to remain), in law, that which remains of a testator’s estate after all debts and legacies are discharged, and funeral, administration and other expenses paid. The •person to whom this residue or surplus is left is termed the residuary legatee; should none be mentioned in the will the residue goes to the next of kin (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Executors and Administrators ; Legacy; Will) .</hi></p><p>RESIN (through O.Fr. <hi rend="italic">resine,</hi>  modern <hi rend="italic">résine,</hi>  from Lat. <hi rend="italic">resina,</hi>  probably Latinized from Greek <hi rend="italic">ρητίνη,</hi>  resin), a secretion formed in special resin canals or passages of plants, from many of which, such as, for example, coniferous trees, it exudes in soft tears, hardening into solid masses in the air. Otherwise it may be obtained by making incisions in the bark or wood of the secreting plant. It can also be extracted from almost all plants by treatment of the tissue with alcohol. Certain resins are obtained in a fossilized condition, amber being the most notable instance of this class; African copal and the kauri gum of New Zealand are also procured in a semi-fossil condition. The resins which are obtained as natural exudations are in general mixtures of different, peculiar acids, named the <hi rend="italic">resin acids,</hi>  which dissolve in alkalis to form resin soaps, from which the resin acids are regenerated by treatment with acids. They are closely related to the terpenes, with which they occur in plants and of which they are oxidation products. Examples of resin acids are abietic (sylvic) acid, Ci<hi rend="sub">9</hi>H<hi rend="sub">28</hi>O<hi rend="sub">2</hi>, occurring in colophony, and pimaric acid, C<hi rend="sub">2</hi>OH<hi rend="sub">jo</hi>O<hi rend="sub">2</hi>, a constituent of gallipo resin. Abietic acid can be extracted from colophony by means of hot alcohol; it crystallizes in leaflets, and on oxidation yields trimellitic, isophthalic and terebic acid. Pimaric acid closely resembles abietic acid into which it passes when distilled in a vacuum; it has been supposed to consist of three isomers. Resins when soft are known as oleo-resins, and when containing benzoic or cinnamic acid they are called balsams. Other resinous products are in their natural condition mixed with gum or mucilaginous substances and known as gum-resins. The general conception of a resin is a noncrystalline body, insoluble in water, mostly soluble in alcohol, essential oils, ether and hot fatty oils, softening and melting under the influence of heat, not capable of sublimation, and burning with a bright but smoky flame. A typical resin is a transparent or translucent mass, with a vitreous fracture and a faintly yellow or brown colour, inodorous or having only a slight turpentine odour and taste. Many compound resins, however, from their admixture with essential oils, are possessed of distinct and characteristic odours. The hard transparent resins, such as the copals, dammars, mastic and sandarach, are principally used for varnishes and cement, while the softer odoriferous oleo-resins (frankincense, turpentine, copaiba) and gum-resins containing essential oils (ammoniacum, asafoetida, gamboge, myrrh, scammony) are more largely used for therapeutic purposes and incense. Amber<hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi>  is a fossil resin.</p><p>RESOLUTION, a word used in the two main senses, separation and decision, of the verb “ to resolve ” (Lat. <hi rend="italic">Tesolvere,</hi>  to loose, unfasten), to separate anything into its constituent elements or component parts, hence, through the subsidiary meaning of to clear up doubts or difficulties, to settle, determine. Theprincipalapplications of the term in its first sense are to the separation of a body into its component parts by chemical process, or, to the eye, by the lens of a microscope or telescope; similarly, in mathematics, to the analysis of a velocity, force, &amp;c., into components. In the second sense, beyond the general meaning of determination, firmness of character, a “ resolution ” is specifically a decision of opinion formally submitted to a legislative or other assembly and adopted or rejected by votes.</p><p>RESORCIN (meta-dioxy benzene), CeIL(OH)<hi rend="sub">2</hi>, one of the dihydric phenols. It is obtained on fusing many, resins (galbanum, asafoetida, &amp;c.) with caustic potash, or by the distillation of Brazil-wood extract. It may be prepared synthetically by fusing meta-iodophenol, phenol meta-sulphonic acid, and benzene meta-disulphonic acid with potash; by the action of nitrous acid on meta-aminophenol; or by the action of 10% hydrochloric acid on meta-phenylene diamine (J. Meyer, <hi rend="italic">Ber.,</hi>  1897, 30, p. 2569). Many ortho and para-compounds of the aromatic series (for example, the brom-phenols, benzene para-disulphonic acid) also yield resorcin on fusion with caustic potash. It crystallizes from benzene in colourless needles which melt at 119° C. and boil at 276-5° C. (L. Calderon), or 280° C. (C. Graebe), and is readily soluble in water, alcohol and ether, but insoluble in chloroform and carbon bisulphide. It reduces Fehling’s solution, and ammoniacal silver solutions. It does not form a precipitate with lead acetate solution, as the isomeric pyrocatechin does. Ferric chloride colours its aqueous solution a dark violet, and bromine water precipitates tribromresorcin. Sodium amalgam reduces it to dihydroresorcin, which when heated to 150-160° C. with concentrated baryta solution gives 7-acetylbutyric acid (D. Vorländer); when fused with caustic potash, resorcin yields phloroglucin, pyrocatechin and diresorcin. It condenses with acids or acid chlorides, in the presence of dehydrating agents, to oxyketones, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  with zinc chloride and glacial acetic acid at 145° C. it yields resacetophenone (HO)<hi rend="sub">2</hi>C<hi rend="sub">e</hi>H<hi rend="sub">3</hi>-CO-CH<hi rend="sub">3</hi>  (M. Nencki and N. Sieber,<hi rend="italic">Jour. prak. Chem., </hi>1881 [2], 23, p. 147). With the anhydrides of dibasic acids it yields fluoresceins <hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi>  When heated with calcium chloride-ammonia to 200° C. it yields meta-dioxydiphenylamine (A. Seyewitz, <hi rend="italic">Bull. Soc. Chirn.,</hi>  1890 [3], 3, p. 811). With sodium nitrite it forms a water-soluble blue dye, which is turned red by acids, and is used as an indicator, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Iacmoid</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>