<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>drawn up by Tiele <hi rend="italic">(Ency. Bril.,</hi> 9th ed., voI. xx. p. 360) will
                show what diversified products are blended together. Why should philosophical
                Brahmanism, or the Buddhism which reacted against it, be associated with so
                undeveloped a form as the religion of the ancient Latin settlers in mid-Italy?
                And why, on the other hand, should the religions of the lower culture, which are
                practically of a common type, be separated genealogically into numerous independent
                families? (2) Whitney@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>found the most important distinction to
                lie between religions which were the collective product of the wisdom of the
                community, race-religions as they might be called, and those which proceeded from
                individual founders. But, as TieIe pointed out, the “ individual ” element cannot be
                eliminated from the “ race-religion,” where each myth has been first uttered,
                each rite first performed, by some single person. And the founder who enters history
                with an impressive personality can only do his work through the response made to him
                by the insight and feeling of his time. (3) Kuenen disengaged another
                characteristic, the scope and aim of any given religion; was it limited to a
                particular people, or could it be thrown open to the world? On this foundation the
                higher religions were classed as national or universal, the latter group being
                formerIy supposed to include Buddhism, Christianity and Mahommedanisra. Here,
                once more, the student is confronted with many qualifications. A missionary religion
                Uke Mithraism, which established itself all the way from Western Asia to the borders
                of Scotland, was certainly not “ national.” Judaism and Brahmanism both passed
                beyond the confines of race. The Confucian morality could be adopted without
                difficulty in Japan. In other words, there was either a definite tendency to
                expansion, or there was no impediment in the religion itself when
                circumstances promoted its transplantation. Further, there are elements of Islam,
                like the usages of the<hi rend="italic">hajj</hi> (or pilgrimage to the
                sacred places at Mecca), the dryness of its official doctrine and the limitations of
                its real character as indicated in the Wahhabi revival, which so impair its apparent
                Universalism that Kuenen found himself obliged to withdraw it from the highest
                rank of religions.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> (4) Professor M. Jastrow, jun., starting
                from the relation of religion to life, distinguishes four groups, the religions of
                savages, the religions of primitive culture, the reUgions of advanced culture and
                the religions which emphasize as an ideal the coextensiveness of religion with life.
                It may, however, be doubted whether the fundamental assumption of such a
                scheme, viz. that in the life of the savage religion plays a comparatively small
                part, can be satisfactorily established. The evidence rather implies that, so far as
                the sanctions of relligion affect the savage at all, they affect him with unusual
                force. In the absence of other competing interests his religious beliefs and
                duties occupy a much larger share of his attention than the votaries of many higher
                faiths bestow on theirs; and though his ethical range may be very limited, yet the
                total influence of his religion in determining for him what he may do and what he
                may not, brings the greater part of conduct under its control. The savage who finds
                himself encompassed by taboos which he dare not break, lives up to his religion with
                a faithfulness which many professing Christians fail to reach. (5) There remains a
                broad distinction between reUgions that are in the main founded on the relation of
                man to the powers of Nature, and those based on ethical ideas, which partly
                corresponds to the philosophical division already cited. This enabled Professor
                Tiele to arrange the chief religions in certain groups, starting from the
                primitive conception of the common life of the objects of the
                    surrounding scene:—@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p>
            <lb/>
            <p>I. <hi rend="italic">Nature Religions—</hi></p>
            <p>1.    Polyzoic Naturalism (hypothetical).</p>
            <p>2.    Polydemonistic-magical religions under the control of</p>
            <p>Animism (religions of savages).</p>
            <p>3.    Purified or organized magical religions. Therianthropic</p>
            <p>Polytheism.</p>
            <p>(fl) Unorganized (religions of the Japanese, Dravidians, Finns, Esths, the ancient
                Arabs, the ancient Pelasgi, the Old-Italian peoples, the Etruscans (?), the
                Old-Slavs).</p>
            <p>(ά) Organized (religions of the half-civilized peoples of America, ancient Chinese
                state-religion, religion of the Egyptians).</p>
            <p>4.    Worship of beings in human form, but of superhuman</p>
            <p>power and half-ethical nature. Anthropomorphic polytheism (religions of the Vedic
                Indians,the ancient Persians, the later Babylonians and Assyrians,thea.dvanced
                Semites, the Kelts, Germans, Hellenes, Greeks and Romans).</p>
            <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Ethical Religions</hi> (spiritualistic ethical religions of
                Revelation)—</p>
            <p>1.    National Nomistic (nomothetic) Religious Communions</p>
            <p>(Taoismand Confucianism<hi rend="sub">i</hi>Brahmanism,Jainism, Mazde-ism, Mosaism
                and Judaism, the two last already passing into 2).’.</p>
            <p>2.    Universalistic Religious Communions(Buddhism,Christian</p>
            <p>ity: Islam with its particularistic and nomistic elements only partially belongs to
                this group).@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi></p>
            <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Revelation.—</hi>The second group in this division practicaIly
                corresponds to the second stage recognized by Caird; but it rests upon a somewhat
                different basis, the conception of revelation addressed to the conscience in the
                form of religious law. Neither Taoism nor Confucianism, indeed, makes this
                claim. The <hi rend="italic">Tao-teh-king,</hi> or book of aphorisms on “ the Tao
                and virtue ” ascribed to Lao Tsze, is wholly unlike such a. composition
                as Deuteronomy; and the disciples of Confucius carefully refrained from attributing
                to him any kind of supernatural inspiration in his conversations about social and
                personal morality. The sacred literatures of India and Israel, however, present
                many analogies, and emerge out of a wide range of phenomena which have their roots
                in the practices of the lower culture. The belief that the Powers controlling man’s
                life are <hi rend="bold">w</hi>illin<hi rend="bold">g </hi>upon occasion to disclose
                something of their purpose, has led to widespread rites of divination, which Plato
                described as the “ art of fellowship between gods and men,” and the Stoics defended
                on grounds of a priori religious expectation as well as of universal experience.
                Through the dream the living was put into communication with the dead, which
                sometimes embodied itself in peculiar and pathetic literary forms, such as
                the Icelandic dream-verses imparted by the spirits of those who had been lost at sea
                or overwhelmed by the snow; and a whole series of steps leads up from necromancy to
                prophecy and oracle, as the higher gods become the teachers of men. The gods
                of revelation are naturally not the highest, since they appear as the interpreters
                of one superior to themselves. The revealing agency may be only a voice like Aius
                Locutius, to which the Romans raised a temple; or, like Hermes, he may be
                the messenger of the gods; or, like Marduk, pre-eminently the god of oracles in
                Babylonia, he may be the son of Ea, the mighty deep encompassing the earth, source
                of all wisdom and culture. To Marduk the prophet-god Nabu in his turn became son,
                and his consort Tasbmit (“ causing to hear ”) was the personification of Revelation.
                Egyptian thought ascribed this function to Thoth, who played somewhat different
                parts in different systems, but emerges as the representative of the immanent
                intelligence</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><hi rend="italic"/>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi><hi rend="italic"> Princeton Review,</hi>
                May 1881, quoted by Tiele, <hi rend="italic">Elements of the Science of
                    Religion</hi> (1897), i. p. 42.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic"/>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">    National Religions
                    and Unwersal Religions</hi> (Hibbert Lectures, 1882).</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic"/>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi><hi rend="italic">    Ency. Brit.,</hi>
                9th ed., art. “ Religions ” ; <hi rend="italic">Elements of the Science
                    of Religion,</hi> vol. i. (1897), with some corrections communicated by
                letter to Professor Chantcpie de la Saussaye, <hi rend="italic">Religionsgesch.</hi>
                (3rd ed., 1905), vol. i. p. n.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>    For a long series of suggested bases of classification
                see Raoul de la Grasserie,<hi rend="italic">Des Religions Comparées au Point de Vue
                    Sociologique </hi>(1899), chap, xii.; cf. further E. von Hartmann, <hi
                    rend="italic">Religionsphilosophie</hi> (1888); Siebeck, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lehrbuch der Religionsphilosofhie</hi> (1893); Domer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Grundriss der Religionsphilosophie</hi> (1903). Siebeck proposed to distribute
                religions in three grades: (1) Nature-Religions, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                those of the lower culture; (2) Morality-Religions in various grades and stages, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.</hi> Mexicans and Peruvians, Arcadians, Chinese,
                Egyptians, Hindus, Persians, Germans, Romans, with the Greek religion in the highest
                rank; (3) Religions of Redemption (Judaism forming the transition from the second
                group), Buddhism in the sense of world-negation, and, positively, Christianity.
                Bousset, <hi rend="italic">Whot is Religion? </hi>(1907) reckons Platonism along
                with Buddhism. For criticism of Siebeck’s scheme see Tiele, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elements of the Science of Religion,</hi> vol. i. (1897), pp. 62,65.
                Pfleiderer, <hi rend="italic">Religion and HistoricFaiths</hi> (1907), p.
                88, recognizes more clearly the difficulty of carrying almost any division through
                the whole field, without frequent breach of historical connexions.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
