<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb07-19-r02-0471-02" facs="eb07_19_Page_484.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSA</label>
the Rose. See the article Botany.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rosa,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Salvator,</hi> an admirable painter, was born at Naples in 1614. He was first instructed by Francesco Francazano, a kinsman ; but the death of his father reduced him to sell drawings sketched upon paper for any thing he could get. One of these happening to fall into the hands of Lanfranc, he took him under his protection, and enabled him to enter the school of Spagnoletto, and to be taught by Daniel Falcone, a distinguished painter of battles at Naples. His pieces are exceedingly scarce and valuable ; one of the best of them being that representing Saul and the witch of Endor, which was preserved at Versailles. He died in 1673 ; and as his paintings are in few hands, he is more generally known by his prints, of which he etched a great number. He painted landscapes more than history ; but his prints are chiefly historical. The principal landscape of this master is a noble picture at Chiswick. We are told that he spent the early part of his life in a troop of banditti ; and that the rocky desolate scenes in which he was accustomed to take refuge, furnished him with those romantic ideas in landscape, of which he is so exceedingly fond, and in the description of which he so greatly excels. His robbers, as his detached figures are commonly called, are supposed also to have been taken from the life.</p><p>Amongst the musical manuscripts purchased at Rome by Dr Burney, was a music-book of Salvator, in which are many airs and cantatas of different masters, and eight entire cantatas, written, set, and transcribed by this celebrated painter himself.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>