<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r05-0813-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0870.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RŪDAGĪ</label> (d. 954). Farīd-eddīn Mahommed 'Abdallāh, the first great
                    literary genius of modern Persia, was born in Rūdag, a village in Transoxiana,
                    about 870-900. Most of his biographers assert that he was totally blind, but the
                    accurate knowledge of colours shown in his poems makes this very doubtful. The
                    fame of his accomplishments reached the ear of the Sāmānid Nasr II. bin Ahmad,
                    the ruler of Khorāsān and Transoxiana (913-42), who invited the poet to his
                    court. Rūdagī became his daily companion, rose to the highest honours and
                    amassed great wealth. In spite of various predecessors, he well deserves the
                    title of “ father of Persian literature,” “ the Adam or ’ Sultan of poets,”
                    since he was the first who impressed upon every form of epic, lyric and didactic
                    poetry its peculiar stamp and its individual character. He is also said to have
                    been the founder of the “ dīwān ”—that is, the typical form of the complete
                    collection of a poet’s lyrical compositions in a more or less alphabetical order
                    which prevails to the present day among all Mahommedan writers. Of the 1,300,000
                    verses attributed to him, there remain only 52 kasīdas, ghazals and rubā‘īs; of
                    his epic masterpieces we have nothing beyond a few stray lines in native
                    dictionaries. But the most serious loss is that of his translation of Ibn
                    Mokaffa’s Arabic version of the old Indian fable book <hi rend="italic">Kalilah
                        and Dimnah,</hi> which he put into Persian verse at the request of his royal
                    patron. Numerous fragments, however, are preserved in the Persian lexicon of
                    Asadī of Tus (ed. P. Hom, Göttingen, 1897). In his kasīdas, all devoted to the
                    praise of his sovereign and friend, Rūdagī has left us unequalled models of a
                    refined and delicate taste, very different from the often bombastic compositions
                    of later Persian encomiasts. His didactic odes and epigrams express in
                    well-measured lines a sort of Epicurean philosophy of human life and human
                    happiness; more charming still are the purely lyrical pieces in glorification of
                    love and wine. Rūdagī survived his royal friend, and died poor and forgotten by
                    the world.</p>
               <p>There is a complete edition of all the extant poems of Rūdagī, in Persian text
                    and metrical German translation, together with a biographical account, based on
                    forty-six Persian MSS., in Dr H. Ethé’s “ Rūdagī der Sāmānidendichter ” <hi
                        rend="italic">{Göttinger Nachrichten,</hi> 1873, pp. 663-742); see also his
                    “Neupersische Literatur” in Geigers <hi rend="italic">Grundriss der iranischen
                        Philologie</hi> (ii.); P. Horn, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. der persischen
                        Literatur</hi> (1901), p. 73; E. G. Browne, <hi rend="italic">Literary
                        History of Persia,</hi> i. (1902); C. J. Pickering, “ A Persian Chaucer ” in
                        <hi rend="italic">National Review</hi> (May 1890).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
