<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0447-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0480.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>RODNEY, GEORGE BRYDGES RODNEY</label>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron</hi>
                    (1718-1792), English admiral, second son of Henry Rodney of</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0448" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0481.jp2"/>
               <p>Walton-on-Thames, was born in February 1718. His father had served in Spain
                    under the earl of Peterborough, and on quitting the army served as captain in a
                    marine corps which was disbanded in 1713. George was sent to Harrow, being
                    appointed, on leaving, by warrant dated the 21st of June 1732, a volunteer on
                    board the “ Sunderland.” While serving on the Mediterranean station he was made
                    lieutenant in the “ Dolphin,” his promotion dating the 15th of February 1739. In
                    1742 he attained the rank of post-captain, having been appointed to the “
                    Plymouth ” on the 9th of November. After serving in home waters, he obtained
                    command of the “ Eagle ” (60), and in this ship took part in Hawke’s victory off
                    Ushant (14th October 1747) over the French fleet. On that day Rodney gained his
                    first laurels for gallantry, under a chief to whom he was in a measure indebted
                    for subsequent success. On the 9th of May 1749 he was appointed governor and
                    commander-in-chief of Newfoundland, with the rank of commodore, it being usual
                    at that time to appoint a naval officer, chiefly on account of the fishery
                    interests. He was elected M.P. for Saltash in 1751, and married his first wife,
                    Jane Compton (1730-1757), sister of the 7th earl of Northampton, in 1753. During
                    the Seven Years’ War Rodney rendered important services. In 17.57 he had a share
                    in the expedition against Rochefort, commanding the “ Dublin ” (74). Next year,
                    in the same ship, he served under Boscawen at the taking of Louisburg (Cape
                    Breton). On the 19th of May 1759 he became a rear-admiral, and was shortly after
                    given command of a small squadron intended to destroy a large number of
                    flat-bottomed boats and stores which were being collected at Havre for an
                    invasion of the English coasts. He bombarded the town for two days and nights,
                    and inflicted great loss of war-material on the enemy. In July 1760, with
                    another small squadron, he succeeded in taking many more of the enemy’s
                    flat-bottomed boats and in blockading the coast as far as Dieppe. Elected M.P.
                    for Penryn in 1761, he was in October of that year appointed commander-in-chief
                    of the Leeward Islands station, and within the first three months of 1762 had
                    reduced the important island of Martinique, while both St Lucia and Grenada had
                    surrendered to his squadron. During the siege of Fort Royal (now Fort de France)
                    his seamen and marines rendered splendid service on shore. At the peace of 1763
                    Admiral Rodney returned home, having been during his absence made vice-admiral
                    of the Blue and having received the thanks of both houses of parliament.</p>               <p>In 1764 Rodney was created a baronet, and the same year he married Henrietta,
                    daughter of John Clies of Lisbon. From 1765 to 1770 he was governor of Greenwich
                    Hospital, and on the dissolution of parliament in 1768 he successfully contested
                    Northampton at a ruinous cost. When appointed commander-in-chief of the Jamaica
                    station in 1771 he lost his Greenwich post, but a few months later received the
                    office of rear-admiral of Great Britain. Till 1774 he held the Jamaica command,
                    and during a period of quiet was active in improving the naval yards on his
                    station. Sir George struck his flag with a feeling of disappointment at not
                    obtaining the governorship of Jamaica, and was shortly after forced to settle in
                    Paris. Election expenses and losses at play in fashionable circles had shattered
                    his fortune, and he could not secure payment of the salary as rear-admiral of
                    Great Britain. In February 1778, having just been promoted admiral of the White,
                    he used every possible exertion to obtain a command, to free himself from his
                    money difficulties. By May he had, through the splendid generosity of his
                    Parisian friend Marshal Biron, effected the latter task, and accordingly he
                    returned to London with his children. The debt was repaid out of the arrears due
                    to him on his return. The story that he was offered a French command is fiction.</p>               <p>Sir George was appointed once more commander-in-chief of the Leeward Islands
                    late in 1779. His orders were to relieve Gibraltar on his way to the West
                    Indies. He captured a Spanish convoy off Cape Finisterre on the 8th of January
                    1780, and eight days later defeated the Spanish admiral Don Juan de</p>               <p>Langara off Cape St Vincent, taking or destroying seven ships. On the 17th of
                    April an action, which, owing to the carelessness of some of Rodney’s captains,
                    was indecisive, was fought off Martinique with the French admiral Guichen.
                    Rodney, acting under orders, captured the valuable Dutch island of St Eustatius
                    on the 3rd of February 1781. It had been a great <hi rend="italic">entrepôt</hi>
                    of neutral trade, and was full of booty, which Rodney
                    confiscated. As large quantities belonged to English merchants- he was entangled
                    in a series of costly lawsuits.</p>               <p>After a few months in England, recruiting his health and defending himself in
                    Parliament, Sir George .returned to his command in February 1782, and a running
                    engagement with the French fleet on the 9th of April led up to his crowning
                    victory off Dominica, when on the 12th of April with thirty-five sail of the
                    line he defeated the comte de Grasse, who had thirty-three sail. The French
                    inferiority in numbers was more than counterbalanced by the greater size and
                    superior sailing qualities of their ships, yet five were taken and one sunk,
                    after eleven hours’ fighting. This important battle saved Jamaica and ruined
                    French naval prestige, while it enabled Rodney to write: “ Within two little
                    years I have taken two Spanish, one French and one Dutch admirals.” A long and
                    wearisome controversy exists as to the originator of the manœuvre of “ breaking
                    the line ” in this battle, but the merits of the victory have never seriously
                    been affected by any difference of opinion on the question. A shift of wind
                    broke the French line of battle, and advantage was taken of this by the English
                    ships in two places.</p>               <p>Rodney arrived home in August to receive unbounded honour from his country. He
                    had already been created Baron Rodney of Rodney Stoke, Somerset, by patent of
                    the 19th of June 1782, and the House of Commons had voted him a pension of £2000
                    a year. From this time he led a quiet country fife till his death, which
                    occurred on the 24th of May 1792, in London. He was succeeded as 2nd baron by
                    his son, George (1753-1802), from whom the present baron is descended.</p>               <p>Rodney was unquestionably a most able officer, but he was also vain, selfish and
                    unscrupulous, both in seeking prize money, and in using his position to push the
                    fortunes of his family. He made his son a post-captain at fifteen. He was
                    accused by his second-in-command, Hood, of sacrificing the interest of the
                    service to his own profit, and of showing want of energy in, pursuit· of the
                    French on the 12th of April 1782. It must be remembered that he was then
                    prematurely old and racked by disease.</p>               <p>See General Mundy, <hi rend="italic">Life and Correspondence of Admiral Lord
                        Rodney</hi> (2 vols., 1830); David Hannay, <hi rend="italic">Life of
                        Rodney;</hi> Rodney letters in 9th <hi rend="italic">Report</hi> of Hist.
                    MSS. Com., pt. iii.; “Memoirs,” in Naval Chronicle,  i. 353-93; and Charnock,
                        <hi rend="italic">Biographia Navalis,</hi> v. 204-28. Lord Rodney published
                    in his lifetime (probably 1789) <hi rend="italic">Letters to His Majesty’s
                        Ministers, &amp;c., relative to St Eustatius, &amp;c.,</hi> of which
                    there is a copy in the British Museum. Most of these letters are printed in
                    Mundy’s <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> vol. ii., though with many variant
                    readings.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
