<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0395-05"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0418.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROBERT I., “THE BRUCE”</label> (1274-1329), king of Scotland, was the son
                    of the 7th Robert de Bruce, earl of Carrick by right of his wife Marjorie,
                    daughter of Niel, or Nigel, carl of Carrick, and was the eighth in direct male
                    descent from a Norman baron who came to England with William the Conqueror.
                    After the death of Margaret, the “ maid of Norway,” in 1290, Bruce’s
                    grandfather, the 6th Robert de Bruce, lord of Annandale, claimed the crown of
                    Scotland as the son of Isabella, the second daughter of David, earl of
                    Huntingdon, and great-granddaughter of King David I.; but John de Baliol,
                    grandson of Margaret, the eldest daughter of Earl David, was preferred by the
                    commissioners of Edward I.</p>
               <p>The birthplace of Bruce is not certainly known, but was probably Turnberry, his
                    mother’s castle on the coast of Ayr. The date is the nth of July 1274. His youth
                    is said by an English chronicler to have been passed at the court of Edward I.
                    At an age when the mind is quick to receive the impressions which give the bent
                    to life he must have watched the progress of the great suit for the crown of
                    Scotland. Its issue in 1292 in favour of Baliol led his grandfather to resign
                    Annandale to his son, the 7th Robert de Bruce, who either then or after the
                    death of his father in 1295 assumed the title of lord of Annandale. Already on
                    his wife’s death in 1292 he had resigned the earldom of Carrick to his son, the
                    future king, who presented the deed of resignation to Baliol at Stirling in
                    August 1293, and offered the homage which his father, like his grandfather, was
                    unwilling to render. Feudal law required that the king should take seisin of the
                    earldom before regranting it and receiving the homage, and the sheriff of Ayr
                    was directed to take it on Baliol's behalf. As the disputes between Edward I. of
                    England and Baliol, which ended in Baliol losing his kingdom, commenced in this
                    year, it is doubtful whether Bruce ever rendered homage; but he is henceforth
                    known as earl of Carrick, though in a few instances this title is still given to
                    his father. Both father and son sided with Edward against Baliol. In April 1294
                    the younger Bruce had permission to visit Ireland for a year and a half, and as
                    a further mark of Edward’s favour a respite of all debts owing by him to the
                    exchequer.</p>
               <p>In August 1296 Bruce and his father swore fealty to Edward I. at Berwick, but in
                    breach of this oath, which had been renewed</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0396" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0419.jp2"/>
               <p>at Carlisle, the younger Robert joined Sir William Wallace, who raised the
                    standard of Scottish independence in the name of Baliol after that king had
                    surrendered his kingdom to Edward in 1296. Urgent letters were sent ordering
                    Bruce to support John de Warenne, earl of Surrey, Edward’s general, in the
                    summer of 1297; but, instead of complying, he assisted to lay waste the lands of
                    those who adhered to Edward. On the 7th of July Bruce and his friends were
                    forced to make terms by a treaty called the capitulation of Irvine. The Scottish
                    lords were not to serve beyond the sea against their will, and were pardoned for
                    their recent violence, in return owning allegiance to Edward. The bishop of
                    Glasgow, James the steward, and Sir Alexander Lindesay became sureties for Bruce
                    until he delivered his daughter Marjorie as a hostage. Wallace almost alone
                    maintained the struggle for freedom which the nobles, as well as Baliol, had
                    given up, and Bruce had no part in the honour of Stirling Bridge in September
                    1297, or the reverse of Falkirk, where in July 1298 Edward in person recovered
                    what his generals had lost, and drove Wallace into exile. Shortly afterwards
                    Bruce appears again to have sided with his countrymen; Annandale was wasted,
                    while he, as Walter of Hemingford says, “when he heard of the king’s coming,
                    fled from his face and burnt the castle of Ayr which he held.” Yet, when Edward
                    was forced by home affairs to quit Scotland, Annandale and certain earldoms,
                    including Carrick, were excepted from the districts he assigned to his
                    followers, Bruce and other earls being treated as waverers whose allegiance
                    might still be retained. About 1299 a regency was appointed in Scotland in the
                    name of Baliol, and a letter of Baliol mentions Robert Bruce, lord of Carrick,
                    as regent, along with William of Lamberton, bishop of St Andrews, and John Comyn
                    the younger, a strange combination—Lamberton the friend of Wallace, Comyn the
                    enemy of Bruce, and Bruce a regent in name of Baliol. Comyn in his own interest
                    as Baliol's nephew and heir was the active regent; the insertion of the name of
                    Bruce was an attempt to secure his co-operation. For the next four years he kept
                    studiously in the background, waiting his time. A statement of Peter Langtoft
                    that he was at the parliament of Lincoln in 1301, when the English barons
                    repudiated the claim of Pope Boniface VIII. to the suzerainty of Scotland, is
                    not to be credited, though his father may have been there. In the campaign of
                    1304, when Edward renewed his attempt on Scotland and reduced Stirling, Bruce
                    supported the English king, who in one of his letters to him says, “ If you
                    complete that which you have begun, we shall hold the war ended by your deed and
                    all the land of Scotland gained.” But, while apparently aiding Edward, Bruce had
                    taken a step which bound him to the patriotic cause. On the nth of June, five
                    weeks before the fall of Stirling, he met Lamberton at Cambuskenneth and entered
                    into a secret bond by which they were to support each other against all
                    adversaries and undertake nothing without consulting together. The death of his
                    father in 1304 may have determined his course, and led him to prefer the chance
                    of the Scottish crown to his English estates and the friendship of Edward.</p>
               <p>This determination closes the first chapter of his life; the second, from 1304
                    to 1314, is occupied by his contest for the kingdom, which was really won at
                    Bannockburn, though disputed until the treaty of Northampton in 1328; the last,
                    from 1314 to his death in 1329, was the period of the establishment of his
                    government and dynasty by an administration as skilful as his generalship. It is
                    to the second of these that historians, attracted by its brilliancy even amongst
                    the many romances of history and its importance to Scottish history, have
                    directed most of their attention, and it is during it that his personal
                    character, tried by adversity and prosperity, gradually unfolds itself. But all
                    three periods require to be kept in view to form a just estimate of Bruce. That
                    which terminated in 1304, though unfortunately few characteristics, personal or
                    individual, have been preserved, shows him by his conduct to have been the
                    normal Scottish noble of the time. A conflict of interest and of bias led to
                    contradictory action, and this conflict was increased in his case by his
                    father’s residence in England, his own upbringing at the English court, his
                    family feud with Baliol and the Cornyns, and the jealousy common to his class of
                    Wallace, the mere knight, who had rallied the commons against the invader and
                    taught the nobles what was required in a leader of the people. The merit of
                    Bruce is that he did not despise the lesson. Prompted alike by patriotism and
                    ambition, at the prime of manhood he chose the cause of national independence
                    with all its perils, and stood by it with an unwavering constancy until he
                    secured its triumph. Though it is crowded with incident, the main facts in the
                    central decade of Bruce’s life may be rapidly told. The fall of Stirling was
                    followed by the capture and execution of Wallace in London in August 1305.
                    Edward hoped still to conciliate the nobles and gain Scotland by a policy of
                    clemency to all who did not dispute his authority. A parliament in London in
                    September 1305 to which Scottish representatives were summoned, agreed to an
                    ordinance for the government of Scotland, which, though on the model of those
                    for Wales and Ireland, treating Scotland as a third subject province under an
                    English lieutenant, was in other respects not severe. Bruce is reputed to have
                    been one of the advisers who assisted in framing it; but a provision that his
                    castle of Kildrummy was to be placed in charge of a person for whom he should
                    answer shows that Edward, not without reason, suspected his fidelity. The
                    details of his final breach with the English king are somewhat obscure.
                    According to one account, the bond between Bruce and Lamberton was revealed to
                    Edward by Comyn while Bruce was at the English court. Alarmed by a hint dropped
                    by Edward, he left England secretly, and in the church of the Friars Minorite at
                    Dumfries on the 10th of February 1306 met Cornyn, whom he slew before the high
                    altar for refusing to join in his plans. So much is certain, though the precise
                    incidents of the interview are variously told. It was not their first encounter,
                    for a letter of 1299 to Edward from Scotland describes Comyn as having seized
                    Bruce by the throat at a meeting at Peebles, where they were with difficulty
                    reconciled by the regents.</p>
               <p>The bond with Lamberton was now sealed by blood, and the confederates lost no
                    time in putting it into execution. Within little more than six weeks Bruce,
                    collecting his adherents in the south-west, passed from Lochmaben to Glasgow and
                    thence to Scone, where he was crowned king of Scotland on the 27th of March
                    1306. Two days later Isabella, countess of Buchan, claimed the right of her
                    family, the Macduffs, earls of Fife, to place the Scottish king on his throne,
                    and the ceremony was repeated with an addition flattering to the Celtic race.
                    Though a king, Bruce had not yet a kingdom, and his efforts to obtain it were
                    disastrous failures until after the death of Edward I. In June 1306 he was
                    defeated at Methven, and on the nth of August he was surprised in Strathfillan,
                    where he had taken refuge. The ladies of his family were sent to Kildrummy in
                    January 1307, and Bruce, almost without a follower, fled to the island of
                    Rathlin. Edward came to the north in the following spring On his way he granted
                    the Scottish estates of Bruce and his adherents to his own followers, Annandale
                    falling to Humphrey de Bohun, 4th earl of Hereford. At Carlisle there was
                    published a bull excommunicating Bruce; and Elizabeth his wife, Marjorie his
                    daughter, and Christina his sister, were captured in a sanctuary at Tain, while
                    three of his brothers were executed. In a moment all was changed by the death of
                    Edward I. on the 7th of July 1307. Instead of being opposed to the greatest,
                    Bruce had now as his antagonist the feeblest of the Plantagenets. Quitting
                    Rathlin, he had made a short stay in Arran, and before, Edward’s death had
                    failed to Take Ayr and Turnberry, although he defeated Aymer de Valence, earl of
                    Pembroke, at Loudoun Hill in May 1306. After wasting the critical moment of the
                    war in the diversions of court life, the new English king, Edward II., made an
                    inglorious march to Cumnock and back without striking a blow; and then returned
                    south, leaving the war to a succession of generals. Bruce, with the insight of
                    military</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0397" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0420.jp2"/>
               <p>genius, seized his opportunity. Leaving Edward, now his only brother in blood
                    and almost his equal in arms, in Galloway, he suddenly transferred his own
                    operations to Aberdeenshire. He overran Buchan either once or twice, and after a
                    serious illness defeated the earl of Buchan, one of his chief Scottish
                    opponents, near Inverurie on the 22nd of May 1308. Then crossing to Argyllshire
                    he surprised another body of his enemies in the pass of Brander early in 1309,
                    took Dunstaffnage, and in March of this year held his first parliament at St
                    Andrews. In 1309 a truce scarcely kept was effected by Pope Clement V. and
                    Philip IV. of France, and in 1310, in a general council at Dundee, the clergy of
                    Scotland, all the bishops being present, recognized Bruce as king. The support
                    given to him by the national church in spite of his excommunication must have
                    been of great importance in that age, and was probably due to the example of
                    Lamberton. The next three years was signalized by the reduction one by one of
                    the strong places still held by the English: Linlithgow towards the end of 1310,
                    Dumbarton in October 1311, Perth, by Bruce himself, in January 1312. Previous to
                    these two latter successes the king had made two raids into the north of
                    England; after which Buittle, Dalsvrinton and Dumfries were reduced, and Berwick
                    was threatened. In March 1313 his lieutenant Sir James Douglas surprised
                    Roxburgh, and Thomas Randolph surprised Edinburgh. In May Bruce was again in
                    England, and though he failed to take Carlisle, he subdued the IsIe of Man.
                    About the same time Edward Bruce took Rutherglen and laid siege to Stirling,
                    whose governor, Sir Philip de Mowbray, agreed to capitulate if not relieved
                    before the 24th of June 1314.</p>
               <p>Bruce's rapidity of movement was one cause of his success. His sieges, the most
                    difficult part of medieval warfare, though won sometimes by stratagem, prove
                    that he and his follower's had benefited from their early training in the wars
                    of Edward I. We know that he had been employed by that king to prepare the
                    siege-train for his attack on Stirhng in 1304. By the close of 1313 Berwick,
                    Stirling and BothwelI alone remained English. Edward II. felt that if Scotland
                    was not to be lost a great effort must be made. With the whole available feudal
                    levy of England, and a contingent from Ireland, he advanced from Berwick to
                    Falkirk, which he reached on the 22nd of June 1314. After a preliminary skirmish
                    on Sunday the 23rd, in which Bruce distinguished himself by a personal combat
                    with Sir Henry de Bohun, whom he felled by a single blow of his axe, the battle
                    of Bannockbum was fought on Monday the 24th; and the complete rout of the
                    English determined the independence of Scotland and confirmed the title of
                    Bruce. The details of the day, memorable in the history of war as well as of
                    Scotland, have been singularly well preserved, and redound to the credit of
                    Bruce, who had studied in the school of Wallace as well as in that of Edward I.
                    He had chosen and knew his ground, lying between St Ninians and the Bannock, a
                    petty bum, yet sufficient to produce marshes dangerous to heavily armed
                    horsemen, while from the rising ground on his right the enemy’s advance was
                    seen. His troops were in four divisions: bis brother Edward commanded the right,
                    Randolph the centre, Douglas the left. Bruce with the reserve planted his
                    standard at the Bore Stone, whence there is the best view of the field. His
                    camp-followers on the Gillies' Hill appeared over its crest at the critical
                    moment which comes in all battles. The plain on the right of the marshes was
                    prepared with pits and spikes. But what more than any other point of strategy
                    made the fight famous was that the Scots fought on foot in battalions with their
                    spears outwards, in a circular formation serving the same purpose as the modem
                    square. A momentary success of the English archers was quickly reversed by a
                    flank movement on the part of Sir Robert Keith. The Scottish bowmen followed up
                    this advantage, and the fight became general; the English horse, crowded into
                    too narrow a space, were met by the steady resistance of the Scottish pikemen,
                    who knew, as Bruce had told them truly, that they fought for their country,
                    their wives, their children, and all that freemen hold dear. The English rear
                    Was either unable to come up in the narrow space, or got entangled in the broken
                    ranks of the van. The first repulse soon passed into a rout, and from a rout
                    into a headlong flight, in which the English king himself barely escaped. In the
                    career of Bruce, Bannockburn was the turning-point. The enthusiasm of the nation
                    he had saved forgot his tardy adhesion to the popular cause, and at the
                    parliament of Ayr on the 25th of April 1315 the succession was settled by a
                    unanimous voice on him, and, failing males of his body, on his brother Edward
                    and his heirs male, or failing them on his daughter Marjorie and her heirs, if
                    she married with his consent. Soon afterwards she married Walter the steward (d.
                    1326). As a result of Bannockburn, Bruce’s queen was restored to her husband;
                    Stirling was delivered up to the Scots; the north of England was ravaged, and
                    Carlisle and Berwick were besieged.</p>
               <p>The last part of Bruce's life, from 1315 to 1329, began with an attempt which
                    was the most striking testimony that could have been given to the effect of
                    Bannockburn, and which, had it succeeded, might have altered the future of the
                    British Isles. This was no less than the rising of the whole Celtic race, who
                    had felt the galling yoke of Edward I. and envied the freedom the Scots had won.
                    In 1315 Edward Bruce crossed to Ireland on the invitation of the natives, and in
                    the following year the Welsh became his allies. In the autumn of 1316 Robert
                    came to his brother, and together they traversed Ireland to Limerick. Dublin was
                    saved by its inhabitants committing it to the flames, and, though nineteen
                    victories were won, of which that at Slane in Louth by Robert was. counted the
                    chief, the success was too rapid to be permanent. The brothers retreated to
                    Ulster, and, Robert having left Ireland in May 1317 to protect his own borders,
                    Edward, who had been crowned king of Ireland, was defeated and killed at Dundalk
                    in October 1318. On his return Bruce addressed himself to the siege of Berwick,
                    a standing menace to Scotland. While he was preparing for it two cardinals
                    arrived in England with a mission from Pope John XXII. to effect a truce, or,
                    failing that, to renew the excommunication of Bruce. The cardinals did not trust
                    themselves across the border; their messengers, however, were courteously
                    received by Bruce, but with a firm refusal to admit the papal bulls into his
                    kingdom because not addressed to him as king. Another attempt by Adam Newton,
                    guardian of the Friars Minorite at Berwick, had a more ignominious result. Bruce
                    admitted Newton to his presence at Aldcamus or Old Cambus, and informed him that
                    he would not receive the bulls until his title was acknowledged and he had taken
                    Berwick. On his return Newton was waylaid and his papers seized, not without
                    suspicion of Bruce’s connivance. In March 1318 the town and soon afterwards the
                    castle of Berwick capitulated, and Bruce wasted the English border as far as
                    Ripon. In December he held a parliament at Scone, where he displayed the same
                    wisdom as a legislator which he had shown as a general. The death of his brother
                    and his daughter rendered a resettlement of the crown advisable, and it was
                    settled on his grandson, Robert, son of Marjorie and Walter the steward, in case
                    Bruce died without sons, with a provision as to the regency in case of a minor
                    heir in favour of Randolph. The defence of the country was next cared for by
                    regulations for the arming of the whole nation, down to every one who owned the
                    value of a cow, a measure far in advance of the old feudal levy. Exports during
                    war, and of arms at any time, were prohibited. Internal justice was regulated,
                    and it was declared that it was to be done to poor and rich alike.
                    Leasing-making—a Scottish term for seditious language—was to be sternly
                    punished. The nobles were exhorted not to oppress the commons. Reforms were also
                    made in the tedious technicalities of the feudal law. In September 1319 an
                    attempt to recover Berwick was repelled by Walter the steward, and Bruce took
                    occasion of a visit to compliment his son-in-law and raise the walls 10 ft.</p>
                <p>The king’s position was now so strong that foreign states began to testify their
                    respect. Bruges and Ypres rejected a request of Edward II. to cut off the
                    Scottish trade with Flanders'. Pope John, who had excommunicated Bruce, was
                    addressed</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0398" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0421.jp2"/>
               <p>by the parliament of Arbroath in April 1320 in a letter which compared Bruce to
                    a Joshua or Judas Maccabaeus, who had wrought the salvation of his people, and
                    declared they fought “ not for glory, truth or honour, but for that liberty
                    which no virtuous man will survive.” Moved by this language and conscious of the
                    weakness of Edward, the pope exhorted him to make peace with Scotland, and three
                    years later Randolph, now earl of Moray, procured the recognition of Bruce as
                    king from the papal see by promising aid for a crusade. In 1326 the French king,
                    Charles IV., made a similar acknowledgment by the treaty of Corbeil. Meantime
                    hostilities more or less constant continued with England, but, though in 1322
                    Edward made an incursion as far as Edinburgh, the internal weakness of his
                    government prevented his gaining any real success, while in October of this year
                    Bruce again ravaged Yorkshire, defeated the English' near Byland, and almost
                    captured their king. Some of his chief nobles—Thomas, earl of Lancaster, in
                    1321, and Sir Andrew Harclay, earl of Carlisle, in 1322—entered into
                    correspondence with the Scots, and, though Harclay’s treason was detected and
                    punished by his death, Edward was forced to make a truce of thirteen years at
                    Newcastle on the 30th of May <hi rend="italic">1323,</hi> which Bruce ratified
                    at Berwick. In 1327 Edward III. became king of England, and one of the first
                    acts of the new reign, after a narrow escape of the young king from capture by
                    Moray, was the treaty of York, ratified at Northampton in April 1328, by which
                    it was agreed that “ Scotland, according to its ancient bounds in the days of
                    Alexander III., should remain to Robert, king of Scots, and his heirs free and
                    divided from England, without any subjection, servitude, claim or demand
                    whatsoever.” Joanna, Edward’s sister, was to be given in marriage to David, the
                    infant son of Bruce, born subsequent to the settlement of 1318 and now
                    recognized as heir to the crown, and the ceremony was celebrated at Berwick on
                    the 12th of July 1328.</p>
               <p>The chief author of Scottish independence barely survived his work. He appears
                    to have conducted an expedition to Ireland in 1327, and on his return led a
                    foray into England. His last years were chiefly spent at the castle of Cardross
                    on the Clyde, which he acquired in 1326, and the conduct of war, as well as the
                    negotiations for peace, had been left to the young leaders, Moray and Sir James
                    Douglas, whose training was one of Bruce’s services to his country. Ever active,
                    he employed himself in the narrower sphere of repairing the castle and improving
                    its domains and gardens, in shipbuilding on the Clyde, and in the exercise of
                    the virtues of hospitality and charity. The religious feeling, which had not
                    been absent even during the struggles of manhood, deepened in old age, and took
                    the form the piety of the times prescribed. He made careful provision for his
                    funeral, his tomb, and masses for his soul. He procured from the pope a bull
                    authorizing his confessor to absolve him even at the moment of death. He died at
                    Cardross from leprosy, contracted in the hardships of earlier life, on the 7th
                    of June 1329, and was buried at Dunfermline beside his second wife, Elizabeth
                    (d. 1327), daughter of Richard de Burgh, earl of Ulster, whom he had married
                    about 1304, and who bore him late his only son, David, who succeeded him. Of two
                    surviving daughters, Matilda married Thomas Ysaak, a simple esquire, and
                    Margaret became the wife of William, earl of Sutherland. Marjorie, an only child
                    by his first wife, Isabella, daughter of Donald, earl of Mar, had predeceased
                    him. Several children not born in wedlock have been traced in the records, but
                    none of them became in any way famous.</p>
               <p>In fulfilment of a vow to visit the Holy Sepulchre, which he could not
                    accomplish in, person, Bruce requested Douglas to carry his heart there, but his
                    faithful follower perished on the way, fighting in Spain against the Moors, and
                    the heart of Bruce, recovered by Sir William Keith, found its resting-place at
                    Melrose. When his corpse was disinterred in 1821 the breast-bone was found
                    severed to admit of the removal of the heart, thus confirming the story
                    preserved in the verses of Barbour. That national poet collected in the earliest
                    Scottish poem, written in the reign of Bruce’s grandson, the copious traditions
                    which clustered round his memory. It is a panegyric ; but history has not
                    refused to accept it as a genuine representation of the character of the great
                    king, in spirit, if not in every detail. Its dominant note is freedom—the
                    liberty of the nation from foreign bondage, and of the individual from
                    oppression. It is the same note which Tacitus embodied in the speech of Galgacus
                    at the dawn of, Scottish history. Often as it has been heard before and since in
                    the course of history, seldom has it had a more illustrious champion than Robert
                    the Bruce.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.</hi> —The chief contemporary authorities for
                    the life of Bruce are coloured to some extent by the nationality of the writers.
                    On the Scottish side <hi rend="italic">The Brus,</hi> a poem by John Barbour,
                    edited by W. W. Skeat (Edinburgh, 1894), and the <hi rend="italic">Chronica
                        gentis Scotorum</hi> of John of Fordun, edited by W. F. Skene (Edinburgh,
                    1871-72), are perhaps the most valuable. The <hi rend="italic">Chronicon de
                        Lanercost,</hi> edited by J. Stevenson (Edinburgh, 1839), is also very
                    important. The English chronicles which may be consulted with advantage are
                    those of Walterof Hemingford, edited by H. C. Hamilton (London, 1848-49) ; and
                    of Peter Langtoft, edited by T. Wright (London, 1866-68), and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scalacronica</hi> of Thomas Gray, edited by J. Stevenson
                    (Edinburgh, 1836). For the documents of the time reference should be made to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Calendar of Documents relating to Scotland,</hi> edited by
                    J. Bain (Edinburgh, 1881-88), <hi rend="italic">Documents and Records
                        illustrating the History of Scotland,</hi> vol. i., edited by F. Palgrave
                    (London, 1837); the <hi rend="italic">Rotuli Scotiae</hi> (London, 1814-19), ana
                    the <hi rend="italic">Foedera</hi> of T. Rymer, vol. i. (London, 1704). The
                    chief general histories are: Sir D. Dalrymple, Lord Hailes, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annals of Scotland</hi> (Edinburgh, 1819) ; P. F. Tytler, <hi rend="italic"
                        >History of Scotland</hi> (Edinburgh, 1841-43); J. H. Burton, <hi
                        rend="italic">History of Scotland,</hi> vol. ii. (Edinburgh, 1905); A. Lang,
                        <hi rend="italic">History of Scotland,</hi> vol. i. (Edinburgh, 1904); R.
                    Pauli, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte von England</hi> (Hamburg, 1834-58). See
                    also Sir H. Maxwell, <hi rend="italic">Robert the Bruce</hi> (London, 1897).
               </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
