<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0403-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0426.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROBERTS, FREDERICK SLEIGH ROBERTS</label>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl</hi>
                    (1832-), British soldier, second son of General Sir Abraham</p>               <p>Roberts, G.C.B., was born at Cawmpore, India, on the 30th of September 1832.
                    Educated at Eton, Sandhurst and Addiscombe, he obtained a commission in the
                    Bengal Artillery on 12th December 1851. In the following year he was posted to a
                    field battery at Peshawar, where he also acted as aide-de-camp to his father,
                    who commanded the Peshawar division. In 1856 Roberts was appointed to the
                    quartermaster-general’s department of the staff, in which he remained for
                    twenty-two years, passing from one grade to another until he became
                    quartermaster-general in India. On the outbreak of the Mutiny in 1857, Roberts,
                    at first, was staff officer to the movable column operating against the
                    mutineers in the Punjab, successively commanded by Colonels Neville Chamberlain
                    and John Nicholson, but, towards the end of June, he joined the Delhi Field
                    Force, and was deputy assistant quartermaster-general with the artillery during
                    the operations against Delhi. He was wounded in the fight of the 14th of July,
                    but w*as sufficiently recovered in September to take command as a regimental
                    officer of the left half of No. 2 Siege Battery during the siege. He rejoined
                    the headquarters staff for the assault, and took part in the storm and
                    subsequent seven days’ fighting in the city. He then accompanied Colonel
                    Greathed’s column to Cawnpore, and during September and October was present at
                    the actions of Bulandshahr, Aligarh, Agra, Bithur and Kanauj. He served under
                    Sir Colin Campbell at the second relief of Lucknow in November, at the battle of
                    Cawnpore on the 6th of December, and the subsequent pursuit and defeat of the
                    Gwalior contingent near Shinrajpur. Roberts distinguished himself at the
                    engagement of Khudaganj, on the 2nd of January 1858, by capturing, in
                    single-handed combat, a standard from two sepoys, and also by cutting down a
                    sepoy about to kill a sowar. For these acts of gallantry he was recommended for
                    the Victoria Cross. He was present at the reoccupation of Fatehgarh on the 6th
                    of January, the storm of Mianganj in February, the siege and capture of Lucknow
                    in March, and the action at Kursi on the 22nd of that month, after which he wænt
                    home on sick leave. For his services in the Mutiny he was seven times mentioned
                    in despatches, received the medal with three clasps, the Victoria Cross, and on
                    his promotion to captain, in October 1860, a brevet majority. On the 17th of May
                    1859 he married, at Waterford, Miss Nora Bews, and on his return to India was
                    entrusted with the organization of the viceroy’s camps during the progresses
                    through Oudh, the North-West Provinces, the Punjab and Central India in i860 and
                    1861. In December 1863 he took part, under</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0404" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0427.jp2"/>
               <p>Major-General Garvock, in the Umbeyla campaign among the mountains to the north
                    of Peshawar, and was present at the storm of Lain, the capture of Umbeyla, and
                    the destruction of Mulka, receiving for his services the medal and clasp.</p>               <p>In 1867 Roberts was appointed assistant quartermaster-general to Sir Donald
                    Stewart’s Bengal Brigade for Abyssinia. He showed judgment in embarking each
                    unit complete in every detail, instead of despatching camp equipage in one ship,
                    transport in another, and so on, as was customary. He arrived at Zula, Annesley
                    Bay, in the Red Sea, the base of the expedition, on the 3rd of February 1868,
                    and remained there as senior base staff officer during the four months’
                    campaign. At its close he superintended the re-embarkation of the whole army.
                    His duties were so well performed that Sir Robert Napier sent him home with his
                    final despatches. He was three times “ mentioned,” and received a brevet
                    lieutenant-colonelcy and the war medal. He returned to India the following year
                    as first assistant quartermaster-general. In the autumn of 1871 he made the
                    arrangements for the expedition into Lushai, between south-east Bengal and
                    Burma, fitted out two columns under Brigadiers-General Bourchier and Brownlow,
                    and himself accompanied the first. A road, over 100 m. long, was cut through
                    dense gloomy forests in stifling heat, and the column was attacked by cholera;
                    but the object of the expedition was successfully accomplished, and Roberts, who
                    was present at the capture of the Kholel villages and the action in the
                    Northlang range, and commanded the troops at the burning of Taikum, was
                    mentioned in despatches and made a Companion of the Bath. On his return in March
                    1872, he became deputy quartermaster-general in Bengal, and in 1875
                    quartermaster-general and colonel. He settled the details of the great camp of
                    exercise at Delhi on the occasion of the visit of the prince of Wales in January
                    1876, and attended H.R.H. at the manœuvres. He also superintended the
                    arrangements for the great durbar at Delhi on the ist of January 1877, when
                    Queen Victoria was proclaimed empress of India.</p>               <p>In 1878 Roberts was appointed to the command of the Frontier Field Force at
                    Abbottabad, in Hazara; but in the autumn, on the repulse of the Chamberlain
                    Mission by the Afghans, and the formation of three columns to advance into
                    Afghanistan by the Khyber, the Bolan and the Kurram passes, he was given the
                    command of the Kurram Field Force, with the rank of major-general. Concentrating
                    his column at Thal, he advanced to Kurram towards the end of November, and
                    having formed an advanced base there, moved on to Habib Kila. Under cover of
                    preparations for a front attack on the Peiwar Kotal, he reconnoitred that
                    formidable position, and on the night of the ist of December moved part of his
                    force to attack the Spingawi Kotal, in order to turn the Afghan left flank,
                    leaving the remainder of the force to feign a front attack on the Peiwar, and to
                    guard the camp. After a very difficult night march the Spingawi Kotal was
                    carried at daybreak on the 2nd, and, later, the Afghans on the Peiwar Kotal,
                    threatened in rear, abandoned the position. The next morning Roberts occupied
                    the Peiwar, and on the 6th advanced to Ali KheL He reconnoitred the Shutargardan
                    and the Sapari passes, and made a strong reconnaissance through Khost, in which
                    some fighting took place, and at the end of January returned to Hagir Pir, in
                    Kurram, where his force remained in occupation. In July Major Cavagnari, the
                    British envoy to the new amir, Yakub Khan, passed through Kurram on his way to
                    Kabul, and, shortly afterwards, Roberts left his Kurram command and went to
                    Simla to take his seat on the army commission, where he strongly advocated the
                    abolition of the three Presidency armies, and the substitution for them of four
                    army corps, a measure which was carried out sixteen years later. While he was at
                    Simla, news arrived on the 5th of September of the murder of Cavagnari and his
                    companions at Kabul. The Peshawar Valley Force had been broken up; Sir Donald
                    Stewart was still at Kandahar, but most of his troops had started for India;
                    Roberts, therefore, had the only force ready to strike rapidly at Kabul. It was
                    hastily reinforced, and he hurried back to Kurram to take command, as a
                    lieutenant-general, of the Kabul Field Force (7500 men and 22 guns). By the 19th
                    of September a brigade was entrenched on the Shutargardan, and as Roberts
                    advanced, the Amir Yakub Khan came into his camp. An Afghan force of 8000 men
                    blocked the way in a strong position on the heights beyond Charasia, and on the
                    6th of October Roberts repeated the tactics that had done him such good service
                    at the Peiwar in the previous year, and sending Brigadier-General T. D. Baker
                    with the greater part of his force to turn the Afghan right flank, threatened
                    the pass in front with the remainder. By the afternoon Baker had seized the
                    position, and the enemy, severely defeated, were in full retreat. Kabul was
                    occupied without further opposition.</p>               <p>The city was spared, but punishment was meted out to those convicted of
                    complicity in the murder of the British Mission. Yakub Khan abdicated on the
                    12th of October, and was eventually deported to India. The troops occupied the
                    Sherpur cantonments; but in November a religious war was proclaimed by the
                    Mullahs, and early in December, in order to prevent a threatening combination of
                    Afghan tribes against him, Roberts moved out two columns to attack them in
                    detail. After considerable fighting around Kabul, the numbers of the enemy were
                    so great that he was forced to concentrate his troops again at Sherpur, the
                    defences of which had been greatly improved and strengthened. Sherpur was
                    invested by the enemy, and early on the 23rd of December was attacked by over
                    100,000 Afghans. They were driven off with great loss; and on making a second
                    attempt to storm the place, were met by Roberts, who moved out, attacked them in
                    flank, and defeated them, when they broke and dispersed. Roberts now recommended
                    the political dismemberment of Afghanistan, and negotiations were carried on
                    with the northern tribes for the appointment of an amir for the Kabul district
                    only. On the 5th of May Sir Donald Stewart arrived with his column from Kandahar
                    and assumed the supreme command in Afghanistan, Roberts retaining, under
                    Stewart, the command of the two Kabul divisions, and organizing an efficient
                    transport corps under Colonel R. Low, which was soon to be of inestimable value.
                    On the 22nd of July Abdur Rahman was proclaimed Amir of Kabul; and Roberts was
                    preparing to withdraw his troops to India by the Kurrara route, when news
                    arrived that a British brigade had been totally defeated at Maiwand on the 27th
                    of July, and that Lieutenant-General Primrose was besieged in Kandahar. Roberts
                    was ordered to proceed thither at once with a specially selected column of
                    10,000 troops and his new transport corps. He started on his famous march on the
                    9th of August and arrived at Kandahar on the morning of the 31st, having covered
                    313 miles in twenty-two days. On the following day he fought the battle of
                    Kandahar and gained a complete victory. His services in the Afghan campaigns of
                    1878 to 1880 are recorded in eight <hi rend="italic">Gazettes,</hi> and were
                    recognized by the thanks of both Houses of Parliament, of the Government of
                    India, and of the Governor-General in Council. He was created K.C.B., G.C.B. and
                    a baronet, received the medal with four clasps and the bronze star, and was
                    given the command of the Madras army.</p>               <p>Before proceeding to Madras, Roberts went home on furlough, and when the news of
                    the disaster at Majuba Hill in South Africa arrived in London at the end of
                    February 1881, he was appointed governor of Natal and commander-in-chief in
                    South Africa. He arrived at Cape Town to find that peace had been made with the
                    Boers, and that instructions were awaiting him to return home. The same year he
                    attended the autumn manœuvres in Hanover as the guest of the German emperor. He
                    declined the post of quartermaster-general to the forces in succession to Sir
                    Garnet Wolseley, and returned to India, arriving at Madras in November. The
                    following year he visited Burma with the viceroy, and in 1885 attended the
                    meeting between Abdur Rahman and Yord Dufferin at Rawalpindi at the time of the
                    Panjdeh incident, in connexion with which he had been nominated to the command
                    of an army corps in</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0405" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0428.jp2"/>
               <p>case of hostilities. In July he succeeded Sir Donald Stewart as
                    commander-in-chief in India, and during his seven years’ tenure of this high
                    position instituted many measures for the benefit of the army, and greatly
                    assisted the development of frontier communications and defence. At the end of
                    1886, at the request of the viceroy, he took personal command for a time of the
                    forces in Burma, and organized measures for the suppression of dacoity. For his
                    services he received the medal, was created G.C.I.E., and promoted supernumerary
                    general. In 1890 he did the honours of the army to Prince Albert Victor at a
                    standing camp at Muridki, and in 1891 his attention was occupied with the Zhob
                    and Hunza Nagar frontier campaigns. On the 1st of January 1892 he was raised to
                    the peerage as Baron Roberts of Kandahar and Waterford. In 1893 he left India
                    for good, and the G.C.S.I. was bestowed upon him. He was promoted to be
                    field-marshal in 1895, and in the autumn of that year succeeded Lord Wolseley in
                    the Irish command and was sworn a privy councillor. At Queen Victoria’s diamond
                    jubilee in 1897 he was created K.P.</p>               <p>After the disastrous actions in the Boer war in South Africa in December 1899 at
                    Magersfontein, Stormberg and Colenso, where his only son was killed, Lord
                    Roberts was sent out as commander-in-chief. He arrived at Cape Town on the 10th
                    of January 1900, and after organizing his force, advanced with sound strategy on
                    Bloemfontein, the capital of the Orange Free State, and soon changed the aspect
                    of affairs. The sieges of Kimberley and Ladysmith were raised, and the Boer
                    general, Cronje, flying towards the capital, was overtaken at Paardeberg and,
                    after a fine defence, compelled to surrender, with 5000 men, on the anniversary
                    of Majuba Day, the 27th of February 1900. Roberts entered Bloemfontein on the
                    13th of March, and after six weeks’ preparation, advanced on Pretoria, the
                    capital of the Transvaal. Mafeking was relieved on the 17th of May, and Pretoria
                    occupied on the 5th of June. The two Boer states were annexed, and the war
                    gradually assuming a guerilla character, Roberts handed over the command to Lord
                    Kitchener and returned to England to fill the office of commander-in-chief of
                    the army in succession to Lord Wolseley.</p>               <p>He arrived in the Solent on the 2nd of January 1901, and the same day, at
                    Osborne, had an audience of Queen Victoria, who handed him the insignia of the
                    Order of the Garter. The next day he was received at Paddington by the prince
                    and princess of Wales, and drove in procession to Buckingham Palace, where he
                    was entertained as the guest of the queen. He again had an audience of the queen
                    at Osborne on the 14th of January on his elevation to an earldom, the last
                    audience given by her majesty before her death, which took place eight days
                    later. When the German emperor came to London for the queen’s funeral, he
                    decorated Lord Roberts with the Order of the Black Eagle. Earl Roberts received
                    the thanks of both Houses of Parliament and a grant of £100,000 for his services
                    in South Africa. In 1905 he resigned his post on the Committee of National
                    Defence, and devoted himself to attempting to rouse his countrymen to the
                    necessity of cultivating rifle-shooting and of adopting systematic general
                    military training and service. As an author he is known by his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rise of Wellington</hi> (1895), and his <hi rend="italic">Forty-One Years
                        in India</hi> (1897), an autobiography which has passed through numerous
                    editions.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
