<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0423-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0456.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROBINSON, JOHN</label> (1575-1625), English Nonconformist divine, was born
                    probably in Lincolnshire or Nottinghamshire about T575- He seems to have
                    Studietl at Cambridge, and to have been influenced by William Perkins. He took
                    orders and held a curacy in Norwich, but was attracted by Puritan doctrines, and
                    finally associated himself with a Congregation meeting at Gainsborough (where
                    the “ John Robinson Memorial Church ” bears witness to his work). In 1606 the
                    members divided into two societies, Robinson becoming minister of the one which
                    made its headquarters at Scrooby, a neighbouring village. The increasing
                    hostility of the authorities towards nonconformity soon forced him and his
                    people to think of flight, and, not without difficulty, they succeeded in making
                    their escape in detachments to Holland. Robinson settled in Amsterdam in 1608,
                    but in the following year removed, with a large contingent, to Leiden, where he
                    ministered to a community whose numbers gradually grew from one hundred to three
                    hundred. In 1620 a considerable minority of these sailed for England in the “
                    Speedwell," and ultimately crossed the Atlantic in the “
                    Mayflower”; it was Robinson’s intention to follow as soon as practicable, along
                    with the rest of his flock, but he died before the plan could be carried out, on
                    the ist of March 1625.</p>
               <p>In the early stages of the Arminian controversy he took the Calvinistic side,
                    and even engaged in a public disputation with the famous Episcopius. He bore a
                    high reputation even among his ecclesiastical opponents, and one of them (Robert
                    Baillie) calls him “ the most learned, polished and modest spirit that ever that
                    sect enjoyed.” He was large-minded and eminently reasonable in spirit,
                    recognizing parish assemblies where “ the pure word and discipline jj prevailed
                    as true churches of God. His sound judgment is seen in the way in which he
                    adjusted the relations of elders and church— the"most delicate practical problem
                    of Congregationalism.</p>
               <p>Amongst his publications may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Justification of
                        Separation from the Church</hi> (1610), <hi rend="italic">Apologia
                        Brownisiarum</hi> (1619), <hi rend="italic">A Defence of the Doctrine
                        propounded by the Synod of Dort</hi> (1624), and a volume of <hi
                        rend="italic">Essays, or Observations Dhine and Moral,</hi> printed in 1625.
                    His Works (with one exception, <hi rend="italic">A Manumission to a
                        Manduction,</hi> since published by the Massachusetts Historical Society,
                    ser. iv., vof. i.), including a memoir, were reprinted by R. Ashton in three
                    vols, in 1851. A summary of their contents is given in G. Punchard <hi
                        rend="sub">1</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">History of Congregationalism</hi> (New York, 1867), iii.
                    300-344.. See further <hi rend="smallcaps">Congregationalism,</hi> and the
                    literature there cited; also O. S. Davis, <hi rend="italic">John Robinson</hi>
                    (Hartford, Connecticut, 1897).</p>
 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
