<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0459-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0492.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROHAN</label>, the name of one of the most illustrious of the feudal
                    families of France, derived from that of a small town in Morbihan, Brittany. The
                    family appears to have sprung from the viscounts of Porhoet, and claims
                    connexion with the ancient sovereigns of Brittany. Since the 12th century it
                    held an important place in the history of Brittany, and strengthened its
                    position by alliances with the greatest houses in France. It was divided into
                    several branches, the eldest of which, that of the viscounts of Rohan, became
                    extinct in 1527. Of the younger branches the most famous is that of Guéménée,
                    from which sprang the branches of Montbazon, Soubise and Gie. The seigneurs of
                    Frontenay, an offshoot of this last branch, inherited by marriage the property
                    of the eldest branch of the house. Hercule de Rohan, duc de Montbazon
                    (1568-1654) served Henry III. and Henry IV. against the League, and was made by
                    Henry IV. governor of Paris and the Isle of France, and master of the hounds.
                    His grandson, Louis de Rohan-Guéménée, the chevalier de Rohan, who was notorious
                    for his dissolute life, conspired with the Dutch against Louis XIV. and was
                    beheaded in Paris in 1674. In the 18th century the Soubise branch furnished
                    several prelates, cardinals and bishops of Strassburg, among others the famous
                    cardinal de Rohan, the hero of the affair of the diamond necklace. The seigneurs
                    of Gie, a branch founded by Pierre de Rohan (1453-1513), a cadet of the branch
                    of Guéménée and marshal of France, were conspicuous on the Protestant side
                    during the wars of religion. René de Rohan, seigneur of Pontivy and Frontenay,
                    commanded the Calvinist army in 1570, and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0460" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0493.jp2"/>
                <p>defended Lusignan with great valour when it was besieged by the Catholics
                    (1574-75). His son Henry, the first duke of Rohan, also distinguished himself in
                    the Protestant army. His only child, Marguerite de Rohan, married in 1645 Henri
                    Chabot, a cadet of a great family of Poitou. This marriage was opposed by hef
                    mother, Marguerite de Bethune, who put forward a rival heir called Tancred, whom
                    she claimed to be her son by the duke of Rohan. This Tancred perished in the
                    Fronde in 1649. The property and titles of Henry de Rohan thus passed to the
                    Chabot family, which under the name of Rohan-Chabot produced some distinguished
                    soldiers and -a cardinal archbishop of Besançon. The male line of the Rohans is
                    now represented by an offshoot of the Rohan-Guéménée branch.</p>


            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
