<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0451-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0484.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   <label>ROEDERER, PIERRE LOUIS,</label>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Comte</hi> (1754-1835), French politician and economist,
                    was born at Metz on the 15th of February 1754, the son of a magistrate. At the
                    age of twenty-five he became councillor at the parlement of Metz, and was
                    commissioned in 1787 to draw up a list of remonstrances. His work advocating the
                    suppression of internal customs houses <hi rend="italic">(Suppression des
                        douanes intérieures),</hi> published the same year, is an elaborate treatise
                    on the laws of commerce and on the theory of customs imposts. In 1788 he
                    published <hi rend="italic">Députation aux États généraux,</hi> a pamphlet
                    remarkable for its bold exposition of liberal principles, and partly on the
                    strength of this he was elected deputy to the states-general by the Third Estate
                    of the <hi rend="italic">bailliage</hi> of Aletz. In the Constituent Assembly he
                    was a member of the committee of taxes <hi rend="italic">(comité des
                        contributions),</hi> prepared a scheme for a new system of taxation, drew up
                    a law on patents, occupied himself with the laws relating to stamps and <hi
                        rend="italic">assignats,</hi> and was successful in opposing the
                    introduction of an income tax. After the close of the Constituent Assembly he
                    was elected, on the nth of November 1791, <hi rend="italic">procureur général
                        syndic</hi> of the department of Paris. The directory of the department, of
                    which the duc de la Rochefoucauld was president, was at this time in pronounced
                    opposition to the advanced views that dominated the Legislative Assembly and the
                    Jacobin Club, and Roederer was not altogether in touch with his colleagues. Thus
                    he took no share in signing their protest against the law against the non-juring
                    clergy, as a violation of religious liberty. But the directory did not long
                    survive. With the growing anarchy of the capital many of its members resigned
                    and fled, and their places could not be filled up. Roederer himself has left in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Chronique des cinquante jours</hi> (1832) an account of
                    the pitiable part played by* the directory of the department in the critical
                    period between the 20th of June and the 10th of August 1792. Seeing the perilous
                    drift of things, he had tried to get into touch with the king; and it was on his
                    advice that Louis, on the fatal 10th, took refuge in the Assembly. His conduct
                    arousing suspicion, he went into hiding, and did not emerge again until after
                    the fall of Robespierre. In 1796 he was made a member of the Institute, was
                    appointed to a professorship of political economy, and founded the <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal d’économie publique, de morale et de législation.</hi>
                    Having escaped deportation at the time of the <hi rend="italic">coup d’état</hi>
                    of 18 Fructidor, he took part in the revolution of 18 Brumaire, and was
                    appointed by Napoleon member of the council of state and senator. Under the
                    Empire, Roederer, whose public influence was very considerable, was Joseph
                    Bonaparte’s minister of finance at Naples (1806), administrator of the grand
                    duchy of Berg (1810), and imperial commissary in the south of France. During the
                    Hundred Days he was created a peer of France. The Restoration government
                    stripped him of his offices and dignities, but he recovered the title of peer of
                    France in 1S32. He died on the 17th of December 1835. His son, Baron Antoine
                    Marie Roederer</p>                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0452" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0485.jp2"/>
               <p>(1782-1865), was also a politician of some note in his day.</p>               <p>Among P. L. Roederer’s writings may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Louis
                        XII.</hi> (1820); <hi rend="italic">François I.</hi> (1825); <hi
                        rend="italic">Comédies historiques</hi> (1827-30); <hi rend="italic"
                        >L'Esprit de la révolution de 1789</hi> (1831); <hi rend="italic">La
                        Première et ta deuxième année du consulat de Bonaparte</hi> (1802); <hi
                        rend="italic">Chronique des cinquante jours,</hi> an account of the events
                    of the 10th of August 1792; and <hi rend="italic">Mémoire pour servir à
                        l'histoire de la société polie en France</hi> (1835).</p>               <p>See his <hi rend="italic">Œuvres,</hi> edited by his son (Paris, 1853 seq.);
                    Sainte-Beuve, <hi rend="italic">Causeries du lundi,</hi> vol. viii.; M. Mignet,
                        <hi rend="italic">Notices historiques</hi> (Paris, 1853).</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
