<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0420-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0453.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   ROBILANT, CARLO FELICE NICOLIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Conte
                        di</hi> (1826-1888), Italian statesman and diplomat, was a native of Turin.
                    He entered the army, and lost his left hand at Novara, where he was aide-de-camp
                    to Charles Albert, king of Piedmont. He fought in 1859, and reached the grade of
                    general in the Austrian campaign of 1866, after which he served on the
                    delimitation commission. He was chief of the Military Academy, and in 1867 was
                    made prefect of Ravenna to suppress political disorder. He was defeated at Turin
                    in the elections for the Chamber in 1870, and was sent in 1871 as minister
                    plenipotentiary to Vienna, where he subsequently became ambassador. He was
                    connected with the Prussian nobility by his mother, and he married an Austrian,
                    a daughter of Prince Edmund Clary-Aldringen. In spite of the active share he had
                    taken in driving Austria from Italy, he was a <hi rend="italic">persona
                        grata</hi> at Vienna, and his policy was steadily directed to an alliance
                    between the two powers. This was accomplished by the secret terms of the Triple
                    Alliance in 1882. He was recalled to Rome in 1885 to become minister for foreign
                    affairs in the Depretis cabinet. Robilant’s independent attitude as foreign
                    minister secured greater consideration for Italy from her allies, but he did not
                    adapt himself to the exigencies of domestic politics, and his excessive
                    unpopularity contributed to* the downfall of the ministry on the 7 th of
                    February 1887, consequent on an adverse vote on the Massawa question. Before
                    leaving office, he completed the negotiations for the renewal of the Triple
                    Alliance, and for its extension to cover Anglo-Italian co-operation in the
                    Mediterranean. In the new Depretis-Crispi administration Robilant was not
                    included. He was sent to London as ambassador in the next year, but died two
                    months after his arrival, on the 17th of October 1888.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
