<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0403-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0426.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROBERTS, DAVID</label> (1796-1864), Scottish painter, was born at
                    Stockbridge, Edinburgh, on the 24th of October 1796. He was apprenticed by his
                    father, a shoemaker, for seven years to a painter and house-decorator; and
                    during this time he employed his evenings in the study of art. In 1820 he formed
                    the acquaintance of Clarkson Stanfield, then painting at the Pantheon,
                    Edinburgh, at whose suggestion he sent three pictures in 1822 to the Exhibition
                    of Works by Living Artists, held in Edinburgh. In the same year he removed to
                    London, where he worked for the Coburg Theatre, and was afterwards employed,
                    along with Stanfield, at Drury Lane. In 1824 he exhibited at the British
                    Institution a view of Dryburgh Abbey, and sent two works to the first exhibition
                    of the Society of British Artists, of which he was elected president in 1831. In
                    the same autumn he visited Normandy, and the works which were the results of
                    this excursion began to lay the foundation of the artist’s reputation—one of
                    them, a view of Rouen Cathedral, being sold for eighty guineas. His scenes for
                    an opera, <hi rend="italic">The Seraglio,</hi> executed two years later, and the
                    scenery for a pantomime dealing with the naval victory of Navarino, and two
                    panoramas executed jointly by him and Stanfield, were among his last work for
                    the theatres. In 1829 he exhibited the “ Departure of the Israelites from
                    Egypt,” in which his style first becomes apparent; three years afterwards he
                    travelled in Spain and Tangiers, returning in the end of 1833 with a supply of
                    effective sketches, elaborated into attractive and popular paintings. His “
                    Interior of Seville Cathedral ” was exhibited in the British Institution in
                    1834, and sold for £300; and he executed a fine series of Spanish illustrations
                    for the <hi rend="italic">Landscape Annual</hi> of 1836, while in 1837 a
                    selection of his <hi rend="italic">Picturesque Sketches in Spain</hi> was
                    reproduced by lithography.</p>
               <p>In 1838 Roberts made a long tour in the East, and accumulated a vast collection
                    of sketches of a class of scenery which had hitherto been
                    hardly touched hy British artists, and which appealed to the public with all the
                    charm of novelty. The next ten years of his life were mainly spent in
                    elaborating these materials. An extensive series of drawings w <hi rend="sup"
                        >T</hi> as lithographed by Louis Haghe in <hi rend="italic">Sketches in the
                        Holy Land and Syria,</hi> 1842-1849. In 1851, and again in 1853, Roberts
                    visited Italy, painting the “ Ducal Palace, Venice,” bought by Lord
                    Londesborough, the “ Interior of the Basilica of St Peter’s, Rome,” “ Christmas
                    Day, 1853,” and “ Rome from the Convent of St Onofrio,” presented to the Royal
                    Scottish Academy. His last volume of illustrations, <hi rend="italic">Italy,
                        Classical, Historical and Picturesque,</hi> was published in 1859. He also
                    executed, by command of Queen Victoria, a picture of the opening of the Great
                    Exhibition of 1851. In 1839 he was elected an associate and in 1841 a full
                    member of the Royal Academy; and in 1858 he was presented with the freedom of
                    the city of Edinburgh. The last years of his life were occupied with a series of
                    views of London from the Thames. He had executed six of these, and was at work
                    upon a picture of St Paul’s Cathedral, when, on the 25th November 1864, he died
                    suddenly of apoplexy.</p>
               <p>A <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of Roberts, compiled from his journals and other
                    sources by James Ballantine, with etchings and pen-and-ink sketches by the
                    artist, appeared in Edinburgh in 1866.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
