<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0259.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0253-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SYNGNATHUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pipe-fish,</hi></label>
 according to Linnaeus, a genus belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">amphibia,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">nantes,</hi> but arranged by Gmelin more properly under the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pisces,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">branchiostegi.</hi> The head is ſmall ; the roſtrum ſomewhat cylindrical, long, and turned up at the point, where the mouth is placed, which is covered with a lid or valve. The gills are covered in the ſame manner. The body is covered with a ſtrong cruſt, and has no ventral fins. There are eight ſpecies ; the tetragonus, typhele, acus, pelagicus, æquoreus, ophidion, barbarus, and hippocampus. Three of theſe are found in the Britiſh ſeas, viz.</p><p>1. The <hi rend="italic">barbarus,</hi> or longer pipe fiſh. One deſcribed by Sir Robert Sibbald, was two feet in length ; that examined by Mr Pennant only 16 inches. The noſe was an inch long, compreſſed ſidewise, and the end of the lower mandible turned up ; the aperture of the mouth was very ſmall. The irides were red ; behind each eye was a deep brown line. The body, in the thickeſt part, was about equal to a ſwan’s quill, hexangular from the end of the dorſal fin ; from thence to the tail, quadrangular. The belly was slightly carinated, and marked along the middle with a duſky line. Under the tail, commencing at the anus, is a fulcus or groove six inches and a half long, covered by two longitudinal valves, which concealed a multitude of young fiſh. On crushing this part, hundreds may be obſerved to crawl out</p><p>2. The <hi rend="italic">acus,</hi> or ſhorter pipe-fiſh, is thicker than the former, yet it has been ſeen of the length of 16 inches. The middle of the body in ſome is hexangular, in others heptangular. The mouth is formed like that of the former : the irides are yellow ; cloſe behind the head are the pectoral fins, which are ſmall and ſhort. On the lower part of the back is one narrow fin ; beyond the vent the tail commences, which is long and quadrangular. At the extremity is a fin round and radiated. The body is covered with a ſtrong cruſt, elegantly divided into ſmall compartments. The belly is white ; the other parts are brown.</p><p>3. The <hi rend="italic">ophidian,</hi> or little pipe-fiſh, ſeldom exceeds five inches in length, is very ſlender, and tapers off to a point. It wants both the pectoral and tail fins ; is covered with a ſmooth ſkin, not with a cruſt as the two former kinds are. The noſe is ſhort, and turns a little up ; the eyes are prominent. On the back is one narrow fin. This ſpecies is not viviparous : on the belly of the female is a long hollow, to which adhere the eggs, diſpoſed in two or three rows. They are large, and not numerous. The ſynonym of <hi rend="italic">ſerpent</hi> is uſed in ſeveral languages to expreſs theſe fiſh : the French call one ſpecies <hi rend="italic">orueul,</hi> from a sort of ſnake not unlike the blind worm : the Germans call it <hi rend="italic">meherschlange</hi>; and the Corniſh the s <hi rend="italic">ea-adder.</hi></p><p>The Sea-horſe, which was claſſed by Artedi under the Syngnathus, is now, by later ichthyologiſts, arranged under <hi rend="smallcaps">Trichecus</hi>; which ſee.</p></div></body></text></TEI>