<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0259.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0253-09" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SYNOD</label>,
in aſtronomy, a conjunction or concourſe of two or more ſtars or planets, in the ſame optical place of the heavens.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Synod</hi> ſignifies alſo a meeting or aſſembly of eccleſiaſtical perſons to conſult on matters of religion.</p><p>Of theſe there are four kinds, viz. 1. <hi rend="italic">General,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">oecumenical,</hi> where biſhops, &amp;c. meet from all nations. Theſe were firſt called by the emperors, afterwards by Chriſtian princes; till in later ages the pope uſurped to himſelf the greateſt ſhare in this busineſs, and by his legates preſided in them when called. 2. <hi rend="italic">National,</hi> where thoſe of one nation only come together, to determine any point of doctrine or discipline. The firſt of this sort which we read of in England, was that of Herudford or Hertford, in 673, and the laſt was that held by cardinal Pole, in 1555. 3. <hi rend="italic">Provincial,</hi> where thoſe only of one province meet, now called the <hi rend="italic">convocation.</hi> 4. <hi rend="italic">Dioceſan,</hi> where thoſe of but one dioceſe meet, to enforce canons made by general councils, or national and provincial <hi rend="italic">ſynods,</hi> and to consult and agree upon rules of discipline for themſelves. Theſe were not wholly laid aſide, till by the act of ſubmission, 25 Hen. VIII. c. 19. it was made unlawful for any <hi rend="italic">ſynod</hi> to meet, but by royal authority, See <hi rend="smallcaps">Council</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Convocation.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Synods,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Provincial, in the Government of the Church of Scotland.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Presbyterians,</hi> n⁰ 14.</p></div></body></text></TEI>