<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0207.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0201-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUS</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">Hog,</hi> in zoology, a genus of quadrupeds belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">mammalia</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">belluae.</hi> There are four cutting teeth in the upper jaw, whoſe points converge; and, for the moſt part, six in the lower jaw, which ſtand forwards : There are two tuſks in each jaw, thoſe in the upper jaw being ſhort, while thoſe of the under jaw are long, and extend out of the mouth. The ſnout is prominent, moveable, and has the appearance of having been cut off, or truncated. The feet are armed with divided or cloven hoofs. There are six ſpecies; the ſcrofa, æthiopicus, tajassu, babyruſſa, porcus, and africanus. The moſt remarkable are,</p><p>I. The <hi rend="italic">ſcrofa,</hi> or common hog, having the body covered with briſtles ; two large teeth above and below. In a wild ſtate, of a dark brinded colour, and beneath the briſtles is a ſoft ſhort hair ; the ears ſhort, and a little rounded. <hi rend="smallcaps">Tame:</hi> the ears long, ſharp-pointed, and ſtouching ; the colour generally white, ſometimes mixed with other colours. In a tame ſtate it is univerſal ; except in the frigid zones, and in Kamtſchatka, where the cold is very ſevere. Since its introduction into America by the Europeans, it abounds to excels in the hot and temperate parts. It is found wild in moſt parts of Europe. In the foreſts of South America there are vast droves, which derive their origin from the European kind relapſed into a ſtate of nature ; and are what Mr Bancroft, in his Hiſtory of Guiana, deſcribes as a particular ſpecies by the name of <hi rend="italic">Warree.</hi> They cannot bear exceſſive cold ; inhabit wooded countries ; and are very ſwift. In America they are uſeful by clearing the country of rattle-ſnakes, which they devour without danger.</p><p>Of all quadrupeds, the hog is the moſt rude and brutal. The imperfections of his form ſeem to have an influence on his nature and diſpoſitions. All his habits are groſs ; all his appetites are impure ; all his ſenſations are confined to a furious luſt, and a brutal gluttony. He devours indiſcriminately every thing that comes in his way, even his own progeny the moment after their birth. This voraciouſneſs ſeems to proceed from the perpetual cravings of his ſtomach, which is of an immoderate ſize ; and the groſſneſs of his appetities, it is probable, ariſes from the bluntness of his ſenses of taſte and of feeling. The rudeneſs of the hair, the hardneſs of the ſkin, and the thickneſs of the fat, render theſe animals leſs ſensible to blows. Mice have been known to lodge upon a hog’s back, and to eat his ſkin and fat, without his ſhowing any marks of ſensibility. The other ſenſes oſ the hog are very good. It is well known to the hunters that the wild boar hears and ſmells at a great diſtance ; for, in order to ſurpriſe him, they are obliged to watch him in ſilence during the night, and to place themſelves oppoſite to the wind, that he may not perceive the ſmell, which never fails to make him turn back.</p><p>But the hog, though the moſt impure and filthy of all quadrupeds, is yet uſeful by the very ſordidness of its manners ; this alone devouring what is the refuſe of all others, and contributing not only to remove what would be a nuiſance to the human race, but alſo converting the moſt nauſeous offals into the richeſt nutriment : for this reaſon its ſtomach is capacious, and its gluttony exceſſive : not that its palate is inſensible to the difference of eatables ; for where it finds variety, it will reject the worſt with as diſtinguiſhing a taſte as other quadrupeds.</p><p>The parts of this animal are finely adapted to its way of life. As its method of feeding is by turning up the earth with its noſe for roots of different kinds, ſo nature has given it a more prone form than other animals ; a ſtrong brawny neck; eyes ſmall, and placed high in the head ; a long ſnout, noſe callous and tough, and a quick ſenſe of ſmelling to trace out its food. Its inteſtines have a ſtrong reſemblance to thoſe of the human ſpecies. The external form of its body is very unwieldly ; yet, by the ſtrength of its tendons, the wild boar (which is only a variety of the common kind) is enabled to fly from the hunters with amazing agility : the back-toe on the feet of this animal prevents its slipping while it deſcends declivities, and muſt be of ſingular uſe when purſued. Yet, notwithſtanding its powers of motion, it is by nature ſtupid, inactive, and drowſy ; much inclined to increaſe in fat, which is diſpoſed in a different manner from that of other animals, and forms a regular coat over the whole body. It is reſtleſs at a change of weather, and in certain high winds is ſo agitated as to run violently, ſcreaming horribly at the ſame time : it is fond of wallowing in the dirt, either to cool its ſurfeited body, or to deſtroy the lice, ticks, and other infects with which it is infeſted. Its diſeaſes generally ariſe from foul feeding and intemperance ; measles, impoſthumes, and ſcrophulous complaints, are reckoned among them. Theſe are beſt prevented by keeping the animals, as the ancients ſtrongly recommended, very clean in their ſties ; allowing them air, exercise, and a ſufficiency of water. Linnæus obſerves, that its fleſh is wholeſome food for athletic conſtitutions, or thoſe that uſe much exerciſe ; but bad for ſuch as lead a ſedentary life : it is, however, of moſt univerſal uſe ; and furniſhes numberleſs materials for epicuriſm.</p><p>The boar, or male of theſe creatures, is choſen with great care, when intended for the propagation of his ſpecies ; and is thus employed from the age of two to five years, and then either ſold or fatted. The males not allotted to this uſe are caſtrated, ſometimes at the age of six weeks, and ſometimes when they are six months old ; and then fed to a great ſize either for ſale or for the uſe of the family. <hi rend="smallcaps">Sows</hi> are kept for breed generally from one year old to ſeven, and are then ſpayed and fatted. They have commonly more greaſe on their inteſtines than hogs, theſe being fatteſt on their backs.</p><p>As to the age of theſe animals, it is ſaid that the life of the wild boar may be extended to twenty-five or thirty years.<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0208.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0202"/>
Ariſtotle ſays, that hogs in general live twenty years ; and adds, that both males and females are fertile till they arrive at the ape of fifteen. They can engender at the age of nine or twelve months ; but it is better to restrain them till they be eighteen months or two years. The firſt litter of the ſow is not numerous ; and, when only one year old, her pigs are weak, and even imperfect. She may be ſaid to be in ſeaſon at all times. Though full, ſhe ſolicits the approach of the male. This may be regarded as an exceſs among animals ; for almoſt every other ſpecies refuſe the male after conception. The ardour of the ſow, though almoſt perpetual, is however marked by paroxyſms and immoderate movements, which always terminate by her wallowing in the mire. She, at the same time, emits a thick whitiſh fluid. She goes four months with young ; brings forth in the beginning of the fifth ; and ſoon afterwards ſolicits the male, is impregnated a ſecond time, and of courſe brings forth twice a-year. The wild ſow, which every way reſembles the domeſtic kind, produces only once a-year. This difference in fertility is probably owing to want of nouriſhment, and the neceſſity of suckling her pigs much longer than the domeſtic ſow, which is never allowed to nurſe her young above fifteen days or three weeks. Only eight or nine of the litter are kept longer ; the reſt are fold. In fifteen days, pigs are excellent food.</p><p>As theſe creatures, though exceedingly voracious, will feed almoſt on any thing, they are bred and kept everywhere, and are quickly and cheaply fatted. In miry and in marſhy grounds (From which they are not averſe) they devour worms, frogs, fern, ruſh, and sedge roots. In drier and in woody countries, they feed on hips, haws, ſloes, crabs, maſt, cheſnuts, acorns, &amp;c. and on this food they will grow fleſhy and fat. They are a kind of natural ſcavengers, will thrive on the traſh of an orchard, the outcaſts of the kitchen, the ſweepings of barns and granaries, the offals of a market, and moſt richly on the refuſe of a dairy. If near the sea, they will ſearch the ſhores for ſhell fiſh ; in the fields, they eat grass ; and in cities and large towns they are kept in great numbers, and ſupported chiefly by grains. It is evident that the facility of feeding them everywhere at a ſmall expence, is a national benefit, more eſpecially in a country where the people are accuſtomed to eat fleſh daily, and could not perhaps perform their daily labour if they did not. It is no less obſervable, that notwithſtanding this facility of feeding, and the multitudes of ſwine maintained, they ſeldom fail of coming to a good market. In no part of Europe is the management of theſe creatures better understood than in Britain. The time of farrowing is adjuſted to the nature of the farm, the food it can ſupply ; and the number of pigs sold and kept are in like manner adjuſted. New kinds of food, more wholeſome and nutritive than what were uſed formerly, have been introduced, ſuch as turnips, carrots, clover, &amp;c. They are in moſt places regularly managed and cloſely attended. Tuſſer, many years ſince, affirmed from his own experience, that a ſow might bring as much profit as a cow. In ſome counties, it is ſaid, a ſow dependent on a dairy hath produced, all expences deducted, about 10 l. in the ſpace of a year. It may be ſome ſatisfaction to the reader to know, that, on a nice calculation, the annual profits of a ſow in France are found to be between 50 and 60 livres.— In Britain, theſe animals in different counties are of very different ſizes. In Leiceſterſhire, Northamptonshire, and Pembrokeſhire, they are very large. In Hampshire, Wiltſhire, and wherever they can run in the woods, and feed on maſt and acorns, their fleſh is firmer and better. The Chineſe ſwine are common with us : they are ſmaller, blacker, and their legs ſhorter than ours : ſo that, when fat, their bellies literally touch the ground. They thrive exceedingly well with us, are very prolific, and their fleſh very fine and well-taſted.</p><p>In conſidering the advantages derived from theſe creatures, it is to be obſerved, that the fleſh of all their different kinds, and at all ages, is looked upon as a very ſubſtantial and agreeable aliment; and of courſe, in their proper ſeaſons, the different sorts of proviſions thus ſupplied are all of them very ſaleable. The wild boar was eſteemed a prime delicacy amongſt the Romans, and the fleſh of the tame was much more in favour with our anceſtors than with us ; though <hi rend="smallcaps">brawn</hi> has ſtill many admirers, is made in the greateſt perfection, and conſidered as a rarity peculiar to this country. Pork, though it might be wisely prohibited in ſome warm countries, is found by experience equally nutritive and ſalutary here. As ſuch it furniſhes a very large proportion of that food which is vended in our markets. It takes salt better, and keeps longer, than the fleſh of any other animal; and the conſumption of it is prodigious when pickled or ſalted, more eſpecially in our foreign garriſons and in the ſea-ſervice. Our bacon is differently cured, ſo as to render it acceptable to all palates ; and our hams are not at all inferior to thoſe of other countries. Freſh pork fells nearly as dear as beef ; the lard brings double or triple the price ; the blood, the inteſtines, the feet, and the tongue, are all prepared as food. The fat of the inteſtines and web, which differs from common lard, is employed for greaſing axles of wheels, and for many other purpoſes. Sieves are made of the ſkin ; and bruſhes, pencils, &amp;c. of the briſtles. The dung is reputed next in value to that of ſheep. Mr Worlidge<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Survey of Husbandry,</hi> <unclear> p </unclear> . 171.</p></note> * propoſes that ſwine ſhould be turned into a cloſe well- paled, and planted with greens, pulſe, and roots, on which they may feed, and by their trampling and their dung raiſe a great quantity of excellent soil. Mr Mortimer<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Art of Husbandry,</hi> vol. i. p. 117.</p></note> * aſſures us that ſome, on poor light ſhallow land in Staffordſhire, ſow a ſmall white pea, which they never reap, but turn in ſo many hogs to eat them as they think they will fat ; and there they lie day and night, and their dung will ſo enrich the land, that it will bring a good ſward upon it, and will graze many years afterwards. Our old huſbandmen had an ill opinion of this dung, as ſupposing it bred weeds, but it will probably not obtain much credit at present. In some places they waſh with hogs dung for want of ſoap ; which anſwers tolerably well, it the linen hangs long enough in the air to become thoroughly ſweet.</p><p>The wild boar was formerly a native of our country, as appears from the laws of Hoel dda, who permitted his grand huntſman to chace that animal from the middle of November to the beginning of December. William the Conqueror puniſhed with the loss of their eyes any that were convicted of killing the wild boar, the flag, or the roebuck ; and Fitz-Stephen tells us, that the vaſt foreſt that in his time grew on the north side of London, was the retreat of ſtags, fallow-deer, wild boars, and bulls. Charles I. turned out wild boars in the New Foreſt, Hampſhire ; but they were deſtroyed in the civil wars.</p><p>On the continent the wild boar is hunted with dogs, or killed by ſurpriſe during the night, when the moon ſhines. As he runs ſlowly, leaves a ſtrong odour behind him, and defends himſelf againſt the dogs, and often wounds them dangerouſly, fine hunting dogs are unneceſſafy, and would have their noſe ſpoiled, and acquire a habit of moving ſlowly by hunting him. Maſtiffs, with very little training, are ſufficient. The oldeſt, which are known by the tract of their ſect, ſhould only be attacked : A young boar of three years old is difficult to hunt down ; becauſe he runs very far without stopping. But the older boars do not run far, allow<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0209.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0203"/>
the dogs to run near, and often ſtop to repel them. During the day, he commonly remains in his soil, which is in the moſt ſequeſtrated part of the woods. He comes out in the night in quest of food. In ſummer, when the grain is ripe, it is eaſy to ſurpriſe him among the cultivated fields, which he frequents every night. As ſoon as he is ſlain, the hunters cut off his teſticles, the odour of which is ſo ſtrong, that in a few hours it would infect the whole fleſh. The ſnout of an old boar is the only part that is eſteemed ; but every part of the caſtrated and young boar, not exceeding one year fed, makes delicate eating. The pork of the domeſtic boar is ſtill worſe than that of the wild boar ; and it can only be rendered fit for eating by caſtration and fattening. The ancients caſtrated the young boars which they could carry off from their mothers, and returned them to the woods, where they grew fat, and their pork was much better than that of domeſtic hogs. There are several varieties of the common hog.</p><p>2. The ae <hi rend="italic">thiopicus,</hi> or Ethiopian hog, with ſmall tuſks in the lower jaw, very large ones in the upper, in old boars bending towards the forehead in form of a ſemicircle : no fore teeth : noſe broad, depressed, and almoſt of a horny hardneſs : head very large and broad : beneath each eye a hollow, formed of looſe ſkin, very ſoft and wrinkled ; under theſe a great lobe or wattle, lying almoſt horizontal, broad, flat, and rounded at the end, placed ſo as to intercept the view of any thing below from the animal. Between theſe and the mouth on each side, there is a hard callous protuberance. The mouth is ſmall: ſkin duſky : briſtles diſposed in faſciculi, of about five each ; longeſt between the ears and on the beginning of the back, thinly diſperſed on the reſt of the back. Ears large and ſharp pointed, inside lined with long whitiſh hairs : tail ſlender and flat, not reaching lower than the thighs, and is covered with hairs diſpoſed in ſaſciculi. Body longer, and legs ſhorter, than in the common swine : its whole length 4 feet 9 inches ; height before. 2 feet 2 inches: but in a wild ſtate, it grows to an enormous ſize.—Theſe animals inhabit the hotteſt parts of Africa, from Senegal to Congo, alſo the iſland of Madagaſcar. We know little of their nature ; but they are repreſented as very fierce and ſwift, and that they will not breed with the domeſtic ſow.</p><p>3. The tajassu, pecary, or Mexican hog, with four cutting teeth above, and six below: two tuſks in each jaw ; thoſe in the upper jaw pointing down, and little apparent when the mouth is ſhut ; the others hid : length from noſe to the end of the rump about three feet : head not ſo taper as in common ſwine : ears ſhort and erect : body covered with briſtles, ſtronger than thoſe of the European kind, and more like thoſe of a hedge-hog ; they are duſky, ſurrounded with rings of white ; thoſe on the top of the neck and back are near five inches long, grow ſhorter on the sides; the belly almoſt naked ; from the ſhoulders to the breaſt is a band of white : no tail : on the lower part of the back is a gland, open at the top, diſcharging a fetid ichorous liquor; this has been by miſtake called a <hi rend="italic">navel.—</hi> Inhabits the hotteſt parts of South America, and ſome of the Antilles : lives in the foreſts on the mountains : not fond of mire or marſhy places : leſs fat than the common hog. Theſe animals go in great droves. They are very fierce, and will fight ſtoutly with the beaſts of prey : the jaguar, or American leopard, is their mortal enemy ; often the body of that animal is found with ſeveral of these hogs ſlain in combat. Dogs will scarce attack this animal : if wounded, it will turn on the hunters. They feed on fruits and roots ; alſo on toads and all manner of ſerpents, which they hold with their fore-feet, and ſkin with great dexterity. The fleſh is reckoned very good food ; but all writers agree that the dorſal gland muſt be cut out as ſoon as the animal is killed, or the fleſh will become ſo infected as not to be eatable. The Indian name oſ this ſpecies is <hi rend="italic">paquiras,</hi> from whence ſeems to be derived that of p <hi rend="italic">ecary.</hi> There are more varieties of this species, the <hi rend="italic">tajaſſu minor</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">patera.</hi></p><p>4. The <hi rend="italic">babyrussa,</hi> or Indian hog, with four cutting teeth in the upper, six in the lower jaw ; ten grinders to each jaw ; in the lower jaw two tuſks pointing towards the eyes, and ſtanding near eight inches out of their ſockets; from two ſockets on the outſide of the upper jaw two other teeth, twelve inches long, bending like horns, their ends almoſt touching the forehead: ears ſmall, erect, ſharp pointed : along the back are ſome weak briſtles ; on the reſt of the body only a sort of wool, ſuch as is on the lambs : the tail long, ends in a tuft, and is often twiſted : the body plump and ſquare. Inhabits Buero, a small iſle near Amboina : it is alſo found in Celebes, but neither on the continent of Aſia or Africa; what M. de Buffon takes for it is the Ethiopian boar. They are ſometimes kept tame in the Indian iſles : live in herds: have a very quick ſcent : feed on herbs and leaves of trees ; never ravage gardens like other ſwine : their fleſh well tasted. When purſued and driven to extremities, they ruſh into the ſea, ſwim very well, and even dive, and paſs thus front iſle to iſle. In the foreſts they often reſt their heads, by hooking their upper tuſks on ſome bough. The tuſks, from their form, are useleſs in fight.</p></div></body></text></TEI>