<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>make with the horizon ; and they are also as the thrusts of those rafters to which they are parallel. Therefore, the thrust which any rafter makes in its own direction is as the secant of its elevation.</p><p>The horizontal thrust is the same at all the angles. For if = ftx = <hi rend="italic">my = nt = psr.</hi>  Therefore both walls are, equally pressed out by the weight of the roof. We can find its quantity by comparing it with the load on one of the joints. Thus, QC : CB = sin. ABC : sin. ABft</p><p>BC : BT = rad. : sin. BCT = rad. ; sin. CB6. Therefore, QC : BT = rad. × sin. ABC : sin. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>BA × sin. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>BC.</p><p>It deserves remark, that the lengths of the beams do not affect either the proportion of the load at the different joints, or the position of the rafters. This depends merely on the weights at the angles. If a change of length affects the weight, it indeed affects the form also ; and this is generally the case. For it seldom happens, indeed it never should happen, that the weight on rafters of longer bearing is not greater. The covering alone increases nearly in the proportion of the length of the rafter.</p><p>If the proportion of the weights at B, C, and D is given, as also the position of any two of the lines, the position of all the rest is determined. If the horizontal distances between the angles are all equal, the forces on the different angles are proportional to the verticals drawn on the lines through these angles from the adjoining angle, and the thrusts from the adjoining angles are as the lines which connect them. If the rafters themselves are of equal lengths, the weights at the different angles are as these verticals and as the secants of the angles of elevation of the rafters jointly.</p><p>This proposition is very fruitful in its practical consequences. It is easy to perceive that it contains the whole theory of the construction of arches ; for each stone of an arch may be considered as one of the rafters of this piece of carpentry, since all is kept up by its mere equilibrium. We may have an opportunity in a future article of exhibiting some very elegant and simple solutions of the most difficult cases of this important problem ; and we now proceed to make use of the knowledge we have acquired for the construction of roofs.</p><p>We mentioned by the by a problem which is not unfrequent in practice, to determine the best form of a kirb-roof. M. Couplet of the Royal Academy of Paris has given a solution of it in an elaborate memoir in 1726, occupying several lemmas and theorems.</p><p>Let AE (fig. 11) be the width, and CF the height; it</p><lb/><p>is required to construct a roof ABCDE, whose rafters AB, BC, CD, DE, are all equal, and which shall be in equilibrio.</p><p>Draw CE, and bisect it perpendicularly in H by the line DHG, cutting the horizontal line AE in G. About the centre G, with the distance GE, describe the circle EKC. It must pass through C, because CH is equal to HE and the angles at H are equal. Draw HK parallel to FE, cutting the circumference in K ; draw CK, cutting GH in D ; and join CD, ED. These lines are the rafters of half of the roof required.</p><p>We prove this by showing that the loads at the angles C and D are equal ; for this is the proportion which results from the equality of the rafters, and the extent of surface of the uniform roofing which they are supposed to support. Therefore produce ED till it meet the vertical FC in N ; and having made the side CBA similar to CDE, complete the parallelogram BCDP, and draw DB, which will bisect CP in R, as the horizontal line KH bisects CF in Q. Draw KF, which is evidently parallel to DP. Make CS perpendicular to CF, and equal to FG ; and about S, with the radius SF, describe the circle FKW. It must pass through K, because SF is equal to CG, and CQ = QF. Draw WK, WS, and produce BC, cutting ND in O.</p><p>The angle WKF at the circumference is one half of the angle WSF at the centre, and is therefore equal to WSC or CGF. It is therefore double of the angle CEF or ECS. But ECS is equal to ECD and DCS, and ECD is one half of NDC, and DCS is one half of DCO or CDP. Therefore the angle WKF is equal to NDP, and WK is parallel to ND, and CF is to CW as CP to CN ; and CN is equal to CP. But it has been shown above that CN and CP are as the loads upon D and C. These are therefore equal, and the frame ABCDE is in equilibrio.</p><p>A comparison of this solution with that of M. Couplet will show its great advantage in respect of simplicity and perspicuity ; and the intelligent reader can easily adapt the construction to any proportion between the rafters AB and BC, which other circumstances, such as garret-rooms, &amp;c. may render convenient. The construction must be</p><p>pr) i ∏F</p><p>such that NC may be to CP as CD to---. What</p><p>ever proportion of AB to BC is assumed, the point D' will be found in the circumference of a semicircle fl'D'Λ', whose centre is in the line CE, and having AB : BC = CH' : ΗΈ <hi rend="italic">= ch'</hi>  : Λ<hi rend="sup">,</hi>E. The rest of the construction is simple.</p><p>In buildings which are roofed with slate, tile, or shingles, the circumstance which is most likely to limit the construction is the slope of the upper rafters CB, CD. This must be sufficient to prevent the penetration of rain, and the stripping by the winds. The only circumstance left in our choice in this case is the proportion of the rafters AB and BC. Nothing is easier than making NC to CP in any desired proportion when the angle BCD is given.</p><p>We need not repeat that it is always a desirable thing to form a truss for a roof in such a manner that it shall be in equilibrio. When this is done, the whole force of the struts and braces which are added to it is employed in preserving this form, and no part is expended in unnecessary strains. For we must now observe, that the equilibrium of which we have been treating is always of that kind which we call the tottering, and the roof requires stays, braces, or hanging timbers, to give it stiffness, or keep it in shape. We have also said enough to enable any reader acquainted with the most elementary geometry and mechanics, to compute the transverse strains and the thrusts to which the component parts of all roofs are exposed.</p><p>It only remains now to show the general maxims by which all roofs must be constructed, and thc circumstances which determine their excellence. In doing this we shall be exceedingly brief, and almost content ourselves with ex-</p></body></text></TEI>