<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>out regard to the line of its course. The river generally adheres to the steepest hills, whether they advance into the plain or retire from it. This general feature may be ob-, served over the whole globe. It is divided into compartments by great ranges of mountains ; and it may be observed, that the great rivers hold their course not very far from them, and that their chief feeders come from the other side. In every compartment there is a swell of the low country at a distance from the bounding ridge of mountains ; and on the summit of this swell the principal feeders of the great river have their sources.</p><p>The name <hi rend="italic">valley</hi>  is given with less propriety to these immense regions, and is more applicable to tracts of champaign land which the eye can take in at one view. Even here we may observe a resemblance. It is not always in the very lowest part of this valley that the river has its bed : although the waters of the river flow in a channel below’ its immediate banks, these banks are frequently higher than the grounds at the foot of the hills. This is very distinctly seen in Lower Egypt, by means of the canals which are carried backward from the Nile for accelerating its fertilizing inundations. When the calishes are opened to admit the waters, it is always observed that the districts most remote are the first covered, and it is several days before the immediately adjoining fields partake of the blessing. This is a consequence of that general opinion of nature by which the valleys are formed. The river in its floods is loadcd with mud, which it retains as long as it rolls rapidly along its limited bed, tumbling its waters over and over, and taking up in every spot as much as it deposits : but as soon as it overflows its banks, the very enlargement of its section diminishes the velocity of the water ; and it may be observed still running in the track of its bed with grcat velocity, while the waters on each side are stagnant at a very small distance: therefore the water, on getting over the banks, must deposit the heaviest, the firmest, and even the greatest part of its burden, and must become gradually clearer as it approaches the hills. Thus a gentle slope is given to the valley in a direction which is the reverse of what one would expect. It is, however, almost always the case in wide valleys, especially if the great river comes through a soft country. The banks of the brooks and ditches are observed to be deeper as they approach the river, and the merely superficial drains run backwards from it.</p><p>We have already observed that the enlargement of the bed of a river, in its approach to the sea, is not in proportion to the increase of its waters. This would be the case even if the velocity continued the same ; and, therefore, since the velocity increases in consequence of the greater energy of a large body of water, which we now understand distinctly, a still smaller bed is sufficient for conveying all the water to the sea.</p><p>This general law is broken, how<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ever, in the immediate neighbourhood of the sea ; because in this situation the velocity of the water is checked by the passing flood-tides of the ocean. As the whole waters must still be discharged, they require a larger bed, and the enlargement will be chiefly in width. The sand and mud are deposited when the motion is retarded. The depth of the mouth of the channel is therefore diminished. It must therefore become wider. If this be done on a coast exposed to the force of a regular tide, which carries the waters of the ocean across the mouth of the river, this regular enlargement of the mouth w’ill be the only consequence, and it will generally widen till it washes the foot of the adjoining hills ; but if there be no tide in the sea, or a tide which does not set across the mouth of the river, the sands must be deposited at the sides of the opening, and become additions to the shore, lengthening the mouth of the channel. In this sheltered situation, every trivial circumstance will cause the river to work more on particular parts of the bottom, and deepen the channel there. This keeps the mud suspended in such parts of the channel, and it is not deposited till the stream has shot farther out into the sea. It is deposited on the sides of those deeper parts of the channel, and increases the velocity in them, and thus still farther protracts the deposition. Rivers so situated will not only lengthen their channels, but will divide them, and produce islands at their mouths. A bush, a tree torn up by the roots by a mountain torrent, and floated down the stream, will thus inevitably produce an island ; and rivers in w hich this is common will be continually shifting their mouths. The Mississippi is a most remarkable instance of this. It has a long course through a rich soil, and disembogues itself into the bay of Mexico, in a place w’here there is no<hi rend="italic">passing tide,</hi>  as may be seen by comparing the hours of high water in difterent places. No river that we know’ carries down its stream such numbers of rooted-up trees ; they frequently interrupt the navigation, and render it always dangerous in the night-time. This river is so beset with flats and shifting sands at its mouth, that the most experienced pilots are puzzled ; and it has protruded its channel above fifty miles in the short period that we have known it. The discharge of the Danube is very similar : so is that of the Nile, for it is discharged into a still corner of the Mediterranean. It may now be said to have acquired considerable permanency ; but much of this is owing to human industry, which strips it as much as possible of its subsideable matter. The Ganges, too, is in a situation pretty similar, and exhibits similar phenomena. The Maragnon might be noticed as an exception ; but it is not an exception. It has flowed very far in a level bed, and its waters come pretty clear to Para ; but, besides, there is a strong transverse tide, or rather current, at its mouth, setting to the south-east both during flood and ebb. The mouth of the Po is perhaps the most remarkable of any on the surface of this globe, and exhibits appearances extremely singular. Its discharge is into a sequestered corner of the Adriatic. Though there be a more remarkable tide in this gulf than in any part of the Mediterranean, it is still but trifling, and it either sets directly in upon the mouth of the river or retires straight away from it. The river has many mouths, and they shift prodigiously. There has been a general increase of the land very remarkable. The marshes where Venice now stands were in the Augustan age everywhere penetrable by the fishing-boats, and in tile fifth century could only bear a few’ miserable huts ; now they are covered with crowds of stately buildings. Ravenna, situated on the southernmost mouth of the Po, was, in the Augustan age, at the extremity of a swamp, and the road to it was along the top of an artificial mound, made by Augustus at an immense expense. It was, however, a fine city, containing extensive docks, arsenals, and other massy buildings, being the great military port of the empire, where Augustus laid up his great ships of war. In the Gothic times it became almost the capital of the western empire, and was the seat of government and of luxury. It must therefore be supposed to have every accommodation of opulence, and we cannot doubt of its having paved streets, wharfs, &amp;c. ; so that its wealthy inhabitants were at least walking dryfooted from house to house. But now it is an Italian mile from the sea, and surrounded with vineyards and cultivated fields, and is accessible in every direction. All this must have been formed by depositions from the Po, flowing through Lombardy loaded witll the spoils of the Alps, which were here arrested by the reeds and bulrushes of the marsh. These things arc in common course ; but when wells are dug, we come to the pavements of the ancient city, and these pavements are all on one exact level, and they <hi rend="italic">ore eight feet below the surface of the sea at low water.</hi>  This cannot be ascribed to the subsiding of the ancient city. This would be irregular, and greatest among the heavy</p></body></text></TEI>