<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the soil and magnitude of its section, that neither do its waters during the annual freshes tear up its banks or deepen its bed, nor do they bring down from the high lands materials which they deposit in the channel in times of smaller velocity. Such a river may be said to be in a <hi rend="italic">permanent state,</hi>  to be in <hi rend="italic">conservation,</hi>  or to have <hi rend="italic">stability.</hi>  Let us call this state of a river its regimen, denoting by the word the proper adjustment of the velocity of the stream to the tenacity of the channel. The velocity of its regimen must be the same throughout, because it is this which regulates its action on the bottom, which is the same from its head to the sea. That its bed may have stability, the mean velocity of the current must be constant, notwithstanding the inequality of discharge through its different sections by the brooks which it receives in its course, and notwithstanding the augmentation of its section as it approaches the sea.</p><p>On the other hand, it behoved this exact regimen to commence at the mouth of the river, by the working of the whole body of the river, in concert with the waters of the ocean, which always keep within the same limits, and make the ultimate level invariable. This working will begin to dig the bed, giving it as little breadth as possible : for this working consists chiefly in the efforts of falls and rapid streams, which arise of themselves in every channel which has too much slope. The bottom deepens, and the sides remain very steep, till they are undermined and crumbled down ; and being then diluted in the water, they are carried down the stream and deposited where the ocean checks its speed. The banks crumble down anew, the valley or hollow forms ; but the section, always confined to its bottom, cannot acquire a great breadth, and it retains a good deal of the form of the trapezium formerly mentioned. In this manner does the regimen begin to be established from<hi rend="italic">f</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">e.</hi></p><p>With respect to the next part <hi rend="italic">d e,</hi>  the discharge or produce is diminished by the want of the brook Z <hi rend="italic">e.</hi>  It must take a similar form, but its area will be diminished, in order that its velocity may be the same ; and its mean depth <hi rend="italic">d </hi>being less than in the portion <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  / below, the slope must be greater. Without these conditions we could not have the uniform velocity, which the assumed permanency in an uniform soil naturally supposes. Reasoning after the same manner for all the portions <hi rend="italic">c d,b c,αh, s α,</hi>  we see that the regimen will be successively established in them, and that the slope necessary for this purpose will be greater as w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>e approach the river head. The vertical section or profile of the course of the river<hi rend="italic">s a b c d ef</hi>  will therefore resemble the line SABCDEF which is sketched above, having its different parts variously inclined to the horizontal line HF.</p><p>Such is the process of nature to be observed in every river on the surface of the globe. It long appeared a kind of puzzle to the theorists ; and it was this observation of the increasing, or at least this continued velocity with smaller slope, as the rivers increased by the addition of their tributary streams, which caused Guglielmini to have recourse to his new principle, the energy of deep waters. We have now seen in what this energy consists. It is only a greater quantity of motion remaining in the middle of a great stream of water after a quantity has been retarded by the sides and bottom ; and we see clearly, that since the addition of a new and perhaps an equal stream does not occupy a bed of double surface, the proportion of the retardations to the remaining motion must continually diminish as a river increases by the addition of new streams. If therefore the slope were not diminished, the regimen would be destroyed, and the river would dig up its channel. We have a full confirmation of this in the many works which have been executed on the Po, which runs with rapidity through a rich and yielding soil. About the year 1600 the waters of the Panaro, a very considerable river, were added to the Po Grande ; and although it brings along with it in its freshes a vast quantity of sand and mud, it has greatly deepened the whole Tronco di Venezia from the confluence to the sea. This point was clearly ascertained by Manfredi about the year 1720, when the inhabitants of the valleys adjacent were alarmed by the project of bringing in the waters of the Rheno, which then ran through the Ferrarese. Their fears were overcome, and the Po Grande continues to deepen its channel every day, with a prodigious advantage to the navigations ; and there are several extensive marshes which now drain off by it, after having been for ages under water : and it is to be particularly remarked, that the Rheno is the foulest river in its freshes of any in that country. We insert tlris remark, because it may be of great practical utility, as pointing out a method of preserving and even improving the depth of rivers or drains in flat countries, which is not obvious, but rather appears improper ; but it is strictly conformable to a true theory, and to the operations of nature, which never fails to adjust every thing so as to bring about an equilibrium. Whatever the declivity of the country may have been originally, the regimen begins to be settled at the mouths of the rivers, and the slopes are diminished in succession as we recede from the coast. The original slopes inland may have been much greater ; but they will (when busy nature has completed her work) be left somewhat, and only so much greater, that the velocity may be the same notwithstanding the diminution of the section and mean depth.</p><p>Freshes will disturb this methodical progress relative only to the successive permanent additions ; but their effects chiefly accelerate the deepening of the bed, and the diminution of the slope, by augmenting the velocity during their continuance. But when the regimen of the permanent additions is once established, the freshes tend chiefly to widen the bed, without greatly deepening it : for the aquatic plants, which have been growing and thriving during the peaceable state of the river, are now laid along, but not swept aw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ay, by the freshes, and protect the bottom from their attacks ; and the stones and gravel, which must have been left bare in a course of years, working on the soil, will also collect in the bottom, and greatly augment its power of resistance ; and even if the floods should have deepened the bottom some small matter, some mud will be deposited as the velocity of the freshes diminishes, and this will remain till the next flood.</p><p>We have supposed the soil uniform throughout the whole course ; this seldom happens ; therefore the circumstances which insure permanency, or the regimen of a river, may be very different in its different parts and in different rivers. We may say in general, that the farther that the regimen has advanced up the stream in any river, the more slowly will it convey its waters to the sea.</p><p>There are some general circumstances in the motion of rivers which it will he proper to take notice of just now, that they may not interrupt our more minute. examination of their mechanism ; and their explanations will then occur of themselves as corollaries of the propositions which we shall endeavour to demonstrate.</p><p>In a valley of small width the river always occupies the lowest part of it ; and it is observed, that this is seldom in the middle of the valley, and is nearest to that side on w hich the slope from the higher grounds is steepest, and this with</p></body></text></TEI>