<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pace even with the surface of our cultivated grounds, which it embellishes and fertilizes.</p><p>We may with safety proceed on the supposition, that the force necessary for overcoming the resistance arising from a rebound is as the square of the velocity ; and it is reasonable to suppose it proportional to the square of the sine of the angle of incidence, and this for the reasons given for adopting this measure of the general <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Resistance of Fluids.</hi></hi>  It cannot, however, claim a greater confidence here than in that application ; and it has been shown in that article with what uncertainty and limitations it must be received. We leave it to our readers to adopt either this or the simple ratio of the sines, and shall abide by the duplicate ratio with Du Buat, because it appears by his experiments that this law is very exactly observed in tubes in inclinations not exceeding 40° ; whereas it is in these small angles that the application to the general resistance of fluids is most in fault. But the correction is very simple if this value shall be found erroneous. There can be no doubt that the force necessary for overcoming the resistance will increase as the number of rebounds. Therefore we may express</p><p>the resistance, in general, by the formula <hi rend="italic">r = --—— ;</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">m</hi></p><p>where <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  is the resistance, V the mean velocity of the stream, sin. I the sine of the angle of incidence, <hi rend="italic">n</hi>  the number of equal rebounds (that is, having equal angles of incidence), and <hi rend="italic">m </hi>is a number to be determined by experiment. Du Buat made many experiments on the resistance occasioned by the bendings of pipes, none of which differed from the result of the above formula above one part in twelve ; and he concludes, that the resistance to one bend may be estimated at V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>1</p><p>- gθθθ—∙ The experiment was in this form. A pipe of one</p><p>inch diameter, and ten feet long, was formed with ten rebounds of 36° each. A head of water was applied to it, which gave the water a velocity of six feet per second. Another pipe of the same diameter and length, but without any bendings, was subjected to a pressure of a head of water, which was increased till the velocity of efflux was also six feet per second. The additional head of water was 5-⅛ inches. Another of the same diameter and length, having one bend of 24° 34', and running eighty-five inches per second, was compared with a straight pipe having the same velocity, and the difference of the heads of water was -⅛j of an inch. A computation from these two experiments will give</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">2</hi> sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> I</p><p>the above result, or, in English measure, <hi rend="italic">r = -    </hi>— <hi rend="sup">ver</hi>y</p><p>nearly. It is probable that this measure of the resistance is too great ; for the pipe was of uniform diameter even in the bends : whereas, in a river properly formed, where the regimen is exact, the capacity of the section of the bend is increased.</p><p>The application of this theory to inclined tubes and to open streams is very obvious, and very legitimate and safe. Let AB (fig. 19) be the whole height of the reservoir AB1K, and BC the horizontal length of a pipe, containing any number of rebounds, equal or unequal, but all regular, that is, constructed according to the conditions formerly mentioned. The whole head of</p><p>water should be conceived as</p><p>performing, or as divided into</p><p>portions which perform, three</p><p>different offices. One portion,</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">t</hi></p><p>AD =-— , impels the water in-o09</p><p>to the entry of the pipe with the</p><p>velocity with which it really</p><p>moves in it; another portion</p><p>EB is in equilibrio with the</p><p>resistances arising from the mere length of the pipe ex</p><p>panded into a straight line ; and the third portion 1 serves to overcome the resistance of the bends. If, the fore, we draw the horizontal line BC, and, taking the p BC out of its place, put it in the position DH, with mouth C in H, so that DH is equal to BC, the water v have the same velocity in it that it had before. I greater simplicity of argument, we may suppose that wl the pipe was inserted at B, its bends lay all in a horizon plane, and that when it is inserted at D, the plane in whi all its bends lie slopes only in the direction DH, and is p∣ pendicular to the plane of the figure. We repeat it, t water will have the same velocity in the pipes BC and D and the resistances will be overcome. If we now prolo the pipe DH towards L to any distance, repeating contin ally the same bendings in a series of lengths, each equal DH, the motion will be continued with the velocity con sponding to the pressure of the column AD ; because t declivity of the pipe is augmented in each length equal DH, by a quantity precisely sufficient for overcoming all t resistances in that length ; and the true slope in these cas is BE + ED, divided by the expanded length of the pi BC or DH.</p><p>The analogy which we were enabled to establish betwe the uniform motion or the train of pipes and of open strean entitles us now to say, that when a river has bendin; which are regularly repeated at equal intervals, its slope compounded of the slope which is necessary for overcomiι the resistance of a straight channel of its whole expand∣ length, agreeably to the formula for uniform motion, and the slope which is necessary for overcoming the resistnn∣ arising from its bending alone.</p><p>Thus, let there be a river which, in the expanded cour of 6000 fathoms, has 10 elbows, each of which has 30° rebound ; and let its mean velocity be 20 inches in a s cond. If we should learn its whole slope in this 6000 f thorns, we must first find (by the formula of uniform m tion) the slope s which will produce the velocity of <hi rend="italic">i </hi>inches in a straight river of this length, section, and met depth. Suppose this to be 5-r⅜∏jj&gt; or 20 inches, in this who</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">λ V® sin? I</hi></p><p>length. We must then find by the formula —&lt;¼yθ<hi rend="sub">t</hi>j— <hi rend="sup">t</hi>'</p><p>slope necessary for overcoming the resistance of ten r bounds of 30° each. This we shall find to be 6y inch in the 6000 fathoms. Therefore the river must have slope of 261 inches in 6000 fathoms, or yg½(yit &gt; <hi rend="sup">a</hi>∏d d slope will produce the same velocity which 20 inches, 3T⅛ira&gt; <hi rend="sup">w0u</hi>lfi do in a straight-running river of tile san length.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">part ιι.—practical inferences.</hi></p><p>Having thus established a theory of a most importa part of hydraulics, which may be confided in as a just r presentation of nature’s procedure, we shall apply it to tl examination of the chief results of every thing which a has contrived for limiting the operations of nature, or m∣ difying them so as to suit our particular views. Trustir to the detail which we have given of the connecting priι ciples, and the chief circumstances which co-operate producing the ostensible effect ; and supposing that su&lt; of our readers as are interested in this subject will n think it too much trouble to make the applications in tl same detail ; we shall content ourselves with merely poin ing out the steps of the process, and showing their foui dation in the theory itself; and frequently, in place of tl direct analysis which the theory enables us to employ fi the solution of the problems, we shall recommend a pr&lt; cess of approximation by trial and correction, sufficient accurate, and more within the reach of practical engineeι</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>