<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and the differentiation in respect of ∙ψ (supposing p constant) gives</p><p>„ ,    2 tan. ∙ψ</p><p>tan. 2 ∙ψ = -τ--—„ -<hi rend="sub">1</hi></p><p><hi rend="sup">τ</hi> 1 — tan.- ∙ψ</p><p>_    2 E cos. p + 2 F sin. ρ</p><p>A cos.<hi rend="sup">s</hi>p + B sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  p — C + 2 D cos. p sin. p'</p><p>On eliminating ∙ψ from these two equations, there results an equation of the following form, in which κ = tan. p, and <hi rend="italic">e,f, g, h,</hi>  are co-efficients depending upon the quantities A, B, C, D, E, F, viz.</p><p>0 = e +∕a + <hi rend="italic">gu<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + hu<hi rend="sup">3</hi>.</hi></p><p>This being a cubic equation, must have at least one real root. But it is easy to see, from the nature of the thing, that all the roots are real ; for if there be one axis for which the moment of inertia is a <hi rend="italic">maximum,</hi>  there must evidently be a second, in respect of which it is a <hi rend="italic">minimum,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">vice versa.</hi>  Hence the equation must have two real roots, and therefore, by the theory of cubic equations, all the roots are real. We are therefore led to this very important conclusion, that through any point of every solid body, however irregular in its form, there may be drawn a system of three axes, such that the differential co-efficient of the moment of inertia in respect of each of them is nothing. In respect of one of these, the moment is a maximum, in respect of another, it is a minimum, and though, in respect of the third it is neither a maximum nor a minimum, it is still such that its value is not altered by a small change in the position of the axis. According to the definition in (19), these are the <hi rend="italic">principal axes</hi>  of the body.</p><p>22.    It would be difficult, in general, to determine the position of the principal axes from the cubic equation found above ; but they possess certain properties, by means of which they may be readily found in almost every case of practical application. On comparing the two equations for tan. ∙ψ and tan. 2-ψ (21), with the expressions for z", y*, z" (20), it will be seen that the first is identical with 2 cos. -ψ <hi rend="italic">fri'ιf'dm,</hi>  and the second with — 2 <hi rend="italic">fx"z"dm ; whence fx"y"dm</hi>  = 0, and <hi rend="italic">fxyz"dm</hi>  = 0 ; and it follows, that if <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  be taken in one of the principal axes, we have, in respect of that <hi rend="italic">nuis, fxydm = 0, fxzdm</hi>  = 0, or the quantities denoted by D and E respectively vanish.</p><p>23.    From this it follow’s, that if all the matter in a body of uniform density be symmetrically disposed about any line, that line is one of the principal axes of rotation (for if <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  be taken in the axis of symmetry, then to every element whose co-ordinates are <hi rend="italic">x, y,</hi>  there corresponds another element whose co-ordinates are <hi rend="italic">x, — y,</hi>  whence <hi rend="italic">fxydm </hi>— 0) ; therefore, in the case of symmetrical figures, the position of one of the principal axes is known, and the positions of the other two are thence readily determined by means of the two equations(2l). On making D = 0, E = 0, the first of these equations gives</p><p>(A — B) sin. <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  cos. <hi rend="italic">φ —</hi>  F cos. ® tan. -ψ = 0, whence cos. <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  = 0, and sin. <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  = 1 ; or <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  = 90°. Substituting this value of <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  in the second of the equations (21), and making at the same time D = 0, E = 0, we get tan. 2+ = 2F ÷ (B ∙—C) ; or 2∙ψ is the angle which has 2F -j- (B — C) for its tangent. Hence the angle ∙ψ has a double value, one corresponding to FOG, and the other to FOG + 90°.</p><p>24.    Hence also it appears, that when one principal axis OX is determined, two others may be found having the same property of maximum or minimum, and, by reason of <hi rend="italic">φ —</hi>  90°, these axes are both in a plane perpendicular to OX. As this conclusion holds good with respect to each of the three axes, it follows that the three principal axes are at right angles to each other, and also, since <hi rend="italic">fxydm = </hi>0, and <hi rend="italic">fxzdm =</hi>  0, that <hi rend="italic">fyzdm</hi>  = 0. We have therefore, in respect of the principal axes, the three equations</p><p>D = <hi rend="italic">fxydm</hi>  = 0, E = <hi rend="italic">fxzdm</hi>  = 0, F = <hi rend="italic">fyzdm</hi>  = 0.</p><p>If the origin of the co-ordinates is placed at the centre of gravity, we have likewise</p><p><hi rend="italic">fxdm ■=. 0,fydm = 0,fzdm</hi>  = 0, by the well-known property of the centre of gravity.</p><p>25.    By means of these equations, the proposition in (20) is considerably simplified when the three axes for which the momenta are respectively given are principal axes. Let</p><p>OX,    OY, OZ (fig. 6) be the three principal axes passing through O, then D = 0, E = 0, F = 0, and the equation (20) for the moment, in respect of the axis OG, becomes</p><p><hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = A (sin? <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  + cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi><hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>∙ψ)</p><p>+ B (cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> p + sin.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> ρ sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> ∙ψ) + C cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi> ∙ψ. Suppose the given moments in respect of the principal axes to be respectively M∙o<hi rend="sup">5</hi>, M∙A<hi rend="sup">5</hi>, M∙c<hi rend="sup">2</hi> ; then, from the values of A, B, C (20) we have M∙α<hi rend="sup">2</hi> = B + C, M∙A<hi rend="sup">5</hi> = A</p><p>+ C, M∙c<hi rend="sup">2</hi> = A + B, whence</p><p>A=¼M(i<hi rend="sup">l</hi> + c<hi rend="sup">,</hi>-β<hi rend="sup">s</hi>),B = i M (α<hi rend="sup">5</hi> +<hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi>  — c<hi rend="sup">2</hi>),</p><p>C = ⅜(α<hi rend="sup">2</hi> + c<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>),</p><p>on substituting which in the above equation, we get <hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = M (α<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  p cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  ∙ψ+A<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  p cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  ∙ψ +<hi rend="italic">c<hi rend="sup">t</hi></hi>  sin.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  ∙ψ). If we now refer the new axis OG to the co-ordinates OX,</p><p>OY,    OZ, and make the angle XOG = &lt;x, YOG = <hi rend="italic">β,</hi>  ZOG <hi rend="italic">= y,</hi>  and observe that because the two planes XOF and FOG are at right angles, cos. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  = cos. p cos. ∙ψ, cos. <hi rend="italic">β = </hi>sin. p cos. ∙ψ, cos. <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  = sin. ∙ψ, the equation becomes</p><p><hi rend="italic">fridm —</hi>  M (α<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  α + A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">β</hi>  + c<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">γ).</hi></p><p>It is to be remarked, that as the co-ordinates are rectangular, cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi>  + cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi><hi rend="italic">β</hi>  + cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  y = 1, so that the position of OG is determined by any two of these angles. If w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>e therefore suppose the moments in respect of two of the principal axes to be equal, for example, if β<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  =<hi rend="italic">b<hi rend="sup">i</hi>,</hi>  the formula for the moment in respect of OG becomes</p><p><hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = M∙α<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  (1 — cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi><hi rend="italic">γ)</hi>  + M∙c<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi><hi rend="italic">y.</hi></p><p>Now when <hi rend="italic">y =</hi>  90°, that is, when OG lies in the plane XOY, then <hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = M∙α<hi rend="sup">2</hi>. Hence, if the moments in respect of the axes OX and OY be equal, the moment will be the same for every axis passing through O, contained in the plane XOY.</p><p>When the moments in respect of the three principal axes are equal, that is, when <hi rend="italic">a- = tri —</hi>  c<hi rend="sup">5</hi>, then</p><p><hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = M<hi rend="sup">-</hi>α<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  (cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">a</hi>  + cos.<hi rend="sup">5</hi><hi rend="italic">β</hi>  + cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">y)</hi>  = M<hi rend="sup">-</hi>α<hi rend="sup">5</hi>, so that the moment is the same in respect of any axis whatever which passes through O. Thus it appears, that for every point of a solid body there are either three principal axes of rotation only, or else an infinite number.</p><p>26.    These conclusions are obviously true in the case of some simple figures. Thus, in the spheroid of revolution, the moments are equal in respect of every diameter which lies in the plane of the equator ; and in the sphere they are the same in respect of any diameter whatever, the bodies being always supposed homogeneous. The existence of three principal axes in every body was first noticed by Segner in 1755, but demonstrated for the first time by Albert Euler, in a memoir which received the prize of the Academy of Sciences of Paris in 1760.</p><p>27.    Having established these general propositions respecting the moments of inertia and principal axes of bodies endowed with a rotatory motion, we now proceed to consider more particularly the rotation of a solid body about a fixed axis.</p><p>When a force is impressed on a body which can only move round a fixed axis, the difference between the motion which actually takes place, and that which would take place if the body were free, is evidently owing to the connexion which its parts have with the axis, and to the action of the points of support upon the axis. This action must be viewed in the light of another external force, such that, if combined with the force impressed on the body, it would produce in the body unconnected with any fixed points the motion which actually takes place.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>