<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cal, or perhaps mythical, that it is utterly in vain to attempt to extract from it any thing like real history. It may have been merely meant to represent the period of the establishment of forms of laws and religion, which naturally follows that of founding a city and collecting a people. And as all ancient lawgivers assumed divine authority for the sanction of their institutions, so the Roman lawgiver is said to have obtained the instructions of Egeria. The legend is too beautiful to be lost, though too imaginative to be believed ; and we turn reluctantly from its evanescent loveliness, to the consideration of matter of a harsher mould.</p><p>An interregnum again followed the death of Numa. At length Tullus Hostilius, a man of Latin or Romish extraction, was chosen by the <hi rend="italic">curiœ ;</hi>  and his election having been sanctioned by the auspices, he, like his predecessor, submitted to the <hi rend="italic">comitia curiata</hi>  the laws which conferred upon him full regal power. The new king was more desirous of military renown, than of the less dazzling fame which may be gained by cultivating the arts of peace. An opportunity was soon offered for indulging his warlike disposition. Plundering incursions had been made into each others’ territories by the borderers of the two states of Rome and Alba. Both nations sent ambassadors at the same time to demand redress. The Roman ambassadors had private orders from Tullus to be peremptory in their demands, and to limit their stay within the stated period of thirty days. They did so, and receiving no immediate satisfaction, returned to Rome. In the mean time, Tullus amused the Alban embassy by shews and banquets, till, when they opened their commission, he had it in his power to answer, that he had already in vain sought redress from Alba, and that now they must prepare for the events of a war, the blame of originating which was chargeable upon them. By this device Tullus thought to avoid the guilt of being the aggressor, and to secure the favour of the gods by the justice of his cause.</p><p>Under the command of Cluilius, the Albans sent a powerful army against Rome, and encamped about five miles from the city. There Cluilius died; and the Albans elected Mettius Fufetius in his stead. Tullus Hostilius, at the head of the Roman army, now drew near the Albans. But when the two armies were ready for a general engagement, Mettius, the Alban general, proposed to save the effusion of blood, by committing the fortune of the war to the valour of certain champions selected from either side. To this proposal Tullus agreed. It so happened that there were in each army three brothers, each three the children of one birth, whose mothers also were sisters, though their fathers belonged to different nations. The three Romans were named Horatii, the three Albans Curiatii. These youthful warriors were chosen to be the champions of their respective nations, and immediately prepared for the combat. It was agreed, that by the issue of this contest should be determined the dominion or subjection of each people. The two armies were drawn up in battle array, each on their own side of the boundary line that divided their territories. The young combatants advanced, and met on the very line. The combat began, and was sustained for some time with equal skill, courage, and ardour, while the two armies gazed on the eventful struggle with the suspended breath of intense anxiety. At length two of the Horatii fell at the feet of their antagonists ; a sight which called forth loud shouts of joy from the Albans, while the Romans remained quivering with suspense for the fate of their remaining champion, and the freedom of their country. Horatius was still unhurt, whilst the three Curiatii were all severely wounded. Believing himself more than a match for each singly, he feigned a flight to divide them. They pursued with unequal strength and speed, and were separated to considerable distances from each other. On a sudden he turned, rushed on the enemy nearest him, and slew him at a blow. With equal impetuosity he assailed and killed the second, while the third was hastening to render his brother aid. There was now but one combatant on either side, yet it could no longer be called a battle. Faint, exhausted, and dispirited, the third of tlle Curiatii sunk beneath the vigorous arm of the victorious Roman, who thus at once avenged his brothers, and won for his country the sovereign sway.</p><p>As the Romans were returning in triumph to the city, Horatius bearing the triple spoils, they were met at the Ca-penian gate by his sister, who had been betrothed to one of the Curiatii. When she beheld the bloody mantle of her lover, which she had wrought witll her own hands, borne aloft by her brother, she burst into loud lamentations, flinging loose her scattered locks. Horatius, enraged at her untimely grief and outcry, drew his sword and pierced her to the heart, exclaiming, “ So perish the Roman woman that shall bewail a foe.” For this tierce deed, Horatius was by the judges condemned to death. But he appealed to the people, and his father defended him, saying, that if his daughter had not deserved to die, he would himself have punished his son, in virtue of his own authority as a father. The people refused to stain the victory which Horatius had achieved for his country by shedding the blood of the conqueror, and therefore spared his life, but caused him to undergo the semblance of capital punishment, and perform certain expiating sacrifices and rites, which thenceforth became hereditary in the Horatian family.</p><p>Notwithstanding the agreement which had been entered into between the Romans and the Albans, the latter were unwilling to forfeit their national independence without an additional struggle. This, however, they were desirous to avoid provoking single-handed. They accordingly encouraged the people of Fidenæ to revolt, hy giving them secret promises of assistance. Tullus Hostilius immediately levied a Roman army, and summoned the Albans to his aid. The two armies met, the Veientes being drawn up opposite to the Romans, and the Fidenates confronting the Albans. When the battle began, Mettius Fufetius, the Alban leader, wanted courage and decision to fulfil his own treacherous pledge ; he neither joined the Romans nor the Fidenates, but drawing his men off from the conflict, stood aloof, to watch the event and act accordingly. His defection struck a temporary panic into the Romans, which was speedily allayed by the bravery and skill of Tullus ; and his remaining aloof caused distrust in the Fidenates, who finally fled before the vigorous onset of their antagonists. Tullus gained a complete victory ; and concealing his knowledge of the treachery of Mettius, next day called an assembly of his whole army. The Albans came unarmed, and arrived first. The Romanscame next, wearing, as they had been directed, their swords hid beneath their mantles, and at a signal surrounded the Albans. Tullus then denounced the treachery of Mettius, and commanded him to be torn asunder by two chariots of four horses, as his mind had been divided between the Romans and the Fidenates in the battle. It was then decreed that Alba should be razed to the ground, and the whole Alban people removed to Rome, to prevent the possibility of future strife. Not only the walls of Alba, but every human habitation, was totally demolished, and the temples of the gods alone left standing in solitary majesty amid the ruins.</p><p>But though Tullus had thus put an end to the separate existence of Alba, he did not reduce its inhabitants to slavery. He assigned them habitations on the Caelian hill, which had formerly been possessed by the followers of the Etruscan Lucumo, Caeles Vibenna. Those who had been of patrician rank at Alba were allowed to retain the same rank at Rome, and a new tribe was formed, called the Luceres. The construction and numbers of this tribe were the same as those of the other two ; so that the entire senate, composed of the beads of houses of the three tribes,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>