<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>able him readily to trace back their steps to the most elementary principles ; which is scarcely possible in any of the works of the most modem school of analysis. Professor Robison, however, seems rarely to have cultivated the higher mathematics for their own sake only, or any further than as they could be applied to the study of the phenomena of nature, or to the practice of the combinations of art : in fact, without some such limitation, there would be no track to guide us in the pathless regions of quantity and number, and their endless relations and functions. But besides the utility of the pure mathematics as a branch of early education, in exercising and fortifying the powers of the mind, it is impossible to foresee with certainty <hi rend="italic">how much</hi>  of mathematics may be wanted by the natural philosopher in any given investigation ; and Professor Robison, as well as many others of his countrymen, would certainly have been the better for the possession of <hi rend="italic">a little more,</hi>  as the author of the criticisms in the Imperial Review has already had occasion to remark.</p><p>Philosophical Magazine, xiii. ; Dr Gleig, in Antijacobin Magazine, xi. 1802; Stark’s <hi rend="italic">Biographia Scotica ;</hi>  Aikin’s General Biography, viii. Lond. 1813, 4to; Playfair, in Edinb. Trans, vii. 1815, p. 495; Chalmers’s Biographical Dictionary, xxv. Lond. 1816, 8vo.    (l.  L.)</p><p>ROBOR ANTS, in <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy,</hi>  medicines which strengthen the parts, and give new vigour to the constitution.</p><p>ROCAB, a small seaport of Hadramaut, in Arabia, on the Indian Ocean, thirty miles south-south-west of Sahar.</p><p>ROCHDALE, a market-town of the county of Lancaster, in the hundred of Salford, 197 miles from London and twelve from Manchester. It is situated in a fine valley on the river Roche, and is overlooked by the church, which stands on an eminence ascended by 118 steps. The hills around it abound in excellent coal. The chief occupation is the manufacture of flannels and other woollen goods. The parish is large, and contains twelve townships, two of which are in the west riding of Yorkshire. The population of the ten in Lancashire amounted in 1801 to 29,954, in 1811 to 45,227, in 1821 to 48,112, and in 1831 to 58,441 ; that of the Yorkshire part amounted in 1831 to 15,997. By the parliamentary reform bill this town has received the privilege of electing one member to the House of Commons, but it has no municipal corporation.</p><p>ROCHE-BERNARD, a town of France, in the department of Morbihan, and arrondissement of Vannes. It is situated on the river Vilaine, and contains 1380 inhabitants ; but within the parish are 6670 persons, who are chiefly employed in making flaxen thread and linen goods.</p><p>ROCHECHOUART, an arrondissement of the department of the Upper Vienne, in France. It extends over 237 square miles, comprehends five cantons, divided into twenty-nine communes, and in 1836 contained 48,818 inhabitants. The capital is the town of the same name, on the banks of the river Grenne. It contains 4123 inhabitants. Long. 0. 45. E. Lat. 45. 43. N. t</p><p>ROCHEFORT, an arrondissement of the department of the Lower Charente, in France, which extends over 295 square miles. It comprises four cantons, divided into forty-two communes, and in 1836 contained 51,727 inhabitants. The capital is a city of the same name, about six miles from the mouth of the river Charente. The harbour is convenient and secure, and constantly contains many men of war. The wharfs are very well contrived, and vessels can take in or discharge the guns and other stores with great facility. It was first made a naval arsenal by Louis XIV. The city is surrounded with walls, and the harbour defended by strong forts. It is a regular, well-built city, with broad streets, containing five churches, a naval hospital, a school of navigation, and fine docks. There were, in 1836, 15,441 inhabitants, besides a garrison in the handsome barracks. There are establishments for making china, for refining sugar, and manufactories of ropes, cables, and sailcloth. Long. 0.2.54. W. Lat 45. 16. 10. N.</p><p>ROCHEFOUCAULT, Francis Duke de la, prince of Marsillac, governor of Poitou, was born in 1603. He was the son of Francis, the first duke of Rochefoucault, and was distinguished equally by his courage and his wit. These shining qualities endeared him to all the nobility at court, who were ambitious of decorating themselves at once with the laurels of Mars and of Apollo. He wrote two excellent works; the one a book of Maxims, which, Voltaire says, has contributed more than any thing else to form the taste of the French nation ; and the other, Memoirs of the Regency of Queen Anne of Austria. It was partly at the instigation of the beautiful duchess de Longueville, to whom he had long been attached, that the duke de Rochefoucault engaged in the civil wars, in which he signalized himself, particularly at the battle of St Antoine. After the civil wars were ended, he thought of nothing but enjoying the calm pleasures of friendship and literature. His house became the rendezvous of every person of genius in Paris and Versailles. Racine, Boileau, and Savigné, found in his conversation charms which they sought for in vain elsewhere. He was not, however, with all his elegance and genius, a member of the French Academy. The necessity of making a public speech on the day of his reception was the only cause that he did not claim admittance. This nobleman, with all the courage he had displayed upon various critical occasions, and with his superiority of birth and understanding over the common run of men, did not think himself capable of facing an audience to utter only four lines in public, without being out of countenance. He died at Paris in 1680, aged sixty-eight, leaving behind him a character which has been variously drawn by those who during his life were proud of his friendship.</p><p>ROCHELLE, an arrondissement of the department of the Lower Charente, in France, extending over 310 square miles. It comprehends seven cantons, divided into fifty-five communes, and in 1836 contained 78,797 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name, the seat of the departmental government and of the courts of law. It is on the sea-shore, is strongly fortified, and has a convenient and secure harbour defended by two forts. It is the seat of a bishop, has a cathedral, one Protestant and five Catholic churches, and in the year 1836 had 14,857 inhabitants, who are traders in wine, brandy, salt, and other domestic products, and in all kinds of colonial articles. It is celebrated for its long siege when held by the Protestants in 1628, which was continued for thirteen months, and was attended with dreadful sufferings. Long. 1.14.17. W. Lat. 46.9. 33. N.</p><p>ROCHESTER, an ancient city in the county of Kent, thirty miles from London. It is commonly supposed to have been founded by the ancient Britons. In the time of the Romans it was one of their military stations, but did not attain any great celebrity until more than a century after the arrival of the Saxons, who in the reign of King Ethel-bert, constituted it the seat of a bishop, and it was considered as a most important military station. By the Britons it was known under the name of <hi rend="italic">Dourbrys ;</hi>  tile Romans called it <hi rend="italic">Durohrivœ,</hi>  which the Saxons changed to <hi rend="italic">Rοflcαster,</hi>  from which its present name has been derived. It is situated on the river Medway, a stream which, rising in the centre of Kent, becomes navigable at Maidstone, and increases, till, near Rochester, it is affected by the tides, which reach it from the Thames at the Nore. At Rochester is the first bridge over that fine stream. This bridge, built in the reign of King John, with the exception of the bridges in London, was long deemed superior to any other in the kingdom in height, strength, and elegance. It consists of eleven arches, three of which have been rebuilt, and the whole, by modern improvement, widened and beautified, and ornamented with balustrades, panels, and bold copings.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>