<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the supposed conditions of his emancipation from the Bastille, orthe ludicrous concatenation of mischances which beset the luckless inmates ofthe Inn in Flanders “ doing or suffering.” Some scenes of this sort, in which Fielding enters into competition with Smollett, such as those at the Inn at Upton, are among the least successful in his novels. The effort to raise the waters, the malice prepense in the preparation of the comic machinery, is too obvious ; and after all, though he creates abundance of confusion, he raises but few smiles.</p><p>In another quality, though he has but rarely availed himself of his powers in this respect, Smollett far surpassed Fielding ; we mean in his power of exciting the emotions of terror,orthe sublime. From scenes ofthis kind, Fielding, knowing the prosaic turn of his own mind, and the limits of his invention, kept at a respectful distance; Smollett, who felt within himself the spirit of a poet, has occasionally ventured upon them, and with complete success. The robber scene in the old woman’s hut in <hi rend="italic">Count Fathom,</hi>  though often imitated since, still remains one of the most impressive and agitating night pieces of its kind ; and the sublimity of the situation on ship board, where Random sits chained to the poop during an engagement, covered with the blood and brains of the wounded, and screaming in delirium, has been often pointed out.</p><p>The morality of Smollett and Fielding is nearly on a par ; with this difference, that the slight dash of generosity which is infused into the blackguardism of Tom Jones, while it renders him more natural, makes him at the same time more dangerous than the selfish and often ruffianly heroes of Smollett ; whom we despise or dislike, even while laughing at the cruel frolics in which they indulge. The heroes of the latter are mere animals, good-natured or savage, as the fit strikes them ; the heroines, with the exception perhaps of Aurelia Darnel in <hi rend="italic">Sir Lancelot Greaves,</hi>  tbe weakest of Smol let’s works, have been justly described as objects rather of appetite than affection. In regard, indeed, to any thing like purity ofmorals, or gentlemanly feeling, the inferiority both of Smollett and Fielding to Richardson is obvious. Richardson sometimes mistook his means, but his aim was certainly always moral. On the contrary, both the theory and the practice of the justice were latitudinarian ; and Smollett, though in real life a man of pure morals, had a boundless toleration in fiction for certain vices ; for most, indeed, which did not imply want of spirit, courage, or pecuniary generosity.</p><p>In the unity of conception and coherence of incident which the plot of the novel, though more pliable than that of the drama demands, Fielding, in his two principal works (for <hi rend="italic">JosephAηdrews</hi>  was merely aparody on Richardson<hi rend="sup">,</hi>sPα∞e∕α) has a great advantage over Smollett, whose plots indeed in general scarcely deserve the name, being simply a series of strange accidents, odd rencontres, tricks and frolics, making little or no progress towards theonlycatastrophewhichSmol-lett seems to have in view, namely, the marriage of his hero. In his<hi rend="italic">Roderick Random, Peregrine Pickle,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Count Fathom,</hi>  Smollett adopted the easy inartificial plan of <hi rend="italic">Gil Bias, </hi>in which we arc carried through a succession of scenes where the personages are constantly changing, and those who take part in the close of the story, are quite different from those by whom we are surrounded at its commencement. Fielding, on the contrary, both in his <hi rend="italic">Tom Jones</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Amelia,</hi>  is singularly attentive to regularity of plan, and to the dexterous evolution and winding up of his plot, which he regarded as of vital importance. From the very commencement we perceive that he keeps his conclusion clearly in view, “ and sees as from a tower the end of all.” From this attention to symmetry, and tendency of all the incidents towards the catastrophe, his best work has been not inaptly termed a prose epic ; it is at all events a happy accommodation of the principles of the epic, so far as they could be rendered applicable, to the manner of the novel. One exception ought perhaps to be made from this remark on the</p><lb/><p>imperfection of Smollett’s plots, in favour of that of <hi rend="italic">Humphrey Clinker,</hi>  in which the plot, though not of much art, is naturally evolved, and a quiet little family romance is gracefully combined with the usual gallery of oddities which Smollett never fails to lay before us. In all respects, this is the most pleasing of his performances. While Lesmahago may rank with the very best of his extravagances, there is more of character and less of caricature in the testy, yet kind-hearted, Matthew Bramble “ frosty but kindly,” than in any personage he has painted ; and though the humour, as usual, is dashed with filth, without a <hi rend="italic">soupçon</hi>  of which indeed Smollett seems always to have thought it wanted pungency, the tale is entirely free from that indecency which deforms both <hi rend="italic">Roderick Random send Peregrine Pickle.</hi>  We rather think, too, that Smollett had the merit of originating in this novel tllat species of the humourous which arises from bad spelling, and which Sheridan afterwards applied to mistakes of words in his Mrs. Malaprop ; a humble kind of humour no doubt in itself, yet capable, as Smollett has proved, of powerfully aiding the ludicrous effect.</p><p>Equal genius, though far more deformed by affectation, is visible in Sterne, (1713—1768)the first two volumes of whose <hi rend="italic">Tristram Shandy</hi>  appeared in 1759∙ If a regular progress of incidents towards a catastrophe, were an essential requisite in a novel, it would be difficult to bring the works of Sterne within the protection of that definition. Story he has none to tell ; at all events he tells it not. But, “what is a plot good for,” says Bayes, “ except to bring in good things,” and Sterne adopted the theory of the dramatist in its full license. At the conclusion of the eighth volume, Tristram is not emancipated from the nursery, and had Sterne lived to fulfil his threat of carrying on hiswork, by the aid of a vegetable diet, through as many more, the Tristrapædia, we fear, would still have made no material progress. Sterne’s singular work owes its interest, as every one knows, not to the narrative, which is broken and interrupted by cross currents of the most wayward and whimsical description, far exceeding all the fair license of digression, but to his power of seizing on and bringing forward into distinct consciousness, as Coleridge says, some of those points on which every man is <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  humorist, and to the mastcrly manner in which he has brought out the characteristics of two beings ot the most opposite natures, the elder Shandy and Toby, and surrounded them with a group of followers sketched with equal life and individuality: in the Corporal, the obstetric Doctor Slop; Yorick,the livelyand careless parson; thewidow Wad-man, and Susannah.</p><p>The clue which Sterne chiefly follows through the mazes of character, is humour;—humour of a very high and peculiar kind, perfectly original, at least in English. For that species of riotous humour arising from comic peculiarities of person, and combinations of ludicrous mischances, Sterne has little taste ; though the admirably painted scene, where Obadiah on the cart horse, careering round the corner like a comet, oversets Dr. Slop in a whirlpool of mud ;—and the cross bills filed by the Doctor and Susannah against each other in applying the cataplasm, show, that if he had considered this tbe highest walk of humour, he might have revelled in it as easily as Smollett himself. But, like Fielding, he preferred the humour which arises from bringing out by light and happy touches, and as if unconsciously, the secrets of character ; only with this difference in his favour, that with Sterne the humour is steeped in sensibility. Flowing, as it does, as much from the heart as the head, it speaks also to the affections ; calm smiles ripple over the countenance as we read, but tears are in the next degree. Thus, in Sterne, humour and feeling helghten and set off each other ; the pathetic rises in gentle relief out of the background of the comic, and sinks gracefully and imperceptibly back into it again. It is this, for instance, w hich gives so irresistible a charm to the story of Le Fevre, and the Corporal’s account in the kitchen</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>