<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of romantic fictions which succeeded to the romance of chi-' valry. But we can only notice briefly works which have long slumbered in oblivion, and which certainly are not worthy to have their slumbers disturbed.</p><p>Even in the time of Cervantes, the pastoral romance, founded upon the <hi rend="italic">Diana</hi>  of George of Monte Mayor, was prevailing to such an extentas made it worthy of his satire. It was, indeed, a system still more remote from common sense and reality than that of chivalry itself. For the maxims of chivalry, high-strained and absurd as they are, did actually influence living beings, and even the fate of kingdoms. If <hi rend="italic">Amadis de Gaul</hi>  was a fiction, the Chevalier Bayard was a real person. But the existence of an Arcadia, a pastoral region, in which a certain fantastic sort of personages, desperately in love, and thinking of nothing else but their mistresses, played upon pipes, and wrote sonnets from morning to night, yet were supposed all the while to be tending their flocks, was too monstrously absurd to be long credited or tolerated.</p><p>A numerous, and once most popular class of fictions, was that entitled the heroic romance of the seventeenth century.</p><p>If the ancient romance of chivalry has a right to be called the parent of those select and beautiful fictions which the genius of the Italian poets has enriched with such peculiar charms, another of its direct descendants, the heroic romance of the seventeenth century, is, with few exceptions, the most dull and tedious species of composition that ever obtained temporary popularity. The old romance of Heliodorus, entitled <hi rend="italic">Theagenes and Chariclea,</hi>  supplied perhaps the earliest model of this style of composition ; but it was from the romances of chivalry that it derives its most peculiar characteristics. A man of a fantastic imagination, Honoré d’Urfé, led the way in this style of composition. Being willing to record certain love intrigues of a complicated nature which had taken place in his own family, and among his friends, he imagined to himself a species of Arcadia on the banks of the Lignon, who live for love, and for love alone. There are two principal stories, said to represent the family history of D’Urfé and his bro</p><lb/><p>ther, with about thirty episodes, in which tlle gallantries and intrigues of Henry IV.’s court are presented under borrowed names. Considered by itself, this is but an example of the pastoral romance ; but it was so popular that three celebrated French authors, Gomberville, Calprenede, and Madame Scuderi, seized the pen, and composed in emulation many interminable folios of heroic romance. In these insipid performances, a conventional character, and a set of family manners and features, are ascribed to the heroes and heroines, although selected from distant ages, and various quarters of the world. The heroines are, without exception, models of beauty and perfection ; and, so well persuaded of it themselves, that to approach them with the most humble declaration of love, was a crime sufficient to deserve the penalty of banishment from their presence ; and it is well if the doom were softened to the audacious lover, by permission, or command to live, without which, absence and death were to be accounted synonymous. On theother hand, the heroes, whatever kingdoms they have to govern, or other earthly duties to perform, live through these folios for love alone ; and the most extraordinary revolutions which can agitate the wwld, art* ascribed to the charms of aMandana, or a Statira, acting upon the crazy understanding of their lovers. Nothing can be so uninteresting as the frigid extravagance with which these lovers express their passion ; or, in their own phrase, nothing can be more freezing than their flames, more creeping than their flights of love. Yet the line of metaphysical gallantry which they exhibited, had its date, and a long one, both in France and England. In the latter country they continued to be read by our grandmothers during the Augustan age of English ; and while Addison was amusing the world with his wit, and Pope by his poetry, the ladies were reading delta, Cleopatra, and the Grand Cyrus. The fashion did not decay till about the reign of George I. ; and even more lately, Mrs. Lennox, patronized by Dr. Johnson, wrote a very good imitation of Cervantes, entitled <hi rend="italic">The Female Quixote,</hi>  which had those works for its basis. They are now totally forgotten.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(d. d.d.)</hi></p><lb/><p><hi rend="smallcaps">modern romance and novel.</hi></p><p>We alluded in the commencement of this essay, to the division of fictitious narratives in prose, into two classes ; the <hi rend="italic">romance,</hi>  in which the interest of the narrative turns chiefly on marvellous and uncommon incidents ; and the <hi rend="italic">novel,</hi>  in which the events are accommodated to the ordinary train of human events, and the modem state of society.</p><p>The rise of this last department of fictitious composition in England, takes place about the commencement of the eighteenth century ; and its coincidence with the decline of the drama is remarkable. The novel aspired, in fact, to perform for a reading and refined age, what the drama had done for a ruder and more excitable period ; to embody the spirit of the times in pictures at once amusing and accurate, and in the form best calculated to awaken attention and interest in those to whom tlιey are addressed. In the earlier periods of a national literature, while the poetical and imaginative spirit of the time takes the direction of the long prose romance, the task of painting manners, and satirizing follies, and displaying the comic oddities of character, is most efficiently periornιcd by the drama. Its strength, terseness, and brevity, with the aid of action and scenery, present the manners living as they rise, with abundance of force at least, and probably, for a time, with sufficient fidelity. But as soαety becomes more decorous, and peculiarities of manners less marked, the pictures exhibited by the stage are apt to become less true ; for dramatic effect appears to demand something more stimulating than rcality affords ; and hence the drama, with a pardonable leaning to the principle of stage effect, often continues to reproduce the man</p><lb/><p>ners, vices, and humours of a preceding age, long after they have ceased to exist, merely because they are found better adapted to that broad and strongly-coloured delineation in which it chiefly deals. Thus, though the age of Van-burgh, Congreve, and Wycherley, was probably not a very moral age, and the tone even of its polite conversation, would probably appear somewhat questionable to modem ears, there seems to be no reason to believe that the universal profligacy of manners, and boundless licence of conversation which are exhibited in the comedies of these writers, really characterised the period at which they wrote. Their Wildairs, Sir John Brutes, Lady Touchwoods, and Mrs. Frails, are conventional reproductions of those wild gallants and demireps which figure in the licentious dramas of Dryden and Shadwell. They represented the manners and the morals of an age gone by ; and the audiences who tolerated these indecencies for the sake of the wit by which they wcre occasionally redeemed, would have been revolted by their exaggeration and incorrectness, if they had looked upon them as exhibitions of society as it existed. The drama, then, had ceased to be the mirror in which the age could contemplate itself, and exhibited the license of a masque, or the extravagance of a caricature, much more than the sobriety of actual life, or the fidelity of a portrait. Besides, there are many lesser traits of character, many sentiments and feelings, which are not at all dramatic, and which had therefore been overlooked by writers for the stage, yet in themselves highly interesting and curious, and capable, when judiciously employed, of exercising a strong influence on the feelings. These become more prominent, and stand out in brighter relief, as the restraints of civilization gradu-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>