<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>In a circle or cylinder turning about its axis, OQ = √½ the radius; for by (18) we have in this case <hi rend="italic">fridm </hi>= ½ Mr<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  ; therefore<hi rend="italic">VJ'ridm</hi>  -+ M = r √ ½. But if the circle turns round one of its diameters, then OQ = ½ the radius ; for in this caβe <hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = ¼ M ri ; therefore <hi rend="italic">Vfridm</hi>  +- M = ⅛ r.</p><p>In the periphery of a circle, or rim of a wheel, turning about a diameter perpendicular to its plane, OQ = radius; for <hi rend="italic">fridm = ri × 2&lt;rr = 2rrri,</hi>  and M = <hi rend="italic">2&lt;rr ;</hi>  therefore <hi rend="italic">√fridm</hi>  -+ M = r.</p><p>A solid sphere turning round a diameter has OQ = r√¾ for (18) the moment of inertia of the sphere is -⅛ <hi rend="italic">vri</hi>  ; and the mass M = ¼ <hi rend="italic">atri</hi>  ; therefore OQ = V-⅛ r<hi rend="sup">1</hi>=r √¾.</p><p>41.    In what precedes, we have supposed that the force applied to a rigid system produces its effect by instantaneous impact, and then ceases to act, so that the motion communicated to the system is uniform. But if the action of the external force continues after the first impact, like the force of gravity on a falling body, the motion of the system will be accelerated. In the case of uniform velocity, it has been shown (14) that the angular velocity is equal to the moment of the applied force divided by the moment of inertia ; that is, assuming F to denote the force, and P the perpendicular from the axis on the line of its direction, <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  = p∙F +∙<hi rend="italic">fridm.</hi>  Suppose now the body to be subjected to the action of an accelerating force, and let <hi rend="italic">dw</hi>  be the increment of the angular velocity in the very small time <hi rend="italic">dt.</hi>  The increment of the actual velocity of the particle <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  the distance of which from the axis is <hi rend="italic">r,</hi>  is then <hi rend="italic">rdw, </hi>and its accelerating force (the ratio of the increment of the velocity to the increment of the time) is <hi rend="italic">r~∙</hi>  Its moving force is consequently ⅛ ∙ <hi rend="italic">rdm ;</hi>  and since the direction of</p><p>this force is perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">r,</hi>  its moment =    <hi rend="italic">∙ ridm.</hi></p><p>But the sum of all these moments, in respect of every particle <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  must be equal to the moment of the impressed force, continuing to act during the same instant of time, therefore<hi rend="italic">^fr'dm -PF,</hi>  whence</p><p>42.    In the case of a heavy body oscillating about an axis by the force of gravity, let HKL be a section of the body passing through the centre of gravity G, and let the axis of suspension be at O,and perpendicular to the plane HKL. Also, let OX be horizontal, and OY vertical. Then the accelerating force being denoted by <hi rend="italic">g (g =</hi>  32 feet in a second of time), the moving force in respect of a particle <hi rend="italic">dm</hi>  at A is <hi rend="italic">gdm ;</hi>  and the direction of this force being parallel to Ο Y, the distance of its direction from the axis is <hi rend="italic">x ; </hi>therefore its moment <hi rend="italic">= gχdrn.</hi>  The sum of all these moments is the moment of the whole gravitating force of the body, that is, <hi rend="italic">gfxdm = p∙F,</hi>  and we have consequently, <hi rend="italic">since fxdm</hi>  = Mar<hi rend="sub">1</hi>,</p><p>⅛fr<hi rend="sup">2</hi>&lt;∕m=pMx<hi rend="sub">1</hi>, whence ⅛ = ⅛∙</p><p>When the centre of gravity is in tlle straight line OY, or in the vertical passing through the axis, then a;, = 0, and the angular velocity is uniform, and the body, if it rest in that position, would have no tendency to turn. But suppose the centre of gravity to be drawn aside from the vertical, and let OG = <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  and the angle GOY = <hi rend="italic">6,</hi>  then <hi rend="italic">x<hi rend="sub">1 </hi>= k</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  and we have</p><p><hi rend="italic">dw gTΛh</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">0 dt fridm. ’</hi></p><p>whence tlle acceleration of the angular velocity is proportional to the sine of the angle which the line OG makes with the vertical.</p><p>43.    Suppose the «’hole mass of the body to be concentrated at a point S in tile straight line OG ; we shall then have <hi rend="italic">τ = OS, fridm</hi>  = M∙OS<hi rend="sup">s</hi>, and the formula will become -- =y  β*n<hi rend="sup">,</hi>∖  Now, if the point S be chosen such that</p><p><hi rend="italic">ut</hi>  Uu</p><p>OS = <hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  M∙A, then the two formulæ will be identical, and the solid body will oscillate exactly in the same time as if all its matter were united at the point S, and connected with the axis by an inflexible rod without weight, that is, in the same time as a simple pendulum, of which the length is OS.</p><p>Since ri = <hi rend="italic">χ<hi rend="sup">t</hi>  + y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>,</hi>  and M ∙ <hi rend="italic">h = fxdm,</hi>  this expression for OS may be put under the following form, in which it is usually exhibited, namely,</p><p>os=∕&lt;^+y⅛</p><p><hi rend="italic">Jxdm</hi></p><p>44.    The point S is called the <hi rend="italic">centre of oscillation.</hi>  On comparing the expression for OS with tllat for OP in (34), it will be seen that it is at the same distance from the axis as the centre of percussion. But the centre of oscillation is not, strictly speaking, limited to a single point ; for it through S a line be drawn perpendicular to the plane HKL, or parallel to the axis of rotation, every point in this line will move with the same angular velocity as if it were entirely unconnected with the other points of the oscillating body, and the line itself is denominated the <hi rend="italic">axis ofoscillation. </hi>It is usual, however, to understand by the term <hi rend="italic">centre ofoscillation,</hi>  the point S which is situated in the straight line, perpendicular to the axis, which contains the centre of gravity.</p><p>45.    If we denote the moment of inertia of the body in respect of the axis which passes through G the centre of gravity, perpendicular to the plane HKL, by M ∙ Λ<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, then A is a given line : and if we also make OG = A, then (17) the moment of inertia in respect of the axis passing through O is M (A<hi rend="sup">2</hi> + A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>). Hence we find OS = —</p><p>A<hi rend="sup">1</hi>    Λ<hi rend="sup">8</hi></p><p>= A +    ; and consequently GS = j-. This formula</p><p>gives the distance of the centre of oscillation below the centre of gravity.</p><p>46.    The point S possesses several very remarkable properties, one of which is, that as S is the centre of oscillation of the body turning about O, so O is the centre of oscillation of the body turning about the parallel axis passing through S ; in other words, the centres of oscillation and suspension are</p><p>A<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>convertible. For it has been shown (45) that GS =-^-A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>    A<hi rend="sup">8</hi></p><p>= τvr, ! therefore OG = <hi rend="sub">5</hi>=, that is to say, if the bodv</p><p>OG    Gb</p><p>oscillates about the axis passing through S, then O is the centre of oscillation. Ί his curious property, which was first demonstrated by Huygens in his <hi rend="italic">Horologium Oscilla-torium,</hi>  was ingeniously applied by Captain Kater as a practical means of determining the length of the seconds pendulum. Two axes being assumed in a bar or rod of metal, the bar is adjusted by filing away one of its ends until the oscillations about each axis are performed exactly in the same time ; and when this equality has been established, the distance betw een the axes is the length of the synchronous simple pendulum. See Pendulum.</p><p>47.    We shall now determine the centre of oscillation in a few particular cases.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>