<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in the field where she excels too, she is much of a mannerist ; the same characters under other names, the same incidents under a thin disguise, re-appear in <hi rend="italic">Evelina, Cecilia, </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Camilla.</hi>  Even the graces of style which she had shewn in her earlier works, in a great measure forsook her in her last novel, the <hi rend="italic">Wanderer;</hi>  a tissue of improbable distresses and silly refinements of sensibility, conveyed in language which is neither good English nor good sense.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Canterbury Tales</hi>  deserve notice on account of the interesting and highly original story of Kruitzner, or the German’s Tale, by Harriet Lee, on which Lord Byron founded his <hi rend="italic">Werner.</hi>  The tales contributed to the work by her sister Sophia, such as the Two Emilys, and the Clergyman’s Tale, though less striking, are written with genuine feeling and tenderness.</p><p>It may be observed, however, in those female novelists to whom we have last adverted that, though the marvellous is thrown aside, and the characters are taken from common life, the sentiments and tone of feeling are yet decidedly strained beyond the natural pitch. The characters display a degree of romantic affection and aprodigal expenditure of sensibility for which the cares and distractions of real life, we fear, afford but little leisure. It remained for Miss Austin (1775-1817,) to shew what a charm might be imparted to truthful pictures of life, as we really see it around us in the quiet monotony of domestic arrangements, with its interchanges of poetry and prose, business and strong feeling, and dialogues at balls and parties alternating with the secret griefs of the heart; just such a picture, in short, as Asmodeus would present, could he remove the roof of many an English home, and place us beside the hearths of the Knightleys, Bennets, Woodhouses, and Bertrams by whom they are inhabited. No species of novel writing exposes itself to a severer trial, since it not only resigns all Bayes<hi rend="sup">,</hi> pretensions “ to elevate the imagination and bring you off in some extraordinary way,” but by professing to give us pictures of our ordinary acquaintances, in their common garb, places its productions within that range of criticism, where all are equally judges, and where Crispin is entitled to dictate to Apelles. And yet with such fine perception and perfect truth of keeping has Miss Austin performed her task, that we never miss in her novels the excitement of uncommon events, and rarely feel her simple annals of English life to be tedious or unworthy of the dignity of fiction. In reading them, we have the feeling of being actually in company with α group of highly respectable persons, of no remarkable ability, though with good sense and a fair proportion of right feeling; with a sprinkling of fools, oddities, and village gossips ; and the conversation, the little incidents, and displays of temper, and sallies of good humour or bad, and small plottings and counter-plottings among the guests, are exactly such as any contemplative Jaquez who should establish himself in an English country house or rectory for a fortnight, and watch the bye play of the society about him, might set down in his note book ; only skilfully selected and arranged, thc superfluities lopped off, the dullness thrown into the background, and the whole wrought up into a picture, painted indeed in sober hues, but with unequalled delicacy of touch, and an all-pervading harmony.</p><p>All the novels of Miss Austin closelyresemble each other; but <hi rend="italic">Northaηger Abbey,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Sense and Sensibility,</hi>  are of a more puerile cast than the others, and betray a more unformed taste. <hi rend="italic">Pride and Prejudice,</hi>  particularly in the characters of the Bennets, was an improvement on the two for-rner, but <hi rend="italic">Emma, Mansfield</hi>  PαrA,and <hi rend="italic">Persuasion</hi>  are justly regarded as her most finished works. Some scenes in <hi rend="italic">Persuasion,</hi>  the last work of this gifted authoress, have always appeared to us models of unobtrusive tenderness.</p><p>Some one has described the novels of Miss Edgeworth as a sort of essence of common sense ; and the definition is not inappropriate, for she is the most anti-sentimental of novelists. The sway of the stronger passions she has almost excluded from her Tales. Love is indeed tile only one which has found entrance, and to qualify him for admission, his wings have been sorely clipped and trimmed, and reason constantly placed as a gentleman usher over him. Miss Edgeworth has even less toleration for splendid faults or bursts of enthusiasm than Miss Austin. Her chief aim is to rebuke folly, by ridicule and comic humour ; to unteach bad habits of mind, to substitute in their stead prudence, firmness, temper, perseverance, and habits of absolute truth, a process which she generally represents as effected by a gradual series of efforts and consequent ameliorations, which are within the power of all minds of ordinary resolution. Her favourite characters are either persons of well-balanced minds, with sound headsanda smattering of physical science, who act rightly and honourably,but always think twice before they act, and weigh inthescalesofutilitywhatare generally considered as matters of feeling, like thePercys: or they are personages who, spoiled by indolence and bad education, succeed by a course of self-discipline, in curing their intellectual or moral maladies, and becoming useful and honourable members of society, like the hero of <hi rend="italic">Ennui,</hi>  Lord Glenthorn. Miss Edgeworth brings to her task the results of much observation of character, particularly that of her countrymen ; a quick perception of the humourous, a dramatic liveliness of dialogue, a high sense of all that is honourable and decorous, with a scorn of meanness and evasion, and that tone of good society, which her pictures, often drawn from fashionable life, demand. If her novels are at times too obviously monitory and didactic, and the ferule peeps out rather alarmingly behind the schoolmistress, this defect, we fear, is in a great measure inseparable from the very qualities which constitute the strength of her mind, and from the conception she had formed for herself of the ideal of novel writing.</p><p>It is singular that a novelist of this rationalizing spirit, and so intolerant of all moral marvels, should have so frequently admitted great improbabilities into her plots, where the catastrophe is often brought about either by some one very unlikely event, or by a concurrence of events, and fortunate accidents, the combination of which render the circumstance at the least passing strange. Miss Edgeworth is also fond of making the discovery of important events turn on little trifles of circumstantial evidence, which are too artificially prepared, and after all are not satisfactory.</p><p>The impression, however, which the perusal of her best novels, such as <hi rend="italic">Ennui</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">Absentee,</hi>  leaves on the mind, is that of high respect for the sagacity, grasp of mind and rectitude of judgment of the author, whose {lower of dramatizing a moral lesson has not often been excelled. And it is gratifying to see that, in the last work of Miss Edge-worth, <hi rend="italic">Helen,</hi>  there appears no diminution of her powers. In wit it is equal to any of her former novels ; in pathetic scenes, superior to most of them.</p><p>At the period when Sir Walter Scott (1814), produced the first of that long file of romances which have since obtained a more than European reputation, the public taste, in regard to novel writing, seemed to have sunk to a low ebb. Miss Edgeworth indeed was popular ; for the wit and good sense of her dialogue, and her happy pictures of Irish character, found favour in the sight even of the readers of circulating libraries ; but the merits of Miss Austin’s more unobtrusive pictures of life were comparatively unknown. At best she was confounded with the writers of Winters in London, or Winters in Paris, and shared a dubious favour with the romantic effusions of Francis Lathom and the other labourers of the <hi rend="italic">Minerva</hi>  press, so called, we presume, upon the <hi rend="italic">lu&lt;ms a non lucendo</hi>  principle, from the goddess of wisdom having so little to do with its productions. Translations, too, from Augustus La Fontaine’s homely but rather vulgar pictures of'little German <hi rend="italic">Krah-winkel</hi>  towns, or tbe broad and indecent extravagances of Pigault le Brun,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>