<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pany with a son of Admiral Knowles ; and Mr Robison was to have instructed his royal highness in mathematics and navigation. On his arrival in London, he was much disappointed to find that the expedition had never been seriously intended ; and he readily accepted an engagement to attend young Knowles as a private tutor, when he went as a midshipman on board of the Neptune of ninety guns, with Admiral Saunders, who had the command of a force intended to co-operate with General Wolfe in the reduction of Quebec ; and upon the appointment of his friend as a lieutenant on board of the Royal William, Robison was himself rated as a midshipman in that ship.</p><p>The fleet arrived on the coast of America in April 1759 ; in May they got up the river, and Mr Robison was one of a party of 100 seamen draughted from the Royal William into the admiral’s ship, under the command of Lieutenant Knowles. In this capacity he had an opportunity of seeing considerable service, and of making some surveys of the river and of the neighbouring country ; an employment for which he was perfectly qualified, both as a geometrician and a draughtsman. He also remarked the effect of the aurora borealis on the compass, which had been noticed by Mairan and Wargentin some years before, but which was then not commonly known. After the battle which was signalized by the victory and death of the gallant Wolfe, the Royal William sailed with his body to Europe, and arrived at Spit-head in November. The next year she was sent to cruise off Cape Finisterre ; but in six months she was obliged to return home, from having the greater part of the men disabled by the scurvy.</p><p>He used to consider the two years that he spent on board of the Royal William as the happiest of his life ; and no in-siderable part of his gratification was derived from the study of seamanship as he saw it practised under the auspices of Captain Hugh Pigot. He did not, however, acquire any firm attachment to the mode of life which he had temporarily adopted ; he was rather disposed to resume his academical pursuits, and he had overcome his earlier objections to the ecclesiastical profession. He could not, however, refuse the kindly invitation of Admiral Knowles to come and live with him in the country, and to assist him in some important experiments which he was making upon mechanical and nautical subjects.</p><p>In the month of February 1762, Lieutenant Knowles was appointed to the Peregrine sloop, of twenty guns, and Mr Robison accompanied him with the hope of becoming a purser. He visited Lisbon and several other parts of Portugal ; but he found a cruise in a small ship much less convenient and agreeable than in a large one, and, fortunately for himself and for mankind, he finally quitted the Peregrine and the naval service in June, and returned to live with Admiral Knowles, who soon after recommended him as a proper person to take charge of Harrison’s timekeeper, w hich had been completed by the labour of thirty-five years, after many unsuccessful experiments, and which was now sent out by desire of the Board of Longitude to the West Indies, under the care of young Harrison and of Mr Robison. The rate of the chronometer was ascertained at Portsmouth the 6th November 1762, and it indicated at Port Royal, in Jamaica, a difference of time amounting to 5∣ι 2∏&gt; 47», which is only four seconds less than the true longitude. After a few days the observers had a prompt opportunity of returning home by the Merlin sloop, which was sent to Europe with despatches. The voyage was most disastrous with respect to wind and weather, and at last the ship took fire ; but she arrived safe at Portsmouth in March, and on the 2d of April the watch gave 1 l<hi rend="sup">b</hi>  58<hi rend="sup">m</hi>  6⅛<hi rend="sup">s</hi>, instead of 12<hi rend="sup">h</hi>, for the time of mean noon, so that the error, after six months, was only 1“ 53½<hi rend="sup">,</hi>, amounting to no more than about twenty miles of distance.</p><p>Mr Robison received, upon his return, the afflicting intelligence of the total loss of the Peregrine, which had foundered at sea with her commander and the whole of the ship’s company. He was also greatly disappointed in the failure of some hopes which had been held out to him from the Admiralty and the Board of Longitude ; though in fact there is little reason for the public to regret that he was not gratified with the pursership, which he claimed as the reward of his services. He was indeed afterwards actually made a purser by Lord Sandwich, in 1763; but he then declined accepting the appointment. His biographers very naturally complain of the neglect of those boards which ought to have recompensed him ; but certainly the Board of Longitude had no power whatever, and probably not much influence, in the appointment of a purser ; and, after all, the delay of a year or two was nothing very uncommon in the navy.</p><p>He had now no other resource than to return to Glasgow, and to resume his academical pursuits with renewed energy. It was from this time that he dated his serious application to his studies. He became extremely intimate with Dr Reid and Dr Alexander Wilson ; and he had the advantage of being a witness of two of the greatest steps in the improvement of physical science that have been made in modern times, Dr Black’s experimental theory of heat, and Mr Watt’s invention of a new steam-engine. Dr Black was the first that determined the quantity of heat required for the conversion of ice into water : Mr Watt, who was settled as a mathematical instrument-maker at Glasgow, had been employed in repairing a working model of New comen’s engine for one of the professors of the university ; and it was the difficulty of supplying this model with steam that suggested to Mr Watt the eligibility of having a separate condenser, and that led him, in conjunction with Dr Black, to a knowledge of the quantity of heat consumed in evaporation.</p><p>Amid the enthusiasm which is always inspired by the progress of scientific discovery and of practical improvement, Mr Robison found every encouragement and every facility for the pursuit of his favourite objects. He was recommended by Dr Black, upon his removal to Edinburgh in 1766, as his successor in the lectureship of chemistry, though without the appointment of a professor. He took charge, also, of the education of Mr Macdowall of Garth-land, and of Mr Charles Knowles, afterwards Sir Charles. Admiral Knowles was soon after recommended by the British government to the empress of Russia, in order to effect a reformation in her navy, having been employed on a similar service in Portugal almost fifty years before; he hadal-ways been a firm friend to Mr Robison, and now engaged him on this mission, with a salary of L.250 a year ; and they proceeded together to St Petersburg in December 1770. Being hospitably entertained on their way by the prince bishop of Liege, whom they found to constitute, w ith his chapter and all his servants, a lodge of freemasons, Mr Robison w as easily persuaded to become one of that fraternity : in a few days he was made an apprentice, and by degrees attained the rank of Scottish master, as he has himself related in his publication upon the subject. He continued nearly two years at St Petersburg, still acting in the capacity of private secretary to Sir Charles, who was appointed president of the Board of Admiralty, much to the advantage of the Russian navy, though his improvements were frequently retarded by the prejudices of the native officers. Mr Robison was then appointed inspector general of the corps of marine cadets at Cronstadt, with a double salary, and with the rank of lieutenant-colonel. His duty was to receive the report of about forty teachers and orofessors, respecting the studies of 400 young noblemen, wno were their pupils, and to class them according to his judgment of their merits ; but he had himself nothing to teach, nor could he have had much occasion for “ lecturing fluently</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>