<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>idea, that he was introduced to flatter the personal vanity 'of the princes of the Valois race, by a portrait of their great predecessor.</p><p>The circumstance that Roland was a lieutenant of Brittany, and the certainty that Marie borrowed from that country the incidents out of which she composed her lays, seems to fortify the theory, that the French minstrels obtained from that country much of their most valuable materials ; and that, after all that has been said and supposed, the history of Arthur probably reached them through the same channel.</p><p>The Latin writers of the middle ages afforded the French romancers the themes of those metrical legends which they have composed on subjects of classical fame.</p><p>The honour of the prose romances of chivalry, exclusive always of the books of Amadis, belongs entirely to the French, and the curious volumes which are now the object of so much research amongst collectors, are almost universally printed at Paris.</p><p>England, so often conquered, yet fated to receive an accession of strength from each new subjugation, cannot boast much of ancient literature of any kind ; and, in the department of which we treat, was totally inferior to France. The Saxons had, no doubt, romances (taking the word in its general acceptation) ; and Mr. Turner, to whose researches we are so much indebted, has given us the abridgment of one entitled <hi rend="italic">Caedmon,</hi>  in which the hero, whose adventures are told much after tlle manner of the ancient Norse Sagas, encounters, defeats, and finally slays an evil being called Grendel, who, except in his being subject to death, seems a creature of a supernatural description. But the literature of the Saxons was destroyed by the success of William the Conqueror, and the Norman knights and barons, among whom England was in a great measure divided, sought amusement, not in the lays of the vanquished, but in those composed in their own language. In this point of view, England, as a country, may lay claim to many of the French romances, which were written, indeed, in that language, but for the benefit of the court and nobles of England, by whom French was still spoken. When the two languages began to assimilate together, and to form the mixed dialect termed the Anglo-Norman, we have good authority for saying that it was easily applied to the purpose of romantic fiction, and recited in the presence of the nobility.</p><p>Robert de Brunne, who composed his <hi rend="italic">History of England </hi>about this time, has this remarkable passage, which we give, along with the commentary of the editor of <hi rend="italic">Sir Tristrem, </hi>as it is peculiarly illustrative of the subject we are inquiring into.</p><p>Als thai baf wryten and sayd,</p><p>Haf I allé in myn Inglis layd,</p><p>In symple speche as I couthe,</p><p>That is lightest in manne's mouthe.</p><p>I mad noght for no disours,</p><p>Ne for no seggours, no harpours,</p><p>Bot for the luf of symple men,</p><p>That strange Inglis cannot ken ;</p><p>For many it ere that strange Inglis,</p><p>In ryme wate never what it is ;</p><p>And bot thai wist what it mente,</p><p>Ellis methought it were allé schente.</p><p>I made it not for to be praysed,</p><p>Bot at the lewed men were aysed.</p><p>If it were made in ryme couwee,</p><p>Or in strangere, or enterlacé,</p><p>That rede Inglis it ere inowe That couthe not haf coppled a kowe,</p><p>That outher in cowee or in baston Sum suld haf ben fordon ;</p><p>So that fele men that it berde Suld not witte hotve that it ferde.</p><p><hi rend="italic">I see in song,</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">sedgeyng tale,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Of Εrceldoun and of Kendale,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Hon tham sayis as thai tham wroght,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">And in ther saying it semes noghi.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">That may thou here in Sir Tristrem,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Over gestes it has the steem,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Over all that is or was,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">If men it sayd as made Thomas.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Bot I here it no man so say,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">That of some copple som is away.</hi></p><p>So thare fayre saying here befome,</p><p>Is thare travayle nere forlome ;</p><p>Thai sayd it for pride and nobleye,</p><p>That were not suylke as thei,</p><p>And allé that thai wild overwhere,</p><p>Allé that ilk wille now forfare.</p><p>Thai sayd it in so quainte Inglis,</p><p>That manyone wate not what it is.</p><p>Therfore heuyed wele the more In strange ryme to travayle sore,</p><p>And my wit was oure thynne,</p><p>So strange speche to travayle in ;</p><p>And forsoth I couth noght So strange Inglis as thai wroght,</p><p>And men besoght me many a tyme To tume it bot in light ryme.</p><p>Thai seyd, if I in strange ryme it turn,</p><p>To here it raanyon suld skorue ;</p><p>For in it ere names fulle selcouthe,</p><p>That ere not used now in mouthe.</p><p>And therfore, for the comoπalte,</p><p>That blythely wild listen to me,</p><p>On light lange I it began,</p><p>For luf of the lewed man.</p><p>“ This passage requires some commentary, as the sense has been generally mistaken. Robert de Brunne does not mean, as has been supposed, that the minstrels who repeated Thomas’s romance of <hi rend="italic">Sir Tristrem,</hi>  disguised the meaning by putting it into <hi rend="italic">quainte Inglis ;</hi>  but, on the contrary, that Kendal and Thomas of Erceldoune did themselves use such <hi rend="italic">quainte Inglis,</hi>  that those who repeated the story were unable to understand it, or to make it intelligible to their hearers. Above all, he complains that, by writing an intricate and complicated stanza, as ‘ <hi rend="italic">ryme cowee, strangere,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">entrelacé,'</hi>  it was difficult for the <hi rend="italic">diseurs</hi>  to recollect the poem ; and of <hi rend="italic">Sir Tristrem,</hi>  in particular, he avers, that he never heard a perfect recital, because of some one <hi rend="italic">‘ coppld</hi>  or stanza, a part was always omitted. Hence he argues at length, that he himself, writing not for the minstrel or harper, nor to acquire personal fame, but solely to instruct the ignorant in the history of their country, does well in chusing a simple structure of verse, which they can retain correctly on their memory, and a style which is popular and easily understood. Besides which, he hints at tlle ridicule he might draw on his poem, should he introduce the uncouth names of his personages into a courtly or refined strain of verse. They were</p><p>Great names, but hard in verse to stand.</p><p>While he arrogates praise to himself for his choice, he excuses Thomas of Erceldoune and Kendale for using a more ambitious and ornate kind of poetry. They wrote, he says, for pride (fame) and for nobles, not such as these my ignorant hearers.”@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>If the editor of <hi rend="italic">Sir Tristrem</hi>  be correct in his commentary, there existed in the time of Robert de Brunne, minstrels or poets who composed English poetry to be recited in the presence of the great, and who, for that purpose, used a singularly difficult stanza, which was very apt to be mutilated in recitation. <hi rend="italic">Sir Tristrem,</hi>  even as it now exists, shows likewise that considerable art was resorted to in constructing the stanza, and has, from beginning to end, a concise, quaint, abstract turn of expression, more like the Saxon poetry, than the simple, bald, and diffuse details of the French minstrel. Besides <hi rend="italic">Sir Tristrem,</hi>  there remain, we</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Sir<hi rend="italic">Tristrem,</hi>  Introduction, pp∙ 61-65. Edin. 1804.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>