<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>both above and below it, and tile widψ of the river, to determine the discharge.</p><p>This is by no means so easily solved as the discharge over a weir, and we cannot do it with the same degree of evidence. We imagine, however, that the following observations will not be very far from a true account of the matter.</p><p>We may first suppose a reservoir LFBM (fig. 22) of stagnant water, and that has a wasteboard of the height AB. We may then determine, by the foregoing problems, the discharge through the plane EC.</p><p>With respect to the discharge through the part CΛ, it should be equal to the product of this part of the section by the velocity corresponding to the fall EC, which is the difference of the heights of water above and below the bar ; for, because the difference of <hi rend="italic">Ea</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Ca</hi>  is equal to EC, every particle <hi rend="italic">a </hi>of water in the plane CA is pressed in the direction of this stream with the same force, viz. the weight of the column EC. The sum of these discharges should be the whole discharge over the bar ; but since the bar is set up across a running river, its discharge must be the same with that of the river. The water of the river, when it comes to the place of the bar, has acquired some velocity by its slope or other causes, and this corresponds to some height FE. This velocity, multiplied by the section of the river, having the height EB, should give a discharge equal to the discharge over the bar.</p><p>To avoid this complication of conditions, we may first compute the discharge of the bar in the manner now pointed out, without the consideration of the previous velocity of the stream. This discharge will be a little too small. If we divide it by the section FB, it will give a primary velocity too small, but not far from the truth. Therefore we shall get the height FE, by means of which we shall be able to determine a velocity intermediate between DG and CH, which would correspond to a weir, as also the velocity CH, which corresponds to the part of the section CA, which is wholly under water. Then we correct all these quantities by repeating the operation with them instead of our first assumptions.</p><p>Du Buat found this computation extremely near the truth, but in all cases a little greater than observation exhibited.</p><p>We may now solve the problem in the most general terms.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. IV. Given the breadth, depth, and the slope of a river, if w</hi><hi rend="sup">,</hi>e confine its passage by a bar or weir of a known height and width, to determine the rise of the waters above the bar.</p><p>The slope and dimensions of the channel being given, our formula will give us the velocity and the quantity of water discharged. Then, by Problem II., find the height of water above the wasteboard. From the sum of these tw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>o heights deduct the ordinary depth of the river. The remainder is the rise of the waters. For example :</p><p>Let there be a river whose ordinary depth is 3 feet, and breadth 40, and whose slope is l½ inch in 100 fathoms, or <hi rend="sub">i</hi>,‰j. Suppose a weir on this river 6 feet high and 18 feet wide.</p><p>We must first find the velocity and discharge of the river in its natural state ; we have <hi rend="italic">l —</hi>  480 inches, <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  = 36, - = <hi rend="sub">τs</hi>½<hi rend="sub">ra</hi>. Our formula of uniform motion gives V= 23∙45,</p><p>and D = 405216 cubic inches.</p><p>The contraction obtains here on the three sides of the orifice. We may therefore take √2G = 26<hi rend="sup">,</hi>1. (This example is Du Buat’s, and all the measures are French.) We have also<hi rend="italic">a</hi>  (the height of the weir) = 72, and <hi rend="italic">2g —</hi>  724.</p><p>Then the equation Λ = (-———’ — (-—=5∙-</p><p>∖0∙431Z√2G∕    V√2y(α+A)∕</p><p>becomes <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  = 30∙182. Add this to the height of the weir, and the depth of the river above the sluice is 102∙182 inches = 8 feet and 6∙ 182 inches. From this take 3 feet, and there remains 5 feet and 6∙182 inches for the rise of the waters.</p><p>There is, however, an important circumstance in this rise of the waters, which must he distinctly understood before we can say what are the interesting effects of this weir. This swell extends, as we all know, to a considerable distance up the stream, but is less sensible as w e go away from the weir. What is the distance to which the swell extends, and what increase does it produce in the depth at different distances from the weir ?</p><p>If we suppose that the slope and the breadth of the channel remain as before, it is plain, that as we come down the stream from that point where the swell is insensible, the depth of the channel increases all the way to the dam. Therefore, as the same quantity of water passes through every section of the river, the velocity must diminish very nearly in the same proportion that the section increases. But this being an open stream, and therefore the velocity being inseparably connected with the slope of the surface, it follows, that the slope of the surface must diminish all the way from that point where the swell of the water is insensible to the dam. The surface, therefore, cannot be a simple inclined plane, but must be concave upwards, as represented in fig. 23,</p><p>where FKLB represents</p><p>the channel of a river,</p><p>and FB the surface of</p><p>the water running in it.</p><p>If this be kept up to A</p><p>by a weir AL, the sur</p><p>face will be a curve FIA,</p><p>touching the natural surface F at the beginning of the swell, and the line AD which touches it in A will have the slope S corresponding to the velocity which the waters have immediately before going to the weir. We know this slope, because we are supposed to know the discharge of the river and its slope and other circumstances before barring it with a dam ; and we know the height of the dam H, and therefore the new velocity at A, or immediately above A, and consequently the slope S. Therefore, drawing the horizontal lines DC, AG, it is plain that CB will be the primary slope of the river, and CA, the slope S corresponding to the velocity in the immediate neighbourhood of A, because these verticals have the same horizontal distance DC. We have therefore CB : CA = S : s very nearly, and S — s : s = CB — CA : CA = AB ; CA. Therefore CA = ⅛- =    <hi rend="sup">But</hi> DA = CA × S, by our</p><p>S — s ⅛ — s</p><p>definition of slope ; therefore DA = ·=--∙.</p><p>This is all that we can say with precision of this curve. Du Buat examined what would result from supposing it an arc of a circle. In this case we should have DA = DF, and AF very nearly equal to 2 AD ; and as we can thus find AD, we get the whole length FIA of the swell, and also the distances of any part of the curve from the primitive surface FB of the river; for these will be very nearly in the duplicate proportion of their distances from F. Thus ID will be one fourth of AB, &amp;c. Therefore we should obtain the depth <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>  of the stream in that place. Getting the depth of the stream, and knowing the discharge, we get the velocity, and can compare this with the slope of the surface at I. This should be the slope of that</p></body></text></TEI>