<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ly observe, that although these pressures by which the parts of a frame support each other in opposition to the vertical action of gravity, are always exerted in the direction of the pieces, they may be resolved into pressures acting in any other direction which may engage our attention.</p><p>All that we propose to deliver on this subject at present may be included in the following proposition.</p><p>Let ABCDE (fig. 10) be an assemblage of rafters in a</p><lb/><p>vertical plane, resting on two fixed points A and E in a horizontal line, and perfectly moveable round all the joints A, B, C, D, E; let it be further supposed to be in equilibrio, and let us investigate what adjustment of the different circumstances of weight and inclination of its different parts is necessary for producing this equilibrium.</p><p>Let F, G, H, I, be the centres of gravity of the different rafters, and let these letters express the weights of each. Then, by what has been said above, the weight which pressses B directly downwards is . The weight on C is in like manner and that on D is .</p><p>Let A<hi rend="italic">bcd</hi>E be the figure ABCDE inverted, in the manner already described. It may be conceived as a thread fastened at A and E, and loaded at <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  with the weights which are really pressing on B, C, and D. It will arrange itself into such a form that all will be in equilibrio. We may discover this form by means of this single consideration, that any part <hi rend="italic">bc</hi>  of the thread is equally stretched throughout, in the direction of its length. Let us therefore investigate the proportion between the weight <hi rend="italic">β,</hi>  which we suppose to be pulling the point <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  in the vertical direction <hi rend="italic">bβ</hi>, to the weight ft, which is pulling down the point <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  in a similar manner. It is evident, that since AE is a horizontal line, and the figures <hi rend="italic">AbcdE</hi>  and ABCDE equal and similar, the lines B<hi rend="italic">b</hi>, C<hi rend="italic">c</hi>, D<hi rend="italic">d</hi>, are vertical. Take <hi rend="italic">bf</hi>  to represent the weight hanging at <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. By stretching the threads <hi rend="italic">b</hi>A and <hi rend="italic">bc</hi>  it is set in opposition to the contractile powers of the threads, acting in the directions <hi rend="italic">b</hi>A and <hi rend="italic">bc</hi>, and it is in immediate equilibrio with the equivalent of these two contractile forces. Therefore make <hi rend="italic">bg</hi>  equal to <hi rend="italic">bf,</hi>  and make it the diagonal of a parallelogram <hi rend="italic">hbig.</hi>  It is evident that <hi rend="italic">bh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">bi,</hi>  are the forces exerted by the threads <hi rend="italic">b</hi>A, <hi rend="italic">bc</hi>. Then, seeing that the thread ftc is equally stretched in both directions, make <hi rend="italic">ck</hi>  equal to <hi rend="italic">bi ; ck</hi>  is the contractile force which is excited at <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  by the weight which is hanging there. Draw <hi rend="italic">kl</hi>  parallel to <hi rend="italic">cd,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">lm</hi>  parallel to <hi rend="italic">bc</hi>. The</p><lb/><p>force <hi rend="italic">lc</hi>  is the equivalent of the contractile forces <hi rend="italic">ck, cm, </hi>and is therefore equal and opposite to the force of gravity acting at C. In like manner, make <hi rend="italic">dn = cm,</hi>  and complete the parallelogram <hi rend="italic">ndpo,</hi>  having the vertical line <hi rend="italic">οd</hi>  for its diagonal. Then <hi rend="italic">dn</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">dp</hi>  are the contractile forces excited at <hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  and the weight hanging there must be equal to <hi rend="italic">od.</hi></p><p>Therefore, the load at <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  is to the load at <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">bg</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">do. </hi>But we have seen that the compressing forces at B, C, D may be substituted for the extending forces at <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">c, d. </hi>Therefore the weights at B, C, D which produce the compressions, are equal to the weights at <hi rend="italic">b</hi>, <hi rend="italic">c, d</hi>  which produce the extensions. Therefore</p><p><hi rend="italic">bg</hi>: <hi rend="italic">dο=</hi></p><p>Let us inquire what relation there is between this proportion of the loads upon the joints at B and D, and the angles which the rafters make at these joints with each other, and with the horizon or the plumb-lines. Produce AB till it cut the vertical C<hi rend="italic">c</hi>  in Q ; then draw BR parallel to CD, and BS parallel to DE. The similarity of the figures ABCDE and A<hi rend="italic">bcd</hi>E, and tile similarity of their position with respect to the horizontal and plumb lines, show, without any further demonstration, that the triangles QCB and <hi rend="italic">gbi</hi>  are similar, and that QB : BC = <hi rend="italic">gi : ib</hi>  = <hi rend="italic">hb</hi>  : <hi rend="italic">ib.</hi>  Therefore QB is to BC as the contractile force exerted by the thread Aft to that exerted by ftc ; and therefore QB is to BC as the compression on BA to the compression on BC.@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>Then, because<hi rend="italic">bi</hi>  is equal to <hi rend="italic">ck,</hi>  and the triangles CBR and <hi rend="italic">ckl</hi>  are similar, CB : BR = <hi rend="italic">ck : kl = ck : cm,</hi>  and CB is to BR as the compression on CB to the compression on CD. And, in like manner, because <hi rend="italic">cm = dn,</hi>  we have BR to BS as the compression on DC to the compression on DE. Also BR : RS = <hi rend="italic">nd : do,</hi>  that is, as the compression on DC to the load on D.     Finally, combining all these ratios,</p><p>QC : CB    =    <hi rend="italic">gb : bi    = gb : kc,</hi></p><p>CB : BR    <hi rend="italic">=    hc : kl    = kc :     dn,</hi></p><p>BR : BS    =<hi rend="italic">nd : no    = dn:    no,</hi></p><p>BS : RS =<hi rend="italic">no : do  = no : do, we</hi>  have finally QC : RS  =<hi rend="italic">gb</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">od</hi>   = load at B : load at D.</p><p>Now</p><p>QC : BC = sin. QBC : sin. BQC = sin. ABC : sin. AB<hi rend="italic">b</hi>,</p><p>BC : BR = sin. BRC : sin. BCR = sin. CD<hi rend="italic">d</hi>  : sin. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>BC,</p><p>BR : RS = sin. BSR : sin. RBS = sin. <hi rend="italic">d</hi>DE : sin. CDE. </p><p>Therefore</p><p>QC : RS = sin. ABC sin. CD<hi rend="italic">d</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">d</hi>DE : sin. CDE sin. AB<hi rend="italic">b</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">b</hi>BC.</p><p>Or</p><p>That is, the loads on the different joints are as the sines of the angles at these joints directly, and as the products of the sines of the angles which the rafters make with the plumb-lines inversely.</p><p>Or, the loads are as the sines of the angles of the joints directly, and as the products of the cosines of the angles of elevation of the rafters inversely.</p><p>Or, the loads at the joints are as the sines of the angles at the joints, and as the products of the secants of the angles of elevation of the rafters jointly ; for tile secants of angles are inversely as the cosines.</p><p>Draw the horizontal line BT. It is evident, that if this be considered as the radius of a circle, the lines BQ, BC, BR, BS are the secants of the angles which these lines</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> This proportion might have been shown directly without any use of the inverted figure, or consideration of contractile forces ; but the substitution gives distinct notions of the mode of acting, even to persons not much conversant in such disquisitions, and we wish to make it familiar to the mind, because it gives an easy solution of the most complicated problems, and furnishes the practical carpenter, who has little science, with solutions of the most difficult cases by experiment. A festoon, as we called it, may easily be made ; and we are certain that the forms into which it will arrange itself are models of perfect frames.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>