<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>28.    In order to determine the strain on the axis, let OY (fig. 7) be the axis of rotation, retained in a fixed position by tile two pivots S, T, and suppose a force = F applied to the body at P, in the direction PQ, which is supposed to lie in a plane perpendicular to OZ. In the plane perpendicular to the axis, and containing PQ, let the rectangular axes OX, OY be drawn, and let <hi rend="italic">x, y, z</hi>  be the co-ordinates of a particle <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  the projection of which on the plane X Y is at A, and let <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  denote its distance from the axis of rotation, so that <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  = OA = √(x<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + y<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) ; also let<hi rend="italic">&lt;f</hi>  = the angle which OA makes with OX. If we now suppose <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  to be the angular velocity communicated to the body, then <hi rend="italic">rw</hi>  is the velocity with which the point A revolves, and the direction of this velocity is in the perpendicular to OA, and from OX towards OY, whence the velocity of A in the direction OX is — <hi rend="italic">wr</hi>  sin. p, and <hi rend="italic">wr</hi>  cos. p in the direction OY. But <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  sin. p = <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  cos. <hi rend="sup">,</hi>p =<hi rend="italic">x ;</hi>  therefore the velocity of A in the direction OX is — <hi rend="italic">wy,</hi>  and in the direction O Y it is + <hi rend="italic">wχ.</hi>  The quantities of motion in these directions are therefore respectively — <hi rend="italic">wydm</hi>  and + <hi rend="italic">wxdm ;</hi>  and the integrals of those expressions extended to the whole mass of the moving body give the whole quantities of motion in those directions, namely, — <hi rend="italic">wfydm,</hi>  and + <hi rend="italic">wfxdm.</hi>  On denoting the mass by M, and the co-ordinates of its centre of gravity by <hi rend="italic">x<hi rend="sub">γ</hi></hi>  and <hi rend="italic">y<hi rend="sub">1</hi>,</hi>  we have (from the well-known expressions for these co-ordinates) <hi rend="italic">fydm</hi>  = M<hi rend="sub">ι</hi>y,, and<hi rend="italic">fxdm </hi>= M∙τ,, therefore — <hi rend="italic">wfydm</hi>  = — wMy,, and + <hi rend="italic">wfxdm </hi>= + wMr<hi rend="sub">1</hi>.</p><p>29.    Now, since the body is supposed to be put in motion by a force F acting in a plane parallel to X0Y, let <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">β</hi>  be the angles which its direction makes with parallels to OX and OY respectively ; then the components of F in those directions are F cos. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  and F cos. <hi rend="italic">β.</hi>  But these two forces are evidently equal respectively to the two former, together with the pressures on the pivots estimated in the same directions ; therefore, calling <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  tlle pressures sustained by the point S in the directions OX and OY, and <hi rend="italic">fl, &lt;f</hi>  the pressures sustained by T in the same directions, we shall have</p><p><hi rend="italic">p + p' =</hi>  F cos. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  + wMy,, <hi rend="italic">q + q'</hi>  = F cos. <hi rend="italic">β —</hi>  wM≈<hi rend="sub">1</hi>.</p><p>In order to determine <hi rend="italic">p, p∕, q, q<hi rend="sup">,</hi>,</hi>  it is still neccssary to find two other equations. These will be obtained by considering, that in respect of the plane XOY, the moments of the forces acting on the two pivots, resolved in the directions <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>  must be equal to the moments of the resultants of all the forces or quantities of motion due to the rotation estimated in the same directions. Let <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  = OS, and <hi rend="italic">h'</hi>  = OT, the moments of the resolved forces which act on the pivots in the directions parallel to OX and OY are <hi rend="italic">ph + p'h</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">qh + q<hi rend="sup">,</hi>h! ;</hi>  and the resultants of the quantities of motion in the same two directions being — <hi rend="italic">wfydm </hi>and + <hi rend="italic">wfxdm,</hi>  their moments in respect of the plane OXY are respectively — <hi rend="italic">wfyzdm</hi>  and + <hi rend="italic">wfxzdm ;</hi>  therefore</p><p><hi rend="italic">ph + ]ik' = — wfyzdm, qh + q<hi rend="sup">,</hi>k' = + wfxzdm.</hi>Combining these with the preceding two equations, <hi rend="italic">p, ji, q,</hi>  ?/ are obtained in terms of known quantities.</p><p>30.    If the axis of rotation OZ be one of the principal axes of the system which intersect at O, then, by (24), <hi rend="italic">fyzdm</hi>  = 0 and <hi rend="italic">fxzdm</hi>  = 0, whence <hi rend="italic">ph</hi>  + ρ'A<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  = 0, and <hi rend="italic">qh + tfh<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  =</hi>  0, and consequently <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">h'</hi>  both vanish, and the percussions sustained by the axis pass through the origin O- Let R represent the single force or shock which the axis supports in this case, and <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  the angle which its direction makes with the axis OX ; then, by (29),</p><p>R cos. <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  = F cos. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  + wMy,, R sin. <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  = F cos.<hi rend="italic">β — wYlx<hi rend="sub">l</hi>,</hi>from which two equations R and <hi rend="italic">&lt;ρ</hi>  are both determined.</p><p>31.    It would be a desirable thing in machines which</p><p>derive their efficacy from a rotatory motion, to apply the pressures arising from the power and from the resistance opposed by the work in such a manner as to annihilate or diminish this pressure on the supports of the axis of motion. Attention to this theorem will point out what may be done ; and it is at all times proper, nay necessary, to know what are the pressures in the points of support. If we are ignorant of this, we shall run the risk of our machine failing in those parts ; and our anxiety to prevent this will make us load it with needless and ill-disposed strength. In the ordinary theories of machines, deduced entirely from the principles of equilibrium, the pressure on the points of support (exclusive of what proceeds firom the weight of the machine itself) is stated to be the same as if the moving and resisting forces were applied immediately to these points in their own directions. But this is in all cases erroneous ; and, in cases of swift motions, it is greatly so. We may be convinced of this by a very simple instance. Suppose a line laid over a pulley, and a pound weight at one end of it, and ten pounds at tlle other ; the pressure of the axis on its support is eleven pounds, according to the usual rule ; whereas we shall find it only 3¼¼. For the direction of the pressure R being in this case parallel to the axis <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>  and the force F also acting in the same direction, we have cos. <hi rend="italic">φ </hi>= 0 cos. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  = 0, sin. <hi rend="italic">φ —</hi>  1, cos. <hi rend="italic">β</hi>  = 1, y<hi rend="sub">1</hi>  = 0, and the two equations of (30) give the single equation</p><p>R = F — ιcMι<hi rend="sub">1</hi>.</p><p>If we now call the radius of the pulley 1, the moment of the moving force isl0×l — l×l = 9j and the moment of inertia (13) is 10 × l<hi rend="sup">s</hi> + 1 × l<hi rend="sup">l</hi> = 11 ; therefore (14) the angular velocity<hi rend="italic">w</hi>  = -⅛. But the distance of the centre of gravity from the axis of motion is also ⅛ because the two weights may be supposed in contact with the circumference of the pulley; therefore, since M = 11, ∞Mr, = -<hi rend="sub">j</hi><hi rend="sup">9</hi>, × S<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  × ^⅛ <hi rend="sup">=</hi>  ⅝⅛∙ Now F = 10 + 1 = 11, therefore R = 11— ¾¼ = ¼¼ = 3-<hi rend="sub">j</hi><hi rend="sup">z</hi><hi rend="sub">r</hi>  pounds, which is the pressure sustained by the axis.</p><p>32.    If we suppose R = 0, the two equations (30) will express the conditions that must be fulfilled in order that the axis may receive no shock from the action of the impressed force F. This supposition gives the equations</p><p>F cos. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  = — wMy,, F cos. <hi rend="italic">β =</hi>  wMz<hi rend="sub">1</hi>, from which, since cos.<hi rend="italic">β =</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  we deduce</p><p><hi rend="italic">— y-<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">a =z x<hi rend="sub">λ</hi></hi>  cos. <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  or — <hi rend="italic">y<hi rend="sub">l</hi></hi>  tan. <hi rend="italic">a = x<hi rend="sub">l</hi>.</hi></p><p>Now’, if a plane be conceived to pass through the axis OZ and the centre of gravity of the body, and if we denote by ∙ψ the angle which it makes with the plane XOZ, we shall have a·, = <hi rend="italic">y<hi rend="sub">1</hi></hi>  tan. +; and therefore, since.r, = —<hi rend="italic">y<hi rend="sub">l</hi></hi>  tan.&lt;x, tan. ∙ψ = — tan. <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>  From this equation it follows that the direction PQ of the impressed force is perpendicular to the plane which passes through the axis and the centre of gravity. It now remains only to find the distance of the point of impulse P from the axis. Let <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  = this distance, and r, = distance of centre of gravity from the axis ; the above equations give F<hi rend="sup">2</hi>cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>α =<hi rend="italic">w"bVy<hi rend="sub">1</hi>",</hi>  F<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">a zz</hi>  w<hi rend="sup">s</hi>M⅛<hi rend="sub">1</hi><hi rend="sup">s</hi>, whence F<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  = je<hi rend="sup">2</hi>M<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  (r,<hi rend="sup">s</hi>  + y,<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) = w'M<hi rend="sup">2</hi>r,-, and F = wMr<hi rend="sub">1</hi>. But (14)<hi rend="italic">w</hi>  = F∙Λ -÷- <hi rend="italic">fridm ;</hi>  therefore, by substitution,</p><p><hi rend="italic">ΓP<hi rend="sup">i</hi>(li)l</hi></p><p>F = F∙AMr<hi rend="sub">1</hi> +∙<hi rend="italic">fridm,</hi>  and consequently A = jj∣—∙∙</p><p>33.    Hence it appears that the conditions which must be fulfilled in order that the axis may receive no shock w’hen the body is struck, are, 1st, that the direction of the force be in the plane of the two axes which make with the axis of rotation a system of principal axes ; <hi rend="italic">2d,</hi>  that its direction be perpendicular to the plane which passes through the axis and the centre of gravity ; and, <hi rend="italic">3d,</hi>  that the distance of the point of its application from the axis be <hi rend="italic">fridm </hi>÷ Mr,.</p><p>34.    The point determined by these conditions is called the <hi rend="italic">centre of percussion</hi>  of the system. The centre of per-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>