<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>alone !<hi rend="sup">,</hi> Alas ! how terrible to imagine a being in possession of such endowments, who could bring himself to think of death!—able to turn back upon his path and meet immortal youth, to see again the morning of his day, and find, in renewed life and beauty, a disguise impenetrable to his former enemies ; yet, in the sadness of his experience, so dreading the mistakes and persecutions of his fellow-men, as to choose rather to lie down with the worm and seek oblivion in the seats of rottenness and corruption.”</p><p>None of Godwin’s other tales have been popular. “ His man of feeling feels but for himself;” and, indeed, the character is in some points so unintelligible, and in others so odious, that notwithstanding many beauties of detail, we cannot wonder at the unpopularity of <hi rend="italic">Fleetwood.</hi>  The same sort of objections apply to the insane vindictiveness of <hi rend="italic">MandevUle. Cloudesley,</hi>  the child of Godwin’s old age, is only remarkable for the gentle beauty of the style, and the contrast which the calmness of the story (turning, like <hi rend="italic">Caleb Williams,</hi>  on the discovery of a murder,) presents to the rapidity and sullen energy of his first production.</p><p>No writer has come so near the manner of Godwin as Charles Brockden Brown, an American novelist, an imitator of the English author, but in a free and noble spirit of imitation. He certainly had not Godwin’s power of mental analysis, and not much of that pathetic tenderness which, contrasted with the general sternness of his tone, shews like araiπbowagainstatroubled sky. He was altogether more prosaic; dealing, indeed,rather with the material than the moral sublime ; producing his strong effects by scenes of sickness, danger, death, or the explosions of insanity ; and often making his characters mere <hi rend="italic">phantasmata,</hi>  which interest us only as the means by which a series of agitating incidents are brought into connexion. But he had a good deal of the same eloquence, and the same dark and mysterious power of imagination ; a certain intensity of portraiture, w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>hether of mental emotion or things external ; great skill in working up a chain of singular events that keep curiosity and suspense upon the stretch, or impress us with a sense of danger and anxiety, and of which he loves to furnish an explanation from those phenomena in our nature which are little understood, such as somnambulism, trances, spontaneous combustion, or ventriloquism. In these respects<hi rend="italic">Wieland, Ormond, Edgar Bluntly,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Arthur Mervyn</hi>  have all nearly the same character, nor do they differ materially in point of merit. Brown has singular power in the delineation of solitude of all kinds, whether the silence of lonely forests, broken only by the howl of panthers, or of deserted mansions dropping to decay. There is one picture of this kind in <hi rend="italic">Arthur Meτvyn,</hi>  of an empty house, evacuated during the yellow fever in Philadelphia, silent and dark in the day time, with the sunshine streaming in through the closed doors and shutters, and faintly discovering that every thing remained undisturbed since its desertion, which produces a strong feeling of awe, and oppresses the spirits with an unaccountable sadness.</p><p>No other novelist of any ability can be said to have adopted the manner of Godwin with success, except his accomplished daughter, the authoress of <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein,</hi>  a production of much originality in its conception, though the execution of the work is unequal, and the whole portion which relates to the self-education of the monster, who is the creation of the new Prometheus, almost ludicrously improbable.</p><p>Several female novelists, towards the close of the eighteenth century, deserve notice, whose tales, though now little read, have the merit either of pathetic or humorous delineation. In the first of these classes are Mrs. Inchbald and Charlotte Smith ; in the latter Madame D’Arblay, or to use the name by which she was best known, Miss Burney.</p><p>The fame of Mrs. Inchbald rests upon her <hi rend="italic">Simple Story. </hi>The title perhaps is but of doubtful application to a novel,</p><lb/><p>which is really complicated with strong and varied passions, which turns on the fate and fortunes of persons plaoed in very peculiar relations to each other, and like Shakspeare’s <hi rend="italic">Winters Tale,</hi>  unites two distinct stories relating to different personages, between the action of which “ time has slid o’er sixteen years ;” for the Perdita of Mrs. Inchbald’s second part is the daughter of that Lady Elmwood, for whose misfortunes and indiscretions our sympathies had been engaged in the first, and who, almost in a sentence, is suddenly consigned to guilt, and to the grave. Dorriforth only remains the connecting link between the two portions of the tale. It is a proof of considerable merit in the novel, that so hazardous an experiment as that of transferring our sympathies to actors in a great measure new to the scene, has not been unsuccessful ; that the interest is, notwithstanding, kept up, partly by the real pathos of some of the scenes, and the natural traits of passion in others, such as that where Lord Elmwood, receiving his deserted daughter as she falls into his arms, calls her by the maiden name of her guilty mother, as if all that passed since those days of innocence had faded from his mind like a dream ; and partly by the dramatic nature of the situations which, though sometimes violent, are generally picturesque and agitating, and the movement of the dialogue, which every where shows the skill of a practical writer for the stage. Her second novel, entitled <hi rend="italic">Nature and Art,</hi>  has been generally and justly reckoned much inferior to the <hi rend="italic">Simple Story.</hi></p><p>Charlotte Smith, (1749—1806) though her novels are extremely defective in plot, betraying marks of haste, and tinged with a melancholy easily to be accounted for from the depressing circumstances under which they were generally composed, cannot be confounded with the ordinary day-labourers for the circulating library, “ who turn a Persian tale for half a crown.” Sir Walter Scott, in one of those kindly notices by which he delighted to cheer the heart of struggling genius, or to do justice to the memory of talents which time was consigning somewhat too rapidly to oblivion, has given her credit for great powers of satire mixed with pathos, and characters sketched with “ firmness of pencil and liveliness of colouring.” The satire indeed seems to have been pretty indiscriminate, since it extends to her own husband, whose pecuniary improvidence and sanguine temperament are glanced at in the character of the projector, who hoped to make a fortune by manuring his estate with old wigs. But apart from satire, the <hi rend="italic">Old Manor House,</hi>  the only one of her novels with which we are acquainted, is really entitled to the character of an interesting and well-written tale. We have a lively recollection of the <hi rend="italic">Manor House</hi>  itself, its neighbourhood, its sea-side scenes, the strange domineering Lady of the Manor, Mrs. Rayland, whom Sir Walter Scott describes as a sort of Queen Elizabeth in private life, and the natural interest which she has succeeded in giving to the love story which is going on within the ancient walls.</p><p>The popularity once enjoyed by the novels of Miss Burney, appears now to have been somewhat overrated, at least we are at a loss to discover any thing in her first work, <hi rend="italic">Evelina,</hi>  except the extreme youth of the writer, then only eighteen, to account for that burst of approbation with which it appears to have been received in 1778 by such men as Burke, Reynolds, and Johnson. She wrote no doubt with sprightliness, with some humour of a broad and superficial kind, and undoubtedly possessed considerable talent in drawing bores and personages of low* manners or odd habits from vulgar middle life ; in imagining scenes of awkward mistakes in society, and exaggerating the teasing distresses thence arising to her heroines and other personages of more refined manners or higher pretensions. Indeed, to mimickry she appears, from her father’s account, to have had a strong leaning from her childhood ; but when she rises from mere manners and habits to paint feelings, we see little but indecision on one hand, or exaggeration on the other. With-</p></body></text></TEI>