<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the rope, the groove of the sheaves shall move such a space as is equivalent to the length of rope that is designed to be made by every turn. When the rope has passed through these sheaves, it is coiled upon a reel in such a manner as merely to require tying up ; but if too unwieldy for reeling, it is coiled on a revolving platform. Such is an outline of the process of making shroud-laid ropes by Mr Chapman’s machinery. For cable-laid ropes the same or similar machinery is used, the chief difference being, that in cable-laid ropes the twists are contrary, and the disparity of turns in the strands and rope not so great as in shroud-laid ropes ; for which reasons, if the same machine be used, the means must be provided for making the shaft to assume contrary motions, and making them to move in different proportions.</p><p>“ By the method previously described,” says Mr Chapman, “ for making a complete rope at one operation, I, during the act of making the strands, unite them into a rope by means of what I then call a rope-shaft, in which they are all concentred, and receive the twist which forms them into a rope ; but I also occasionally omit the concentring of them, and the subsequent part of the operation, during the making of the strand or strands, and in place of twisting them into a rope, I only draw the strand forward as made, and coil it or them in any manner whatsoever, they in this instance having no rotative motion. The apparatus for drawing them forward is not fixed to the revolving shaft, containing the reel or reels and other necessary appendages, but may be permanent, and receive its motion in any proportion whatever to the revolutions or twists given to the strand by that shaft.</p><p>“ The principles of making the strand in these two different ways are obviously portions of the process that would, as has been described, make the whole rope at one operation. And these two methods of making the strand, independently of making the complete rope, are reducible to the following principle : That in making a strand simply, one end need only to be twisted, and the other held from turning, but that both be permitted to pass forward, and progressively change place ; and that the yams be, if deemed necessary, so regulated as to come off these reels in such a manner as the part of the strand they come into may require.</p><p>“ There is a third method of making a strand, compounded of the two preceding, which may be followed, viz. that of using two revolving shafts in place of one ; the reels being placed on one of them, and the strand coiling upon the other. These two shafts ought to turn in contrary directions to each other.”</p><p>The part of the invention in which a common rope-walk is made use of is thus described by the inventor : “ At the head of the ropey, or in any other part, I fix upon pins so many reels as will contain all the yarns requisite for a strand, or the given number of strands determined to be made at one time, each reel containing one or more yarns ; then in the instance of making three strands, I fix to three different hooks on the foreboard of a sledge, so many yarns, separately concentring to each other, as are requisite; the yarns being previously passed through the openings of these separate fixed tops or yam-guides, one opposite to or correspondent with each hook. Before, or on the face, or on the face of each top, toward the sledge, there may or may not be fixed a cylinder, such as I have described, below the laying block at the head of the rope-shaft. The yarns are then to be prevented from passing too easily off their reel, either by a pressure on the reels themselves, or on the yarns in their passage to or upon their separate tops, or in any manner that will permit them to come off as wanted.</p><p>“ The men are then to heave upon, or turn round, the hooks of the sledge in the usual way ; and the only remaining difference consists in the sledge being drawn progressively backwards, as the strand is making, until the</p><p>whole, or any determinate part, of the strand be made. The process of drawing back thc sledge may be done in various ways ; amongst others, by a rope to a capstan, moved either by a horse or men, according to the strength requisite.” When the strands are thus twisted, the rope may be completed in the usual way. Such, then, is a brief outline of the general features of these important inventions of Mr Chapman ; but his own specification, with illustrative drawings, will be found in the ninth volume of the first series of the Repertory of Arts.</p><p>1798. In this year also Mr Belfour obtained a patent ft&gt;r an improvement on his former machinery; and in 1799 Mr Belfour’s machinery was adopted in the government-yards, and the sum of L.4000 was paid to the inventor for his superintendence of the erection of his machine, and the use of his patent.</p><p>1798. November 8th, Mr Chapman at this time patented an invention, which was so to regulate the motion of the sledge that for every revolution of the strand it should move backward through the exact length of axis assigned to it, and thus render the twist uniform. The sledge, in this case, travelled backwards on a railroad ; and along the whole length of the walk, a rope, called a ground-rope, was laid. This rope was passed in the form of an S round two or more grooved wheels, which were pressed together so as to bind the rope, and having upon their axles toothed wheels connecting them with each other, and with the hooks for twisting the strands, which in this case were driven by one great crank. Thus, when the hooks were driven by the crank to twist the strands, the sledge was also moved backwards by the grooved wheels acting upon the rope ; and by changing the connecting toothed wheels the backward motion could be given in any ratio to the twist of the hooks. Besides this, Mr Chapman connected the sledge by a rope to a horse capstan at the foot of the walk ; and as the horse’s power applied to the capstan could not draw the sledge faster backwards than tile ground-rope permitted, the spare power was of course given in aid of the twisting of the strands by means of the wheels which connect that operation with the backward motion.</p><p>1798.    November 17th, Mr John Curr of Sheffield took a patent for forming flat ropes for the use of mines, &amp;c. “ The said flat rope may be formed,” says Mr Curr, “ by connecting two or more small ropes sideways together, by sewing or stitching, lapping, or interlacing them with thread, or small rope made of hemp, flax, or other fit material, or with brass or iron wire, in such a manner as to prevent their separating from each other, and so as to cause them to exhibit, as nearly as possible, a flat form, or flat pliable rope.</p><p>1799.    April 30th, Mr Belfour obtained another patent for a further improvement on his invention. This consisted, among other things, in winding a number of yarns, not exceeding four, upon each reel, and forming them, as before, into strands. He farther proposed to spin the hemp after having been tarred ; and also to place a spinning-wheel at each end of the rope-walk, to enable the spinners to spin both up and down in the manner now practised. If we mistake not, this method of spinning up and down is mentioned by Duhamel as being in use in his time. However this be, it was, on Mr Belfour’s recommendation, adopted in the government rope-works, and, according to the report of Mr Fenwick, the master rope-maker at Chatham, a saving was effected by it to the amount of a sixth part of a day’s work to each man.</p><p>1799. July 26th, Mr William Chapman, in conjunction with Mr Edward Chapman, took a patent for many improvements in the art ; the first of which was for machinery to spin the yarns in such a manner that the fibres of hemp, on entering the thread, were shortened in proportion to their proximity to the axis ; and further, that by this machinery, women, children, and invalids could be employed as spinners.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>