<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>His private Memoirs and Diaries, with a selection from his correspondence and other papers, were published by his sons in 1840, in two volumes octavo. An <hi rend="italic">Eloge,</hi>  by M. Constant, was published at Paris in 1819.    (b. l.)</p><p>ROMNEY, NEW, a town in the county of Kent, in the Lathe of Sheepway, seventy-two miles from London. It was once a place of much more importance than it is at present. It is surrounded with rich but unhealthy marshes, and is defended against the sea by a strong dyke, called Dunchurch Wall, on which is a good carriage road over the marshes. The population was in 1801, 755; in 1811, 841; in 1821, 962, and in 1831,983.</p><p>ROMORANTIN, an arrondisement of the department of the Loire and Cher, in France, eight hundred and eleven square miles in extent. It comprehends six cantons, divided into forty-eight communes, containing, in 1836, 47,722 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name at the junction of the Romorantin and the Saudre, and has some beautiful promenades on the bank of the former river. It contains 1200 houses, with 7181 inhabitants, who manufacture to a considerable extent woollen cloth and tanned leather.</p><p>ROMSEY, or Rumsey, a large market and borough town of the county of Hants, seventy-three miles from London. It is in the division of Andover, of the hundred of King’s Sombome, and stands on the river Test, on the road between Southampton and Salisbury, and is surrounded by pleasant meadows, which, by irrigation, are rendered highly fertile. It is divided into two parishes; with one church in common, a spacious building in the form of a cross, which, in ancient times, was the chapel of a richly endowed abbey. All the early abbesses were of royal blood, and so distinguished by their piety as to be deemed saints. The trade, which formerly consisted in making woollen stuffs, has nearly been annihilated; by the late law it elected annually four aldermen and twelve counsellors, who chuse the mayor. The population was in 1801, 4274; in 1811, 4297; in 1821,5128; andin 1831,5432.</p><p>ROMPEE, or Rompu, in <hi rend="italic">Heraldry,</hi>  is applied to ordinaries that are represented as broken; and to chevrons, bends, or the like, whose upper points are cut off.</p><p>RONA, one of the Hebrides, is reckoned about twenty leagues distant from the north-east point of Ness in Lewis, and is about a mile long, and half a mile broad.</p><p>RONCESVALLES, a valley in Spain, in the province ofNavarne, and district ofSanguessa. It stands at the foot of the Pyrenees, and is the largest valley in the province, but covered with wood. The town of the name is small, but on the great road from France to Madrid, having a church, an Augustin monastery, and an hospital. It has become a place of celebrity from the warlike deeds which the spot has witnessed, both by the defeat of Roland and the twelve peers of France at a remote period, and by the operations under the Duke of Wellington and Marshal Soult.</p><p>RONDA, a city of Spain, in the kingdom of Granada, and province of Andalusia. Ronda is about four thousand five hιmdred feet above the level of the sea, but being surrounded with mountains of vast elevation, it is, in fact, with regard to them, a largely extended valley. The mountains that surround it are more or less covered with snow throughout the whole year; and it is conveyed to the cities of Seville, Cadiz, Gibraltar, and other places, for the daily consumption of their luxurious inhabitants. The plain on which the city stands is one of the most verdant and fertile spots in this the best part of Spain. This city, long a Roman station, under the name of Arunda, abounds with inscriptions, monuments, and ruins of that people, which has been diligently explored by sundry antiquarians. The inhabitants amount to about twenty thousand. Longevity is</p><lb/><p>so very general, that it is a proverb in Andalusia, that in Ronda a man at eighty is still a boy. The public buildings are numerous, but not striking, though some of the churches and convents have the ornaments and riches so commonly belonging to spiritual edifices in this country.</p><p>ROORTERPOOR, a considerable town of Hindustan, province of Delhi, district of Morabad, forty-two miles north hy east from Bareilly. Long. 79. 20. E. Lat. 29. 1.</p><p>RONSARD, Peter de, a French poet, was born at the castle of Poissoniere in Vendomois in 1524. He was descended of a noble family, and was educated at Paris in the college of Navarre. Academical pursuits not suiting his genuis, he left college, and became page to the duke of Orleans, who resigned him to James Stuart, king of Scots, married to Magdalene of France. Ronsard continued in Scotland with King James upwards of two years, and afterwards went to France, where he was employed by the duke of Orleans in several negotiations. He accompanied Lazarus de Baif to the diet of Spires. Having from the conversation of this learned man imbibed a passion for the belles-lettres, he studied the Greek language with BaiPs son under Dorat. It is reported of Ronsard, that his practice was to study till two o’clock in the morning; and when he went to bed, to awaken Baif, who resumed his place. The muses possessed in his eyes an infinity of charms; and he cultivated them with such success, that he acquired the appellation of the <hi rend="italic">Prince of Poets</hi>  of his time. Henry II. Francis II. Charles IX. and Henry III. loaded him with favours. Having gained the first prize of the <hi rend="italic">Jeux Floraux,</hi>  they thought the reward promised below the merit of the work, and the reputation of the poet. The city of Toulouse caused a Minerva of massy silver of considerable value to be made and sent to him. This present was accompanied with a decree, declaring him <hi rend="italic">The French Poet, </hi>by way of distinction. Ronsard afterwards made a present of his Minerva to Henry II., and this monarch appeared as much eluted with this mark of the poet’s esteem for him, as the poet himself could have been had he received the present from his sovereign. Mary, the beautiful and unfortunate queen of Scots, who was equally sensible of his merit with the Toulonese, gave him a rich set of table-plate.</p><p>He wrote hymns, odes, a poem called the <hi rend="italic">Franciad, </hi>eclogues, epigrams, sonnets, &amp;c. In his odes he takes bombast for poetic raptures. He wishes to imitate Pindar; and by labouring too much for lofty expressions, he loses himself in a cloud of words. He is obscure and harsh to the last degree; faults which he might easily have avoided by studying the works of Marot, who had, before he wrote, brought French poetry very near to perfection. But what could be expected from a man who had so little taste, that he called Marot’s works, ‘ a dunghill, from which rich grains of gold, by industrious working, might be drawn ?’ He has, however, some pieces not destitute of real merit; and there are perhaps few effusions of the French muse more truly poetical than his Four Seasons of the Year, where a most fertile imagination displays all its riches. Ronsard, though it is doubtful whether he ever was in orders, held several benefices in commendam; and he died at Saint-Cosme-les-Tours, one of these, December 27, 1585, being then 61 years of age. He appeared more ridiculous as a man than as a poet; he was particularly vain, and his immoderate indulgence in pleasure, joined to his literary labours, served to hasten his old age. In his 50th year he was weak and valetudinary, and subject to attacks of the gout. He retained his wit, his vivacity, and his readiness at poetic composition, to his last moments. Ronsard’s poems have been published in folio, in quarto, and in 10 volumes duodecimo, in 1567.</p><p>ROOD, a quantity of land equal to forty square perches, the fourth part of an acre.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>