<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>appearance of this edition, Mr Bowles published “ A final Appeal to the Literary
                Public, relative to Pope, in Reply to certain Observations of Mr Roscoe, in his
                Edition of that Poet’s Works ; to which are added, some Remarks on Lord Byron’s
                Conversations, so far as they relate to the same subject and the Author : in Letters
                to a Literary Friend.” To this publication Mr Roscoe speedily replied in “ A Letter
                to the Rev. W. Lisle Bowles, A. M. Prebendary of Sa-rum, &amp;c. in Reply to his ‘
                Final Appeal to the Literary Public relative to Pope.’” His edition, as well as his
                Letter, obtained a favourable notice in the Quarterly Review for October 1825 ; and
                Mr Bowles was induced to publish “ Lessons in Criticism to William Roscoe, Esq. F.
                R. S. &amp;c. in Answer to his Letter to the Rev. W. L. Bowles, on the Character and
                Poetry of Pope. With further Lessons in Criticism to a Quarterly Reviewer.” These
                lessons in criticism were not very satisfactory to the public, and Mr Roscoe wisely
                desisted from any further controversy.</p>
            <p>In 1827 he published an edition of the Life of Lorenzo in two, and of the History of
                Leo in four volumes octavo. He had now reached an advanced period of life, and
                had begun to feel the pressure of age. Towards the close of tllis year, he was
                suddenly attacked with paralysis, which affected one side of hie face, and deprived
                him of the use of one hand ; but medical aid was promptly procured, and he recovered
                the use of his hand, as well as of his speech. Botany had been among the number of
                his favourite pursuits. He had been a contributor to the Transactions of the
                Lin-næan Society, and was regarded as no mean proficient in this science. After his
                recovery from the paralytic attack, he published the fifteenth and concluding number
                of a splendid volume on Monandrian Plants. Towards the end of June 1831 he
                experienced a severe atcack of influenza; and after he seemed to be recovering, he
                was on the 27th of that month seized with a violent fit of shivering, accompanied
                with almost total prostration of strength. The near approach of death he
                contemplated with calm resignation to the will of God. On the 30th he closed his
                mortal career, after having completed the seventy-eighth year of his age. The
                proximate cause of his death was an effusion into the chest. His remains were
                interred in the burying ground of the Unitarian chapel in Renshaw Street, the
                service being performed by his intimate friend Mr Shepherd. Six sons and two
                daughters survived him. One daughter he had lost in her infancy, and a son in his
                mature age. His eldest daughter was married to Thomas Jcvons, Esq. of Liverpool. One
                of his sons, who still survives, is well known as a man of letters. Another has too
                speedily followed the father to the grave. He was a barrister at law ; and, besides
                several works connected with his own profession, he published an interesting though
                somewhat diffuse account of his honoured father’s life.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p>
            <p>Dr Traill, the friend and physician of this eminent man, speaks of him in the
                following terms. “ In person, Mr Roscoe was tall and rather slender. In early life
                he possessed much bodily activity. His hair was light auburn, almost inclining to
                red; his full grey eye was clear and mild ; his face expressive and cheerful. As he
                advanced in life, the benevolent expression of his countenance remained, but the
                vivacity of the features was tempered into a noble dignity, which it was impossible
                to see without respect and admiration ; while the mouth bespoke taste and feeling,
                and the clustering hoary hair round his temples gave a venerable air to his manly
                features....Of the qualities of his heart, as a private individual, it is impossible
                to speak too highly. In the relations of husband, father, and friend, his conduct
                was most exemplary ; and it would be</p>
            <p>difficult to point out a man who possessed the fascination of manner which attracts
                and rivets attachment, in a higher degree than William Roscoe.”@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >2</hi>    (x.)</p>
            <p>ROSCOMMON, an inland county in the province of Connaught, in Ireland, is bounded on
                the north by the county of Sligo, on the east by those of Leitrim, Longford, and
                Westmeath, on the south-east by the King’s County, on the south-west by Galway, and
                on the west by the same county and by Mayo. It extends over a surface of
                609,405 acres, of which 453,555 are cultivated, 131,063 are uncultivated mountain or
                bog, and 24,787 are under water. According to Ptolemy, it was inhabited by the
                Auteri ; afterwards the tribes or septs of the O’Conors, O’Kellys, M'Dermots,
                O'Flanegans, O’Flyns, and O’Hanlys, were the chief possessors of it. Shortly after
                the arrival of the English in the reign of Henry II. it was seized upon by the new
                settlers, and their maintenance of it secured by the erection of several fortresses.
                For a long period afterwards the whole province was considered as consisting but of
                two counties, that of Roscommon being one, and all the remainder, with the county of
                Clare included, the other, under the name of the county of Connaught. This
                arrangement continued until the beginning of the reign of Elizabeth, when the whole
                province underwent a new classification, and the county of Roscommon was divided
                into the baronies of Athlone, Ballintubber, Boyle, Moycarnon, and Roscommon. At the
                close of the war of 1641, nearly all the former proprietors were dispossessed for
                having espoused the royal cause, and their possessions transferred to the republican
                adventurers and soldiers ; since which period, that branch of the O’Conor family,
                once sovereigns of all Ireland, now known by the name of the O’Conor Don, is
                the only one of the former possessors who holds any part of ancestral possessions in
                the country. The five baronies are subdivided into fifty-three parishes, and four
                parts of parishes, the remaining parts of which are in some of the adjoining
                counties. According to the ecclesiastical arrangements of the country, Roscommon
                contains fifty-seven parishes, of which fifty-one are in the diocese of
                Elphin, three in Tuam, two in Clonfert, and one in Ardagh. The seat of the bishopric
                of Elphin is in the town of the same name in the county.</p>
            <p>Roscommon is in shape long and narrow, extending sixty miles in a northern and
                southern direction, whilst its breadth from east to west, where greatest, is but
                thirty-two miles ; and it decreases gradually until it terminates in a point in its
                southern extremity. The greatest part of it is level, forming the western portion of
                the central flœtz limestone field of Ireland ; varied, however, by frequent
                inconsider-ble elevations, and by long low ridges or escars formed of limestone
                gravel. In the north the country rises into rugged mountains with abrupt precipitous
                sides and flattened summits, the highest of which, Bracklieve and Slieve Corkagh,
                are upwards of a thousand feet above the level of the sea. The equally wild though
                less elevated range of the Curlew Mountains also forms part of the northern
                boundary. The Slieve Bawn Mountains range along the middle part of the eastern
                boundary. Slieve Aluyn, in the west, is also of considerable height. No large river
                passes through the county, but both its eastern and western limits are watered by
                navigable streams. To the east the Shannon rolls its immense volume of waters along
                that whole side, and on the west the Suck, which is navigable for barges to
                Ballina-sloe, unites with the Shannon at the extreme south point. The rivers in the
                interior, which are small and insignificant, are all tributaries to one or other of
                these main channels, and chiefly to the former, discharging themselves into
                their</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The Life of William Roscoe, by his son, Henry Roscoe. Lend.
                1833, 2 vols. 8vo. </p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>Edinburgh New Philosophical Journal,
                vol. xiii. p. 220.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
