<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>given to the wheel, the top was moved slowly up the walk, by the workman, the reels at the same time giving out the yams as they were taken up by the twisting. When the workman arrived at the first separator, the iron rods were, by the contrivance already alluded to, at once withdrawn, and the yarns left free, and so the workman proceeded until he arrived at the reel-frame, when the turning or heaving at the hook was stopped, and the strand prevented from untwisting, by being seized in a kind of nipper formed of iron. The ends of the yams were then unfastened from the reels, and the strand was completed. By increasing the size of the reel-frames and separators, and by using three top-minors fixed to a sledge or otherwise, three strands could at the same time have been formed. The strands formed by this machinery were then laid together into ropes in the ordinary manner.</p><p>1793. In April 12th of this year, Mr Richard Fothergill obtained a patent for rope-machinery, embracing the following objects : First, freeing the hemp from its native husk, and fitting it for the subsequent processes ; secondly, dressing the hemp, and drawing it out into slivers fit for spinning ; thirdly, spinning the hemp ; and, fourthly, twisting or making it into ropes or cordage. All these operations required no rope-walk to carry them on. Engravings of the machinery will be found in the fourteenth volume of the second series of the Repertory of Arts.</p><p>1793. In April 25th, Mr Joseph Huddart took out a patent for certain improvements in the formation of ropes. His method of registering the strands, in order to acquire an additional degree of strength, by giving the length of the yarns which compose the strand a certain ratio, according to the angle and hardness or compression the rope is intended to be laid with, and thereby acquiring a more equal distribution of the strain upon the yarns than ropes made in the common way, consisted of the following principles : First, by keeping the yarns separate from each other, and drawing them from bobbins which revolve, to keep up the twist whilst the strand is forming ; secondly, by passing through a register which divides them by circular shells of holes, the number in each shell being agreeable to the distance from the centre of the strand, and the angle the yarns make with a line parallel to it, and gives them a proper position to enter ; thirdly, by a cylindrical tube, which compresses the strand, and maintains a cylindrical figure to its surface ; fourthly, by a gauge to determine the angle which the yarns in the outside shell make with a line parallel to the centre of the strand when registering, and according to the angle made by the yams in this shell, the length of all the yarns in the strand will be determined ; lastly, by hardening up the strand, and thereby increasing the angle in the outside shell, which compensates for the stretching of the yams and compression of the strand.</p><p>In this, as in Belfour’s invention, the rcgistering apparatus was moved up the rope-walk by the twisting of the strand ; but the machine differs from Belfour’s in the following particulars. First, in place of the bobbins or reels being fixed in an upright frame, they are placed in horizontal ranges, each range rising higher from the front towards the back part of the machine. Secondly, in place of the separator of Belfour, sets of horizontal rails, notched to receive the yams, and hung in cleats fixed to upright posts, are placed at regular intervals down the walk, so as to keep the yarns separate the whole length of the strand. Thirdly, in place of Mr Belfour’s <hi rend="italic">top minor,</hi>  a plate pierced with concentric circles of holes is made use of, the circles being about two inches asunder ; and behind this plate a smaller plate, pierced with a similar number of holes, is fixed, the holes in the latter plate being so close together as merely to keep the yarns clear of each other. Immediately behind this last plate is fixed a tube made of thin steel, of a spring temper, and in two parts longitudinally ;</p><p>the thin edges of the one part overlapping those of the other, and the two parts being compressed by a thong or wire wound round them several times, and fastened to the jaws of an instrument called a heaver. By means of this, the yarns, in passing through the tube, can be compressed by a constant force ; and if the yams be thicker or smaller in different parts of the strand, the tube will expand or contract, to suit the difference of size.</p><p>In addition to these, an instrument called a register-gauge is used to measure the angle of twist of the yarns in the strands, with the view to employ the same twist when the strands are formed into a rope. Some of the parts of the machinery above noticed, it will be seen, have been adopted by other inventors, and some of them are still in use.</p><p>1797, September 13. At this time Mr William Chapman of Newcastle obtained a first patent for laying, twisting, or making ropes or cordage, of any number of yams or strands, or any number of threads tarred or untarred, from the size of a cable down to the smallest line formed of more than one thread. The machinery for this purpose was less complicated than those formerly mentioned, but was only capable of forming ropes on the common principle. In the month of January 1798 he obtained a patent for Scotland for further improvements in rope-machinery, and containing the substance of his former one and of another taken out for England on the 6th of March</p><p>1798. The inventions embrace the making of ropes either by stationary machines, or by moving machinery on a rope-walk. In the former, the operations of forming the yarns into strands, twisting the strands into a rope, and coiling away the rope, on reels or otherwise, go on at the same time. One of the arrangements of the machinery by which these different operations are carried into effect, is as follows. Three or more discs, according to the number of strands, are placed round a common centre, with their planes inclined to each other in such a manner that their produced axes would meet in a given point. These discs are by the inventor termed strand-tables, and each of them is fixed to a hollow shaft, capable of revolving round its axis ; which shaft is called the strand-shaft or upper shaft. These shafts are on the sides of the discs which are inclined to each other. On the opposite sides of the discs yarn-reels are suspended on spindles, on which they can turn freely. The yams from the reels are passed through the shafts, and by the turning of the discs or strand-tables they are twisted into strands. In a part of the shaft there is a transverse opening to admit of two blocks of hard wood or other matter being applied on each side to press the yarns, and retard their passage through the shafts, so that they may be twisted to the degree required. These blocks are called press-blocks or compressors, and are held together by springs or weights. Instead of blocks the patentee sometimes substitutes rollers moving round their axes, and holding the yarns by their friction. Besides these, the yams pass through a perforated plate called a yarn-guide.</p><p>The strand-tables all move round in one direction, and the strands as they proceed from the shafts are concentrated into a point, over a fixed grooved block, corresponding to the top in the ordinary process. Behind this block the strands are received into a hollow axis, which turns round in a direction contrary to the twist of the strand-tables, and in which the strands are formed into a shroud-laid rope, by being twisted by the apparatus attached to the shaft. This consists of a pair of wheels or sheaves, moving easily on their axes, to admit the rope a free passage, and at the same time compel it to twist equally round with the shaft. These sheaves are grooved in such a manner as to prevent the rope from turning sideways, and are called twisting-sheaves. Instead of the sheaves moving freely on their axes, such a motion may be given to them as. in every revolution of the rope-shaft, which makes one turn</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>