<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that we may be able in every case to distinguish between the force expended in the entry of the water into the conduit or canal, and the force employed in overcoming the resistances along the canal, and in preserving or accelerating its motion in it.</p><p>The motion of running water is produced by two causes : 1. The action of gravity ; and, 2. the mobility of the particles, which makes them assume a level in confined vessels, or determines them to move to that side where there is a defect of pressure. When the surface is level, every particle is at rest, being equally pressed in all directions ; but if the surface is not level, not only does a particle on the very surface tend by its own weight towards the lower side, as a body would slide along an inclined plane, but there is a force, external to itself, arising from a superiority of pressure on the upper end of the surface, which pushes this superficial particle towards the lower end ; and this is not peculiar to the superficial particles, but affects every particle within the mass of water. In the vessel ACDE (fig. 6), containing water with</p><p>an inclined surface AE, if we suppose all frozen but the extreme columns AKHB,</p><p>FGLE,and a connecting portion HKCDLG, it is evident, from hydrostatical laws, that the water on this connecting</p><p>part will be pushed in the direction CD ; and if the frozen mass BHGF were moveable, it would also be pushed along. Giving it fluidity will make no change in this respect ; and it is indifferent what is the situation and shape of the connecting column or columns. The propelling force (MNF being horizontal) is the weight of the column AMNB. The same thing will obtain wherever we select the vertical columns. There will always be a <hi rend="italic">force</hi>  tending to push every particle of water in the direction of the declivity. The consequence will be, that the water will sink at one end and rise at the other, and its surface will rest in the horizontal position <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  O <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  cutting the former in its middle O.</p><p>This cannot be, unless there be not only a motion of perpendicular descent and ascent of the vertical columns, but also a real motion of translation from K towards L. It perhaps exceeds our mathematical skill to tell what will be the motion of each particle. Newton did not attempt it in his investigation of the motion of waves, nor is it at all necessary here. We may, however, acquire a very distinct notion of its general effect. Let OPQ be a vertical plane passing through the middle point O. It is evident that every particle in PQ, such as P, is pressed in the direction QD, with a force equal to the weight of a single row of particles whose length is the difference between the columns BH and FG. The force acting on the particle Q is, in like manner, the weight of a row of particles = AC — ED.</p><p>Now if OQ, OA, OE, be divided in the same ratio, so that all the figures ACDE, BHGF, &amp;c. may be similar, we see that the force arising solely from the declivity, and acting on each particle on the plane OQ, is proportiona. to its depth under the surface, and that the row- of particles ACQDE, BHPGF, &amp;c. which is to be moved by it, is in the same proportion. Hence it unquestionably follows, that the accelerating force on each particle of the row is the same in all. Therefore the whole plane OQ tends to advance forward together with the same velocity ; and in the instant immediately succeeding, all these particles would be found again in a vertical plane indefinitely nearer to OQ ; and if we sum up the forces, we shall find them the same as if OQ were the opening of a sluice, having the water on the side of D standing level with O, and the water on the other side standing at the height AC. This result is extremely different from that of the hasty theory of Guglielmini. He considers each particle in OQ as urged</p><lb/><p>by an accelerating force proportional to its depth, it is true ; but he makes it <hi rend="italic">equal</hi>  to the weight of the row OP, and never recollects that the greatest part of it is balanced by an opposite pressure, nor perceives that the force which is not balanced must be distributed among a row of particles which varies in the same proportion with itself. When these two circumstances are neglected, the result will be incompatible with observation. When the balanced forces are taken into the account of pressure, it is evident that the surface may be supposed horizontal, and that motion should obtain in this case as well as in the case of a sloping surface ; and indeed this is Guglielmini’s professed theory, and what he highly values himself upon. He announces this discovery of a new principle, which he calls the energy of deep waters, as an important addition to hydraulics. It is owing to this, says he, that the great rivers are not stagnant at their mouths, where they have no perceptible declivity of surface, but, on the contrary, have greater energy and velocity than farther up, where they are shallower. This principle is the basis of his improved theory of rivers, and is insisted on at great length by all the subsequent writers. Buffon, in his theory of the earth, makes much use of it. We cannot but wonder that it has been allowed a place in the <hi rend="italic">theory of</hi>  rivers given in the great <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie of</hi>  Paris, and in an article having the signature (O) of D’/ilembert. We have been very anxious to show the falsity of this principle, because we consider it as a mere subterfuge of Guglielmini, by which he was able to patch up the mathematical theory which he had so hastily taken from Newton or Galileo ; and we think that we have secured our readers from being misled by it, when we show that this energy must be equally operative w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>hen the surface is on a dead level. The absurdity of this is evident. We shall see by and by, that deep waters, when in actual motion, have an energy not to be found in shallow running waters, by w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>hich they are enabled to continue that motion ; but this is not a moving principle ; and it will be fully explained, as an immediate result of principles, not vaguely conceived and indistinctly expressed, like this of Guglielmini, but easily understood, and appreciable with the greatest precision. It is an energy common to all great bodies. Although they lose as much momentum in surmounting any obstacle as small ones, they lose but a small portion of their velocity.</p><p>At present, employed only in considering the progressive motion of an open stream, whose surface is not level, it is quite enough that we see that such a motion must obtain, and that w'e see that there are propelling forces ; that those forces arise <hi rend="italic">solely</hi>  from the want of a level surface, or from the slope of the surface ; and that, with respect to any one particle, the force acting on it is proportional to the difference of level between each of the two columns (one on each side of the particle) which produce it. Were the surface level, there would be no motion ; if it is not level, there will be motion ; and this motion will be proportional to the want of level or the declivity of the surface : it is of no consequence whether the bottom be level or not, or what is its shape.</p><p>Hence we draw a fundamental principle, that the <hi rend="italic">motion of rivers depends entirely on the slope of the surface.</hi></p><p>The slope or declivity of any inclined plane is not properly expressed by the difference of height alone of its extremities : we must also consider its length ; and the measure of the slope must be such that it may be the same while the declivity is the same. It must therefore be the same over the whole of any one inclined plane. We shall answer these conditions exactly, if we take for the measure of a slope the fraction which expresses the elevation of one extremity above the other divided by the length of the AM</p><p>plane. Thus -^-j, will express the declivity of the plane AF.</p></body></text></TEI>