<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which had been made in this part of hydraulics, that our readers might form some opinion of the many dissertations which have been written on the motion of rivers, and of the state of the arts depending on it. Much of the business of the civil engineer is intimately connected with it ; and we may therefore believe, that since there was so little principle in the theories, there could be but very little certainty in the practical operations. The fact has been, that no engineer could pretend to say, with any precision, what would be the effect of his operations. One whose business had given him many opportunities, and who had kept accurate and judicious registers of his own works, could pronounce, with some probability, how much water would be brought off by a drain of certain dimensions and a given slope, when the circumstances of the case happened to tally with some former work in which he had succeeded or failed ; but out of the pale of his own experience he could only make a sagacious guess. A remarkable instance of this occurred some time ago. A small aqueduct was carried into Paris. It had been conducted on a plan presented to the academy, who had corrected it, and gave a report of what its performance would be. When executed in the most accurate manner, it was deficient in the proportion of five to nine. When the celebrated Desagιdiers was employed by the city of Edinburgh to superintend the bringing in the water for the supply of the city, he gave a report on the plan which was to be followed. It was executed to his complete satisfaction ; and the quantity of water delivered was about one sixth of the quantity which he promised, and about one eleventh of the quantity which the no less celebrated Maclaurin calculated from the same plan.</p><p>Such being the state of our theoretical knowledge (if it can be called by this name), naturalists began to be persuaded that it was but losing time to make use of a theory so incongruous with observation, and that the only safe method of proceeding was to multiply experiments in every variety of circumstances, and to make a series of experiments in every important case, which should comprehend all the practical modifications of that case. Perhaps circumstances of resemblance might occur, which would enable us to connect many of them together, and at last discover the principles which occasioned this connection ; by which means a theory founded on science might be obtained. And if this point should not be gained, we might perhaps find a few general facts, which are modified in all these particular cases, in such a manner that we can still trace the general facts, and see the part of the particular case which depends on it. This would be the acquisition of what may be called an empirical theory, by which every phenomenon would be explained, in so far as the explanation of a phenomenon is nothing more than the pointing out the general fact or law-under which it is comprehended ; and this theory w-ould answer every practical purpose, because we should confidently foresee what consequences would result from such and such premises ; or if we should fail even in this, we should stili have a series of experiments so comprehensive, that we could tell what place in the series would correspond to any particular case which might be proposed.</p><p>There are two gentlemen whose labours in this respect deserve very particular notice, Professor Michelotti of Turin, and the Abbé Bossut of Paris. The first made a prodigious number of experiments, both on the motion of water through pipes and in open canals. They were performed at the expense of the sovereign, and no expense was spared. A tower was built of the finest masonry, to serve as a vessel from which the water was to issue through holes of various sizes, under pressures of from five to twenty-two feet. The water was received into basins constructed of masonry and nicely lined with stucco, from whence it was conveyed in canals of brickwork lined with stucco, and of various forms and declivities. The experiments on the expense of water through pipes are, of all that have yet been made, the most numerous and exact, and may be appealed to on every occasion. Those made in open canals are still more numerous, and are no doubt equally accurate ; but they have not been so contrived as to be so extensively useful, being in general very unlike the important cases which will occur in practice ; and they seem to have been contrived chiefly with the view of establishing or overturning certain points of hydraulic doctrine which were probably prevalent at the time among the practical hydraulists.</p><p>The experiments of Bossut are also of both kinds ; and though on a much smaller scale than those of Michelotti, seem to deserve equal confidence. As far as they follow the same tract, they perfectly coincide in their results, which should procure confidence in the other ; and they are made in situations much more analogous to the usual practical cases. This readers them doubly valuable. They are to be found in his two volumes entitled <hi rend="italic">Hydrodynamique.</hi>  He has opened this path of procedure in a manner so new and so judicious, that he has in some measure the merit of such as shall follow him in the same path.</p><p>This has been most candidly and liberally allowed him by the Chevalier du Buat, who has taken up the matter where the Abbe Bossut left it, and has prosecuted his experiments with great assiduity, and, we must now add, with singular success. By a very judicious consideration of the subject, he hit on a particular view of it, which saved him the trouble of a minute consideration of the small internal motions, and enabled him to proceed from a very general and evident proposition, which may be received as the key to a complete system of practical hydraulics. We shall follow this ingenious author in what we have further to say on the subject; and we doubt not but that our readers will think we do a service to the public by making these discussions of the Chevalier du Buat more generally known in this country. It must not however be expected that we shall give more than a synoptical view of them, connected by such familiar reasoning as may be either comprehended or confided in by persons not deeply versed in mathematical science.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect. I.— </hi><hi rend="italic">Theory of Rivers.</hi></p><p>It is certain that the motion of open streams must, in some respects, resemble that of bodies sliding down inclined planes perfectly polished ; and that they would accelerate continually, were they not obstructed ; but they are obstructed, and frequently move uniformly. This can only arise from an equilibrium between the forces which promote their descent and those which oppose it. Du Buat, therefore, assumes the leading proposition, that,</p><p><hi rend="italic">When water flows uniformly on any channel or bed, the accelerating farce which obliges it to move is equal to the sum of all the resistances which it meets with, whether arising from its own viscidity, or from the friction of its bed.</hi></p><p>This law is as old as the formation of rivers, and should be the key of hydraulic science. Its evidence is clear ; and it is, at any rate, the basis of all uniform motion. And since it is so, there must be some considerable analogy between the motion in pipes and in open channels. Both owe their origin to an inequality of pressure, both would accelerate continually if nothing hindered, and both are reduced to uniformity by the viscidity of the fluid and the friction of the channel.</p><p>It will therefore be convenient to examine the phenomena of water moving in pipes by the action of its weight only, along the sloping channel. But, previously to this, we must take some notice of the obstruction to the entry of water into a channel of any kind, arising from the deflection of the many different filaments which press into the channel from the reservoir from every side. We shall then be able</p></body></text></TEI>