<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Sage enlightens his whole narτative. It is a work which renders the reader pleased with himself and with mankind ; where faults are placed before him in the light of follies rather than vices ; and where misfortunes are so interwoven with the ludicrous, that we laugh in the very act of sympathizing with them. All is rendered diverting, both the crimes and the retribution which follows them.”@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>Though Le Sage rightly considered his characters as his chief object, he was well aware of the pleasing relief which might be given to his story by the judicious combination of the repose of landscape painting with the bustle of incident; and though he does not succeed in bringing before us, with the vividness of Cervantes, the sombre and parched plains or rugged mountain scenery of Spain, his work contains some country pictures, in a style of placid beauty, which are models of stillness, comfort, and serenity. To whom, for instance, does not that modest demesne at Lirias, watered by the Guadalaviar, with its mansion-house of four little pavilions, its garden bordered with orange trees, and ornamented with its basin of white marble, and the quaint, respectable, old Moorish furniture of the apartments, not to mention the olla podridas of Master Joachim, and the revenue of five hundred ducats a-year, rise up before the mind’s eye, as the very ideal of that happy rural retreat which, to each of us, is to be the Euthanasia of a life of carefulness and toil ; making us long for the time when we may be able to say with its fortunate possessor,</p><p>“ Inveni portum ; spes et fortuna valete Sat me lusistis, ludite nunc alios."</p><p>It is unnecessary to dwell long on the romances of the younger Crebillon, (1707—1777), as to which the only circumstance which is remarkable is, that so much frivolity of manner, and real poverty of invention, could have obtained a temporary popularity even by the licence in which they indulged ; yet that they were very popular for a time, we know ; for Sterne represents his fille de chambre inquiring, at a circulating library, for the <hi rend="italic">Egarements du Cœur et de l’Esprit,</hi>  in 1768. French writers, however, appear to recognise in his pictures some resemblance to the society ofthe time ; for D’Alembert says of him, “ he draws with a delicate and just pencil the refinement, the shades, and the graces of our vices.”</p><p>Much higher talent, though, like Crebillon’s, stained by a shameful association with licentious and profligate pictures, appears in the romances of Diderot, (1713—1784). His talent as a narrator, in particular, was scarcely inferior to Voltaire’s. He had the picturesque particularity of Richardson, with a more condensed expression. It is not, however, in his larger and more notorious romances, such as the <hi rend="italic">Religeuse,</hi>  that this talent is displayed. In these the tedium is as conspicuous as the indecency and impiety. It is in such short talcs as <hi rend="italic">ΐHistoire de Mademoiselle de la Chaux,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Les Deux Amis de la Bourbonne,</hi>  short popular simple histories, contrasting strongly with that air of false simplicity, in reality tricked out with sentimental fard and tinsel, which Marmontel (1719—1798) has given to his amusing, but not very moral tales.</p><p>The romances of Voltaire, (1694—1778), such as <hi rend="italic">Zadig, </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Princess of Babylon, Bαbouh</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Candide,</hi>  have but slender pretensions to the title. They are chiefly satirical fictions, or illustrations, in the form of a tale, of irreligious or antisocial opinions. Their wit, their biting irony, their familiarity with the baser parts of human nature, their power of rendering trifles pleasing by the art of narration, are undeniable; but we must not look in them for probable incident, for Voltaire generally chooses, as if on purpose, some extravagant oriental groundwork as his canvass, and borrows from Ariosto, from Gulliver, from the Arabian</p><lb/><p>Nights, or any source which suits his purpose ;—nor for the delineation of natural characters, for both the incidents and personages are merely made the instruments for working out the preconceived theorem. They produce their effect, such as it is, not by their fidelity to nature, but by the ingenious malice with which its features are distorted.</p><p>From the time of Marivaux downwards, the tendency of the French novel had been to narrow the province of incident, and to extend proportionally that of sentiment. With Rousseau, (1712—1778), this tendency reaches its height. The description of feelings, and particularly of such as, though often experienced, are seldom expressed in words, was his peculiar field. Invention, either of character or incident, he has none. To paint one strong passion, to invest vice with an air of insane but reasoning morality,</p><p>“ To make matinées beautiful, and cast O’er erring deeds and thoughts a heavenly hue Of words like sunbeams, dazzling as they past</p><p>this is the main aim of his <hi rend="italic">Julie,</hi>  and the only one in which Rousseau has been at all successful. Even in this respect, too, the declamatory tone, the continued delirium of feeling, the total want of repose, which characterise the work, combined with the pedantry of its dissertations, become painful and oppressive. “ Ce sont des amans,” said Rousseau himself, speaking of his characters, “ et non pas des académiciens.” Never was an apology more misplaced. The real fault of <hi rend="italic">Julie</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">St. Preux</hi>  is, that they have both too much of the academician in their composition, and too little of the lover, so far as the expression of natural passion in simple words is concerned. We have never been able, in reading the romance, to persuade ourselves that its real eloquence was not as dubious as its morality. It is not easy, indeed, in perusing Rousseau’s apostrophes to purity and virtue, to avoid thinking of the strange commentary which his practice furnished to his theory. It was said of Sterne with severity, but perhaps with some justice, that he could bestow upon a dead ass the pity which he denied to a living mother. And the man of nature and of truth, who expends his trembling sensibilities on paper, suffers a fellow-servant to be punished for the theft he had himself committed, and provides for his natural children in the foundling hospital.</p><p>The total corruption of an exhausted society, tottering to its fall, with tile external varnish of gaiety and wit by which it tried to gild its decay, are aptly represented in the licentious romances of Louvet and La Clos ; its still more vulgar profligacy in the coarse and incoherent, but occasionally striking and original novels of Restif de la Bretonne, (1734—1806). The works of the two former writers are unfortunately but too well known ; the numerous and hasty productions of the eccentric printer, who was accustomed often to set up his strange compositions in type, without a manuscript, as the ideas occurred to him, are now almost completly forgotten. Yet Schiller and several eminent German critics, have spoken with high approbation of the vigour and talent which they evince in some parts, however defective or revolting in others. “ I have scarcely <hi rend="italic">imagined</hi>  any thing,” says Restif, in his <hi rend="italic">Drame dc la Vie;</hi>  “ I have simply related ; my life has been so full of events, that I have made four-and-twenty volumes out of it.” Any one, indeed, who writes, as Laharpe says of Restif in his <hi rend="italic">Correspondence Russe,</hi>  under the persuasion, that all that he had seen, and thought, or learnt, deserved to be printed, and who acted faithfully on that principle, could hardly fail to produce compositions with very nearly the merits and demerits of the novels of Restif ; that is to say, with the coarseness of feeling which was natural to the man, with the disjointed air which a set of unconnected incidents from life must present, and yet with that degree of freslmess and truthfulness of painting, which sketches from life almost invariably possess,</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Sir Walter Scott’s<hi rend="italic">Lives of the Novelists—</hi>Le Sage.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>