<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>according to the proportion in which their truth is debased by fiction, or their fiction mingled with truth.</p><p>A moment’s glance at the origin of society will satisfy the reader why this can hardly be otherwise. The father of an isolated family, destined one day to rise into a tribe, and in further progress of time to expand into a nation, may, indeed, narrate to his descendants the circumstances which detached him from the society of his brethren, and drove him to form a solitary settlement in the wilderness, with no other deviation from truth, on the part of the narrator, than arises from the infidelity of memory, or the exaggerations of vanity. But when the tale of the patriarch is related by his children, and again by his descendants of the third and fourth generation, the facts it contains are apt to assume a very different aspect. The vanity of the tribe augments the simple annals from one cause ; the love of the marvellous, so natural to the human mind, contributes its means of sophistication from another ; while, sometimes, the king and the priest find their interest in casting a holy and sacred gloom and mystery over the early period in which their power arose. And thus altered and sophisticated from so many different motives, the real adventures of the founder of the tribe bear as little proportion to the legend recited among his children, as the famous hut of Loretto bears to the highly ornamented church with which superstition has surrounded and enchased it. Thus the definition which we have given of Romance as a fictitious narrative turning upon the marvellousorthesupernatural, might, in a large sense, be said to embrace</p><p>--quicquid Gracia mendax</p><p>Audet in historia,</p><p>or, in fine, the mythological and fabulous history of all early nations.</p><p>It is also important to remark, that poetry, or rather verse, rhythm at least of some sort or other, is originally selected as the best vehicle for these traditional histories. Its principal recommendation is probably the greater facility with which metrical narratives are retained in the memory, a point of the last consequence, until the art of writing is generally introduced ; since the construction of the verse itself forms an artificial association with the sense, the one of which seldom fails to recall the other to recollection. But the medium of verse, at first adopted merely to aid the memory, becomes soon valuable on account of its other qualities. The march or measure of the stanza is gratifying to the ear, and, like a natural strain of melody, can be restrained or accelerated, so as to correspond with the tone of feeling which the words convey ; while the recurrence of the necessary measure, rhythm or rhyme, is perpetually gratifying the hearer by a sense of difficulty overcome. Verse being thus adopted as the vehicle of traditional history, there needs but the existence of a single man of genius, in order to carry the composition a step higher in the scale of literature than that of which we are treating. In proportion to the skill which he attains in his art, the fancy and ingenuity of the artist himself are excited; the simple narrative transmitted to him by ruder rhymers is increased in length ; is decorated with the graces of language, amplified in detail, and rendered interesting by description ; until the brief and barren original bears as little resemblance to the finished piece, as the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi>  of Homer to the evanescent traditions, out of which the blind bard wove his tale of Troy Divine. Hence, the opinion expressed by the ingenious Percy, and assented to by Ritson himself. When about to present to his readers an excellent analysis of the old romance of <hi rend="italic">Ly-bius Disconius,</hi>  and making several remarks on the artificial management of the story, the Bishop observes, that “ if an epic poem may be defined a fable related by a poet to excite admiration and inspire virtue, by representing the action of some one hero favoured by Heaven, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ho executes a great design in spite of all the obstacles that oppose him, I know not why we should withhold the name of<hi rend="italic">epic poem </hi>from the piece which <hi rend="italic">I</hi>  am about to analyse.”@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>Yet although tllis levelling proposition has been laid down by Percy, and assented to by Ritson (writers who have few opinions in common,) and although, upon so general a view of the subject, the <hi rend="italic">Iliad,</hi>  or even the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey of</hi>  Homer, might be degraded into the class of romances, as <hi rend="italic">Le Beau Decoηηu</hi>  is elevated into tllat of epic poems, there lies in ordinary speech, and in common sense, as wide a distinction betw<hi rend="sup">,</hi>een these two classes of composition, as there is betwixt the rude mystery or morality of the middle ages, and the regular drama by which these were succeeded. Where the art and the ornaments of the poet chiefly attract our attention; where each part of the narrative bears a due proportion to the others, and the whole draw’s gradually towards a final and satisfactory conclusion ; where the characters are sketched with force, and sustained with precision ; where the narrative is enlivened and adorned with so much, and no more, of poetical ornament and description, as may adorn, without impeding its progress ; where this art and taste arc displayed, supported, at the same time, by a sufficient tone of genius, and art of composition, the work produced must be termed an epic poem, and the author may claim his seat upon the high and honoured throne occupied by Homer, Virgil, and Milton. On the other hand, when a story languishes in tedious and minute details, and relies for the interest which it proposes to excite, rather upon the wild excursions of an unbridled fancy, than upon the skill of the poet; when the supernatural and the extraordinary are relied upon exclusively as the supports of the interest, the author, though his production may be distinguished by occasional flashes of genius, and though it may be interesting to the historian, as containing some minute fragments of real events, and still more so to the antiquary, from the light which it throws upon ancient manners, is still no more than a humble romancer, and his w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ork must rank amongst those rude ornaments of a dark age, which are at present the subject of our consideration. Betwixt the extremes of the two classes of composition, there must, no doubt, exist many works, which partake in some degree of the character of both ; and after having assigned most of them, each to their proper class, according as they are distinguished by regularity of composition and poetical talent, or, on the contrary, by extravagance of imagination, and· irregularity of detail, there may still remain some, in which these properties are so equally balanced, that it may be difficult to say to which class they belong. But although this may be the case in a very few instances, our taste and habits readily acknowledge as complete and absolute a difference betwixt the epopeia and romance, as can exist betwixt two distinct species of the same generic class.</p><p>We have said of romance, that it first appears in the form of metrical history, professes to be a narrative of real facts, and is, indeed, nearly allied to such history as an early state of society affords; which is always exaggerated by the prejudices and partialities of the tribe to which it belongs, as well as deeply marked by their idolatry and superstition. These it becomes the trade of the romancers still more to exaggerate, until tbe thread of truth can scarce be discern ed in the web of fable which involves it ; and we are compelled to renounce all hope of deriving serious or authentic information from the materials upon which the compounders of fiction have been so long at work, from one generation to another, that they have at length obliterated tile very shadow of reality or even probability.</p><p>The view we have given of the origin of romance will be</p><p>@@@<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Reliques of Ancient EnglishPoeirt),</hi>  III. xxvii. The Prelate is citing a discourse on epic poetry, prefixed to <hi rend="italic">Telemachus.</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>