<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed against the two usurpers; but was abandoned by his own troops, yielded, and was slain. Galerius levied a great army, and marched into Italy against Maximian and Maxentius; who, dreading his power, retired to Gaul, and endeavoured to procure the support of Constantine. This politic prince did not consider it expedient to provoke a war at that time, and for no better cause; and Galerius having withdrawn from Italy, and returned to the east, Maximian and Maxentius returned to Rome. To aid him in the struggle, Galerius conferred the title of emperor on his friend Licinius; and thus there were at once six pretenders to the sovereignty of the empire, namely, Galerius and Licinius, Maximian and his son Maxentius, Maximin, who had been nominated Cæsar by Galerius, and Constantine, the son and successor of Constantius. Among these rivals, Constantine possessed a decided superiority in prudence and abilities, both military and political.</p><p>The harsh temper of Maximian soon led to a quarrel between him and his son Maxentius; and finding himself unable to obtain an ascendancy over one who was no less intractable than himself, he quitted Rome, and went to Gaul to Constantine. There also he found himself disappointed of that power which he so greatly longed to possess, and began to plot against the life of Constantine, his son-in-law. But being detected, he was condemned to death, the only favour shewn to his age and former dignity being permission to choose in what manner he should die. Thus perished one competitor for the throne. Nor did Galerius long survive him. A loathsome disease, contracted by excessive indulgence in habits of sensuality, brought his turbulent life to its termination, leaving his power to be divided between his Cæsars, Maximin and Licinius. There were now four rivals contending for the empire, Constantine, Maxentius, Maximian, and Licinius. Maxentius speedily provoked open hostilities with Constantine, who marched at the head of a powerful army towards Rome.</p><p>It was while Constantine was proceeding on this momentous expedition, that he made an open and public declaration in favour of Christianity. Before that time, the persecuting edicts of Diocletian had been much mitigated by the forbearance and leniency of Constantius ; and Constantine not only followed his father’s example, in being merciful to the persecuted Christians, but even shewed them some marks of positive favour. Very considerable numbers of them, in consequence, flocked to his standards, and swelled the ranks of his army. Their peaceful, orderly, and faithful conduct, contrasting most favourably with the turbulent and dissolute behaviour of those who formed the mass of common armies, won his entire confidence. To what extent this led Constantine to form a favourable opinion of Christianity, or inclined him to view with esteem and respect tenets which had produced such results, cannot be ascertained. How far his avowed reception of Christianity was influenced by the prudence of the politician, how far by the convictions of the convert, it is impossible to determine. The accounts of his dream, and his vision, which united to enforce his trust in Christianity, bear too much the aspect of fiction, or of having been the illusive consequences of mental anxiety, brooding intensely on the possible results of a great religious revolution, to be woven into the narrative of sober history. This, at least, is certain, Constantine caused the <hi rend="italic">cross</hi>  to be employed as the imperial standard, and advanced with it to promised victory.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>After the armies of Maxentius, led by his generals, had sustained two successive defeats, he found it imperatively necessary to rouse himself from his sensual and inactive life at Rome, and to advance against his formidable assailant. He accordingly mustered a very numerous army, put himself at its head, marched out of Rome, and met the host of Constantine near the little river Cremera, about nine miles from the city. A dreadful encounter took place, both parties being stimulated by every motive that could animate men to erect the utmost energies of mind and body. It was not merely a battle of emperors ; it seemed also a strife of religions. At length the troops of Maxentius gave way, wavered, broke, and fled in headlong and irretrievable confusion ; Maxentius himself, endeavouring to enter the city by the Milvian bridge, amidst the crowd of fugitives, was precipitated into the Tiber, and perished, partly weighed down by his armour, and partly encumbered and overwhelmed among numbers of struggling wretches, whose dying gripes knew not to respect the purple.</p><p>Constantine entered Rome victorious, restored to the senate their authority, disbanded the prætorian guards, and destroyed their fortified camp, from which they had so long awed the city and given rulers to the empire. After a brief stay in Rome, he proceeded towards Illyricum to meet Licinius, with whom he had formed a secret alliance before marching against Maxentius. The two emperors met at Milan, where their alliance was ratified by the marriage of Licinius to Constantine’s daughter. During this calm interview, Constantine prevailed upon Licinius to consent to the repeal of the persecuting edicts of Diocletian, and to the issuing of a new edict, by which not only the sanguinary enactments of the former emperor were revoked, but Christianity was encouraged, its religious teachers were honoured, and its adherents advanced to places of trust and influence in the state.</p><p>This placid and beneficial intercourse between the emperors, was speedily interrupted by an irruption of the Franks into Gaul, to which they afterwards gave their name. Constantine hastened to oppose them. Anxious to take advantage of this opportunity to crush separately the two emperors, whom united he could not match, Maximin made a very rapid march against Licinius, and almost succeeded in overpowering him unawares. Licinius however, kept his enemy at bay till he had mu-lcrcd sufficient force, and then gave him a total overthrow near Adrianople. Maximin fled almost alone to Nicomedia, and there died, either of poison or of mortified rage and despair.</p><p>The peace, which had seemed to be established on so firm a foundation between Constantine and Licinius, was soon interrupted. A war, conducted with great skill and courage on both sides, arose fbr the sole supremacy of the empire. But the activity, talents, and enterprise of Constantine prevailed. Licinius was defeated in a bloody battle near Sirmium ; but though defeated, he was not overpowered. He speedily rallied the remains ofhis beaten army, mustered fresh forces, and again met his rival in the field, again to sustain another and a more complete discomfiture. Through the intervention of Constantine’s daugh-</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> It is not necessary to attempt nny explanation of the celebrated dream and vision of Constantine, which have so much engaged the attention of both ecclesiastical and infidel historians. The circumstances, according to the be3t authorities, were the following. While he was marching towards Rome against Maxentius, at the head of his army, on a sudden there appeared in the air, about noon-day, a luminous cross, bearing the following inscription : Έ,<hi rend="italic">∏irf risu, </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">By this Conquer. During the ensuing night, he was directed in a dream, to frame a standard resembling the vision he had seen, aud to inscribe on it, and on the shields of his soldiers, the </hi><hi rend="italic">labarum,</hi>  or monogram of the sacred name of Christ. That such a standard was at that time used, and that Constantine conquered, are historical facts beyond dispute ; for the reality of the dream and tbe vision, we must refer to the testimony of the emperor himself, and of contemporaneous historians.</p></body></text></TEI>