<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>If the body is a heavy straight line suspended by one extremity, the OS = ⅜ of its length ; for making <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  = the length of the rod, we have (18) <hi rend="italic">fridm — ½ a<hi rend="sup">3</hi>,</hi>  and in this case the mass M = <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  and the centre of gravity is at the middle of the line, or <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  = ½β, whence MA = ½α<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, and OS <hi rend="italic">= ffldm</hi>  -÷- MA = ¼α<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  +∙ ½a<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  = ¾Λ.</p><p>This is nearly the case ot a slender rod of a cylindrical or prismatic shape, and it would be accurately so if all the points of a transverse section were equally distant from the axis of suspension.</p><p>If the oscillating body is an isosceles triangle suspended by its apex, and vibrating perpendicularly to its plane, O = ¼ of its height. For let <hi rend="italic">a —</hi>  the height, <hi rend="italic">na</hi>  = the base, j = a section parallel to the base, then <hi rend="italic">y = nx, r = x, </hi>and <hi rend="italic">dm = ydx ;</hi>  whence <hi rend="italic">fridm — τfx^dχ — </hi><hi rend="italic">⅙</hi><hi rend="italic">tιa*</hi>  (when <hi rend="italic">x — a).</hi>  But in this case M = area = ½ <hi rend="italic">a × na = ½ ηa<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  ; </hi>and the distance of the centre of gravity from the vertex being two thirds of the height, we have A = ∣α, whence MA = ¼ nα<hi rend="sup">3</hi>, and consequently OS =<hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  MA = ⅜α.</p><p>48.    The problem to find the centre of oscillation of a sphere suspended by a thread or an inflexible rod, is important on account of its application to the measurement of the seconds pendulum. Let us first suppose that the weight of the thread is insensible in comparison of that of the ball. Let <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  = radius of ball, Z = length of thread from the point of suspension to the ball, and <hi rend="italic">a = l + r</hi>  = distance from the point of suspension to the centre of the ball. The moment of inertia of the sphere in respect of an axis passing through its centre (18) is <hi rend="italic">2Mri</hi>  ; therefore (17) the moment in respect of a parallel axis at the distance <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  is M (α<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  + ¼r<hi rend="sup">i</hi>) ; and on dividing this by MA ( = Mα), we get the distance from the point of suspension to the centre</p><p>2r<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>of oscillation = <hi rend="italic">a + ∙—</hi>, or the centre of oscillation is be-5α</p><p>low the centre of gravity by the distance ¾r<hi rend="sup">2</hi>-+β.</p><p>49.    Let us now suppose the weight of the thread or rod to be taken into account. Let C (fig. 10) be the centre of the ball, G the centre of gravity of the ball and</p><p>rod OA, S the centre of oscillation ; also let <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  = weight of ball, and <hi rend="italic">f∕' =</hi>  weight of rod. The moment of the sphere, oscillating about O, supposing the weight of the rod insensible, is found above = M (β<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  +<hi rend="italic">iri)</hi>  ; and (18) the moment of the rod alone is ½OA<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  = ½Z<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  = ½M'Z<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  (putting M' = mass of the rod) ; therefore, substituting the weightsfor the masses, that is, making M = A, and M'= A<hi rend="sup">,</hi>, the moment of the compound body is A<hi rend="italic">(α°</hi>  + ⅞r<hi rend="sup">i</hi>) +½A'Z<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. Now, to find the position ofG the centre of gravity, we have this theorem in statics, that the product of the whole mass multiplied into the distance of its centre of gravity from the axis, is equal to the sum of the products of the masses of the several parts into the respective distances of their centres of gravity ; that is, putting OG = A, we have (M + M')A = Aα + ½A'Z, and consequently (45),</p><p><hi rend="sub">os</hi> _*(«* + ?»")+ ⅜^<hi rend="sup">s </hi>Aα + ½A7</p><p>50.    Hitherto we have supposed the axes of rotation to be absolutely fixed ; but the rotation may be performed about axes which are themselves in motion, as in the case of a ball or cylinder rolling down an inclined plane. When a ball rolls down an inclined plane, the point of the ball which rests on the plane is hindered from sliding down by friction ; and therefore the ball tumbles, as it were, over this point of contact, and is instantly caught by another point of contact, over which it tumbles in the same manner. A cylinder rolls down in the very same way ; and its motion is nearly the same as if a fine thread had been lapped round it, and one end of it made fast at the head of the</p><p>inclined plane. The cylinder rolls down by unwinding this thread.</p><p>The mechanism of all such motions (and some of them are important) may be understood by considering them as follows : Let a body of any shape be connected with a cylinder HO K (fig. 11), whose axis passes through G, the centre of gravity of the body. Suppose the body suspended from a fixed point A by a thread wound round the cylinder. The body will descend by the action of gravity, and it will also turn round, unwinding the thread. Draw the horizontal line SGO ; this will pass through the point of contact O of the thread and cylinder, and O is the point round which the cylinder <hi rend="italic">begins</hi>  to turn in descending. Let S be its centre of oscillation correspond</p><p>ing to the momentary centre of rotation O.</p><p>The body will begin to descend in the same</p><p>manner as if all its matter were collected in</p><p>S ; for it may be considered, in this instant,</p><p>as a pendulum suspended at O. But in this</p><p>case S will descend in the same manner</p><p>as if the body were falling freely. There</p><p>fore the velocity of G (that is, the velocity</p><p>of descent) will be to the velocity with</p><p>which a heavy body would fall as OG to</p><p>OS. Now since the points O, G, S, are always in a horizontal line, and the radius OG is given, as also OS (43), the velocity of a body falling freely, and of the body unwinding from this thread, will always be in the same proportion of OS to OG, and so will the spaces described in any given time. And thus we can compare their motions in every case when we know the place of the centre of oscillation.</p><p>It follows from this that the weight of the descending body will be to the tension of the thread as OS to GS; for the tension of the thread is the difference between the moment of the rolling body and that of the body falling freely. It is to be remarked, that this proportion between the weight of the body and the tension of the thread will be always the same ; for it has been demonstrated (46), that if O be in the circumference of a circle whose centre is G, S will be in the circumference of another circle round the same centre, and therefore the ratio of OG to OS is constant.</p><p>If a circular body HOK roll down an inclined plane by unfolding a thread, or by friction which prevents all sliding, the space described will be to that which the body would describe freely as OG to OS ; for the tendency down the inclined plane is a determined proportion of the weight of the body. The motion of rotation in these cases, both progressive and whirling, is uniformly accelerated.</p><p>51. In order to give an example of the application of the preceding formulæ for the rotation of bodies about fixed axes to the theory of machines actually performing work, we shall suppose the machine to be the wheel and axle, and that a weight W, attached to a chain passing over the cylinder, is to be raised by means of a power acting on another chain which passes over the wheel. Let the radius of the wheel = <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  the radius of the cylinder = A, and suppose the moving power to be another weight P, or a mass of matter descending by the accelerating force of gravity.</p><p>Since the machine is in this case impelled by an accelerating force, the angular velocity <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  is obtained from thc equation (41), namely,</p><p><hi rend="italic">dw</hi>  _ moment of impelling force <hi rend="italic">dt</hi>    moment of incrtia</p><p>Now, because the weight P acts in a straight line whose distance from the axis = a, the moment of its force is Pa ; and in like manner the moment of the force exerted by W is WA. But this last moment retards the motion, and must be taken as negative ; therefore the moment of the impelling force is Pα — WA. Again, the moment of inertia is made up of three parts : first, the moment of inertia of the</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>