<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>roof ABCD will be as strong as the roof AGD furnished with the king-post and braces, because the truss-beam gives a support of the same kind at B and C as the brace would have done.</p><p>But this roof ABCD would have no firmness of shape. Any addition of weight on one side would destroy the equilibrium at the angle, would depress that angle, and would cause the opposite one to rise. To give it stiffness, it must either have ties or braces, or something partaking of the nature of both. The usual method of framing is to make the heads of the rafters abut on the joggles of two side-posts BE and CF, whilst the truss-beam, or strut as it is generally termed by the carpenters, is mortised square into the inside of the heads. The lower ends E and F of the side-posts are connected with the tie-beam either by mortises or straps.</p><p>This construction gives firmness to the frame ; for the angle B cannot descend in consequence of any inequality of pressure, without forcing the other angle C to rise. This it cannot do, being held down by the post CF. And the same construction fortifies the tie-beam, which is now suspended at the points E and F from the points B and C, whose firmness we have just now shown.</p><p>But although this roof may be made abundantly strong, it is not quite so strong as the plain roof AGD of the same scantling. The compression which BC must sustain in order to give the same support to the rafters at B and C that was given by braces properly placed, is considerably greater than the compression of the braces. And this strain is an addition to the transverse strain which BC gets from its own load. This form also necessarily exposes the tie-beam to cross strains. If BE is mortised into the tie-beam, then the strain which tends to depress the angle ABC presses on the tie-beam at E transversely, whilst a contrary strain acts on F, pulling it upwards. These strains, however, are small ; and tllis construction is frequently used, being susceptible of sufficient strength, without much increase of the dimensions of the timbers ; and it has the great advantage of giving free room in the garrets.</p><p>Were it not for this, there is</p><p>a 'much more perfect form</p><p>represented in fig. 19. Here</p><p>the two posts BE, CF are</p><p>united below. All transverse</p><p>action on the tie-beam is now</p><p>entirely removed. We are</p><p>almost disposed to say that this is the strongest roof of the same width and slope. For if the iron strap which connects the pieces BE, CF with the tie-beam have a large bolt G through it, confining it to one point of the beam, there are five points, A, B, C, D, G, which cannot change their places, and there is no transverse strain in any of the connections.</p><p>When the dimensions of the building are very great, so that the pieces AB, BC, CD, would be thought too weak for withstanding the cross strains, braces may be added as is expressed in fig. 18 by the dotted lines. The reader will observe, that it is not meant to leave the top flat externally ; it must be raised a little in the middle, to shoot off the rain. But this must not be done by incurvating the beam BC. This would soon be crushed, and spring upwards. The slopes must be given by pieces of timber added above the strutting-beam.</p><p>And thus we have completed a frame of a roof. It consists of these principal members : the rafters, which are immediately loaded with the covering ; the tie-beam, which withstands the horizontal thrust by which the roof tends to fly out below and push out the walls ; the king-posts, which hang from fixed points and serve to uphold the tie-beam, and also to afford other fixed points on which we may rest the braces which support the middle of the rafters; and,</p><lb/><p>lastly, the truss or strutting-beam, which serves to give mutual abutment to the different parts which are at a distance from each other. The rafters, braces, and trusses are exposed to compression, and must therefore have not only cohesion, but stiffness. For if they bend, the prodigious compressions to which they are subjected would quickly crush them in this bended state. The tie-beams and king-posts, if performing no other office but supporting the roof, do not require stiffness; and their places might be supplied by ropes, or by rods of iron of one-tenth part of the section that even the smallest oak stretcher requires. These members require no greater dimensions than what is necessary for giving sufficient joints, and any more is a needless expense. All roofs, however complicated, consist of these essential parts ; and if pieces of timber are to be seen which perform none of these offices, they must be pronounced useless, and they are frequently hurtful, by producing cross strains in some other piece. In a roof properly constructed there should be no such strains. All the timbers, excepting those which immediately carry the covering, should be either pushed or drawn in the direction of their length. And this is the rule by which a roof should always be examined.</p><p>These essential parts are susceptible of numberless combinations and varieties. But it is a prudent maxim to make the construction as simple, and consisting of as few parts, as possible. We are the less exposed to the imperfections of workmanship, such as loose joints, &amp;c. Another essential harm arises from many pieces, by the compression and the shrinking of the timber in the cross direction of the fibres. The effect of this is equivalent to the shortening of the piece which abuts on the joint. This alters the proportions of the sides of the triangle on which the shape of the whole depends. Now, in a roof such as fig. 18, there is twice as much of this as in the plain pent-roof, because there are two posts. And when the direction of the abutting pieces is very oblique to the action of the load, a small shrinking permits a great change of shape. Thus, in a roof of what is called pediment pitch, where the rafters make an angle of thirty degrees with the horizon, half an inch compression of the king-post will produce a sagging of an inch, and occasion a great strain on the tie-beam, if the posts are mortised into it.</p><p>This method of including a truss within the rafters of a pent-roof is a very considerable addition to the art of carpentry. But to insure its full effect, it should always be executed, with abutting rafters under the principal ones, abutting on joggles in the heads of the posts. Without this the strut-beam is hard</p><p>ly of any service. We</p><p>would therefore recom</p><p>mend fig. 20 as a</p><p>proper construction of</p><p>a trussed roof ; and</p><p>the king-post which is</p><p>placed in it may be em</p><p>ployed to support the</p><p>upper part of the rafters, and also for preventing the strut-beam from bending in their direction in consequence of its great compression. It will also give a suspension for the great burdens which are sometimes necessary in a theatre. The machinery has no other firm points to which it can be attached ; and the portions of the single rafters which carry this king-post are but short, and therefore may be considerably loaded with safety.</p><p>We observe in the drawings which we sometimes have of Chinese buildings, that the trussing of roofs is understood by them Indeed they must be very experienced carpenters. We see wooden buildings run up to a great height, which can be supported only by such trussing. One of these is sketched in fig. 21. There are some very excellent specimens to be seen in the buildings at Deptford, be-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>