<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the sum of the moments of all the particles of the body in actual motion, this integral expresses the energy or effort of all the resistances made to the rotation by the inertia of the particles, and is therefore called the <hi rend="italic">moment of inertia </hi>of the moving body with respect to the axis from which the distances <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  are reckoned. We have therefore these definitions :</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">moment of a force</hi>  in respect of a given axis, is the product of the force into the perpendicular from the axis upon the line of its direction.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">moment of inertia</hi>  of a body in respect of any axis is the sum of the products obtained by multiplying each particle of the body into the square of its distance from the axis.</p><p>14.    From tlle equation F ∙ <hi rend="italic">h = wfι<hi rend="sup">3</hi>dm</hi>  (12), we have tlle following expression for the angular veloαty, namely,</p><p>F∙Λ</p><p><hi rend="sup">w =</hi> ? ι'j  'i <hi rend="italic">fr-dm</hi></p><p>that is to say, the angular velocity about any axis is equal to the moment of the external or applied force divided by the moment of inertia. This fraction expresses a number ; for the force F may be represented by the product of a mass M into a certain velocity = <hi rend="italic">v,</hi>  so that F = Mt&gt; ; and therefore, since <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  represents a line, the numerator and denominator have both the same dimension. The fraction also expresses the part of the radius which is equal to the arc measuring the angle ; and since the radius is equal to the arc of 57<hi rend="sup">o</hi>∙2958, if we make the radius = 1, we have only to multiply the fraction by 57∙2958 in order to obtain the value of<hi rend="italic">w</hi>  in degrees.</p><p>15.    Since the relation between the angular velocity and the external impelling force is expressed in terms of the moment of inertia, it is evident that this moment is an important element in the theory of rotation. We shall therefore now proceed to consider the subject under a more general view, and point out the method by which it is computed for bodies of any form revolving about given axes.</p><p>Let the different points of a solid body be referred to three rectangular co-ordinates ar, <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>  z, and let <hi rend="italic">dm</hi>  be the differential element of the mass ; then the distance of any particle from the axis <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  is <hi rend="italic">s∕{fl<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi>  + z<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), and, by the definition, the moment of inertia relative to the axis<hi rend="italic">x,</hi>  is ∕(y<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + z<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)<hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  the integral extending to the whole mass of the body. In like manner, the moments of inertia relative to the axes <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  and z are respectively <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  (z<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + z<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)<hi rend="italic">dm</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">f (f<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi>  4" <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">z</hi>'<hi rend="sup">i</hi>) yim∙</hi>  It <hi rend="sup">18</hi>  thus evident that the determination of the moments of inertia, with respect to any body whatever, consists in forming the analytical expression of the product of the differential element of the body into the square of its distance from the axis, and integrating for the whole extent of the body. The integration may always be effected by the method of quadratures.</p><p>16.    Since the same body may be referred to an infinite number of different axes, in respect of all of which the moments of inertia will have different values, it follows that the moment cannot be absolutely defined unless it be referred to a determinate axis. But when it is required to investigate the moments of inertia of a body in respect of several axes successively, it is not always necessary to compute the formula<hi rend="italic">fr<hi rend="sup">2</hi>dm</hi>  for each case. For example, when the moment of inertia has been determined in respect of any one axis, we may find its value in respect of any other parallel axis without further calculation, if we know the mass of the body and the distances of both axes from the centre of gravity.</p><p>17.    The moment of inertia of any body in respect of an axis AO (fig. 4) being given, to find the moment of inertia in respect of another axis <hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  parallel to OA.</p><p>Let the origin of the rectangular co-ordinates be at O, and let <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  be taken on the axis OA, and <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  in the plane of</p><p>OA and <hi rend="italic">oa.</hi>  Also let Z be the place of an element <hi rend="italic">dm, </hi>and Y the projection of Z on the plane <hi rend="italic">xy ;</hi>  and from Y draw YX perpendicular to OA, meeting OA in X and <hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">x ;</hi>  then OX = <hi rend="italic">x,</hi>  XY <hi rend="italic">= y,</hi>  YZ = z. The moment of inertia in respect of the axis OA is <hi rend="italic">fr<hi rend="sup">3</hi>dm =f(y∙ + χ<hi rend="sup">ν</hi>)drn.</hi>  But by hypothesis this is given ; suppose it = MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  (M being the mass of the body), and we have ∕(y<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  +<hi rend="italic">z<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)drn</hi>  = MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>. In like manner, if we assume the distance of<hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  from OA to be A, we have <hi rend="italic">ox</hi>  = r, <hi rend="italic">xY</hi>  = A+y, YZ = z, and the moment of inertia in respect of <hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  is <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  {(A + y)<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  + z<hi rend="sup">s</hi>}<hi rend="italic">dm = k<hi rend="sup">i</hi>fdm </hi>+ 2A<hi rend="italic">fydm</hi>  + ∕(y<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  +<hi rend="italic">z<hi rend="sup">ν</hi>)dm.</hi>  But<hi rend="italic">fk<hi rend="sup">1</hi>dm —</hi>  MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, and<hi rend="italic">f</hi>(y<hi rend="sup">2 </hi>+z<hi rend="sup">,</hi>-)⅛w = MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  ; therefore the moment in respect of the new axis is MΛ<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  +<hi rend="italic">2kfydm.</hi>  Suppose the centre of gravity of the body to be at G ; let GF be perpendicular to the plane <hi rend="italic">xy,</hi>  and draw FE perpendicular to the axes, meeting OA in E and <hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  in e. From the nature of the centre of gravity<hi rend="italic">fydm</hi>  = M ∙ EF ; therefore the moment in respect of <hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  becomes MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + 2A∙M∙EF. But A = cE, and 2M∙A∙EF = 2M∙eE∙EF = M(eF<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  — A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  — EF<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) ; whence we have finally for the moment of inertia in respect of the new axis<hi rend="italic">οa,</hi></p><p>MΛ<hi rend="sup">2</hi> + M∙eF<hi rend="sup">i</hi>-M∙EF<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Corollary</hi>  1. If the original axis OA passes through the centre of gravity G, then EF vanishes, and the moment in respect of tlle new axis <hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  becomes MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + M∙eF<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, or MA<hi rend="sup">2 </hi>+ MA<hi rend="sup">2</hi>. And if<hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  passes through the centre of gravity, then eF vanishes, and the moment in respect of <hi rend="italic">oa</hi>  becomes MΛ<hi rend="sup">2</hi>—M∙EF<hi rend="sup">2</hi>. Hence we infer that the moment of inertia in respect of the axis which passes through the centre of gravity is less than the moment in respect of any other parallel axis.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Corol.</hi>  2. The moment of inertia is the same in respect of every axis parallel to that which passes through the centre of gravity, and is at the same distance from it ; or the same in respect of every straight line which lies in the surface of a cylinder having the centre of gravity in its axis.</p><p>18. We shall now give a few examples of the application of the preceding formulæ.</p><p>I.    Let it be proposed to find the moment of inertia of a very slender rod (the breadth and thickness of which may be neglected), in respect of an axis passing through its extremity and perpendicular to its length.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  = the length of the rod, and <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  = the distance of any point from the axis, then the element of the body is <hi rend="italic">dx,</hi>  and the moment of inertia <hi rend="italic">= fx<hi rend="sup">i</hi>dx,</hi>  the limits of "the integral being <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  = 0 and <hi rend="italic">x = a.</hi>  For those limits we have <hi rend="italic">fx<hi rend="sup">i</hi>dx</hi>  = ⅙α<hi rend="sup">3</hi>, which therefore is the moment of inertia.</p><p>II.    To find the moment of inertia of a very thin rectangle, the thickness of which may be neglected, in respect of an axis coinciding with one of its sides.</p><p>Let the side which coincides with the axis = <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  and the other side = <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  and let <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  be taken in the axis. The co-ordinates of any point in the rectangle being <hi rend="italic">x, y,</hi>  the element of the body is <hi rend="italic">dxdy,</hi>  and the distance from the axis = <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>  therefore the moment of inertia is <hi rend="italic">ffy<hi rend="sup">i</hi>dxdy.</hi>  The integral of this in respect of <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  is/<hi rend="italic">xy°dy,</hi>  which from <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  = 0 to <hi rend="italic">x = a </hi>gives <hi rend="italic">af'y<hi rend="sup">i</hi>dy.</hi>  A second integration gives ½βy<hi rend="sup">s</hi>, which from <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  = 0 to <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  = 6, becomes ⅙αZr<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  ; therefore, since M = αά,</p><p><hi rend="italic">fft/dxdy —</hi>  ⅜aA<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  = ½M ∙ A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.</p><p>III.    To find the moment of inertia of a circle in respect of one of its diameters.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">α</hi>  be the radius of the given circle, <hi rend="italic">r —</hi>  the radius of a concentric circle passing through a point P whose coordinates are <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">y, x</hi>  being taken on the axis of rotation, and <hi rend="italic">r + dr</hi>  the radius of a second concentric circle, very near the other. If we now assume <hi rend="italic">dz — sf(dχ<hi rend="sup">1</hi></hi>  + tfy<hi rend="sup">2</hi>), then <hi rend="italic">dz ∙ dr</hi>  is the area of the elementary surface included between</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>