<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>introduce landscape painting into her romances as a component part of the interest of the piece. The frequency of her pictures of external scenery, and their want of distinctness and local truth, have i ndeed been blamed by many who would willingly, on Puff’s principle, have abridged her descriptions of the rising sun, and dispensed with a great deal about gilding the eastern hemisphere. But it is certain that these descriptions, though occasionally tedious, and sometimes too obviously brought forward upon a principle of melo-dramatic contrast, have a powerful effect in heightening the impression communicated by tlle incidents or tbe sentiments. Set off against the calm beauty of a summer evening, or the magnificent gloom of a thunder storm, her pastoral or banditti groupes stand out with double effect ; while to the charge of vagueness of description, it may be answered, that Mrs. Radcliffe is by no means vague, where distinctness of imagery is, or ought to be her object ; as any one may satisfy himself who recalls to his recollection her description of tbe lonely house by tlle Mediterranean, with the scudding clouds, the screaming sea-birds, and the stormy sea, the scene selected for the murder of Ellena ;—or another picture, in the best manner of Salvator, of the first glimpse of the Castle of Udol-pho rising over a mountain pass, with theslant sunbeam lighting up its ancient weather-beaten towers. Indeed, the whole description of that Appenine fastness, both without and within, is in the best style, not of literal indeed, but of imaginative painting—“fate sits on those dark battlements and frowns:” the very intricacy of its internal architecture, and its endless passages,—a mighty maze, and we fear without a plan,—only serve to deepen the impression of imprisonment and bewilderment and gloom.</p><p>Less, certainly, is to be said for those descriptions in verse wfith which her novels are rather profusely interspersed, and which are, of course, represented as emanating from some of the personages of her stories. Without denying the merit of some of her occasional verses, it is certain that she always shew<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s more of the spirit of poetry in her prose. Indeed, independently of the mediocrity of many of these effusions, they often assume a ludicrous air from their contrast with the circumstances under which they are produced. Under all situations of alarm and anxiety, in the seclusion of convents, and in the castles of Condottieri, where drunken ruffians are brawling “ along the corridor,” paper, pencils, and poetical enthusiasm are never wanting to her heroines, and the sun is seldom suffered to rise or set without a tribute to his beams. Indeed, it is even observable that the poetical sensibilities of her heroines generally become more lively after any domestic calamity, such as the demise of a parent ; as Beau Clincher’sexuberance of spirits was accounted for by the fact, that he was in mourning for his father.</p><p>For a particιdar notice of the individual works of Mrs. Radcliffe, we refer to our biographical article on that subject. Two of them are now wholly and deservedly forgotten. Neither the <hi rend="italic">Castles of Athlin and Dunbayne,</hi>  nor tlle <hi rend="italic">Sicilian Romance,</hi>  crowded with violent yet ineffective incidents, gave any indication of that ability which she afterwards displayed. Of her remaining fictions, it may be said in a word, that the <hi rend="italic">Romance (&gt;f the Forest,</hi>  founded on a French <hi rend="italic">eause celebre,</hi>  has the fewest faults ; that the <hi rend="italic">Italian,</hi>  though extremely unequal, and in the third volume a comparative failure, contains the most striking and dramatic scenes; but that the <hi rend="italic">Mysteries of Udolpho</hi>  is on the whole, and justly, considered the best.</p><p>To be fiιlly enjoyed, tbe Romances of Mrs. Radcliffe must be perused in youth. In after age, they appear too uniformly visionary, and the straight-laced stiffness of her heroines, who never manifest the least warmth except in poetry, “ female punctuation not permitting them to do more,” as Mrs. Malaprop observes, suggests the recollection ofthe pruderies of the pastoral and heroic romance. But when these</p><lb/><p>tales are read in youth, and only remembered in manhood in their better portions, they leave upon the memory a pleasing impression of a varied pageant of gloomy castles and caves, moon-illumined streets and palaces, “dance and Provençal song and vintage mirth,” aerial music floating over haunted forests, or the chant of monk or nun borne to the ear over the waters of some Italian lake, amidst the stillness and the shadows of evening.</p><p>We have devoted a larger space to Mrs. Radcliffe than some may think justly due to the rank in fiction which she occupies,butwehavedone so,—first, because we think justice has seldom been done to the real genius which she threw into the style of fiction she chose to adopt, whatever may be its precise order of precedence in the calendar of fiction ; and, secondly, because, although that style became more universally popular, and more generally imitated than any which had preceded it, she herself, with two exceptions only, which we shall notice, remains the solitary writer of genius by whom it has been adorned. The truth is, that the sarcasms which have been directed against the puerile horrors of Mrs. Radcliffe ought justly to have been confined to the extravagances of her successors, who imitated her manner without either her imagination or her judgment, and conceived that the surest means of producing effect consisted in pressing the springs of the terrible as far as they would go. In the hands of these, “ imitated imitators,” tbe castles became twice as large and ten times as perplexing in their architecture ; the heroine could not open an empty drawer without stumbling on a mysterious manuscript written by her father or mother ; nor leave her room to take a twilight walk, of which heroines are always strangely fond, without stumbling on a nest of banditti ; the gleam of daggers grew more incessant ; the faces of the monks longer and more cadaverous, and the visits of ghosts so common-place, that they came at last to be viewed with the same indifference by the reader,as they were of old by honest Aubrey, or less honest Dr. Dee.</p><p>One word may be said in fhvour of the Romances of Mrs. Radcliffe and her school, addressed to those who think that every romance should embody the moral conveyed in the concluding couplet of the <hi rend="italic">Mourning Bride.</hi>  Their general tendency is moral, poetical justice is in most cases rigidly enforced, and crime punished,and virtue rewarded by some unexpected good fortune, even on this earth. “ All this,” says Mr.Dunlop, “may be very absurd, but life, perhaps, has few better things than sitting at the chimney corner in a winter evening,after a well-spent day,and readingsuch absurdities.”</p><p>The two exceptions from the general dullness and common place of the imitators of Mrs. Radcliffe, are <hi rend="italic">The Monk of'M.G. Lewis,</hi>  which appeared in 1796, and <hi rend="italic">The Montοriο ofMαturin,</hi>  published in 1807, and among the last romances written on that now antiquated plan. Much injustice, we believe, was done to Lewis at the time. A single unfor</p><p>tunate remark of an irreligious tendency, and some descriptions of undue warmth, pardonable in a youth of twenty, and retrenched in the second edition, gave a blow to the popularity of this romance from which it never recovered. And yet the traces of considerable genius are visible both in its plan and in the execution of several of its powerful scenes. The mere hint of the story, that is to say, the general idea of the gradual corruption of a proud, and enthusiastic, and self-relying nature, was taken, as Lewis acknowledged, from that ofthe Santon Barsisa in the <hi rend="italic">Guardian;</hi>  the incident of the escape of the baroness from the banditti, was an expansion, executed with much skill, of the scene in the hut in <hi rend="italic">Count Fathom ;</hi>  for the story of the bleeding nun, he was indebted to a German legend, while he has borrowed several hints for his wandering Jew from the incomprehensible Armenian of Schiller. But to these hackneyed materials he has given a force and look of novelty that are surprising; the escape, the conjuration scene, where the Jew, withdrawing the black ribband, unveils the burning cross on his</p></body></text></TEI>