<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>other consequences are equally contrary to experience. When a stream has its section diminished by narrowing the channel, the current increases in depth, and this is always accompanied by an increase of velocity through the whole of the section, and most of all at the surface; and the area of the section does not increase, but diminishes, all the phenomena thus contradicting in every circumstance the deduction from the theory; and when the section has been diminished by a sluice let down into the stream, the water gradually heaps up on the upper side of the sluice, and, by its pressure, produces an acceleration of the stream below the sluice, in the same way as if it were the beginning of a stream, as explained in the theory. The velocity now is composed of the velocity preserved from the source and the velocity produced by this subordinate accumulation; and this accumulation and velocity continually increase till they become such that the whole supply is again discharged through this contracted section: any additional water not only increases the quantity carried along the stream, but also increases the velocity, and therefore the section does not increase in the proportion of the quantity.</p><p>It is surprising that a theory really founded on a conceit, and which in every one of the most familiar and obvious circumstances is contradicted by facts, should have met with so much attention. That Varignon should immediately catch at this notion of Guglielmini, and make it the subject of many elaborate analytical memoirs, is not to be wondered at. This author only wanted <hi rend="italic">donner prise au calcul ;</hi>  and it was a usual joke among the academicians of Paris, when any new theorem was invented, <hi rend="italic">donnons le à Varignon à généraliser.</hi>  But his numerous theorems and corollaries were adopted by all, and still make the substance of the present systems of hydraulics. Gravesande, Muschenbroeck, and all the elementary treatises of natural philosophy, deliver no other doctrines ; and Belidor, who has been considered as the first of all the scientific engineers, details the same theory in his great work the <hi rend="italic">Architecture Hydraulique.</hi></p><p>Guglielmini was, however, not altogether the dupe of his own ingenuity. He was not only a pretty good mathematician, but an assiduous and sagacious observer. He had applied his theory to some important cases which occurred in the exercise of his profession as inspector of the rivers and canals in the Milanese, and to the course of the Danube ; and could not but perceive that great corrections were necessary for making the theory quadrate in some tolerable manner with observation ; and he immediately saw that the motion was greatly obstructed by inequalities of the canal, which gave to the contiguous filaments of the stream transverse motions, which thwarted and confused the regular progress of the rest of the stream, and thus checked its general progress. These obstructions, he observed, were most effectual in the beginning of its course, while yet a small rill, running among stones, and in a very unequal bed. The whole stream being small, the inequalities bore a great proportion to it, and thus the general effect was great. He also saw that the same causes (these transverse motions produced by the unequal bottom) chiefly affect the contiguous filaments, and were the reasons why the velocity at the sides and bottom was so much diminished as to be iess than the superficial velocity, and that even this might come to be diminished by the same cause. For he observed, that the general stream of a river is frequently composed of a sort of boiling or tumbling motion, by which masses of water are brought up to the surface and again descend. Every person must recollect such appearances in the freshes of a muddy river ; and in this way Guglielmini was enabled to account in some measure for the disagreement of his theory with observation.</p><p>Mariotte had observed the same obstruction even in the smoothest glass pipes. Here it could not be ascribed to</p><lb/><p>the checks occasioned by transverse motions. He therefore ascribed it to friction, which he supposed to diminish <hi rend="sup">v </hi>the motion of fluid bodies in the same manner as of solids ; and he thence concludes, that the filaments which immediately rub on the sides of the tube have their velocity gradually diminished, and that the filaments immediately adjoining to these, being thus obliged to pass over them or outstrip them, rub upon them and have their own velocity diminished in like manner, but in a smaller degree ; and that the succeeding filaments towards the axis of the tube suffer similar but smaller diminutions. By this means the whole stream may come to have a smaller velocity ; and at any rate, the medium velocity by which the quantity discharged is determined, is smaller than it would have been independent of friction.</p><p>Guglielmini adopted this opinion of Mariotte, and, in his next work on the Motion of Rivers, considered this as the <hi rend="italic">chief</hi>  cause of the retardation ; and he added a third circumstance, which he considered as of no less consequence, the viscidity or tenacity of water. He observes that syrup, oil, and other fluids, where this viscidity is more remarkable, have their motions prodigiously retarded by it, and supposes that water differs from them only in the degree in which it possesses this quality ; and he says, that by this means not only the particles which are moving more rapidly have their motions diminished by those in their neighbourhood which move slower, but that the filaments also which w'ould have moved more slowly arc accelerated by their more active neighbours, and that in this manner the superficial and inferior velocities are brought nearer to an equality. But this will never account for the universal fact that the superficial particles are the swiftest of all. The superficial particles, says he, acquire by this means a greater velocity than the parabolic law allows them ; the medium velocity is often in the middle of the depth ; the numerous obstacles continually multiplied and repeated, cause the current to lose the velocity acquired by the fall ; the slope of the bottom then diminishes, and often becomes very small, so that the force remaining is hardly able to overcome the obstacles which are still repeated, and the river is reduced almost to a state of stagnation. He observes that the Rheno, a river of the Milanese, has near its mouth a slope of no more than .¾'', which he considers as quite inadequate to the task ; and here he introduces another principle, which he considers as an essential part of the theory of open currents. This is, that there arises from the very depth of the stream a propelling force, which restores a part of the lost velocity. He offers nothing in proof of this principle, but uses it to account for and explain the motion of water in horizontal canals. The principle has been adopted by the numerous Italian wτiters on hydraulics, and, by various contrivances, interwoven with the parabolic theory, as it is called, of Guglielmini. Our readers may see it in various modifications in the <hi rend="italic">Idrostati&lt;a e Idraulica</hi>  of P. Lecchi, and in the <hi rend="italic">Spmenze ldrauliche</hi>  of Michelotti. It is by no means distinct either in its origin or in the manner of its application to the explanation of phenomena, and seems only to serve for giving something like consistency to the vague and obscure discussions which have been published on this subject in Italy. We have already remarked, that in that country the subject is particularly interesting, and has been much investigated. But the writers of England, France, and Germany, have not paid so much attention to it, and have more generally occupied themselves with the motion of water in close conduits, which seem to admit of a more precise application of mathematical reasoning.</p><p>Some of them have considered with more attention the effects of friction and viscidity. Sir Isaac Newton, with his usual penetration, had seen distinctly the manner in which it behoved these circumstances to operate. In his</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>