<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>longing to the victualling-office, commonly called the <hi rend="italic">Red-house,</hi>  which were erected about the year 1788, and we believe are the performance of Mr James Ar</p><p>row of the Board of Works, one of the most</p><p>intelligent artists in this kingdom.</p><p>Thus have we given an elementary, but a rational or scientific, account of this important part of the art of carpentry. It is such, that any practitioner, with the trouble of a little reflection, may always proceed with confidence, and without resting any part of his practice on the vague notions which habit may have given him of the strength and supports of timbers, and of their manner of acting. That these frequently mislead, is proved by the mutual criticisms which are frequently published by the rivals in the profession. They have frequently sagacity enough, for it seldom can be called science, to point out glaring blunders ; and any person who wili look at some of the performances of Mr Price, Mr Wyatt, Mr Arrow, and others of acknowledged reputation, will readily see them distinguishable from the works of inferior artists by simplicity alone. A man without principles is apt to consider an intricate construction as ingenious and effectual ; and such roofs sometimes fail merely by being ingeniously loaded with timber, but still more frequently by the wrong action of some useless pieces, which produces strains that are transverse to other pieces, or which, by rendering some points too firm, cause them to be deserted by the rest in the general subsiding of the whole. Instances of this kind are pointed out by Price in his British Carpenter. Nothing shows the skill of a carpenter more than the distinctness with which he can foresee the changes of shape which must take place in a short time in every roof. A knowledge of this will often correct a construction which the mere mathematician thinks unexceptionable, because he does not reckon on the actual compression which must obtain, and imagines that his triangles, which sustain no cross strains, invariably retain their shape till the pieces break. The sagacity of the experienced carpenter is not, however, enough without science for perfecting the art. But when he knows how much a particular piece will yield to compression in one case, science will then tel! him, and nothing but science can do it, what will be the compression of the same piece in another very different case. Thus he learns how far it will now yield, and then he proportions the parts so to each other, that when all have yielded according to their strains, the whole is of the shape he wished to produce, and every joint is in a state of firmness. It is here that we observe the greatest number of improprieties. The iron straps are frequently in positions not suited to the actual strain on them ; and they are in a state of violent twist, which both tends strongly to break the straps, and to cripple the pieces which they surround.</p><p>In like manner, we frequently see joints or mortises in a state of violent strain on the tenons, or on the heels and shoulders. The joints were perhaps properly shaped for the primitive form of the truss ; but by its settling, tile bearing of the push is changed. The brace, for example, in a very low-pitched roof, comes to press with the upper part of the shoulder, and, acting as a powerful lever on the tenon, breaks it. In like manner, the lower end of the brace, which at first abutted firmly and squarely on the joggle of the king-post, now presses with one corner in prodigious force, and seldom fails to splinter off on that side. We cannot help recommending a maxim of M. Perronet, the celebrated hydraulic architect of France, as a golden rule, viz. to make all the shoulders of abutting pieces in the form of an arch of a circle, having the opposite end of the piece for its centre. Thus, in fig. 18, if the joggle-point B be of this form, having A for its centre, the sagging of tile roof will make no partial bearing at the joint ; for in the sagging of the roof the piece AB turns or bends round the centre A, and the counter-pressure of the joggle is still directed to A, as it ought to be. We have just now said <hi rend="italic">bends </hi>round A. This is too frequently the case, and it is always very difficult to give the tenon and mortise in this place a true and invariable bearing. The rafter pushes in the direction BA, and the beam resists in the direction AD. The abutment should be perpendicular to neither of these, but in an intermediate direction, and it ought also to be of a curved shape. But the carpenters perhaps think that this would weaken the beam too much to give it this shape in the shoulder ; they do not even aim at it in the heel of the tenon. The shoulder is commonly even with the surface of the beam. When the bearing therefore is on this shoulder, it causes the foot of the rafter to slide along the beam till the heel of the tenon bears against the outer end of the mortise (See Price’s British Carpenter, plate C, fig. IK). This abutment is perpendicular to the beam in Price’s book ; but it is more generally pointed a little outwards below, to make it more secure against starting. The consequence of this construction is, that when the roof settles, the shoulder comes to bear at the inner end of the mortise, and it rises at the outer, and the tenon, taking hold of the wood beyond it, either tears it out or is itself broken. This joint therefore is seldom trusted to the strength of the mortise and tenon, and is usually secured by an iron strap, which lies obliquely to the beam, to which it is bolted by a large bolt quite through, and then embraces the outside of the rafter foot. This strap is very frequently not made sufficiently oblique, and we have seen some made almost square with the beam. When this is the case, it not only keeps the foot of the rafter from flying out, but it binds it down. In this case, the rafter acts as a powerful lever, whose fulcrum is in the inner angle of the shoulder, and then the strap never fails to cripple the rafter at the point. All tllis can be prevented only by making the strap very long and very oblique, and by making its outer end (the stirrup part) square with its length, and making a notch in the rafter foot to receive it. It cannot now cripple the rafter, for it will rise along with it, turning round the bolt at its inner end. We have been thus particular on this joint, because it is here that the ultimate strain of the whole roof is exerted, and its situation will not allow the excavation necessary for making it a good mortise and tenon.</p><p>Similar attention must be paid to some other straps, such as those which embrace the middle of the rafter, and connect it with the post or truss below it. We must attend to the change of shape produced by the sagging of the roof, and place the strap in such a manner as to yield to it by turning round its bolt, but so as not to become loose, and far less to make a fulcrum for any thing acting as a lever. The strains arising from such actions, in framings of carpentry which change their shape by sagging, are enormous, and nothing can resist them.</p><p>We shall close this part of the subject with a simple method, by which any carpenter, without mathematical science, may calculate with sufficient precision the strains or thrusts which are produced on any point of his work, whatever be tlιe obliquity of the pieces.</p><p>Let it be required to find the horizontal thrust acting on the tie-beam AD of fig. 18. This will be the same as if the weight of the whole roof were laid at G on the two rafters GA and GD. Draw the vertical line GH. Then, having calculated the weight of the whole roof that is supported by this single frame ABCD, including the weight of the pieces AB, BC, CD, BE, CF themselves, take the number of pounds, tons, &amp;c. which expresses it from any scale of equal parts, and set it from G to H. Draw HK,</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>