<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tavius. He was the more encouraged to hope for success in consequence of a fierce war in which the Romans had been engaged with the Sabines, and by which they had been considerably weakened. For a time the Latins hesitated to provoke an encounter with Rome; and in the mean while the Sabine war continued to harass the republic. Valerius gained repeated victories over them, and some of the Sabines, wearied with fruitless hostilities, were anxious for peace. Attus Clausus, a Sabine chief of great power, came over to the Romans, became a Roman citizen, and took the name of Appius Claudius, on being admitted into the Patrician order. At length Valerius, after gaining another triumph, died, was buried at the public cost, and mourned by the matrons for a year.</p><p>The entreaties of Tarquinius, and the influence of Mamilius, had by this time prevailed among the Latins, and they prepared for a contest with Rome. Nor were the Romans unaware of the approaching struggle; and that it might be full and final, an opportunity was given on both sides for the dissolution of intermarriages, and such other ties as had been mutually contracted by the two nations. The Romans were determined to meet the decisive struggle as it ought to be met. They created a new magistrate, called a Dictator, to whom was entrusted for a period uncontrolled dominion. He was Master of the people; and he chose to be his second in command another officer, whom he named Master of the knights. The dictator was Aulus Postumius; the master of the horse Titus Æbutius. With these were joined in command the most distinguished Romans who had already signalized themselves in war. On the side of the Latins were Mamilius, and the whole of the exiled Tarquinian family, resolved to regain their sway, or perish in tile attempt. The two armies met at the lake Regillus. The dictator and the banished king encountered hand to hand, but were parted by their followers. Mamilius and Æbutius were likewise separated, after the infliction of mutual wounds. Marcus Valerius fell while rushing into the throng of the fight against Sextus Tarquinius. The exiled princes bore down or put to flight all opposed to them, till the dictator himself, assailing indiscriminately the pursuers and the pursued, turned the tide of battle, and forced his way even into the enemy’s camp. In this battle fell the two sons of Tarquinius, Mamilius, and the chief of the Roman warriors who had been the means of gaining their country’s liberty; but the victory was complete. Tarquinius retired to Cumae, where he died, and the Romans were left to enjoy the victory, so gloriously yet dearly purchased.</p><p>Thus terminate the poetic legends respecting the wars waged between the Romans and the banished Tarquinii; and while it must be evident that a great deal of imaginative embellishments have been added to and intermingled with the course of the actual events, still there is enough of verisimilitude in them to give them currency, as at least a very spirit-stirring representation of what might have occurred. Besides, the effect produced on the Roman character by these poetic lays can scarcely be over-estimated, in stirring them up to that stern, unyielding courage, that unswerving energy of will, and that boundless ambition and confidence in the fortunes of Rome, which gained for them the empire of the world. While, therefore, we admit that it is impossible to state how much of fiction has been introduced into the narrative of these events, we see no reason to discredit the general truth of the history. The pride of the Roman historians concurred with the imagination of the poets, in maintaining to the utmost the glory of Rome; yet even from what they have agreed to record, we may arrive at conclusions somewhat different from those which they were anxious to establish. Rome was undoubtedly taken by</p><p>Porsenna; and within twelve years after the expulsion of the last king, the Romans had lost all their territory on tile Etruscan side of the Tiber, and all their dominion over Latium.</p><p>The principles of political liberty had also been severely shaken. It is plain that the Tarquinian family attempted to render the crown hereditary; and availed themselves of the jealousy between the patrician populus and the plebeian commonalty, to deprive each of their rights, and tyrannize over both. A junction enabled the nation to expel its tyrant; but tile contest cost Rome her independence for a few years, and the loss of all her previous acquisitions. The defeat of the Etruscan army at Aricia enabled the Romans to recover their independence, but left them reduced almost within their original limits immediately around the city. The liberties of the commonalty were in danger in another manner, and from a different foe. Instead of a period of peace in the enjoyment of their recovered freedom after tile decisive battle of Regillus, we find dissensions of the most serious kind arising almost immediately between the patricians and the plebeians. As these contests form a very important part of Roman history, especially in a constitutional point of view, and have been much misunderstood, it is necessary to offer a few remarks on their origin and nature.</p><p>It was the policy of Tarquinius to depress the growing power of the commons <hi rend="italic">(plebs)</hi>  as much as possible, that he might the better succeed in his ambitious designs. In this the patricians <hi rend="italic">(populus)</hi>  injudiciously joined him; and all the wise laws of Servius were repealed, or allowed to fall into desuetude. Additional enactments against debtors were flamed, and every step was taken to reduce tile plebeians to a condition little better than slavery. The wars arising out of the expulsion of the Tarquinian family blended for a time the interests of both classes, by the pressure of a common danger; but no sooner was this pressure removed, than the patricians resumed the oppression to which they had been too much accustomed, and were too prone. Again were the comitia centuriata allowed to fall into neglect, while in the senate, and in the comitia curiata, where they possessed exclusive power, the patricians enacted new laws against debtors, by which the plebeians were grievously oppressed.</p><p>The plebeians being composed generally of the population sprung from conquered cities, and admitted to settle at Rome in the enjoyment of personal freedom, were chiefly occupied in the culture of the public lands, or the lands held by patrician families. The loss of territory sustained by Rome in the Etruscan wars, deprived great numbers of the plebeians of their property and employment. Being reduced to poverty, they were compelled to borrow money from the patricians, whose lands lay chiefly within the Ager Romanus, and were not lost, and who also were alone permitted to enjoy the profits of commerce. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> By tile Roman law of debtor and creditor, when a man borrowed money, and his poverty continued, so that he became insolvent, there were but two resources to which he could betake himself. He might sell himself to his creditor, on the condition, that at the expiration of a stated term, if he did not discharge the debt, he should become the slave of his creditor. This was called the entering into a<hi rend="italic">nexum,</hi>  and the person entering into this conditional sale of himself was called a <hi rend="italic">nexus. </hi>When the day came, the creditor claimed possession, the magistrates awarded it; and the debtor, his family, and all  that belonged to him, passed into the power of the creditor as slaves, and were termed <hi rend="italic">addicti.</hi>  If, on the other hand, a man were unwilling thus to sell himself and family, and resolved to meet in his own person the consequences of his debt, the danger thus incurred was much greater. If he</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  See Niebuhr, vol. i. pp. 571,<hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq</hi>.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>