<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the death of Tristram’s elder brother, enforced by the eloquent stroke of dropping the hat, as if a lump of clay had been kneaded into the crown of it. There is nothing sneering, nothing unkindly, nothing that revolts the better feelings in his playful irony. <hi rend="italic">Circum prœcordia ludU. </hi>That of Swift and Voltaire is blighting like an east wind; the sympathies of the heart close themselves up against it; but beneath the genial and balmy humour of Cervantes and Sterne, they relax and blow like flowers expanding beneath the west wind in spring.</p><p>The wonderful resources of characteristic invention, and the very finest perception of the limits of true humour, are shown in the contrasted characters of the two brothers, the main personages in the history ; the man of pure intellect, restless, nervous, eloquent, hair-splitting, half-crazed by learned theories, which he insists on carrying into action, craving sympathy, and yet courting discussion, as delineated in the elder Shandy ; and the man of pure good nature and benevolence, as drawn in Toby; without learning, with no head for reasoning, but with a heart always in the right place ; eloquent too, in his way, when his feelings are touched, or his favourite pursuits depreciated, (witness his animated and beautiful defence of his reasons for prolonging the war) chaste as a woman, gentle, harmless and credulous as a child ; riding his hobby, in short, in so captivating a manner, that, if the truth were told, most of his readers are in their hearts inclined to mount along with him. There are few, we suppose, who have not been seduced into something of his own mania by the scene on the bowling green, when he discovers the ingenious invention by which Trim, having converted the jack-boots into mortars, is directing a hot fire from these engines against the counterscarp of Lisle ; when the tobacco pipes, withdrawn from the mouth of the corporal, are gradually insinuated into his own, merely to try them ; and puff succeeds puff, till the enthusiast is swept into the torrent of a furious cannonade. Nothing, too, can be at once more humourous or characteristic than that scene where Toby mistakes the elder Shandy’s quotation from Sulpicius’ consolatory letter to Cicero, for a real account of his brother’s trip to the Levant, a stroke of humour so natural in tlle circumstances, and yet so original, that it would of itself be sufficient to prove that Sterne was a man of genius.</p><p>The two great defects of Sterne, as noticed by Sir Walter Scott, are his affectation and his indefensible indecency. For his plagiarisms from other authors, we regard as of little importance. So ingeniously are they turned to account, and so much in general does Sterne improve what he borrows, that he may fairly claim in them tllat right of property which the civil law allowed in articles where the labour bestowed by the borrower exceeded the intrinsic value of the material on which it was bestowed. It must be confessed, however, that few writers have carried their coolness and assurance in this respect so far as Sterne has done, who, not content with denouncing the plagiarisms of authors, has actually stolen from Burton the passage in which he exposes tlle iniquities of his neighbours.</p><p>But the other objections less admit of defence. The affectation of Sterne is the more to be regretted, because his manner in its happiest moods is the very perfection of a lively, spirited, spoken style, idiomatic, imaginative, pliant, and varied. “ Writing, when properly managed,” he himself observes, “ is but a different name for conversation.” Unfortunately he did not always conform his practice to his precept. He is sometimes <hi rend="italic">fade</hi>  in his sentimentality, and aiming after a sort of false sublime in his imagery. Some portions of the story of Maria are examples of the first ; the well-known personification of the recording angel in tlle close of Le Fevre, is an instance of the second. Still more unw'orthy of Sterne are those quackeries of the black page and the white one, the sudden transitions and affected openings of the chapters, with other harlequinades of authorship, which are carried to excess in <hi rend="italic">Tristram Shandy.</hi></p><p>The indecency of Sterne is more obtrusive and indefensible than that of either Fielding or Smollett ; whose highly-coloured scenes seem to be the result of an unchecked imagination, running on heedless whether its course lie through purity or filth. Sterne, on the other hand, goes coldly and deliberately in search of impurity ; seeks for it in books, refines upon it, mixes it up with his reflections, and is continually insinuating some equivoque or double entendre into scenes where we can ill bear with such adulteration.</p><p>Richardson, Fielding, Smollett, and Sterne, are the four great novelists of this period (the reign of George II.) which was pre-eminently the age of novel-writing in England. For though we should indeed be sorry to undervalue the merits of Goldsmith, or the charm of his <hi rend="italic">Vicar of Wakefield,</hi>  we cannot quite rank the powers displayed in that delightful little tale, which appeared in 1763, so highly as the varied invention displayed by tlle writers we have named, upon the broader canvass which they selected. To use his own words, it has many faults, and a hundred things might plausibly be said to prove them beauties. Fortunately, they lie more in the minor parts, than in the essentials of tlle tale. In fact, the improbability ofthe plot is only equalled by the wonderful truth, nature and keeping of the principal character, for the “limæ labor” which, in tllis instance, Goldsmith willingly bestowed upon his style, and on the creation and apposition of traits of character, be scrupled to waste upon the selection of his incidents. The real interest lies in the development in the character of the amiable Vicar, so rich in heavenly, so poor in earthly wisdom ;—possessing little for himself, yet ready to make that little less, whenever misery appeals to his compassion ;—with enough of literary vanity about him to shew that he shares the weaknesses of our nature,—ready to be imposed upon by cosmogonies and fictitious bills of exchange, and yet commanding, by the simple and serene dignity of goodness, the respect even of the profligate, and making “ those who came to mock remain to pray.” Doubtless, the probability and look of life which a character drawn with such quiet strokes of the pencil, and with such sobriety of colouring, possesses, is in some measure owing to the fact, that not a few ofthe incidents of which Goldsmith has availed himself, are drawn from circumstances in his personal history, such as the mistakeof setting out to teach the French English, without recollecting that it was a necessary preliminary for the tutor to acquire a little French himself; but the skill which can make such trifles in real life subservient to the purposes of real fiction, is scarcely less worthy of praise than would have been their original invention. Perhaps there is no better proof of the broad and general truth of delineation which a novel possesses, than our being in the habit of resorting to it in conversation for cases in point, and comic illustrations of our opinions. In this respect the Fleer <hi rend="italic">of Wahefleld</hi>  forms a storehouse of allusion. How naturally does any ridiculous investment in Mexican mines, or Spanish stock, recall to our recollection Moses’ bargain for the gross of green spectacles ? Who is there that has not been reminded of the aristocratic Miss Skeggs turning out to be no better than she should be, notwithstanding her intimacy with the Duchess, and her taste for Shakspeare and the musical glasses, by some case of the same kind within our own experience, where, reversing the denouement of the Double Arrangement, the Knight Templar of the company has sunk into the waiter ? And for our ow n part, we must admit, that we have never been able to treat with due gravity any allusion to the learned speculations of Manetho, Be-rosus, or Sanconiathon, from their indissoluble connexion in our minds with the more finished cosmogony of Jenkinson.</p><p>In one respect Goldsmith rises conspicuously superior to his brethren ; he has no passages, which, dying, he need have</p></body></text></TEI>