<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ing and trembling at the chimæras with which his imagination peopled solitudes—could the phantoms bred in his eccentric brain, and nurtured amidst the fumes of a Berlin tavern, have ever assumed tllat appearance of reality and belief which could render their introduction into a work of fiction at all practicable. Only by a mind accustomed, from a painful experience, to brood over and dissect the origin and connexion of these strange phenomena, half mental half physical, which make “ life a dream,” but with a nightmare accompaniment, could the possible connexion of this phantasmagoria with real existence, in morbid minds, be rendered so far intelligible as to redeem them from the charge of the merest puerility. Hoffmann’s tales, though they constantly suggest the idea that they have had their source in tile inspiration of opium, seem really to be the only compositions in this style of grotesque horror, which can be said to possess the redeeming quality of genius. They remind us of the images of our dreams, calling up before us, as in sleep, long perspectives of gloomy vastness, broken here and there by the light of the strangest ignes fatui, along which are seen, flitting in antic movements, bands of the most fantastic creatures, such as those which, in the pictures of Teniers, disturb the solitude of St. Anthony, or which give a strange blending of the humorous and the horrible to the distempered sketches of Callot. Yet, as a proof that the talent of Hoffmann was by no means confined merely to the fantastic and the supernatural, we may notice his truthful and vigorous picture of the German burgher life of the middle ages, in his <hi rend="italic">Master Martin and his Apprentices,</hi>  and his <hi rend="italic">Mademoiselle de Scudery,</hi>  a tale of vivid and fascinating interest, founded on a historical groundιvork, moving in the simplest and most direct manner towards its object, and exciting the feeling of curiosity and suspense even to the last.</p><p>Some notoriety of an evil kind was obtained by a class of novels, in which the attempt was made to invest sensuality with tlle graces of art, or to merge art in sensuality. Such were the <hi rend="italic">Ardιηghello</hi>  of Heinse (1749—1803), in which painting was made the apology for the introduction of voluptuous pictures, and his <hi rend="italic">Hildegard von Hοhenthal,</hi>  in which music was made to minister to a similar purpose,— no unfit sequel to a literary life which commenced with a translation of Petronius. In truth, in the whole range of the German novels, the tendency to an undue license of this kind is observable. In those of Goethe, though veiled by an appearance of decency, it is sufficiently perceptible ; nor does Tieck appear free from the common taint. Many passages in <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Meister</hi>  are highly objectionable ; and such a novel as the <hi rend="italic">Wahlverwandschαften</hi>  we regard as untranslateable into English.</p><p>Of Goethe’s novels we have already expressed our opinion in our biographical article on Goethe himself. If the merits of a novel consisted, not in exhibiting an epitome of human life, more or less poetically conceived, according to the prosaic or imaginative turn of the writer’s mind, but in speculating ingeniously on painting, agriculture, landscape, gardening, tile rules of good composition, or the state of the theatre, connecting these speculations by a thread of mystical narrative, and introducing us to a set of beings without the least trace of reality about them, who all appear to be playing some theatrical part in a dreamy representation of life, which seems to have no intelligible object,—Goethe may be a great novelist. With an English public, demanding some firm basis of reality, instead of that unsubstantial cloud-land which envelopes us in the <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Meister’s Lehrjahre</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Wandcrjahre,</hi>  and accustomed to insist on a plain meaning as a preliminary to poetical embellishment, he never can be a favourite. A novel which does not explain its purpose without a commentary, seems to violate the essential laws of such compositions ; but a novel, in regard to the object of which no two commentators agree, is an anomaly in literature. Most of the German critics, indeed, though professing a great admiration of these singular performances of Goethe, are careful to confine their observations, in regard to the meaning or object of the novels, to the merest generalities. They describe <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Meister,</hi>  to use the congenial language of an English admirer, as a picture “ of warm, hearty, sunny, human endeavour, a free recognition of life in its depth, variety, and majesty, <hi rend="italic">but as yet nο divinity recognised there?</hi>  The latter portion of the sentence is intelligible, and is unfortunately true, but the rest reminds us of Mr. Dangle’s remark, that the interpreter appears tlle harder to be understood of the two.</p><p>These observations apply, with slight modification, to the novels of Tieck, when be abandons the province of the traditional tale, and attempts subjects connected witll real life ; the characters, the incidents, tlle whole cast of the tale, appear so extravagant, that, but for the grave and laudatory criticism with which these effusions seem invariably to be received by his countrymen, it would be difficult to believe the author serious. His first romance, <hi rend="italic">William Lovef </hi>was a gloomy and revolting extravagance, and his later caprices, such as <hi rend="italic">Das Alte Buch,</hi>  (the Old Book), the Fo-<hi rend="italic">gelscheuche,</hi>  (Scarecrow), <hi rend="italic">Eigcnsinη und Laune,</hi>  (Self-will and Humour), <hi rend="italic">Wundxrlichheiteη,</hi>  (Marvels), are utterly unworthy of a man of genius. Even the merits,ofhis <hi rend="italic">Dich-terlxben,</hi>  (a Poet’s Life), have been greatly exaggerated. Any tale, in which Marlowe and Shakespeare figure as actors, has a certain interest for a Briton ; but beyond some eloquent disputations on the drama, and the formation of a poet’s mind, in which Shakespeare and his companions are made to utter modern German theories, the most opposite to English notions of the sixteenth century, we cannot perceive wherein tlle peculiar merit of this much-lauded performance lies. Tieck has said absurdly and presumptuously of Sir Walter Scott, that “ it is surprising how little he wants to be a poet, but how much that little outw<hi rend="sup">r</hi>eiglιs all that he is.” Let any one who has read Tieck’s<hi rend="italic">Aufmhτ in den Cevenηeη,</hi>  in which he has come in competition with the Scotch novelist on an historical subject, judge whether he has himself made a nearer approximation to that character.</p><p>The talent displayed by Schiller inhis <hi rend="italic">Verbreeher aus Eltre, </hi>and his fine fragment of the <hi rend="italic">Armenian, or the Ghost Seer, </hi>excites regret that he did not give us less of philosophy’, and more of fiction. The latter is an unfinished taleof mystery,of deep interest, the idea of which, it is supposed, was suggested by the juggleries of Cagliostro, and in which Schiller, though he never witnessed the scenery which he describes, has caught the spirit of silence and secrecy which seems to pervade Venice, with the same success as, in hislf<hi rend="sup">z</hi>i7∕zcwt<hi rend="italic">Tell, </hi>he has transported us into the mountain recesses ofthe Ober-land. And Lord Byron has recorded the strong impression made upon his mind by the recollection of the incomprehensible Armenian, one ofthose conceptions which he w as accustomed by anticipation to associate with the image of the city of the sea.</p><p>Several female novelists, too, have respectably supported the pretensions of their sex; such as Fanny Tarnυw, the Baroness de la Motte Fouque, Johanna Schopenhauer, Henrietta Hanke, and Caroline Pichler, the able authoress of <hi rend="italic">Agathocles.</hi>  Many of their productions exhibit talent, grace, and facility of style, but we should be at a loss to name any for which the praise of genius could justly be claimed.</p><p>The class of romances called <hi rend="italic">Krirninal Geschichten,</hi>  t urn-ingon stories of secret guilt discovered by circumstantial evidence,has been a numerous one in Germany. At the head of this class of novelists stands Kruse, who certainly possesses in a high degree a power, which at the present day appears to be rather a rare one,—that of constructing an ingenious and complicated plot, keeping the curiosity constantly on the stretch, and defying conjecture as to the result, till the au-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>