<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>right posts, <hi rend="italic">aaa,</hi>  fig. 3, between which the wheel <hi rend="italic">bb</hi>  is hung on its axis c. A belt from this wheel passes over and gives motion to a number of small pulleys, called whirls, <hi rend="italic">ddd,</hi>  inserted in a circular arc <hi rend="italic">ee, </hi>called the head, fixed to the top of the posts. The axis of each of these pulleys is prolonged in front of the head, and bent into a hook, as shown more distinctly at <hi rend="italic">f;</hi>  and on this hook the fibres of hemp are hung to be twisted.</p><p>The spinning-wheel for the smaller sorts ot threads differs from this chiefly in being smaller, and having the parts slightly modified to suit the diminution of size.</p><p>The operation of spinning is conducted as follows. The spinner takes a bundle of hemp of sufficient size to make one or more threads the whole length of the walk ; he puts this bundle round his waist, the bight or double being in front, and the ends passing each other at his back ; and he secures it in this position by buckling a strap round it, or by fastening it with his apron. He then draws out from the face of his bundle as many fibres as he thinks will make the size of yarn required ; the bight of these fibres he hangs on one of the whirl-hooks, and the wheel being now turned by an assistant, it throws twist or turn into the fibres. The spinner having laid a piece of thick woollen cloth in the hollow of his right hand, with the end hanging over his forefinger, grasps with it the fibres he had drawn out, pressing them firmly with his thumb and forefinger, the interposed cloth preserving his fingers from being cut by the fibres as they pass. He now walks backward down the walk, that is, from the head to the foot, the wheel-man all the while turning the wheel just so fast as to keep the turn or twist up to the spinner, of which he is admonished by signs made by the left hand of the latter, or, in complete establishments, by a bell, the cord of which traverses the walk. The aim of the spinner is to regulate the supply of fibres from his bundle in such a manner as to render the thread equal in size throughout. This he does with his left hand, drawing back the fibres as they enter his right hand in too great number, and pulling forward more when the supply is deficient in quantity. He takes care, too, that many ends of fibres do not come together in the same place, and that they so arrange themselves as that the strength of the thread shall be equal throughout. If the spinner slacken his grasp of the fibres with his fore-finger and thumb, the turn will pass his hand, and the thread will be spoiled ; and it is necessary not only that the thread be firmly grasped by the thumb and fore-finger, but also by the whole hand, that it may be compressed and moulded into a cylindrical form.</p><p>We have hitherto described the operation as performed by one spinner ; but as many spinners may work together as there are whirls in the head. Suppose, then, that all the spinners have set on, as the fastening of their threads to the whirls is termed. They proceed together down the walk, and when they are a few paces below the first rail, <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>  fig. 2, every man throws his thread on one of the hooks, and so at each rail, until they arrive at the foot. They then join the ends of every pair of yarns, and hang them over the post already mentioned ; and for the convenience of afterwards separating them, the pairs are kept apart in the following manner. A piece of twine is tied by its middle to the first pair, a little in advance of the post ; the second pair is then put over the post, and the string is tied over them ; and in like manner every pair is tied in. This is called nettling. The spinners now set on at the foot or back-end wheel, and spin up the walk. The fore-end wheelman having unhooked the yarns from the whirls of his wheel, and hung them over the post, and tied them in pairs as at the back-end, proceeds down the walk, collecting the yarns from the hooks of the rails, and laying them in a heap in the large hooks c, c, fig. 2. When the spinners again spin down the walk, these same operations are performed by the back-end wheel-man. When the collected yams number about 400, they are coiled up in a haul, and are ready either for tarring, or laying into white ropes. Previous to the haul being taken up for tarring, there is a slight turn put into it to keep it from getting entangled in the tar-kettle. In the government rope-works, by the regulations of 1802, the spinners had to produce, from a bundle of hemp weighing 64 lbs., 18 threads of 170 fathoms each ; 400 of such threads constituted a haul, and weighed 12 cwt. 2 qrs, and when tarred 15 cwt.</p><p><hi rend="italic">3dly, Ι'arring.—</hi>The next operation is that of tarring. This is variously performed. Here we shall describe the simplest method of doing it.</p><p>The apparatus used in tarring consists of a copper bedded in brickwork with a proper furnace below, and flues around it. The copper is termed the tar-kettle, and at one side of it is erected a strong frame, in which a capstan works.</p><p>Fig. 4 shows this arrangement. Here <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  is the kettle ; <hi rend="italic">bb</hi>  the frame ; <hi rend="italic">cc</hi>  the capstan, which may be turned either by manual labour, or horse or other power; <hi rend="italic">dd</hi>a truck, on which the haul is being coiled away as it comes from the capstan ; and <hi rend="italic">ee.</hi>  small rollers by which the haul is supported. In the upright nearest the boiler is fixed the nipper for squeezing the superfluous tar out of the haul. The nipper is drawn to a</p><p>larger size in fig. 5. Here <hi rend="italic">aα</hi>  is a copper-plate with a hole in it about two and a half inches diameter ; above it another plate <hi rend="italic">bb </hi>slides, and out of its lower edge a semicircular piece is cut, corresponding to the hole in the lower plate, so that by sliding this plate down, the aperture is diminished.</p><p>A lever <hi rend="italic">dd</hi>  of the second order is fixed at one end to the chain c, and presses on a stud fixed on the upper plate, so that by moving the weight on the lever the yarn may be pressed to the degree necessary as it passes through the aperture ; and as die tar oozes out of the yarn, it is received and carried bacKfy&gt; the kettle by the spout<hi rend="italic">f</hi>  fig. 4.</p><p>The tar having been put into the kettle and heated to the proper degree, which is about the temperature of boiling water, and is known to the workman, in the absence of more correct means, by a scum closing over its surface, the</p></body></text></TEI>