<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>she told what had befallen her, required of them the pledge of their right hands that they would avenge her injuries, then drawing a knife from under her robe, stabbed herself to the heart and died. Her husband and father burst into a loud cry of agony ; but Brutus snatching the weapon from the wound, held it up, and swore by the chaste and noble blood which stained it, that he would pursue to the uttermost Tarquinius and all his accursed race, and thenceforward suffer no man to be king in Rome. He then gave the bloody knife to her husband, her father, and Valerius, and called on them to take the same oath. Brutus thus became at once the leader of the enterprise. They bore the body of Lucretia to the market place. There Brutus addressed the people, and moved them to vengeance. The youth immediately enrolled themselves into an army. Part remained to guard the city, and part proceeded with Brutus to Rome. Their coming raised a tumult, and drew together great numbers of the citizens. Brutus, availing himself of his rank and authority, as tribune of the celeres, or captain of the knights, summoned the people to the forum, and proceeded to relate the bloody deed which the villany of Sextus Tarquinius had caused. Nor did he content himself with that, but set before them in the most animated manner the cruelty, tyranny, and oppression of Tarquinius himself ; the guilty manner in which he obtained the kingdom, the violent means he had used to retain it, and the unjust repeal of all the laws of Servius Tullius, by which he had robbed them of their liberties. By this means he so effectually roused the people, that they passed a decree abolishing the kingly power itself, and banishing for ever Lucius Tarquinius Superbus, and his wife and children. In the midst of the tumult the wicked Tullia fled from her house and the city, pursued by the curses of the whole population wherever she passed, imprecating upon her head the vengeance of the furies, for the murder of her sister, husband, and father.</p><p>Intelligence of the tumult had in the mean time reached the camp at Ardea. Tarquinius hastened to the city, if possible to suppress it; and Brutus, assigning the command of the city to Lucretius, set out himself for the camp, taking a different road, so as to avoid meeting the dethroned usurper. When he reached the camp he soon roused in the army the same indignation against the tyrant, which had blazed so strongly at Rome. The commanders of the troops joined him ; the army adhering to the observances of the comitia centuriata, confirmed in legal form the decree of the citizens, banishing the Tarquin family, and abolishing the regal name and power tbr ever. They then made a truce with the Ardeans for fifteen years, and marched towards Rome. Tarquinius, finding the gates shut against him, and learning the defection of the army, fled with his sons to Caere in Etruria. Thus ended the reign of Tarquinius Superbus ; and with it the existence of the monarchical form of government at Rome.</p><p>The monarchical form of government being thus abolished, the next step was to constitute another in its stead. Lucretius was appointed <hi rend="italic">inter-rex,</hi>  and the comitia centuriata were held by his authority in the Campus Martius, when Brutus and Collatinus were chosen to be supreme magistrates, at first with the name of prætors, which was afterwards changed to that of consuls, by which title, as the better known, we shall continue to designate these colleagues in the chief power. They retained all the power of the kings, and all the insignia of royalty, except the diadem ; but the rods and axes, the emblems of tlle power of life and death, were carried before each alternately for a month. In order that the sacred rites might be duly performed, they appointed a priest with the title of <hi rend="italic">king of the sacrifices,</hi>  but without political power. They then proceeded to fill up the due number of three hundred in the senate, which had been diminished partly by the tyranny of the last king, and partly by the flight ofhis adherents, who were implicated in his crimes. They restored those laws of Servius Tullius which were favourable to the commonalty ; and re-appointed the meetings and common sacrifices of the tribes.</p><p>Rome seemed now to have regained its liberties, but it had not obtained the sense of security. It was thought necessary to banish Collatinus, who was the nephew of Tarquinius, that there might remain none of that hated race in the city. Collatinus yielding without a struggle, withdrew to Lavinium, and there died in old age. Publius Valerius was elected consul in his stead, by the comitia centuriata.</p><p>It was not to be expected that the banished king would submit without a contest. He first attempted to induce the Latin states to espouse his quarrel ; and finding them unwilling, he applied to the Etruscans. Ambassadors were sent from Etruria to demand the restitution of his private property. This demand gave rise to warm discussions, whether they should obey justice by giving up the private property ofTarquinius, or prudence, by refiιsing to put money into the hands of an enemy, which they foresaw would soon be used against themselves. The plea of justice prevailed, and the property was ordered to be restored. But during the discussion, and the period required for collecting the property, the Etruscan ambassadors were intriguing with the younger patricians in the formation of a plot to restore the king. Considerable numbers of the more haughty of them, offended with the favour shewn to the commons, joined in the conspiracy, among whom were the two sons of Brutus himself. The conspiracy was discovered by the information of a slave, who had overheard them while concocting this plot in secret. The two consuls called the people to the comitium, and commanded the conspirators to be brought bound before them. The whole plot was detected ; the Etruscan ambassadors permitted to depart uninjured, out of respect to the laws of nations ; and the convicted traitors thrown into prison to await their trial. Next day the trial was conducted in public, and sentence of condemnation passed. Brutus commanded the sentence to be put in execution upon his own sons. They were stripped, beaten with rods, and then beheaded. Nor till this fearful example of stern retributive justice had been completed did Brutus leave the assembly ; and when he departed, the people could do no less than inflict an equal doom on the remaining conspirators.</p><p>The private danger was thus turned aside, but a public tempest was at hand. The Etruscan cities of Tarquinii and Veii took up arms in the cause of the banished king, and advanced against Rome. The Romans crossed the Tiber to encounter the foe ; and the two armies met near the grove of Arsia. Before the battle began, Brutus, who was riding at the head of the Roman cavalry, was descried by Aruns Tarquinius, who led those of Etruria. The banished prince, burning with personal hatred, spurred his steed furiously against the consul. Brutus, with equal animosity, met him in mid career ; and in the shock each pierced the body of his antagonist with his spear, and they fell wounded and dying together to the ground. The cavalry on each side hastened to avenge their leaders ; the battle became general ; each right wing lvas victorious over its opponent ; and after a long and bloody struggle, night put an end to the undecided contest. Both parties kept the field; but in the dead of night a voice was heard from the adjacent grove, declaring that the Etruscans had lost one man more than the Romans, who were, and would be victorious. A panic seized the enemy, they deserted their camp and fled ; and at dawn the Romans found nothing to do but to carry off the booty. Valerius returned to the city in triumph, and in the forum pronounced a funeral oration over the body of Brutus. The matrons mourned for him a whole year, and his statue was placed in the Capitol, among the kings, with a sword in his hand.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>