<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>principle which had led to his selection of Maximian as his own colleague, the principle of dissimilitude. A man comparatively peaceful himself, he chose to be associated with Maximian, a rough warrior: to this rugged Augustus, or emperor, he assigned a peaceful and mild Cæsar, Constantius, again choosing for his own Cæsar the warlike and fierce Galerius. A new division of the empire followed. Diocletian took the eastern provinces; Galerius was appointed to Thrace and Illyricum ; Maximian received Italy and Africa; and Gaul, Spain, and Britain, were entrusted to Constantius. Each of the Cæsars, although they differed in their dispositions, was a man of courage and military experience ; and for a time the arrangement seemed productive of the very best consequences, but it ultimately tended to hasten the dismemberment of the empire and its consequent overthrow.</p><p>Constantius, to whom Britain had been assigned, had to begin his tenure of power by a war for its possession. The usurper Carausius had several years before raised himself to the chief command in Britain, which he retained in spite of the efforts of the imperial generals. He was slain by Allectus, a new usurper, just as Constantius was preparing to cross from Gaul against him. Constantius speedily defeated Allectus, and gained the complete possession of his province, which he maintained with equal valour and moderation, governing with such justice as to make himself equally beloved by hie army and the native inhabitants. In the mean time, Galerius was equally successful on the Danube, where he defeated the invaders; Maximian in Africa, and Diocletian in Egypt; so that this division of power seemed to secure the defence of the empire, by enabling its rulers to oppose every new assailant. A war against the Persians threatened more disastrous consequences. Diocletian had sent for Galerius to conduct this war; but in the first battle the Persians gained the victory, and inflicted on the Romans a very severe defeat. Next year Galerius, at the head of a more powerful army again invaded Persia; but profiting by experience, he kept his forces on the hilly regions of Armenia, where the Persian cavalry could not act, and watching his time, rushed like a mountain torrent on the Persians, and gave them a terrible overthrow. The rout was complete and irrecoverable, and so greatly were the Persians dispirited, that they were glad to yield to the conditions of peace offered by the conqueror. The province of Mesopotamia was ceded to the Romans, and the Tigris again became the eastern boundary of the empire.</p><p>These successful wars might have been followed by a period of peace and prosperity; they ushered in scenes of unparalleled atrocity. Diocletian had made the city of Nicomedia the seat of his residence; and there he maintained a court of eastern splendour, to which he invited men of learningand philosophy. But the philosophers who frequented his court being all animated with extreme hatred against Christianity, exerted themselves in instigating the emperor to extirpate a religion too pure and lofty to suit their polluted minds. Galerius is said also to have stimulated Diocletian to undertake the destruction of a religion, the gentle and peaceful spirit of which he could neither understand nor appreciate. Three imperial edicts were successively published, requiring the books of the Christians to be everywhere sought for and burned, forbidding them to meet together for the purpose of religious worship on pain of death, inflicting punishments of every kind, imprisonment, slavery, infamy, and death upon all the dignitaries of the church, and sanctioning the employment of every possible method to produce, enforce, or compel apostacy, and a return to the established idolatry of the empire. The barbarities which followed upon the issuing of these edicts were utterly inconceivable. Malicious ingenuity was racked to the utmost to devise tortures for the persecuted followers of Jesus. For the space of ten years did this persecution rage with scarcely mitigated horrors; and such multitudes were massacred in all parts of the empire, that at last the imperial murderers ventured to erect a triumphal column, bearing the barbarously boastful, yet false inscription, that they had extinguished the Christian name and superstition, and restored the worship of the gods to its former purity and splendour.</p><p>The scheme of this great and bloody persecution was devised by the emperor Diocletian and his Cæsar Galerius, during a winter residence in the palace of Nicomedia. Soon after the issuing of the persecuting edicts, Diocletian repaired to Rome, and there, along with his colleague Maximian, enjoyed the honours of a triumph for the various victories which had been gained in their joint sovereignty. This was remarkable as the last triumph that ever entered the proud gates of Rome. Diocletian had already set the example of a residence in the provinces; and other causes soon conspired to render this example both common and expedient, so that Rome ceased to be the capital of even the Roman world. Wearied with the cares of government, offended witll the rude freedoms of the citizens of Rome, and feeling the effects of advancing age, Diocletian began to entertain serious intentions of abdicating the imperial powcr. These intentions were confirmed by a severe illness under which he laboured, after his return to Nicomedia; and at length he prevailed on his reluctant colleague Maximian to accompany him in his abdication, as he had in his assumption of the toils and the honours of sovereign dominion. Accordingly, the two emperors formally relinquished the imperial station, power, and titles; and were succeeded by Galerius and Constantius, who now from being Cæsars, became each an Augustus. A new division of the empire necessarily followed, of which Galerius seized the lion’s share, without however provoking any hostile opposition from Constantius. Galerius retained all the eastern provinces, together with Italy and Africa; Constantius was satisfied with tile possession of Spain, Gaul, and Britain. Galerius appointed two Cæsars, Severus, to whom he consigned Italy and Africa, and Maximin, to whom he entrusted the Asiatic provinces. Diocletian survived his abdication about nine years, which he spent in tranquillity, ease, and luxurious retirement at Salona (Spalatro), amusing himself in the erection of a magnificent palace, and the calm pleasures of rural and horticultural pursuits, resisting every attempt to induce him to return to the paths of ambition, and declaring that he had never known the true enjoyment of life till after his resignation of pow<hi rend="sup">,</hi>er.</p><p>Constantine, son of Constantius, was detained for some time by Galerius, who was apprehensive of danger from the talents of that young prince ; but he contrived to escape, and by a rapid flight secured his safety, and joined his father in Britain, who was preparing to march against the Scots and Picts, as the inhabitants of the northern regions of tllat island now began to be called. While Constantius was on his march northwards, he lvas seized with a mortal illness, and died at York, having nominated as successor, his son Constantine, who was accordingly saluted Augustus by his army. Galerius refused to ratify this elevation to the imperial dignity of a prince whom he at once hated and feared; but sanctioned his being termed a Cæsar, bestowing the now vacant rank of Augustus upon Severus, one ofhis own Cæsars. This dignity had been expected by Maxentius, son of the abdicated emperor Maximian. Indignant at his disappointment, Maxentius caused himselfto be proclaimed emperor by his army; and to colour this usurpation, he induced his father to leave his retreat, and resume the imperial title. A scene of contention followed, scarcely paralleled in the annals of Rome. Severus march</p></body></text></TEI>