<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>again to a certain extent untwisted. The untwisting suffered by the thread in forming the strands is much greater than the subsequent retwisting in forming the rope ; and if the thread had been at the first too little twisted, or too soft, as it is termed, it would never make a serviceable rope ; and for such ropes as require to be impervious to water, it would be totally unsuitable.</p><p>It is, then, on the proper angle of twist in the <hi rend="italic">combined </hi>threads, and not in the threads when <hi rend="italic">separate,</hi>  that the efficiency of the rope depends ; and this can be determined by experiment alone.</p><p>When many threads or yarns are combined to form strands, the effects produced on the latter by strains are analogous to those produced on the fibres when formed into threads, and, from the greater size of the component parts, are more apparent.</p><p>In the ordinary method of procedure the threads are all stretched to the same length, and then twisted together in a direction contrary to their individual twist. This, by winding the external yarns round those beneath them, shortens the whole mass, and puckers up the yarns nearest the centre, and thus the greatest share of any strain is thrown on the external yarns. It has therefore been considered of primary importance in all inventions intended to improve the making of ropes, to equalize the strain on the yarns in the strands.</p><p>Belfour attempted to effect this by shortening the internal yarns in the degree necessary to prevent their puckering up. Now, although the fibres of hemp are not in themselves very extensible, yet the rope formed from them is ; and when such an extension takes place in a rope formed by Belfour⅛ method, the strain is thrown entirely upon the internal yarns, which, if the strain be great enough, will break from the centre outwards.</p><p>The manner in which the external yams of a strand lengthen, will be seen at once by fig. 2. Here α is a section of a newly formed strand ; o' a section of the same strand after having been used ; while <hi rend="italic">yd</hi>  is a part of the surface of the first, on the stretch out ; and <hi rend="italic">bid</hi>  a part of the surface of the other. By the straining produced by use, the yarns in <hi rend="italic">α</hi>  are brought into closer contact, and the diameter of the strand is reduced. If in the strand α, <hi rend="italic">be</hi>  represents the angle at which any external yarn is</p><p>supposed to lie, this, by the reduction of the diameter, will in o’ be changed to <hi rend="italic">yd; </hi>and if in σ, <hi rend="italic">de</hi>  represents a heart-yarn, this yam in α<hi rend="sup">, </hi>must stretch to<hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  or break, which, as it is very little extensible, it is likely to do.</p><p>It is of importance to observe, that the breaking of the heart-yarns of a strand in this manner is attended with much greater danger than the breaking of the external yams, as the injury not only remains concealed, but water can easily penetrate to the core of the strand, which in consequence speedily decays.</p><p>It would appear, then, that a certain degree of puckering in the internal yarns of a strand is necessary to compensate for the extension that the superficial yarns undergo by use ; and where ropes are made by machinery, it would be perfectly possible to arrange it so that, from the central yam outwards, every one could be wrought into the strand in due length to allow for the stretching.</p><p>The further operations are the forming the strands into hawser-laid ropes, and these again into cable-laid ropes. The many uses to which ropes are applied preclude the possibility of applying specific rules to their manufacture·</p><lb/><p>Some require flexibility, others impenetrability to water ; strength may in some be of primary importance, or it may be secondary to other qualities which better adapt the rope for its peculiar purpose. The goodness of the rope depends upon the previous operations ; but it must be a standing rule in all the processes, never to make use of so much twist as will impair the strength of the fibre.</p><p>To prevent the decay of such ropes as are exposed to continual changes from wet to dry, the yarns forming them are soaked in hot tar previously to their being worked up. It would be well if some other substance than tar could be found suited for this purpose, as it unfortunately happens that ropes lose much of their strength in the operation of tarring ; and after having been kept for some time, the loss of strength is progressively increased, and this to a greater extent in hot than in cold climates. M. Duhamel made several experiments on this subject in 1741-1746, and from the results obtained he concludes,</p><p>1st, That untarred cordage in constant use is one third more durable than the same cordage when tarred ;</p><p>2dly, That untarred cordage retains its strength for a longer time when kept in store ;</p><p>3dly, That untarred cordage resists the ordinary influence of the weather one fourth longer than when it is tarred.</p><p>Some experiments were made in 1803 by Mr Chapman, civil engineer, to determine the effects of a new process of washing the tar to free it from the soluble substances contained in it, and for which process he had obtained a patent. Yet although the result of these experiments proved beyond a doubt the superiority of Mr Chapman’s method, it is singular that it has never come into use. The same gentleman made some other experiments in 1806—1807, confirmatory of those of M. Duhamel. The result of one series is given in the table below.</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Date of Experiment.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Girth in Inches.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Breaking</p><p>Weight.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Compara</p><p>tive</p><p>Strength.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Cwts. on each Inch of Square of Girth.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1806, Oct 2.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>White rope.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2∙75</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>75 cwt.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>100</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9∙9 cwt.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Oct. 24.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2∙8</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>55</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>73∙3</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1807, May 8.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Same rope...</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2∙8</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>41∙4</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>S5∙2</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5∙3</p></cell></row></table><lb/><p>We shall now offer a few of the rules which have been given by different authors for computing the strength of ropes.</p><p>Mr Tredgold says, “ that in a hawser-rope, it may be proved that the strength of the straight fibres of hemp is to the strength of the rope as the radius is to the mean between the square and the cube of the cosine of the angle of twist, when the fibres are all equally extended, and the angle of twist measured at the greatest stretch the rope will endure without fracture. The cosine of the angle under these circumstances is in general about 0∙87, and therefore the strength is about 0∙708 times the strength of the hemp, or very little exceeding two thirds of its strength ; but in most cases the loss of strength will be greater than one third, because the stretching of the different parts is unequal. And in a cable-laid rope, that the strength of the hemp is to that of the cable as the radius is to the mean of the third or fourth power of the cosine of the angle ot twist under the same circumstances as before; or, that its strength is to that of the ropes which form it simply as the cosine of the angle of twist. This, in usual cases, will be nearly as eighty-seven to a hundred, that is, there are thirteen parts in every hundred of the strength lost in forming cable-laid ropes.”</p><p>The following rule is given by Dr Robison for finding the strength of ropes : Multiply the circumference of the rope in inches by itself, and the fifth part of the product will be the number of tons which the rope will carry. Thus, in the experiment of Mr Chapman, the weakest tarred rope</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>