<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The largest arch is forty feet span, and the others thirty feet. The length is 560 feet, and the breadth twenty-four feet between the parapets. The river Medway is capable of receiving the largest vessels up to Rochester, but few are moored off the city, as Chatham, a mile lower down the river, is more convenient from the vicinity to the naval arsenal and the docks.</p><p>The ancient castle is an interesting object to all antiquaries. It stands on the south-west side of the city, on such an elevated spot that it can be seen at thirty miles distance. The streets of this city have no peculiar feature, except the narrowness and length ; for in fact it consists chiefly of a single street, which is a continuation of Stroud towards the west and of Chatham towards the east, forming two rows of moderate houses, more than two miles from one end to the other, with a few short streets or lanes leading from them southward. With the exception of the cathedral, hereafter to be noticed, the town-hall is the most remarkable edifice : it was built in 1687. It is a handsome structure, with a spacious entrance-hall and staircase, the ceilings of both which are very curiously ornamented. Here the city business is transacted ; and at the back part is the city jail. There is a free school, several charitable institutions, a customhouse, and a market-house. The diocese of Rochester is the smallest in the kingdom. It had a cathedral as early as the year 600, which was destroyed by Ethelbert, king of Mercia, in 676 ; and a few years after the city suffered much by the incursions of the Danes, but appears to have recovered some degree of respectability by the accession of King Athelstan, who appointed masters of the mint to superintend the coinage of money. The cathedral had been dilapidated at the Norman conquest ; but Gundulph, who was removed from Normandy to fill the see, acquired money sufficient to rebuild the sacred edifice, though he died in 1094, before it was finished. Like most of the more ancient ecclesiastical erections, its plan is an improvement on the basilica of Rome, and it is built in the form of the cross of Christ, with a massive square tower at the point of intersection. The interior space to the west of the cross was the nave or body of the church, which represented the ship of St Peter : this part is more ancient than the nave of any other cathedral in the kingdom, and still retains most of the peculiar features of the style in which it was originally built, and is indeed one of the most interesting specimens of Norman architecture. The whole length of this nave is a hundred and fifty feet, and its breadth between the pillars thirty-three feet, and from one wall to the other seventy-five feet. The choir has an ascent of tcn steps, and is a hundred and fifty-six feet in length. The western front of the cathedral, one of the most perfect specimens of Anglo-Norman architecture, was constructed with consummate ability at a period when the art had arrived at a high point of perfection. The centre door is formed of a semicircular arch, composed of rich mouldings, and is supported by four pillars, with capitals of wreathed foliage. Two of these pillars take the form of Caryatides, and present statues of King Henry I. and his queen Matilda, the daughter of Malcolm III. king of Scotland, being undoubtedly two of the most ancient statues remaining in England. This building presents many other objects of very high interest to the student and the admirer of ancient architecture. The cathedral contains but few monuments, and none with any striking peculiarity.</p><p>Rochester is not a place of much trade, except what arises from the great number of travellers passing through it in their way by Dover to and from the continent. The chief occupation is a considerable oyster-fishery, from beds in the river Medway, which river is under the concurrent jurisdiction of its own corporate body, and that of the lord-mayor and aldermen of London. The latter body make periodical visits of conservancy by water, and on such occasions the two corporations indulge together in sumptuous</p><p>festivity. For municipal purposes, the city is divided into three wards, and is governed by a mayor, six aldermen, and seventeen councillors. The recorder and justices of the peace are appointed by the crown. The city returns two members to parliament. There is a well-supplied market on Fridays, and several annual fairs. The population amounted in 1821 to 8795, and in 1831 to 9811.</p><p>ROCHFORD, a market-town of the county of Essex, in the hundred of the same name, thirty-nine miles from London. It is situated on a small river that empties itself into the Crouch. It has a good market on Thursday. The population amounted in 1801 to 1228, in 1811 to 1214, in 1821 to 1382, and in 1831 to 1256.</p><p>ROCKET, an artificial fire-work, consisting of a cylindrical case of paper, filled with a composition of certain combustible ingredients ; which, being tied to a stick, mounts into the air, and then bursts. See Pyrotechny.</p><p>ROCKY Mountains, a great mountain chain which traverses the western part of North America, extending from about latitude 70° north to Mexico, where it is continued by the Cordilleras of the Andes. These ranges are considered as forming part of one vast chain, which in South America, near the equator, attains its greatest elevation. At the Isthmus of Panama it is so low as nearly to disappear; but this is in conformity with the narrowness of the land in that quarter, and but for a short space. This slight interruption is not sufficient to entitle us to consider the continuity as broken, so that we have in the western hemisphere one great mountain range extending along both continents, from the Polar Sea on the north, to Cape Horn on the south, a distance of more than one hundred and twenty degrees of latitude, without including the windings. The eastern side of North America is traversed by a similar range of mountains called the Alleghanies, which stretch along in continued and parallel lines ; but the extent, breadth, and height of the Rocky Mountains are much greater than those of the former. It is however supposed that the Rocky Mountains extend along the western part of the continent, at about the same distance from the Pacific Ocean that the Alleghanies on the eastern side extend from the Atlantic Ocean. Although but partially explored, the primitive character of the Rocky Mountains is clearly established. Their eastern sides are covered to the height of two hundred or three hundred feet, with a sandstone consisting of the ruins of the granitic rocks upon which it reposes, where disintegration was apparently effected by the gradual agency of an ancient ocean, once occupying the immense plain or basin now extending eastward from the base of these mountains to the chain of the Alleghanies. They have not however been sufficiently explored to admit our advancing any scientific details in regard to them. Many of the detached mountains and prominent peaks have not yet been either named, classified, or described. It does not appear that many of them rise above the region of perpetual refrigeration. But we have the concurrent testimony of Lewis and Clarke, as well as others, that in latitude 47<hi rend="sup">c</hi> north, immense quantities of snow are on their summits, between the Missouri and Columbia, in the months of June and July. They are seen like a vast rampart rising from the grassy plains, stretching from north to soutll. Sometimes their aspect is that of continued ranges of a grayish colour, rising into the blue of the atmosphere, above the region of the clouds. A grcat number are black, ragged, and precipitous ; and their bases are strewn with· immense boulders and fragments of rock, detached by earthquakes and the elements. From this iron-bound and precipitous character they probably received the appellation of Rocky Mountains. Some of the peaks are supposed to be twelve or thirteen thousand feet in height ; and the general range is considerably higher than any other in North America, with the exception of the</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>