<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Aurelian withdrawn his forces, when the Palmyrenians again revolted ; and the angry conqueror having again made himself master of this city of romance, reduced it to ruins, of which the extent, beauty, and magnificence still amaze the traveller. Among the victims of the emperor's wrath was Longinus, the secretary of Zenobia, and the reputed author of an admirable treatise on the sublime. Having thus reduced and destroyed Palmyra, he suppressed an insurrection in Egypt, and returned to Rome, where he celebrated his victories and conquest by a triumph the most remarkable that the city had ever witnessed. Zenobia, who had been compelled to grace this triumph, by walking on foot in the train of her conqueror, received afterwards from him a small estate at Tibur, where she spent in tranquillity the remainder of her life as a Roman matron, leaving a family which was not extinct in the fifth century.</p><p>A violent sedition soon afterwards arose at Rome, in consequence of an attempt by Aurelian to debase the coinage. It was followed by so much bloodshed, and gave so much offence to the emperor, that his native sternness, and the pitiless decision of a warrior, degenerated into harshness and cruelty. Being again obliged to lead his army against the Persians, he left the city, and sought the more congenial pursuits of war ; but was afterwards assassinated at the instigation of his private secretary Mnestheus. The murderers were torn to pieces by the enraged soldiery, who almost adored their warlike emperor.</p><p>Nothing can better prove the effect of the masculine government of Aurelian, and the regulated subordination which it had given to the troops, than the fact that the army actually allowed six months to pass in tranquillity, while they awaited the election of an emperor by the senate. That body at length elected Marcus Claudius Tacitus, an aged senator of high character, and a descendant of the celebrated historian of that name. He had scarcely begun to prove the wisdom of their choice, by the enactment of some salutary laws, when he was compelled to march against the Alani, a Scythian tribe, who were devastating Asia Minor. He was successful in the war ; but the fatigues and anxieties of the campaign were too severe for a frame already enfeebled by age, and he died in Cappadocia.</p><p>The imperial diadem was immediately assumed by Flori-anus, brother of the late emperor; but the Syrian army chose Marcus Aurelius Probus, a general of great and varied merit, ro be the successor to the throne. Florian finding himself opposed by a man against whom he could not hope for success, put an end to his own life, and thus left the empire to his rival.</p><p>Closely resembling Aurelian in personal bravery, and, like him, also a native of Sirmium, Probus began a reign scarcely less warlike and glorious than that of his great countryman. He defeated the Germans in several battles, and drove them beyond the Rhine and Danube, which were now considered the natural limits of the empire. To complete the boundary-line in that quarter, he constructed a strong wall from the Danube to the Rhine. Passing along the northern frontier of the empire, he reduced the Goths to quiescence, entered Asia, and led his army against Varames (Bahram) king of Persia. That monarch not daring to encounter the hardy veterans of Probus, consented to a peace of which the terms were dictated by the emperor. Three competitors next fell before his power, and he now seemed at leisure to cultivate the arts of peace, for which he had a strong natural predilection. He accordingly employed his legions in draining pestilential fens, planting vineyards, and improving instead of devastating the face of the country. This restoration of the ancient and wise military discipline of earlier and more virtuous days, gave offence to tlle licentious soldiery; who mutinied and slew the brave and good emperor.</p><p>Reverting to the custom formerly so prevalent, the army proclaimed as emperor Carus, prefect of the prætorian guards, and the senate reluctantly ratified their choice. In the hope of promoting tranquillity, and securing the inheritance of the imperial dignity in his own family, Carus gave the title of Cæsar to his two sons, Carinus and Nu-merianus, who were thus his appointed successors. He led his army against the Goths, who had renewed their predatory incursions, and defeated them ; but was prevented from following up his victory in consequence of a new invasion of the Persians. Leaving Carinus to protect the western provinces, and taking Numerianus along with him, he marched into Asia, and gave the Persians a complete overthrow. Pursuing the defeated enemy, he entered their own country, advanced to Ctesiphon, and began the siege, when he was killed in his tent, some authors say by a flash of lightning, more probably by some secret conspiracy.</p><p>Numerianus was acknowledged by the army as his successor ; but his gentle and pacific disposition exposed him to the ambition of Aper, præfect of the prætorian guards, by whom he w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>as privately murdered, and his death was concealed till the traitor might have time to secure his own elevation. But the bloody deed being discovered, a tumult arose in the army, in the midst of which Diocletian slew Aper, and was proclaimed emperor in his stead. He did not, however, at once obtain undisputed possession ; for Carinus, hearing ofhis brother's death, assembled a powerful army, and began his march against the usurpers. On his way he encountered and defeated another rival, Julianus, and advancing into Mœsia, was met and opposed by Diocletian. The troops of Diocletian, however, were unable to contend with the hardy veterans of Carinus, who gained the victory, but was slain in the moment of his success by a tribune, to avenge the violated honour of his wife; and thus, though defeated, Diocletian remained in possession of the diadem.</p><p>The reign of Diocletian is one of much historical importance. It was rendered conspicuous by the introduction of a new system of imperial government, and by the last and greatest persecution of the Christians. Very soon after his accession to the throne, Diocletian, feeling the weight of the imperial government greater than he was disposed to bear alone, chose as his colleague Maximianus, who had been his companion in arms, and to whom he was willing to delegate the chief part of the military cares. Maximian had soon an opportunity of using his power and displaying his courage, in consequence of an insurrection in Gaul. This insurrection he speedily suppressed, and obtained some victories over the German invaders of the province. In the mean time, Diocletian had been equally successful against the Sarmatians and the Persians. But scarcely had they obtained these victories, when new disturbances and new invasions broke out in every part of the wide empire, the wandering nations pressing inwards from all quarters, and threatening to crush the entire Roman power. To make head against so many invading armies seemed impossible, without a further division of power. For Diocletian seems to have entertained the opinion, that to entrust large armies to experienced commanders was only to put it in their power to become aspirants for the throne; and that the only way to secure their fidelity was to give them such a share in the imperial government as should engage their own interest in its preservation.</p><p>In pursuance of this scheme, he induced his colleague Maximian to name as his Cæsar and successor Constantius Chlorus; while he himself chose Maximinus Galerius. In this choice Diocletian was apparently guided by the same</p></body></text></TEI>