<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>quick enough to take off the water as fast as it was supplied ; and we imagine that a foot or two would suffice in most cases. The best way for a prudent engineer will be to observe the utmost rise remembered by the neighbours in some gorge, where the river cannot spread out. Measure the increased section in this place, and at the same time recollect that the water increases in a much greater proportion than the section; because an increase of the hydraulic mean depth produces an increase of velocity in nearly the duplicate proportion of the depth. But as this augmentation of velocity will also obtain between the embankments, it will be sufficiently exact to suppose that the section must here be increased nearly in the same proportion as at the gorge already mentioned. Neglecting this method of information, and regulating the height of our embankments by the greatest swell that has been observed in the plain, will assuredly make them too low, and render them totally useless.</p><p>A line of embankment should always be carried on by a strict concert of the proprietors of both banks through its whole extent. A greedy proprietor, by advancing his own embankment beyond that of his neighbours, not only exposes himself to risk by the working of the waters on the angles which this will produce, but exposes his neighbours also to danger, by narrowing the section, and thereby raising the surface and increasing the velocity, and by turning the stream athwart, and causing it to shoot against the opposite bank. The whole should be as much as possible in a line ; and the general effect should be to make the course of the stream straighter than it was before. All bends should be made more gentle, by keeping the embankment farther from the river in all convex lines of the natural bank, and bringing it nearer where the bank is concave. This will greatly diminish the action of the waters on the embankment, and insure their duration. The same maxim must be followed in fencing any brook which discharges itself into the river. The bends given at its mouth to the two lines of embankment should be made less acute than those of the natural brook, although by this means two points of land are left out. And the opportunity should be embraced of making the direction of this transverse brook more sloping than before, that is, less athwart the direction of the river.</p><p>It is of great consequence to cover the outside of the dike with very compact turf closely united. If it admit water, the interior part of the wall, which is always more porous, becomes drenched in water, and this water acts with its statical pressure, tending to burst the bank on the land side, and will quickly shift it from its seat. The utmost care should therefore be taken to make it and keep it perfectly tight. It should be a continued fine turf, and every bare spot should be carefully covered with fresh sod and rat-holes must be carefully closed up.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Of Straighting or Changing the Course of Rivers.</hi></p><p>We have seen that every bending of a river requires an additional slope in order to continue its train, or enable it to convey the same quantity of water without swelling in its bed. The effect of taking away any of these bends must be to sink the waters of the river. It is proper, therefore, to have it in our power to estimate these effects. It may be desirable to gain property by taking away the sweeps of a very winding stream ; but this may be prejudicial, by destroying the navigation on such a river. It may also hurt the proprietors below, by increasing the velocity of the stream, which will expose them to the risk of its overflowing, or of its destroying its bed, and taking a new course. Or this increase of velocity may be inconsistent with the regimen of the new channel, or at least require larger dimensions than we should have given it if ignorant of this effect.</p><p>Our principles of uniform motion enable us to answer every question of this kind which can occur; and Du Buat proposes several problems, to this effect. The regular solutions of them are complicated and difficult ; and we do not think them necessary in tllis place, because they may all be solved in a manner not indeed so elegant, because indirect, but abundantly accurate, and easy to any person familiar with those which we have already considered.</p><p>We can take the exact level across all these sweeps, and thus obtain the whole slope. We can measure with accuracy the velocity in some part of the channel which is most remote from any bend, and where the channel itself has the greatest regularity of form. This will give us the expense or discharge of the river, and the mean depth connected with it. We can then examine whether this velocity is precisely such as is compatible with stability in the straight course. If it is, it is evident that if we cut off the bends, the greater slope which this will produce will communicate to the waters a velocity incompatible with the regimen suited to this soil, unless we enlarge the width of the stream, that is, unless we make the new channel more capacious than the old one. We must now calculate the dimensions of the channel which, with this increased slope, will conduct the waters with the velocity that is necessary. All this may be done by the foregoing problems ; and we may accomplish this most easily by steps. First, suppose the bed the same with the old one, and calculate the velocity for the increased slope by the general formula. Then change one of the dimensions of the channel, so as to produce the velocity we want, which is a very simple process. And in doing this, the object to be kept chiefly in view is not to make the new velocity such as will be incompatible with the stability of the new bed.</p><p>Having accomplished this first purpose, we leam, in the very solution, how much shallower this channel with its greater slope will be than the former, while it discharges all the waters. This diminution of depth must increase the slope and the velocity, and must diminish the depth of the river above the place where the alteration is to be made. How far it produces these effects may be calculated by the general formula. We then see whether the navigation will be hurt, either in the old river up the stream, or in the new channel. It is plain that all these points cannot be reconciled. We may make the new channel such, that it shall leave a velocity compatible with stability, and that it shall not diminish the depth of the river up the stream. But having a greater slope, it must have a smaller mean depth, and also a smaller real depth, unless we make it of a very inconvenient form.</p><p>The same things viewed in a different light, will show us what depression of waters may be produced by rectifying the course of a river in order to prevent its overflowing. And the process which we would recommend is the same with the foregoing. We apprehend it to be quite needless to measure the angles of rebound, in order to <hi rend="italic">compute</hi>  the slope which is <hi rend="italic">employed</hi>  for sending the river through the bend, with a view to supersede tllis by straighting the river. It is infinitely easier and more exact to measure the levels themselves, and then we know the effect of removing them.</p><p>Nor need we follow Du Buat in solving problems for diminishing the slope and velocity, and deepening the channel of a river by bending its course. The expense of this would in every case be enormous ; and the practices which we are about to discuss afford infinitely easier methods of accomplishing all the purposes which are to be gained by these changes.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Of Bars, Weirs, and Jetties, for raising the Surface of Rivers.</hi></p><p>We propose, under the article Water-works, to consider in sufficient practical detail all that relates to the construction and mechanism of these and other erections</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>