<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>provements in the manufacture of hempen rope or cordage. The improvements consist in impregnating the yarns with tannin, by steeping them in an infusion of oak-bark, catechu, sumach, or valonia, previous to their being twisted into cordage.</p><p>1832. February 1st, Mr James Lang, flax-dresser, Greenock, obtained a patent for such improvements in the construction of the gill spreading or drawing heads, and roving or spinning frames, as adapted them for the spinning of rope-yarns. Fig. 14 shows a side view, and fig. 15 a top view, of the first drawing or spreading machine ; and fig. 16</p><lb/><p>is a diagram illustrative of its mode of action. The same letters refer to the same parts in all the figures. Here α is a portion of a board called the spreading-board. Over the surface of this board an endless band of leather travels, in the direction indicated by the arrow; and on this band the hemp to be operated upon is spread. By the motion of the band the hemp is carried forward until it is taken hold of by the feeding rollers <hi rend="italic">bb,</hi>  by the motion of which it is carried onwards to be acted on by the gills or travelling hackles <hi rend="italic">ccc ; </hi>and the gills are fixed to slips of brass screwed to bars which extend across the machine, as seen in fig. 15. These bars pass through grooves formed in the links of an endless chain, by the motion of which they are carried round ; and their ends move in peculiarly formed slits in the framing of the machine, by which they are confined to their proper course. By the gills being made to move faster than the surfaces of the feeding rollers, they pass through the hemp many times in the course of its passage across the space in which it is acted on by them, and they are thus enabled to split and straighten the fibres. The hemp now passes between the drawing rollers <hi rend="italic">ee,</hi>  the surfaces of which can be made to move from forty to sixty times faster than those of the feeding rollers, according to the material to be acted</p><lb/><p>on. By them the hemp is drawn into a sliver of a certain state of fineness, and this sliver, after passing through the delivering rollers, falls into the can <hi rend="italic">g.</hi>  When a certain quantity of sliver is delivered into the can, a bell is rung by the machinery ; the filled can is then removed by the attendant, and an empty one substituted. The filled cans are then conveyed to the second drawing machine, which differs from the first chiefly in being smaller, in having no spreading-board, and in having a double set of rollers and gills in the width, as will be seen by the top view, fig. 17. The cans containing the slivers from the first drawing machine are placed at the end of this, in such number as may be required, and many slivers are then passed together through each set of feeding rollers. After having been acted on by the gills and the drawing rollers, the slivers may be delivered separately, or they may be combined, as shown in the drawing, by passing through a tray previous to entering the last pair of delivering rollers. The slivers, after having been subjected to a third drawing, in a machine the parts of which are still finer than those <hi rend="italic">ot</hi>  the second machine, are carried to the roving or spinning machine. This machine has feeding rollers, gills, and drawing rollers similar to the drawing machines ; but the parts are still finer than those of the last machine. In fig. 18 the spinning apparatus is shown. The slivers, on leaving the drawing rollers, pass into the trumpet-mouthed tubes <hi rend="italic">aa.</hi>  The upper part of these tubes is in two halves, one of which is fixed to the cross rail of the machine, while the other is pressed against it by means of a spring, in such a manner as gently to compress the sliver on entering the tube. The bottom of the tube is set into another tube serving as a socket, and into this last tube discs of felt or cloth are put, through which a slit is made for the reception of the thread, which is thus com-</p></body></text></TEI>