<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roof expresses the covering of a house or building, by which its inhabitants or contents are protected from the injuries of the weather. It is perhaps the essential part of a house, and is frequently used to express the whole. To </hi><hi rend="italic">come under a person’s roof</hi>  is to enjoy his protection and society, to dwell with him. <hi rend="italic">Tectum</hi>  was used in the same sense by the Romans. To be within our walls, rather expresses the being in our possession. A roof, therefore, is not only an essential part of a house, but it even seems to be its characteristic feature.</p><p>The Greeks, who have perhaps excelled all nations in taste, and who have given the most perfect model of architectonic ordonnance within a certain limit, never erected a building which did not exhibit this part in the most distinct manner ; and though they borrowed much of their model from the orientals, as will be evident to any one who compares their architecture with the ruins of Persepolis, and of the tombs in the mountains of Shiraz, they added that form of roof which their own climate taught them was necessary for sheltering them from the rains. The roofs in Persia and Arabia are flat, but those of Greece are without exception sloping. It seems therefore a gross violation of the true principles of taste in architecture, at least in the regions of Europe, to take away or to hide the roof of a house ; and it must be ascribed to that rage for novelty which is so powerful in the minds of the rich. Our ancestors seemed to be of a very different opinion, and turned their attention to the ornamenting of their roofs as much as any other part of a building. They showed them in the most conspicuous manner, running them up to a great height ; broke them into a thousand fanciful shapes, and stuck them full of highly-dressed windows. We laugh at this, and call it Gothic and clumsy ; and our great architects,'not to offend any more in this way, conceal the roof altogether by parapets, balustrades, and other contrivances. Our forefathers certainly did offend against the maxims of true taste, when they enriched a part of a house with marks of elegant habitation, which every spectator must know to be a cumbersome garret But their successors no less offend, who take off the cover of the house altogether, and make it impossible to know whether it is not a mere screen or colonnade we are looking at.</p><p>We cannot help thinking that Sir Christopher Wren erred when he so industriously concealed tile roof of St Paul’s Church in London. The whole of the upper order is a mere screen. Such a quantity of wall would have been intolerably offensive, had he not given it some appearance of habitation by the mock windows or niches. Even in this state it is gloomy, and it is odd, and a puzzle to every spectator. There should be no puzzle in the design of a building, any more than in that of a discourse. It has been said that the double roof of our great churches which have aisles is an incongruity, looking like a house standing on the top of another house. But there is not the least occasion for such a thought We know that the aisle is a shed, a cloister. Suppose only that the lower roof or shed is hidden by a balustrade, it then becomes a portico, against which the connoisseur has no objection. Yet there is no difference ; for the portico must have a cover, otherwise it is neither a shed, cloister, nor portico, any more than a building without a roof is a house. A hpuse without a visible roof is like a man abroad without his hat; and we may add, that the whim of concealing the chimneys, now so fashionable, changes a house to a barn or storelωuse. A house should not be a copy of any thing. It has a title to be an original ; and a screen-like house and a pillar-like candlestick are similar solecisms in taste,</p><p>The architect is anxious to present a fine object and a very simple outline discusses all his concerns with the roof. He leaves it to the carpenter, whom he frequently puzzles, by his arrangements, with coverings almost impossible to execute. Indeed it is seldom that the idea of a roof is admitted by him into his great compositions ; or if he does introduce it it is from mere affectation, and we may say pedantry. A pediment is frequently stuck up in the middle of a grand front in a situation where a roof cannot perform its office ; for the rain that is supposed to flow down its sides must be received on the top of the level buildings which flank it. This is a manifest incongruity. The tops of dressed windows, trifling porches, and sometimes a projecting portico, are the only situations in which we see the figure of a roof correspond with its office. Having thus lost sight of the principle, it is not surprising that the draughtsman, for he should not be called architect runs into every whim ; and we see pediment within pediment a round pediment, a hollow pediment, and, the greatest of all absurdities, a broken pediment. Nothing could ever reconcile us to the sight of a man with a hat without its crown, because we cannot overlook the use of a hat.</p><p>But when one builds a house, ornament alone will not do. We must have a cover ; and the enormous expense and other great inconveniences which attend the concealment of this cover by parapets, balustrades, and screens, have obliged architects to consider the pent-roof as admissible, and to regulate its form. Any man of sense, not under the influence of prejudice, would be determined in this by its fitness for answering its purpose. A high-pitched roof will undoubtedly shoot off the rains and snows better than one of a lower pitch. The wind will not so easily blow the dropping rain in between the slates, nor will it have so much power to strip them off. A high-pitched roof will exert a smaller thrust on the walls, both because its strain is less horizontal, and because it will admit of lighter covering. But it is more expensive, because there is more of it It requires a greater size of timbers to make it equally strong, and it exposes a greater surface to the wind.</p><p>There have been great changes in the pitch of roofs. Our forefathers made them very high, and we make them very low. It does not however, appear that this change has been altogether the effect of principle. In the simple unadorned habitations of private persons, every thing comes to be adjusted by an experience of inconveniences which have resulted from too low-pitched roofs ; and their pitch will always be nearly such as suits the climate and covering. Our architects, however, go to work on different principles. Their professed aim is to make a beautiful object. The sources of the pleasures arising from what we call <hi rend="italic">taste</hi>  are so various, so complicated, and even so whimsical, that it is almost in vain to look for principle in the rules adopted by our professed architects. We cannot help thinking, that much of their practice results from a pedantic veneration for the beautiful productions of Grecian architecture. Such architects as have written on the principles of the art in respect of proportions, or what they call the “ ordonnance,” are very much puzzled to make a chain of reasoning; and the most that they have made of the Greek architecture is, that it exhibits a nice adjustment of strength and strain. But when we consider the extent of this adjustment we find that it is wonderfully limited. The whole of it consists of a basement, a column, and an entablature, and the entablature, it is true, exhibits something of a connection with the framework and roof of a wooden building ; and we believe that it really originated from this in the hands of the</p></body></text></TEI>