<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>hibiting the principal forms, of which the endless variety of roofs are only slight modifications. We shall not trouble the reader with any account of such roofs as receive part of their support from the interior walls, but confine ourselves to the more difficult problem of throwing a roof over a wide building, without any intermediate support ; because when such roofs are constructed in the best manner, that is, deriving the greatest possible strength from the materials employed, the best construction of the others is necessarily included. For all such roofs as rest upon the middle walls are roofs of smaller bearing. The only exception deserving notice is the roofs of churches, which have aisles separated from the nave by columns. The roof must rise on these. But if it is of an arched form internally, the horizontal thrusts must be nicely balanced, that they may not push the columns aside.</p><p>The simplest notion of a roof-frame is, that it consists of two rafters AB and BC (fig. 12), meeting in the ridge.</p><p>But even this simple form is susceptible of better and worse. We have already seen, that when the weight of a square yard of covering is given, a steeper roof requires stronger rafters, and that when the scantling of the timbers is also given, the relative strength of a rafter is inversely as its length.</p><p>But there is now another circumstance to be taken into the account, viz. the support which one rafter leg gives to the other. The best form of a rafter will therefore be that in which the relative strength of the legs, and their mutual support, give the greatest product. Mr Muller, in his Military Engineer, gives a determination of the best pitch of a roof, which has considerable ingenuity, and has been copied into many books of</p><p>military education both in this</p><p>island and on the continent. De</p><p>scribe on the width AC (fig. 13)</p><p>the semicircle AFC, and bisect it</p><p>by the radius FD. Produce the</p><p>rafter AB to the circumference</p><p>in E, join EC, and draw the per</p><p>pendicular EG. Now AB : AD</p><p>= AC ; AE, and AE=-∙y∣j——, and AE is inversely</p><p>as AB, and may therefore represent its strength in relation to thc weight actually lying on it. Also the support which CB gives to AB is as CE, because CE is perpendicular to AB. Therefore the form which renders AE × EC a maximum seems to be that which has the greatest strength.</p><p>But AC : AE = EC : EG, and EG = <hi rend="sup">A</hi>-<hi rend="sup">E</hi>-*,<hi rend="sup">E</hi>-, and is AC</p><p>therefore proportional to AE × EC. Now EG is a maximum when B is in F, and a square pitch is in this respect the strongest. But it is very doubtful whether this construction is deduced from just principles. There is another strain to which the leg AB is exposed, which is not taken into the account. This arises from the curvature which it unavoidably acquires by the transverse pressure of its load. In this state it is pressed in its own direction by the abutment and load of the other leg. The relation between this strain and the resistance of the piece is not very distinctly known. Euler has given a dissertation on this subject, which is of great importance, because it affects posts and pillars of all kinds ; and it is very well known that a post of ten feet long and six inches square will bear with great safety a weight which would crush a post of the same scantling and twenty feet long in a minute ; but his determination has not been acquiesced in by the first mathematicians. Now it is in relation to these two strains that the strength of the rafter should be adjusted. The firmness of the support given by the other leg is of no consequence, if its own strength is inferior to the strain. The force which tends to crush the leg AB, by compressing it in its curved state, is to its weight as AB to BD, as is easily seen by the composition of forces ; and its incurvation by this force has a relation to it, which is of intricate determination. It is contained in the properties demonstrated by Bernoulli of the elastic curve. This determination also includes the relation between the curvature and the length of the piece. But the whole of this seemingly simple problem is of much more difficult investigation than Mr Muller was aware of ; and his rules for the pitch of a roof, and for the sally of a dock-gate, which depends on the same principles, are of no value. He is, however, the first author who attempted to solve either of these problems on mechanical principles susceptible of precise reasoning. Be-lidor⅛ solutions, in his <hi rend="italic">Architecture Hydraulique,</hi>  are below notice.</p><p>Reasons of economy have made carpenters prefer a low pitch ; and although this does diminish the support given by the opposite leg faster than it increases the relative strength of the other, it is not of material consequence, because the strength remaining in the opposite leg is still very great ; for the supporting leg is acting against compression, in which case it is vastly stronger than the supported leg acting against a transverse strain.</p><p>But a roof of this simplicity will not do in most cases. There is no notice taken, in its construction, of the thrust which it exerts on the walls. Now this is the strain which is the most hazardous of all. Our ordinary walls, instead of being able to resist any considerable strain pressing them outwards, require, in general, some ties to keep them on foot. When a person thinks of the thinness and height of the walls of even a strong house, he will be surprised that they are not blown down by any strong puff of wind. A wall three feet thick, and sixty feet high, could not withstand a wind blowing at the rate of thirty feet per second (in which case it acts with a force considerably exceeding two pounds on every square foot), if it were not stiffened by cross walls, joists, and roof, which all help to tie the different parts of the building together.</p><p>A carpenter is therefore exceedingly careful to avoid every horizontal thrust, or to oppose them by other forces. And this introduces another essential part into the construction of a roof, namely, the <hi rend="italic">tie</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">beam</hi></p><p>AC (fig. 14), laid from wall to wall,</p><p>binding the feet A and C of the</p><p>rafters together. This is the sole</p><p>office of the beam ; and it should</p><p>be considered in no other light</p><p>than as a string to prevent the roof</p><p>from pushing out the walls. It is</p><p>indeed used for carrying the ceiling</p><p>of the apartments under it, and it is even made to support a flooring. But, considered as making part of a roof, it is merely a string ; and the strain which it withstands tends to tear its parts asunder. It therefore acts with its whole absolute force, and a very small scantling would suffice if we could contrive to fasten it firmly enough to the foot of the rafter. If it is of oak, we may safely subject it to a strain of three tons for every square inch of its sec</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>