<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Before the close of that day Ariminum was seized by Cæsar. With the speed of a torrent, and the gathering strength of an Alpine avalanche, he advanced on Rome. City after city opened its gates at his approach, their garrisons swelling the number of his troops. Pompey and his party were paralyzed by his boldness, and terror-struck by the celerity of his movements. They abandoned the city and fled to Capua, leaving the public treasure behind them. Thence they fled to Greece, without daring once to turn upon their swift pursuer. Corfinium alone seemed disposed to make a show of resistance ; but the garrison declared for Cæsar, and their commander, Domitius, surrendering at discretion, was treated with the kindness due to an honourable foe. Cæsar then retraced his course to Rome, and entered it without opposition, having subdued all Italy in sixty days. He assembled such members of the senate as had remained in the city ; declared himself driven to hostilities by the machinations of his enemies, yet still a friend to the republic ; seized upon the funds in the public treasury, and after a short delay of six days, set out to attack Pompey’s lieutenants in Spain.</p><p>In his march through Gaul he was joined by his veteran troops, at whose head he had gained so much glory, and whom he had doubtless been training for that enterprise in which he was now engaged. On his arrival in Spain he began a series of manœuvres surpassed by nothing in the history of war, for the purpose of compelling Afranius and Petreius, not to a battle, hut to a capitulation of their entire army, which he wished thus to preserve and make his ow n. This he at length accomplished ; and on his return through Gaul reduced Massilia, which had till then held out against him. But these successes, where he commanded in person, were somewhat counter-balanced by some severe defeats sustained by his generals in Illyricum and Africa.</p><p>Returning victorious to Rome, he was named dictator, a title which he soon afterwards exchanged for that of consul ; and after spending a short time in the arrangement of public affairs, he prepared to sail for Greece, in order to bring the struggle to a close, by encountering his great rival in person. Pompey had assembled an immense army, drawn from the various Asiatic states where Roman troops had been stationed; and his camp was dignified by tbe presence of great numbers of the fugitive senate. Cæsar with much difficulty and danger transported his army from Brundusium to the vicinity of Dyracchium, where Pompey was encamped. For some time the contest between these two great generals was a war of tactics, each endeavour!ng toout-manœuvre his antagonist, beforeputting the final issue to the hazard of a decisive battle. As Pom-pey’s fleets had the command of the sea, he was enabled to act on the defensive, without the danger of falling short of provisions, to which Cæsar was much exposed. Cæsar therefore used his utmost efforts to draw his adversary to a general engagement ; in which he had almost succeeded, when he was himself surprised, one division of his army thrown into confusion, and the whole so greatly endangered, that nothing but the most desperate efforts made by himself in person, prevented a total rout.</p><p>Soon after this hazardous encounter Csesar withdrew from Dyracchium, and marched to Thessaly, where he had better access to both provisions and reinforcements. He was followed by Pompey, who still abstained from battle, hoping to exhaust his foe. But this wary policy of Pompey was disliked by the young nobility, who longed for the fight, especially since their partial success at Dyracchium. At length Pompey drew out his army on the plains of Pharsalia, and offered Cæsar the opportunity which he had so long sought, of deciding the empire of the world. In this great battle the superior skill of Cæsar was manifest. Being deficient in cavalry, in which the strength of Pompey’s army lay, he altered the usual form of drawing up the army in three lines, placing a fourth in reserve for the support of his cavalry, with particular directions how to act. When the signal was given, the troops of Cæsar rushed on with their usual impetuosity ; those of Pompey stood still to receive the shock. The cavalry of Pompey at first repulsed that of Cæsar ; but being unexpectedly assailed by the reserve, they were thrown into confusion, and fled, leaving the flank of the main body exposed, which was instantly assailed by Cæsar’s victorious wing. This decided the fate of the day. Pompey’s legions were thrown into irretrievable confusion, driven to their camp, the entrenchments carried by storm, and thc whole either scattered over the country, or compelled to surrender at discretion. Cæsar finding the victory secure, hun∙ied from olace to place across the bloody field, calling aloud to spare the Roman citizens ; and all who yielded were treated with the utmost clemency.</p><p>Pompey, as if bereft of his usual courage and presence of mind, made no effort to retrieve the fortunes of the day. Hc at first retired to his camp, and when its entrenchments wcre forced, he fled in disguise from the scene not more of ruin than of disgrace. He directed his course to the Ægean sea, purposing to renew the war in Syria ; but finding the Asiatic states not inclined to support what they now deemed a fiιlling cause, he altered his plan, and steered for Egypt, having taken on board his wife Cornelia. When he drew near the Egyptian shore, he found the young king besieging Pelusium, and sent intimation ofhis approach, and ofhis intention of joining his forces with those of Egypt. The perfidious Egyptians resolved to allure him on shore, and then put him to death, as the safest mode of escaping the danger ofhis own resentment, if they should refuse him succour, or that of his rival, if they should grant it. Achillas, the commander of the Egyptian forces, and Septimius, a Roman soldier who had formerly served under Pompey, proceeded in a boat to the galley to conduct him to land. He left his vessel with strong forebodings of what might follow ; and as the boat drew near the shore, Septimius stabbed him in the back, and the others falling upon him, completed the treacherous and bloody deed. The galley in which he came had anchored so near the shore, that the murder of Pompey was distinctly visible to those on board. The wild shriek of anguish raised by Cornelia as she beheld her beloved husband fall, reached even to the shore ; and on the instant, the Roman galley cutting her cable, and putting to sea, escaped the pursuit of the Egyptians. Thus perished Pompey the Great, a fugitive and alone on a barbarian shore, after having held for many years a scarcely divided sway at Rome, which he failed in making his exclusively and permanently, only because his rival and antagonist was Cæsar.</p><p>Immediately after his victory at Pharsalia, Cæsar commenced a close pursuit of Pompey, knowing that the war could only end with his death or captivity. Tracing the course of his defeated rival’s flight, he arrived at Alexandria, where he not only received the tidings of his death, but the Egyptian messengers laid before him the head and ring of Pompey. From these melancholy memorials of his mighty rival Cæsar turned away with strong shudderings, and with bursting tears of pity ; and gave orders that near Pompey’s tomb, a magnificent temple should be erected to Nemesis. He next employed himself in settling the disputed claims fbr the succession to the Egyptian throne, which he bestowed on the celebrated Cleopatra, influenced more by the beauty of her person than tlle superiority of her pretensions. While in Egypt, he was exposed to great danger, from an insurrection of the dethroned king’s partisans ; but the opportune arrival of his forces enabled him completely to subdue it, and to establish the sovereignty of Cleopatra. From Egypt he marched into Asia, against Pharnaces, son of Mithridates the Great ; and in the short space of thirty</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>