<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>reflected in the line ST, and work again on the opposite bank at T. We know that the effect of the superficial motion is great, and that it is the principal agent in destroying the banks of canals. So far therefore Du Buat is right. We cannot say with any precision or confidence how the actions of the under filaments are modified ; but we know no reason for not extending to the under filaments what appears so probable with respect to the surface-water.</p><p>3.    The third position is no less evident. We do not know the mode of action of the water on the bank ; but our general notions on this subject, confirmed by common experience, tell us that the more obliquely a stream of water beats on any bank, the less it tends to undermine it or wash it away. A stiff and cohesive soil therefore will suffer no more from being almost perpendicularly buffeted by a stream than a friable sand would suffer from water gliding along its face. Du Buat thinks, from experience, that a clay bank is not sensibly affected till the angle FEB is about thirty-six degrees.</p><p>4.    Since there are causes of retardation, and we still suppose that the discharge is kept up, and that the mean velocity, which had been diminished by the enlargement of the section, is again restored, we must grant that there is provided, in the mechanism of these motions, an accelerating force adequate to this effect. There can be no accelerating force in an open stream but the superficial slope. In the present case it is undoubtedly so ; because by the deepening of the bottom where there is an elbow in the stream, we have of necessity a counter slope. Now, all this head of water, which must produce the augmentation of velocity in that part of the stream which ranges round the convex bank, will arise from the check which the water gets from the concave bank. This occasions a gorge or swell up the stream, enlarges a little the section at BVC; and this, by the principle of uniform motion, will augment all the velocities, deepen the channel, and put every thing again into its train as soon as the water gets into the next reach. The water at the bottom of this basin has very little motion, but it defends the bottom by this very circumstance.’</p><p>Such are the notions which Du Buat entertains of this part of the mechanism of running waters. We cannot say that they are very satisfactory, and they are very opposite to the opinions commonly entertained on the subject. Most persons think that the motion is most rapid and turbulent on the side of the concave bank, and that it is owing to this that the bank is worn away till it has become perpendicular, and that the opposite bank is flat, because it has not been gnawed away in this manner. With respect to this general view of the matter, these persons may be in the right ; and when a stream is turned into a crooked and yielding channel for the first time, this is its manner of action. But Du Buat's aim is to investigate the circumstances which obtain in tlιe case of a regimen ; and in this view he is undoubtedly right as to the facts, though his mode of accounting for these facts may be erroneous. And as this is the only useful view to be taken of the subject, it ought chiefly to be attended to in all our attempts to procure stability to the bed of a river, without the expensive helps of masonry, &amp;c. If we attempt to secure permanency by deepening on the inside of the elbow, our bank will undoubtedly crumble down, diminish the passage, and occasion a more violent action on the hollow bank. The most effectual mean of security is to enlarge the section ; and if we do this on the inside bank, we must do it by widening the stream very much, that we may give a very sloping bank. Our attention is commonly drawn to it when the hollow bank is giving way, and with a view to stop the ravages of the stream. Things are not now in a state of permanency, but nature is working in her own way to bring it about. This may not suit <hi rend="italic">our</hi>  purpose, and we must thwart her. The phenomena which we then observe are frequently very unlike to those described in the preceding paragraphs. We see a violent tumbling motion in the stream towards the hollow bank. We see an evident accumulation of water on that side, and the point B is frequently higher than C. This regorging of the water extends to some distance, and is of itself a cause of greater velocity, and contributes, like a head of stagnant water, to force the stream through the bend, and to deepen the bottom. This is clearly the case when the velocity is excessive, and the hollow bank able to abide the shock. In this situation the water thus heaped up escapes where it best can ; and as the water obstructed by an obstacle put in its way escapes by the sides, and there has its velocity increased, so here the water gorged up against the hollow bank swells over towards the opposite side, and passes round the convex bank with an increased velocity. It depends much on the adjustment between the velocity and consequent accumulation, and the breadth of the stream and the angle of the elbow, whether this augmentation of velocity shall reach the convex bank ; and we sometimes see the motion very languid in that place, and even depositions of mud and sand are made there. The whole phenomena are too complicated to be accurately described in general terms, even in the case of perfect regimen : for this regimen is relative to the consistence of the channel ; and when this is very great, the motions may be most violent in every quarter. But the preceding observations are of importance, because they relate to ordinary cases and to ordinary channels.</p><p>It is evident from Du Buat’s second position, that the proper form of an elbow depends on the breadth of the stream as well as on the radius of curvature, and that every angle of elbow will require a certain proportion between the width of the river and the radius of the sweep. Du Buat gives rules and formula for all these purposes, and shows that in one sweep there may be more than one reflection or rebound. It is needless to enlarge on this matter of mere geometrical discussion. It is with the view of enabling the engineer to trace the windings of a river in such a manner that there shall be no rebounds which shall direct the stream against the sides, but preserve it always in the axis of every reach. This is of consequence, even when the bends of the river are to be secured by masonry or piling ; for we have seen the necessity of increasing the section, and the tendency which the waters have to deepen the channel on that side where the rebound is made. This tends to undermine our defences, and obliges us to give them deeper and more solid foundations in such places. But any person accustomed to the use of the scale and compasses will form to himself rules of practice equally sure and more expeditious than Du Buat’s formulæ.</p><p>We proceed, therefore, to what is more to our purpose, the consideration of the resistance caused by an elhow, and the methods of providing a force capable of overcoming it. We have already taken notice of the salutary consequences arising from the rambling course of rivers, inasmuch as it more effectually spreads them over the face of a country. It is no less beneficial by diminishing their volocity. This it does both by lengthening their course, which diminishes the declivity, and by the very resistance which they meet with at every bend. We derive the chief advantages from our rivers when they no longer shoot their way from precipice to precipice loaded with mud and sand, but peaceably roll along their clear waters, purified during their gentler course, and offer themselves for all the purposes of pasturage, agriculture, and navigation. The more a river winds its way round the foot of the hills, the more is the resistance of its bed multiplied ; the more obstacles it meets with in its way from its source to the sea, the more moderate is its velocity ; and instead of tearing up the very bowels of the earth, and digging for itself a deep trough, along which it sweeps rocks and rooted-up trees, it flows with majestic</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>