<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>was a circle of ground, called the Pomœrium, consecrated by the augurs, and held sacred ; and it was unlawful to build within its limits, or even to pass the plough over it.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> This consecrated circle, however, was not necessarily preserved close to the walls, and it was frequently extended without any change being made in the walls themselves. But the boundaries of the city could only be enlarged by those who had made any acquisition of territory to the Roman state.@@<hi rend="sup">2 </hi>The first who took advantage of this privilege was Sylla, and bis example was followed by Augustus, Claudius, Nero, and Trajan.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> All their improvements, however, consisted in restoring or enlarging the Pomœrium ; and no change was made in the walls of Rome till the time of Aurelian, who built a wall round the city, and enlarged it so as to comprehend the Janiculum and the Pincian hill, with great part of the Campus Martius.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Various exaggerated accounts have been given of the walls of Aurelian, and antiquaries are much divided respecting them, but their probable compass appears to have been about twenty-one miles. The walls of Rome were repaired during the reign of the emperors Arcadius and Honorius. One-third of them was destroyed by Totila about the middle of the sixth century. His ravages were hastily restored with rude and dissimilar materials, by Belisarius, to stand the second siege. Since that period they have been so often shattered, repaired, and remodelled, that but little of their original structure can now remain.</p><p>The number and situation of the ancient gates of the city are involved in hopeless obscurity. Rome at present has sixteen gates, including the four of the <hi rend="italic">Citta Leoninα,</hi>  but several of them have been walled up.</p><p>The Palatine mount is about a mile and a half in circuit, and is nearly square. The ruins of the successive edifices which have stood upon it have raised the soil around its base considerably above the ancient level. About one-half of the surface of it is called the Villa Famese, which occupies all the north-west side, and about one-half of the two sides contiguous, and is let and cultivated as a kitchen-garden. Adjoining, on the south, is the Villa Spada, which lies along a part of the west side overlooking the site of the Circus. Another part of the hill is covered by the upper and lower gardens. Roncioni, and the side opposite to the Cælian mount, is partly occupied by the convent and gardens of Saint Bonaventura. This celebrated spot, which contained the whole Roman people, till the destruction of the republic, was the site of the dwellings of her senators, and the temples of her gods. But the mansions of the Gracchi, of Hortensius, Crassus, Clodius, Catiline, Cicero, and many others, were all swept away, to make room for the palace of Augustus,@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> which is supposed to have stood on the north-west part of the Palatine, looking down on the<hi rend="italic">pulchrum littus,</hi>  “the beautiful shore” near the Tiber. His successor, Tiberius, erected a dwelling for himself on the north side of the Palatine, looking into the Velabrum.@@<hi rend="sup">6 </hi>Another was built on the north-east corner fronting the Capitol by Caligula, who joined the Palatium and the Capitol by a bridge thrown across the Forum.@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi>  But by far the most</p><lb/><p>magnificent was the “ Domus Aurea,” erected by Nero. The only description on record of this gorgeous palace is that of Suetonius, which we shall give in his own words : “ In nothing was he so ruinous as in building. He erected a house extending from the Palatine as far as the Esquiliæ. At first he called it his House of Passage ; afterwards, when it had been destroyed by fire and restored again, he gave it the name of the Golden House. To form an idea ofits extent and magnificence, it may suffice to state tlle following particulars. The vestibule admitted his colossal statue, which was 120 feet high. The building was on so large a scale that it had a triple portico a mile long, also an immense pool like a sea, enclosed by buildings, presenting the appearance of towns. There were moreover grounds laid out for tillage, and for vineyards, and for pasturage and woods, and stocked with a vast number of every description of cattle and wild animals. In other respects, every thing was overlaid with gold, embellished with gems, and with mother-of-pearl. The ceilings of the banqueting-rooms were fretted into ivory coffers, made to turn, that flowers might be showered down upon the guests, and were furnished with pipes for discharging perfumes. The principal banqueting-room was round, and by a perpetual motion, day and night, was made to revolve after the fashion of the universe. There vzere baths streaming with salt and sulphurous waters.”@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi>    “ On</p><p>the ruins ofhis native country,” says Tacitus,@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi> “ Nero erected a palace, in which the profusion of gold and precious stones did not raise the chief admiration, for these were ornaments that widely-diffused luxury had rendered common ; but universal astonishment was excited by its spacious glades, and large artificial lakes, by its thick woods and shades, like vast wildernesses, by its ample lawns and avenues, and far extended prospects.” The successors of Nero made various alterations on the imperial palace. It suffered by fire for the third time under Commodus.@@<hi rend="sup">10</hi> The Goths and Vandals, in the fifth century, pillaged it of most of its treasures, but they do not appear to have rendered it uninhabitable ; for even so late as the beginning of the seventh century He-raclius held a state ceremony in the palace of the Cæsars. Its final destruction seems to have been in a great measure the work of the Farnese popes and princes, who carried off its materials to build their palaces and villas, and buried its magnificent halls beneath their wretched gardens. Many extensive chambers and halls have at different times been discovered, but after being rifled of their statues and ornaments, they have all been filled up again. The whole mount is now one mass of confused and undistinguishable ruins. The very soil is formed of crumbled brick-work. Nothing has been told, nothing can be told, to satisfy the belief of any but a Roman antiquary.</p><p>The celebrated Capitoline hill, the least of all in extent, but greatest in fame and importance, is 470 yards long and 185 broad, and contains about sixteen acres. It exhibits two summits separated by a valley, which is called by antiquaries the <hi rend="italic">lntermontium.</hi>  The height of this hill has been materially diminished, both by the ruins around its base, and by the repeated earthquakes that have shattered the</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Vide Tit. Liv. lib. i. cap. 44.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> “ Pomœrio autem nemini principum licet addere, nisi ei qui agri Barbarici aliqua parte Romanam rempublicam locupletaverit ; addidit autem Augustus, addidit Trajanus, addidit Nero,” &amp;c. Vopiscus in Aurelian, cap. 21.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>    “ Et Pomœrium auxit Cæsar, more prisco ; quo iis, qui protulere imperium etiam terminos urbis propagare datur. Nec tamen duces Romani, quanquam magnis nationibus subactis, usurpaverant nisi L. Sulla et Divus Augustus.” Tacit. Annal, lib. xii. cap. 23. See also Dioιw Cassius—De August, lib. iv. cap. 6, tom. ii. p 776.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>    Vopiscus in Aurelian, cup. 21 ; Ovid, cap. 39; Aurelius, Victor. De Cæsar, cap. 35; Roma Antica Nardini, lib. i. cap. 8.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> Vide Middleton's Life of Cicero ; Suetonius’ Life of Augustus.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi>    ft should be stated, however, that when mention is made of tbe houses of the emperors, it does not mean that these were all separate</p><p>buildings, but such parts of the imperial palace as the emperors added, and which bore their respective names. Vide Josep. Antiq. lib. xix. cap. i. sect. 15.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> Suet in vit. Caligul∙ cap. xxii.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi>    Suet, in vit. Néron, cap. xxxi. Vide Alexan. Ponct. de Urb. Vetera, lib. iii. apud Gravium, tom. iii. p. 68. Dr. Adam’s Roman</p><p>Antiq. p. 491.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi> Tacit. Annul, lib. xv. cap. 42.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">10</hi> Dion. Cassius—In Commod. lib. lxxii. p. 1224. Euseb. Chronicon.<hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>  186.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>