<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>superintendent begins to pass through the haul. A rope attached to the capstan is passed through the nippers, and attached to the end of the haul. The haul is then coiled gradually into the kettle, and the capstan is moved round. The haul is thus drawn slowly through the tar, and the superfluous tar squeezed out of it as it passes through the nippers, the superintendent regulating the weight on the lever, so as to produce the required pressure ; and the end of the haul, as it comes from the capstan, is coiled away, or reeled upon large reels. In this operation the heat of the tar is the most important point to be attended to. If it be too hot, the yarn will be charred ; and if too cold, it will be black, whereas yam intended to be made into ropes should be of a bright-brown colour. The proper heat is indicated, as was before stated, by a scum closing over the surface of the tar, which takes place at</p><p>about 212° Fahrenheit. If</p><p>this scum do not rise, the tar</p><p>is too cold ; and if there be</p><p>an appearance of ebullition,</p><p>the tar is too hot.</p><p><hi rend="italic">⅛thly,Forming Strands.—</hi></p><p>The yam is now ready for</p><p>the next operation, which is</p><p>the making of the strands.</p><p>This comes under the head</p><p>of laying. The place where</p><p>this and the subsequent</p><p>operations are carried on is</p><p>termed the laying-walk ; it is generally part of the alley of which the spinning-walk forms a portion, and it may be of such a width as to allow of many ropes being made at one time. The fixtures of this walk consist of tackle-boards and wheels for twisting strands, and stakes and stake-heads for supporting them. The tackle-board for twisting large strands is fixed at the head, and is represented in fig. 6 ; <hi rend="italic">aa</hi>  strong upright posts, <hi rend="italic">bb</hi>  a plank pierced with holes corresponding to the</p><p>number of strands in</p><p>a rope, which is gene</p><p>rally three. Through</p><p>these holes winches,</p><p>called forelock hooks,</p><p>work. Fig. 7 is an en</p><p>larged section of the</p><p>board, with a forelock</p><p>hook in its place; <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  is</p><p>the handle, <hi rend="italic">b</hi>  a collar</p><p>w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>orking against the</p><p>board, and c the fore</p><p>lock let into an eye in that end of the hook which points down the walk. Fig. 8 is a representation of one of the wheels for twisting smaller strands ; <hi rend="italic">bbb</hi>  being pinions with their axes prolonged, and bentintohooksati<hi rend="sup">,</hi>,∙<hi rend="italic">aa </hi>is the driving-wheel, moved round by the winch c, and <hi rend="italic">dd</hi>  is a strong post fixed at the head of the walk, and to which the wheel is attached in such a manner that it can be easily disengaged, and a larger or smaller wheel applied, as the rope may require. Corresponding to every twisting apparatus, at the head there is a row of bearers or stake-hcads for sup</p><lb/><p>porting the strands when twisting, and extending from the top to the bottom of the walk. These are represented in fig. 9, where <hi rend="italic">aa</hi>  is an upright post, called the stake, firmly fixed, and standing four feet above the ground ; and ύ the stake-head, let through a mortise in the upright at a. foot below the head of the post. In the stake-head there are upright pins, between which the strands are laid, as seen by the drawing. There are also posts at the head and foot for fastening the yarns to when run out for laying. As twisting the strands shortens them, it is necessary to provide at the foot moveable machines for communicating twist. These are called sledges; the largest are formed as in fig. 10, and the smaller sizes as in fig. 11.</p><p>In fig. 10, <hi rend="italic">aa</hi>  corresponds to the tackle-board, and is called a breast-board ; it is bolted to the uprights <hi rend="italic">bb,</hi>  which again are firmly fixed and stayed to the frame <hi rend="italic">cccc.</hi>  The part of the frame behind the uprights is called the tail of the sledge, and on it are laid weights to afford pressure enough to keep the strands stretched. These weights consist of old tar-barrels filled with clay, and are called press-barrels. In laying large ropes, sufficient pressure cannot be obtained by the barrels ; and in that case a double block and tackle is used, one end being fastened to a strong bolt behind the sledge, and the other to the tail of the sledge, and with the tackle-fall a turn or two is taken round a post. The smaller sledges (fig. 11) have only one upright post, to which some one of the wheels, similar to fig. 8, is fixed ; and they have likewise two trucks to run on.</p><p>Of the smaller implements used, the first are the tops (fig. 12) for laying the strands into a rope. These consist of conical blocks of wood, of different sizes, having three equidistant grooves along their surface, and pins through them laterally, serving for handles.</p><p>A piece of soft rope is attached to each handle of the top by its bight, and the ends are used to wrap round the rope in the process of laying.</p><p>These ropes are called tails. When the top is very large, it requires to be supported on a sledge, as shown in fig. 13 ; and in that</p></body></text></TEI>