<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a vessel of the same size and shape, in which, however, the water is at rest. In both, gravity is the sole cause of pressure and motion; but there must be some circumstance peculiar to running waters which modifies the exertion of this active principle, and which, when discovered, must be the basis of hydraulics, and must oblige us to reject every theory founded on fancied hypothesis, and which can only lead to absurd conclusions; and surely absurd consequences, when legitimately drawn, are complete evidence of improper principles.</p><p>When it was discovered experimentally, that the velocities of water issuing from orifices at various depths under the surface were as the square roots of those depths, and the fact was verified by repeated experiments, this principle was immediately, and without modification, applied to every motion of water. Mariotte, Varignon, and Guglielmini, made it the basis of complete systems of hydraulics, which prevail to this day, after having received various amendments and modifications. The same reasoning obtains through them all, though frequently obscured by other circumstances, which are more perspicuously expressed by Guglielmini in his Fundamental Theorems.</p><p>He considers every point P (fig. 1) in a mass of fluid as an orifice in the side of a vessel, and conceives the particle as having a tendency to move with the same velocity with which it would issue from the orifice. Therefore, if a vertical line APC be drawn through that point, and if this be made the axis of a parabola ADE, of which A at the surface of the fluid is the vertex, and AB (four times the height through which a heavy body would fall in a second) is the parameter, the velocity of this particle will be represented by the ordinate PD of this parabola; that is, PD is the space which it would uniformly describe in a second.</p><p>- From this principle is derived the following theory of running waters.</p><p>Let DC (fig. 2) be the horizontal bottom of a reservoir, to which is joined a sloping channel CK of uniform breadth, and let AB be the surface of the standing water in the reservoir.</p><p>Suppose the vertical plane BC pierced with an infinity of holes, through each of which the water issues. The velocity of each filament will be that which is acquired by falling from the surface AB.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The filament C, issuing with this velocity, will then glide down the inclined plane like any other heavy body; and (by the common doctrine of the motion down an inclined plane) when it has arrived at F, it will have the same velocity which it would have acquired by falling through the height OF, the point O being in the horizontal plane AB produced. The same may be said of its velocity when it arrives at H or K. The filament immediately above C will also issue with a velocity which is in the subduplicate ratio of its depth, and will then glide down above the first filament. The same may be affirmed of all the filaments, and of the superficial filament, which will occupy the surface of the descending stream.</p><p>From this account of the genesis of a running stream of water, we may fairly draw the following consequences.</p><p>1. The velocity of any particle R, in any part of the</p><p>stream, is that acquired by falling from the horizontal plane AN.</p><p>2.    The velocity at the bottom of the stream is everywhere greater than anywhere above it, and is least of all at the surface.</p><p>3.    The velocity of the stream increases continually as the stream recedes from its source.</p><p>4.    The depths EF, GH, &amp;c. in different parts of the stream, will be nearly in the inverse subduplicate ratio of the depths under the surface AN: for since the same quantity of water is running through every section EF and GH, and the channel is supposed of uniform breadth, the depth of each section must be inversely as the velocity of the water passing through it. This velocity is indeed different in different filaments of the section; but the mean velocity in each section is in the subduplicate ratio of the depth of the filament under the surface AB. Therefore the stream becomes more shallow as it recedes from the source; and in consequence of this the difference between LH and MG continually diminishes, and the velocities at the bottom and surface of the stream continually approach to equality, and at a great distance from the source they differ insensibly.</p><p>5.    If the breadth of the stream be contracted in any part, the depth of the running water will be increased in that part, because the same quantity must still pass through; but the velocity at the bottom will remain the same, and that at the surface will be less than it was before; and the area of the section will be increased on the whole.</p><p>6.    Should a sluice be put across the stream, dipping a little into the water, the water must immediately rise on the upper side of the sluice till it rises above the level of the reservoir; and the smallest immersion of the sluice will produce this effect. For, by lowering the sluice, the area of the section is diminished, and the velocity cannot be increased till the water heap up to a greater height than the surface of the reservoir; and this acquires a pressure which will produce a greater velocity of efflux through the orifice left below the sluice.</p><p>7.    An additional quantity of water coming into this channel will increase the depth of the stream, and the quantity of water which it conveys; but it will not increase the velocity of the bottom filaments unless it comes from a higher source.</p><p>All these consequences are contrary to experience, and show the imperfection at least of the explanation.</p><p>The third consequence is of all the most contrary to experience. If any one will but take the trouble of following a single brook from its source to the sea, he will find it most rapid in its beginnings among the mountains, gradually slackening its pace as it winds among the hills and gentler declivities, and at last creeping slowly along through the flat grounds, till it is checked and brought to rest by the tides of the ocean.</p><p>Nor is the second consequence more agreeable to observation. It is universally found that the velocity of the surface in the middle of the stream is the greatest of all, and that it gradually diminishes from thence to the bottom and sides. </p><p>And the first consequence, if true, would render the running waters on the surface of this earth the instruments of immediate ruin and devastation. If the waters of our rivers, in the cultivated parts of a country, which are two, three, and four hundred feet lower than their sources, ran with the velocity due to that height, they would in a few minutes lay the earth bare to the very bones.</p><p>The velocities of our rivers, brooks, and rills, being so greatly inferior to what this theory assigns to them, the</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> See Guglielmini’s Hydraulics, 21.</p></body></text></TEI>