<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>citizens ; and another proposed the granting of the privileges of Roman citizenship to all the Italian allies, as also the formation of colonies, not only in Italy, but in the provinces, and in particular at Carthage. By these popular enactments he raised himself to such a height of power in the state, that the senate did not venture to oppose him by direct means, but first endeavoured secretly to diminish his influence with the people. Forthis purpose they encouraged Livius Drusus, another tribune, to rival Gracchus in the race of popularity, by producing measures of a still more democratic nature, which measures the senate readily consented to pass, thinking by this deep yet base policy to weaken the power of Gracchus before attempting any more direct attack upon him. Such was the fickleness and venality of the democratic party, that they soon began to applaud Drusus above their recent leader; and when Caius stood candidate a third time for the tribuneship, he was unsuccessful. The senate saw the hour of retribution at hand, Opimius, the most daring of the aristocratic party, was elected consul, and the two factions prepared for a final struggle.</p><p>An accidental quarrel, in which Antylias, one of the consul’s lictors, was killed by the friends of Gracchus, precipitated the strife. The senate conferred the dictatorial power on Opimius in the usual terms. Gracchus with his followers took possession of the Aventine hill, and attempted to open a negotiation with the consul. This was refused, and an unconditional surrender required, which not being yielded, the consul attacked the insurgents, gained the hill, and slew great numbers of them ; and Gracchus himself, after a fruitless endeavour to save his life by flight, fell either by his own hand, or by that of a faithful slave who accompanied him, and from whom he exacted this bloody proof of fidelity. Not less than three thousand of the friends and followers of Gracchus fell in this ill-omened struggle ; and their bodies were ignominiously cast into the Tiber, as those of traitors to the commonwealth, and conspirators against its laws and government.</p><p>These contests, known in history by the designation of “ the seditions of the Gracchi,” shewed but too plainly that the ancient patriotic spirit of Rome had departed, never more to return. The attempt to check the growth of the already exorbitant wealth and power of the nobles had utterly failed; failed, although all legal and constitutional means had been exerted for its enforcement ; failed even partly in consequence of the violent methods pursued with a view to compel its adoption ; failed by being met with at least equally subtle, unconstitutional, and violent opposition ; and the two antagonist powers, wealth and poverty, avarice and wretchedness, equally corrupt and unprincipled, sunk for a time into quiescence, though unreconciled, waiting but for another opportunity toburst into fiercer and more implacable hostility. The fires of the feud were not extinguished by the defeat and death of the Gracchi ; they were but covered up with deceitful ashes, beneath which they smouldered scarcely observed, but acquiring tenfold strength, and preparing for an eruption which should devastate not Italy alone, but every region of the Roman world.</p><p>Within a few years after the death of Caius Gracchus, the senate not only found means to evade the Agrarian law, but also to procure its repeal ; and even the land-tax which had been introduced as an intermediate step, the produce of which was to be distributed among the people, was annulled; and on the one hand, the extortion and rapacity of the nobles, and on the other, the degeneracy of the populace, proceeded with increased rapidity. Neither the authority of the censors, nor the enactment of sumptuary laws, could retard the luxuries of the wealthy ; while the very means taken to support the poorer classes out of the surplus riches of the state and of great families, increased their venality, turbulence, and licentiousness.</p><lb/><p>This universal corruption of public morals was manifested in a very striking manner in the next great war into which Rome entered, which was that against Jugurtha. This crafty and far-sighted Numidian had served in the Roman armies, and made himself intimately acquainted with both the strength and the weakness of the Roman character. Having been left joint-heir to the kingdom of Numidia, along with his two cousins, the sons of Micipsa, he resolved to sieze the whole, and procured the murder of the one, while the other fled for safety and redress to Rome. But at Rome Jugurtha’s gold was more powerful than the appeals of the wronged Adherbal ; and the senate decreed that the kingdom should be divided equally between the two. Scarcely had Adherbal returned to Numidia, when Jugurtha, stimulated to fresh crimes by his recently experienced impunity, declared war against his cousin, obtained possession of his person, and put him to death in violation of the terms of his surrender. The tribune Memmius constrained the senate to declare war against the usurper ; which was frustrated by his purchasing a peace of the consul. He was then ordered to repair to Rome, under safe conduct, to answer for his guilt. Once more was the Numidian gold too powerful for the course of justice, and Jugurtha would have been acquitted, had he not again embrued his hands in the blood of another kinsman. He was now ordered to quit Rome, return to his dominions, and there prepare either to submit unconditionally, or to meet the utmost hostility of the offended and outraged republic. The war was conducted for a time with little success on the part of the Romans, till the command was entrusted to Metellus, a man of great military skill and incorruptible integrity. When this general had almost completed the conquest of Numidia, he was supplanted in the command by Caius Marius, a man of the lowest extraction, but of great abilities, courage, and force of character, and of at least equal perfidy, deceitfulness, and ferocity, who, by his popular talents, and his intriguing spirit, had got himself raised to the consulship. Marius speedily reduced Jugurtha to the necessity of taking refuge with Bocchus king of Mauritania, defeated the united armies of these two monarchs, and began to treat with Bocchus fbr the surrender, or rather betrayal of Jugurtha. This, however, was accomplished by Sylla, who was at that time quaestor in the army of Marius, and who so far succeeded in depriving Marius of the honour arising from the capture of Jugurtha, as Marius had done Metellus. This incident, in all probability, laid the foundation of that rancorous animosity between those two formidable rivals, which afterwards blazed out so fiercely, and spread such extensive devastation throughout the Roman dominions. Jugurtha was at length brought captive to Rome, and after being exhibited in the triumphant procession of Marius, was cast naked into a dungeon, and left to perish in the agonies of hunger.</p><p>The elevation of Marius to the consulship was an event of a very momentous character, both in itself and in its con -sequences. In his previous tribuneship he had shewn himself to be fully qualified to act the part of a demagogue in every respect. Being himself a person of the most obscure origin, all his habits and feelings were thoroughly adapted to those of the very lowest of the people ; and yet the consciousness of great native powers of mind, gave him a certain haughtiness of bearing which could not brook control either from the senate wdlicħ he braved, or the people whom he at once led and governed. Upon his appointment to tlle consulship, and previously to his departure for Numidia to supersede Metellus, the senate gave him little encouragement in the raising of those levies which were requisite for the vigorous prosecution ofthe war,being probablywilling to see the popularity of the new demagogue abated, though at the expense of their country’s military reputation. But Marius was not a person to be easily baffled. Instead of</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>