<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>quently we remain ignorant of their foundation ; but it is not necessary for the prosperity of the subject that he have the talents of the senator; he can profit by the statute without understanding its grounds. It is so in the present instance. We have not as yet been able to infer the law of retardation observed in the filaments of a running stream from any sound mechanical principle. The problem, how-ever, does not appear beyond our powers, if we assume, with Sir Isaac Newton, that the velocity of any particular filament is the arithmetical mean between those of the filaments immediately adjoining. We may be assured, that the filament in the axis of an inclined cylindrical tube, of which the current is in train, moves the fastest, and that all those in the same circumference round it are those which glide along the pipe. We may affirm the same thing of the motions in a semicylindrical inclined channel conveying an open stream. But even in these we have not yet demonstrated the ratio between the extreme velocities, nor in the different circles. This must be decided experimentally.</p><p>And here we are under great obligations to Du Buat. He has compared the velocities in the axes of a prodigious number and variety of streams, differing in size, form, slope, and velocity, and has computed in them all the mean velocities, by measuring the quantities of water discharged in a given time. His method of measuring the bottom velocity was simple and just. He threw in a gooseberry, as nearly as possible of the same specific gravity with the water. It was carried along the bottom almost without touching it. See Resistance op Fluids, p. 180.</p><p>He discovered the following laws : 1. In small velocities the velocity in the axis is to that at the bottom in a ratio of considerable inequality. 2. This ratio diminishes as the velocity increases, and in very great velocities approaches to the ratio of equality. 3. What was most remarkable was, that neither the magnitude of the channel, nor its slope, had any influence in changing this proportion, while the mean velocity remained the same. Nay, though the stream ran on a channel covered with pebbles or coarse sand, no difference worth noticing was to be observed from the velocity over a polished channel. 4. And if the velocity in the axis is constant, the velocity at the bottom is also constant, and is not affected by the depth of water or magnitude of the stream. In some experiments the depth was thrice the width, and in others the width was thrice the depth. This changed the proportion of the magnitude of the section to the magnitude of the rubbing part, but made no change on the ratio of the velocities. This is a thing which no theory could point out.</p><p>Another most important fact ιvas also the result of his observation, viz. that <hi rend="italic">the mean velocity in any pipe or open stream is the arithmetical mean between the velocity in the axis and the velocity at the sides of a pipe or bottom of an open stream.</hi>  We have already observed, that the ratio of the velocity in the axis to the velocity at the bottom diminished as the mean velocity increased. This variation he was enabled to express in a very simple manner, so as to be easily remembered, and to enable us to tell any one of them by observing another.</p><p><hi rend="italic">If we take unity from the square root of the superficial velocity, expressed in inches, the square of the remainder is the velocity at the bottom ; and the mean velocity is the half sum of these two.</hi>  Thus, if the velocity in the middle of the stream be 25 inches per second, its square root is five ; from which if we take unity, there remains four. The square of this, or 16, is the velocity at the bottom, and — lθ, or 20½, is the mean velocity.</p><p>This is a very curious and most useful piece of information. The velocity in the middle of the stream is the easiest measured of all, by any light small body floating down ; and the mean velocity is the one which regulates the train, the discharge, the effect on machines, and all the most important consequences.</p><p>We may express this by a formula of most easy recollection. Let V be the mean velocity, <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  the velocity in the axis, and <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  the velocity at the bottom ; we have</p><p>« = (√t&gt; —1)', and V =</p><p>Also <hi rend="italic">v =</hi>  (√∖ΓΞ7¼ + ¼)≈, and <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  = (√w + 1)<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.</p><p>V <hi rend="italic">={V~v-</hi>  ⅛)* + ¼, and V <hi rend="underline">= (√κ+⅛</hi>)<hi rend="sup">2</hi>+ ¼.u = (√c — 1)<hi rend="underline"><hi rend="sup">2</hi>, and</hi>u<hi rend="italic">  = {VV — ¼ — ⅜)<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.</hi></p><p>Also <hi rend="italic">v — u</hi>  = 2 s∕ V — ¼ and <hi rend="italic">v —</hi>  V, = V — <hi rend="italic">u, = </hi>√V — ¼5 that is, the difference between these velocities increases in the ratio of the square roots of the mean velocities diminished by a small constant quantity.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>This may perhaps give the mathematicians some help in ascertaining the law of degradation from the axis to the sides. Thus, in a cylindrical pipe, we may conceive the current as consisting of an infinite number of cylindrical shells sliding within each other like the draw-tubes of a spy-glass. Each of these is in equilibrio, or as much accelerated by the one within it as it is retarded by the one without ; therefore, as the <hi rend="italic">momentum</hi>  of each diminishes in the proportion of its diameter (the thickness being supposed the same in all), the velocity of separation must increase by a certain law from the sides to the axis. The magnitude of the small constant quantity here spoken of seems to fix this law.</p><p>The place of the mean velocity could not be discovered with any precision. In moderate velocities it was not more than one fourth or one fifth of the depth distant from the bottom. In very great velocities it was sensibly higher, but never in the middle of the depth.</p><p>The knowledge of these three velocities is of great importance. The superficial velocity is easily observed, hence the mean velocity is easily computed. This multiplied by the section gives the expense ; and if we also measure the expanded border, and then obtain the mean depth (or √<hi rend="italic">d),</hi>  we can, by the formula of uniform motion, deduce the slope, or, knowing the slope, we can deduce any of the other circumstances.</p><p>The following table of these three velocities will save the trouble of calculation in one of the most frequent questions of hydraulics.</p><table><row><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>Velocity in Inches.</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>Velocity in Inches.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Sur-</p><p>face.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Bottom.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mean.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Sur-</p><p>face.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Bottom.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Mean.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0∙000</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0∙5</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9∙</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12-5</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0∙172</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1∙081</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9∙753</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13∙376</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0∙537</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1∙768</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>18</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10∙463</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14-231</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2∙5</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>19</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>11∙283</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15-141</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1∙526</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3∙263</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12∙055</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16∙027</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2∙1</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4∙050</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12∙674</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16∙837</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2-709</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4∙854</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>22</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13-616</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17-808</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3∙342</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5∙67</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>23</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14-402</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>18-701</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4∙</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6∙5</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>24</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15-194</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>19-597</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4∙674</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7∙337</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16∙</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>20-5</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>11</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5∙369</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8∙184</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>26</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16∙802</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21-401</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6∙071</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9∙036</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>27</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>17∙606</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>22-303</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6∙786</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9∙893</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>28</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>18∙421</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>23-210</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7-553</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>10-756</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>29</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>19∙228</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>24-114</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8∙254</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>11-622</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>30</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>20∙044</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25-022</p></cell></row></table><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  In these formula;, and in the following table, the velocities are understood to be expressed in French inches.VOL. XIX.</p></body></text></TEI>