<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>guished by a very peculiar vein of dry humour intermingled with a tinge of orientalism in their notions of birth and pride of ancestry and personal dignity, and hence the Spanish novelists seem to have been perfectly alive to the ridiculous features of their countrymen, while sharing very probably in the same exaggerated pretensions themselves. Accordingly, alongwith the adventures of rogues, and beggars, and gipsies, who, during the reigns of the Austrian Philips, appear to have literally swarmed in Madrid, are interspersed ample illustrations of this union of poverty and pride, and the stratagems with which many a pompous cavalier, walking the streets, as Lazaro says, like the Duke of Arcos, is occupied at home in order “ to procure a crust of dry bread, and having eat it, to appear with due decorum in public, by the art of fitting on a ruffle so as to suggest the idea of a shirt, and adjusting a cloak in such a manner as to make it be believed there are clothes under it.”@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Mendoza’s novel contains a sketch of one of these shirtless and famished hidalgos eagerly devouring some crusts which Lazaro had begged in the morning, on pretence of trying whether the bread was sufficiently wholesome, which gives an image of starvation, in which the painful is strangely blended with a sort of sombre gaiety.</p><p>Equal, if not superior to Mendoza’s romance, is the <hi rend="italic">Gusman d‘Alfατache</hi>  of Matteo Aleman (1599,) which, though dealing in the same gloomy pictures of want and misery, has more variety in its pictures, and a more severe and caustic character in its sarcasm. It has been erroneously supposed to have furnished many particulars to Gil Blas ; in fact, it would be difficult to point out one, except the incident of the parasite who obtains a supper at the expense of the eighth wonder of the world. In the same taste is the <hi rend="italic">Gran Tacαno of</hi>  Quevedo.</p><p>The merit of having supplied Le Sage with much of his materials, may be more plausibly claimed by Vicente Espine), the author of the <hi rend="italic">Vida del Escudero Marcos de Obregon,</hi>  printed in 1618. Indeed, while the superior grace, spirit, and gay philosophy of Le Sage are apparent, it is impossible not to make a considerable deduction from his mere invention after reading the w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ork of Espinel. The prologue, the adventure of the parasite, the dispersion of the company at Cacabelos by the muleteer, the adventure of the robber’s cave, the surprise by the corsairs, the contributions levied by those pious hermits, Don Raphael and Ambrose de Lamela, the service with the Duke of Lerma, and many of the other incidents, have nearly an exact parallel in the ruder and drier work of Espinel. Even some of the witty points, which we might be disposed at first sight to believe were Le Sage’s, turn out to be the property of the Spanish chaplain ; such as Don Matthias de Silva’s reply, when asked to fight a duel early in the morning, that he never rose before one, even for a party of pleasure, and could not be expected to rise at six to have his throat cut.</p><p>This much, however, must be said for Le Sage, that he shows no desire to conceal the source of his obligations, for one of his characters is termed Marcos Obregon, and the Sangrado of his novel is, undisguisedly, the Sagredo of Espinel. Le Sage, however, knew that after every deduction was made on the score of invention, the merit of his novel would remain much the same. He threw lightness and sunshine into the mean and gloomy pictures of the Spaniards, taking care to efface the recollections of folly and knavery in his adventurers, by a cheerful and respectable termination of their career ; and though the graduation of the fool into the knave, and the knave into the honest man, upon a mere principle of utility, be not perhaps in itself a very lofty moral, it is at all events far more agreeable than that of the Spanish novelists, where the rogue continues such to the last, and his only advancement is to a higher degree in the curriculum of knavery. A romance of a more pleasing and political cast than these tales of knavery, was the historical romance, the <hi rend="italic">Civil Wars of Granada,</hi>  by Gines Perez de la Hita, printed in 1604, turning on the dissensions of the Zegris and Abencerrages during the reign of Boabdil, and giving occasion, as might be expected, to many fine descriptions of tournaments, feasts of canes, Moorish palaces and gardens, and the contrast between the Christian and the Moorish chivalry. From this romance Florian has mainly borrowed the idea and materials of his <hi rend="italic">Goη-salvo of Cordova.</hi></p><p>One other work offiction deserving notice, though partak-ingmore of the nature of the satire than the novel, is the <hi rend="italic">Fray Gerundio</hi>  (Friar Gerund) of the Jesuit de l’Isla,—a severe, but rather tedious satire upon the absurdities and bad taste of the popular preachers of the time. In romantic literature the Spaniards at the present day seem to be entirely deficient. Translations of the popular French and English novels abound, but native talent or invention appear to be at an end.</p><p>In France the pastoral romances of D’Urfé and his imitators, and the heroic romances of Gomberville, Scudery, and Calprenede, whose object was “peindre Caton galant et Brutus dameret,” were succeeded by an inundation of <hi rend="italic">conies des fees</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">voyages imaginaires,</hi>  appearing about the close of the seventeenth and the commencement of the eighteenth century. This species of nursery literature, which, like the character of the fair Arricidia in <hi rend="italic">Clelia,</hi>  was “ furieusement extraordinaire et terriblement merveilleux,” seemed peculiarly well suited to the frivolous tastes which then pervaded French society ; and its temporary attraction was perhaps based in some degree upon the very w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ant of reason and common sense, which rendered its permanent popularity impossible. When the sage Oglou in Voltaire asked the sultanas “ comment preferez vous des contes que sont sans raison et que ne signifient rien,” the answ<hi rend="sup">,</hi>er of the sultanas was, “ c’est précisément pour cela que nous les aimons.”</p><p>The chief writers in this school of fiction, with whose compositions mostof us have in our early days been rendered familiar, through the little gilded volumes of Mr. Newberry or his successors, were Perrault, the Countess D’Aulnoy, Madame Murat, and Mademoiselle de laForce,of whom Perrault isde-cidedly the best, his tales being distinguished by a simplicity and naivete of style indispensable in this style of writing, and in which the productions of the ladies are deficient. No great share of original invention is displayed by any of them. The chief storehouse from which they drew was the <hi rend="italic">Notti Pia-cevoli</hi>  of the Italian novelist Straparola, and the very remarkable Neapolitan collection by Giambattista Basile, entitled the <hi rend="italic">Peηtαmeroηe,</hi>  of which the first edition appeared in 1637.</p><p>A sightly different direction was given to this taste for marvels by the translation into French of <hi rend="italic">daaArabimNights </hi>by Galland, and of the <hi rend="italic">Persian Tales</hi>  by Petit de la Croix and Le Sage, which led to a host of oriental imitations. And the childishness and absurdity of the whole of this department of literature was exposed with great wit and liveliness by Count Antony Hamilton, in his <hi rend="italic">Fleur &lt;ΓEpiηe,</hi>  and in his unfinished tale of the <hi rend="italic">Four Facardins.</hi></p><p>But this same period was distinguished by the produc- ∖  tions of some writers of a higher order : Marivaux, (1688— 1763), Prevot, (1697—1763), and Le Sage, (1668—1746). Marivaux had a good deal of Richardson’s power of delicate portrait painting, by an accumulation of miniature touches : nor is he deficient in the power of managing the interesting situations with which his <hi rend="italic">Mariamne</hi>  especially abounds. And certainly, if we except Mademoiselle La Fayette’s pleasing romance of the <hi rend="italic">Princess of Cleves,</hi>  he may claim the merit of having been the first, in France, to reduce the novel from mere extravagance, both of incident and charac</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Dunlop’s<hi rend="italic">History of Fiction,</hi>  vol. iii. p. 119.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>