<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to be given up to them, as there had been no war declared between the Romans and the Gauls. The Romans refused to yield up their brave countrymen to torture and death ; and the Gauls, finding their demands rejected, broke up in haste from Clusium, and marched away, shouting <hi rend="italic">“ to</hi>  Rome, to Rome.”</p><p>The Roman army had marched towards the Etrurian frontier, expecting to meet the enemy at some distance from the city ; but the Gauls had crossed the Tiber considerably higher up, and were proceeding along its left bank towards Rome. Upon receiving this intelligence, the consuls hastened back to the city, crossed the river, and marched rapidly against the enemy. The Romans had scarcely time to assume a hasty position on the banks of the Alia, where, through a deep bed, that slight stream joins the Tiber. The Gauls at the very beginning of the battle, turned the right flank of the enemy, drove it back in confusion on the main body, and rushing impetuously in their victorious career, hurled the broken mass headlong into the river. The rout was total, the slaughter great. Many were drowned, and many more slain by the Gaulish javelins, while attempting to swim across the river ; those who succeeded fled to Veii, and there sought an ignoble safety. Others fled to Rome, carrying the tidings of their utter discomfiture ; and thence continued their flight to Veii, despairing of being able to save Rome. The Capitol alone was garrisoned by a devoted few, who were resolved to defend this last bulwark of their country, or perish in its ruins.</p><p>The city was left open and undefended, but it was on the third day after the battle that the Gauls entered it. In the interval, the great body of the Roman citizens had abandoned their homes, and fled for refuge to the neighbouring cities, carrying the most sacred of their images and relics to Caere, and leaving those which they could not remove deeply buried in a secret retreat. But some of the priests, and the aged patricians of the highest rank and dignity, could not endure the thought of quitting their native city, and dragging out the remainder of their feeble days in a foreign land. They solemnly devoted themselves and the Gauls to the infernal deities, and then seated themselves in the forum to wait their death, by which they hoped to draw down on the Gauls the vengeance of the gods. When the Gauls entered, all was silence in the forsaken city, nor did they see a human being till they reached the forum. There they beheld the majestic fathers of Rome, seated each on his ivory chair of office, and clad in his senatorial robes, unmoving, silent, awful impersonations of sublime despair. The Gauls gazed on them with reverential respect, regarding them as more than mortal. At length one of the Gauls drew near to M. Papirius, and began to stroke gently his long white beard. Papirius, a priest of the highest rank and sanctity, indignant at the profane touch of the barbarian, struck him on the head with his ivory sceptre. The Gaul cut down the venerable man with his sword. The spell was broken ; barbarian fury kindling at the sight of blood, rushed on its defenceless prey, and in an instant the vows of tlle aged senators were ratified in their blood.</p><p>After pillaging the forsaken city, the Gauls turned their attention to the Capitol ; but being unable to scale the rock, were repulsed from the only access with considerable loss. They now changed their plan, made the city their head-quarters, continued the blockade of the Capitol, and spread devastation into the surrounding country. Meanwhile the Romans who had taken shelter at Veii, began to recover courage, and to seek to open a communication with the brave garrison in the Capitol. This was accomplished by a daring youth named Pontius Cominius, who swam across the Tiber and scaled the cliff during the night, and having explained to the garrison the state of affairs at Veii, returned as he came, undiscovered by the Gauls. But in the morning some traces of his exploit were seen by the besiegers, who concluded that if the cliff had been scaled by one, it might by more. They made the attempt, and the spot being thought inaccessible, and therefore left unguarded by the garrison, they had nearly reached the summit, when the sacred geese kept in the temple of Juno, hearing the unwonted sound at such an hour, made so much noise as to awaken M. Manlius, a young patrician, whose house was hard by the temple. He sprang up, seized his arms, called on his sleeping comrades, and ran to the edge ofthe cliff just as the head of a Gaul was appearing above it. Manlius rushed upon him, dashed the boss of his shield into his face, and tumbled him down the precipice. Thc falling Gaul bore down many of his countrymen along with him, and the rest, perceiving themselves discovered, and struck with terror, leapt, fell, or scrambled down the crags, and abandoned the attempt.</p><p>But though the Capitol was thus secured against direct force or surprise, it might be reduced by famine, and therefore the Gauls continued the siege. The brave garrison were reduced to the utmost extremities, but still continued the defence of their impregnable citadel, till the Gauls began to suffer scarcely inferior calamities, arising likewise from the want of food, aggravated by the unhealthiness of a Roman autumn. Great numbers daily perished; and the place where their bodies were burned was long afterwards known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Gallica busta,</hi>  or Gallic funeral piles. These calamities induced the Gauls to offer more reasonable terms, which the exhausted garrison was willing to accept. The demand was one thousand pounds of gold, on payment of which the Gauls agreed to depart from the Roman city and territories. It is also related that the Gauls had received intelligence of their own country being inva&lt;led by the Venetians, which increased their willingness to come to terms with Rome.</p><p>A truce was concluded ; both parties met in the forum ; and the military tribune, Q. Sulpicius, proceeded to weigh the stipulated sum. The Gauls fraudulently attempted to falsify the weights ; and when Sulpicius complained, Brennus, the king of the Gauls, cast his heavy broadsword into the scale which contained the weights. The tribune asked what was meant by this action ; and the haughty barbarian insultingly replied, “It means, woe to the vanquished.” Having received this large ransom, the Gauls appear to have departed from central Italy, and returned to their own.settle-ments on the regions in the valley of the Po, leaving the Romans to set about repairing, as they might, their sacked and desolated city.</p><p>The accounts which represent Camillus to have entered the forum at the moment when Brennus had uttered his insulting <hi rend="italic">Vae</hi><hi rend="italic">victis,</hi>  and to have ordered the gold to be taken away, saying, it was the custom of Romans to ransom their country with steel, not gold ; to have driven the Gauls out of the city, and next day to have defeated them so totally that not a man was left alive to carry the tidings of their defeat to their countrymen ; these accounts are manifestly parts of some poetical lays in honour of Camillus, the hero of his age and country. But they are too inconsistent with the more plain statements of other historians, and with the well known facts of the case in other respects, to receive any other than a poetic credence best suited to their poetic character.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>But when the first feelings of exulting triumph abated, and the Romans began to gaze around them on the scene of ruin and desolation, their hearts sunk within them, and they were on the point of yielding to the wretched dictates of cowardly despair. It had been previously proposed by the popular party, that a large body of the Roman citizens</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  See Niebuhr, vol. ii. p. 517,<hi rend="italic">et scq∙</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>