<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the chief interest connected with these novelists consists 'in the hints or materials furnished by them to Shakspeare, Massinger, Beaumont and Fletcher, and our dramatic writers of the time of Elizabeth and James, to whom indeed these works, particularly those of Bandello, afforded a perfect storehouse for plots. Among the nine volumes of Ban-dello’s works contained in the Novelliero, some interesting and a few pathetic tales may be pointed out ; but Cintio’s can have no interest in themselves except for those who love to sup full of horrors ; for he was one of those wholesale dealers in the terrible, who thought that poetical effect was to be produced by a vigorous operation on the nerves rather than the feelings, and therefore piqued himself, like the schoolmaster in Gil Blas, on massacring all the personages of his tragedies, even to the prompter.</p><p>Towards the close of the last century, a taste for novels in a style somewhat resembling our own, appears to have gained ground, and several tales of a melancholy kind made their appearance. With these we do not profess to be acquainted ; nor has any one which appeared prior to the <hi rend="italic">Promessi Sposi </hi>ofManzoni, attained the least reputation beyond Italy, with the exception of the <hi rend="italic">Ultime Lettere di Jacopo Ortis,</hi>  an early production of Ugo Foscolo, (1802) ; and the result partly of a melancholy event occurring in his own family, and partly of the study of Goethe’s <hi rend="italic">Werther,</hi>  by which the enthusiastic mind of Foscolo appears to have been very powerfully affected. Like <hi rend="italic">Werther,</hi>  it is a story of love and suicide, full of fervour, violence, and, to speak the truth, of absurdity ; yet delivered with a species of eloquence, and a certain appearance of conviction, which, so far at least as regarded the expression of mental discomfort, and the misery arising from a total want of all fixed opinion, was perhaps sufficiently real. To the Italians, who knew little or nothing of Goethe, this stormy effervescence of an impassioned temperament, and all this eloquent “ questioning of fate,” possessed even an air of originality; and being the first successful attempt to introduce the sentimental romance of the school of Rousseau and Goethe into Italy, it naturally awakened a degree of enthusiasm which now appears somewhat disproportioned to its real merit.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Promessi Sposi</hi>  of Manzoni certainly approaches much more nearly to the idea of a good romance than any thing which Italy has yet produced ; but, after all, it too is essentially an imitation. If we had had no Scott, we should have had no Manzoni. The idea of illustrating a subject connected with the Italian history of the commencement of the seventeenth century ; the introduction of historical characters, such as that of Cardinal Borromeo, who is the <hi rend="italic">deus ex machina</hi>  of the piece ; the antiquarian lore displayed in the way in which the bread-riot in Milan (a close parallel to the insurrection of the Liegeois in <hi rend="italic">Quentin Durward),</hi>  is wrought up ; the account of the plague in tlle Milanese, in which Manzoni has tried to imitate at once Boccacio and Scott,—all concur to satisfy us, that Manzoni, though an able lyric poet, has no great share of original invention, and that though he can make a good use of materials furnished by others, he is one of those literary commercialists who require to borrow the main portion of the capital with which they are to trade. We are far, however, from denying the real merits of this performance of Manzoni, in which the characters of Cardinal Borromeo, and the peasant hero and heroine, Renzo and Lucia, are naturally and pleasingly drawn, and in which some of the scenes, such as the opening scene at Don Abbondio’s house, the riot in Milan, the interview between the unknown and the Cardinal, and some of the incidents and descriptions connected with the plague, are of vivid interest.</p><p>Since the appearance of the romance of Manzoni, who has lately abandoned both fiction and poetry for religion, many attempts have been made by Rosini, D’Azeglio, Guerazzi, Tommaseo, Belmonte, and others, to transfer the historical</p><p>romance to an Italian soil, and to give a romantic interest to the delineation of the Italian feudal history of the middle ages, or of periods somewhat later. The first, and we believe the best, of these appears to be the <hi rend="italic">Monaca de Monza </hi>of Rosini, who has founded his story on an episode in the <hi rend="italic">Promessi Sposi.</hi>  Were we to form a judgment from a few of these attempts which we have read, as to the merits of those of which we remain ignorant, we should be inclined to say generally, that nothing is more remarkable than the total want of interest which Italian subjects possess in Italian hands ; a result which appears the more singular, since at one time it was only necessary in our English romances to transfer the scene to Italy, to enlist at once our warmest sympathies in favour of the story. Now-a-days, we think, when the subject is almost entirely in the hands of native novel-writers, the very idea of embarking on an Italian story of the middle ages, seems to act upon the fancy as the most powerfid refrigerative. Strangely enough, too, it is to be observed, that the Italian novelistβ of modern times never appear to greater advantage than in the description of the most furious battles, carried on with all the determination and bloody-mindedness of an Esplan-dian or a Bobadil, as in <hi rend="italic">Ettοre Fieramosca,</hi>  by Massimo D’Azeglio, a son-in-law ofManzoni, <hi rend="italic">οτEAssεdiο di Firenze, </hi>by Gualandi ; an expenditure of valour on paper which we fear is scarcely justified by the fact, since, if we are to give credit to the accounts of Guacciardini, many of their most doughty encounters were as harmless in their results as the protracted passage of arms between Gymnast and Tripet, in <hi rend="italic">Rabelais,</hi>  as to which uncle Toby, after listening to an endless detail of the various complicated manœuvres, declared, that one home-thrust of the bayonet would have been worth them all.</p><p>In Spain, which, though not the birth-place, had certainly become by adoption pre-eminently the country of the chivalrous romance, and where, perhaps, its extravagances had been less redeemed by talent than any where else, it is well known that a revolution in taste was effected by the inimitable satire of Cervantes, (1547-1616), which Montesquieu, with amusing extravagance, describes as the single admirable book in the Spanish language which shews the absurdity of all the rest. So effectually, indeed, did that work (published in 1605) attain its end, or rather one of its ends, that after its appearance no romance of chivalry appeared in Spain, and the old ones so entirely ceased to be printed, that it is with difficulty that copies of them are now to be obtained. The “ ultimus Romanorum,” the last adherent of the good old romance, was Don Juan de Silva y Toledo, who published his <hi rend="italic">Don Policisne de Boecia</hi>  in 1602, three years before the appearance of the <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote.</hi></p><p>But, had that book been solely devoted to the object of exploding the old romances of chivalry, it would probably have shortly been forgotten with the extravagances it exposed. The charm which has given a perennial life and continued popularity to <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote,</hi>  is the deeper idea w hich it contains of illustrating, in comic colours, the contest between imagination and reality ; the danger, both to its possessor and to others, of all misdirected enthusiasm, whether it take the direction of reviving an extinct age of chivalry, or any other course plainly running counter to the current of society all around it, by means of which a constant collision is produced, in which, whatever becomes of the world, the visionary himself is sure to be the sufferer. For the fuller development of this idea, he has placed beside the knight, who represents the imagination without the common sense, a squire who is the type of the vulgar common sense without the imagination. Between these children of his brain, he parcels out tlle treasures of his mind, bequeathing to the knight his own high spirit and courage, his learning, his generosity, and his love of truth ;</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>