<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>amounted now to 300, which continued to be its stated number.</p><p>Soon after these events, Tullus made war upon the Sabines, and in a bloody, and for some time doubtful encounter, again obtained the victory. Another war arose with the confederate towns of Latium, who began to dread the growing polver of Rome after the destruction of Alba. The Latian war terminated without any decided reverses sustained by either party ; and an alliance was formed between the Romans and the Latins. Tullus had now leisure to direct his attention to the arts of peace, in which, however, he did not equally excel. The only public works ascribed to him were the enclosing of a space for the Comitium, or assembly of the people ; and the building of a Curia, or senate-house. Towards the end of his reign his mind was disturbed by prodigies, indicating the wrath of the gods, for religion neglected, and temples left desolate. A shower of stones fell from heaven on the Alban mount ; and the awful accents of a supernatural voice were heard to issue from the consecrated summit of the hill. A plague swept away numbers of the Roman people. The king himself sickened ; and from having been neglectful of religion, became the slave of superstitious terrors. In vain did he supplicate the gods. He had disregarded them in his days of prosperity, and in his adversity no deity regarded his prayers, or sent relief. In his despair he presumed to use the divinations of Numa, by the rites of Jupiter Elicius; but tlle only answer returned tvas the lightning of the offended gods, by which Tullus himself and his whole household were smitten and consumed. Such is the legend of Tullus Hostilius, said to have been the third king of Rome.</p><p>After the death of Tullus Hostilius there followed another interregnum, during which the senate, as usual, exercised the functions of sovereignty. An assembly was then held, in which Ancus Marcius, a son of the daughter of Numa, and a Sabine by race, was chosen king. He assumed the sovereignty with the usual formalities, receiving the sanction of the comitia curiata. Ancus seems to have taken the conduct and character of Numa for his model rather than those of his more warlike predecessors. His first object was to restore those religious rites which had been neglected by Tullus ; and for this purpose he caused the institutions of Numa to be inscribed on tables, and suspended in public places, that all might read, know, and observe them.</p><p>While he was thus busied in restoring religious worship, the Latins imagined they might recover that power which had been wrested from them by Tullus. They soon found that Ancus, though peacefully inclined, was by no means incapable of resenting injuries. He raised an army, encountered the insurgent Latins, and after a severe struggle, not only defeated them in the field wherever he met them, but also took from them several cities, whose inhabitants he removed to Rome, and settled on the Aventine hill, on the south of the Palatine. On the left bank of the Tiber he prosecuted his conquests till he reached the sea, where he built Ostia, and settled a colony in it to secure it as a permanent conquest, and that it might be a sea-port for Rome. He obtained also some advantages over the Sabines and Veientines ; and to render his intercourse with the right bank of the river both more easy and more secure, he formed a wooden bridge across the Tiber, and fortified the hill Janiculum. The oldest remaining monument of Rome, the prison, formed out of a stone quarry on the Capitoline hill, is also said to have been the work of Ancus. He died in peace, respected and beloved, and was known in tradition by the designation of “ the good Ancus.”</p><p>That part of Roman history at which we have now arrived, is at once characterized by great interest and by great obscurity. It has the appearance of a great poem, containing just enough of fact to give it credibility in the ears of willing listeners, and enough of fiction and embellishment to destroy all its pretensions to the severely simple character of history. In our opinion this is its real character ; and we are by no means disposed to discard more of it than seems of itself to assume no claim upon our belief. No reader can possibly mistake poetic ornament for fact ; but there is one aspect of the narrative in which the common reader may be mistaken. It is not enough that an event be strange, or even almost marvellous, in order to be discredited. Many things are abundantly strange in our eyes which nevertheless did actually occur. The wild, strange, and daring exploits recorded of the early founders of nations are liable to bc disbelieved by posterity, in the exercise of its cool philosophic criticism. But the founders of a nation are generally men of daring and enthusiastic character, whose actual deeds are constantly hovering on the brink of the incredible. Nations, like individuals, have a period of youth, in which their history is naturally full of deeds of lofty daring, strange adventure, and all but miraculous exploit. The most truthful narrative of a nation’s youth must contain accounts of those deeds of scarcely imaginable hardihood ; and such a narrative will seem utterly unworthy of belief to the cool philosopher of a calmer and more thoughtful age. Hitherto we have been attempting to obtain a glimpse ot the very infancy of Rome ; now we are to view the exploits of its fiery and impetuous youth. We are not lightly to credit every miraculous statement that claims our attention ; but neither are we to demand a succession of events regulated by a cool deliberate prudence, such as our own habits of thought and action could alone approve.</p><p>In the days of Ancus Marcius a noble and wealthy Tuscan sought a residence in Rome. He was the son of a citizen of Corinth of some distinction, who had left his native country to avoid the tyranny of an usurper. Having settled at Tarquinii, a city on the coast of Etruria, he married an Etruscan lady of the highest rank. His son, in virtue of his mother’s rank, belonged to the ruling caste of Etruria, the Lucumones ; but the pride of that caste would not permit them to suffer a person of mixed descent to participate in their hereditary honours. He married an Etruscan lady of the noblest birth, Tanaquil by name, who could not brook that her husband should be disparaged by her haughty kindred. They left Tarquinii, and journeyed to Rome, in the hope of being received by Ancus in a manner more suited to their dignity. They had reached the brow of the Janiculum, and were in sight of Rome, when an eagle hovering over them, stooped, snatched his cap, and after soaring aloft with it to a great height, again descended and placed it on his head. Tanaquil, versed in the lore of Tuscan augury, understood the omen, and embracing her husband, bade him proceed joyfully, for the loftiest fortunes awaited him. He was received as a Roman citizen, and assumed the name of Lucius Tarquinius. His courage, his wisdom, and his wealth, soon recommended him to the favourable notice of the king, and made him greatly esteemed also by the people generally. On the death of Ancus he was chosen king, and received from the assembly the customary sanction to his assumption of sovereignty.</p><p>Scarcely was Tarquin seated on the throne when the Latin states broke the treaty which they had made with Ancus, and began to make inroads upon the Roman territor)·. Tarquinius marched against them, defeated them in battle, and took and plundered Apiolae, where he obtained an immense booty. Prosecuting his victorious career, he made himself master of Cameria, Crustumerium, Medullia, Ameriola, Ficulnea, Corniculum, and Nomentum. The Æqui also felt the power of his arms, and were obliged to humble themselves before him. While he was engaged with the Latins, the Sabines availed themselves of his absence, mustered their forces, crossed the Anio, and ravaged the country up to the very walls of Rome. Tarquinius returning from his Latin wars, encountered the Sabines, and after a</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>