<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>sword, was most cruelly wasted. Under Fyzoola Khan, one of the eons of Aly Mohammed, the country was in a most flourishing condition ; and several of the Rohilla chiefs resided in each of the large towns, where they lived in a princely and hospitable manner, and gave every protection and encouragement to the farmers, so that the revenue amounted to a million sterling ; but under the waste and ruin of this cruel invasion the revenue decreased in the course of twenty years to L.400,000, and the country went gradually to ruin. The country was transferred to the British in 1801, and is now governed by a civil establishment of officers stationed at Bareilly.</p><p>ROLL, or Roller, is a piece of wood, iron, brass, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c. of a</hi>  cylindrical form, used in the construction of several machines, and in several works and manufactures.</p><p>ROLLAND, an island in the Southern Ocean, discovered by Kerguelen in 1773, about nine miles in circumference. Long. 68. 43. E. Lat. 48. 37. N.</p><p>ROLLI, Paul, an Italian poet, was born at Rome in 1687. He was the son of an architect, and a pupil of the celebrated Gravina, who inspired him with a taste for learning and poetry. An intelligent and learned English peer, having brought him to London, introduced him to the royal family as a master of the Tuscan language. Rolli remained in England till the death of Queen Caroline his protectress, and the patroness of literature in general. He returned to Italy in 1747, where he died in 1767, in the eightieth year of his age, leaving behind him a very curious collection in natural history, with a valuable and well-chosen library. His principal works first appeared in London in 1735 in 8vo. They consist of odes in blank verse, elegies, songs, and other poems, after the manner of Catullus. A collection of his epigrams was printed at Florence in 1776, in 8vo, to which is prefixed an account of his life by Fondini. What Martial said of his own collection may be said of this, “ that there are few good, but many indifferent or bad pieces in it.” Rolli, however, bore the character of one of the best Italian poets of his age. During his stay in London he procured editions of several authors of his own country. The principal of these were the Satires of Ariosto, the burlesque works of Berni, Varchi, &amp;c. two vols, in 8vo ; the Decameron of Boccace, 1727, in 4to and folio, in which he has faithfully copied the celebrated and valuable edition published by the Juntas in 1527 ; and, lastly, of the elegant Lucretia of Marchetti, which was printed at London in 1717, in 8vo, through the influence and attention of Rolli. This edition is beautiful ; but the work is thought to be of a pernicious tendency. He likewise translated into Italian verse the Paradise Lost of Milton, printed at London in folio in 1735 ; and the Odes of Anacreon, London, 1739, in 8 vo.</p><p>ROLLIN, Charles, a celebrated French writer, was the son of a cutler at Paris, and was born there on the 30th of January 1661. He studied at the College du Plessis, in which he obtained an exhibition through the interest of a Benedictine monk whom he had served at table, and who discovered in him some marks of genius. Here he acquired the regard of M Gobinet, principal of the college, who had a particular esteem for him. After having studied humanity and philosophy, he applied to divinity three years at the Sorbonne ; but he did not prosecute this study, and was satisfied with obtaining the tonsure. He afterwards became professor of rhetoric in his own college; and in 1688 succeeded Horsan, his master, as professor of eloquence in the Royal College. No man ever exercised the functions of it with greater eclat ; he often made Latin orations to celebrate the memorable events of the times, and frequently accompanied them with poems, which were generally read and esteemed. In 1694 he was chosen rector of the university, and he continued in that office two years, which was then a mark of distinction. By virtue of lιis office, he spoke the annual panegyric upon Louis XIV. He made many very useful regulations in the university ; and particularly revived the study of the Greek language, which was then much neglected. He substituted academical exercises in the place of tragedies ; and introduced the practice which had been formerly observed, of causing the students to get by heart passages of Scripture. He wεfe a man of indefatigable application, and trained innumerable persons, who did honour to the church, the state, and the army. The first president Portail was pleased one day to reproach Rollin in a jocular strain, as if he exceeded even himself in doing business ; to whom Rollin replied, with that plainness and sincerity which was natural to him, “ It becomes you well, sir, to reproach me with this ; it is this habit of labour in me which has distinguished you in the place of advocate-general, which has raised you to that of first president ; you owe the greatness of your fortune to me.”</p><p>Upon tile expiration of the rectorship, Cardinal Noailles engaged him to superintend tile studies of his nephews, who were in the College of Laon ; and in this office he was agreeably employed, when, in 1699, he was with great reluctance made coadjutor to the principal of the College of Beauvais. This college was then a kind of desert, inhabited by very few students, and without any regular discipline ; but Rol-lin’s great industry soon repeopled it, and raised it to that credit which it long retained. In this situation he continued till 1712 ; when the war between the Jesuits and the Jansenists drawing towards a crisis, he fell a sacrifice to the prevalence of the former. Father le Tellier, the king’s confessor, a furious agent of the Jesuits, infused into his master prejudices against Rollin, whose connection witll Cardinal de Noailles would alone have sufficed to make him a Jansenist ; and on this account he lost his share in the principality of Beauvais. No man, however, could thus have suffered a smaller loss than Rollin, who had every thing left that was necessary to make him happy ; retirement, books, and enough for his support. He now began to be employed upon Quinctilian ; an author whom he justly valued, and could not without uneasiness see neglected. He retrenched in him w hatever he thought rather curious than useful for the instruction of youth ; he placed summaries or contents at the head of each chapter, and he accompanied the text with short and select notes. His edition appeared in 1715, in two vols. 12mo, with an elegant preface explaining his method and view's.</p><p>In 1710, the university of Paris, willing to have a head suitable to the importance of their interests in a very critical conjuncture of affairs, chose Rollin again rector; but he was displaced in about two months by a lettre de cachet. The university had presented to the parliament a petition, in which it protested against taking any part in the adjustment of the late disputes ; and their being congratulated in a public oration by Rollin on this step, occasioned the letter, which ordered them to choose a rector of more moderation. Whatever the university might suffer by the removal of Rollin, the public was probably a gainer ; for he now applied himself to the composition of his Treatise on the Manner of Studying and Teaching the Belles Lettres, which was published in octavo, two volumes in 1726, and two more in 1728.</p><p>This work, though greatly deficient in order, and displaying neither depth nor philosophy, has been exceedingly successful ; and its success encouraged its author to undertake another work of equal use and entertainment ; his “ Ancient History of the Egyptians, Carthaginians, Assyrians, Babylonians, Medes and Persians, Macedonians, and Greeks,” which he finished in thirteen volumes 8vo, and published between 1730 and 1738. Voltaire, after having observed that Rollin was “ the first member of the university of Paris who wrote French with dignity and correctness,” says of this work, that “ though the last volumes,</p></body></text></TEI>