<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>His chariot, and whose company was courted for his wit and talent, was, after all, by profession, the same with the unfortunate stroller, whom tile British laws condemn as a vagabond, and to whose dead body other countries refuse even the last rites of Christianity. In the same manner it is easy to suppose that, when in compliance with the taste of their age, monarchs entertained their domestic minstrels,@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>those persons might be admitted to the most flattering intimacy with their royal masters ; sleep within the royal chamber,@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> amass considerable fortunes, found hospitals,@@<hi rend="sup">3 </hi>and receive rewards singularly over-proportioned to the perquisites of the graver professions ;@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> and even practise in company with their royal masters the pleasing arts of poetry and music, which all are so desirous of attaining ;@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> whilst, at the same time, those who ranked lower in the same profession were struggling with difficulty to gain a precarious subsistence, and incurring all the disgrace usually attached to a vagabond life and a dubious character. In the fine arts, particularly, excellence is demanded, and mere mediocrity is held contemptible; and, while the favour with which the former is loaded, sometimes seems disproportion-ed to the utility of the art itself, nothing can exceed the scorn poured out on those who expose themselves by undertaking arts which they are unable to practise with success. Self-conceit, however, love of an idle life, and a variety of combined motives, never fail to recruit the lower orders of such idle professions with individuals by whose performances, and often by their private characters, the art which they have rashly adopted can only be discredited without any corresponding advantage to themselves. It is not, therefore, surprising that, while such distinguished examples of the contrary appeared amongst individuals, the whole body of minstrels, with the romances which they composed and sung, should be reprobated by graver historians in such severe terms as often occur in the monkish chronicles of the day.</p><p>Respecting the style of their composition, Du Cange informs us, that the minstrels sometimes devoted their strains to flatter the great, and sing the praises of those princes by whom they were protected ; while he owns, at the same time, that they often recommended to their hearers the path of virtue and nobleness, and pointed out the pursuits by which the heroes of romance had rendered themselves renowned in song.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Hc quotes from the romance of<hi rend="italic">Bertrand Guesclin,</hi>  the injunction on those who would rise to fame in arms to copy the valiant acts of the Paladins of Charles, and the Knights of the Round Table, narrated in romances ; and it cannot be denied, that those high tales, in which the virtues of generosity, bravery, devotion to his mistress, and zeal for the Catholic religion, were carried to the greatest height of romantic perfection in the character of the hero, united with the scenes passing around them, were of the highest importance in affecting the character of the age. The fabulous knights of romance were so completely identified with those of real history, that graver historians quote the actions of the former in illustration of, and as a corollary to the real events which they narrate.@@<hi rend="sup">7 </hi>The virtues recommended in romance were, however, only of that overstrained and extravagant cast which consisted with the spirit of chivalry. Great bodily strength, and perfection in all martial exercises, was the universal accomplishment inalienable from the character of the hero, and which each romancer had it in his power to confer. It was also easily in the composer's power to devise dangers, and to free his hero from them by the exertion of valour equally extravagant. But it was more difficult to ftame a story which should illustrate tile manners as well as the feats of chivalry ; or to devise the means of evincing that devotion to duty, and that disinterested desire to sacrifice all to faith and honour ;—that noble spirit of achievement which laboured for others more than itself—which form, perhaps, the fairest side of the system under which the noble youths of the middle ages were trained up. The sentiments of chivalry, as we have explained in our article on that subject, were founded on the most pure and honourable principles, but unfortunately carried into hyperbole and extravagance ; until the religion of its professors approached to fanaticism, their valour to frensy, their ideas of honour to absurdity, their spirit of enterprise to extravagance, and their respect for the female sex to a sort of idolatry. All those extravagant feelings, which really existed in the society of the middle ages, were magnified and exaggerated by the writers and reciters of romance ; and these given as resemblances of actual manners, became, in their turn, the glass by which the youth of the age dressed themselves ; while the spirit of chivalry and of romance thus gradually threw light upon and enhanced each other.</p><p>The romances, therefore, exhibited the same system of manners which existed in the nobles of the age. The character of a true son of chivalry was raised to such a pitch</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Berdic<hi rend="italic">lΒegis Joculator),</hi>  the jongleur or minstrel of William the Conqueror, had, as appears from the Domesday record, three vills and five caracates of land in Gloucestershire without rent. Henry I. had a minstrel called Galfrid, who received an annuity from the abbey of Hyde.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> A minstrel of Edward I., during that prince’s expedition to the Holy Land, slept within his tent, and came to his assistance when an attempt was made to assassinate him.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>    The Priory and Hospital of Saint Bartholomew, in London, was founded in the reign of Henry L by Royer or Raher, a minstrel of that prince.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> In 1441, the monks of Maxlock, near Coventry, paid a donation of four shillings to the minstrels of Lord Clinton for songs, harping, and other exhibitions, while, to a doctor who preached before the community in the same year, they assigned only sixpence.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> The noted anecdote of Blondel and bis royal master, Richard Cœur de Lion, will occur to every reader.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">6</hi>     Ministelh dicti præsertim scurrae, mimi, joculatores, quos etiamnum vulgo</hi><hi rend="italic">Menestreux</hi>  vel <hi rend="italic">Menestriers,</hi>  appellamus.-Porro ejus</p><p>modi scurrarum erat Principes, non suis duntaxat ludicris oblectare, sed et eorum aures variis avorum, adeoque ipsorum Principum laudibus, non sine assentatione, cum cantilenis et musicis instrumentis, demulcere.-Interdum etiam virorum insignium et heroum gesta, aut</p><p>explicata et jucunda narratione commemorabant, aut suavi vocis inflectione, fidibusque decantabant, quo sic dominorum, caeterorumque qui his intererant ludicris, nobilium animos ad virtutem capessendam et summorum virorum imitationem accenderent : quod fuit olim apud Gallos Bardorum ministerium, ut auctor est Tacitus. Neque enim alios à <hi rend="italic">Minislcllis,</hi>  veterum Gallorum <hi rend="italic">Bardos</hi>  fuisse pluribus probat Henricus Valesius ad 15. Ammiani—<hi rend="italic">Chroniam</hi>  Bertrandi Guesclini:</p><p>Qui veut avoir renom des bons et des vaillans,</p><p>II doit aler souvent à la pluie et au champ,</p><p>Et estre en la bataille, ainsy que fu Rollans,</p><p>Les quatre fils Haimon et Charlon li plus grans,</p><p>Li Dus Lions dc Bourges, et Guion de Connans,</p><p>Perceval li Galois, Lancelot et Tristans,</p><p>Alexandres, Artus, Godefroy li sachans,</p><p>De quoy cils menestriers font les nobles Romans.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> Barbour, the Scottish historian, censures a Highland chief, when, in commending the prowess of Bruce in battle, he likened him to the Celtic hero, Fin Mac Coul, and says, he might in more mannerly fashion bave compared him to Gaudifer, a champion celebrated in the romance of Alexander.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>