<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>than <hi rend="italic">Vs.</hi>  3. It must deviate from the proportion of Vs so much the more as <hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  is smaller. 4. It must not vanish when the velocity is infinite. 5. It must agree with a range of experiments with every variety of channel and of slope.</p><p>We shall understand the nature of this quantity X better by representing by lines the quantities concerned in forming it·</p><p>If the velocities were exactly as the square roots of the slopes, the equilateral hyperbola NKS (fig. 11) between</p><p>its asymptotes MA, AB, would represent the equation A    —</p><p>V = ±. The values of Vi would be represented by the</p><p>abscissæ, and the velocities by the ordinates, and V s = A would be the power of the hyperbola. But since these ve-</p><p>A    —</p><p>locities are not sensibly equal to except when Vi is very</p><p>great, and deviate the more from this quantity as Vs is smaller, we may represent the velocities by the ordinates of another curve PGT, which approaches very near to the hyperbola, at a great distance from A along AB ; but separates from it when the abscissæ are smaller: so that if AQ represents that value of Vs (which we have seen may become less than unity) which corresponds to an infinite velocity, the line QO may be the asymptote of the new curve. Its ordinates are equal to while those of the</p><p><hi rend="italic">A</hi></p><p>hyperbola are equal to    Therefore the ratio of these</p><p>∖∕ 5</p><p>ordinates, or -=, should be such that it shall be so much</p><p>Λ.</p><p>nearer to unity as <hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  is greater, and shall surpass it so much the more as Vi is smaller.</p><p>To express X, therefore, as some function of V i so as to answer these conditions, we see in general that X must be less than <hi rend="italic">Vs.</hi>  And it must not be equal to any power of</p><p><hi rend="italic">√ S</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  whose index is less than unity, because then -~- would</p><p>differ so much the more from unity as√sis greater. Nor must it be any multiple of Vi, such as <hi rend="italic">q Vs,</hi>  for the same reason. If we make X = Vi — K, K being a constant quantity, we may answer the first condition pretty well. But K must be very small, that X may not become equal to nothing, except in some exceedingly small value of Vi. Now the experiments will not admit of this, because the</p><p><hi rend="italic">g</hi></p><p>ratio --— does not increase sufficiently to correspond</p><p>with the velocities which we observe in certain slopes, unless we make K greater than unity, which again is inconsistent with other experiments. We learn from such canvassing that it will not do to make K a constant quantity. If we should make it any fractionary power of Vi, it would make X = 0, that is, nothing, when <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is =: 1, which is also</p><p>contrary to experience. It would seem, therefore, that nothing will answer for K but some power of Vs which has a variable index. The logarithm of Vs has this property. We may therefore try to make X = Vs — log. V s. Ac-cordingly, if we try the equation V =    _,</p><p><hi rend="italic">we</hi>  shall find a very great agreement with the experiments till the declivity becomes considerable, or about <hi rend="sub">5</hi><hi rend="sup">1</hi><hi rend="sub">l</hi>τ, which is much greater than any river. But it will not agree with the velocities observed in some mill-courses, and in pipes of a still greater declivity, and gives a velocity that is too small ; and in vertical pipes the velocity is not above one half of the true one. We shall get rid of most of these incongruities if we make K consist of the hyperbolic logarithm of Vs augmented by a small quantity ; and by trying various values for this constant quantity, and comparing the results with experiment, we may hit on one sufficiently exact for all practical purposes.</p><p>Du Buat, after repeated trials, found that he would have a very great conformity with experiment by making K = log. V s + 1∙6, and that the velocities exhibited in his experiments would be very well represented by the for-</p><p><hi rend="sub">raula</hi> v = ¾⅛,</p><p>Vs — L Vs + 1∙6</p><p>There is a circumstance which our author seems to have overlooked on this occasion, and which is undoubtedly of great effect in these motions, viz. the mutual adhesion of the particles of water. This causes the water which is descending (in a vertical pipe, for example) to drag more water after it, and thus greatly increases its velocity. We have seen an experiment in which the water issued from the bottom of a reservoir through a long vertical pipe having a very gentle taper. It was fifteen feet long, one inch diameter at the upper end, and two inches at the lower. The depth of the water in the reservoir was exactly one foot ; in a minute there were discharged <hi rend="italic">2f<hi rend="sub">5</hi></hi>  cubic feet of water. It must therefore have issued through the hole in the bottom of the reservoir with the velocity of 8∙85 feet per second. And yet we know that this head of water could not make it pass through the hole with a velocity greater than 6∙56 feet per second. This increase must therefore have arisen from the cause we have mentioned, and is a proof of the great intensity of this force. We doubt not but that the discharge might have been much more increased by proper contrivances ; and we know many instances in water-pipes where this effect is produced in a very great degree·</p><p>The following case is very distinct. Water is brought into the town of Dunbar, in the county of Haddington, from a spring at the distance of about 3200 yards. It is conveyed along the first 1100 yards in a pipe of two inches diameter, and the declivity is 12 feet 9 inches ; from thence the water flows in a pipe of 1½ diameter, with a declivity of 44 feet three inches, making in all 57 feet. When the work was carried as far as the two-inch pipe reached, the discharge was found to be 27 Scotch pints, of 103½ cubic inches each, in a minute. When it was brought into the town, the discharge was 28. Here it is plain that the descent along the second stretch of the pipe could derive no impulsion from the first- This was only able to supply 27 pints, and to <hi rend="italic">deliver</hi>  it into a pipe of equal bore. It was not equivalent to the forcing it into a smaller pipe, and almost doubling its velocity. It must therefore have been <hi rend="italic">dragged</hi>  into this smaller pipe by the weight of what was descending along it, and this water was exerting a force equivalent to a head of 16 inches, increasing the velocity from 14 to about 28.</p><p>It must be observed, that if this formula be just, there can be no declivity so small that a current of water will not</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>