<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and Syria reduced to a state of dependence on her imperious will, with the Grecian states in the condition of ready instruments in her hands of future aggrandisement, whenever she might be disposed to take or make an opportunity.</p><p>It is even painful to state, that after the conclusion of the Antiochian war, the two Scipios were accused of having received bribes from that monarch, and ofhaving embezzled the public money. Africanus went into voluntary exile at Liternum, where he died the same year that Hannibal fell a victim to the cruel and mean revenge of Rome. Asiaticus refused to pay the fine exacted, and all his property was confiscated.</p><p>A new Macedonian war soon arose, caused by the imperious authority assumed and exercised by the Roman ambassadors over the conduct of the king. Philip had endured their control with impatience ; but his son Perseus was less able to suppress his dissatisfaction, and hostilities were soon commenced. The war for a time was favourable to tlle Macedonians, who gained one considerable victory, and were successful in several conflicts of smaller importance. At length the command was given to Paulus Æmilius, an old and skilful general, under whose care the aspect of affairs changed. A decisive battle was fought near the city Pydna, remarkable as the conclusion both of the Macedonian kingdom and the Macedonian phalanx. In the first shock of battle the phalanx was irresistible, and bore down all opposition ; but the skilful Roman general, by causing his men to retire fighting, and lead the phalanx upon broken and uneven ground, obliged it to open its dense array of serried pikes, when the legionary soldiers immediately penetrating these openings like a wedge, rent asunder the unwieldy mass, and scattered it into hopeless and irretrievable confusion and rout, like the bursting of a cloud of vapour by a whirlwind. Perseus was captured soon after the battle, and reserved to grace the victor’s triumph. Macedonia, Epirus, and Illyricum, were reduced to the condition of provinces, and the foundation of a foreign territorial empire laid, was instead of one merely of influence and military power.</p><p>The utter destruction of Carthage was next resolved upon, partly through the vindictive remembrance ofthe terror which Rome had formerly felt from Carthaginian prowess, partly from the instigation of the stern, haughty, and implacable Cato the censor. A pretext fbr a war was not difficult to find, though the Carthaginians endeavoured to avert their fate by even the most abject submission. But when the Romans, after inducing them to yield up their weapons, informed them that they must abandon their city, witness its demolition, and remove to a new position remote from the sea, despair itself roused them to make the fiercest resistance. They sprung at once into an attitude of the most determined defiance, forged new weapons, framed new military engines, the women cutting off their hair to form ropes to work their machinery ; and clad in glittering panoply, they manned their walls, and met the unappeasable hatred of Rome with hatred not less keen and mortal. The Roman armies sustained several reverses ; but under the command of Scipio Æmilianus, son of Paulus Æmilius, and adopted son of Scipio Africanus, victory again began to crown their efforts. After a fierce and protracted struggle, the Romans forced their way into the city on the side next the port, and obtained possession of the city wall. But the conflict was not over though the city wall was seized. The Carthaginians fought from street to street, from house to house ; and the Romans gained the city but by yards and inches, every house being contested from the ground floor to the roof, like a separate fortress. At length all was carried but the citadel and the temple of Æsculapius. These the Romans were prepared to storm, when the citadel surrendered, Asdrubal, who had the command, yielding to Scipio, on condition that his life should be spared. Those who had fled to the temnle, some of whom were deserters from the</p><p>Roman army, prepared to destroy it and themselves by fire, rather than fall into the hands of the Romans. Among these was the wife of Asdrubal, who had been placed in the temple before her husband yielded to Scipio. Seeing Asdrubal along with the Roman general, and detesting his cowardice, she arrayed herself in her richest attire, took her two children with her, and displaying herself on the top of the temple, upbraided her husband, stabbed her two children before his face, and threw them into the flames, which were now bursting furiously from the interior. She then sprung after them into the heart of the blazing ruin. Thus perished Carthage, leaving Rome to pursue unrivalled her guilty and self-destroying career.</p><p>While the third Punic war was still raging, hostilities again broke out in Macedonia, excited by an impostor named Andriscus, who, pretending to be the son of Philip, instigated the disaffected Macedonians to throw off the Roman yoke, and forming an alliance with the Thracians, strove to accomplish his purpose by force of arms. Metellus, after a short struggle, overpowered the insurgent Macedonians, and then attempted to procure the dissolution of the Achæan league. This led to the Achæan war, which terminated in the complete subjugation of Greece, and its reduction to the form of a Roman province. Mummius tlle consul, who conducted this war, sacked and burned Corinth ; and after having pillaged the city of its most valuable effects, its rich paintings and beautiful sculptures, demolished its walls, temples, and public buildings, and reduced it to a heap of blackened ruins. The plundered ornaments of Corinth were sent by the consul to Rome ; and it has been recorded, proving at once his care and his ignorance, that he stipulated with the masters of the vessels employed in transporting these matchless treasures of art, that “ if they suffered any of them to be lost or injured, they should furnish others in their stead.”</p><p>Another enemy of still more stubborn mould continued to engage the attention of Rome, and to put to the severest test the courage of her armies and the skill of her generals. The wars and conquests of the Carthaginians in Spain had directed the attention of the Romans to that country ; and a war for the awowed purpose of its subjugation was begun soon after the expulsion of the Carthaginians. Partly in consequence ofthe defensible nature of the country, abounding in mountain ridges and deep and rapid streams, and partly from the brave and determined character of the inhabitants, the war was protracted, obstinate, and bloody. Repeatedly did the arms of Rome sustain signal reverses; and still with invincible energy of will was the contest maintained. At length the Lusitanians obtained a leader undeι whom they seemed likely to secure their possession of liberty and independence. This was Viriatus, a shepherd, a hunter, a robber, and finally a military hero, almost unrivalled in fertility of resources under defeat, skill in the conduct of his forces, and courage in the hour of battle. Like the guerilla leaders of modern times, he knew how to avail himself of the wild chivalry of his countrymen, and the almost impenetrable fastnesses of his country ; but, superior to them, he was equally able to guide a troop and to marshall an army. Six years did he maintain the contest ; and at length the consul Cæpio, unable to subdue him in the field, procured his assassination. The Lusitanians, deprived of tbeir brave leader, were soon afterwards completely subdued.</p><p>Undismayed by the overthrow of their countrymen, tlle Numantines still maintained the unequal conflict against the collected might of Rome. Pompey was baffled; his successor Mancinus shared a similar disgrace ; and at length the Romans raised Scipio Æmilianus, the conqueror of Carthage, to the consulship, and assigned him Spain as his province, and even prolonged his command, after thc expiration of his year as proconsul. At the head of a large army he</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>