<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>able. It is true Niebuhr@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> hazards another very ingenious conjecture. He thinks that Tarquinius may have been him-'self one oι the tribe of the Luceres, that Priscus may have been a name belonging to him, as one of a Priscan gens, or house, ana that the legend of his Etruscan conquests and acknowledged sovereignity may have some connexion with the much more ancient tradition of the fabulous Tuscan hero, Tarchon, to which the name Tarquinius itself may allude. It is sufficiently evident, that there did exist at some remote period, an intimate intercourse between Rome and the Etrusci ; and there appears to have been some connexion between this Etruscan influence and the tribe ofthe Luceres. What the exact nature and extent of this Etruscan intercourse and influence were, it seems a hopeless task to inquire, and it would be fruitless to indulge in framing conjectures.</p><p>It is stated, that Tarquinius wished to add to the centuries of the Equites, established by Romulus, three new centuries, and to call them by his own name, and the names of his friends. In this intention he was opposed by the augur Attus Navius, who affirmed that what had been instituted with augury, could not be changed without it, and that the omens forbade any change. The king, in order to cast discredit on the art ofthe augur, asked him to divine whether what he was then thinking of could be done. The augur observed the omens, and answered that it could. “ I was thinking,” said the king, “ whether you could cut this whetstone in two with a knife.” Navius instantly took the whetstone, and cut it sheer asunder, to the amazement of the king. This proof of the augur’s skill caused Tarquinius to desist from his intention to its full extent ; and he .merely added to each of the former centuries a second or latter century under the same name. In this legend may be contained an account of the opposition which Tarquinius experienced from the patrician body, when he purposed to raise a number of the most distinguished of the free citizens to the equestrian rank,—an opposition to which he was so far obliged to yield.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>It has been already stated, that the constitution of Rome@@<hi rend="sup">3 </hi>was founded on the patriarchal principle, as to its essential characteristic, while the numerical divisions of the government by tens were arbitrary, so far as can be traced. Every head of a house was an integral member of the state, as a free citizen ; but there is no very manifest reason why houses should have been aggregated into<hi rend="italic">tens,</hi>  or curiæ, these into other <hi rend="italic">tens</hi>  forming the senate, or patres, of one hundred. But this division or rather aggregation having been adopted, it influenced all the arrangements of the body politic, both in peace and war. While there was but one people, the followers of Romulus, there was but one tribe, the Ramnenses, or, as some term it, the Ramnes, and the senate amounted to one hundred. Upon the junction ofthe Sabines, there were two tribes, the Titienses or Tities being added, and consequently the senate then numbered two hundred. The elevation of the third tribe, the Luceres, completed the number of curiæ, decuriæ, tribes, and senators, till thirty and three hundred became the ruling numbers in this division.</p><p>It is worth remarking, that, according to the statement of ancient authors, when Romulus formed the Pomœrium, including all that composed ancient Rome, his city merely contained one thousand wretched huts, clustered together on the Palatine hill. Now, if it could be shewn that the union of ten families formed a house, ten houses a curia, and ten curiæ the entire tribe, we should have the exact number of the first huts erected on the Palatine, and of the primitive mansions of the Roman fathers.</p><p>The army followed in its construction the numerical ar</p><lb/><p>rangement of the people. The earliest Roman legion could contain no more than the male inhabitants of Rome, which would be at that time only a thousand capable of bearing arms. As the senate was formed from the hundred chief men of the curiæ, so there were an hundred of the braves selected from the curiæ to fight on horseback. Thus th∣ equites, or knights, were at first equal in number with tin senate, and equal in rank, as members of the curiæ, thougl not senators, because not the heads of the curiæ. Whel the senate was increased to three hundred, by the additior of the other two tribes, there were also three centuries oι hundreds of knights, retaining the proportion. The legion would then consist of 3000 infantry, and 300 cavalry ; and though in later periods the numbers of the infantry were increased, 300 continued to be the legitimate number of cavalry in a legion. Although the name remained, the numbers fluctuated according to the dictates of policy or necessity, so that when we read of a century, we are not to assume that an hundred is meant, and neither more nor less.</p><p>Adopting recognised terms and divisions, Servius, in his endeavours to improve the constitution of Rome, divided the large body of unprivileged yet free citizens, the plebs, or true commons, into thirty tribes, according to the thirty curiæ of the senatorial patricians. Of these thirty tribes four were contained in the city itself, and the remaining twenty-six in the lands that had been added to the dominions of Rome by conquest. Each tribe was under the dominion of a magistrate of their own body, called a Tribunus. There were also judges appointed, three for each tribe, to determine private causes among the plebeian citizens. For the appointment of these official persons, and other matters connected with their own interests, the plebeians were empowered to hold their own meetings, called the comitia tributa. These were held on the <hi rend="italic">nundinœ,</hi>  or market days, when the country people came to Rome, and in the forum or market-place adjacent to the comitium, or meeting place of the patricians, but quite distinct from it. These comitia tributa were entirely plebeian, and at first referred only to the decision of disputes respecting private rights among the plebeians themselves. They were not convoked by the patricians, nor held under patrician auspices. They had nothing to do with national affairs as such, but were confined entirely to the private business of tile plebeian order. Neither had the patricians at first any thing to do with this plebeian assembly : they formed no part of it, and had no authority over it. Yet, though thus distinct from the state in its original formation, it gave an organized form to the plebeian body, which soon proved its importance, as the very thews and sinews of the body politic, and therefore essential to its growth and strength.</p><p>The institution of the comitia tributa, though at first of an entirely private character with reference to the state, tended to the formation of a new assembly, in which all the orders of the people were included, and arranged for the discussion of public affairs. It was not possible that the plebeian body could be so far organized as to have its own, magistracy, elected by itself in an assembly of its own, without producing an early necessity for its admission into the state ; for organization both gives power, and the consciousness of power, in the body politic. The most natural occasion and mode ofits admission, had amilitary origin and character, like mostof the other Roman institutions. Though the patricians and plebeians remained completely distinct in their civic character, and in the time of peace, yet in the time of war they acted together in one great body, tl ιe army. The arrangements of the army were therefore those which led to their junction in another aspect, and were in</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Niebuhr, vol. i. pp. 376, 377.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> See Niebuhr, vol. i. pp. 360, 361.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  For a full view of the Servian constitution of Rome, see Niebuhr, vol. i. pp. 405-487. Arnold, vol. 1. pp. 64-82.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>