<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>failed to pay, and could neither himself give security, nor obtain any person to give it for him, he might be thrown into a dungeon, loaded with chains, and half starved for sixty days. If during that time he refused to come to any terms with his creditor, he might be again brought to the market place, and the amount of his debt stated, to see whether any person would yet become security for him. On the third day, if no friend appeared, he might be put to death, or sold for a slave beyond the Tiber; nay, if there were more creditors than one, they might actually hew his body in pieces, and divide it among them; and whether a creditor cut off a greater or smaller piece than in due proportion to the debt, he incurred no penalty.</p><p>In this manner vast numbers of the commonalty were reduced to the utmost wretchedness ; and instead of the influence which they had been promised by the Servian constitution, they were in a worse condition than the veriest slaves. The old Roman populus, the patricians and their clients, had engrossed all the wealth and power of the community, and formed the government into an exclusive aristocracy. Great numbers of the plebeians were <hi rend="italic">next,</hi>  though not yet <hi rend="italic">addicti;</hi>  and in this condition felt themselves trembling on the brink of utter ruin. Driven to despair by their distress, the commonsresolved that they would no longer endure their misery and degradation. Such of them as were in the city seized upon and began to fortify the Aventine hill, their own quarter ; those who were at the time in the field, deserted their generals, marched to a hill on the north bank of the Anio, beyond the limits of the Ager Romanus, and within that of the Crustuminian tribe. There they established themselves, and proposed to found a new city. The patricians, perceiving the ruin that must fall upon Rome if thus deserted by the great body of the commons, entered into négociations with them for a return. Their demands were not extravagant. They required a general cancelling of the obligations of insolvent debtors, <hi rend="italic">(nexi),</hi>  and the release of those who in default of payment had been assigned to the power of their creditors, <hi rend="italic">(addicti).</hi>  They further stipulated, that two of their own body should be acknowledged as their public protectors, and that the persons of these two should be held sacred and inviolable. To these terms the patricians agreed ; a solemn treaty was concluded ; the two protectors of the commons were chosen, and called Tribunes, and the commons returned to Rome. The spot where this treaty had been concluded was enclosed, and consecrated to Jupiter, and received the name of the Sacred Hill.</p><p>This event was almost of equal importance with the expulsion of the kings and the abolition of the monarchical power. It laid the foundation of the liberties which the body of Roman citizens subsequently enjoyed ; and by giving them legal rights and legal protectors, converted into legal contests what might otherwise have rent the state asunder. But at the same time it gave to the tribunate, in the inviolability of the persons of those who held it, the means of acquiring an unlimited power in the state, such as might and did lead to ultimate despotism.</p><p>The termination in an amicable manner of these feuds was greatly promoted by the fact, that the state was then at war with tbe Æqui and Volsci, two nations of Oscan race, whose lands lay south from Rome. It was no time for protracted civil broils when the country was ravaged, and the city itself threatened by such dangerous neighbours. To the same necessity may be traced the alliance with the Latin states, formed in the consulship of Spurius Cassius, on terms of perfect equality ; and seven years afterwards by the same Spurius Cassius, with the Hernicians, on similar terms. These leagues were of the utmost importance to Rome, both as restoring to her the power which she had lost after the expulsion of the kings, and that too on a more equitable and therefore more permanent basis, and in commencing that thoroughly incorporating and blending system which afterwards converted all the inhabitants of Italy into Roman citizens, and thus consolidating her growth, confirmed her power.</p><p>A measure of equal justice, and not less importance, was also attempted by Spurius Cassius, the passing of which would have established the frame of Roman liberties on a secure foundation. This was an Agrarian law. The nature of the Agrarian laws, proposed from time to time at Rome, and always the cause of bitter contests between the patricians and plebeians, was never accurately known till it was explained by Niebuhr.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> From him we learn, that when a new territory was gained in war, by the third being taken from the conquered people, part of it was left unenclosed for pasture, and the cultivated parts were either divided among the new citizens who had not previously received any allotment, or left to be occupied by certain individuals, who were required to pay a tithe of tlle produce to the state. The persons thus allowed to occupy these new acquisitions were generally members of powerful patrician families ; and, although tenants at will of the state, they were actual proprietors with respect to the other citizens. When a number of new citizens had been added to the state, it was consistent with the whole polity of Rome to allot them lands : but in order to do so it would be necessary for the state to resume its property from its tenants at will, and divide it among the new citizens ; for it was equally a matter of strict justice and sound policy to unite by permanent ties to the state those menby whose blood its victories were gained, and could alone be preserved. To this the occupiers would by no means consent; and thus the public land was wholly unprofitable to the commons, though they had been largely instrumental in conquering it for Rome.</p><p>The Agrarian law proposed by Spurius Cassius had for its object the division of a certain proportion of the public land ; while from the occupiers of the remainder he intended to demand the regular payment of the tithe, which had been greatly neglected. His colleague, Proculus Virginius, headed the more aristocratical party of the patrician body in opposing the passing of this law, kept it in abeyance, if not uncarried, till the termination of his consulship, and then accused him before the comitia curiata of having treasonably conspired to make himself king, and for that purpose seeking to ingratiate himself with the commons. He was sentenced to die as a traitor, and was scourged and beheaded, and his house razed to the ground. Such was the fate of the first proposer of an Agrarian law ; a topic equally detested by the Roman aristocracy, misinterpreted by the historians, and misunderstood by the moderns, yet a measure of strict justice and sound policy, and sufficiently intelligible when fairly stated.</p><p>The contests between the patricians and the plebeians still continued; but the plebeians had now obtained the means of insuring ultimate success, though for a time defeated and overborne. They refused to serve as soldiers in the wars with which the state was still harassed, and their tribunes protected them in this refusal, till the consuls held their enrolment without the city, where their power was unlimited. At length the patricians consented that one of the consuls should be chosen by the plebeians in their centuries, the other by themselves, as usual, in their curiæ. This was a considerable advantage obtained by the plebeians; and they requited it by gaining a victory over the enemy.</p><p>For seven successive consulships the family of the Fabii had been elected, and had headed the patrician party. At length they resolved to conciliate the commons, and thereby incurred the hatred of their own order. Feeling them-</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Niebuhr, vol. ii. pp. 129,<hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq.</hi>  Arnold, vol. i. pp∙ 156, <hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>