<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>depth <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  Having therefore augmented the unknown • dimension, which is here the height, make use of this to form a new mean depth, and then the new equation √5 <hi rend="sup">=</hi>-Sh^7—— + 0∙ I will give us another value of ∕ι,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">w h</hi> (√b-°∙<hi rend="sup">3</hi>)</hi></p><p>which will rarely exceed the truth by -⅛. This serves (by the same process) for finding another, which will commonly be sufficiently exact. We shall illustrate this by an example.</p><p>Let there be a river whose channel is a rectangle 150 feet wide and six feet deep, and which discharges 1500 cubic feet of water per second, having a velocity of twenty inches, and slope of y<hi rend="sub">3</hi>⅙<hi rend="sub">sπ</hi>, or about ∙⅛ of an inch in 100 fathoms. How much will it rise if it receives an addition which triples its discharge ? and what will be its velocity ?</p><p>If the velocity remained the same, its depth would be tripled ; but we know by the general formula that its velocity will be greatly increased, and therefore its depth will not be tripled. Suppose it to be doubled, and to become twelve feet. This will give <hi rend="italic">d —</hi>  10∙34483, or 124∙138 inches ; then the equation <hi rend="italic">Vd—</hi>0∙l =-==-—, or</p><p>≈^(i⅛-o∙<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)</p><p>A <hi rend="sub">=</hi>--==-r« and in which we have</p><p>w(√d-0-1) (12-0-3)</p><p>√B = 107∙8, D = 4500 × 1728 = 7776000 cubic inches, <hi rend="italic">w—</hi>  1800 inches, √&lt;∙7—0∙l = 11-0417, will give A = 159∙33 inches or 13-276 feet; whereas it should have been 12. This shows that our calculated value of <hi rend="italic">d 'κta</hi>  too small. Let us therefore increase the depth by 0∙9, or make it 12∙9, and repeat the calculation. This will give us √<hi rend="sup">,</hi>rf— 0∙l = 11∙3927, and<hi rend="italic">lι</hi>  = 12-867, instead of 13-276. Therefore, augmenting our data, 0∙9 changes our answer 0409. If we suppose these small changes to retain their proportions, we may conclude that if 12 be augmented by the quantity <hi rend="italic">x ×</hi>  0∙9, the quantity 13∙276 will diminish by the quantity <hi rend="italic">x ×</hi>  0-409. Therefore, that the estimated value of A may agree with the one which results from’the calculation, we must have 12 + <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  × 0∙9 — 13∙276 — <hi rend="italic">x×</hi>  0∙409. This</p><p>1∙276</p><p>will give <hi rend="italic">x =    </hi>= 0-9748; and <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  × 0∙9 = 0-8773;</p><p>and A = 12-8773. If w-e repeat the calculation with this value of <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  we shall find no change.</p><p>This value of <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  gives <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  = 131-8836 inches. If we now compute the new velocity by dividing the new discharge 4500 by the new area 150 × 12-8773, we shall find it to be 27∙95 inches, in place of 20, the former velocity.</p><p>We might have made a pretty exact first assumption, by recollecting what was formerly observed, that when the breadth is very great in proportion to the depth, the mean depth differs insensibly from the real depth, or rather follows nearly the same proportions, and that the velocities are proportional to the square roots of the depths. Call the first discharge <hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  the height A, and velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi>  and let D, H, and V, express these things in their augmented</p><p><hi rend="italic">,    d . .<hi rend="sub">r</hi> D ,    .. d</hi>  D</p><p>state. We have <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  = —=-and V =—and <hi rend="italic">v</hi>  : V = <hi rend="sub">T</hi>; <hi rend="sub">π</hi>-,</p><p><hi rend="italic">w h    w</hi>  Η    A H</p><p>&lt;Z<hi rend="sup">8</hi> D<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>and e<hi rend="sup">2</hi>; V<hi rend="sup">2</hi> =^-∙ jp∙ But by this remark t∣<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  : V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  = A : H.<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sub">f</hi>p</hi>  D<hi rend="sup">2</hi>    AD<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  Hd<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>Therefore A : H =⅛⅛, and ⅛¼=-^⅛-, andΛ<hi rend="sup">3</hi>D<hi rend="sup">2</hi> = H<hi rend="sup">3</hi>tZ<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, A<hi rend="sup">2</hi> H<hi rend="sup">z</hi>    H* ∕*<hi rend="sup">,</hi></p><p>Λ<hi rend="sup">3</hi>D<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>and <hi rend="italic">&lt;P</hi>  : D<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  =<hi rend="italic">h<hi rend="sup">3</hi></hi>  : H<hi rend="sup">s</hi>  (a useful theorem), and H<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  =</p><p>Or we might have made the same assumption by th mark also formerly made on this case, that the squar the discharges are nearly as the cubes of the height 1500<hi rend="sup">2</hi> : 4500<hi rend="sup">2</hi> = 6<hi rend="sup">3</hi> : !2∙48<hi rend="sup">3</hi>.</p><p>And in making these first guesses, we shall do it 1 exactly, by recollecting that a certain variation of the 1 depth <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  requires a greater variation of the height, ant increment will be to the height nearly as half the hi to the width, as may easily be seen. Therefore, if we</p><p>6-24</p><p>to 12-48 its th part, or its 24th part, viz. 0-52, we</p><p>13 for our first assumption, exceeding the truth onl inch and a half. W’e mention these circumstances, those who are disposed to apply these doctrines to the lution of practical cases may be at no loss when one curs of which the regular solution requires an intri analysis.</p><p>It is evident that the inverse of the foregoing probl will show the effects of enlarging the section of a r that is, will show how much its surface will be sunk by-proposed enlargement of its bed. It is therefore neet to propose such problems in this place. Common si directs us to make these enlargements in those parts of river where their effect will be greatest, that is, where shallowest when its breadth greatly exceeds its depth where it is narrowest (if its depth exceed the brea which is a very rare case), or, in general, where the sloj the smallest for a short run.</p><p>The same general principles direct us in the metho embankments for the prevention of floods, by enablinj to ascertain the heights necessary to be given to our ba This will evidently depend, not only on the additi∣ quantity of water which experience tells us a river br down during its freshes, but also on the distance at wl we place the banks from the natural banks of the ri This is a point where mistaken economy frequently def its own purpose. If we raise our embankment at s∣ distance from the natural banks of the river, not only a smaller hcight suffice, and consequently a smaller h which will make a saving in the duplicate proportion of height ; but our works will be so much the more dur nearly, if not exactly, in the same proportion. For by <hi rend="sup">, </hi>enlarging the additional bed which we give to the swc river, we diminish its velocity almost in the same , portion that we enlarge its channel, and thus diminisl power of ruining our works. Except, therefore, in the of a river whose freshes are loaded with fine sand to des the turf, it is always proper to place the embankment considerable distance from the natural banks. Placing t at half the breadth of the stream from its natural ba will nearly double its channel ; and, except in the∣ here mentioned, the space now detached from our fi will afford excellent pasture.</p><p>The limits of such a work as ours will not permit u enter into any detail on the method of embankment, would require a volume to give instructions as to the π ner of founding, raising, and securing the dikes wl must be raised, and a thousand circumstances which r be attended to. But a few general observations may made, which naturally occur while we are considering manner in which a river works in settling or altering channel.</p><p>It must be remarked, in the first place, that the 1 will rise higher when embanked than it does while it allowed to spread ; and it is by that means easy to 1 clude to what height it will rise from the greatest heigl which it has been observed to rise in its floods. Whe liberty to expand over a wide valley, then it could ∣ rise till it overflowed with a thickness or depth of w sufficient to produce a motion backwards into the va</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>