<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>halls, in the midst of which some aged trees have taken root in the soft green turf which now supplies the place of the pavement of costly marble and rich mosaic. One of these halls, the famous Cella Soleares, held 1600 seats of polished marble,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  and was entirely covered witll a flat roof of stone, supported by cancellated work of brass or copper, which, from the resemblance to the lacing of a sandal, is supposed to have given the hall its designation. On the western side of the ruins there are the remains of a rotondo, and a great number of smaller divisions of all sizes and forms. This enormous fabric was adorned with an immense number of statues and paintings. The celebrated Farnese Hercules, the Glycon, the bull, now in the museum at Naples, the Torso Belvidere, the Flora, the Cal-lypigean Venus, together with many other statues, columns, bas reliefs, &amp;c., were all found in these ruins. The thermae and palace of Titus were built with the materials, and on the site of the buildings and pleasure grounds, of Nero’s golden house. They were finished or enlarged by Trajan, and afterwards repaired and embellished by Hadrian. They appear to have been of remarkable extent and magnificence. Part of the theatre of one of the temples, and of one of the great halls, still remains above, and many vaults and long galleries under ground. Some of these subterraneous apartments are curiously painted, and the ceiling of one of them contains some most exquisite specimens of paintings in arabesque, which afforded a model to the genius of Raphael, and enabled him to restore an art which had been lost for so many centuries.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  In the time of Leo X. some excavations were made, and the famous group of the Laocoon was discovered in one of the halls, and several pillars of granite, alabaster, and porphyry, have since been found in various partial researches. In another part of the Esquiline Hill stand the Sette Salle, nine halls of one hundred feet in length, by fifteen in breadth, and twenty in depth, which have evidently been immense reservoirs of water, to supply the baths of Titus, and occasionally the enormous arena of the Coliseum, when naval engagements were represented.</p><p>The thermae of Diocletian, which are scattered over the summit of the Quirinal and Viminal hills, are said to have surpassed all the thermae of ancient Rome in extent and splendour. One of the circular halls has been converted into a granary, another into the church of St. Bernard. The <hi rend="italic">xystum penacotheca,</hi>  or great covered hall of the thermae, has been transformed into the church of St. Maria degli angeli, and still retains much of its original grandeur. It is 350 feet in length, 80 in breadth, and 90 in height. It was paved and incrusted with the finest marble by Benedict XIV. The vaulted roof is supported by sixteen Corinthian columns, eight of which are ancient, and are formed of one vast piece of Egyptian granite. This noble edifice is adorned with a variety of paintings ; among others, with the martyrdom of St. Sebastian, by Domeni-chino ; and the circular vestibule contains the monuments of Salvator Rosa and Carlo Maratti.</p><p>Seven bridges formerly conducted over the Tiber to the Janiculum and the Vatican Mount. Three of these, the Pons Sublicius, the Pons Palatinus, and the Pons Triumphalis, were long ago destroyed. Those which now remain are the Bridges of the Island, the Ponte Sisto, and the Ponte San Angelo. Out of Rome there is only one bridge over the Tiber, the famous Milvian or Æmilian bridge, now corrupted into Ponte Molle. Here the ambassadors of the Allobroges were seized by the vigilance of Cicero ;@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  and here was fought the eventful battle in which Constantine defeated Maxentius. About three miles from</p><p>Rome, the Anio, now the Te verone, is crossed by the Ponte Lamentano, formerly the <hi rend="italic">Pons Nomentanus,</hi>  beyond which rises the broad green height of Monte Sagro, the famous <hi rend="italic">Mons Sacer,</hi>  to which the Roman army and people twice retired from the tyranny of the Patricians.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  The Ponte Salario, a very singular and picturesque structure, which also crosses the Anio, about three miles beyond the gate of the same name, was the scene of thc celebrated combat between Manlius Torquatus and the gigantic Gaul.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  The ground on the other side of it is supposed to be that on which Hannibal encamped during the few days he remained before Rome.</p><p>Rome contains the ruins of a number of triumphal arches. The most important of these are the arches of Titus, of Septimius Severus, and of Constantine. The arch of Titus is the oldest triumphal arch now existing in Rome. It is peculiarly rich in sculpture. The interior is decorated with two fine bas reliefs, representing on one side Titus in his car of triumph, and, on the other, the spoils of the temple of Jerusalem and the captive Jews. It was greatly mutilated, but has been recently restored. The arch of Severus, though more entire, is much less beautiful. The arch of Constantine is thought by far the most noble of the triumphal arches of Rome, but its columns, its beautiful sculptured medallions and bas reliefs, have evidently been pilfered from one of the triumphal arches of Trajan.</p><p>Of all the stupendous aqueducts of ancient Rome, two alone remain even in ruins, the Martian and the Claudian. The former, which was built by Quintus Martius Rex the prætor, 125 years <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c.,</hi>  conveyed to Rome three different waters in three distinct channels; the latter was built by the emperor Claudius, and conveyed two waters to Rome, the aqua Claudia, and the Anio vetus. The first was conveyed a distance of thirty-five, the last of sixty-two miles. There is reason to believe that the aqueducts were destroyed by Totila, but notwithstanding their destruction, Rome is still tlle city in the world the best supplied with water, three popes having conducted to it three noble streams.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi></p><p>Rome alone, of all the cities of the world, boasts those sublime monuments of antiquity, the obelisks of Egypt.@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> The most important of these are the obelisk that stands in the Piazza del Popolo ; it was the first ever seen in Rome, and was brought from Egypt by Augustus, and placed in the Circus Maximus, where it served as the gnomon of a dial ; the obelisk in the grand piazza of St. Peter’s, brought from Egypt by Caligula ; the obelisk in front of the Lateran church, the largest of them all, transported from Egypt by Constantius ; the obelisk mentioned by Pliny, which was brought to Rome by Augustus, and erected in the Campus Martius; it now stands on Monte Citorio; and the obelisk which stood in the circus of Sallust, and now crowns the lofty summit of the Pincian hill.</p><p>The Roman tombs were distinguished by their impressive grandeur and magnificence. All along the long line of the Appian way are the mouldering remains of the ruined and blackening sepulchres,</p><p>“ Where Cæsars, heroes, peasants, hermits lie,</p><p>Blended in dust together.”</p><p>But among the immense number of proud sepulchres of the most distinguished Romans which crowded that “ Queen of ways,” all, with a very few exceptions, are unknown. About sixty years ago the tomb of the Scipios was brought to light, but “ the Scipios tomb contains no ashes now.” Exactly on the opposite side of the road to it is the sepulchre of the Maniglia family. The tomb of Cecilia Metella, tile daughter of Metellus, and “ the wealthiest Roman’s</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Olympiodorus in Bibliothec. Pbotii, p. 114.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Eustace's Classical Tour, p. 388. Rome in the 19th Century, vol. ii. p. 99.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  Sallust, Bell. Catil.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  Livy, lib. ii. cap. 32.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  Ibid. lib. vii. cap. 10.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi>  Rome in 19th century, vol. ii. p. 150.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi>  Ibid. p. 158—165.</p></body></text></TEI>