<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>orientals, from whom the Greeks certainly borrowed their forms and their combinations. We could easily show in the ruins of Persepolis, and amongst the tombs in the mountains, which were long prior to the Greek architecture, the fluted column, the base, the Ionic and Corinthian capitals, and the Doric arrangement of lintels, beams, and rafters, all derived from unquestionable principle. The only addition made by the Greeks was the pent-roof ; and the changes made by them in the subordinate forms of things are such as we should expect from their exquisite judgment of beauty.</p><p>But the whole of this is very limited ; and the Greeks, after making the roof a chief feature of a house, went no further, and contented themselves with giving it a slope suited to their climate. This we have followed, because in the milder parts of Europe we have no cogent reasoning for deviating from it ; and if any architect should deviate greatly in a building where the outline is exhibited as beautiful, we should be disgusted ; but the disgust, though felt by almost every spectator, has its origin in nothing but habit. In the professed architect or man of education, the disgust arises from pedantry. For there is not such a close connection between the form and uses of a roof as shall give precise determinations ; and the mere form is a matter of indifference.</p><p>We should not therefore reprobate the high-pitched roofs of our ancestors, particularly on the Continent. It is there where we see them in all the extremity of the fashion ; and the taste is by no means exploded, as it is with us. A baronial castle in Germany and France is seldom rebuilt in the pure Greek style, or even like the modem houses in Great Britain ; the high-pitched roofs are retained. We should not call them Gothic, and ugly because Gothic, till we show their principle to be false or tasteless. Now we apprehend that it will be found quite the reverse ; and that though we cannot bring ourselves to think them beautiful, we ought to think them so. The construction of the Greek architecture is a transference of the practices that are necessary in a wooden building to a building of stone. To this the Greeks have adhered, in spite of innumerable difficulties. Their marble quarries, however, put it in their power to retain the proportions which habit had rendered agreeable. But it is next to impossible to adhere to these proportions with freestone or with brick, when the order is of magnificent dimensions. Sir Christopher Wren saw this ; for his mechanical knowledge was equal to his taste. He composed the front of St Paul’s Church in London of two orders, and he coupled his columns; and still the lintels which form the architrave are of such length that they could carry no additional weight, and he was obliged to truss them behind. Had he made but one order, the architrave could not have carried its own weight. It is impossible to execute a Doric entablature of this size in brick. It is attempted in a very noble front, the Academy of Arts in St Petersburg. But the architect was obliged to make the mutules and other projecting members of the corniche of granite, and many of them broke down by their own weight.</p><p>Here is surely an error in principle. Since stone is the chief material of our buildings, ought not the members of ornamented architecture to be refinements on the essential and unaffected parts of a simple stone building ? There is almost as much propriety in the architecture of India, where a dome is made in imitation of a lily or other flower inverted, as in the Greek imitation of a wooden building. The principles of masonry, and not of carpentry, should be seen in our architecture, if we would have it according to the rules of just taste. Now we affirm that this is the characteristic of what is called the Gothic architecture. In this no dependence is had on the transverse strength of stone. No lintels are to be seen, and no extravagant projections. Every stone is pressed to its neighbours, and none is exposed to a transverse strain. The Greeks were enabled to execute their colossal buildings only by using immense blocks of the hardest materials. The Norman mason could raise a building to the skies without using a stone which a labourer could not carry to the top on his back. Their architects studied the principles of equilibrium ; and having attained a wonderful knowledge of it, they indulged themselves in exhibiting remarkable instances. We call this false taste, and say that the appearance of insecurity is the greatest fault in it. But this is owing to our habits ; our thoughts may be said to run in a wooden train, and certain simple maxims of caη&gt;entry are familiar to our imagination ; and in the careful adherence to these consist the beauty and symmetry of the Greek architecture. Had we been as much habituated to the equilibrium of pressure, this apparent insecurity would not have met our eye ; we should have perceived the strength and relished the ingenuity.</p><p>The Gothic architecture is perhaps entitled to the name of rational architecture, and its beauty is founded on the characteristic distinction of our species. It deserves cultivation ; not the pitiful, servile, and unskilled copying of the monuments ; this will produce incongruities and absurdities equal to any that have crept into the Greek architecture ; but let us examine with attention the nice disposition of the groins and spaundrels ; let us study the tracery and knots, not as ornaments, but as useful members ; let us observe how they have made their walls like honeycombs, and admire their ingenuity as we pretend to admire the instinct infused by the great Architect into the bee. All this cannot be understood without mechanical knowledge, a thing which few of our professional architects have any share of. Thus would architectonic taste be a mark of skill ; and the person who presents the design of a building would know how to execute it, without committing it entirely to the mason and the carpenter.</p><p>These observations are not a digression from our subject- The same principles of mutual pressure and equilibrium have a place in roofs and many wooden edifices ; and if they had been as much studied as the Normans and Saracens seem to have studied such of them as were applicable to their purposes, we might have produced wooden buildings as far superior to what we are familiarly acquainted with, as the bold and wonderful churches still remaining in Europe are superior to the timid productions of our stone architecture. The centres used in building the bridge of Orleans and the corn-market of Paris are recent instances of what may be done in this way. The last mentioned is a dome of 200 feet diameter, built of fir planks ; and there is not a piece of timber in it more than nine feet long, a foot broad, and three inches thick.</p><p>The Norman architects frequently roofed with stone. Their wooden roofs were in general very simple, and their professed aim was to dispense with them altogether. Fond of their own science, they copied nothing from a wooden building, and ran into a similar fault with the ancient Greeks. The parts of their buildings which were necessarily of timber were made to imitate stone buildings ; and Gothic ornament consists in cramming every thing full of arches and spaundrels. Nothing else is to be seen in their timber-works, nay even in their sculpture. Look at any of the maces or sceptres still to be found about the old cathedrals ; they are silver steeples.</p><p>But there appears to have been a rivalship in old times between the masons and the carpenters. Many of the baronial halls are of prodigious width, and are roofed with timber ; and the carpenters appeared to have borrowed much knowledge from the masons of those times, and their wide roofs are frequently constructed with great ingenuity. Their aim, like the masons, was to throw a roof over a very wide building, without employing great logs of timber. We have seen roofs sixty feet wide, without having a piece of</p></body></text></TEI>