<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>machine, which depends on the quantity of dead matter contained in the wheel and cylinder, and which we may denote by K ; second, the moment of inertia of the weight P, which may be considered as attached to the extremity of the radius of the wheel ; third, the moment of inertia of the weight W, which may be considered as attached to the extremity of the radius of the cylinder. Let M and M<hi rend="sup">,</hi> be the masses of the bodies whose weights are P and W, then the moments of inertia are respectively Ma<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and M'Z∣<hi rend="sup">2</hi>. Let also<hi rend="italic">g</hi>  = the acceleration of gravity, then the weight of a body being the product of its mass into the force of gravity, we have P = ^M, W = ^M', whence the whole moment of inertia is</p><p>K + ‰^, <hi rend="italic">g g</hi></p><p>and we have consequently</p><p><hi rend="italic">dw _ g (Pa —</hi>  Wδ) <hi rend="italic">df ~</hi>  &lt;<hi rend="sub">z</hi>K + Pα<hi rend="sup">2</hi>+WA<hi rend="sup">s</hi>∙</p><p>For the sake of abridging, let us assume</p><p>U = +<hi rend="sup">1</hi>p<hi rend="sub">n</hi>s + W⅛<hi rend="sup">2</hi>' <hi rend="sup">an</hi>^ <hi rend="sup">t</hi>'<hi rend="sup">le an</hi>8<hi rend="sup">ular</hi>  velocity will be</p><p>given by the equation <hi rend="italic">w = gfCdt.</hi>  Also let <hi rend="italic">v —</hi>  the velocity of the <hi rend="italic">impelled point</hi>  of the machine, or the velocity with which P descends, and <hi rend="italic">u</hi>  = the velocity of the <hi rend="italic">working point,</hi>  or velocity with which W is raised; then <hi rend="italic">v = aw,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="italic">  = bw,</hi>  at the end of the time <hi rend="italic">t ;</hi>  and if we denote the respective accelerating forces by <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  and ∙ψ, we shall have</p><p><hi rend="italic">&lt;fo <hi rend="sub">lτ</hi> , da , <hi rend="sub">rτ</hi></hi></p><p>52.    To find the proportion of the velocities of the impelled and working points which give the greatest performance when the weight and power are both given, we may treat the formula which expresses the work, that is, the accelerating force, or W, as a fluxionary quantity, and find its maximum. Thus, to find the radius of the wheel by which the weight will be raised with the greatest velocity, we have to difterentiate the quantity denoted by U, on the ■ supposition that <hi rend="italic">α</hi>  is variable, and make the result equal to zero. This will give an equation from which <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  will he obtained in terms of P, W, and A ,∙ and it will be observed, that as K varies with <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  the value of K in terms of <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  must be substituted in the value of U before the differentiation.</p><p>53.    The friction may be taken account of by considering it as a quantity to be added to the weight W. Let/ = the co-efficient of friction, and c = radius of the pivots supporting the machine, then the friction will be expressed <hi rend="italic">by fc</hi>  (P + W), and we have only to substitute WA + <hi rend="italic">fc</hi>  (P + W) for WA in the above expression for U.</p><p>54.    In the case of the fixed pulley, the velocities of P and W are equal, and we have also <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  = A. If we denote the weight of the pulley by Q, then its mass will be Q +- <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  and (18) its moment of inertia = ½ Qo<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  -÷-<hi rend="italic">g ;</hi>  therefore the formula for the accelerating force with which P descends or W rises will be</p><p>P —W</p><p><hi rend="sup">p</hi>~<hi rend="sup">s,</hi>'⅜Q+P +W</p><p>55.    We now proceed to consider the motion of a solid body which is entirely free.</p><p>When a solid body or rigid system is impressed at a single point by a force of which the direction does not pass through the centre of gravity, the body, if free to move in every direction, acquires two motions, one progressive, and equal to that which would have resulted if the direction of tlle force had passed through the centre of gravity, and the other rotatory, and equal to that which would have resulted if the body had been only at liberty to move round a fixed axis passing through the centre of gravity, and perpendicular to the plane which contains that centre, and the line of the direction of the impelling force.</p><lb/><p>56.    In order to demonstrate this proposition, let HKL (fig. 12) be a section of the body passing through G the centre of gravity, and containing the line in</p><p>which the force is directed ; let P</p><p>be the point at which the given</p><p>force F is applied, and PA its direc</p><p>tion ; through G draw GA perpen</p><p>dicular to PA, and let PA repre</p><p>sent the intensity of the force F.</p><p>Bisect AP in B, produce AG un</p><p>til GC = AG, and through C draw</p><p>CD, CE perpendicular to AC, and make each equal to AB. If we now conceive a force represented by DC to be applied at D in the direction DC, and another force represented by EC to be applied at E in the direction EC, these two forces being equal, and acting in opposite directions, will destroy each other, or produce no movement in the body, and the motion which actually takes place in consequence of the application of the force PA at P, will be the same as would result from the application of the four forces PB, BA, DC, EC. Now it is evident, that if the two forces BA and DC acted alone, they would produce no rotatory motion about the axis passing through G, for their moments BA ∙ AG and DC ∙ CG are equal, and they tend to turn the body in opposite directions. But the same two forces both tend to give the body a progressive motion ; and as the resultant of two equal and parallel forces is a force equal to their sum, and acting at the point which bisects the distance between their directions, the initial progressive motion of the body in consequence of the forces BA and DC will be the same as if the force PA = F were applied at the point G in the direction parallel to PA. We have now to consider the two remaining forces PB and EC. As these two forces act on the line AC in opposite directions, their resultant is nothing, or their separate tendencies to produce a progressive motion in the centre of gravity of the body, are counteracted by their joint effort. But they conspire in tending to produce a rotatory motion in the same direction about the axis passing through G ; and the moment of the first in respect of that axis being PB ∙ AG, and that of the second EC ∙ CG, the sum of their moments is (PB + EC) AG or PA ∙ AG. The whole effect of these two forces is therefore to produce the same initial angular velocity about the axis through G, perpendicular to HKL, as would be produced by the single force PA applied at the point A ; and it has been shown, that the whole effect of the forces BA and DC is to produce the same progressive movement of the centre of gravity as if the single force PA were applied at that point, consequently the proposition is demonstrated, and it appears that the two motions produced by the application of a force which is not directed towards the centre of gravity may be considered independently of each other.</p><p>57.    Let V = the progressive velocity of the centre of gravity in the direction parallel to PA ; then the mass of the body being M, we have the force F = MV, and consequently V = F -+ M. Again, if we make AG = <hi rend="italic">l,</hi>  the angular velocity produced by the force F applied at A is <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  = F ∙ <hi rend="italic">l ÷ fridm</hi>  (14), therefore V : <hi rend="italic">w :: Jridm</hi>  : MZ. Now, since <hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  and M are both known from the nature of the body, it follows, that when the distance Z is given, the ratio of the progressive motion of the centre of gravity to the velocity of angular rotation can be found ; and, conversely, when the ratio of the two velocities is given, the distance Z can be found. For example, let <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  be the space described by the centre of gravity while the body makes one revolution about its axis, then 2w is the space described, in consequence of the rotatory motion, by a point of the body whose distance from the axis = 1, and the above proportion gives ,2» <hi rend="italic">fridm</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">l</hi>~^T' IT’</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>