<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>YEARS.</p></cell><cell cols="4" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inhabited.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>&lt;</p><p>1</p><p>⅛</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Building.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Uninhabited.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in</p><p>Agricul</p><p>ture.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly em-ployed in Trade, Manufactures, and Handicraft</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in the two preceding classes.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1811</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12,829</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13,574</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>159</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>292</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7,490</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,499</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,585</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>27,640</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>33,213</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>60,853</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1821</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>13,638</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>14,506</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>146</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>345</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7,947</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,356</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,203</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>32,324</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>36,504</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>68,828</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>15,039</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16,187</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>131</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>352</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8,498</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2,611</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,078</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>34,927</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>39,893</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>74,820</p></cell></row></table><lb/><p>ROSTAK, a city of Arabia, in the district of Ommon. It is the residence of the imaum ; but Muskat is the chief town through which the intercourse with the Europeans is carried on. It is situated near Jebel Akdar, the largest and highest mountain in Ommon, and is celebrated for its fine grapes. It is seventy miles west from Muskat.</p><p>ROSTOCK, a city of the grand duchy of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, which was formerly the capital of the two duchies of Mecklenburg, but since 1695 it has become the sole possession of the present branch. It is situated on the navigable river Wornow, about eight miles from the Baltic Sea. It is strongly fortified, and contains a citadel, seven churches, 2180 houses of an antique style of building, and about 16,000 inhabitants. It is the place at which the assembly of the states, and the courts of law, are held ; and it contains a university founded in 1419, which has a due number of professors, and about a hundred students, to which are attached an observatory, an anatomical theatre, and a library of thirty thousand volumes. It is the most considerable trading place in the German part of the Baltic, and the export of wheat is greater than from any other German port. It has a variety of manufactures for brandy, vinegar, beer, cloths, glass, leather, iron ware, soap, sugar, and linen, and 140 ships belonging to the port. This place gave birth to Prince Blucher, to whom a statue has been erected in the square. Long. 12. 32. E. Lat. 54. 10. N.</p><p>ROSTOW, a city of Russia, in the province of Jaros-low, the capital of a circle of its own name, situated on the lake of Nero or Rostow. It contains twenty-four churches, six hospitals, 1016 houses, and 6500 inhabitants ; and has extensive trade in corn, hemp, linen, tallow, leather, honey, and wax, and some in salt. It is 530 miles from St Petersburg. Long. 39. 35. E. Lat. 58. 57. N.</p><p>ROSTRA, a part of the Roman forum, in which orations, pleadings, and funeral harangues, were delivered. It derived its name from the circumstance of its exhibiting the beaks of ships taken from the Antiates.</p><p>ROSTRUM literally denotes the beak or bill of a bird ; and hence it has been figuratively applied to the beak or head of a ship.</p><p>ROT, a very fatal disease incident to sheep, arising from wet seasons, and too moist pasture. It is very difficult of cure, and is attended with the singular circumstance of a kind of animals being found in the blood-vessels.</p><p>ROTA, a city of Spain, in the province of Seville, and the district of St Lucar. It stands on the bay of Cadiz, and being strongly fortified, forms one of the means of defence to that important estuary. It is situated on an elevation, and, like most Spanish towns, has a beautiful appearance when viewed at a distance. It contains some very fine buildings, and about 6500 inhabitants, who partly follow the occupation of fishing, whilst others deal in wine, as this place supplies the kind of red wine known in England by the name of Tent, which is produced on the banks of the river Tinto.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rota, the name of an ecclesiastical court of Rome, composed of twelve prelates, of whom one must be a German, another a Frenchman, and two Spaniards ; the other eight are Italians, three of whom must be Romans, and the other five a Bolognese, a Ferraran, a Milanese, a Venetian, and a Tuscan. This is one of the most august tribunals in Rome, which takes cognizance, by appeal, of all suits in the territory of the church, and also of all matters, beneficiary and patrimonial.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rota Aristotelica, or </hi><hi rend="italic">Aristotle's Wheel,</hi>  denotes a celebrated problem in mechanics, concerning the motion or rotation of a wheel about its axis, so called because Aristotle was the first who took notice of it. The difficulty of it may be represented in the following manner. While the circle makes one revolution on its centre, advancing at the same time in a right line along a plane, it describes on that plane a right line which is equal to its circumference. Now, if this circle carry with it another smaller circle, concentric with it, like the nave of a coach-wheel, then this smaller circle or nave will describe a line in the time of the revolution which shall be equal to that of the large wheel or circumference itself, because its centre advances in a right line as fast as that of the wheel does, being in reality the same with it- Aristotle attempted to solve this problem ; but his solution can only be regarded as a good account of the difficulty. It was next attempted by Galileo, who had recourse to an infinite number of infinitely small vacuities in the right line described by the two circles, and imagined that the little circle never applies its circumference to those vacuities, but in reality only applies it to a line equal to its own circumference, though it appears to have applied it to a much larger. This, however, is nothing to the purpose. According to Tacquet, the little circle making its rotation more slowly than the great one, does, on that account, describe a line longer than its own circumference, yet without applying any point of its circumference to more than one point of its base. This is not more satisfactory than the former. After the fruitless endeavours of many great men, M. Dortous de Mey-ran, a French gentleman, had the good fortune to hit upon a solution which, after being fully examined by a committee of the Academy of Sciences, was declared to be satisfactory. The following is his solution. The wheel of a coach is only acted on or drawn in a right line ; its rotation or circular motion arises purely from the resistance of the ground. Now this resistance is equal to the force which draws the wheel in a right line, as it defeats that direction, and therefore the causes of the two motions are equal. The wheel therefore describes a right line on the ground equal to its circumference. On the contrary, the nave is drawn in a right line by the same force as the wheel, but it only turns round because the wheel does so, and can only turn in the same time with it. Hence its circular velocity is less than that of the wheel, in the ratio of the two circumferences, and therefore its circular motion is less than the rectilinear one. Since it must describe a right line equal to that of the wheel, it can only do it by partly sliding and partly revolving, the sliding part being more or less as the nave itself is smaller or greater.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>