<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rating force is <hi rend="italic">dbs</hi>  × p or <hi rend="italic">db.</hi>  But if we would only consider this resistance as corresponding to an unit of the length of the channel, we must divide the quantity <hi rend="italic">db</hi>  by s,</p><p>and the resistance is then —. And if we would consider s</p><p>the resistance only for an unit of the border, we must divide this expression by <hi rend="italic">b;</hi>  and thus this resistance (taking an inch for the unit) will be expressed for one square inch of the bed by the weight of a bulk of water w hich has a square inch for its base, and - for its height. And lastly, if E</p><p>be taken for any given superficial extent of the channel or bed, and F the obstruction, which we consider as a sort of E√</p><p>friction, we shall have F = —∙.</p><p>s</p><p>Thus, let it be required to determine in pounds the resistance or friction on a square yard of a channel whose current is in train, which is ten feet wide, four feet deep, and has a slope of one foot in a mile. Here E is nine feet. Ten feet width and four feet depth give a section of forty</p><p>40</p><p>feet. The border is eighteen feet. Therefore <hi rend="italic">d = — = </hi>18</p><p>2∙2222, and ί is 5280. Therefore the friction is the weight of a column of water whose base is nine feet, and height 2∙2222</p><p>—<hi rend="sup">or</hi> nearly 3¾&gt;<hi rend="sub">n</hi> ounces avoirdupois.</p><p>§ 3. <hi rend="italic">Settlement of the Beds of Rivers.</hi></p><p>He who looks with a careless eye at a map of the world, is apt to consider the rivers which ramble over its surface as a chance-medley disposition of the drainers which carry off the waters. But it w ill afford a most agreeable object to a considerate and contemplative mind to take it up in this very simple light ; and, having considered the many ways in w hich the drenched'surface might have been cleared of the superfluous waters, to attend particularly to the very way which nature has followed. In pursuing the troubled waters of a mountain torrent, or the pure streams which trickle from their bases, till he sees them swallowed up in the ocean, and in attending to the many varieties in their motions, he will be delighted with observing how the simple laws of mechanism are made so fruitful in good consequences, both by modifying the motions of the waters themselves, and also by inducing new- forms on the surface of the earth, fitted for re-acting on the waters, and producing those very modifications of their motions which render them so beneficial. The permanent beds of rivers are by no means fortuitous gutters hastily scooped out by dashing torrents ; but both they and the valleys through which they flow are the patient but unceasing labours of nature, prompted by goodness and directed by wisdom.</p><p>Whether we trace a river from the torrents which collect the superfluous waters of heaven, or from the springs which discharge what would otherwise be condemned to perpetual inactivity, each feeder is but a little rill, which could not ramble far from its scanty source among growing plants and absorbent earth, without being sucked up and evaporated, did it not meet w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ith other rills in its course. When united, they form a body of water still inconsiderable, but much more able, by its bulk, to overcome the little obstacles to its motion ; and the rivulet then moves with greater speed, as we have now learned. At the same time, the surface exposed to evaporation and absorption is diminished by the union of the rills. Four equal rills have only the surface of two when united. Thus the portion which escapes arrestment, and travels downward, is continually increasing. This is a happy adjustment to the other opetations of nature. Were it otherwise, the lower and more valuable countries would be loaded with the passing waters in addition to their own surplus rains, and the immediate neighbourhood of the sea would be almost covered by the drains of the interior countries. But, fortunately, those passing waters occupy less room as they advance, and by this wise employment of the most simple means, not only are the superfluous waters drained off from our fertile fields, but the drains themselves become an useful part of the country by their magnitude. They become the habitation of a prodigious number offishes, which share the Creator’s bounty ; and they become the means of mutual communication of all the blessings of cultivated society. The vague ramblings of the rivers scatter them over the face of the country, and bring them to every door. It is not even an indifferent circumstance, that they gather strength to cut out deep beds for themselves. By this means they cut open many springs. Without this, the produce of a heavy show<hi rend="sup">,</hi>er would make a swamp which would not dry up in many days. And it must be observed, that the same heat which is necessary for the vigorous growth of useful plants will produce a very copious evaporation. This must return in showers much too copious for immediate vegetation, and the overplus would be destructive. Is it not pleasant to contemplate this adjustment of the great operations of nature, so different from each other, that if chance alone directed the detail, it was almost an infinite odds that the earth would be uninhabitable ?</p><p>But let us follow the waters in their operations, and note the face of the countries through which they flow. Attending to the breadth, the depth, and the slope of the valleys, we shall be convinced that their present situation is extremely different from what it was in ancient days ; and that the valleys themselves are the works of the rivers, or at least of waters which have descended from the heights, loaded with all the lighter matters which they were able to bring away with them. The rivers now flow in beds which have a considerable permanency ; but this has been the work of ages. This has given stability, both by filling up and smoothing the valleys, and thus lessening the changing causes, and also by hardening the beds themselves, which are now covered with aquatic plants, and lined with the stones, gravel, and coarser sand, out of which all the lighter matters have been washed away.</p><p>The surface of the high grounds is undergoing a continual change ; and the ground on which we now walk is by no means the same which was trodden by our remote ancestors. The showers from heaven carry down into the valleys, or sweep along by the torrents, a part of the soil which covers the heights and steeps. The torrents carry this soil into the brooks, these deliver part of it into the great rivers, and these discharge this fertilizing fat of the earth into the sea, where it is swallowed up, and for ever lost for the purposes of vegetation. Thus the hillocks lose of their height, the valleys are filled up, and the mountains are laid bare and show their naked precipices, which formerly w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>ere covered over with flesh and skin, but now look like the skeleton of this globe. The low- countries, raised and nourished for some time by the substance of the high lands, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ill go in their turn to be buried in the ocean ; and then the earth, reduced to a dreary flat, will become an immense uninhabitable mass. This catastrophe is tar distant, because this globe is in its youth, but it is not the less certain ; and the united labours of the human race could not long protract the term.</p><p>But, in the mean time, we can trace a beneficent purpose, and a nice adjustment of seemingly remote circumstances. The grounds near the sources of all our rivers are indeed gradually stripped of their most fertile ingredi-</p></body></text></TEI>