<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Supplement, by Arch, Astronomy, Boscovich, Carpentry, Centre, Dynamics, Electricity, Impulsion, Involution, Machinery, Magnetism, Mechanics, Percussion, Pianoforte, Position, Temperament, Thunder, Trumpet, Tschirnhaus, and Watch-work. Notwithstanding some degree of prolixity and want bf arrangement, which could scarcely be avoided in the preparation of original articles for such a mode of publication, the whole of them, taken together, undeniably exhibit a more complete view of the modern improvements of physical science than had ever before been in the possession of the British public ; and display such a combination of acquired knowledge with original power of reasoning, as has fallen to the lot of a few only of the most favoured of mankind.</p><p>4.    It is not altogether with so high approbation that his friends and his biographers have mentioned a work, of a nature rather political than philosophical, entitled Proofs of a Conspiracy against all the Religions and Governments of Europe, Edinb. 1797, 8vo ; though it went through several editions. The principal part of the book consists of the history of the <hi rend="italic">Illuminati</hi>  and the German Union, whom he considers as having become the chief agents in a plot first formed by the freemasons, at the suggestion of some ex-jesuit, who proposed for their model the internal economy of the order which he had quitted ; and whatever foundation this outline may have had in truth, there is no doubt that the manner in which Professor Robison has filled it up, betrays a degree of credulity extremely remarkable in a person used to calm reasoning and philosophical demonstration : for example, in the admission of a story told by an anonymous German author, that the minister Turgot was the protector of a society that met at Baron d’Hol-bach’s, for the purpose of examining the brains of <hi rend="italic">living children,</hi>  in order to discover the principle of vitality. He does not accuse the English freemasons of having participated in the conspiracy ; but he considers the continental lodges as having been universally implicated in it.</p><p>5.    After the death of Dr Black, in 1799, he undertook to superintend the publication of his Lectures on Chemistry, which appeared in 1803, 2 vols. 4to. And this task, which w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>as rather laborious than difficult, he executed with equal zeal and ability. He endeavoured to reduce to their just estimate the comparative pretensions of the French and British chemists, though he is somewhat puritanically severe in criticizing the literal meaning of the compliments paid to Black by Lavoisier, on which he founds a charge of insincerity.</p><p>6.    His last publication was the first volume of a series which was to form a complete system, entitled Elements of Mechanical Philosophy, Edinb. 1804,8vo. It comprehended only Dynamics and Astronomy, and it never became very popular : it was too difficult for the many, who wished for general and philosophical notions only, and not sufficiently precise and demonstrative for the few, who wanted practical and numerical results. In attempting to combine the separate merits of the <hi rend="italic">Exposition du Système du Monde, </hi>and of the <hi rend="italic">Mécanique Céleste,</hi>  the author sacrificed both the popular simplicity of the former, and the mathematical perfection of the latter. A few inaccuracies, which ought not to escape the attention of the reader of the work, have been pointed out in the Imperial Review for March 1805 ; a journal long since discontinued.</p><p>7.    The contents of the volume last mentioned, together with some manuscripts intended to have formed part of a second, and the greater part of the articles furnished by Professor Robison to the Encyclopædia, were collected into a System of Mechanical Philosophy, with Notes, by David Brewster, LL. D. Edinb. 1822, 4 vols. 8vo ; a spirited bookseller in London having undertaken the risk of the publication. 1. The first volume begins with the articles Dynamics, Projectiles, Corpuscular Forces, Capillary Attraction, Boscovich’s Theory, and Rotation, all as remodelled for the Elements ; then follow Strength op Materials, Carpentry, Roof, Construction of Arches, Construction of Centres. 2. The article Steam-Engine is enriched with notes and an appendix by the late Mr Watt : the next is Machinery, then Resistance of Fluids, Rivers, Water-works, Pumps. 3. Astronomy, Telescope, Pneumatics. 4. Electricity, Magnetism, Variation, Temperament, Trumpet, Watch-work, and Seamanship. The notes are not numerous, and the editor’s principal labour has been to retrench some passages that appeared to him superfluous when the papers were to stand as parts of such a collection.</p><p>“ Although Dr Robison’s name,” says Dr Brewster in his preface, “ cannot be associated with the great discoveries of the century which he adorned, yet the memory of his talents and his virtues will be long cherished by his country. Imbued with the genuine spirit of the philosophy which he taught, he was one of the warmest patrons of genius wherever it was found. His mind was nobly elevated above the mean jealousies of rival ambition, and his love of science and of justice was too ardent to allow him either to depreciate the labours of others, or to transfer them to himself. To these great qualities as a philosopher, Dr Robison added all the more estimable endowments of domestic and of social life. His friendship was at all times generous and sincere. His piety was ardent and unostentatious. His patriotism was of the most pure and exalted character ; and, like the immortal Newton, whose memory he cherished with a peculiar reverence, he was pre-eminently entitled to the high distinction of a Christian, patriot, and philosopher.” His person was handsome, and his physiognomy prepossessing ; and he appears to have been endowed with an extraordinary combination of talents, even exclusively of those which were called into immediate activity in his professional pursuits ; for he was a good linguist, an excellent draughtsman, and an accomplished musician. His conversation was always energetic and interesting, and sometimes even poetical ; and his liberality of sentiment was only limited by his regard for what he considered as the best interests of mankind.</p><p>A short account of his life was published in 1802, by a contributor to the Philosophical Magazine, who, among other inaccuracies, thought himself at liberty to assert that he was an admirer of the algebraical form of representation, in preference to the geometrical. His friend Dr Gleig soon after stepped forward to correct these mistakes, in the Antijacobin Review* for 1802, and his letter was copied into the Philosophical Magazine. He asserts, from his own knowledge, that even yet Professor Robison “ delights much more in geometry than in any of the modes of algebra, assigning as the reason of his preference, that in the longest demonstration the geometrician has always clear and adequate ideas, which the most expert algebraist can very seldom have.” It may perhaps be asserted, on the other hand, that the same reasoning would lead us always to employ actual multiplication or division, in preference to the use of logarithms or of a sliding rule ; and that the whole of the magic of calculation depends on the abstraction of the results from the numerous and separately unimportant steps by which they are obtained ; but the having once seen those steps clearly is certainly of great importance to the process of reasoning, even when the memory no longer retains them ; and no mathematician of correct taste can study the ancient geometricians without admiring the elegance and precision of their method, even amidst the pedantry which too frequently envelopes their expressions, and without being grateful for their punctuality in collecting their results into the very convenient form of distinct propositions, and in making such references from each proposition to the foundations on which it depends, as to en-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>