<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>desperate conflict, drove them from the Roman territories. Next year they again passed the Anio by a bridge of boats, and advanced towards Rome. Tarquinius met them in battle, and by the superiority of his cavalry gained a complete victory. During the battle a party of Romans, sent for that purpose, burned the bridge of boats, so that the routed Sabines were cut off from their retreat, and driven into the river, where great numbers of them perished. Their bodies and arms, floating down the Tiber, brought the first intelligence of the victory to Rome. He then crossed the river, inflicted upon them a second defeat, and compelled them to surrender the town and lands of Collatia, which they had previously taken from the Latins. Tarquinius placed a strong garrison in the town, and assigned the capture to his brother’s son, who thence took the name of Collatinus. In this war the king’s son, a youth of fourteen, slew a foe with his own hand, and received as a reward of honour a robe bordered with purple, and a hollow ball of gold to be suspended round his neck ; and these continued to be the distinctive dress and ornament of the Roman youth of patrician rank, till they assumed the <hi rend="italic">toga virilis,</hi>  or manly gown.</p><p>Tarquinius is likewise said to have engaged in war with the Etruscan nations, to have taken several of their cities, and to have overthrown them, notwithstanding a confederacy of all their twelve states against him. In token of their submission to his power, the Etruscans at length sent him a golden crown, an ivory throne and sceptre, a purple tunic and robe figured with gold, and twelve axes bound up in bundles of rods to be borne before him, such as they used when their twelve cities chose a common leader in war. These, by the permission of the people, Tarquinius adopted as the insignia of kingly power ; and, witll the exception of the crown, and of the embroidered robe, they remained as such both to his successors on the throne, and to the consuls, unless on the days when they went in public triumph to the Capitol.</p><p>Such were the military exploits ascribed to Tarquinius ; and there is nothing so improbable in them as to startle our belief. It is indeed manifest from other indications, that about the period assumed as the reign of Tarquinius Priscus, as he is called for the sake of distinction, the dominions of Rome must have comprised nearly all the territory which he is said to have conquered, and also that the city must have risen to great wealth and power. The latter point is proved by the great public works, which all accounts agree in ascribing to him. He built the cloaca maxima, or great sewers, to drain off the water from between the Capitoline and Palatine, and the Palatine and Aventine hills. This vast drain was constructed of huge blocks of hewn stone, triply arched, and of such dimensions, that a barge could float along in it beneath the very streets of the city. Earthquakes have shaken the city and the adjacent hills; but the cloaca maxima remains to this day unimpaired, an enduring monument of the power and skill of the king and the people by whom it was constructed. The Circus Maximus, or great race-course, was also a work of this monarch, intended for the display of what were called the great, or Roman games, “ ludi magni Romani.” The forum, with its rows of shops, was also the work of Tarquinius ; and he began to surround the city with a wall of massy hewn stones. He likewise made preparation to fulfil a vow to build a great temple on the Capitoline hill to the chief deities of Rome.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>To conclude the legendary history of Tarquinius, he is said to have been murdered by the treachery of the sons of his predecessor Ancus Marcius. They, perceiving the favour with which the king regarded Servius Tullius, and fearing an attempt to make him king, to the exclusion of their own pretensions and hopes, hired two countrymen to pretend a quarrel, and to appear before the king seeking redress. While he was listening to the complaint of one, the other struck him on the head with an axe, and then they both made their escape. The conspirators did not, however, obtain the fruit of their treachery. Tanaquil gave out that the king was not dead, but only stunned by the blow, and had appointed Servius Tullius to rule in his name till he should recover. Servius immediately assumed the ensigns and exercised the power of royalty. The murderers were seized and punished, and the Marcii fled disappointed from the city. When the death of Tarquinius could no longer be concealed, the power of Servius was so well established, that the people were perfectly ready to grant him the usual confirmation in the powers of the sovereignty.</p><p>The accounts respecting the origin of Servius Tullius are as obscure as those of any of his predecessors. The most ancient and poetical legend represents him as the son of Ocrisia, a captive and slave of Tanaquil the queen, by the Lar, or household god. Later legends made him a son of one of the king’s clients, and for sometime a slave ; or the son of a man of rank and power in one of the conquered Latin cities, who being slain in the war, his widow was carried to Rome in her pregnancy, and she and her infant son were protected by Tanaquil.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> All accounts represent him as enjoying the favour of Tarquinius and his queen, and obtaining the throne in a great measure by the judicious management of the latter. It would seem as if Servius had in the very beginning of his reign encountered the opposition of the patricians. He is said not to have allowed any interregnum, or to have permitted the senate to take the lead in his election to the sovereignty ; but as he had already acted as king before the death of Tarquinius was publicly known, so to have made a direct application, without any other preliminary process, to the comitia curiata, and to have been by them invested with the powers of former kings. The only historical conclusion which can be deduced from these incidental notices is, that a contest had begun between the kings and the patrician body, in which the kings deemed it their soundest policy to diminish the power of the patricians, in order to maintain their own. But as no direct diminution of their power could have been attempted without exciting an immediate insurrection, it was deemed expedient by these kings to raise a counterbalancing power in the state, which, having received its existence from them, might be expected to lend them aid in repressing the exorbitant power of thepatrician body, combined with their hereditary privileges.</p><p>This view, it will be observed, both coincides completely with the tradition that Tarquinius first elevated the tribe of the Luceres to the possession of full senatorial power; and</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>    This mention of the building of temples on the Capitoline hill to the chief deities of Rome by Tarquinius Priscus, refers in all probability to tbe introduction to Rome of the refined and poetical idolatry of Greece, and receives some colouring of credibility from the account of his descent from a native of Corinth. Beaufort proves, that for the first 170 years of its existence at least, there were no images at Rome, unless the rude block of stone called the god Terminus might be considered an image. See<hi rend="italic">La République Romaine,</hi>  par M. de Beaufort.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>    Another account of the origin of Servius has been preserved by a speech of the emperor Claudius, as given in the Etruscan Annals. Claudius begins to recount how often the form of government had been changed, and even the royal dignity bestowed on foreigners. Then, be says of Servius Tullius, “ According to our Annals, he was the son of the captive Ocrisia; but if we follow the Tuscans, he was the faithful follower of Caeles Vibenna, and shared all his fortunes. At last, driven by various fortunes, he quitted Etruria with the remains of the army which had served under Caeles, went to Rome, and occupied the Caelian hill, giving it that name after his former commander. He exchanged his Tuscan name, Mastarna, for a Roman one, obtained the kingly power, and employed it to the great advantage of the state.” See Niebuhr, vol. t. p. 381.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>