<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tyrant. He felt he had no friend ; he knew he could not be loved ; he was content to be hated, provided he were feared. At length, feeling the approach of death, he named as his successor Caius Caligula, the only surviving son of his murdered nephew Germanicus. Still, though consciously dying, the consummate dissembler strove to deceive not only his courtiers, but even his physicians. Pretending to feel a restoration of health and strength, he made a sumptuous feast, and continued at table, as if in the height of enjoyment, till he was seized with a fainting fit which threatened to be mortal. His courtiers forsook him in haste to flock to Caligula; but Tiberius reviving, they became alarmed lest he should recover, and Macro, the captain of the guard, smothered the helpless wretch, whose fate was thus hastened by the recoil of his own deceit and cruelty.</p><p>Caius Cæsar Caligula (so surnamed from the common military buskins, <hi rend="italic">caligœ,</hi>  which he was accustomed to wear), was joyously welcomed to the throne by both the senate and the people, on account of the deep love and regard still cherished for the memory of his father Germanicus. His first acts served to confirm the hopes which had been entertained of him. He liberated all the state prisoners, and drove from the court and senate all the spies and informers whom Tiberius had employed. His voyage to the islands of Pandataria and Pontia in the midst of tempestuous weather, to remove the ashes of his mother and brothers, seemed also an amiable proof of a sincere filial and fraternal piety. He restored some of the most equitable of the decrees of Augustus, which Tiberius had repealed, and gave other proofs of his intention to act in all respects for the promotion of the public welfare. But these hopeful symptoms were doomed to suffer an early and a fatal blight. He had been only about eight months on the throne when he was seized with a severe and dangerous illness, from which he recovered, so far as bodily health was concerned ; but his mental sanity appears to have sustained an irremediable shock.</p><p>From that time forward, animal passions of the fiercest kind domineered over him uncontrolled, or, if not animal passions merely, with no more of intellect than was enough to render them fearfully malevolent. To enumerate his crimes would be too hideously revolting, so utterly and excessively unnatural were· the murders, the incests, and the brutalities in which this insane, or demon-possessed monster revelled. Murder was his daily amusement; and he took a fiendish delight in witnessing the dying pangs of his victims, whose sufferings he strove to protract, that they might, as he said, “ feel themselves dying.” He assumed divine honours, erected a temple to himself, and instituted a college of priests, to superintend the worship of the new god. He likewise deified one of his sisters ; and on her death, it was equally dangerous to rejoice in her divinity, and to mourn for her death. It was customary for him to invite his favourite horse to sup with him ; and he was only prevented by death from raising the animal to the dignity of consul. His prodigality was equally extravagant with his other crimes. In one year he expended the almost boundless wealth which had been accumulated by Tiberius, in shows of the most lavish and wasteful kind. One of these was a vast bridge of vessels at Puteoli, across an arm of the sea, three miles and a half broad, and so formed as to resemble a street at Rome. A feverish dream of military glory next seized his distempered brain ; and he made great preparations for an expedition against the Germans. Like all his undertakings, it ended in consummate folly. Instead of conquering Germany, he led his army to the sea-shore at Boulogne in France, drew out his troops in order of battle, then causing them to fill their helmets with shells, which he termed the spoils of the ocean, he returned to Rome, and demanded from the senate the honours of a triumph for his warlike exploits.</p><p>Rome at length grew sick of enduring the frantic guilt and reckless tyranny of Caligula. A conspiracy was formed against him, and he was assassinated by Cassius Chærea and Cornelius Sabinus, two officers of the prætorian guards. His body was allowed to lie for some time exposed to public contumely, but was finally thrown into a grave, without any marks of honour or respect. His wife and infant child were also slain by the conspirators, who thought thus to secure themselves against the danger of future punishment.'</p><p>Upon the death of Caligula, the senate began to cherish hopcs of altogether abolishing the imperial power, and restoring, if not a republican, at least an aristocratic form of government. But the populace had too long enjoyed the donations of grain, and the amusements of the amphitheatre, supplied to them by dictators and emperors, to be disposed to favour a restoration of power to the senate. And the prætorian cohorts, stationed on the Quirinal hill, were too well aware that the continuation of their power depended upon the continuation of a monarchy, to be willing to tolerate any such revolution. Numbers of the conspirators, or those who were suspected to be such, were slain by the excited populace and tlle soldiers ; and when the soldiers accidentally discovered Tiberius Claudius, brother of Germanicus, and uncle of the late emperor, they dragged him from his hiding place, and resolved to raise him to the vacant throne. The senate found it impossible to resist ; and thus a person who had hitherto passed his life in unregarded obscurity, despised on account of his mental imbecility, was placed at the head of the empire. Thus raised to the throne by the power of the prætorian guards, Claudius set the pernicious custom of rewarding their deed by granting them a donative. This weak man was governed, as usually happens, by worthless favourites, and abandoned women. The infamous conduct of the empress Messalina has rendered her name proverbial ; and her cruelty and rapacity were as unbounded as her licentiousness. At her instigation, it was but too common for the emperor to put to death some of the most wealthy of the nobles, and to confiscate their estates, with the money arising from which she pampered her numerous paramours. To such a pitch of unblushing effrontery did this abandoned woman proceed, that she at length openly married Silius, a noble youth, one of the partners of her crimes, purposing to complete her guilt by the murder of the emperor ; but Claudius having received private information, gave orders for her death, and she was slain in the gardens which she had so long polluted by her unequalled criminality.</p><p>Messalina had accompanied Claudius in an expedition to Britain, and given birth to a son named Britannicus, whom he exhibited to the army as his destined successor in the empire. This expedition was occasioned by the previous success of one led by the prætor Aulus Plautius, and by Vespasian, who, after a succession of severe battles, subdued all the country south of the Thames. After the emperor’s return to Rome, Ostorius Scapula continued to conduct the war in Britain with great vigour and success, extended the province to the banks of the Severn, and finally succeeded in taking prisoner the celebrated Caractacus, or Ca-radoc, who had so long withstood the power of Rome. The native grandeur of soul displayed by this comparatively rude hero, excited in the mind of Claudius so much admiration, that he ordered his fetters to be struck off, and treated him with the most marked distinction.</p><p>The fall of Messalina was brought about in a great measure through the intervention of Narcissus, the emperor’s freedman, who, alongwith Pallas, another manumitted slave, engrossed the chief favour of the weak-minded sovereign of Rome. The power wielded by this race of men, was a new feature in the degeneracy of the imperial court, but</p></body></text></TEI>