<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Sceleratus,</hi>  between the forum and the Esquiline, was the scene of his daughter’s horrible impiety, when she caused her chariot wheel to pass over the body of her father.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>Before the Augustan age, the Esquiline mount was inhabited by the meanest of the Roman people ; and in that part of it which was without the wall their unburied bodies were promiscuously deposited.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Maecenas having received a present of the ground from Augustus, covered it with gardens and groves, and erected on its summit a palace.@@<hi rend="sup">3 </hi>On this mount Julius Cæsar was bom. Here also was the house of the younger Pliny, part of Nero’s golden house, and the palace and baths of the emperor Titus. Here Virgil also is said to have had a house, near the palace of his patron Mæcenas. It is stated by Suetonius, that Horace was buried near the tomb of Mæcenas, at the extremity of the hill.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> The Esquiline mount has two summits, the Cis-pius, on which stands the basilica of Santa Mari Maggiore, and which was supposed to have been anciently occupied with the temple of Juno Lucina ; and the Oppius, crowned with the church of St. Pietro in Vincula, built upon a part of the extensive baths of Titus. Toward the extremity of the Esquiline, and not far from the Porta Maggiore, in a vineyard, stands a ruined edifice called the temple of Minerva Medica. Nothing now remains but the walls and part of the vaulted roof. Many beautiful statues have been found in the grounds that border it.</p><p>The Viminal hill, which probably derived its name from the osiers <hi rend="italic">(vimines)</hi>  that grew upon it,@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  lies between the Esquiline and the Quirinal, but the fall of the ruins from these hills has rendered it almost impossible to recognize it. The only conspicuous object upon it is the church of S. Lorenzo in Pane Perna, with its adjoining buildings and vineyards. Near the Viminal hill stood the celebrated prætorian camp, which forms such a distinguished object in the decline of the Roman empire.</p><p>The Quirinal hill was adorned in ancient times with the famous temple of Romulus Quirinus. On the opposite side, the magnificent temple of the Sun, built by Aurelian, is supposed to have stood. The Quirinal is the only one of the seven hills that is populous. It is covered with palaces, churches, streets, and fountains. But the only remains of antiquity that it can now boast, are the vestiges of the baths of Constantine, in that part of the Colonna gardens which overlooks the Piazza Pilotta, and a considerable part of the baths of Diocletian, one of the grandest remains of ancient splendour.</p><p>The site of the Roman Forum is between the Palatine and Capitoline hills. Its present surface is from fifteen to twenty feet above its ancient level, and various excavations are now making in it in the hope of discovering some relics of antiquity. “ Here were held the comitia, or assemblies of the people ; here stood the rostra from which the orators harangued them; the curia, or senate-house; the basilica, or courts of justice; the public tribunals, the statues and memorials of great men, and some of the most sacred temples of religion.” After the destruction of the republic, another forum was built by Julius Cæsar; and his example was followed by Augustus, Nerva, Domitian, Trajan, Vespasian, and Antoninus Pius. The only remains of antiquity that now stand within the limits of the Roman forum are those commonly designated as the triumphal arch of Septimius Severus, the temple of Jupiter Tonans, the temple of Fortune, and the temple of Concord, and the solitary column dedicated by the Greek Exarch, Smaragdus, Ito the emperor Phocas, the ruined wall of the curia, and the three</p><p>beautiful columns near the base of the Palatine hill, generally called “ the disputed columns.” Of the immense number of other buildings of all kinds, temples, basilicas, columns, statues, which once stood here, not a vestige now remains, and their very situations are a matter of bitter dispute. At the north-east corner of the Forum is the church of Santa Martina and St. Luke, which is supposed, with some probability, to occupy the site of the beautiful temple of Mars the Avenger, erected by Augustus. Near it is the church of St. Adrian, called <hi rend="italic">in tribus foris, </hi>from the Roman forum, and the forums of Julius Cæsar and Augustus, of which it forms thc connecting point. Behind these are three fluted Corinthian columns, and one pilaster of Parian marble, of the grandest and most perfect style of architecture, supposed to be the remains of thc forum of Nerva. To the eastward, and at the base of the Quirinal hill, is the forum of Trajan, the centre of which has been excavated, down to the level of the ancient pavement, by the F rench. Here stood the famous equestrian statue of Trajan, which excited the admiration and envy of Constantine,@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi>  and many other honorary statues of distinguished individuals ; and here still stands the triumphal column of Trajan, the finest in the world. This superh pillar is of the finest white marble, about 128 feet in height, and is covered with sculptured figures representing the wars and triumphs of the emperor Trajan. The ascent to the summit is by a winding staircase of 185 steps of solid Parian marble. A little to the north is the triumphal column of Marcus Aurelius, formed of the same materials and workmanship, though inferior in the beauty and perfection of its sculpture to that of Trajan. These columns formerly supported each a colossal statue of Trajan and Marcus Aurelius, but they have long since disappeared, while bronze statues of the apostles Peter and Paul have been substituted in their stead. In a deserted spot, which was once the forum boarium, or cattle-market of Rome, there is a magnificent four-fronted arch, commonly called Janus quadrifrons, which is the only one now remaining of the many ancient Jani of ancient Rome. It is built of immense blocks of Grecian marble, now so darkened and discoloured by time, and covered with bushes and ivy, that it has a peculiarly picturesque and venerable appearance. Near this arch, by passing under some low brick vaults opposite the church of S. Giorgio in Velabro, the best view is obtained of the celebrated “ Cloaca Maxima," unquestionably the most ancient of all the ruins of Rome, and the only remains of the work of her kings. This stupendous and useful work was executed by Tarquinius Superbus.@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi>  In ancient times the arches were so large, that it is stated by Strabo and Pliny, that a waggon load of hay might pass through them.@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi>  Though greatly choked up by the elevation of the soil of modern Rome, it still, after a lapse of 3000 years, serves as the common sewer of the city. Almost close to the cloaca maxima is the far-famed fountain of Juturna.@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi></p><p>Proceeding along the Via Sacra, we come to some ruins which are supposed to be the remains of Vespasian’s temple of Peace, built at the close of the Jewish war. It was one of the most magnificent temples of antiquity, and within it were deposited the spoils taken from the temple of Jerusalem. Others maintain, however, that these ruins belonged to the basilica of Constantine. Crossing to the opposite side, and passing under the broken and defaced triumphal arch of Titus, we behold the majestic ruins of the mighty Coliseum. This stupendous building was erected by Vespasian and Titus, on the spot which had previously</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Liv. lib. i. cap. 48.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">  Vide</hi>  Horace, Sat. lib. i. viii. 7, 17 ; Juvenal, &amp;c.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> Hor. Carm. iii. 29.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Suet, in vita Horat.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> “Viminalis a Jove Viminis quod ibi aræ aunt ejus, aut quod ibi vimineta fuerunt.” Varro de Ling. Lat. lib. iv. ; Juvenal, Sat. lib.</p><p>iii. 71.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Arnmian Marcel. Hist. lib. xvi.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> Livy, lib. i. cap. 56.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi> Strabo, Geograph, lib. v. ; Plin. Hist. Nat. lib. xxxv. cap. 15.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi><hi rend="italic">  Vide</hi>  Æn. lib. xii 878.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>