<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>decree for his dethronement and death, which was almost instantly executed, thus depriving Didius of the enjoyment of his ill-purchased honours in the short space of two months.</p><p>Severus began his reign by accomplishing what Pertinax was murdered for attempting. He disarmed and disbanded the prætorian guards, and banished them to a distance of one hundred miles from Rome, death being the penalty of a nearer approach. The murderers of Pertinax were executed without mercy, and some degree of order and subordination restored. But Severus, accustomed to military sway, knew no other method of maintaining his authority except by force of arms. Though he punished the late prætorian guards, he replaced them with a chosen body of his own troops greatly more numerous ; not reflecting that the enjoyment of similar leisure, and the possession of similar favour, would soon render them equally licentious and turbulent.</p><p>Having thus seized the sceptre, it was necessary to defend it against those rivals who were eager to wrench it from his grasp. As he was most apprehensive of danger from Pescennius Niger, he wrote deceptive letters to Clodius Albinus, styling him Cæsar, and thus lulling him to inaction. He then marched against Niger, whom, after several contests, he finally defeated in a great battle near the Issus. Niger was soon afterwards slain ; and Severus put to death, without remorse, all «horn he suspected of being favourable to the cause of his competitor. He next attempted to compass the death of Albinus by assassination ; but the plot being detected, Albinus prepared to defend himself by dethroning his enemy. Severus hastened towards Britain, and Albinus crossed from thence to Gaul. The two rivals met near Lyons; and a very bloody battle was fought between two disciplined and numerous Roman armies, which ended in Severus gaining a complete victory. When he saw that his hopes were destroyed, Albinus fell by his own hand ; and Severus, after insulting the dead body of his antagonist, again displayed the innate ferocity of his heart, by murdering in cold blood all his friends and adherents. A second Parthian war demanded the presence of Severus in the East, where he was again victorious, and where his exploits almost rivalled those of Trajan.</p><p>The avarice and insolence of Plautianus, commander of the prætorian guard, produced great oppression and suffering, till he was killed by Caracalla, the son of Severus, in the very presence of the emperor. Severus next turned his attention to Britain, where the Romans had been losing ground, partly in consequence of Albinus having withdrawn a great portion of the army in his attempt to elevate himself to the throne. The emperor being at the head of a very powerful army speedily drove back the independent natives of Caledonia, and regained the country south of the wall of Antoninus, but lost so many troops in the successive battles which he was obliged to fight, that he did not think proper to push his conquests beyond that boundary. Feeling at length his end approaching, he retired to Eboracum (York), where he appointed his two sons, Caracalla and Geta, to succeed him and reign conjointly, and soon afterwards expired, in the eighteenth year of his reign.</p><p>The two brothers, Caracalla and Geta, had scarcely begun their reign, when they also began their dissensions. After their return to Rome, the utter impossibility of any permanent reconciliation taking place between them, led to a proposal by mutual friends that they should divide the empire. To this neither would agree ; and soon afterwards Geta was murdered in the arms of his mother by the hand of the furious and savage Caracalla.</p><p>Having now obtained the undivided possession of a throne stained with the blood of his brother, he prosecuted his murderous course, exhibiting the tiger-like propensities of his savage nature, by destroying almost indiscriminately men</p><lb/><p>and women, young and old, wealthy and humble. He lavished presents, treasures, and amusements among the soldiery with an unsparing hand, trusting by their means to maintain his power, and setting at defiance the hatred of senate and people. He traversed the provinces along the Danube, partly in a hostile, partly in a friendly manner; thence passed into Asia, where, by treachery, he obtained some advantages over the Parthians ; thence to Egypt, where, being enraged against the Alexandrians, who had ridiculed his pretensions to be regarded as another Alexander, he almost depopulated the city by a dreadful massacre. Vengeance at length overtook the sanguinary tyrant; and he w as murdered by the orders of Macrinus commander of the prætorian guards.</p><p>Marcus Opelius Macrinus was next placed at the head of the empire, by the soldiers, who were not aware that he had been accessory to the death of Caracalla. The new emperor was soon engaged in a war against the Parthians, where he gained no laurels, being obliged to purchase peace on terms highly disadvantageous to Rome. Some attempts which he made to restrain the extreme licentiousness of the soldiery excited a spirit of disaffection, of which Maesa, maternal aunt of the late emperor, availed herself to procure the empire to her grandson, a youth of fourteen, said tc be the son of Caracalla, and a priest in the temple of the Sun at Emesa in Syria. This youth, named Heliogabalus, was proclaimed emperor by the legionary forces, on account of their attachment to the memory of his reputed father, Caracalla. Macrinus was defeated in an attempt to crush this rebellion, and fell while endeavouring to escape by flight. His son, Diadumenus, whom he had associated in the empire, shared his fate.</p><p>Heliogabalus, thus raised to the throne, repaired to Rome, and began a course of licentiousness unparalleled in the annals of depravity. He was, in short, the most infamous wretch that ever disgraced a throne ; his very existence seemed a stain upon human nature. To form some check to his shameless conduct, his grandmother caused him to assume his cousin, Alexander Severus, as his partner in the empire ; but the abandoned and brutal boy attempted to procure his assassination, an attempt which soon proved fatal to himself. The prætorian guards, disgusted with the effeminate, licentious, and cruel tyrant, mutinied, and discovering him in a loathsome hiding place, a cloaca, dragged him through the streets, put him to death in the most ignominious manner, and threw his body into the river, loaded with weights, that it might not be found and buried.</p><p>The new emperor, Alexander Severus, was of a character diametrically opposite to that of his predecessor. Among the first acts of his sovereignty, he banished all the guilty and abandoned creatures of Heliogabalus, restored the authority of the senate, and chose his counsellors and ministers of state of the best members of that body, and revoked all the persecuting edicts that had been issued by his predecessor against the Christians. This just and merciful procedure is thought to have been adopted by the advice ofhis mother, Mammæa, who maintained an intercourse with some of the most distinguished Christians, among others the celebrated Origen, and who was perhaps herself a convert. She was unquestionably a woman of great virtue, wisdom, and amiability of character ; and as Alexander paid the utmost deference to her opinions and wishes, to her may be ascribed much of what was meritorious in the conduct of this young and excellent monarch.</p><p>But however desirous of peace, that he might prosecute his schemes of reform, Alexander was soon called to encounter the perils and toils of war. A revolution in the east, which began in the fourth year of his reign, was productive of consequences deeply important to all Asia. Ar-deshir Babegan, or Artaxerxes, who pretended to be descended from the imperial race of ancient Persia, raised a</p></body></text></TEI>