<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>quaintance with Dr Robertson, Mr Hume, and other literary characters.</p><p>Having completed his medical course at Edinburgh, he afterwards spent some time at the university of Leyden, where in 1743 he took the degree of M. D. He began to practise as a physician at Birmingham, a place which was then making rapid progress in arts, manufactures, and population, and where a favourable opening was presented to him by the death of an aged physician.</p><p>The extensive use of sulphuric acid in chemistry led many to various methods of obtaining it; and Dr Roebuck attempted to prepare it in such a manner as to reduce the price, for which purpose he substituted leaden vessels in the room of glass ; and he had the good fortune to effect his benevolent design. Of this useful article he established a manufactory at Prestonpans in the year 1749, which was opposed by Dr Ward, but without success, as Roebuck’s discovery did not come within Ward’s patent? Dr Roebuck and his partner retained the advantages of their industry and ingenuity for a number of years, supplying the public with sulphuric acid at a much cheaper rate than had been formerly done. He found it expedient to relinquish his medical profession, and he resided in Scotland during the greater part of the year. He made some discoveries in the smelting of ironstone, greatly facilitating that process by using pit-coal instead of charcoal. He and his partner therefore projected a very extensive manufactory of iron, for which they soon procured a sufficient capital, as their friends had much confidence in their integrity and abilities. Dr Roebuck at length made choice of a spot on the banks of the river Carron, as the most advantageous situation for the establishment of their manufactory, abundance of ironstone, limestone, and coal, being found in its immediate vicinity. The preparations for this establishment were finished in the end of the year 1759; the first furnace was blown on the 1st of January 1760 ; and a second was soon afterwards erected.</p><p>These works turned the attention of Dr Roebuck to the state of coal in the neighbourhood, and to the means of procuring the extraordinary supplies which the iron-works might require. He therefore became lessee of the extensive coal and salt works at Borrowstownness, the property of the duke of Hamilton ; in which he sunk, in the course of a few years, not only his own, and a considerable part of his wife’s fortune, but the regular profits of his more successful works ; and, what distressed him above every thing else, the great sums of money which he borrowed from his relations and friends, without the prospect of ever being able to repay them. This ruinous adventure cut off for ever the flattering prospects of an independent fortune which his family had once cherished ; and he drew from his colliery only a moderate annual support, for which he was indebted to the indulgence of his creditors. Some years before his death, he was seized with a disorder that required a dangerous operation, and this he bore with’ his usual spirit and resolution. He was restored to a considerable share of his wonted health and activity ; but its effects never wholly left him. He visited his works till within a few weeks of his decease, in order to give instructions to his clerks and overseers, and was confined to bed only a few days. He departed this life on the 17th of July 1794, retaining all his faculties, spirit, and good humour, to the last.</p><p>ROEMER, Olaus, a celebrated Danish mathematician and astronomer, was born at Arhusen in Jutland, in the year 1644, and was sent to the university of Copenhagen at the age of eighteen. By his assiduous application to the study of astronomy and mathematics, he became so eminent in those sciences, that Picard was astonished and delighted with him, when making observations in the north, by the order of Louis XIV. He was prevailed on to accompany Picard to France, and being presented to the king, he was chosen the dauphin’s tutor in the study of mathematics. He was afterwards united with Picard and Cassini in making astronomical observations, and became a member of the Academy of Sciences in 1672. His discoveries acquired him great reputation during his ten years’ residence at Paris ; and he did not scruple to assert, that Picard and Cassini took the merit of many things which belonged exclusively to himself. Roemer was the first person who discovered the velocity with which light moves, by means of the eclipses of Jupiter’s satellites, determining it to be about seven or eight minutes in coming from the sun to the earth. This opinion was opposed by many, but it was afterwards demonstrated in a most ingenious manner by Dr Bradley.</p><p>Christian V. king of Denmark, recalled Roemer to his native country in the year 1681, when he was appointed professor of astronomy at Copenhagen. He was also employed in the reformation of the coin and architecture of the country, in regulating the weights and measures, and in laying out the high roads throughout the kingdom ; and his conduct was truly creditable to himself, and gave the greatest satisfaction to his royal employer. The consequence was that the king bestowed many dignities upon him, and among· others appointed him chancellor of the exchequer. In fine, he was made councillor of state and burgomaster of Copenhagen under Frederic IV. who succeeded the king already mentioned. While Roemer was engaged in preparing to publish the result of his observations, he was cut off on the 19th of September 1710, when about sixty-six years of age. Horrebow, his disciple, made up this loss, by publishing in 4to, in 1753, when professor of astronomy at Copenhagen, various observations of Roemer, with his method of observing, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Basis Astronomia.</hi>  He had printed various astronomical observations and pieces in several volumes of the Memoirs of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris.</p><p>ROERMOND, or Ruremonde, one of the circles into which the province of Limburg is divided. It contains six cantons. The capital is the city of the same name, which stands on the left bank of the Maas, where the river Roer falls into it. It is fortified, but not strongly, and contains 4480 inhabitants, who make woollen cloths and carry on trade by the river. Long. 5. 53.54. E. Lat. 51. 11. 48. N.</p><p>ROGA, in <hi rend="italic">Antiquity,</hi>  a present which the emperors made to the senators, magistrates, and even to the people ; and the popes and patriarchs to their clergy. These rogæ were distributed by the emperors on the first day of the year, on their birthday, or on the <hi rend="italic">natalis dies</hi>  of the cities ; and by the popes and patriarchs in passion-week. Roga is also used for the common pay of tbe soldiers.</p><p>ROGATION, Rogatio, in Roman jurisprudence, a demand made by the consuls or tribunes of the Roman people, when a law was proposed to be passed. <hi rend="italic">Rogαtio</hi>  is also used for the decree itself made in consequence of the people’s giving their assent to this demand ; to distinguish it from a <hi rend="italic">senatus consultum,</hi>  or decree of the senate.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Rogation- Week,</hi></hi>  the week immediately succeeding Whitsunday ; so called from the three feasts therein, viz. on Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday.</p><p>ROGER de Hoveden, a learned man of the thirteenth century, was bom in Yorkshire, most probably at the town of that name, now called <hi rend="italic">Howden,</hi>  some time in the reign of Henry I. After he had received the first parts of education in his native country, he studied the civil and canon laws, which were then become the most fashionable and lucrative branches of education. He was appointed domestic chaplain to Henry II. who employed him to transact several ecclesiastical affairs, in which he acquitted himself with honour. But his most meritorious work was, his Annals of England from a. d. 731, when Bede’s Ecclesiastical History</p></body></text></TEI>