<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>sure by the expense of water in a given time. We judge the velocity to diminish when the quantity discharged diminishes ; yet it may be otherwise, and probably is otherwise. The absolute velocity of many, if not all, of the particles, may even be increased ; but many of the motions being transverse to the general direction, the quantity of motion in this direction may be less, while the sum of the absolute motions of all the particles may be greater. When we increase the general velocity, it is not unreasonable to suppose that the impulses on all the inequalities are increased in this proportion ; and the number of particles thus impelling and deflected at the same time will increase in the same proportion. The whole quantity, therefore, of these useless and lost motions will increase in the duplicate ratio of the velocities, and the force necessary for keeping up the motion will do so also ; that is, the resistances should increase as the squares of the velocities.</p><p>Or if we consider the resistances as arising merely from the curvature of the imperceptible internal motions occasioned by the inequalities of the sides of the pipe, and as measured by the forces necessary for producing these cur-vilineal motions ; then, because the curves will be the same whatever are the velocities, the deflecting forces will be as the squares of the velocities ; but these deflecting forces are pressures, propagated from the parts urged or pressed by the external force, and are proportional to these external pressures by the principles of hydrostatics. Therefore the pressures or forces necessary for keeping up the velocities are as the squares of these velocities ; and they are our only measures of the resistances which must be considered as following the same ratio. Whatever view therefore we take of the nature of these resistances, we are led to consider them as proportional to the squares of the velocities.</p><p>We may therefore express the resistances by the symbol V<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">—, m</hi>  being some number to be discovered by experiment.</p><p>Thus, in a particular pipe, the diminution of the motion or the resistance may be the 1000th part of the square of the</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">s</hi></p><p>velocity, and R = yθθθ∙</p><p>Now if <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  be the accelerating power of gravity on any particle, '- will be its accelerating power by which it would</p><p>urge it down the pipe whose slope is 'i. Therefore, by</p><p>the principle of uniform motion, the equality of the accele-V- <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p><p>rating force, and the resistance, we shall have — = —, and <hi rend="italic">m s</hi></p><p>V V<hi rend="sup">z</hi>s =<hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">fmg ;</hi>  that is, the product of the velocity, and the reciprocal of the square root of the slope, or the quotient of the velocity divided by the square root of the slope, is a constant quantity <hi rend="italic">Vmg</hi>  for any given pipe ; and the primary formula for all the uniform velocities of one pipe is</p><p>v = <hi rend="underline">*<hi rend="sup">z </hi></hi>n'y √s</p><p>Du Buat therefore examined this by experiment, but found, that even with respect to a pipe or channel which was uniform throughout, this was not true. We could give at once the final formula which he found to express the velocity in every case whatever ; but this would be too empirical. The chief steps of his very sagacious investigation are instructive. We shall therefore mention them briefly, at least as far as they tend to give us any collateral information ; and let it always be noted, that the instruction which they convey is not abstract speculation, but experimental truths, which must ever remain as an addition to our stock of knowledge, although Du Buat’s deductions from them should prove false.</p><p>He found, in the first place, that in the same channel the product of V and <hi rend="italic">∙fs</hi>  increased as <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">fs</hi>  increased ; that is, the velocities increased faster than the square roots of the slope, or the resistances did not increase as fast as the squares of the velocities. We beg leave to refer our readers to what we said on the resistance of pipes to the motion of fluids through them, in the article Pneumatics, when speaking of bellows. They will there see very valid reasons, we apprehend, for thinking that the resistances must increase more slowly than the squares of the velocities.</p><p>It being found, then, that V <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">Ps</hi>  is not equal to a constant quantity <hi rend="italic">Vmg,</hi>  it becomes necessary to investigate some quantity depending on √<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  or, as it is called, some function of <hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  which shall render v<hi rend="sup">z</hi><hi rend="italic">mg</hi>  a constant quantity. Let X be this function of V<hi rend="sup">z</hi>s, so that we shall alw<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ays have VX equal to the constant quantity<hi rend="italic">Vmg,</hi>  or —,”<hi rend="sup">1</hi>·— equal to the</p><p>actual velocity V of a pipe or channel which is in train.</p><p>Du Bunt, after many trials and reflections, the chief of which will be mentioned by and by, found a value of X which corresponded with a vast variety of slopes and velocities, from motions almost imperceptible, in a bed nearly horizontal, to the greatest velocities which could be produced by gravity alone in a vertical pipe ; and when he compared them together, he found a very discernible relation between the resistances and the magnitude of the section ; that is, that in two channels which had the same slope, and the same propelling force, the velocity was greatest in the channel which had the greatest section relative to its border. This may reasonably be expected. The resistances arise from the mutual action of the water and this border. The water immediately contiguous to it is retarded, and this retards the next, and so on. It is to be expected, therefore, that if the border, and the velocity, and the slope, be the same, the diminution of this velocity will be so much the less as it is to be shared among a greater number of particles ; that is, as the area of the section is greater in proportion to the extent of its border. The diminution of the general or medium velocity must be less in a cylindrical pipe than in a square one of the same area, because the border of the section is less.</p><p>It appears evident, that the resistance of each particle is in the direct proportion of the whole resistance, and the inverse proportion of the number of particles which receive equal shares of it. It is therefore directly as the border, and inversely as the section. Therefore, in the expression V<hi rend="sup">!</hi></p><p>— which we have given for the resistance, the quantity <hi rend="italic">m</hi></p><p>cannot be constant, except in the same channel ; and in different channels it must vary along with the relation of the section to its border, because the resistances diminish in proportion as this relation increases.</p><p>Without attempting to discover this relation by theoretical examination of the particular motions of the various filaments, Du Buat endeavoured to discover it by a comparison of experiments. But this required some manner of stating this proportion between the augmentation of the section and the augmentation of its border.</p><p>His statement is this : he reduces every section to a rectangular parallelogram of the same area, and having its base equal to the border unfolded into a straight line. The product of this base by the height of the rectangle will be equal to the area of the section. Therefore this height will be a representative of this valuable ratio of the section to its border (we do not mean that there is any ratio between a surface and a line : but the ratio of section to section is different from that of border to border ; and it is the ratio of these ratios which is thus expressed by the height of this</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>