<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The writer of this article@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> verified the observation by a very simple and instructive experiment. He was making experiments on the production of vortices, in the manner suggested by Sir Isaac Newton, by whirling a very accurate and smoothly polished cylinder in water ; and he found that the rapid motion of the surrounding water was confined to an exceedingly small distance from the cylinder, and it was not till after many revolutions that it was sensible even at the distance of half an inch. We may, by the way, suggest this as the best form of experiments for examining the resistances of pipes. The motion excited by the whirling cylinder in the stagnant water is equal and opposite to the motion lost by water passing along a surface equal to that of the cylinder with the same velocity. Be this as it may, we are justified in considering, with Du Buat, the section of the stream as thus diminished by cutting off a narrow border all round the touching parts, and supposing that the motion and discharge is the same as if the square root of the mean depth of the section were diminished by a small quantity, nearly constant. We see, too, that the effect of this must be insensible in great canals and rivers ; so that, fortunately, its quantity is best ascertained by experiments made with small pipes. This is attended with another conveniency, in the opinion of Du Buat, namely, that the effect of viscidity is most sensible in great masses of water in slow motion, and is almost insensible in small pipes, so as not to disturb these experiments. We may therefore assume 297 as the</p><p>general value of —y—∙</p><p><hi rend="sup">fe</hi>    √&lt;Z-0∙1.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>Since we have —=    — = 297, we have also <hi rend="italic">m</hi></p><p>√tZ-0∙l</p><p>= !∣Z!(√a-0∙l)<hi rend="sup">s</hi>, =^^(√d — 0∙])<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, = 243∙7</p><p>(√tf—0∙l)<hi rend="sup">i</hi>. This we may express by<hi rend="italic">n (fld—</hi>0∙l)<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. And thus, when we have expressed the quantity of friction</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">a</hi></p><p>by —, the quantity <hi rend="italic">m</hi>  is variable, and its general value is V<hi rend="sup">a</hi></p><p>—-,-.^.-,∙.7∣<hi rend="sup">1n</hi>  which<hi rend="italic">n</hi>  is an invariable abstract number</p><p>w(√ι∕— 0∙1)*</p><p>equal to 243∙7, given by the nature of the resistance which water sustains from its bed, and which indicates its intensity.</p><p>And, lastly, since <hi rend="italic">m = n{fld—</hi>0∙l)<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, we have<hi rend="italic">Vmg</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">= Vng (fld —</hi>  0∙1), and the expression of the velocity V, which water acquires and maintains along any channel whatever, now becomes V = ⅜(√⅛ <hi rend="sub">θr</hi><hi rend="underline">297(√rf-0∙I)</hi></p><p>in which X is also a variable quantity, depending on the slope of the surface or channel, and expressing the accelerating force which, in the case of water in train, is in equilibrio with the resistances expressed by the numerator of the fraction.</p><p>Having so happily succeeded in ascertaining the variations of resistance, let us accompany Du Buat in his investigation of the law of acceleration, expressed by the value of X.</p><p>Experience, in perfect agreement with any distinct opinions that we can form on this subject, had already shown him that the resistances increased in a slower ratio than that of the squares of the velocities, or that the velocities increased slower than √ <hi rend="italic">s.</hi>  Therefore, in the formula</p><p>√zγ∕(√rf—0∙1)</p><p>V = ——,-, which, for one channel, we may ex-</p><p>A</p><p>press thus, V = we must admit that X is sensibly equal -</p><p>to √∙s when the slope is very small or s very great. But, that we may accurately express the velocity in proportion as the slope augments, we must have X less than <hi rend="italic">Vs ;</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">S    ∕~~</hi></p><p>and, moreover, =- must increase as <hi rend="italic">y s</hi>  diminishes. These</p><p>Λ.</p><p>conditions are necessary that our values of V, deduced from A</p><p>the formula V = =, may agree with the experiment.</p><p>Λ.</p><p>In order to comprehend every degree of slope, we must particularly attend to the motion through pipes, because open canals will not furnish us with instances of exact trains with great slopes and velocities. We can make pipes vertical. In this case - is p and the velocity is the</p><p>greatest possible for a train by the action of gravity : but we can give greater velocities than this by increasing the head of water beyond what produces the velocity of the train.</p><p>Let AB (fig. 10) be a vertical tube, and let CA be the head competent to the velocity in the tube, which we suppose to be in train. The slope is 1, and the full weight of the column in motion is the precise</p><p>measure of the resistance. The value of-, con-<hi rend="italic">s</hi></p><p>sidered as a slope, is now a maximum ; but, con</p><p>sidered as expressing the proportion of the weight</p><p>of the column in motion to the weight which is</p><p>in equilibrio with the resistance, it may not be a</p><p>maximum ; it may surpass unity, and s may be</p><p>less than 1. For if the vessel be filled to E, the</p><p>head of water is increased, and will produce a</p><p>greater velocity, and this will produce a greater</p><p>resistance. The velocity being now greater, the</p><p>head EF which imparts it must be greater than</p><p>CA. But it will not be equal to EA, because the uniform velocities <hi rend="italic">are found</hi>  to increase faster than the square roots of the pressures. This is the general fact. Therefore F is above A, and the weight of the column FB, now employed to overcome the resistance, is greater than the weight of the column AB in motion. In such cases, therefore, -,</p><p>greater than unity, is a sort of fictitious slope, and only represents the proportion of the resistance to the weight of the moving column. This proportion may surpass unity.</p><p>But it cannot be infinite : for, supposing the head of water infinite, if this produce a finite velocity, and we deduct from the whole height the height corresponding to this finite velocity, there will remain an infinite head, the measure of an infinite resistance produced by a finite velocity. This does not accord with the observed law of the velocities, where the resistances actually do not increase as fast as the squares of the velocities. Therefore an infinite head would have produced an infinite velocity, in opposition to the resistances : taking off the head of the tube, competent to this velocity, at the entry of the tube, which head would also be infinite, the remainder would in all probability be finite, balancing a finite resistance.</p><p>Therefore the value of s may remain finite, although the velocity be infinite ; and this is agreeable to all our clearest notions of the resistances.</p><p>Adopting this principle, we must find a value of X which will answer all these conditions. 2. It must be sensibly proportional to <hi rend="italic">Vs,</hi>  while <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  is great. It must always be less</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The late Professor Robison of Edinburgh.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> In this formula, and in the subsequent part’ of the investigation, French inches are employed. For English inches the constant number is 307.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>