<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>What has now been said of a horizontal pipe AB would have been equally true of any inclined pipe AB A'B (fig. 8). Drawing the horizontal line CB, we see that DC is the whole head or propelling pressure for either pipe AB or A'B ; and if DE is the head necessary for the actual velocity, EC is the head necessary for balancing the resistances ; and the pipe EF, of the same length with AB, and terminating in the same horizontal line, will have the same velocity : and its inclination being thus determined, it will have the same velocity and expense whatever be its length.</p><p>Thus we see that the motion in any pipe, horizontal or sloping, may be referred to or substituted for the motion in another inclined pipe, whose head of water, above the place of entry, is that productive of the actual velocity of the water in the pipe. Now, in this case, the accelerating force is equal to the resistance : we may therefore consider this last pipe as a river, of which the bed and the slope are uniform or constant, and the current in a state of permanency ; and we now may clearly draw this important conclusion, that pipes and open streams, when in a state of permanency, perfectly resemble each other in the circumstances which are the immediate causes of this permanency. The equilibrium between the accelerating force obtains not only in general, but takes place through the whole length of the pipe or stream, and is predicable of every individual transverse section of either. To make this more palpably evident, if possible, let us consider a sloping cylindrical pipe, the current of which is in a state of permanency. We can conceive it as consisting of two half cylinders, an upper and a lower. These are running together at an equal pace ; and the filaments of each immediately contiguous to the separating plane and to each other are not rubbing on each other, nor affecting each other’s motions in the smallest degree. It is true that the upper half is pressing on the lower, but in a direction perpendicular to the motion, and therefore not affecting the velocity ; and we shall see presently, that although the lower side of the pipe bears somewhat more pressure than the other, the resistances are not changed. Indeed this odds of pressure is accompanied with a difference of motion, which need not be considered at present ; and we may suppose the pipe so small or so far below the surface that this shall be insensible. Now let us suppose, that in an instant the upper half cylinder is annihilated : we then have an open stream ; and every circumstance of accelerating force and of resistance remains precisely as it was. The motion must therefore continue as it did ; and in this state the only accelerating force is the slope of the surface. The demonstration therefore is complete.</p><p>From these observations and reasonings we draw a general and important conclusion, “ that the same pipe will be susceptible of different velocities, which it will preserve uniform to any distance, according as it has different inclinations ; and each inclination of a pipe of given diameter has a certain velocity peculiar to itself, which will be maintained uniform to any distance whatever ; and this velocity increases continually, according to some law, to be discovered by theory or experiment, as the position of the pipe changes from being horizontal till it becomes vertical ; in which po-</p><p>sition it has the greatest uniform velocity possible relative to its inclination, or depending on inclination alone.”</p><p>Let this velocity be called the train, or tile rate, of each pipe.</p><p>It is evident that this principle is of the utmost consequence in the theory of hydraulics ; for by experiment we can find the train of any pipe. It is in train when an increase of length makes no change in the velocity. If lengthening the pipe increases the velocity, the slope of the pipe is too great, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa.</hi>  And having discovered the train of a pipe, and observed its velocity, and computed the head productive of this velocity with the contraction at the entry, the remainder of the head, that is, the slope (for this is equivalent to EA), is the measure of the resistance. Thus we obtain the measure of the resistance to the motion with a given velocity in a pipe of given diameter. If we change only the velocity, we get the measure of the new resistance relative to the velocity ; and thus discover the law of relation between the resistance and velocity. Then, changing only the diameter of the pipe, we get the measure of the resistance relative to the diameter. This is the aim of a prodigious number of experiments made and collected by Du Buat, and which we shall not repeat, but only give the results of the different parts of his investigation.</p><p>We may express the slope of a pipe by the symbol i, I</p><p>being an inch, for instance, and s being the slant length of a pipe which is one inch more elevated at one end than at the other. Thus a river which has a declivity of an inch and a half in 120 fathoms or 8640 inches, has its slope</p><p>l⅜ I</p><p>= 8640’ °<hi rend="sup">r</hi>5760'    <hi rend="sup">order t0 θ</hi>'<hi rend="sup">,ta</hi>'<hi rend="sup">n</hi>  ^<hi rend="sup">le</hi>  hydraulic</p><p>slope of a conduit-pipe, the height of the reservoir and place of discharge being given, we must subtract from the difference of elevation the height or head of water necessary for propelling the water into any pipe with the velocity V,</p><p>V*</p><p>which it is supposed actually to have. This is    The</p><p>remainder <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is to be considered as the height of the declivity, which is to be distributed cqually over the whole length <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  of the pipe, and the slope is then γ = ~∙</p><p>There is another important view to be taken of the slope, which the reader should make very familiar to his thoughts. It expresses the proportion between the weight of the whole column which is in motion and the weight which is employed in overcoming the resistance ; and the resistance to the motion of any column of water is equal to the weight of that column multiplied by the fraction -, which expresses its slope.</p><p>We now come to consider more particularly the resistances which in this manner bring the motion to a state of uniformity. If we consider the resistances which arise from a cause analogous to friction, we see that they must depend entirely on the inertia of the water. What we call the resistance is the diminution of a motion which <hi rend="italic">would</hi>  have, obtained but for these resistances ; and the best way we have of measuring them is by the force which we must employ in order to keep up or restore this motion. We estimate this motion by a progressive velocity, which we mea-</p><lb/><p>Lecchi, in his Hydraulics, published in 1766, ascribes something like it to Daniel Bernoulli ; but Bernoulli, in the passage quoted only speaks of the partition of pressure in the instant of opening an orifice. Part of it, says he, is employed in accelerating the quiescent water, and producing the velocity of efflux, and the remainder produces the pressure (now diminished) on the sides of the vessel. Bernoulli, Bossut, and all the good writers, make this distribution in express terms in their explanation of the motion of water through successive orifices ; and it is surprising that no one before the Chevalier du Buat saw that the resistance arising from friction required a similar partition of the pressure ; but though we should call this good fortune, we must ascribe to his great sagacity and justness of conception the beautiful use that he has made of it : <hi rend="italic">suum euique</hi>.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>