<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the same time, were jealous of the power of Philip. No sooner, therefore, did the Macedonian king manifest his disposition to form a confederacy with Hannibal against Rome, than the Roman ambassadors were able to excite against him such hostility among the neighbouring states of Greece, as to prevent the possibility of his making a descent on Italy to aid the terrible Carthaginian. This is a very striking instance of the deep policy of Rome ; by means of which she was always able to keep a powerful enemy in check till she might have leisure to collect her strength for a decisive effort.</p><p>Notwithstanding these disappointments, Hannibal continued to maintain his ground, repulsing the most daring assailants, and out-manoeuvring the most skilful. Marcellus, who had conquered Sicily, and again returned to Italy, and who was the most gallant opponent ever Hannibal met, was at last drawn into an ambush and slain. But still, without supplies, the Carthaginian army must melt away ; and Hannibal’s hopes of ultimate success now depended upon the army led by his brother Asdrubal reaching him safely from Spain. His hopes from Sicily, Macedonia, and Africa, had failed ; though it was doubtless to secure them that he had made Lower Italy the basis of his operations ; and he now waited eagerly the arrival of his brother. Asdrubal had in the mean time left Spain, crossed the Pyrenees, and the Alps, and entered Cisalpine Gaul, where he was joined by considerable numbers of tbe natives. A messenger, whom he sent to apprise Hannibal of his approach, was intercepted ; the consul Nero hastened to join bis colleague Livius, and assailing Asdrubal on the banks of the Metaurus in a disadvantageous position, they completely routed his whole army. Asdrubal himself was slain, and 56,000 of his army fell with him on the fatal field. The first tidings which Hannibal received of his brother’s defeat and death, was by the head of that luckless brother being thrown into his camp. From that time forward the contest was without hope on the part of the Carthaginians. The Roman consuls were not indeed able to cope with even an enfeebled army commanded by Hannibal ; but the youthful Scipio, having been sent to Spain, speedily overran it, and reduced the greater part of it to complete subjection, putting an end to Carthaginian power in that quarter. On bis return he obtained permission, against the opinion of Fabius, to transfer the war to Africa.</p><p>The invasion of Africa by Scipio, so alarmed the Cartha ginians, that they immediately recalled Hannibal from Italy for the defence of Cathage itself. To this command Hannibal most reluctantly submitted ; and quitted Italy with expressions of the utmost mortification and regret. In the mean while, Scipio had approached to the near vicinity of Carthage. The two armies met at Zama, to decide the fate of Rome and Carthage, and, with them, of the world. The battle was obstinate and bloody, but the Roman army was decidedly superior in numbers, and still more so in that high hope which so often determines the day; so that, in spite of the utmost exertion of his unrivalled military skill, Hannibal saw his army completely overthrown. Carthage had now no resource but in peace ; and she was compelled to submit to the terms dictated by Scipio. These terms were abundantly severe ; that the Carthaginians should retain in Africa only the territory annexed to their government ; that they should yield up all their elephants, and all their ships of war, except ten triremes ; that they shoιdd pay at specified times ten thousand talents of silver ; that they should commence no war without the consent of Rome ; and that they should restore all Numidia to Massinissa, and give an hundred hostages for the performance of the treaty. Thus ended the second Punic war, after having shaken Rome to her centre, and threatened for a time to change the destinies of western Europe, and, with that, the destinies of mankind; yet the result was exactly correspondent to the character and resources of the two great rival republics.</p><p>Rome had now removed her mighty rival from the strife of nations, and saw the sceptre of universal dominion but little removed beyond her own grasp. The Roman senate had fully entered upon that course of far-sighted policy, which enabled them to gratify and amuse the nation with foreign conquest, the wealth and powers of which they almost wholly engrossed. Such was its aspect and aim at home ; while with regard to foreign nations, the constant policy pursued was to grant assistance to the weaker states against the stronger, and by taking them under Roman protection, to have at all times the means of provoking a contest, whenever it seemed conducive to her interest. The character of Rome, as a great military republic, was now completely developed, as the overbearing friend or the jealous foe of overy other state.</p><p>The next field of Roman warfare was Macedon. Philip, the king of that country, ambitious of obtaining the sovereignty over Greece, made some aggressions on the Athenians. They complained to Rome, which soon led to a declaration of war against that monarch, and the sending of an army to carry hostilities into his dominions. The management of the war was entrusted to T. Quintus Flaminius, whose diplomatic skill was still more conspicuous than his military talents. After several inferior engagements, a great battle was fought at Cynoscephalæ, in which the Macedonians were completely routed, and Philip compelled to submit to such terms as the conqueror pleased to dictate. The chief of these were the reduction of his fleet, and his abandonment of all pretensions to the sovereignty of Greece, the various states of which were taken under the protection of Rome. At the conclusion of this war, the politic Roman, or rather the wily Italian, caused the liberty of Greece to be publicly proclaimed at the Isthmian games ; while the lavish expressions of gratitude uttered by the thoughtless crowds were the gilding of the chains by which they were securely fettered.</p><p>Rome still regarded Carthage with a jealous eye, and could not feel secure so long as the dreaded Hannibal influenced her councils, and might again lead her armies. Fearing that his dispirited countrymen would surrender him to his implacable enemies, that great man fled to the court of Antiochus, king of Syria. About the same time the Ætolians, being dissatisfied with the conduct ofthe Romans, besought tlle aid of Antiochus, who was already quite disposed to interfere in the affairs of Greece. He accordingly seized upon Euboea, and proceeded to take measures for additional aggressions on states which claimed the protection of Rome. War was immediately declared against him, and an army sent into Greece, under the command of the consul Glabrio, who defeated the Syrians at the pass of Ther-mopylæ. Next year Lucius Scipio, brother to the conqueror of Carthage, Africanus, was sent against Antiochus, accompanied by his brother as legate. They reduced Greece to subjection, and crossing into Asia, defeated Antiochus in a great battle at Magnesia. Antiochus purchased peace, by resigning all his possessions in Europe, and those in Asia north of Mount Taurus, paying 15,000 Eubœan talents, and promising to give up Hannibal. The latter vindictive article caused the flight of Hannibal to Prusias, king of Bithynia ; but being still pursued by the remorseless hatred of Rome, he put an end to his mortal existence by swallowing poison, which for such an emergency he always carried with him.</p><p>The war with Antiochus fairly introduced Rome to the beginning of her oriental sovereignty ; and the battle of Magnesia may be viewed as the event which terminated the Grecian or Macedonian sway as a universal empire. Little absolute territory was indeed gained by Rome in this preliminary war ; but at its conclusion she saw both Macedon</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>