<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r01-0038-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0061.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>REGICIDE</label> (Lat. <hi rend="italic">rex,</hi> a king, and <hi
                        rend="italic">caedere,</hi> to kiwi), the name given to any one who kills a
                    sovereign. Regicides is the name given in English history at the Restoration of
                    1660 to those persons who were responsible for the execution of Charles I. On
                    the 4th of April 1660 charges II. in the Declaration of Breda promised a free
                    pardon to all his subjects “ excepting only such persons as shall hereafter be
                    excepted by parliament,” and on the 14th of May the House of Commons ordered the
                    immediate arrest of “ all those persons who sat in judgment upon the late king’s
                    majesty when sentence was pronounced.” The number of regicides was estimated at
                    84, this number being composed of the 67 present at the last sitting of the
                    court of justice, ii others who had attended earlier sittings, 4 officers of the
                    court and the 2 executioners. Many of them were arrested or surrendered
                    themselves, and the House of Commons in considering the proposed bill of
                    indemnity suggested that only twelve of the regicides, who were named, should
                    forfeit their lives; but the House of Lords urged that all the king’s judges,
                    with three exceptions, and some others, should be treated in this way.</p>
               <p>Eventually a compromise was agreed upon, and the bill as passed on the 29th of
                    August 1660 divided the regicides into six classes for punishment: (1) Four of
                    them, although dead—Cromwell, Ireton, Bradshaw and Pride—were to be attainted
                    for high treason. (2) The estates of twenty others, also dead, were to be
                    subjected to fine or forfeiture. (3) Thirty living regicides were excepted from
                    all indemnity. (4) Nineteen living regicides were also excepted, but with a
                    saving clause that their execution was to be suspended until a special act of
                    parliament was passed for this purpose. (5) Six others were to be punished, but
                    not capitally. (6) Two, Colonels Hutchinson and Thomas Lister, were simply
                    declared incapable of holding any office. Two regicides—Ingoldsby, who declared
                    he had only signed the warrant under compulsion, and Colonel Matthew
                    Thomlinson—escaped without punishment. A court of thirty-four commissioners was
                    then appointed to try the regicides, and the trial took place in October 1660.
                    Twenty-nine were condemned to death, but only ten were actually executed, the
                    remaining nineteen</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0039" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0062.jp2"/>
                <p>with six others being imprisoned for life. The ten who were executed at Charing
                    Cross or Tyburn, London, in October 1660, were Thomas Harrison, John Jones,
                    Adrian Scrope, John Carew, Thomas Scot, and Gregory Clement, who had signed the
                    death-warrant; the preacher Hugh Peters; Francis Hacker and Daniel Axtel, who
                    commanded the soldiers at the trial and the execution of the king; and John
                    Cook, the solicitor who directed the prosecution. In January 1661 the bodies of
                    Cromwell, lreton, ana Bradshaw were exhumed and hanged at Tyburn, but Pride’s
                    does not appear to have been treated in this way. Of the nineteen or twenty
                    regicides who had escaped and were living abroad, three, Sir John Barkstead,
                    John Okey and Miles Corbet, were arrested in Holland and executed in London in
                    April 1662; and one, John Lisle, was murdered at Lausanne. The last survivor of
                    the regicides was probably Edmund Ludlow, who died at Vevey in 1692.</p>
                <p>Ludlow’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> , edited by C. H. Firth (Oxford, 1894),
                    give interesting details about the regicides in exile. See also D. Masson, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Life of Milton,</hi> vol. vi. (1880), and M. Noble, <hi
                        rend="italic"> Lives of the English Regicides</hi> (1798). (A. W. H.*)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
