<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0609.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0603-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOLSTICE</label>,
in aſtronomy, that time when the ſun is in one of the ſolſtitial points ; that is, when he is at his greateſt diſtance ſrom the equator ; thus called becauſe he then appears to ſtand ſtill, and not to change his diſtance from the equator for ſome time; an appearance owing to the obliquity of our ſphere, and which thoſe living under the equator are ſtrangers to.</p><p>The ſolſtices are two in each year ; the æstival or ſummer ſolſtice, and the hyemal or winter ſolſtice. The ſummer ſolſtice is when the sun ſeems to deſcribe the tropic of cancer, which is on June 22. when he makes the longeſt day : the winter ſolstice is when the ſun enters the firſt degree, or ſeems to deſcribe the tropic of capricorn, which is on December 22. when he makes the ſhorteſt day. This is to be underſtood as in our northern hemisphere ; for in the ſouthern, the ſun’s entrance into capricorn makes the ſummer ſolſtice, and that into cancer the winter ſolſtice. The two points of the ecliptic, wherein the ſun’s greateſt aſcent above the equator, and his deſcent below it, are terminated, are called the solst <hi rend="italic">itial points ;</hi> and a circle, ſuppoſed to paſs through the poles of the world and theſe points, is called the <hi rend="italic">ſolſtitial colure.</hi> The ſummer ſolſtitial point is in the beginning of the firſt degree of cancer, and is called the aestival or <hi rend="italic">ſummer point</hi>; and the winter ſolſtitial point is in the beginning of the firſt degree of capricorn, and is called the <hi rend="italic">winter point.</hi> Theſe two points are diametrically oppoſite to each other.</p></div></body></text></TEI>