<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0468.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0462-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIDON</label>
(anc. geog.), a city of Phoenicia in Asia, famous in Scripture for its riches, arising from the extenſive commerce carried on by its inhabitants. Heavy judgments were denounced againſt the Sidonians on account of their wickedneſs, which were accompliſhed in the time of Ochus king of Perſia : for that monarch having come againſt them with an army on account of their rebellion, the city was betrayed by its king ; upon which the wretched inhabitants were ſeized with deſpair ; they ſet fire to their houſes, and 40,000, with their wives and children, periſhed in the flames.</p><p>This city is now called <hi rend="italic">Saide,</hi> and, according to Mr Bruce’s account, not only its harbour is filled up with sand, but the pavement of the ancient city ſtood 7½ feet lower than the ground on which the preſent city ſtands. Volney defcribes it as an ill-built dirty city. Its length along the ſea-ſhore is about 600 paces, and its breadth 150. At the north-west side of the town is the caſtle, which is built in the ſea itſelf, 80 paces from the main land, to which it is joined by arches. To the west of this caſtle is a ſhoal 15 feet high above the ſea, and about 2c0 paces long. The ſpace between this ſhoal and the caſtle forms the road, but veſſels are not ſafe there in bad weather. The ſhoal, which extends along the town, has a baſon incloſed by a decayed pier. This was the ancient port ; but it is ſo choaked up by fand, that boats alone can enter its mouth near the caſtle. Fakr-el-din, emir of the Druſes, deſtroyed all theſe little ports from Bairout to Acre, by sinking boats and ſtones to prevent the Turkiſh ſhips from entering them. The baſon of Saide, if it were emptied, might contain 20 or 25 ſmall veſſels. On the ſide of the ſea, the town is abſolutely without any wall; and that which encloſes it on the land ſide is no better than a priſon- wall. The whole artillery does not exceed six cannons, and theſe are without carriages and gunners. The garriſon ſcarcely amounts to 100 men. The water comes from the river <hi rend="italic">A</hi> oula, through open canals, from which it is fetched by the women. Theſe canals ſerve alſo to water the orchards of mulberry and lemon trees.</p><p>Saide is a conſiderable trading town, and is the chief emporium of Damaſcus and the interior country. The French, who are the only Europeans to be found there, have a conſul, and ſive or ſix commercial houſes. Their exports conſiſt in silks, and particularly in raw and ſpun cottons. The manufacture of this cotton is the principal art of the inhabitants, the number of whom may be eſtimated at about 5000. It is 45 miles west from Damaſcus. E. Long. 36. 5. N. Lat. 37.</p></div></body></text></TEI>