<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0604.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0598-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOLDER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sodder,</hi></label>
 or <hi rend="italic">Soder,</hi> a metallic or mineral compoſition uſed in ſoldering or joining together other metals.</p><p>Solders are made of gold, ſilver, copper, tin, biſmuth, and lead ; uſually obſervſing, that in the compoſition there be ſome of the metal that is to be ſoldered mixed with ſome higher and finer metals. , Goldſmiths uſually make four kinds of ſolder, viz. ſolder of eight, wſhere to ſeven parts of ſilver there is one of braſs or copper ; ſolder of six, where only a ſixth part is copper ; ſolder of four, and ſolder of three. It is the mixture of copper in the ſolder that makes raiſed plate come always cheaper than flat.</p><p>As mixtures of gold with a little copper are found to melt with leſs heat than pure gold itſelf, theſe mixtures ſerve as folders for gold : two pieces of fine gold are ſoldered by gold that has a ſmall admixture of copper; and gold alloyed with copper is ſoldered by ſuch as is alloyed with more copper : the workmen add a little ſilver as well as copper, and vary the proportions of the two to one another, ſo as to make the colour of the ſolder correspond as nearly as may be to that of the piece, A mixture of gold and copper is alſo a ſolder for fine copper as well as for fine gold. Gold being particularly diſpoſed to unite with iron, proves an excellent ſolder for the finer kinds of iron and ſteel inſtruments.</p><p>The ſolder uſed by plumbers is made of two pounds of lead to one of block-tin. Its goodneſs is tried by melting it, and pouring the bigneſs of a crown piece on a table ; for, if good, there will ariſe little bright ſhining stars therein. The ſolder for <hi rend="italic">copper</hi> is made like that of the plumbers ; only with copper and tin; and for</p><p>very nice works, inſtead of tin, they ſometimes uſe a quantity of ſilver. Solder for <hi rend="italic">tin</hi> is made of two-thirds of tin and one of lead, or of equal parts of each ; but where the work is any thing delicate, as in organ pipes, where the juncture is ſcarce diſcernible, it is made of one part of biſmuth and three parts of pewter. The pewterers uſe a kind of ſolder made with two parts of tin and one of biſmuth ; this compoſition melts with the leaſt heat of any of the folders.</p><p>Silver ſolder is that which is made of two parts of ſilver and one of braſs, and uſed in ſoldering thoſe metals. Spelter ſolder is made of one part of braſs and two of spelter or zinc, and is uſed by the braziers and copperſmiths for ſoldering braſs, copper, and iron. This ſolder is improved by adding to each ounce of it one pennyweight of ſilver ; but as it does not melt without a conſiderable degree of heat, it cannot be uſed when it is inconvenient to heat the work red-hot ; in which caſe copper and braſs are ſoldered with ſilver.</p><p>Though spelter ſolder be much cheaper than ſilver- ſolder, yet workmen in many caſes prefer the latter. And Mr Boyle informs us, that he has found it to run with ſo moderate a heat, as not much to endanger the melting of the delicate parts of the work to be ſoldered; and if well made, this ſilver ſolder will lie even upon the ordinary kind itſelf ; and ſo fill up thoſe little cavities that may chance to be left in the firſt operation, which is not eaſily done without a folder more eaſily fuſible than the firſt made uſe of. As to iron, it is ſufficient that it be heated to a white heat, and the two extremities, in this ſtate, be hammered together ; by which means they become incorporated one with the other.</p></div></body></text></TEI>