<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0581.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0575-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOCIETIES</label>,
aſſociations voluntarily formed by a number of individuals for promoting knowledge, induſtry, or virtue. They may therefore be divided into three claſſes; ſocieties for promoting ſcience and literature, societies for encouraging and promoting arts and manufactures, and ſocieties for diffusing religion and morality and relieving diſtreſs. Societies belonging to the firſt claſs extend their attention to all the ſciences and literature in general, or devote it to one particular ſcience. The fame obſervation may be applied to thoſe which are inſtituted for improving arts and manufactures. Thoſe of the third claſs are eſtabliſhed; either with a view to prevent crimes, as the Philanthropic Society ; for the diffusion of the Chriſtian religion among unenlightened nations, as the Society for the Propagation of the Goſpel in Foreign Parts; or for introducing arts and civilization, along with a knowledge of the Chriſtian religion, as the Sierra Leona company.</p><p>The honour of planning and inſtituting ſocieties for thoſe valuable purpoſes is due to modern times. A literary aſſociation is ſaid to have been formed in the reign of Charlemagne (see ACADEMY) ; but the plan ſeems to have been rude and defective. Several others were inſtituted in Italy in the 16th century ; but from the accounts which we have ſeen of them, they ſeem to have been far inferior to thoſe which are moſt flouriſhing at preſent. The moſt enlarged idea of literary societies ſeems to have originated with the great Lord Bacon, the father oſ modern philosophy, who recommended to the reigning prince to inſtitute ſocieties of learned men, who ſhould give to the world from time to time a regular account of their reſearches and diſcoveries. It was the idea of this great philosopher, that the learned world ſhould be united, as it were, into one immenſe republic; which, though conſiſting of many detached ſtates, ſhould hold a ſtrict union and preſerve a mutual intelligence with each other, in every thing that regards the common intereſt. The want of this union and intelligence he laments as one of the chief obſtacles to the advancement of ſcience ; and, juſtly conſidering the inſtitutiou oſ public ſocieties, in the different countries of Europe, under the auſpices of the ſovereign, to be the beſt remedy for that defect, he has given, in his fanciful work, the New Atlantis, the delineation of a philoſophical<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0582.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0576"/>
ſociety on the moſt extended plan, ſor the improvement of all arts and ſciences ; a work which, though written in the language, and tinctured with the colouring oſ romance, is full of the nobleſt philoſophic views. The plan of Lord Bacon, which met with little attention from the age in which he lived, was deſtined to produce its, effect in a period not very diſtant. The ſcheme of a philoſophical college by Cowley is acknowledged to have had a powerful influence in procuring the eſtabliſhment of the Royal Society of London by charter from Charles II.<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>§ Sprat's History of the Royal Society, 2d edit.</p></note> § ; and Cowley’s plan is manifeſtly copied in almoſt all its parts from that in the New Atlantis. The inſtitution of the Roval Society of London was ſoon followed by the eſtabliſhment of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris ; and theſe two have ſerved as models to the philoſophical academies of higheſt reputation in the other kingdoms of Europe.</p><p>The experience oſ ages has ſhown, that improvements of a public nature are best carried on by ſocieties of liberal and ingenious men, uniting their labours without regard to nation, ſect, or party, in one grand purſuit alike intereſting to all, whereby mutual prejudices are worn off, and a humane philoſophical ſpirit is cheriſhed. Men united together, and frequently meeting for the purpoſe of advancing the ſciences, the arts, agriculture, manufactures, and commerce, may oftentimes ſuggeſt ſuch hints, to one another as may be improved to important ends : and ſuch ſocieties, by being the repoſitories of the obſervations and diſcoveries of the learned and ingenious, may from time to time furniſh the world with uſeful publications which might otherwiſe be loſt: for men of ingenuity and modeſty may not chooſe to riſk their reputation, by ſending abroad unpatronized what a learned ſociety might judge richly worthy the public eye ; or perhaps their circumſtances being ſtraitened, they may not be able to defray the expence of publication. Societies inſtituted for promoting knowledge may alſo be of eminent ſervice, by exciting a ſpirit of emulation, and by enkindling thoſe sparks of genius which otherwiſe might for ever have been concealed ; and if, when poſſeſſed of funds ſufficient for the purpoſe, they reward the exertions of the induſtrious and enterprising with pecuniary premiums or honorary medals, many important experiments and uſeful diſcoveries will be made, from which the public may reap the higheſt advantages.</p><p>Eminent inſtances of the beneficial effects of ſuch inſtitutions we have in the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, the Royal Society, and the Society inſtituted for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, in London, and many others of a ſimilar kind. Hereby a ſpirit of diſcovery and improvement has been excited among the ingenious in almoſt every nation ; knowledge of various kinds, and greatly uſeful to mankind, has taken place of the dry and unintereſting ſpeculations of ſchoolmen ; and bold and erroneous hypotheſis has been obliged to give way to demonſtrative experiment. In ſhort, since the eſtabliſhment of theſe ſocieties, solid learning and philoſophy have more increaſed than they had done for many centuries before.</p><p>As to thoſe ſocieties eſtabliſhed for promoting induſtry, religion and morality, and relieving diſtreſs, the deſign is laudable and excellent, and preſents a beautiful picture of the philanthropy of modern times. We are happy to find, from the minutes of ſome of theſe ſo</p><p>cieties, that their beneficial effects are already conſpicuous.</p><p>We will now give ſome account oſ the moſt eminent ſocieties ; arranging them under the three claſſes into which we have divided them : I. <hi rend="italic">Religious and Humane Societies.</hi> II. <hi rend="italic">Societies for Promoting Science and Literature.</hi> III. <hi rend="italic">Societies for Encouraging Arts, Manufactures,</hi> &amp; c.</p><p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Religious and Humane Societies.</hi></p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Society for the Propagation of the Goſpel in Foreign Parts,</hi> was inſtituted by King William III. in 1701, in order to ſecure a maintenance for an orthodox clergy, and to make other proviſions for propagating the goſpel in the plantations, colonies, and factories beyond the ſeas. To that end he incorporated the archbishops, ſeveral of the biſhops, and others of the nobility, gentry, and clergy, to the number of 90, into one body, which, by the name of T <hi rend="italic">he Society ſor the Propagation of the Goſpel in Foreign Parts,</hi> was to plead and be impleaded; to have perpetual ſucceſſion, with privilege to purchaſe L. 2000 a-year inheritance, and eſtates ſor lives or years, with other goods and chattels to any value. By its charter the ſociety is authoriſed to uſe a common ſeal ; and to meet annually on the third Friday in February for the purpoſe of chooſing a preſident, vice- preſident, and officers for the year enſuing ; and on the third Friday in every month, or oftener if there ſhould be occaſion, to tranſact buſineſs, and to depute perſons to take ſubscriptions, and collect money contributed for the purpoſes aforesaid ; and of all moneys received and laid out, it is obliged to give account yearly to the lord-chancellor or keeper, the lord chief-juſtice of the King’s-bench, the lord-chief-juſtice of the Common- pleas, or to any two of theſe magiſtrates. Of this ſociety there is a ſtanding committee at St Paul’s chapter-houſe, to prepare matters for the monthly meeting, which is held at St Martin’s library.</p><p>Before the incorporation of the ſociety for the propagation of the goſpel in foreign parts, there had been formed, for the promoting of Christian knowledge both at home and in the colonies, a voluntary aſſociation of perſons of rank and respectability, who in March 1699 began to hold ſtated meetings in London for that purpoſe, regulating themſelves by the laws of the land and the canons of the church ; and when the new ſociety was formed, they had already tranſmitted to America and the West Indies L. 800 worth of Bibles, Books of Common Prayer, and treatiſes of practical religion, beſides ſecuring a tolerable maintenance to ſeveral clergyman on that continent. This aſſociation ſtill ſubſiſts under the denomination of <hi rend="italic">The Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge,</hi> and has been productive of much good in the cities of London and Weſtminſter ; but upon the formation of the new ſociety, into which all its original members were incorporated by name, the care which the voluntary aſſociation had taken of the colonies devolved of courſe upon the incorporated ſociety ; of which incorporation we believe the object has been ſometimes miſtaken, and the labours of its miſſionaries groſsly miſrepresented. It has by many been suppoſed that the ſociety was incorporated for the <hi rend="italic">ſole</hi> purpoſe of converting the ſavage Americans ; and it has been much blamed for ſending miſſionaries into provinces where, in the deſpicable cant of the complainers, a <hi rend="italic">gospel-ministry</hi> was already eſtabliſhed, But an impartial view of the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0583.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0577"/>
riſe and progreſs of the American provinces, now become independent ſtates, will ſhow the folly and injuſtice of thoſe complaints,</p><p>The Engliſh colonies in North America were in the laſt century formed and firſt proposed by religious men ; who, made uneaſy at home by their intolerant brethren, left the <hi rend="italic">old world</hi> to enjoy in peace that firſt and chief prerogative of man, <hi rend="italic">the free worſhip of God according to his own confidence.</hi> At one time <hi rend="smallcaps">Puritans</hi> were driven acroſs the Atlantic by the epiſcopal church ; at another, <hi rend="smallcaps">Churchmen</hi> were forced away by the preſbyterians juſt as the revolutions of ſtate threw the civil power into the hands of the one or the other party ; and not a few members of the <hi rend="smallcaps">church of Rome</hi> were chased to the wilds of America by the united exertions of both. It has been often obſerved, that people perſecuted for their religion become for the moſt part enthuſiaſtically attached to it ; and the conduct of thoſe coloniſts was in perfect harmony with this obſervation. Their zeal, inflamed by their violent removal to the other hemiſphere, kept religion alive and active among themſelves ; but their poverty diſabled them from ſupplying fuel to the flame, by making proviſion for a miniſtry to inſtruct their offspring. The conſequence was, that the new Chriſtian commonwealth, without the kindly aſſiſtance of its mother-country, would have been, in the words of the Roman hiſtorian, <hi rend="italic">Res unius aetatis.</hi> Againſt this danger a timely aid was to be provided by the ſociety ; which, as it conſiſted not of fanatical members, would not intruſt the important buſineſs of the miſſion to fanatical preachers, who, though always ready for ſuch ſpiritual enterpriſes, are never qualified to carry them on with ſucceſs.</p><p>It was therefore thought fit to aſſign a decent maintenance for clergymen of the church of England, who might preach the goſpel to their brethren in America : and though thoſe miſſionaries in general carefully avoided the conduct of thoſe of Rome, whoſe principal aim is to reduce all churches under ſubmiſſion to the papal tyranny ; yet ſo lately as 1765, did ſome of the colonies, in which the puritanic ſpirit of the laſt century characteriſed the church eſtabliſhed by law, raiſe a hideous outcry againſt the ſociety for sending a miſſion into their quarters, though only for the ſervice of the diſperſed members of the Epiſcopal church reſiding among them, and for the converſion of thoſe men whom their rigid fanaticiſm had prejudiced againſt Chriſtianity itſelf.</p><p>Indeed the commodity called <hi rend="smallcaps">freethinking,</hi> as Biſhop Warburton expreſſes it, was at an early period imported by the opulent and faſhionable coloniſts.<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>See his sermon, Vol II. of his Works, vol 4to.</p></note> The celebrated Berkeley, who had reſided ſome years in Rhode Iſland, and at his return was called upon to preach the anniversary ſermon before the ſociety, informs us, that the iſland where he lived was inhabited by an Engliſh colony, conſiſting chiefly of sectaries of many different denominations ; that ſeveral of the better sort of the inhabitants of towns were accuſtomed to affemble themſelves regularly on the Lord’s day for the performance of divine worſhip ; but that moſt of thoſe who were diſperſed through the colony rivalled ſome well bred people of other countries, in a thorough indifference for all that is ſacred, being equally careleſs of outward worſhip and of inward principles. He adds, that the miſſionaries had done, and were continuing to do, good ſervice in bringing thoſe planters to a ſenous ſenſe of religion. “ I ſpeak it knowingly (ſays he), that the miniſters of the goſpel, in thoſe provinces which go by the name of New England, ſent and ſupported at the expence of the ſociety, have, by their fobriety of manners, diſcreet behaviour, and a competent degree of uſeful knowledge, ſhown themſelves worthy of the choice of thoſe who ſent them.” We have the honour to be acquainted with ſome of the miſſionaries ſent at a later period, and have reaſon to believe that, down to the era of the American revolution, they had the ſame virtues, and were doing the ſame good ſervices, which procured to their predeceſſors this honourable teſtimony from one of the greateſt and the beſt of men. Surely ſuch a miſſion deſerved not to be evil ſpoken of by ſectariſts of any denomination who believe in Chriſt ; eſpecially as the very charter of incorporation aſſigns as a reaſon for miſſionaries being ſent to the colonies, “ that by reaſon of their poverty thoſe colonies were deſtitute and unprovided of a <hi rend="smallcaps">maintenance</hi> for miniſters and the public worſhip of God.”</p><p>The ſociety, however, was incorporated for other purpoſes than this. It was obliged by its charter to attempt the converſion of the native Americans and the negro ſlaves ; and we have reason to believe, that, as ſoon as the ſpiritual wants of the coloniſts were decently ſupplied, it was not inattentive to theſe glorious objects. Its success indeed in either purſuit has not been ſo great as could be wiſhed ; but it would be raſh and unfair to attribute this failure to the preſident, vice- preſident, or other officers of the corporation at home. An erroneous notion, that the being baptized is inconſiſtent with a ſtate of ſlavery, rendered the ſelfiſh coloniſts for a long time averſe from the converſion of their negroes, and made them throw every obſtacle in the way of all who made the attempt ; while the difficulties of the Indian miſſion are ſuch as hardly any clergyman educated in a Proteſtant country can be ſuppoſed able to ſurmount.</p><p>He who hopes ſucceſsfully to preach the goſpel among a tribe of ſavage wanderers, muſt have an ardent zeal and unwearied diligence ; appetites ſubdued to all the diſtreſſes of want ; and a mind ſuperior to all the terrors of mortality. Theſe qualities and habits may be acquired in the church of Rome by him who from infancy has been trained up in the ſeverities of ſome of the monaſtic orders, and afterwards ſent to the college <hi rend="italic">de propaganda fide</hi> to be instructed in the languages, and inured to the manners and cuſtoms of the barbarous nations whoſe converſion he is deſtined to attempt. But in the reformed churches of Britain there are no monaſtic orders, nor any college <hi rend="italic">de propaganda fide ;</hi> and, yet without the regular preparation, which is to be looked for in ſuch inſtitutions alone, it is not in nature, whatever grace may effect, for any man cheerfully, and at the ſame time soberly, to undergo all the accumulated diſtreſſes ever ready to overtake a faithful miſſionary among savage idolaters. A fanatic zealot will indeed undertake it, though he is totally unqualified for every sober and important work ; and a man of ruined fortunes may be preſſed into the ſervice, though the imρotency of his mind has ſhown him unable to bear either poverty or riches. The failure of the ſociety therefore in its attempts to convert the American Indians may be attributed, we think, in the firſt in-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0584.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0578"/>
ſtance, to the want of a college <hi rend="italic">de propaganda</hi> for training up young men for the American miſſion.</p><p>Perhaps another cauſe of this failure may be found in the conduct of the miſſionarſes, who, it is to be preſumed, have not always employed in a proper manner even the ſcanty qualifications which they actually poſſeſſed. The goſpel, plain and ſimple as it is, and fitted in its nature ſor what it was ordained to effect, cannot be apprehended but by an intellect ſomewhat raiſed above that of a ſavage. Such of the miſſionarſes therefore as began their work with <hi rend="italic">preaching to ſavage and brutal men,</hi> certainly ſet out at the wrong end ; for to make the goſpel underſtood, and much more to propagate and eſtabliſh it, thoſe ſavages ſhould have been firſt taught the neceſſary arts of civil life, which, while they improve every bodily accommodation, tend at the ſame time to enlarge and enlighten the underſtanding. For want of this previous culture, we doubt not, it hath happened that ſuch of the ſavages as have been baptized into the faith have ſo ſeldom perſevered themſelves, or been able in any degree to propagate among their tribes the Chriſtianity which they had been taught, and that ſucceſſive miſſions have always found it neceſſary to begin anew the work of converſion.</p><p>To one or other of theſe cauſes, or to both, may juſtly be attributed the little progreſs which reformed Chriſtianity has made among the Indians of North America ; and not to any want of zeal, attention, or liberality, in the directors of the ſociety at home. During the dependence of the United States on the mother- country, great part of the ſociety’s funds was properly expended in keeping alive a juſt ſenſe of religion among the Chriſtian coloniſts from Europe, who had ſurely the firſt claims upon this beſt of charities ; but now that America has ſeparated herſelf from Great Britain, and shown that ſhe is able to maintain her independence, and to make simple proviſion for a regnlar clergy of her own, the members of the corporation muſt feel themſelves at liberty to beſtow greater attention, and to expend more money than they could formerly do, on the converſion of ſuch Indians as have any intercourſe with the ſettlements which we ſtill poſſeſs. To a body ſo reſpectable, we preſume not to offer advice ; but we cannot help thinking, with Biſhop Berkeley, that the moſt ſucceſsful miſſionaries would be children of Indians, educated in a conſiderable number together from the age of ten or twelve in a college <hi rend="italic">de propaganda fide,</hi> where they ſhould be in no danger of loſing their mother-tongue while they were acquiring a competent knowledge of religion, morality, hiſtory, practical mathematics, and agriculture. “<note anchored="true" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Proposal for the better supplying of Churches in our Foreign Plantations, &amp;c.</p></note> If there were a yearly ſupply (ſays he) of a dozen ſuch miſſionarſes ſent abroad into their reſpective countries, after they had received the degree of maſter of arts, and been admitted into holy orders, it is hardly to be doubted but that in a little time the world would ſee good and great effects of their miſſion.”</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Society in Scotland for Propagating Christian Knowledge,</hi> was inſtituted in the beginning of the preſent Century. At that period the condition of the Scotch Highlanders was truly deplorable. Shut up in deſolate iſlands by tempeſtuous ſeas, or diſperſed over a wide extent of country, interſected by high mountains, rapid rivers, and arms of the ſea, without bridges or highways, by which any communication could be kept open either with remote or neighbouring diſtricts, they lived in ſmall detached companies in hamlets or ſolſtary huts, Being thus ſecluded from intercourſe with the more civilized part of the iſland, they could not enjoy the advantages of trade and manufactures. As their ſoil was barren and their climate ſevere, in agriculture no progreſs was to be expected : and as they were acquainted with no language but Gaelic, in which no books were then written, to poſſeſs knowledge was impoſſible. Their pariſhes being of great extent, often 30 or 40 miles long and of a proportionable breadth, and ſometimes conſiſting of ſeveral iſlands ſeparated by ſeas, which are often impassable, a conſiderable number of the inhabitants was entirely deprived of religious inſtruction or fell a prey to Popiſh emiſſarſes. A ſingle ſchool in ſuch extenſive pariſhes could be of little benefit; yet many pariſhes were entirely deſtitute even of this reſource ; and where ſchools were eſtabliſhed, the want of books prevented them from producing the uſeful effects otherwiſe to have been expected from them<note anchored="true" n="4" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> Even ſo late as the year 1758, no fewer than 175 pariſhes, within the bounds of 39 preſbyteries, had no parochial ſchool. We are ſorry to add, that even in the preſent enlightened and benevolent age the complains is not entirely removed.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> To all this we muſt add, that they lived in a ſtate of the greateſt oppreſſion : For though the Highlands formed a part of the Britiſh empire, the bleſſings oſ the Britiſh conſtitution had not reached them. The feudal ſyſtern reigned in its utmoſt rigour ; the chieftains exerciſing the moſt deſpotic ſway over the inferior Highlanders, whom at their pleaſure they deprived of their lives or property<note anchored="true" n="5" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> The feudal syſtem was at length aboliſhed in the year 1748 by the juriſdiction act.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(b).</hi></p><p>Thus the Highlanders were ignorant, oppreſſed, and uncivilized ; ſlaves rather than ſubjects ; and either entirely deſtitute of the advantages of the Chriſtian religion, or unqualified to improve them. Hitherto they had been unhappy and uſeleſs to themſelves and dangerous to the ſtate ; for they were ready at the call of their chieftains to iſſue from their mountains, and to turn their arms againſt their lawful king and his loyal ſubjects. This character, however, aroſe from their ſituation. It was therefore impoſſible for benevolent minds to contemplate this unhappy ſituation of their countrymen without feeling a deſire to raiſe them to the dignity of rational beings, and to render them uſeful as citizens.</p><p>Accordingly, in the year 1701, ſome private gentlemen of the city of Edinburgh, who had formed themſelves into a ſociety for the reformation of manners, directed their attention to the Highlands of Scotland, and endeavoured to deviſe ſome plan for alleviating the diſtreſſes of the inhabitants. The remedy which promiſed to be moſt efficacious was, to eſtabliſh charity ſchools in different places. But as the exigency was great, it was no eaſy matter to raiſe a sufficient fund for<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0585.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0579"/>
this purpoſe, They began therefore with what voluntary ſubſcriptions they could procure, hoping afterwards to increaſe their capital by vacant ſtipends and public contributione. A memorial with this view was preſented to the General Assembly in 1704, which received their approbation ; and they accordingly passed an act, recommending a general contribution. In 1706 the General Assembly appointed ſome oſ their number to inquire more carefully into the state of the Highlands, and the year following appointed a ſelect committee to confer with the gentlemen who had suggested the plan. The reſult of theſe conferences was the publication of propoſals “ for propagating Chriſtian knowledge in the Highlands and iſlands of Scotland, and in foreign parts of the world.” Copies of theſe propoſals, with ſubscription papers, were diſtributed through the kingdom ; and the contributions having ſoon amounted to L. 1000, her majeſty Queen Anne encouraged this infant ſociety by her royal proclamation, and at the ſame time issued letters patent under the great ſeal of Scotland for erecting certain of the ſubſcribers into a corporation ; the firſt nomination of whom was lodged with the lords of council and ſeſſion.</p><p>This corporation held its firſt meeting on Thurſday 3d November 1709. It was attended by ſeveral of the nobility, fourteen of the lords of ſeſſion, many gentlemen of rank, together with moſt of the miniſters of the city of Edinburgh and neighbourhood. A president, ſecretary, and treaſurer, with a committee of fifteen directors, were appointed for the diſpatch of busineſs. At their ſecond meeting in January 1710, a ſcheme of management was formed and approved ; in which it was propoſed, I. To erect and maintain ſchools in ſuch places of Scotland, particularly in the Highlands and Iſlands, as ſhould be found to need them moſt ; in which ſchools all perſons whatſoever ſhould be taught by fit and well qualified ſchoolmaſters, appointed by the ſociety, to read the Holy Scriptures and other pious books ; as alſo to write, and to underſtand the common rules of arithmetic, with ſuch other things as ſhould be thought ſuitable to their circumſtances. 2. That the ſchoolmaſters ſhould be particularly careful to inſtruct their ſcholars in the principles of the Chriſtian reformed religion ; and for that end ſhould be obliged to catechiſe them at leaſt twice a week, and to pray publicly with them twice a-day. 3. That not only ſuch as were unable to pay ſhould be taught gratis, but that thoſe whole circumſtances required it, ſhould have ſuch farther encouragement as the ſociety ſhould think fit in a conſiſtency with their patent. 4. To name ſome prudent perſons, miniſters and others, to be overſeers of thoſe ſchools, who ſhould take care that the ſchoolmaſters do their duty, and that the inſtructions to be given from time to time by the ſociety or their committee be punctually obſerved ; which overſeers ſhould make their report to the ſociety quarterly or half-yearly at fartheſt. 5. To give ſuitable encouragement to ſuch miniſters or catechiſts as ſhould be willing to contribute their aſſiſtance towards the farther inſtruction of the ſcholars remote from church, by not only catechising, but preaching to them ; which miniſters or catechiſts ſhould take the ſame care of the other inhabitants as of the ſcholars. 6. To extend their endeavours for the advancement of the Chriſtian religion to heathen na</p><p>tions ; and for that and to give encouragement to miniſters to preach the goſpel among them. Having thus formed a plan, they immediately proceeded to eſtabliſh ſchools in the moſt useful and economical manner ; and as the capital continued to accumulate, the intereſt was faithfully applied, and the utility of the inſtitution was more extensively diffuſed.</p><p>Until the year 1738 the attention of the ſociety had been wholly directed to the eſtabliſhment of ſchools ; but their capital being then conſiderably augmented, they began to extend their views of utility much farther. The grand object of all public associations ought certainly to be the promoting of religion and morality. It muſt, however, be evident to every man of reflection, that theſe can neither be propagated nor preſerved among a people without agriculture, unaccuſtomed to commerce and manufactures, and conſequently without labour or exertion. Languor and debility of mind muſt always be the companions of idleneſs. While the Highlanders roved about with arms in their hands, the latent vigour of their minds muſt often have been called forth into action ; but when their arms were taken away, and themſelves confined to a domeſtic life, where there was nothing to rouſe their minds, they muſt have sunk into indolence and inactivity. All attempts therefore to inſtruct them in religion arid morality, without introducing among them ſome of the necessary arts of life, would probably have been unavailing. The ſociety accordingly reſolved to adopt what appeared to them the moſt effectual methods of introducing induſtry among the Highlanders. But as their patent did not extend far enough, they applied to his majeſty George II. for an enlargement of their powers ; and accordingly obtained a ſecond patent, by which they are empowered, “ besides fulfilling the purpoſes of their original patent, to cauſe ſuch of the children as they ſhall think fit to be bred to husbandry and houſewifery, to trades and manufactures, or in ſuch manual occupations as the ſociety ſhall think proper.”</p><p>The objects of this ſecond patent the ſociety have not failed to purſue ; and though many obſtacles and diſcouragements to their efforts occurred among a rude and barbarous people, yet their perſeverance, and the obvious utility of their plans, at length ſo far overcame the reluctance of the inhabitants, that no leſs than 94 ſchools of induſtry in various parts of the Highlands and iſlands are now upon their eſtabliſhment, at which are educated 2360 ſcholars.</p><p>The ſociety, while anxiouſly endeavouring to diffuſe a ſpirit of induſtry through the Highlands, were ſtill equally ſolicitous to promote the knowledge of the Chriſtian religion. As the Engliſh language had been the only channel by which knowledge was conveyed to them (a language which, being not uſed in converſation, was in all reſpects foreign to them), it was judged requisite that they ſhould have the Scriptures in their vernacular tongue. The ſociety therefore firſt appointed a tranſlation of the New Teſtament to be made into Gaelic : A tranſlation was accordingly undertaken by the Rev. Mr Stewart miniſter of Killin in Perthſhire, and printed in 1767, which is ſaid to be executed with much fidelity. Of this work many thouſand copies have been diſtributed in the Highlands, The greater part of the Old Teſtament has alſo been tranſlated<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0586.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0580"/>
by the Rev. Dr Smith of Campbelton and others, but chiefly by the Rev. Dr Stewart of Luſs, by the appointment and at the expence of the ſociety : and as ſoon as the remaining part can be got ready, the whole will be ſold at ſo low a price as the poor may without difficulty afford. This plan the ſociety have judiciously choſen, in order to prevent diſcontent and murmuring ; effects which the diffuſion oſ the Scriptures ought never to produce ; but which could not possibly have been prevented, had the diſtribution been gratuitous, and of courſe partial.</p><p>For ſome years paſt the funds of the ſociety have rapidly accumulated, from the very liberal donations of ſeveral individuals.</p><table> <row> <cell>Lady Glenorchy</cell> <cell>L. 5,000</cell> </row> <row> <cell>By a perſon unknown</cell> <cell>10,000</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Lord Van Vryhouven of Holland</cell> <cell>20,000</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Miſs Gray of Teasses</cell> <cell>3,500</cell> </row> </table><p>In conſequence of theſe great additions to their ſtock, inſinuations have been thrown out that the ſociety have become ſo wealthy as to be at a loſs for proper objects on which to beſtow their increaſed revenue. If ſuch an opinion be <hi rend="italic">ſeriouſly</hi> entertained by any one, we muſt beg him to remember, that the ſociety have erected and endued no leſs than 323 ſchools for religion, the firſt principles of literature and induſtry, at the annual expence of L. 3214, 10s. Sterling ; and that at theſe ſeminaries are educated from 14,000 to 15,000 children ; who, but for the means of inſtruction thus obtained, would in all probability be bred up in ignorance and idleneſs : That they employ 12 miſſionary miniſters and catechiſts in remote parts of the Highlands and iſlands, or among the ignorant Highlanders ſettled in the great towns of Scotland, at the annual expence of L. 296 : That they beſtow a burſary or penſion of L. 15 <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi> on each of six ſtudents of divinity having the Gaelic language : That they employ two miſſionary miniſters and one ſchoolmaſter among the Oneida and Stockbridge Indians of North America (being the deſtination of certain legacies bequeathed to them for that purpoſe), at the annual expence of L. 140. Such is their fixed ſcheme of annual expenditure, amounting in all to L.3740, 10s. Sterling—a ſum it will be acknowledged of very conſiderable magnitude. The whole of their incidental expences ariſing from the Gaelic tranſlation of the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament ; from annuities which they have to pay, in conſequence of ſums left them as reſiduary legatees ; from land and houſe-taxes ; ſrom enabling candidates for the office of ſchoolmaſter to come to Edinburgh for examination ; from furniſhing books to poor ſcholars in their various ſchools ; and from removing ſchoolmaſters from one ſtation to another, is generally about L. 875, which added to the former ſum makes the whole annual expence amount to L. 4615, 10 s.</p><p>If it be inquired at what expence, in the <hi rend="italic">management</hi> of it, this extenſive and complicated charity is annually conducted, we are authoriſed to ſay, that the treaſurer,</p><p>bookholder, and clerk, are allowed each L. 25 <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> the ſame ſalaries which were annexed to theſe offices from the commencement of the ſociety. The beadle or officer is allowed L. 12 <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi> No ſalary whatever is enjoyed by any of the other officers of the ſociety. The ſecretary, comptroller, accountant, and librarian, although ſubjected, ſome of them eſpecially, to no ſmall expence of time and labour, have no pecuniary recompenſe or emolument. Theirs are labours of love, for which they ſeek and expect no other reward than the consciouſneſs of endeavouring to promote the beſt intereſts of mankind. The whole amount of the expence of managing the buſineſs of the ſociety, including the above ſalaries, and coals, candle, ſtationary ware, poſtages, and other incidents, exceeds not at an average L. 115 <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi> From this ſtatement it appears, that hitherto at leaſt the directors have been at no loſs for important objects within the proper ſphere of their inſtitution on which to beſtow their increaſed funds. They have, it is true, the diſpoſal of very conſiderable ſums for promoting the objects of the inſtitution ; but they are ſo far from accumulating wealth, that every year their expenditure, notwithſtanding the late increaſe of their capital, exceeds rather than falls ſhort of their income. They have depended upon a kind Providence and a generous public to refund theſe anticipations of their revenue, and hitherto they have never been diſappointed.</p><p>Thus has the Society for Propagating Chriſtian Knowledge proceeded for almoſt a century. It was founded by the pious exertions of a few private individuals, whoſe names are unknown to the world ; and its funds, by faithful and judicious management, as well as by generous contributions, have now become of ſuch magnitude, as to excite the hope that they will be productive of the moſt valuable effects. The benefits ariſing from public ſocieties, it is well known, depend entirely upon the management of their directors. If ſo, the advantages which have accrued from this ſociety inside it to the praiſe and gratitude of the nation. While eager to increaſe the number of ſchools, the ſociety have not been inattentive to their proſperity. In the year 1771 Mr Lewis Drummond, a gentleman in whom they placed great confidence, was commiſſioned by them to viſit their ſchools, and to make an exact report of their ſtate and circumſtances. Again, in the year 1790, a commiſſion was granted to the Rev. Dr Kemp, one of the miniſters of Edinburgh and ſecretary to the ſociety, to viſit all the ſchools on their eſtabliſhment. This laborious and gratuitous task he accompliſhed in the courſe of four ſummers with much ability and care, and highly to the ſatisfaction of the ſociety. At his return he communicated a variety of important information reſpecting the ſtate of the Highlands and iſlands, and the means neceſſary for their improvement in religion, literature, and induſtry ; an abſtract of which was publiſhed by the ſociety in appendixes to the anniverſary sermons preached before them in the years 1789, 90, 91, and 92<note anchored="true" n="6" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(c) It is well known, that the number of Roman Catholics in the Highlands is conſiderable ; but it muſt give much pleaſure to the Proteſtant reader to be informed, that the ancient malignant ſpirit of Popery has in that diſtrict given place to mildneſs and liberality. This is chiefly owing to the gentleman who ſuperintends the prieſts in that quarter, whoſe mind is enlightened by ſcience and learning. So far from being hoſtile to the views of the ſociety, he recommended to his clergy to promote them. They accordingly received the secretary with much politeneſs ; exhorted the people to ſend their children to the Proteſtant ſchools to be inſtructed in literature, to be taught to read the Scriptures in their own language, and to be made acquainted with thoſe great principles of religion in which all Chriſtians are agreed. What a bleſſed reformation!</p></note> (c).<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0587.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0581"/>
The following table will exhibit at a glance the funds, eſtabliſhment, and expenditure, of the ſociety, from a few years after its commencement to the preſent time. Where the number of ſcholars is not mentioned, the defect may be ſupplied by taking an average from thoſe years where a computation has been made. Where the capital is not mentioned, it may eaſily be made out by conſidering the ſalaries as the intereſt.</p><table> <row> <cell>A. D.</cell> <cell>Capital.</cell> <cell>Schools.</cell> <cell>Scholars.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>1713</cell> <cell/> <cell>12</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>1715</cell> <cell>L.6,177</cell> <cell>25</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>1719</cell> <cell>8,168</cell> <cell>48</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>1727</cell> <cell>9,131</cell> <cell>78</cell> <cell>2757</cell> </row> <row> <cell>1732</cell> <cell>13,318</cell> <cell>109</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>1742</cell> <cell>19,287</cell> <cell>128</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>1753</cell> <cell>24,308</cell> <cell>152</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>1758</cell> <cell>28,413</cell> <cell>176</cell> <cell>6409</cell> </row> <row> <cell>1781</cell> <cell>34,000 Salaries</cell> <cell>180</cell> <cell>7000</cell> </row> <row> <cell>1793</cell> <cell>3,080</cell> <cell>307</cell> <cell>12,913</cell> </row> <row> <cell>1794</cell> <cell>3214</cell> <cell>323</cell> <cell>14,370</cell> </row> </table><p>Hitherto we have taken no notice of the correſponding board which was eſtabliſhed at London ſo early as the year 1729, to receive ſubſcriptions and lay out firms. That board indeed remained long inactive ; but in 1773 its members began to co-operate more cordially with their brethren in Scotland. Since that period an annual ſermon has been preached in recommendation of the charity ; and the preacher is now ſelected without any regard to the religious denomination to which he belongs ; ſometimes from the church of England, ſometimes from the church of Scotland, and ſometimes from ſectaries of different perſuaſions. The meetings of the correſpondent board have been attended by many of the nobility and gentry, who have made great exertions to promote the views of the ſociety. From its preſent flouriſhing ſtate therefore, from the indefatigable exertion and laudable zeal of the managers, and from the countenance and ſupport which they have received from perſons of the firſt rank and reſpectability in the nation, the benevolent mind may look forward with much confidence and ſatisfaction to a period not very diſtant, when its beneficial effects ſhall be felt not only in the Highlands, but ſhall be communicated to the reſt of the nation. We have been thus particular in our account of the Society for Propagating Chriſtian Knowledge, becauſe we have had acceſs to the moſt authentic ſources of information, and becauſe we know it to be an inſtitution calculated to enlighten and improve a conſiderable part of the Britiſh nation.</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">Society of the Sons of the Clergy,</hi> was incorporated by King Charles II. in 1678, by the name of <hi rend="italic">The Governors of the Charity for Relief of the Poor Widows and Children of Clergymen.</hi> This ſociety is under the direction and management of a preſident and vice-preſident, three treaſurers, and a court of aſſiſtants compoſed of forty members. Several hundreds of widows and chil</p><p>dren of the clergy have annually received conſiderable relief from this uſeful charity.</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">Society for the Sons of the Clergy of the Establiſhed Church of Scotland,</hi> was inſtituted at Edinburgh in February 1790, and was conſtituted a body corporate by his majesty’s royal charter in 1792. The ſociety, after ſeveral meetings, are of opinion, that the period in which the families of clergymen feel moſt urgently the need both of friends and of pecuniary aid, is that which commences with the introduction of the ſons either to an univerſity or to buſineſs, and terminates with their eſtabliſhment in their reſpective profeſſions ; that many of the miniſters of this church, living at great diſtances from the ſeats either of univerſities or of buſineſs, posseſs incomes which, in the preſent ſtate of the country, are inadequate to the purpoſes of procuring for their ſons either the literary or profeſſional education which might enable them to come forward' with credit end ſucceſs in the world ; that the ſons of clergymen, from domeſtic tuition and example, have in genetal very advantageous means of receiving in their early years the impreſſions of virtue and honour, together with the rudiments of liberal knowledge ; and that of courſe the public intereſt may be promoted, by enabling this class of young men to obtain their ſhare in the reſpectable ſituations of life. The views of the ſociety have been limited to the ſons only of clergymen ; as they are of opinion, that within the limits which they have fixed, the field of beneficence will be ſtill very extenſive, and the claims for aid as many and as great as their funds can be ſuppoſed able to anſwer, at leaſt for many years to come. If the ſociety ſhall ever be in a ſituation to undertake more than the aids which will·be necessary in bringing forward the ſons of the clergy, it may then be conſidered in what manner the daughters alſo may become ſharers in its bounty.</p><p>5. <hi rend="italic">Royal Humane Society,</hi> was inſtituted in London in 1774, for the recovery of perſons drowned or otherwiſe ſuffocated. We have already given ſome account of societies inſtituted in other countries with the ſame views, and have alſo copied the directions of this ſociety for the recovery of life, for which ſee the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Drowning.</hi> We have therefore only to ſtate, that the plan of this ſociety is ſo adverſe to any private intereſted views, that it acquits its founders of all ſordid motives. For the medical practitioners accept no pecuniary recompenſe for the time which they devote to a difficult and tedious proceſs ; for the anxiety which they feel while the event is doubtful ; for the mortification which they too often undergo, when death, in ſpite of all their efforts, at laſt carries off his prey ; nor for the inſults to which they willingly expoſe themſelves from vulgar incredulity. Their ſole reward is in the holy joy of doing good. Of an inſtitution thus free in its origin from the ſuſpicion of ambitious views, and in its plan renouncing ſelf-intereſt in every ſhape, philanthropy muſt be the only baſis. The good intention therefore of the ſociety is proved by its conſtitution ;<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0588.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0582"/>
the wiſdom and utility of the undertaking are proved by its ſucceſs : not leſs than 3000 fellow-creatures having since its commencement been (1794) reſtored to the community by its timely and indesatigable exertions. For it is to be obſerved, that the benefit of this ſociety is by no means confined to the two caſes of drowning and ſuſpenſion. Its timely ſuccours have rouſed the lethargy of opium taken in immoderate and repeated doſes ; they have reſcued the wretched victims of intoxication ; rekindled the life extinguiſhed by the ſudden ſtroke of lightning ; recovered the apoplectic ; reſtored life to the infant that had lost it in the birth ; they have proved efficacious in caſes of accidental ſmothering and of ſuffocation by noxious damps ; in instances in which the tenderneſs of the infant body or the debility of old age greatly leſſened the previous probability of ſucceſs ; inſomuch that no ſpecies of death ſeems to be placed beyond the reach of this Society’s aſſiſtance, where the miſchief had gone no farther than an obſtruction of the movements of the animal machine without any damage of the organs themſelves. In conſequence of every neceſſary aſſiſtance afforded by this ſociety, similar inſtitutions have been eſtabliſhed at Algiers, Liſhon, Philadelphia, Boſton, Jamaica, Dublin, Leith, Glaſgow, Aberdeen, Birmingham, Glouceſter, Shropſhire, Northamptonſhire, Lancaſter, Briſtol, Whitehaven, Norwich, Exeter, Kent and Newcaſtle. The ſociety has publiſhed an 8vo volume with plates, conſiſting of caſes, correſpondence, and a variety of intereſting matter relating to the object of this benevolent inſtitution.</p><p>6. <hi rend="italic">The Philanthropic Society,</hi> was inſtituted in September 1788. It aims at the prevention of crimes, by removing out of the way of evil counſel, and evil company, thoſe children who are, in the preſent ſtate of things, deſtined to ruin. It propoſes to educate and inſtruct in ſome uſeful trade or occupation the children of convicts or other infant poor who are engaged in vagrant or criminal courſes ; thus to break the chain of thoſe pernicious confederacies, deprive the wicked of ſucceſſors, the gaols of inhabitants, juſtice of its victims, and by all theſe means add citizens to ſociety. This inſtitution is not only calculated to decreaſe vice and infamy, but to increaſe uſeful induſtry ; ſo that thoſe children who would otherwiſe ſucceed to their parents hereditary crimes, and become the next race of beggars and thieves, will now be taught to ſupply by honeſt means their own wants and the wants of others.</p><p>To carry into effect theſe desirable purpoſes, it is the firſt bufineſs of the ſociety to ſelect from priſons, and from the haunts of vice, profligacy, and beggary, ſuch objects as appear moſt likely to become obnoxious to the laws, or prejudicial to the community ; and, in the execution of this duty, the aſſiſtance of the magiſtrates, the clergy, and all who are intereſted in the promotion of good morals and good government, is moſt earneſtly requeſted. For the employment of the children, ſeveral houſes are ſupported, at Cambridge Heath, near Hackney, in each of which a maſter-workman is placed for the purpoſe of teaching the children ſome uſeful trade. The trades already eſtabliſhed are thoſe of a printer, carpenter, ſhoemaker, and taylor. The girls are at preſent educated as menial ſervants.</p><p>In the year 1791 no less than 70 children were un</p><p>der the protection of this ſociety, among whom were many who have been guilty of various felonies, burglaries, and other crimes. Yet, singular as it may appear, in leſs than two years thoſe very children became no leſs remarkable for induſtry, activity, decency, and obedience, than they formerly were for the contrary vices. Such are the grounds on which the Philanthropic Society now claims the attention and ſolicits the patronage of the public. If we regard humanity and religion, this inſtitution opens an aſylum to the moſt forlorn and abject of the human race ; it befriends the moſt friendleſs ; it ſaves from the certain and fatal conſequences of infamy ard vicious courſes orphans and deſerted children. If we regard national proſperity and the public welfare, it is calculated to increaſe induſtry ; and it directs that induſtry into the moſt uſeful and neceſſary channels. If we regard ſelf-intereſt, its immediate object is to protect our perſons from assault and murder, our property from depredation, and our peaceful habitations from the deſperate fury oſ midnight incendiaries.</p><p>One guinea <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi> conſtitutes a member of the ſociety ; and L. 10 at one payment a member for life. A life-ſubſcription, or an annual payment of at leaſt two guineas, is a neceſſary qualification for being elected into the committee.</p><p>II. <hi rend="smallcaps">Societies for Promoting Science and Literature.</hi></p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Royal Society of London</hi> is an academy or body of perſons of eminent learning, inſtituted by Charles II. for the promoting of natural knowledge. The origin of this ſociety is traced by Dr Sprat, its earlieſt historian, no farther back than to “ ſome ſpace after the end of the civil wars” in the laſt century. The ſcene of the firſt meetings of the learned men who laid the foundation of it, is by him fixed in the univerſity of Oxford at the lodgings of Dr Wilkins warden of Wadham college. But Dr Birch, on the authority of Dr Wallis, one of its earlieſt and moſt considerable members, aſſigns it an earlier origin. According to him, certain worthy perſons, refilling in London about the year 1645, being “ inquiſitive into natural and the new and experimental philoſophy, agreed to meet weekly on a certain day, to discourſe upon such ſubjects, and were known by the title of <hi rend="italic">The Invisible</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Philoſophical College.”</hi> In the years 1648 and 1649, the company who formed theſe meetings were divided, part retiring to Oxford and part remaining in London ; but they continued the ſame purſuits as when united, correſponding with each other, and giving a mutual account of their reſpective discoveries. About the year 1659 the greater part of the Oxford ſociety returned to London, and again uniting with their fellow-labourers, met once, if not twice, a-week at Greſham college, during term time, till they were ſcattered by the public diſtractions of that year, and the place of their meeting made a quarter for ſoldiers. On the reſtoration 1660 their meetings were revived, and attended by a greater concourſe of men eminent for their rank and learning. They were at laſt taken notice of by the king, who having himſelf a conſiderable taſte for phyſical ſcience, was pleaſed to grant them an ample charter, dated the 15th of July 1662, and afterwards a ſecond dated 15th April 1763, by which they were erected into a corρo-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0589.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0583"/>
ration, conſiſting of a preſident, council, and fellows, for promoting natural knowledge ; and to give their inveſtigations, againſt which ſtrange prejudices were entertained, every poſſible ſupport, he sometimes honoured their meetings with his preſence.</p><p>Their manner of electing fellows is by balloting. Their council are in number 21, including the preſident, vice-preſident, treaſurer, and two ſecretaries ; 11 of which are continued for the next year, and 10 more added to them; all choſen on St Andrew’s day. Each member at his admiſſion ſubſcribes an engagement that he will endeavour to promote the good of the ſociety ; from which he may be freed at any time, by ſignifying to the preſident that he deſires to withdraw. The charges have been different at different times, and were at firſt irregularly paid ; but they are now five guineas paid to the treaſurer at admiſſion ; and 13 s. per quarter ſo long as the perſon continues a member : or, in lieu of the annual ſubſcription, a compoſition of 25 guineas in one payment.</p><p>Their deſign is, to “ make faithful records of all the works of nature or art which come within their reach; ſo that the preſent as well as future ages may be enabled to put a mark on errors which have been ſtrengthened by long preſcription ; to reſtore truths that have been neglected ; to puſh thoſe already known to more various uſes ; to make the way more paſſable to what remains unrevealed,” &amp; c. To this purpoſe they have made a great number of experiments and obſervations on moſt of the works of nature ; and alſo numbers of ſhort hiſtories of nature, arts, manufactures, uſeful engines, contrivances, &amp; c <hi rend="italic">.</hi> The ſervices which they have rendered to the public are very great. They have improved naval, civil, and military architecture ; advanced the ſecurity and perfection of navigation ; improved agriculture ; and put not only this kingdom, but alſo Ireland, the plantations, &amp; c. upon planting. They have regiſtered experiments, hiſtories, relations, obſervations, &amp; c. and reduced them into one common ſtock; and have, from time to time, publiſhed thoſe which they reckoned moſt uſeful, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Philoſophical Transactions, Sec.</hi> and laid the rest up in public regiſters, to be nakedly tranſmitted to poſterity, as a ſolid groundwork for future ſyſtems.</p><p>They have a library adapted to their inſtitution ; towards which Mr Henry Howard, afterwards duke of Norfolk, contributed the Norfolcian library, and which is, at this time, greatly increaſed by a continual ſeries of benefactions. The muſeum or repoſitory of natural and artificial rarities, given them by Daniel Colwal, Eſq; and ſince enriched by many others, is now removed to the Britiſh muſeum, and makes a part of that great repoſitory. Their motto is <hi rend="italic">Nullius in verba;</hi> and their place of aſſembling is Somerſet-houſe in the Strand. Sir Godfrey Copley, baronet, left five guineas to be given annually to the perſon who ſhould write the beſt paper in the year, under the head of experimental philoſophy. This reward, which is now changed to a gold medal, is the higheſt honour the ſociety can beſtow. It is conferred on St Andrew’s day.</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">The Royal Society of Edinburgh,</hi> was incorporated by royal charter on the 29th of March 1783, and has for its object the cultivation of every branch of ſcience, erudition, and taſte. Its rise and progreſs towards its preſent ſtate was as follows : In the year 1718 a literary</p><p>ſociety was eſtabliſhed in Edinburgh by the learned Ruddiman and others, which in 1731 was ſucceeded by a ſociety instituted for the improvement of medical knowledge. In the year 1739 the celebrated .-Maclaurin conceived the idea of enlarging the plan of this ſociety, by extending it to ſubjects of philoſophy and literature. The inſtitution was accordingly new-modelled by a printed ſet of laws and regulations, the number of members was increaſed, and they were diſtinguiſhed from that time by the title of <hi rend="italic">The Society for Improving Arts and Sciences,</hi> or more generally by the title of <hi rend="italic">The Philoſophical Society of Edinburgh.</hi> Its meetings, however, were ſoon interrupted by the diſorders of the country during the rebellion in 1747 ; and they were not renewed till the year 1752. Soon after this period the firſt volume of the Tranſactions of the Philoſophical Society of Edinburgh was publiſhed, under the title of Essays <hi rend="italic">and Obſervations, Phyſical and Literary,</hi> and was followed by other volumes of acknowledged merit. About the end of the year 1782, in a meeting of the profeſſors of the univerſity of Edinburgh, many of whom were likewiſe members of the Philoſophical Society, and warmly attached to its interests, a ſcheme was propoſed by the Rev. Dr Robertſon, principal of the univerſity, for the eſtabliſhment of a new ſociety on a more extended plan, and after the model of ſome of the foreign academies. It appeared an expedient meaſure to ſolicit the royal patronage to an inſtitution of this nature, which promiſed to be of national importance, and to requeſt an eſtabliſhment by charter from the crown. The plan was approved and a~ dopted ; and the Philoſophical Society, joining its influence as a body in ſeconding the application from the univerſity, his majeſty, as we have already obſerved, was moſt graciouſly pleaſed to incorporate The Royal Society of Edinburgh by charter.</p><p>This ſociety conſiſts of ordinary and honorary members ; and the honorary places are reſtricted to perſons reſiding out of Great Britain and Ireland. The election of new members is appointed to be made at two ſtated general meetings, which are to be held on the fourth Monday of January and the fourth Monday of June. A candidate for the place of an ordinary member muſt ſignify by a letter, addreſſed to one of the members, his wiſh to be received into the ſociety. He muſt then be publicly propoſed at leaſt a month before the day of election. If the propoſal be ſeconded by two of the members preſent, his name is to be inſerted in the lift of candidates, and hung up in the ordinary place of meeting. The election is made by ballot, and is determined in favour of a candidate, if he ſhall have the votes of two thirds of thoſe preſent, in a meeting conſiſting of at leaſt 21 members. The general buſineſs of the ſociety is managed by a preſident, two vice preſidents, with a council of 1 <hi rend="italic">2,</hi> a general ſecretary, and a treaſurer. Theſe officers are choſen by ballot annually on the laſt Monday of November. All public deeds, whether of a civil or of a literary nature, are tranſacted by this board, and proceed in the name of the preſident or vice-preſident.</p><p>As it was thought that the members would have a greater inducement to punctual attendance on the meetings of the ſociety, if they had ſome general intimation of the nature of the ſubjects which were to be conſidered, and made the topics of converſation, it was there<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0590.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0584"/>
fore reſolved to divide the ſociety into two classes, which ſhould meet and deliberate ſeparately, One of theſe classes is denominated the <hi rend="italic">Phyſical Claſs,</hi> and has for its department the ſciences of mathematics, natural philoſophy, chemiſtry, medicine, natural hiſtory, and whatever relates to the improvement of arts and manufactures. The other is denominated the <hi rend="italic">Literary Claſs,</hi> and has for its department literature, philology, hiſtory, antiquities, and ſpeculative philoſophy. Every member is deſired at his admiſſion to intimate which of thoſe classes he wiſhes to be more particularly associated with; but he is at the ſame time intitled to attend the meetings of the other claſs, and to take part in all its proceedings. Each of the classes has four presidents and two ſecretaries, who officiate by turns. The meetings of the phyſical claſs are held on the firſt Mondays of January, February, March, April, July, Auguſt, November, and December; and the meetings of the Literary claſs are held on the third Mondays of January, February, March, April, June, July, November, and December, at 7 o’clock afternoon.</p><p>At theſe meetings the written essays and obſervations of the members of the ſociety, or their correpondents, are read publicly, and become the ſubjects of converſation. The ſubjects of theſe essays and observations are announced at a previous meeting, in order to engage the attendance of thoſe members who may be particularly intereſted in them. The author of each dissertation is likewiſe desired to furniſh the ſociety with an abſtract of it, to be read at the next enſuing meeting, when the converſation is renewed with increaſed advantage, from the knowledge previouſiy acquired of the ſubject. At the ſame meetings are exhibited ſuch ſpecimens of natural or artificial curiosities, ſuch remains of antiquity, and ſuch experiments, as are thought worthy of the attention of the ſociety. All objects of natural hiſtory preſented to the ſociety, are ordered by the charter of the inſtitution to be depoſited, on receipt, in the muſeum of the university of Edinburgh ; and all remains oſ antiquity, public records, or ancient manuſcripts, in the library belonging to the faculty of advocates at Edinburgh.</p><p>The ordinary members, whoſe uſual residence is in the city of Edinburgh or its immediate neighbourhood, are expected to attend regularly the monthly meetings ; and are required to defray, by an annual contribution, the current expences of the inſtitution. The members who reſide at ſuch a diſtance from Edinburgh, that they cannot enjoy the advantages arising from a regular attendance on the meetings of the ſociety, are not ſubjected to any contribution for defraying its expences, but have a right to attend thoſe meetings when occaſionally in Edinburgh, and to take part in all their proceedings.</p><p>Three volumes of the Tranſactions of the ſociety have been publiſhed, which bear simple teſtimony to the learning and acuteness of their various authors.</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">Medical Society</hi> of London, inſtituted in the year 1752, on the plan recommended by Lord Bacon <hi rend="italic">(De Augm. Scient.</hi> lib. iv. cap. 2.), to revive the Hippocratic method of composing narratives of particular caſes, in which the nature of the diſeaſe, the manner of treating it, and the conſequences, are to be ſpecified ; to attempt the cure of thoſe diſeaſes which, in his opinion, have been too boldly pronounced incurable ; and, laſt</p><p>ly, to extend their inquiries after the powers of particular medicines in the cure oſ particular caſes ; the collections of this ſociety have been already publiſhed, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Medical Obſervations and Inquiries,</hi> in ſeveral volumes.</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Medical Society</hi> of Edinburgh was incorporated by royal charter in 1778 ; but there appears to have been in that city a voluntary affectation of the ſame name from the first eſtabliſhment of a regular school of physic in the university. To the voluntary ſociety the public is indebted for six volumes of curious and uſeful essays, collected principally by the late Dr Monro from June 1731 to June 1736; but in the year 1739 that ſociety was united to another, as we have already obſerved in a former article. The ordinary members of the preſent medical ſociety are elected by ballot, and three disſentient exclude a candidate ; an ordinary member may alſo be elected an honorary member, who enjoys the privileges of the others, and receives a diploma, but is freed from the obligation of attendance, delivering papers in rotation, &amp; c. to which the ordinary members are ſubject ; but in this caſe the votes muſt be unanimous. The meetings of this ſociety are held every Saturday evening in their own hall, during the winter ſeaſon, when pipers on medical ſubjects are delivered by the ſeveral members in rotation ; and four of theſe are annually elected to fill the chair in rotation, with the title of annual presidents.</p><p>5. The <hi rend="italic">Royal Medical Society</hi> of Paris was inſtituted in 1776. The members are divided into associates ordinary, limited to 30, honorary to 12, extraordinary to 60, and foreign to 60, and correspondents. This ſociety has publiſhed ſeveral volumes of Memoirs in 4to .</p><p>6. Asiatic <hi rend="italic">Society,</hi> an inſtitution planned by the late illuſtrious Sir William Jones, and actually formed at Calcutta on the 15th of January 1784, for the purpoſe of tracing the hiſtory, antiquities, arts, ſciences, and literature, of the immenſe continent of Asia. As it was reſolved to follow as nearly as poſſible the plan of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Royal Society</hi> of London, of which the king is <hi rend="italic">patron,</hi> the patronage of the Asiatic Society was offered to the governor-general and council, as the executive power in the territories of the company. By their acceptance of this offer, Mr Haſtings, as governor-general, appeared among the patrons of the new ſociety ; “ but he ſeemed in his private ſtation as the first liberal promoter of uſeful knowledge in Bengal, and eſpecially as the great encourager of Persian and Shanſcrit literature, to deſerve a particular mark of diſtinction :” he was requeſted, therefore, to accept the honorary title of president. This was handsomely declined in a letter from Mr Haſtings, in which he requeſted " to yield his pretensions to the gentleman whoſe genius planned the inſtitution, and was moſt capable of conducting it to the attainment of the great and ſplendid purpoſes of its formation.” On the receipt of this letter, Sir William Jones was nominated president of the ſociety ; and we cannot give the reader a view of the object of the inſtitution in clearer language than that which he employed in his firſt diſcourſe from the chair.</p><p>It is your design, I conceive (ſaid the president), to take an simple ſpace for your learned inveſtigations, bounding them only by the geographical limits oſ Alia; ſo that, conſidering Hindoſtan as a centre, and turning your eyes in idea to the north, you have on your right<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0591.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0585"/>
many important kingdoms in the eaſtern peninſula, the ancient and wonderful empire of China with all her Tartarian dependencies, and that of Japan, with the clutter of precious iſlands, in which many lingular curioſities have too long becn concealed: before you lies that prodigious chain of mountains, which formerly perhaps were a barrier against the violence of the ſea, and beyond them the very intereſting country of Tibet, and the vaſt regions of Tartary, from which, as from the Trojan horſe of the poets, have issued ſo many conſummate warriors, whoſe domain has extended at leaſt from the banks of the Ilyſſus to the mouths of the Ganges : on your left are the beautiful and celebrated provinces of Tran or Perſia, the unmeaſured and perhaps unmeaſurable deſerts of Arabia, and the once flouriſhing kingdom of Yemen, with the pleaſant iſles that the Arabs have ſubdued or colonized ; and farther weſtward, the Aſiatic dominions of the Turkish sultans, whoſe moon ſeems approaching rapidly to its wane. By this great circumference the field of your uſeful reſearches will be incloſed ; but ſince Egypt had unqueſtionably an old connection with this country, if not with China, ſince the language and literature of the Abyſſinians bear a maniſeſt affinity to thoſe of Aſia, ſince the Arabian arms prevailed along the African coaſt of the Mediterranean, and even erected a powerful dynaſty on the continent of Europe, you may not be diſpleaſed occasionally to follow the ſtreams of Aſiatic learning a little beyond its natural boundary ; and, if it be neceſſary or convenient that a ſhort name or epithet be given to our ſociety, in order to diſtinguiſh it in the world, that of <hi rend="italic">Aſiatic</hi> appears both claſſical and proper, whether we conſider the place or the object of the inſtitution, and preferable to <hi rend="italic">Oriental,</hi> which is in truth a word merely relative, and though commonly uſed in Europe, conveys no very diſtinct idea.</p><p>“ If now it be asked, What are the intended objects of our inquiries within theſe ſpacious limits ? we answer, <hi rend="smallcaps">Man</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Nature;</hi> whatever is performed by the <hi rend="italic">one</hi> or produced by the <hi rend="italic">other.</hi> Human knowledge has been elegantly analyſed according to the three great faculties of the mind, <hi rend="italic">memory, reaſon,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">imagination,</hi> which we conſtantly find employed in arranging and retaining, comparing and distinguiſhing, combining and diverſifying, the ideas, which we receive through our ſenſes, or acquire by reflection : hence the three main branches of learning are, Hi <hi rend="italic">ſtory, ſcience,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">art ;</hi> the firſt comprehends either an account of natural productions, or the genuine records of empires and ſtates ; the ſecond embraces the whole circle of pure and mixed mathematics, together with ethics and law, as far as they depend on the reaſoning faculty ; and the third includes all the beauties of imagery and the charms of invention, diſplayed in modulated language, or repreſented by colour, figure, or found.</p><p>“ Agreeably to this analyſis, you will inveſtigate whatever is rare in the ſtupendous fabric of nature, will correct the geography of Aſia by new obſervations and diſcoveries; will trace the annals and even traditions of thoſe nations who from time to time have peopled or desolated it ; and will bring to light their various forms of government, with their inſtitutions civil and religious; you will examine their improvements and methods in arithmetic and. geometry ; in trigonometry, menſuration, mechanics, optics, aſtronomy, and general phyſics; their ſyſtems of morality, grammar, rhetoric, and dialectic ; their skill in chirurgery and medicine ; and their advancement, whatever it may be, in anatomy and chemiſtry. To this you will add reſearches into their agriculture, manufactures, trade ; and whilſt you inquire with pleaſure into their music, architecture, painting, and poetry, will not neglect thoſe inferior arts by which the comforts and even elegancies of ſocial life are ſupplied or improved. You may obſerve, that I have omitted their languages, the diverſity and difficulty of which are a ſad obſtacle to the progreſs of uſeful knowledge ; but I have ever conſidered languages as the mere inſtruments of real learning, and think them improperly confounded with learning itſelf : the attainment of them is, however, indiſpenſably neceſſary ; and if to the Perſian, Armenian, Turkiſh, and Arabic, could be added not only the Shanſcrit, the treaſures of which we may now hope to ſee unlocked, but even the Chineſe, Tartarian, Japaneſe, and the various insular dialects, an immenſe mine would then be open, in which we might labour with equal delight and advantage.”</p><p>Of this ſociety three volumes of the Tranſactions have been publiſhed, which are replete with information in a high degree curious and important ; and we hope that the European world ſhall ſoon be favoured with another. The much-to be lamented death of the accompliſhed preſident may indeed damp the ſpirit of inveſtigation among the members ; for to conquer difficulties ſo great as they muſt meet with, a portion ſeems to be neceſſary of that enthuſiaſm which accompanied all the purſuits of Sir William Jones ; but his ſucceſſor is a man of great worth and learning, and we truſt will uſe his utmoſt endeavours to have the plan completed of which Sir William gave the outlines.</p><p>5. <hi rend="italic">The American Philoſophical Society,</hi> held at Philadelphia, was formed in January 1769 by the union of two ſocieties which had formerly subſisted in that city. This ſociety extends its attention to geography, mathematics, natural philosophy, and aſtronomy ; medicine and anatomy; natural hiſtory and chemiſtry; trade and commerce ; mechanics and architecture ; husbandry and American improvements. Its officers are a patron, preſident, three vice-preſidents, one treaſurer, four ſecretaries, and three curators, who are annually choſen by ballot. The duty of the preſident, vice-preſidents, treaſurer, and ſecretaries, is the ſame as in other ſocieties. The buſineſs of the curators is to take the charge of all ſpecimens of natural productions, whether of the animal, vegetable, or fossil kingdom ; all models of machines and inſtruments ; and all other matters belonging to the ſociety which ſhall be intruſted to them. The ordinary meetings are held on the firſt and third Fridays of every month from October to May inclusive. This ſociety was incorporated by charter 15th March 1780 ; and has publiſhed three volumes of its Tranſactions, containing many ingenious papers on general literature and the ſciences, as well as reſpecting thoſe ſubjects peculiar to America. It is a delightful proſpect to the philosopher to conſider, that Aſia, Eurppe, and America, though far ſeparated and divided into a variety of political ſtates, are all three combined to promote the cauſe of knowledge and truth.</p><p>6. <hi rend="italic">A Literary and Philoſophical Society</hi> of conſiderable reputation has been lately eſtabliſhed at Mancheſter, under the direction of two preſidents, four vice-preſi-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0592.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0586"/>
dents, and two Secretaries. The number of members is limited to 50 ; beſides whom there are ſeveral honorary members, all of whom are elected by ballot ; and the officers are choſen annually in April. Four volumes of valuable eſſays have been already publiſhed by this ſociety.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Society for Promoting the Discovery of the interior Parts oſ Africa.</hi> This ſociety or aſſociation for exploring the internal diſtricts of Africa, of which ſo little is at preſent known, was formed in London by ſome opulent individuals in 1788 ; who, ſtrongly impreſſed with a conviction of the practicability and utility of thus enlarging the fund of human knowledge, determined if poſſible to rescue the age from that ſtigma which attaches to its ignorance of ſo large and ſo near a portion of the globe. The founders of this ſociety reſolved to admit no man a member for a ſhorter period than three years, during which he muſt pay annually into the public fund five guineas. After three years, any member, upon giving a year’s notice, may withdraw himſelf from the aſſociation. During the firſt 12 months each oſ the members was allowed to recommend for the approbation of the ſociety ſuch of his friends as he might think proper to be admitted into it ; but ſince that period we believe all additional members have been elected by a ballot of the aſſociation at large. A committee was choſen by ballot to manage the funds of the ſociety, to chooſe proper perrons to be ſent on the discovery of the interior parts of Africa, and to carry on the society’s correſpondence, with expreſs injunctions to diſeloſe no intelligence received from their agents but to the ſociety at large. But a fuller account of the nature of this eſtabliſhment, and the very happy efforts they have made, may be ſeen in the ſuperb edition of their proceedings printed in 1790, 4to, for their own uſe ; or in the 8vo edition ſince made public. They ſoon found two gentleman, Mr Lucas and Mr Ledyard, who were ſingularly well qualified for the important miſſion. The information they have acquired will be found in the above work ; with a new map by Mt Renneſe exhibiting the geographical knowledge collected by the African aſſoeiatioa. Mr Ledyard very unfortunately died during his reſearches at Cairo.</p><p>8. <hi rend="italic">The Society oſ Antiquaries of London,</hi> was founded about the year 1572 by Archbishop Parker, a munificent patron of learned men. For the ſpace of 20 years it aſſembled in the houſe of Sir Robert Cotton ; in 1589 they reſolved to apply to Queen Elizabeth for a charter and a public building where they might hold their meetings ; but it is uncertain whether any ſuch application was ever made. In the mean time, the reputation of the ſociety gradually increaſed, and at length it excited the jealouſy of James I. who was afraid leſt it ſhould preſunre to canvaſs the ſecret tranſactions of his government. He accordingly diſſolved it. But in the beginning of the preſent century, the Antiquarian Society began to revive ; and a number of gentlemen, eminent for their affection to this ſcience, had weekly meetings, in which they examined the antiquities and hiſtory oſ Great Britain preceding the reign of James I. but without excluding any other remarkable antiquities that might be offered to them. From this time the ſociety grew in importance ; and in 1750 they unanimouſly reſolved to petition the king for a charter of incorporation. This they obtained the year following, by</p><p>the influence oſ the celebrated earl <hi rend="italic">of Hardwicke,</hi> then lord chancellor, and Martin Folkes, Eſq; who was then their president. The king declared himſelf their founder and patron, and empowered them to have a body oſ ſtatutes, and a common ſeal, and to hold in perpetuity lands, &amp; c. to the yearly value of L. 1000.</p><p>The chief object of the inquiries and reſearches of the ſociety are Britiſh antiquities and hiſtory ; not, however, wholly excluding thoſe of other countries. It muſt be acknowledged, that the ſtudy of antiquity offers to the curious and inquiſitive a large field for reſearch and amuſement. The inquirer in this branch furniſhes the hiſtorian with his beſt materials, while he diſtinguiſhes from truth the fictions of a bold invention, and ascertains the credibility of facts ; and to the philoſopher he preſents a fruitful ſource of ingenious peculation, while he points out to him the way of thinking, and the manners of men, under all the varieties of aſpect in which they have appeared.</p><p>An antiquarian ought to be a man of ſolid judgment, poſſeſſed of learning and ſcience, that he may not be an enthuſiaſtic admirer of every thing that is ancient merely becauſe it is ancient ; but be qualified to diſtinguiſh between thoſe reſearches which are valuable and important, and those which are trifling and useleſs. It is from the want oſ theſe qualifications that ſome men have contracted ſuch a blind paſſion for every thing that is ancient, that they have expoſed themſelves to ridicule, and their ſtudy to contempt. But if a regard to utility were always to regulate the purſuits of the antiquarian, the ſhafts of ſatire would ho longer be levelled at him; but he would be reſpected as the man who labours to reſtore or to preſerve ſuch ancient productions as are ſuited to illuminate religion, philosophy, and hiſtory, or to improve the arts of life.</p><p>We by no means intend to apply theſe obſervations to any particular ſociety of antiquarians ; but we throw them out, becauſe we know that an aſſiduous ſtudy of antiquity is apt, like the ardent pursuit of money, to lose sight of its original object, and to degenerate into a paſſion which miſtakes the mean for the end, and considers poſſeſſion without a regard to utility as enjoyment.</p><p>An aſſociation ſimilar to that of the Antiquarian Society of London was founded in <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</hi> in 1780, and received the royal charter in 1783.</p><p>Beſides theſe literary ſocieties here mentioned, there are a great number more in different parts of Europe, ſome of which are noticed under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Academy,</hi> Thoſe which are omitted are not omitted on account of any idea of their inferior importance ; but either becauſe we have had <hi rend="smallcaps">ho</hi> accuse to authentic information, or becauſe they reſemble the ſocieties already deſcribed ſo cloſely, that we could have given nothing but their names.</p><p>III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Societies for Encouraging and Promoting Arts, Man utactures,</hi> &amp; c.</p><p>I. London <hi rend="italic">Society for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce,</hi> was inſtituted in the year 1754 by Lord Folkſtone, Lord Romney, Dr Stephen Hales, and a few private gentlemen ; but the merit of this inſtitution chiefly belonged to Mr William Shipley,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0593.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0587"/>
an ingenious mechanic ; who, though deriving no advantages from learning, by unwearied perſonal attendance found means to engage a few perſons of rank and fortune to meet at Peele’s coffeehouſe in Fleetſtreet, and to adopt a plan for promoting arts and manufactures.</p><p>The office-bearers of this ſociety are a preſident, 12 vice-presidents, a ſecretary, and regiſter. Their proceedings are regulated by a body of rules and orders eſtabliſhed by the whole ſociety, and printed for the uſe of the members. All queſtions and debates ate determined by the holding up of hands, or by ballot if required; and no matter can be confirmed without the assent of a majority at two meetings. They invite all the world to propoſe ſubjects for encouragement ; and whatever is deemed deſerving attention, is referred to the consideration of a committee, which, after due inquiry and deliberation, make their report to the whole ſociety, where it is approved, rejected, or altered. A list is printed and publiſhed every year of the matters for which they propoſe to give premiums ; which premiums are either ſums of money, and thoſe ſometimes very considerable ones ; or the ſociety’s medal in gold or ſilver, which they conſider as the greateſt honour they can beſtow. All poſſible care is taken to prevent partiality in the diſtribution of their premiums, by deſiring the claimants names to be concealed, and by appointing committees (who when they find occaſion call to their aſſiſtance the moſt ſkilful artiſts) for the ſtrict examination of the real merit of all matters and things brought before them, in conſequence of their premiums.</p><p>The chief objects of the attention oſ the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, in the application of their rewards, are ingenuity in the ſeveral branches of the polite and liberal arts, uſeful diſeoveries and improvements in agriculture, manufactures, mechanics, and chemiſtry, or the laying open of any ſuch to the public ; and, in general, all ſuch uſeful inventions, diſcoveries, or improvements (though not mentioned in the book of premiums), as may appear to have a tendency to the advantage of trade and commerce.</p><p>The following are ſome of the moſt important regulations of this ſociety. It is required that the matters; for which premiums are offered be delivered in without names, or any intimation to whom they belong ; that each particular; thing be marked in what manner each claimant thinks fit, ſuch claimant lending with it a paper ſealed; up, having on the outside a correſponding mark, and on the inside the claimant’s name and addreſs ; and all candidates are to take notice, that no claim for a premium will be attended to, unleſs the conditions of the advertiſement are fully complied with. No papers ſhall be opened but ſuch as ſhall gain premiums, unleſs where it appears to the ſociety abſolutely neceſſary for the determination, of the claim : all the rest ſhall be returned unopened, with the matters to which they belong, it inquired after by the marks within two years; after which time, if not demanded, they ſhall, be publicly burnt unopened at ſome meeting of the ſociety. All the premiums of this ſociety are deſigned for that part of Great Britain called England, the dominion of Wales, and the town of Berwick upon Tweed, unleſs, expreſsly mentioned to the contrary.</p><p>No perſon ſhall receive any premium, bounty, or encouragement, from the ſociety for any matter for which he has obtained or propoſes to obtain a patent. No member of this ſociety ſhall be a candidate for or intitled to receive any premium, bounty, or reward whatſoever, except the honorary medal of the ſociety.</p><p>The reſpectability of the members who compoſe it may be ſeen by perusing the list which generally accompanies their Tranſactions. In the laſt volume (vol. xii.) it occupies no leſs than 43 pages. Some idea may be formed of the wealth of this ſociety, by obſerving that the list of their premiums fills 96 pages, and amounts to 250 in number. Theſe conſiſt of gold medals worth from 30 to 50, and in a few inſtances to 100, guineas ; and ſilver medals valued at 10 guineas.</p><p>This ſociety is one of the moſt important in Great Britain. Much money has been expended by it, and many are the valuable effects of which it has been productive. Among theſe we reckon not only the diſcoveries which it has excited, but the inſtitution of other ſocieties on the ſame principles to which it has given birth ; and we do not heſitate to conclude, that future ages will conſider the founding of this ſociety as one of the moſt remarkable epochs in the hiſtory of the arts. We contemplate with pleaſure the beneficial effects which muſt reſult to this nation and to mankind by the diffuſion of ſuch inſtitutions ; and rejoice in the hope that the active minds of the people of Great Britain, inſtead of being employed as formerly in controverſies about religion, which engender ſtrife, or in discuſſions concerning the theory of politics, which lead to the adoption of schemes inconſiſtent with the nature and condition of man, will ſoon be more generally united into aſſociations for promoting uſeful knowledge and ſolid improvement, and for alleviating the diſtreſſes of their fellow-creatures.</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Society inſtituted at Bath for the Encouragement of Agriculture, Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce.</hi> It was founded in the year 1777 by ſeveral gentlemen who met at the city of Bath. This scheme met with a very favourable reception both from the wealthy and learned. The wealthy ſubſcribed very liberally, and the learned communicated many important papers. On application; to the London and provincial ſocieties inſtituted for the like purpoſes, they very politely offered their aſſiſtance. Seven volumes of their tranſactions have already been, publiſhed, containing very valuable experiments and obſervations, particularly reſpecting agriculture, which well deſerve the attention of all farmers in the kingdom. We have conſulted them with much ſatisfaction on ſeveral occaſions, and have frequently referred to them in the courſe of this work ; and therefore, with pleaſure, embrace the preſent opportunity' of repeating our obligations. We owe the ſame acknowledgments to the Society for the Improvement of Arts, &amp; c. of London.</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">Society for Working Mines;</hi> an aſſociation lately formed on the continent of Europe. This inſtitution aroſe horn the accidental meeting of ſeveral mineralogists at Skleno near Schemnitz in Hungary, who were collected in order to examine a new method of amalgamation. Struck with the ſhackles impoſed on mineralogy by monopolizers of new and uſeful processes, they thought no method ſo effectual to break them, as forming a ſociety, whoſe common labours ſhould be directed to fix mining on its ſureſt principles; and whoſe memoirs,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0594.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0588"/>
ſpread over all Europe, might offer to every adventurer the reſult of the researches, of which they are the object. By theſe means they ſuppoſed, that there would be a mats of information collected ; the intereſts of individuals would be loſt in the general intereſt ; and the one would materially aſſiſt the other. Impoſture and quackery would, by the ſame means, be baniſhed from a ſcience, which muſt be improved by philoſophy and experience; and the ſociety, they ſuppoſed, would find, in the confidence which they inſpired, the reward and the encouragement of their labours. They deſign, that the memoirs which they publiſh ſhall be ſhort and clear ; truth muſt be their balls, and every idle diſcuſſion, every foreign digreſſion, muſt be baniſhed ; politics and finance muſt be avoided, though the diſſertations may ſeem to lead towards them ; and they oblige themſelves to oppoſe the affectation of brilliancies, and the oſtentation of empty ſpeculation, when compared with plain, ſimple, and uſeful facts.</p><p>The object of the ſociety is phyſical geography ; mineralogy founded on chemiſtry; the management of ore in the different operations which it undergoes ; ſubterraneous geometry ; the hiſtory of mining ; founderies, and the proceſſes for the extraction of metals from the ores, either by fuſion or amalgamation, in every inſtance applied to practice. The end of this inſtitution is to collect, in the moſt extenſive ſenſe, every thing that can aſſiſt the operations of the miner, and to communicate it to the different members, that they may employ it for the public good, in their reſpective countries. Each member muſt conſider himſelf as bound to send to the ſociety every thing which will contribute to the end of its inſtitution ; to point out, with precision, the ſeveral facts and obſervations ; to communicate every experiment which occurs, even the unſuccessful ones, if the relation may ſeem to be advantageous to the public ; to communicate to the ſociety their examination of ſchemes, and their opinions on queſtions propoſed by it ; and to pay annually two ducats (about 18 s. 6 d.) to the direction every Eaſter. The ſociety, on the other hand, is bound to publiſh every novelty that ſhall be communicated to it ; to communicate to each member, at the member’s expence, the memoirs, designs, models, productions, and every thing connected with the inſtitution ; to answer all the neceſſary demands made, relating in any reſpect to mining ; and to give its opinion on every plan or project communicated through the medium of an honorary member.</p><p>The great centre of all intelligence is to be at Zellerfield in Hartz, Brunſwſick : but the ſociety is not fixed to any one ſpot ; for every particular ſtate ſome practical mineralogiſt is nominated as director. Among theſe are the names of Baron Born, M. Pallas, M. Charpentier, M. Prebra, and M. Henkel. Their office is to propoſe the members ; to take care that the views of the ſociety are pursued in the different countries where they reſide ; to anſwer the requeſts of the members of their country who are qualified to make them ; in caſe of the death of a director, to chooſe another ; and the majority is to determine where the archives and the ſtrong box is to be placed.</p><p>All the eminent mineralogists in Europe are members of this ſociety. It is erected on ſo liberal and ſo extenſive a plan, that we entertain the higheſt hopes of its ſucceſs ; and have only to add, that we wiſh much</p><p>to ſee the ſtudy of ſeveral other ſciences purſued in the ſame manner.</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Society for the Improvement of Naval Architecture,</hi> was founded in 1791. The object of it is to encourage every uſeful invention and diſcovery relating to naval architecture as far as ſhall be in their power, both by honorary and pecuniary rewards. They have in view particularly to improve the theories of floating bodies and of the reſiſtance of fluids ; to procure draughts and models of different veſſels, together with calculations of their capacity, centre of gravity, tonnage, &amp; c. ; to make obſervations and experiments themſelves, and to point out ſuch obſervations and experiments as appear beſt calculated to further their designs, and moſt deſerving thoſe premiums which the ſociety can bellow. But though the improvement of naval architecture in all its branches be certainly the principal object of this inſtitution, yet the ſociety do not by any means intend to confine themſelves merely to the form and ſtructure of veſſels. Every ſubordinate and collateral purſuit will claim a ſhare of the attention of the ſociety in proportion to its merits ; and whatever may have any tendency to render navigation more ſafe, ſalutary, and even pleaſant, will not be neglected.</p><p>This inſtitution owes its exiſtence to the patriotic diſpoſition and extraordinary attention of Mr Sewel a private citizen of London, who (though engaged in a line of buſineſs totally oppoſite to all concerns of this kind) has been led, by mere accident, to take ſuch occular notice of, and make ſuch obſervations on, the actual ſtate of naval architecture in this country, as naturally occurred to a man of plain underdtanding, zealous for the honour and intereſt of his country, and willing to bestow a portion of that time for the public good, which men of a different deſcription would rather have devoted to their own private advantage. His attention was the more ſeriouſly excited, by finding that it was the opinion of ſome private ſhip-builders, who, in a debate on the failure of one of our naval engagements, pronounced, that ſuch “ would ever be the caſe while that buſineſs (the conſtruction of our ſhips of war) was not ſtudied as a ſcience, but carried on merely by precedent ; that there had not been one improvement in our navy that did not originate with the French, who had naval ſchools and ſeminaries for the ſtudy of it ; and that our ſhips were not a match for thoſe of that nation either singly or in a fleet, &amp; c. &amp; c.”</p><p>In a ſhort time the ſociety were enabled to offer very conſiderable premiums for particular improvements in the conſtruction of our ſhipping, &amp; c. &amp; c. and alſo to encourage our philoſophers, mathematicians, and mechanics, to make ſatisfactory experiments, tending to aſcertain the laws of reſiſtance of water to ſolids of different forms, in all varieties of circumſtance. On this head the reward is not leſs than L. 100 pounds or a gold medal, Other premiums of 50, 30, and 20 guineas, according to the importance or difficulty of the particular ſubject or point of inveſtigation, are likewiſe offered, for different diſcoveries, inventions, or improvements. The terms of admiſſion into the ſociety are a ſubſcription of two guineas annually, or twenty guineas for life.</p><p>5. <hi rend="italic">Society of Artists of Great Britain,</hi> which conſiſts of directors and fellows, was incorporated by charter in 1765, and empowered to purchaſe and hold hands, not<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0595.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0589"/>
exceeding L. 1000 a year. The directors of this ſociety, annually elected, are to conſiſt of 24 perſons, including the preſident, vice-preſident, treaſurer, and ſecretary ; and it is required that they be either painters, ſculptors, architects, or engravers by profeſſion.</p><p>6. <hi rend="italic">Britiſh Society for Extending the Fiſheries and Improving the Sea-Coasts of this Kingdom,</hi> was inſtituted in 1786. The end and deſign of this ſociety will beſt appear from their chatter, of which we preſent an abstract.</p><p>The preamble ſtates, “ the great want oſ improvement in fiſheries, agriculture, and manufactures, in the Highlands and iſlands of North Britain ; the prevalence of emigration from the want of employment in thoſe parts ; the proſpect of a new nurſery of ſeamen, by the eſtabliſhment oſ fiſhing towns and villages in that quarter. The act therefore declares, that the perſons therein named, and every other perſon or perſons who ſhall thereafter become proprietors of the joint ſtock mentioned therein, ſhall be a diſtinct and ſeparate body politic and corporate, by the name of <hi rend="italic">The Britiſh Society for Extending the Fiſheries and Improving the Sea-coasts of this Kingdom :</hi> That the ſaid ſociety may raiſe a capital joint ſtock not exceeding L. 150,000, to be applied to purchasing or otherwiſe acquiring lands and tenements in perpetuity, for the building thereon, and on no other land whatever, free towns, villages, and fiſhing stations : That the joint ſtock ſhall be divided into ſhares of L. 50 each : That no one perſon ſhall in his or her name poſſess more than ten ſhares, or L. 500 : That the ſociety ſhall not borrow any ſum or ſums of money whatſoever : That the ſums to be advanced for this undertaking, and the profits ariſing therefrom, ſhall be divided proportionably to the ſum ſubſcribed ; and that no perſon ſhall be liable for a larger ſum than he or ſhe ſhall have reſpectively subscribed : That one or two ſhares shall intitle to one vote and no more, in perſon or by proxy, at all meetings of proprietors ; three or four ſhares to two votes ; five, six, or ſeven ſhares, to three votes ; eight or nine ſhares to four votes ; and ten ſhares to five votes and no more ; That more perſons than one inclining to hold in their joint names one or more ſhares ſhall be intitled to vote, by one of ſuch perſons, according to the priority of their names, or by proxy : That bodies corporate ſhall vote by proxy under their ſeal : That all perſons holding proxies ſhall be proprietors, and that no one perſon ſhall hold more than five votes by proxy : That the affairs of the ſociety ſhall be managed by a governor, deputy governor, and 13 other directors, to be elected annually on the 25th of March, from among the proprietors of the ſociety, holding at leaſt one full ſhare, by signed lists of their names to be tranſmitted by the proprietors to the ſecretary of the ſociety : that five proprietors, not being governor, director, or other officer, ſhall be in like manner annually elected to audit the accounts of the ſociety ; That there ſhall be one general meeting of the proprietors annually on the 25th oſ March : That occasional general meetings ſhall be called on the requeſt of nine or more proprietors : That the general meetings of the proprietors ſhall make all bye laws and conſtitutions for the government of the ſociety, and for the good and orderly carrying on of the buſineſs of the ſame : That no transfer shall be made of the ſtock of the ſociety for three years from the 10th of Auguſt 1786 : That</p><p>the caſh of the ſociety ſhall be lodged in the hank of England, bank of Scotland, or the royal bank of Scotland : That no director, proprietor, agent, or officer of the ſociety, ſhall retain any firm or ſums of money in his hands beyond the ſpace of 30 days, on any account whatſoever : That all payments by the ſociety ſhall be made by drafts on the ſaid banks, under the bands of the governor or deputy-governor, countersigned by the ſecretary or his deputy, and two or more directors ; And that the books in which the accounts of the ſociety ſhall be kept ſhall be open to all the proprietors.”</p><p>The inſtitution of this public-ſpirited ſociety was in a great meaſure owing to the exertions of the patriotic John Knox ; who, in the courſe of 23 years, traverſed and explored the Highlands of Scotland no leſs than 16 times, and expended ſeveral thouſand pounds of his own fortune in purſuing his patriotic designs.</p><p>7. <hi rend="italic">Britiſh Wool Society.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Britiſh W</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> ool</hi> <hi rend="italic">Society.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Society</hi> <hi rend="italic">Isles,</hi> a cluſter oſ iſles, ſo named by Captain Cook in 1769. They are ſituated between the latitudes of 16. 10. and 16. 55. ſouth, and between the longitudes of 150. 57. and 152, west. They are eight in number ; namely, Otaheite, Huahine, Ulietea, Otaha, Bolabola, Maurua, Toobouai, and Tabooyamanoo or Saunders’s Iſland. The ſoil, productions, people, their language, religion, cuſtoms, and manners, are ſo nearly the ſame as at OTASHEITE, that little need be added here on that ſubject. Nature has been equally bountiful in uncultivated plenty, and the inhabitants are as luxurious and as indolent. A plantain branch is the emblem of peace, and exchanging names the greateſt token of friendlhip. Their dances are more elegant, their dramatic entertainments have ſomething of plot and conſiſtency, and they exhibit temporary occurrences as the objects of praiſe or ſatire ; ſo that the origin of ancient comedy may be already diſcerned among them. The people of Huahine are in general ſtouter and fairer than thoſe of Otaheite, and this iſland is remarkable for its populouſneſs and fertility. Thoſe of Ulietea, on the contrary, are ſmaller and bladker, and much leſs orderly. Captain Cook put on ſhore a Cape ewe at Bolabola, where a ram had been left by the Spaniards ; and alſo an Engliſh boar and ſow, with two goats, at Ulietea, If the valuable animals which have been tranſported thither from Europe ſhould be ſuffered to multiply, no part of the world will equal theſe illands in variety and abundance of refreſhments fot future navigators.</p></div></body></text></TEI>