<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0566.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0560-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SNAKE</label>,
in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anguis</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Serpens.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Method oſ Preſervmg</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> SnaKESs.</hi> When the ſnake is killed, it muſt firſt be waſhed clean, and freed from all filth and naſtineſs ; then it is to be put into a glaſs of a proper fize, the tail firſt, and afterwards the reſt of the body, winding it in ſpiral aſcending circles, and diſposing the back, which is alway the moſt beautiful, outwardly. A thread, connected with a ſmall glaſs bead, is, by the help of a needle, to be passed through the upper jaw from within outwardly, and then through the cork of the bottle, where it muſt be faſtened ; by this means the head will be drawn into a natural poſture, and the mouth kept open by the bead, whereby the teeth, &amp; c. will be diſcovered : the glaſs is then to be filled with rum, and the cork ſealed down to prevent its exhalation. A label, containing the name and properties of the ſnake, is then to be affixed to the wax over the cork; and in this manner the ſnake will make a beautiful appearance, and may be preſerved a great number of years ; nor will the ſpirits impair or change the luſtre of its colours.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0567.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0561"/>
<hi rend="italic">Si-iAKB-Stones, Ammonitae,</hi> in natural hiſtory, the name of a large genus of foſſil ſhells, very few if any of which are yet known in their recent ſtate, or living either on our own or any other ſhores ; ſo that it ſeems wonderful whence ſo vaſt a number and variety of them ſhould be brought into our ſubterranean regions. They ſeem indeed diſperſed in great plenty throughout the world, but nowhere are found in greater numbers, beauty, and variety, than in our iſland.</p><p>Mr Harenberg found prodigious numbers of them on the banks oſ a river in Germany. He traced this river through its ſeveral windings for many miles, and among a great variety of belemnſtse, cornua ammonis, and cochlitæ, of various kinds ; he found alſo great quantities of wood of recent petrifaction, which ſtill preſerved plain marks of the axe by which it had been cut from the trees then growing on the ſhore. The water of this river he found in dry ſeaſons, when its natural ſprings were not diluted with rains, to be conſiderably heavier than common water ; and many experiments ſhowed him that it contained ferruginous, as well as ſtony particles, in great quantity, whence the petrifactions in it appeared the leſs wonderful, though many of them of recent date.</p><p>Oſ the cornua ammonis, or ſerpent-ſtones, he there obſerved more than 30 different species. They lie immerſed in a bluiſh foſſil ſtone, of a ſoft texture and fatty appearance, in prodigious numbers, and of a great variety of ſizes, from the larger known forts down to ſuch as could not be ſeen without very accurate inſpection or the aſſiſtance of a microſcope. Such as lie in the ſofteſt of theſe ſtones are ſoft like their matrix, and eaſily crumble to pieces ; others are harder. In a piece of this ſtone, of the bigneſs of a finger, it is common to find 30 or more of theſe foſſils ; and often they are ſeen only in form of white ſpecks, ſo minute that their figure cannot be diſtinguiſhed till examined by the microſcope.</p><p>They all conſiſt of ſeveral volutae, which are different in number in the different species, and their striae alſo are extremely various ; some very deep with very high ridges between them, others very flight ; ſome ſtraight, others crooked ; others undulated, and ſome terminating in dots, tubercles, or cavities, towards the back, and others having tubercles in two or three places. They are all compoſed of a great number of chambers or cells, in the manner of the <hi rend="italic">nautilus Gracorum,</hi> each having a communication with the others, by means of a pipe or ſiphunculus. There is a ſmall white ſhell fiſh of Barbadoes, which ſeems truly a recent animal of this genus ; and in the Eaſt Indies there is another alſo, ſmall and greyiſh ; but the large and beautifully marked ones are found only foſſil.</p><p>They are compoſed of various foſſil bodies, often of quarry ſtone, ſometimes of the matter of the common pyrites, and of a great variety of other ſubſtances ; and though they appear uſually mere ſtones, yet in ſome the pearly part of the original ſhell is preſerved in all its beauty. Sometimes alſo, while the outer ſubſtance is of the matter of the pyrites, or other coarſe, ſtony, or mineral matter, the inner cavity is filled with a pure white ſpar of the common plated texture. This gives a great beauty to the ſpecimen. The cornua ammonis, or snake-ſtones, are found in many parts of England, particularly in Yorkſhire, where they are very plentiful in the alum rocks of ſeveral ſizes.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SHAKE-Root,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Polygala.</hi> <hi rend="italic">SNAKE-Weed,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Polygonum,</hi> SNAPEDRAGON, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Antirrhinum.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>