<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0520.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0514-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SIVA</label>,
a name given by the Hindoos to the Supreme</p><p>Being, when conſidered as the avenger or deſtroyer. Sir William Jones has ſhown that in ſeveral reſpects the character of Jupiter and Siva are the ſame.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Asiatic Researches,.</p></note> As Jupiter overthrew the Titans and giants, ſo did Siva overthrow the Daityas, or children of Diti, who frequently rebelled againſt Heaven ; and as during the conteſt the god of Olympus was furniſhed with lightning and thunderbolts by an eagle, ſo Brahma, who is ſometimes repreſented riding on the Garuda, or eagle, presented the god of deſtruction with fiery ſhafts. Siva alſo correſponds with the Stygian Jove, or Pluto ; for, if we can rely on a Perſian tranſlation of the Bhagavat, the ſovereign of Pâtâla, or the infernal regions, is the king of ſerpents, named <hi rend="italic">Seſhanaga,</hi> who is exhibited in painting and ſculpture, with a diadem and ſceptre, in the same manner as Pluto. There is yet another attribute of Siva, or Mahadéva, by which he is viſibly diſtinguiſhed in the drawings and temples of Bengal. To deſtroy, according to the Vedantis of India, the Sufis of Perſia, and many philoſophers of our European ſchools, is only to generate and reproduce in another form. Hence the god of deſtruction is holden in this country to preside over generation, as a ſymbol of which he rides on a white bull. Can we doubt that the loves and feats of Jupiter Genitor (not forgetting the white bull of Europa), and his extraordinary title of Lapis, for which no ſatisfactory reaſon is commonly given, have a connection with the Indian philoſophy and mythology ?</p></div></body></text></TEI>