<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0622.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0616-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOUP</label>,
a ſtrong decoction of fleſh or other ſubſtances.</p><p><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Chaptal's Chemistry.</p></note> Portable or dry ſoup is a kind of cake formed by boiling the gelatinous parts of animal ſubſtances till the watery parts are evaporated. This ſpecies of ſoup is chiefly uſed at ſea, and has been found of great advantage. The following receipt will ſhow how it is prepared.</p><p>Of calves feet take 4 ; leg of beef 12 lbs. ; knuckle of veal 3 lbs. ; and leg of mutton 10 lbs. Theſe are to be boiled in a ſuſſicſent quantity of water, and the ſcum taken off as uſual ; after which the ſoup is to be ſeparated from the meat by ſtraining and preſſure. The meat is then to be boiled a ſecond time in other water ; and the two decoctions, being added together·, muſt be left to cool, in order that the ſat may be exactly ſeparated. The ſoup muſt then be clarified with five or fix whites of eggs, and a ſuſſicſent quantity of common ſalt added. The liquor is then ſtrained through flannel, and evaporated on the water bath to the conſiſtence of a very thick paſte ; alter which it is ſpread rather thin upon a ſmooth ſtone, then cut into cakes, and laſtly dried in a ſtove until it becomes brittle: theſe cakes are kept in well cloſed bottles. The ſame proceſs may be uſed to make a portable ſoup of the fleſh of poultry ; and aromatic herbs may be uſed as a ſeaſoning, if thought proper.</p><p>Theſe tablets or cakes may be kept four or five years. When intended to be uſed, the quantity of half an ounce is put into a large glaſs of boiling water, which is to be covered, and ſet upon hot aſhes for a quarter of an hour, or until the whole is entirely dissolved. It forms an excellent ſoup, and requires no addition but a ſmall quantity of ſalt.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SOUR-croute.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">CroutE.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SOUR-Gourd,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">African Calabash-tree.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Adan-</hi> SONIA.</p></div></body></text></TEI>