<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0612.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0606-09" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOPHISM</label>,
in logic, a ſpecious argument having the appearance of truth, but leading to falſehood. Sophiſms are reduced by Ariſtotle into eight claſſes, an arrangement so juſt and comprehenſive, that it is equally proper in preſent as in former times. 1. <hi rend="italic">ignoratio elenchi,</hi> in which the ſophiſt ſeems to determine the queſtion, while he only does it in appearance. Thus the queſtion, “ Whether excels of wine be hurtful?” ſeems to be determined by proving, that wine revives the ſpirits and gives a man courage: but the principal point is here kept out of sight ; for ſtill it may be hurtful to health, to fortune, and reputation. 2. <hi rend="italic">Petitio principii,</hi> a begging of the queſtion, or taking for granted that which remains to be proved, as if any one ſhould undertake to prove that the soul is extended through all the parts of the body, becauſe it reſides in every member. This is affirming the ſame thing in different words. 3. Reaſoning in a circle ; as when the Roman Catholics prove the Scriptures to be the word of God by the authority of the church, and the authority of the church from the Scriptures. 4. <hi rend="italic">Non causa pro cauſa,</hi> or the aſſigning of a falſe cauſe to any effect. Thus the ſuppoſed principle, that nature abhors a vacuum, was applied to explain the riſing of water in a pump before Galileo diſcovered that it was owing to the preſſure of the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0613.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s04-0607"/>
atmoſphere. In this way the vulgar aſcribe accidents to divine vengeance, and the heresies and infidelity of modern times are ſaid to be owing to learning. 5. <hi rend="italic">Fallacia accidentis,</hi> in which the ſophiſt repreſents what is merely accidental as eſſential to the nature of the ſubject. This is nearly allied to the former, and is committed by the Mahometans and Roman Catholics. The Mahometans forbid wine, becauſe it is ſometimes the occaſion of drunkenneſs and quarrels ; and the Roman Catholics prohibit the reading of the Bible, becauſe it has ſometimes promoted hereſies. 6. By deducing an univerſal assertion from what is true only in particular circumſtances, and the reverſe ; thus ſome men argue, “ tranſcribers have committed many errors in copying the Scriptures, therefore they are not to be depended on.” 7. By aſſerting anything in a compound ſenſe which is only true in a divided ſenſe; ſo when the Scriptures assure us, that the worſt of ſinners may be ſaved, it does not mean that they ſhall be ſaved while they remain ſinners, but that if they repent they may be ſaved. 8. By an abuſe of the ambiguity of words. Thus Mr Hume reaſons in his Eſſay on Miracles : “ Experience is our only guide in reaſoning concerning matters of fact ; now we know from experience, that the laws of nature are fixed and invariable. On the other hand, teſtimony is variable and often falſe; therefore ſince our evidence for the reality of miracles reſts ſolely on teſtimony which is variable, and our evidence for the uniformity of the laws of nature is invariable, miracles are not to be believed.” The ſophiſtry of this reaſoning depends on the ambiguity of the word <hi rend="italic">experience,</hi> which in the firſt propoſition ſignifies the maxims which we form from our own obſervation and reflection ; in the ſecond it is confounded with teſtimony ; for it is by the teſtimony of others, as well as our own obſervation, that we learn whether the laws of nature are variable or invariable. The Eſſay on Miracles may be recommended to thoſe who wiſh to ſee more examples of sophiſtry ; as we believe moſt of the eight ſpecies of ſophifms which we have mentioned are well illuſtrated by examples in that eſſay.</p></div></body></text></TEI>