<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-29T16:51:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in 1909, the liabilities on account of loans upon mortgage and otherwise amounting at the latter date to £662,235. The assets of the Trade Departments were valued at <hi rend="italic">£</hi>110,657 in 1909.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Statistics of Spiritual Operations </hi>(<hi rend="italic">Compiled from the "S.A. Year Book, 1910").</hi></p><p>supreme duty of self-sacrifice for the sake of the salvation of others.</p><p>The Army is under the control of the General for the time being, who issues all orders and regulations. Large powers devolve upon other officers, such as the “ Chief of the Staff,” the “ Foreign Secretary,” and the “ Chancellor,” who direct affairs from the “ International Headquarters ” in London. The system of government is autocratic, “ unquestioning obedience ” being required throughout all ranks. The Army is divided, usually in harmony with national boundaries, into “ territories,” each under a “ Commissioner,” with headquarters in the capital of the country. The Territories are generally divided into “ Provinces ’’ and these again into “ Divisions,” which include a number of corps, each supporting its own “ Captain ” and “ Lieutenant.” The “ soldiers ” or members are drawn from all classes of the community. The property of the Army in the United Kingdom is held by the General for the time being, for the benefit of the Army exclusively, he being constituted the sole trustee of the property, in the disposal of which and in the appointment of his successor he is placed under the government of a deed poll, executed by Booth while the body was still known as “ The Christian Mission,” and enrolled in the Court of Chancery in August 1878. In other countries various modifications have been necessary, but the General’s ultimate con</p><p>trol has been practically assured. A further deed poll providing for the removal of a General in the contingency of “ mental incapacity ” or other “ unfitness,” and for the election of a successor, was executed by Booth in July 1904.</p><p>Funds are raised from 'the voluntary offerings of the corps, from open-air and other collections, from friends interested in evangelical and charitable work, and from the profits on publications and general trading. The financial statements of the various national headquarters funds are annually published, certified by public accountants, in each country. In 1909 the general income and expenditure account of International Headquarters in London dealt with a total of £64,345.</p><p>Details of the aggregate income raised in the United Kingdom by the corps are not published. The annual Self-Denial offering (Great Britain) was £12,663 in 1888, £72,562 in 1906 and £69,034 in 1910. The value of the assets of the spiritual work in the United Kingdom increased from £558,992 in 1891 to £1,357,706</p><table><row><cell/><cell>Corps and Outposts.</cell><cell>Officers and Cadets.</cell></row><row><cell>The British Isles	</cell><cell>1447</cell><cell>3.191 <hi rend="superscript">l</hi></cell></row><row><cell>The United States .	.</cell><cell>871</cell><cell>2,983</cell></row><row><cell>South America and West Indies</cell><cell>128</cell><cell>188</cell></row><row><cell>Canada and Newfoundland .</cell><cell>465</cell><cell>950</cell></row><row><cell>Australasia and Java ....</cell><cell>1283</cell><cell>1,721</cell></row><row><cell>India, Ceylon, Japan and Korea .</cell><cell>2584</cell><cell>1,626</cell></row><row><cell>South Africa and St Helena .</cell><cell>113</cell><cell>278</cell></row><row><cell>France, Belgium, Switzerland and</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Italy	</cell><cell>374</cell><cell>499</cell></row><row><cell>Germany and Holland</cell><cell>248</cell><cell>772</cell></row><row><cell>Sweden, Norway, Finland, Denmark</cell><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>and Iceland	</cell><cell>1067</cell><cell>1,513</cell></row><row><cell>Gibraltar and Malta....</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>8582</cell><cell>13,726</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Employees (without rank), 6269.</cell></row></table><p>Booth’s scheme for <hi rend="italic">Social Relief,</hi> described in <hi rend="italic">In Darkest England, and the Way Out</hi> (1890), attracted wide-spread interest,</p><p>and was started with subscriptions amounting to over £100,000. A separate deed poll, making the General sole trustee, was executed by Booth in regard to the property and funds of this branch of work. Since then, both in Great Britain and abroad, the scheme has been actively carried on. The amount received in the year ending 30th September 1909 for cheap food and lodging in the United Kingdom was returned at £42,022 for the men’s work, and £6417 for the women’s. Large numbers of unemployed, ex-criminal and other needy persons have been aided or dealt with. In the year ending 30th September 1909, the number of persons received into the “ elevators ” or factories was reported as 6425, of women and girls received into rescue homes as 2559. The farm colony at Hadleigh in Essex has a large acreage under cultivation, with fruit and market gardens and various industrial undertakings. The emigration department, although a development of the Darkest England Scheme, has no connexion with the rescue work; in 1907 the passage money received amounted to £85,014, and in 1909 to £38,179. An “ anti-suicide bureau ” was opened in 1907, and at Boxted, near Colchester, a scheme for Small Holdings has been initiated. In 1909 the value of the property held under the Darkest England Scheme in the United Kingdom was returned at £329,645, and the income of the central fund at £50,594.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Summary of Social Operations throughout the World (Compiled from the</hi> “ <hi rend="italic">S.A. Year-Book, 1910 ”).</hi></p><table><row><cell/><cell cols="4">Number of Institutions.</cell></row><row><cell/><cell><p>United</p><p>Kingdom.</p></cell><cell>Abroad.</cell><cell>Total.</cell><cell><p>Total</p><p>Accommo</p><p>dation.</p></cell></row><row><cell>Men’s Work—</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>. Shelters and Food Depots .</cell><cell>31</cell><cell>156</cell><cell>187</cell><cell>18,531</cell></row><row><cell>Labour Bureaus ....</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>50</cell><cell>58</cell><cell>. .</cell></row><row><cell>Labour Homes and Factories .</cell><cell>28</cell><cell>117</cell><cell>145</cell><cell>4.936</cell></row><row><cell>Ex-criminal Homes </cell><cell>. <hi rend="superscript">1</hi></cell><cell>18</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>486</cell></row><row><cell>Farm Colonies ....</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>17</cell><cell/></row><row><cell>Women’s Work—</cell><cell/><cell/><cell/><cell/></row><row><cell>Rescue and Maternity Homes .</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>107</cell><cell>139</cell><cell>3.469</cell></row><row><cell>Shelters and Food Depots</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>1,934</cell></row><row><cell>Children’s Homes and Crèches .</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>57</cell><cell>59</cell><cell/></row><row><cell>Slum Posts	....</cell><cell>44</cell><cell>103</cell><cell>147</cell><cell>. .</cell></row><row><cell>Other Social Institutions . .</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>87</cell><cell>104</cell><cell/></row><row><cell>Total Institutions</cell><cell>174</cell><cell>730</cell><cell>904</cell><cell>29,356</cell></row><row><cell>Total number of officers engaged exclusively</cell><cell cols="3">in social work, 2520.</cell><cell/></row></table><p>There are a number of subsidiary branches of work, such as the Young People’s Legion, and the Naval and Military League for work among men in the military, naval and merchant services. In England there is a bank (the Reliance Bank, Ltd.) and a Life Assurance Society, the funds of the latter amounting to £566,309 in 1909. All officers and many of the rank and file wear a uniform. Music is universally employed. While the organization has succeeded in securing recognition and favour in high places both in England and abroad, it has been seriously criticized at times, notably by Huxley and others in 1890-1891, and more recently by J. Manson in <hi rend="italic">The Salvation Army and the Public,</hi> a work which led to much public discussion of the Army’s religious, social and financial operations and methods. In 1910 some resignations took place among the higher officials.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Authorities.</hi>—William Booth, <hi rend="italic">Orders and Regulations for Soldiers ; Orders and Regulations for Field Officers; Orders and Regulations for Staff Officers', Salvation Soldiery', Interview with W. E. Gladstone', In Darkest England and the Way Out</hi> (1890); Bramwell Booth, <hi rend="italic">Social Reparation', Servants of All</hi> (1899); Booth-Tucker, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Catherine Booth</hi> (1892); Railton, <hi rend="italic">Heathen England', Twenty-one Years' Salvation Army',</hi> Arnold White, <hi rend="italic">Truth about the Salvation Army</hi> (1892, 1900 and 1906); <hi rend="italic">The Great Idea</hi> (1909; 2nd ed., 1910); T. F. G. Coates, <hi rend="italic">The Life Story of General Booth </hi>(<hi rend="italic">2nd</hi> ed., 1906); Harold Begbie, <hi rend="italic">Broken Earthenware</hi> (1909); various reports and accounts; <hi rend="italic">The War Cry, The Social Gazette, The Salvation Army Year Book, &amp;c.</hi> Criticism; Thomas H. Huxley, “Social Diseases and Worse Remedies” in <hi rend="italic">Collected Essays,</hi> vol. ix. (1895); John</p><p><hi rend="superscript">l</hi> Officers and employees (British Isles), 7538.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">1</hi> In the United Kingdom ex-criminals are now received in the ordinary labour homes and factories.</p></body></text></TEI>