<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-29T16:52:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the clearness with which he realized that the independence of each state could only be secured by the co-operation of all, and in the perseverance with which he carried his views into execution he showed himself a far-seeing and honest statesman.</p><p>See W. Pilling, <hi rend="italic">Emancipation of South America</hi> (London, 1893), a translation of B. Mitre’s life of San Martin; P. B. Figueroa, <hi rend="italic">Diccionario biografico de Chile</hi> (Santiago, 1888) and J. B. Suarez, <hi rend="italic">Rαsgos biograficos de hombres notables de Chile</hi> (Valparaiso, 1886), both giving sketches of prominent characters in Chilean history. See also works on the period mentioned under <hi rend="smallcaps">Chile : </hi><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.</hi></p><p>SANMICHELE, MICHELE (1484-1559), Italian architect, was born in San Michele near Verona. He learnt the elements of his profession from his father Giovanni and his uncle Bartolommeo, who both practised as architects at Verona with much success. He went at an early age to Rome to study classic sculpture and architecture. Among his earliest works are the duomo of Montefiascone (an octagonal building surmounted with a cupola), the church of San Domenico at Orvieto, and several palaces at both places. He also executed a fine tomb in S. Domenico. He was no less distinguished as a military architect, and was much employed by the signoria of Venice, not only at home, but also in strengthening the fortifications of Corfu, Cyprus and Candia. One of Sanmichele’s most graceful designs is the Cappella de’ Peregrini in the church of S. Bernardino at Verona—square outside and circular within, of the Corinthian order. He built a great number of fine palaces at Verona, including those of Canossa, Bevilacqua and Pompei, as well as the graceful Ponte Nuovo. In 1527 Sanmichele began to transform the fortifications of Verona according to the newer system of corner bastions—a system for the advancement of which he did much valuable service. His last work, begun in 1559, was the round church of the Madonna di Campagna, 1½ m. from Verona on the road to Venice. Like most other distinguished architects of his time he wrote a work on classic architecture, <hi rend="italic">I Cinque Ordini dell' architettura,</hi> printed at Verona in 1735.</p><p>See Ronzani and Luciolli, <hi rend="italic">Fabbriche . . . di M. Sanmichele </hi>(Venice. 1832) ; and Selva, <hi rend="italic">Εlogio di Sanmichele</hi> (Rome, 1814).</p><p>SAN MIGUEL, the capital of the department of San Miguel, Salvador; 80 m. E. by S. of San Salvador, near the right bank of the Rio Grande, and at the foot of the volcano of San Miguel or Jucuapa (7120 ft.). Pop. (1905) about 25,000. San Miguel is an important and attractive city, although the extensive swamps in the Rio Grande Valley render malaria common. It possesses several handsome churches, municipal buildings, law courts and two well-equipped hospitals. Near it are the ruins of an ancient Indian town. San Miguel has a flourishing trade in indigo, grain, rubber and cattle. Its port is La Union (<hi rend="italic">q.v.</hi>)<hi rend="italic">.</hi> San Miguel was founded in 1530 by Spanish settlers, and became a city in 1586. Its fairs formerly attracted merchants from all parts of Salvador, Guatemala and Honduras, and it is now third in size among the cities of the republic.</p><p>SAN MIGUEL DE MAYUMO, a town of the province of Bulacan, Luzon, Philippine Islands, about 40 m. N. of Manila. Pop. (1903) 14,919. In 1903, after the census had been taken, San IIdefonso (pop. 5326) was annexed to San Miguel. It has a cool and very healthy climate, and commands a beautiful view of the surrounding country. The soil is very fertile, and many of the inhabitants have acquired much wealth from the cultivation of rice. Sugar-cane, Indian corn and cotton are also produced in abundance, and cattle arc raised. Near the town are iron mines and quarries of limestone, and on the neighbouring mountains are forests containing valuable hardwood timber. About 8 m. N.E. are the medicinal springs of Sibul, to which large numbers of patients from the neighbouring provinces come. The San Miguel river, which flows near, affords a means of transportation, and the town has considerable commerce. Some beautiful furniture is made out of the hardwood from the mountains, and cotton fabrics are woven in considerable quantities by the women. The principal language is Tagalog. The chief buildings were destroyed in 1901 in a fire started by a band of thieves.</p><p>SAN MINIATO, a town and episcopal see of Tuscany, Italy, in the province of Florence, 26 m. W. by S. of Florence by the</p><p>railway to Pisa, 512 ft. above sea-level, on a hill <hi rend="italic">2</hi> m. S. of the railway. Pop. (1901) 4421 (town); 20,242 (commune). Its cathedral dates from the 10th century. It was remodelled in 1488, and has a façade decorated with disks of majolica. It manufactures glass, olive oil, leather and hats. It has a castle of the emperor Frederick I., the residence of the imperial governors of Tuscany from 1226 to 1286, and from them bears the name of San Miniato al Tedesco.</p><p>SANNAZARO, JACOPO (1458-1530), Italian poet of the Renaissance, was born in 1458 at Naples of a noble family, said to have been of Spanish origin, which had its seat at San Nazaro near Pavia. His father died during the boyhood of Jacopo, who was brought up at Nocera Inferiore. He afterwards studied at Naples under Giovanni Pontanus, when, according to the fashion of the time, he assumed the name Actius Syncerus, by which he is occasionally referred to. After the death of his mother he went abroad—driven, we are told, by the pangs of despised love for a certain Carmosina, whom he has celebrated in his verse under various names; but of the details of his travels nothing is recorded. On his return he speedily achieved fame as a poet and place as a courtier, receiving from Frederick III. as a country residence the Villa Mergillina near Naples. When his patron was compelled to take refuge in France in 1501 he was accompanied by Sannazaro, who did not return to Italy till after his death (1504). The later years of the poet seem to have been spent at Naples. He died on the 27th of April 1530.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Arcadia</hi> of Sannazaro, begun in early life and published in 1504, is a somewhat affected and insipid Italian pastoral, in which in alternate prose and verse the scenes and occupations of pastoral life are described. See Scherillo’s edition (Turin, 1888). His now seldom read Latin poem <hi rend="italic">De partu Virginis,</hi> which gained for him the name of the “ Christian Virgil,” appeared in 1526, and his collected <hi rend="italic">Sonetti e canzoni</hi> in 1530.</p><p>SAN NICOLÁS DE LOS ARROYOS, a town and river port of Argentina, in the province of Buenos Aires, on the W. bank of the Paraná, 150 m. by rail N.W. of the city of Buenos Aires. Pop. (1904, estimate), 18,000. It is a flourishing commercial town, and a port of call both for river and ocean-going steamers of medium tonnage. It is a station on the Buenos Aires &amp; Rosario, and the terminus of a branch from Pergamino of the Central Argentine railway, and exports wheat, flour, wool and frozen mutton. The town is the judicial centre for the northern district of Buenos Aires. San NicoIás was founded in 1749 by José de Aguillar on lands given for that purpose by his wife (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Ugarte). Its growth was very slow until near the end of the 19th century.</p><p>SAN PABLO, a town of the province of Laguna, Luzon, Philippine Islands, 9½ m. S. of Laguna de Bay and about 35 m. S.S.E. of Manila. Pop. (1903) 22,612. It is an important road centre, and in the vicinity are five small mountain lakes. Coconut palms grow in great abundance in the town and vicinity, and copra is the principal product; hemp and, to a less degree, rice, are grown here. The language is Tagalog.</p><p>SANQUHAR, a royal and police burgh of Dumfriesshire, Scotland. Pop. (1901) 1379. It is situated on the Nith, 26 m. N.W. of Dumfries by the Glasgow &amp; South-Western railway. It became a burgh of barony in 1484 and a royal burgh in 1596, and was the scene of the exhibition of the Covenanters’ Declaration, attached to the market cross in 1680 by Richard Cameron and in 1685 by James Renwick. The industries include coalmining and the making of bricks and tiles, spades and shovels. The coal-field, measuring 7 m. long by 2½ m. broad, is the most extensive in the shire and is the main source of supply for Dumfries and other towns. The cattle and sheep fairs are important, and an agricultural show is held every May. Sanquhar Castle, on a hill overlooking the Nith, once belonged to the Crichtons, ancestors of the marquess of Bute, but is now a ruin. Eliock House, in the parish, was the birthplace of James (“ the Admirable ”) Crichton in 1560.</p><p>SAN REMO, a seaport of Liguria, Italy, in the province of Porto Maurizio, on the Riviera di Ponente, 9¾ m. É. of Ventimiglia by rail, and 84 m. S.W. of Genoa. Pop. (1901) 17,114 (town); 20,027 (commune). Climbing the slope of a steep hill</p></body></text></TEI>