<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-29T16:51:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>It may appear that the grant of salvage to ships of war, the duty of whose commanders it is, according to the naval instructions, “ if possible, to rescue any British vessel which he may find attacked or captured by the enemy, ” needs some justification. Objections on this ground have never been seriously treated, it being urged that it is poh*tic to encourage the undertaking of such enterprises, even where they coincide with the path of duty. Where, however, a transport was rescued from under the guns of an enemy by a ship of war, under whose charge she sailed, salvage was refused on the ground that the salvor was only doing what he was bound to do (the “ <hi rend="italic">Belle,</hi> ” Edw. 66). So no salvage is due to a crew who rescue a ship from mutineers, this being only their duty under a subsisting contract (the “ <hi rend="italic">Governor Raffles</hi>,” 2 Dod. 14). On the other hand, a crew who rescue their ship from the prize crew of a belligerent are entitled to salvage, since the capture discharges them from their contract with the owner, and they act as volunteers (the “ <hi rend="italic">Two Friends</hi>,” 1 C. Rob. 271). In the case of a neutral captured by one belligerent and recaptured by the other, which has been already alluded to, no salvage is as a rule allowed, upon the supposition that if the vessel had been carried into the port of the enemy justice would have been done and the vessel restored. In the case of the French war at the opening of the 19th century no such supposition existed, and salvage was usually awarded on the recapture of neutral property from the French.	(M. Bτ.)</p><p>SALVAGE CORPS. The London Salvage Corps is maintained by the fire offices of London. The corps was first formed in 1865 and began operations in March 1866. The staff of the corps when first formed consisted of 64. Since that time, owing to the many improvements that have taken place in the system of dealing with salvage, and the increase in the work to be done, the corps has necessarily been strengthened, and the staff now numbers over 100. The various stations of the corps are well placed, and the Metropolis has been mapped out so that when a fire takes place it may be attended to at the earliest possible moment. The headquarters are situated at Watling Street, which is called the No. 1 station, and this station protects the City of London enclosed by the Euston Road, Tottenham Court Road, City Road and the river Thames; this is known as the “ B ” district. No. 2 station is at Commercial Road, and attends to the whole of the E. and N.E. portion of London to the N. of the Thames, and is known as the “ C ” district. No. 3 station, opposite the headquarters of the Metropolitan Fire Brigade Station in the Southwark Bridge Road, protects the whole of S. London, and is known as the “ D ” district. No. 4 station, at Shaftesbury Avenue, is called the “ A ’’ district, and covers the West End and Kensington. Finally, No. 5 station, in Upper Street, Islington, guards the parish of Islington. The working staff, which is mainly recruited from the royal navy, consists of the chief officer and a superintendent, foreman and crew of men at each station. The stations of the corps arc connected by telephone with the fire brigade stations from whence the “ calls ” are received. In addition to the home staff, there is also a staff constantly employed during the daytime in inspecting docks, wharves, Manchester goods and uptown warehouses, and reports are made weekly to the committee.</p><p>Generally speaking, the work of the Corps may be divided into two distinct classes—(1) services at fires; (2) watching and working salvage.</p><p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Services at Fires</hi> form the most important feature of the work. Much depends upon the method of dealing with the salvage. If, for instance, a large Manchester goods warehouse was on fire in the top part, it would be very little advantage to the offices interested in the risk if the men were set to work removing the stock off the ground floor. The best method would be to cover up with tarpaulin all goods there, and prevent the water from collecting on the lower floors. It will be gathered that the most important work of the corps is to prevent damage to goods, and that water is mostly looked after. The damage from fire is left almost entirely to the fire brigade. The traps, which immediately on receipt of an alarm proceed to the scene of the fire with their crew of men, carry every kind of appliance</p><p>for the saving of goods from destruction by fire or damage by water, as well as lime-light apparatus for use in working after the fire has been extinguished, thus enabling the men to note the position of dangerous walls, &amp;c. ; and a portable coal-gas apparatus, which can be employed in the interior of buildings when the ordinary means of illumination has failed; in addition to ambulance appliances for emergencies.</p><p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Working Salvage.—</hi>When a fire takes place, a man is left behind in charge of the salvage if the property is insured; or if that fact cannot be ascertained, but it appears probable that it is, a man is left until the information is obtained later. The duty, if an important one, is divided into a day and night duty. This enables an experienced man to be sent on day duty to meet the surveyor, and to carry out his instructions regarding the working out of the salvage; and a junior man at night. The day man, if working out salvage, would employ a number of men called strangers, over whom he acts as a kind of foreman. The “ working out ” may take the form of dividing up damaged goods into lots ready for a sale to be held by the surveyor, or of sifting over the débris to find remains of certain articles claimed for. If, for instance, a large fire occurred at a pianoforte manufacturer’s, and the debris was all in one common heap, the London Salvage Corps might have to arrange certain quantities of pegs and wires in order to give an idea of the number of pianos before the fire. The watching continues until the loss is settled, when the charge of the premises is given over to the assured.</p><p>There are also salvage corps on similar lines, but on a smaller scale, in Liverpool and Glasgow.	(C. J. F.)</p><p>SALVANDY, NARCISSE ACHILLE (1795-1856), French politician, was bom at Condom (Gers)on the 11th of June 1795, of a poor family Irish by extraction. He entered the army in 1813, and next year was admitted to the household troops of Louis XVIII. A patriotic pamphlet on <hi rend="italic">La Coalition et la France</hi> (1816) attracted the attention of Decazes, who employed him to disseminate his views in the press, and he waged war against the Viflèle ministry of 1822-1828. Under the July monarchy he sat almost continuously in the Chamber of Deputies from 1830 till 1848, giving his support to the Conservative party. Minister of education in the Molé cabinet of 1837-1839, and again in 1845, he superintended the reconstitution of the Council of Education, the foundation of the French School at Athens and the restoration of the École des Chartes. For short periods in 1841 and 1843 he was ambassador at Madrid and at Turin, and became a member of the French Academy in 1835. Under the Empire he took no part in public affairs, and died at Graveron (Eure) on the 16th of December 1856.</p><p>SALVATION ARMY, a religious philanthropic organization founded by William Booth (<hi rend="italic">q.υ.</hi>)<hi rend="italic">,</hi> who in 1865 began to hold meetings for preaching in the streets in London and in tents, music halls, theatres and other hired buildings. Large numbers attended, many of whom had never entered a place of worship, and presently an organized society was formed called “The Christian Mission.” Booth was assisted by his wife, Catherine Booth, a woman of remarkable gifts, who won for the new movement the sympathy of many among the cultured classes. In 1878 the Mission, which had spread beyond London, was reorganized on a quasi-military basis, and the title of “ The Salvation Army ” was definitely adopted in June 1880. The local societies became “ Corps,” and their evangelists “ Field Officers,” with Booth as “ General ” of the whole body. The spiritual operations of the Army at once rapidly expanded in spite of much disorderly opposition in some places. In 1878 there were 75 corps and 120 officers in the United Kingdom, the amount contributed by the outside public being £1925. Since then the number of corps and officers has greatly increased. Very large numbers who have “ professed conversion ” are reported annually. No figures of membership, however, are published. In doctrine, the Army is in harmony with the main principles of the evangelical bodies, “ as embodied in the three creeds of the Church.” Its preaching is practical and direct, asseverating the reality of Sin, “ the everlasting punishment of the wicked,” and Redemption. The Army proclaims the</p></body></text></TEI>