<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-29T16:53:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SANTILLANA, IÑIGO LOPEZ DE MENDOZA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquis of </hi>(1398-1458), Castilian poet, was bom at Carrión de los Condes in Old Castile on the 19th of August 1398. His father, Diego Hurtado de Mendoza, grand admiral of Castile, having died in 1405, the boy was educated under the eye of his mother, Doña Leonor de la Vega, a woman of great strength of character. From his eighteenth year onwards he became an increasingly prominent figure at the court of Juan II. of Castile, distinguishing himself in both civil and military service; he was created marques de Santillana and conde del Real de Manzanares for the part he took in the battle of Olmedo (19th of May 1455). In the struggle of the Castilian nobles against the influence of the constable Álvaro de Luna he showed great moderation, but in 1452 he joined the combination which effected the fall of the favourite in the following year. From the death of Juan II. in 1454 Mendoza took little part in public affairs, devoting himself mainly to the pursuits of literature and to pious meditation. He died at Guadalajara on the 25th of March 1458.</p><p>Mendoza shares with Juan de Villalpando the distinction of introducing the sonnet into Castile, but his productions in this class are conventional metrical exercises, He was much more successful in the <hi rend="italic">serranilla</hi> and <hi rend="italic">vaqueirα</hi>—highland pastorals after the Provençal manner. His rhymed collection of <hi rend="italic">Proverbios de gtoriosa doctrina é fructuosa enseñanza</hi> was prepared for the use of Don Enrique, the heir-apparent. To the same didactic category belong the hundred and eighty stanzas entitled <hi rend="italic">Dialogo de Bias contra Fortuna,</hi> while the <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal de Privados</hi> is a bitter denunciation of Alvaro de Luna. The <hi rend="italic">Comedieta de Ponza</hi> is a Dantesque dream-dialogue, in octave stanzas <hi rend="italic">(de arte mayor),</hi> founded on the disastrous sea-fight off Ponza in 1425, when the kings of Aragon and Navarre and the Infante Enrique were taken prisoners by the Genoese. The three last-named compositions are the best of Santillana’s more ambitious poems, but they are deficient in the elegant simplicity of the <hi rend="italic">serranillas.</hi> These unpretentious songs are in every Spanish anthology, and are familiar even to uneducated Spaniards.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.—</hi><hi rend="italic">Obras,</hi> edited by José Amador de los Ríos (Madrid, 1852); M. Menéndez v Pelayo, <hi rend="italic">Antología de poetas liricas Castellanos</hi> (Madrid, 1894), vol. v. pp. 78-144; B. Sanvisenti, <hi rend="italic">I Primi Influssi di Dante, del Petrarca e del Boccaccio sulla letteratura spagnuola</hi> (Milan, 1902), pp. 127-186.</p><p>SANTINI, GIOVANNI (1787-1877), Italian astronomer, was born on the 30th of January 1787 at Caprese, in the province of Arezzo. He was from 1813 professor of astronomy at the university and director of the observatory at Padua. He wrote <hi rend="italic">Elementi di astronomia (2</hi> vols. 1820, 2nd ed. 1830), <hi rend="italic">Teoria degli stromenti ottici</hi> (2 vols. 1828), and many scientific memoirs and notices, among which are five catalogues of telescopic stars between +10° and -15° declination, from observations made at the Padua observatory. He died on the 26th of June 1877.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Astronomische Nachrichten,</hi> No. 90; <hi rend="italic">Month. Not. Roy. Astr. Soc.,</hi> No. 38.</p><p>SANTLEY, SIR CHARLES (1834-	), English vocalist,</p><p>son of an organist at Liverpool, was born on the 28th of February 1834. He was given a thorough musical education, and having determined to adopt the career of a singer, he went in 1855 to Milan and studied under Gaetano Nava. He had a fine baritone voice, and while in Italy he began singing small parts in opera. In 1857 he returned to London, and on 16th November made his first appearance in the part of Adam in <hi rend="italic">The Creation </hi>at St Martin’s Hall. In 1858, after appearing in January in <hi rend="italic">The Creation,</hi> he sang the title-part in <hi rend="italic">Elijah</hi> in March, both at Exeter Hall. In 1859 he sang at Covent Garden as Hoel in the opera <hi rend="italic">Dinorah,</hi> and in 1862 he appeared in Italian opera in <hi rend="italic">Il Trovatore.</hi> He was then engaged by Mapleson for Her Majesty’s, and his regular connexion with the English operatic stage only ceased in 1870, when he sang as Vanderdecken in <hi rend="italic">The Plying Dutchman.</hi> His last appearance in opera was in the same part with the Carl Rosa Company at the Lyceum Theatre in 1876. Meanwhile, in 1861 he sang <hi rend="italic">Elijah</hi> at the Birmingham Festival, and in 1862 was engaged for the Handel Festival at the Crystal Palace At the musical festivals and on the concert stage his success was immense. In such songs as “ To Anthea,” “ Simon the Cellarer ” or “ Maid of Athens,” he was unapproachable, and his oratorio singing carried on the finest</p><p>traditions of his art. He was knighted in 1907. In 1858 Santley married Gertrude Kemble, and their daughter, Edith Santley, had a great success as a concert singer.</p><p>SANTO DOMINGO <hi rend="smallcaps">[San Domingo, Dominican Republic,</hi> or officially <hi rend="smallcaps">RepÚblica Dominicana],</hi> a state in the West Indies. It occupies two-thirds of the island of Haiti <hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> and has an area of about 18,045 sq. m. The administration is in the hands of three co-ordinate “ powers ”—the executive, the legislative and the judicial. Under the constitution of 1844, modified in 1879, 1880, 1881, 1887, 1896, and 1908, the president is the head of the executive. He is chosen by an electoral college and serves for six years, and he is assisted by a cabinet of seven ministers. The legislature, called the National Congress, con- sists of a Senate of 12 members, and a Chamber of Deputies of 24 members elected for four years by a limited suffrage. The Supreme Court comprises a chief-justice, six justices appointed by the Congress, and one justice appointed by the president. The republic is divided into six provinces and six maritime districts. Each province and district is administered by a governor appointed by the Cabinet. There is a small army, most of which is stationed at the City of Santo Domingo, and military service is compulsory in the event of foreign war. The navy consists of one small gun-boat. Primary education is free and compulsory: elementary schools are supported largely by the local authorities, and the higher, technical and normal schools by the government. There is a professional school with the character and functions of a university. The Roman Catholic is the state religion, but all others are allowed under certain restrictions. The monetary unit is a silver coin of the value of a franc, called the <hi rend="italic">dominicano,</hi> but in 1897 the United States gold dollar was adopted as the standard of value. The roads in the interior are primitive, but the government encourages the construction of railways. A line runs between Sanchez and La Vega, and another between Santiago and Porto Plata. The republic joined the Postal Union in 1880. The exports include tobacco, coffee, cacao, sugar, mahogany, logwood, cedar, satinwood, hides, honey, gum and wax. The collection of the customs and other revenues specially assigned to the secur- ance of bonds was in the hands of an American company until 1899, when this defaulted in the payment of interest and the government took over the collection. In 1905, to forestall foreign intervention for securing payment of the State debt, President Roosevelt made an agreement with Santo Domingo, under which the United States undertook to adjust the republic’s foreign obligations, and to assume charge of the customs houses. A treaty was ratified by the United States Senate in 1907, and an American citizen is temporarily receiver of customs. In June 1907 the debts amounted to $17,000,000.</p><p>Santo Domingo has the finest sugar lands in the West Indies; tobacco and cacao flourish; the mountain regions are especially suited to the culture of coffee, and tropical fruits will grow anywhere with a minimum of attention. During the earlier years of the Spanish occupation gold to the value of £90,000 was sent annually to Spain, besides much silver. Platinum, manganese, iron, copper, tin, antimony, opals and chalcedony are also found. In the Neyba valley there are two remarkable hills, composed of pure rock salt. Only an influx of capital and an energetic population are needed to develop these resources.</p><p>Santo Domingo, the capital of the republic, is situated on the south coast. At a distance of 45 m. N. lies the town of Azua (pop. 1500) founded in 1504 by Diego Columbus. It stands in a plain, rich in salt and asphalt, which was the scene of the first planting of sugar in the West Indies. Santiago (pop. 12,000), the capital of the Vega Real, stands on the banks of the Yaqui river, 160 m. N.W. of the capital, in the richest agricultural district in the state. It controls the tobacco trade which is chiefly in German and Dutch hands. Its port, Porto Plata (pop. 15,000), is the outlet of the entire Vega Real district. La Vega, perhaps the most beautiful city of Santo Domingo, lies in the midst of a lovely savanna, or plain, surrounded by well- wooded hills, and has a magnificent old cathedral. Six miles away is the Cerro Santo, a hill 787 ft. in height, rising abruptly from the plain, on the summit of which Columbus planted a great cross on his first visit in 1493. Seybo (5000), Monti Cristi (3000) and Samana (1500) are the only other towns of any size. The population of the republic is about 500,000. The people are mainly mulattoes of Spanish descent, but there are a considerable number of negroes and whites of both Creole and European origin. Politically the</p></body></text></TEI>