<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-29T16:51:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>group. Between the Hagengebirge and the Tennengebirge, which are situated on each side of the Salzach valley, is one of the most magnificent narrow passes of the Alps. It is below Werfen, and near its exit, just at the narrowest part, is the Lueg Pass, which was fortified as early as 1316 and offered a firm resistance to the French in the years 1800, 1805 and 1809. A portion of the Ischler Alps, as well as of the Dachstein group, also belongs to Salzburg. The principal river of Salzburg is the Salzach. The Enns and the Mur also rise in this province. The four Krimmler falls, together 2085 ft. high, are the most important falls in the Eastern Alps. The two falls at Wildbad-Gastein (196 and 296 ft.); the fall, by which the Gasteiner Ache discharges itself into the Salzach, near Lend; the Tauern fall (660 ft.), formed by the Tauern Ache on the N. side of the Radstäter Tauern; and the Gollinger fall (202 ft. ) also deserve notice. Among the <hi rend="italic">Klammen, i.e.</hi> narrow passages leading from the Salzach valley to the valleys of smaller rivers, the most celebrated are the Kitzloch Klamm and the Liechtenstein Klamm. The Kitzloch Klamm is formed by the Rauris Thal and the Liechtenstein Klamm by the Gross-Arle Thal. A path through the last Klamm leads to the magnificent fall (174 ft.) of the Gross-Arle river, which discharges itself in a series of cascades into the Salzach. The most important lake is the Zeller-see (2424 ft. above sea- level, 2 sq. m. in extent, 238 ft. deep), whose waters are carried off by the Salzach. The Waller-see or Lake of Seekirchen (1653 ft. above sea-level), the Fuschl-see (2095 ft.), the Hinter-see (2580 ft.), the Ober-Trumer-see and Nieder-Trumer-see are all situated in the Alpine foothill region. The Mond-see (1560 ft.) and Aber-see, or Lake St Wolfgang, are on the frontier between Salzburg and Upper Austria. The climate, although healthy, is very changeable, with great extremes of temperature and heavy rainfall, especially in the summer. The most settled season is the autumn. The annual mean temperature at Salzburg is 46°∙4 F. The population of the duchy in 1900 was 193,247, which is equivalent to 69 inhabitants per square mile. It is the most sparsely populated province of Austria. Between 1880 and 1900 the population increased by 17·5%. The inhabitants are a handsome and powerfully built peasant race, very conservative in religion, manners, customs and national costume. They are almost exclusively of German stock and are Roman Catholics. Elementary education is much more advanced here than in any other Alpine province. Although 13∙71% of the soil is unproductive and 32∙4% is covered with forests, Salzburg is one of the principal pastoral regions of Austria. Of its total area, 28∙9% consists of Alpine pastures available during the summer months, 4∙95⅜ of lowland pasturages and 8∙3% of meadows, while only 9·2% is arable. Cattle-breeding and dairy-farming are very developed and constitute the chief resources of the province. Next in importance comes the timber trade; game is also plentiful. The mineral wealth of Salzburg includes salt at Hallein, copper at Mitterberg, iron-ore at Werfen, marble in the Untersberg region and small quantities of gold near the Goldberg in the Rauris valley and at Böckstein in the Gastein valley. The duchy contains also a great number of mineral springs, as the celebrated springs at Gastein, alkaline springs at Mauterndorf and at St Wolfgang, and saline springs at Golfing and Hallein. Commerce and manufacture are poorly developed. The duchy is divided into six departments, of which the capital, Salzburg, is one and its environs the second. The other four are Hallein, St Johann, Tamsweg and Zell-am-See. The local diet, of which the archbishop is a member <hi rend="italic">ex-officio, </hi>is composed of 28 members, and the duchy sends 7 members to the reichsrat at Vienna. At Hallein, pop. (1900) 6608, with celebrated saline springs known since the beginning of the 12th century, in October 1809, encounters between the French and the Tirolese under Joachim Johann Haspînger took place. To the N.E. lies Adnet with extensive marble quarries, and to the N. Oberalm, with manufacture of marble articles. The ascent of the Hoher Göll is made from here. Zell-am-See (2473 ft.), pop. 1561, is a favourite tourist resort. To the E. is the Schmit- tenhöhe (6455 ft.), which is easily accessible. On the summit is a meteorological station. Sankt Johann (pop. 1343) was one</p><p>of the earliest settlements in the Salzach valley, and was a principal centre of Protestantism. Near it is the Liechtenstein Klamm.</p><p>For the history of the archbishopric and duchy see the article on the town of Salzburg (below).</p><p>SALZBURG, capital of the Austrian duchy and crownland of Salzburg and formerly of the archbishopric of the same name, 195 m. W. by S. of Vienna by rail. Pop. (1900) 32, 934. The city occupies a position of singular beauty on the Salzach which passes at this point between two isolated hills, the Mönchsberg (1646 ft.) on the left and the Capuzinerberg (2132 ft.) on the right. In the lovely valley so formed, and stretching into the plain beyond, lies Salzburg. The older and main part of the city lies on the left bank of the Salzach, in a narrow semicircular plain at the base of the Mönchsberg; the newer town is on the right bank at the foot of the Capuzinerberg, which is separated from the river by the narrow suburb of Stein. At the S. of the old town, below the Nonnberg, of S.E. spur of the Mönchsberg, is the suburb of Nonnthal; and at the N. end is Mülln. The steep sides of the Mönchsberg rise directly from amidst the houses of the town, some of which have cellars and rooms hewn out of the rock; and the ancient cemetery of St Peter, the oldest in Salzburg, is bounded by a row of vaults cut in the side of the hill. The narrowest part of the ridge, which has a length of above 2 m. is pierced by the Neu Thor, a tunnel 436 ft. long and 23 ft. broad, completed in 1767, to form a convenient passage from the town to the open plain. The S. end of the Mönchsberg is occupied by the imposing Hohen-Salzburg, a citadel originally founded in the 9th century, though the present buildings, the towers of which rise 400 ft. above the town, date chiefly from 1496-1519. Its chapel contains statues of the twelve apostles in red marble. The citadel is now used for barracks. The streets in the older quarters are narrow, crooked and gloomy; but the newer parts of the city, especially those laid out since the removal of the fortifications about 1861, are handsome and spacious. Owing to the frequent fires the private buildings of Salzburg are comparatively modern; and the existing houses, lavishly adorned with marble, are, like many of the public buildings, monuments of the gorgeous taste of the archbishops of the 17th and 18th centuries. From the style of the houses, the numerous open squares, and the abundant fountains which give an Italian aspect to the town, Salzburg has received the name of “ the German Rome.” Both sides of the river are bordered by fine promenades, planted with trees. The Salzach is spanned by four bridges, including a railway bridge.</p><p>Salzburg is full of objects and buildings of interest. The cathedral, one of the largest and most perfect specimens of the Renaissance style in Germany, was built in 1614-1668 by the Italian architect Santino Solari, in imitation of St Peter’s at Rome. On three sides it is bounded by the Dom-Platz, the Kapitel-Platz and the Residenz- Platz; and opening on the N.E. and N.W. of the last are the Mozart- Platz and the Markt-Platz. In the Mozart-Platz is a statue of Mozart by Schwanthaler erected in 1842. On one side of the Residenz-Platz is the palace, an irregular though imposing building in the Italian style, begun in 1592 and finished in 1725. It contains a picture-gallery and is now occupied by the grand-duke of Tuscany. Opposite is the Neu Bau, begun in 1588, in which are the government offices and the law courts. In the middle of the Residenz- Platz is a handsome fountain, the Residenz-Brunnen, 46 ft. high, executed in marble by Antonio Dario in 1664-1680. The palace of the present archbishop is in the Kapitel-Platz. Across the river, with its French garden adjoining the public park, is the Mirabell palace, formerly the summer residence of the archbishops. Built in 1607, and restored after a fire in 1818, it was presented to the town in 1867 by the emperor Francis Joseph. The town hall of Salzburg was built in 1407 and restored in 1675. Other interesting secular buildings are the Chiemseehof, founded in 1305 and rebuilt in 1697, formerly the palace of the suffragan bishop of Chiemsee, and now the meeting-place of the Salzburg diet and the Carolino-Augusteum- Museum, containing an interesting collection of antiquities and a library of 20,000 volumes.</p><p>Of the twenty-five churches the majority are interesting from their antiquity, their architecture or their associations. Next to the cathedral, the chief is perhaps the abbey church of St Peter, a Romanesque basilica of the 12th century which was tastelessly restored in 1745, and which contains a monument to St Rupert. St Margaret’s, in the midst of St Peter’s churchyard, built in 1485, and restored in 1865, is situated near the cave in the side of the Mönchsberg, said to have been the hermitage of St Maximus, who</p></body></text></TEI>