<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-29T16:49:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“S. Thomé ” B.S.G. <hi rend="italic">Lisboa</hi> (1908), pp. 113-134; W. A. Cadbury, <hi rend="italic">Labour in Portuguese West Africa</hi> (2nd ed., London, 1910); <hi rend="italic">A ilha de S Thomé</hi> (Lisbon, 1907); <hi rend="italic">The Boa Entrada Plantations </hi>(Edinburgh, 1907); and British Consular reports.</p><p>ST THOMAS, an island in the Danish West Indies. It belongs to the Virgin Island group, and lies 40 m. E. of Porto Rico, in 18° 20' N. and 64° 55'W. Pop. (1901) 11,012, mostly negroes. It is 13 m long, varies in width from 1 m. to 4 m. and has an area of 33 m. It consists of a single mountain ridge, the peaks of a submerged range, culminating in West Mountain (1555 ft.). St Thomas stands on a prolongation of the range which supports the Greater Antilles, and is built up of much disintegrated eruptive rock (porphyry and granite). The climate is tropical, varying in temperature between 70° F. and 80° F., modified, however, by the sea breezes. The average yearly rainfall is about 45 in., earthquakes are not unknown, and hurricanes at times sweep over the island. The only town, Charlotte Amalie (pop. 8540), lies in the centre of the S coast, at the head of one of the finest harbours in the West Indies. This consists of an almost land- locked basin, about ¾ m. across, varying in depth from 27 to 36 ft., and entered by a narrow channel only 300 yds. wide. It is equipped with a floating dock, which can accommodate ships up to 30∞ tons, a patent slip for smaller vessels and a repairing yard. Danish is the official language, but English predominates, while French, Spanish and Dutch are also spoken. St Thomas was once the greatest distributing centre in the West Indies, but the introduction of steamships and cables led to its decline, and the removal of the Royal Mail Steamship Company’s headquarters to Barbados in 1885 was the final blow. The production of sugar, which decayed gradually after the abolition of slavery, is practically extinct. Aloes, fibrous plants and fruit are grown. St Thomas is the seat of government for the Danish West Indies (St Thomas, St John and St Croix), a crown colony administered by a governor, who is assisted by a colonial council. The governor resides for half the year in St Thomas, and in St Croix for the rest. The chief importance of St Thomas lies in the fact that it is a coaling station for ships plying to and from the West Indies.</p><p>The island was discovered by Columbus in 1493, and first colonized by the Dutch in 1657. After their departure in 1667 the island came into the hands of the British, and it was held by them till 1671, when it passed into the hands of the Danish West India Company, which was succeeded in 1685 by the so-called Brandenburg Company, the shareholders of which were mainly Dutch. The king of Denmark having taken over the island in 1754, declared it a free port, and during the European wars of the 18th century the neutrality of Denmark gave a great impetus to the trade of St Thomas. It was during this period that the distributing trade of the island grew up. It was held by the British in 1801 and again from 1807 to 1815, during which it was the great rendezvous of British merchant vessels waiting for convoy. In 1867, when the islands were governed at a loss to the mother country, a treaty was concluded under which the United States agreed to buy them for 7 ½ million dollars, but, although the suggestion first emanated from the United States, its Senate refused to ratify the treaty. In 1902 another treaty of cession was signed by which the United States was to buy the islands for 5 million dollars, hut the Danish parliament rejected it. The importance of the islands to the United States consists in their suitability as a West Indian naval base.</p><p>ST TROND, a town of Belgium in the province of Limburg about 18 m. N.W. of Liege. Pop. (1904) 15,116. It occupies an important strategical position with regard to the N.E. frontier of Belgium, and General Brialmont recommended its fortification. In the middle ages it was a fortified town belonging to the bishops of Liége, and Charles the Bold captured it in 1467. In 1566 the Assembly of Compromise met at St Trond.</p><p>SAINT-VICTOR, PAUL BINS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Comte de</hi> (1827-1881), known as Paul de Saint-Victor, French author, was born in Paris on the 11th of July 1827. His father Jacques B. M. Bins, comte de Saint-Victor (1772-1858), is remembered by his poem <hi rend="italic">L’Espérance,</hi> and by an excellent verse translation of Anacreon.</p><p>Saint-Victor, who ceased to use the title of count as being out of keeping with his democratic principles, began as a dramatic critic on the <hi rend="italic">Pays</hi> in 1851, and in 1885 he succeeded Théophile Gautier on the <hi rend="italic">Presse.</hi> In 1866 he migrated to the <hi rend="italic">Liberté, </hi>and in 1869 joined the staff of the <hi rend="italic">Moniteur universel.</hi> In 1870, during the last days of the second empire, he was made inspector- general of fine arts. Almost all Saint-Victor’s work consists of articles, the best known being the collection entitled <hi rend="italic">Hommes et dieux</hi> (1867). His death interrupted the publication of <hi rend="italic">Les Deux Masques,</hi> in which the author intended to survey the whole dramatic literature of ancient and modern times. Saint- Victor’s critical faculty was considerable, though rather onesided. He owed a good deal to Théophile Gautier, but he carried ornateness to a pitch far beyond Gautier’s. Saint-Victor died in Paris on the 9th of July 1881.</p><p>See also Deljant, <hi rend="italic">Paul de Saint-Victor</hi> (1887).</p><p>ST VINCENT, JOHN JERVIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Earl of</hi> (1735-1823), British admiral, was the second son of Swynfen Jervis, solicitor to the admiralty, and treasurer of Greenwich hospital. He was born at Meaford in Staffordshire on the 9th of January 1735, and entered the navy on the 4th of January 1749. He became lieutenant on the 19th of February 1755, and served in that rank till 1759, taking part in the conquest of Quebec. He was made commander of the “ Scorpion ” sloop in 1759, and postcaptain in 1760. During the peace he commanded the “ Alarm ” 32 in the Mediterranean, and when he was put on half pay he travelled widely in Europe, taking professional notes everywhere. While the War of American Independence lasted, he commanded the “ Fourroyant ” (80) in the Channel, taking part in the battle of Ushant on the 27th of July 1778 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Keppel, Viscount) </hi>and in the various reliefs of Gibraltar. His most signal service was the capture of the French “ Pégase ” (74) after a long chase on the 19th of April 1782, for which he was made K.B. In 1783 he entered parliament as member for Launceston, and in the general election of 1784 as member for Yarmouth. In politics he was a strong Whig. On the 24th of September 1787 he attained flag rank, and was promoted vice-admiral in 1793. From 1793 till 1795 he was in the West Indies co-operating with the army in the conquest of the French islands. On his return he was promoted admiral. In November 1795 he took command in the Mediterranean, where he maintained the blockade of Toulon, and aided the allies of Great Britain in Italy.</p><p>But in 1796 a great change was produced by the progress of the French armies on shore and the alliance of Spain with France. The occupation of Italy by the French armies closed all the ports to his ships, and Malta was not yet in the possession of Great Britain. Then the addition of the Spanish fleet to the French altered the balance of strength in the Mediterranean. The Spaniards were very inefficient, and Jervis would have held his ground, if one of his subordinates had not taken the extraordinary course of returning to England, because he thought that the dangerous state of the country required that all its forces should be concentrated at home. He was therefore obliged to act on the instructions sent to him and to retire to the Atlantic, withdrawing the garrisons from Corsica and other places. His headquarters were now on the coast of Portugal, and his chief duty was to watch the Spanish fleet at Cadiz. On the 14th of February 1797 he gained a most complete victory against heavy odds (see Sτ <hi rend="smallcaps">Vincent, Battle of).</hi> The determination to fight, and the admirable discipline of his squadron, which was very largely the fruit of his own care in preparation, supply the best proof that he was a commander of a high order. For this victory, which came at a very critical time, he was made an earl and was granted a pension of £3000. His qualities as a disciplinarian were soon to be put to a severe test. In 1797 the grievances of the sailors, which were of old standing, and had led to many mutinies of single ships, came to a head in the great general mutinies at Spithead and the Nore. Similar movements took place on the coast of Ireland and at the Cape of Good Hope (see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Navy: </hi><hi rend="italic">History</hi>). The spirit spread to the fleet under St Vincent, and there was an undoubted danger that some outbreak would take place in his command. The</p></body></text></TEI>