<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Napoleon, so in <hi rend="italic">Ut mine Stromtid</hi>  he presents many aspects of the revolutionary movement of 1848.</p><p>In 1863 Reuter transferred his residence from Neubrandenburg to Eisenach; and here he died on the 12th of July T874. In the works produced at Eisenach he did not maintain the high level of his earlier writings.</p><p>Reuter’s <hi rend="italic">Sämtliche Werke,</hi>  in 13 vols., were first published in 1863-68. To these were added in 1875 two volumes of <hi rend="italic">Nachgelassene Schriften,</hi>  with a biography by A. Wilbrandt; and in 1878 two supplementary volumes to the works appeared. A popular edition in 7 vols, was published in 1877-78 (last edition, 1902); there are also editions by K. F. Muller (18 vols., 1905),and W. Seelmann (7 vols., 1905-6)· See O. Glagau, <hi rend="italic">F. Reuter und seine Dichtungen</hi>  (1866; 2nd ed., 1875); H. Ebert, <hi rend="italic">F. Reuter und seine Werke</hi>  (1874); F. Latendorf, <hi rend="italic">Zur Erinnerung an F. Reuter</hi>  (1879); K. T. Gadertz<hi rend="sub">1 </hi><hi rend="italic">  Reuter-Studien</hi>  (1890); by the same, <hi rend="italic">Aus Reuters alten und jungen Tagen</hi>  (3 vols., 1894-1900); <hi rend="italic">Briefe F. Reuters an seinen Vater, </hi>edited by F. Engel (2 vols., 1895); A. Römer, <hi rend="italic">F. Reuter in seinem Leben und Schaffen</hi>  (1895); θ· Raatz, <hi rend="italic">Wahrheit und Dichtung in Reuters Werken</hi>  (1895); E. Brandes, <hi rend="italic">Aus F. Reuters Leben</hi>  (1899); K. F. Müller, <hi rend="italic">Der Mecklenburger Volksniund und F. Reuters Schriften </hi>(1902). A complete bibliography of F. Reuter will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Niederdeutsche Jahrbuch</hi>  for 1896 and 1902.</p><p>REUTER, PAUL JULIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Baron de</hi>  (1821-1899), founder of Reuter’s News Agency, was born at Cassel, Germany. At the age of thirteen he became a clerk in his uncle’s bank at Göttingen, where he chanced to make the acquaintance of Professor Gauss, whose experiments in telegraphy were then attracting some attention. Reuter’s mind was thus directed to the value of the speedy transmission of information, and in 1849, <hi rend="sup">on</hi>  the completion of the first telegraph lines in Germany and France, he found an opportunity of turning his ideas to account. There was a gap between the termination of the German line at Aix-la-Chapelle and that of the French and Belgian lines at Verviers. Reuter organized a news-collecting agency at each of these places, his wife being in charge of one, himself at the other, and bridged the interval by a pigeon-post. On the establishment of through telegraphic communication, Reuter endeavoured to start a news agency in Paris, but finding that the French government’s restrictions would render the scheme unworkable, removed in 1851 to England and became a naturalized British subject. The first submarine cable—between Dover and Calais—had just been laid, and Reuter opened an office in London for the transmission of intelligence between England and the continent. At first, however, his business was practically confined to the transmission of private commercial telegrams to places not connected with the new telegraph system. He appointed agents at the various telegraph termini on the continent to take these despatches off the wires and forward them by rail or pigeon-post to the addresses. Simultaneously he endeavoured to induce the English papers to publish the foreign news telegrams supplied by his various agents. These efforts were for some years unsuccessful, until in 1858<hi rend="italic">The Times </hi>published the report of an important speech by Napoleon III. forwarded by Reuter’s Paris agent. Reuter now extended his sphere of operations all over the world, and in 1859 obtained leave for the presence of representatives at the headquarters of the Austrian and French armies during the war. In 1866 he laid down a special cable from Cork to Crookhaven, which enabled him to circulate news of the American Civil War several hours before the steamer could reach Liverpool. A concession for a cable beneath the North Sea to Cuxhaven was granted him by the king of Hanover in 1865, and in the same year a concession was granted him for a cable between France and the United States, the line being worked jointly by Reuter (whose business had just been converted into a Iimitedliability company) and the Anglo-American Telegraph Company. In 1872 he obtained from the shah of Persia an exclusive concession to develop the internal resources of that country, but the concession was annulled and its privileges transferred to the Imperial Bank of Persia. Reuter was in 1871 given the title of baron by the duke of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha, and by a special grant of Queen Victoria he and his heirs were authorized to have the privileges of this rank in England. Baron Reuter died at Nice on the 25th of February 1899.</p><p>REUTERHOLM, GUSTAF ADOLF, <hi rend="smallcaps">Baeon</hi>  (1756-1813), Swedish statesman. After a brief military career he was appointed <hi rend="italic">Kammerherr</hi>  to Sophia Magdalena, queen consort of Gustavus III., and subsequently became intimately connected with the king’s brother, Charles, then duke of Sudermania. He remained in the background throughout the reign of Gustavus IIL, whom he constantly opposed and by whom he was imprisoned along with the other malcontents in 1789. He was abroad at the time of the king’s death, but a summons from his friend, now duke regent, speedily recalled him, and in 1793 he was made a member of the council of state and one of the “ lords of the realm.” At first he seemed inclined to adopt a liberal system, and reintroduced the freedom of the press. Hc did this solely, however, to reverse the Gustavian system, and persecuted the stalwarts of the late king <hi rend="italic">(e.g.</hi>  G. M. Armfelt, J. K. Toll) with a petty vindictiveness which excited general disgust. Towards the end of the regency, Reuterholm inclined towards an alliance with Russia on the basis of a marriage between the young king, Gustavus IV., and the empress Catherine’s granddaughter, Alexandra Pavlovna, an alliance frustrated by the bigotry of the intended groom. At home the Swedish government ended as ultra-reactionary, owing to an insignificant riot in Stockholm which so alarmed Reuterholm that he threatened all printers who printed anything relating to the constitutions of the French republic or the United States of America with the loss of their privileges. In March 1795 he closed the Swedish Academy because A. G. Silfverstolpe in his inaugural address had ventured to disapprove of the <hi rend="italic">coup PHat </hi>of 1789. On the accession of Gustavus IV. (November ist, 1796) Reuterholm was expelled from Stockholm. For the next twelve years he lived abroad under the name of Tempelcrentz. After the revolution of 1809 he returned to Sweden, but was denied all access to Charles XIII., and quitted his country for good. He died in Schleswig on the 27th of December 1813.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">SverigePHistoria</hi>  (Stockholm, 1877-1881 ), vol. v. (R. N. B.)</p><p>REUTLINGEN, a town of Germany, in the kingdom of Württemberg, situated on the Echatz, an affluent of the Neckar, near the base of the Achalm and 36 m. by rail S. of Stuttgart. Pop. (1905) 23,850. It is a quaintly built town, with many picturesque houses and a fine Gothic church of the 13th and 14th centuries dedicated to St Mary, which was restored in 1893-1901; it contains in the choir a replica of the Holy Sepulchre and a sculptured stone font, and has a tower 240 ft. high. Reutlingen has three other Evangelical churches, a Roman Catholic church, a town hall, and several monuments, including one to the emperor William I. and another to Friedrich List. The industries of the town are numerous, and include the spinning and weaving of cotton, dyeing and bleaching; also the manufacture of leather, machinery, furniture, shoes, paper, clothing, hardware, bricks, beer and woollen goods. Hops, vines and fruit are grown in the neighbourhood. Reutlingen has several schools and educational establishments, including a celebrated pomological institute. It is also famous as the place where PastorGustav Werner (1809-1887) founded his Christian Socialist refuge, which has become widely known in philanthropic circles.</p><p>Reutlingen, which is first mentioned in 1213., became a free imperial town in the 13th century and was fortified by the emperor Frederick II., remaining loyal to him and to his son, Conrad IV. A member of the league of Swabian towns, its citizens defeated Count Ulrich of Württemberg on the 14th of May 1377. Later it joined the Swabian League and was favoured by the emperor Maximilian I. It came into the possession of Württemberg in 1802. An explosion which took place on the 27th of December 1852 destroyed many houses in the town.</p><p>See Rupp, Aws <hi rend="italic">der Vorzeit Reutlingens und seiner Umgegend </hi>(Stuttgart, 1869); Hochstetter, <hi rend="italic">Führer durch Reutlingen und Umgehung</hi>  (Reutlingen, 1901); and Zwiesele, <hi rend="italic">Geognostischer Führer in der UrngegendvonReutlingen</hi>  (Stuttgart, 1897).</p><p>REVAL, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Revel</hi>  (Russ. <hi rend="italic">Revel,</hi>  formerly <hi rend="italic">Kolyvair, </hi>Esthonian, <hi rend="italic">Tallina</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Tannilin),</hi>  a fortified seaport town of Russia, capital of Esthonia, situated on a bay on the S. coast of the gulf of Finland, 230 m. W. of St Petersburg by rail. Pop. (1900) 66,292, of whom half were Esthonians and 30%</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>