<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by the invasion of the Hungarians, took refuge at Remiremont<hi rend="sub">f </hi>which had grown up round a villa of the Frankish kings, and in the nth century they permanently settled there. Enriched by dukes of Lorraine, kings of France and emperors of Germany, the ladies of Remiremont attained great power. The abbess was a princess of the empire, and received consecration at the hands of the pope. The fifty canonesses were selected from those who could give proof of noble descent. On Whit-Monday the neighbouring parishes paid homage to the chapter in a ceremony called the “ Kyrioles and on their accession lhe dukes of Lorraine, the immediate suzerains of the abbey, had to come to Remiremont to swear to continue their protection. The “ War of the Scutcjieons ” (Panonceaux) in 1566 between the duke and the abbess ended in favour of the duke; and the abbess never recovered her former position. In the 17th century the ladies of Remiremont fell away so much from the original monastic rule as to take the title of countesses, renounce their vows and marry. The town was attacked by the French in 1638 and ruined by the earthquake of 1682. With the rest of Lorraine it was joined to France in 1766. The monastery on the hill and the nunnery in the town were both suppressed in the Revolution.</p><p>REMONSTRANTS, the name given to those Dutch Protestants who, after the death of Arminius <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi>  maintained the views associated with his name, and in 1610 presented to the states of Holland and Friesland a “ remonstrance ” in five articles formulating their points of departure from stricter Calvinism. These were: (1) that the divine decree of predestination is conditional, not absolute; (2) that the Atonement is in intention universal; (3) that man cannot of himself exercise a saving faith; (4) that though the grace of God is a necessary condition of human effort it does not act irresistibly in man; (5) that believers are able to resist sin but are not beyond the possibility of falling from grace. Their adversaries (the Gomarists) met them with a “ counter-remonstrance,” and so were known as the Counter-Remonstrants. Although the states-general issued an edict tolerating both parties and forbidding further dispute, the conflict continued, and the Remonstrants were assailed both by personal enemies and by the political weapons of Maurice of Orange, who executed and imprisoned their leaders for holding republican views. In 1618-19 the synod of Dort (see Dort, Synod of), the thirteen Arminian pastors headed by Simon Episcopius <hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi>  being shut out, established the victory of the Calvinist school, drew up ninety-three canonical rules, and confirmed the authority of the Belgic Confession and the Heidelberg Catechism. The judgment of the synod was enforced by the deposition and in some cases the banishment of Remonstrant ministers; but the government soon became convinced that their party was not dangerous to the state, and in 1630 they were formally allowed liberty to reside in all parts of Holland and build churches and schools. In 1621 they had already received liberty to make a settlement in Schleswig, where they built the town of Friedrichstadt. This colony still exists. The doctrine of the Remonstrants was embodied in 1621 in a <hi rend="italic">Confessio </hi>written by Episcopius<hi rend="sub">f</hi>  their great theologian, while J. Uyten-bogaert gave them a catechism and regulated their churchly order. The Remonstrants adopted a simple synodical constitution; but their importance was henceforth more theological than ecclesiastical. Their seminary in Amsterdam has boasted of many distinguished names—Curcellaeus, Limborch, Wetstein, Lc Clerc; and their liberal school of theology, which naturally grew more liberal and even rationalistic, reacted powerfully on the state church and on other Christian denominations. The Remonstrants first received official recognition in 1795. As a church they now number 27 communities with about 12,500 members, in a flourishing condition and respected for their traditions of scholarship and liberal thought. Their chief' congregation is in Rotterdam.</p><p>REMPHAN, the Authorized Version’s rendering of the Greek word variously appearing in Acts vii. 48 as <hi rend="italic">'Ρομφά, 'Ρεμφάν, 'Ρεμφάμ, 'Ραιφάν, 'Ρεφάν.</hi>  It is part of a quotation from Amos V. 26, where the .Septuagint 'Ραιφάν or <hi rend="italic">'Ρεφάν</hi>  stands</p><p>«</p><p>for the Hebrew P*9 Chuin or Kewan. The Greek forms are probably simple mistakes for the Hebrew, k (°) having been replaced by r ("&gt;) and ph (φ) substituted for v (’)· Kewan is probably the old Babylonian <hi rend="italic">Ka(y)awanu,</hi>  the planet Saturn, another (the Akkadian) name for which is <hi rend="italic">Sakkut,</hi>  which appears as <hi rend="italic">Siccuth</hi>  in the earlier part of the verse.</p><p>REMSCHEID, a town of Germany, in the Prussian Rhine Province, situated on an elevated plateau, 1100 ft. above sea-level, 6 m. by rail S. of Barmen and 20 m. N.E. of Cologne. Pop. (1905) 64,340. Remscheid is a centre of the hardware industry, and large quantities of tools, scythes, skates and other small articles in iron, steel and brass are made for export to all parts of Europe, the East, and North and South America. The name of Remscheid occurs in a document of 1132, and the town received the first impulse to its industrial importance through the immigration of Protestant refugees from France and Holland.</p><p>RÉMUSAT, CHARLES FRANÇOIS MARIE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Comte de</hi>  (1797-1875), French politician and man of letters, was born in Paris on the 13th of March 1797. His father, Auguste Laurent, Comte de Remusat, of a good family of Toulouse, was chamber-lain to Napoleon, but acquiesced in the restoration and became prefect first of Haute Garonne, and then of Nord. His mother’s maiden name was Claire Élisabeth Jeanne Gravier de Vergennes, born in 1780. She married at sixteen, and was attached to Josephine as <hi rend="italic">dame du palais</hi>  in 1802. Talleyrand was among her admirers, and she was generally recognized as a woman of great intellectual capacity and personal grace. After her death (1824) an <hi rend="italic">Essai sur Fêducation des femmes</hi>  was published and received an academic <hi rend="italic">couronne.</hi>  But it was not until her grandson Paul de Rémusat published her <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi>  (3 vols., Paris, 1879-80), which have since been followed by some correspondence with her son (2 vols., 1881), that justice could be done to her literary talent. Much light was thrown on the Napoleonic court by this book, and on the youth and education of her son Charles. He early developed political views more liberal than those of his parents, and, being bred to the bar, published in 1820 a pamphlet on trial by jury. He was an active journalist, showing in philosophy and literature the influence of Cousin, and is said to have furnished to no small extent the original of Balzac’s brilliant egoist Henri de Marsay, He signed the journalists’ protest against the Ordinances of July 1830, and in the following October was elected deputy .for Haute Garonne. He then ranked himself with the <hi rend="italic">doctrinaires,</hi>  and supportéd most of those measures of restriction on popular liberty which made the July monarchy unpopular with French Radicals. In 1836 he became for a short time undersecretary of state for the interior. He then became an ally of Thiers, and in 1840 held the ministry of the interior for a brief period. In the same year he became an Academician. For the rest of Louis Philippe’s reign he was in opposition till he joined Thiers in his attempt at a ministry in the spring of 1848. During this time Rémusat constantly spoke in the chamber, but was still more active in literature, especially on philosophical subjects, the most remarkable of his works being his book on <hi rend="italic">Abelard</hi>  (2 vols., 1845). In 1848 he was elected, and in 1849 re-elected, for Haute Garonne, and voted with the Conservative side. He had to leave France after the <hi rend="italic">coup Petal*,</hi>  nor did he re-enter political life during the Second Empire until 1869, when he founded a moderate opposition journal at Toulouse. In 1871 he refused the Vienna embassy offered him by Thiers, but in August he was appointed minister of foreign affairs in succession to M. Jules Favre. Although minister he was not a deputy, and on standing for Paris in September 1873 he was beaten by Désiré Barodet. A month later he was elected (having already resigned with Thiers) for Haute Garonne by a great majority. He died in Paris on the 6th of January 1875.</p><p>During his abstention from politics Rémusat continued to write on philosophical history, especially English. <hi rend="italic">Saint Anselme de Cantorbery</hi>  appeared in 1854; <hi rend="italic">L<hi rend="sup">t</hi>Angleterre au XVIIIème siècle</hi>  in 1856 (2nd ed. enlarged, 1865); <hi rend="italic">Bacon, sa vie.</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>