<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>was no more heard of—this being the sequel of the abduction by Don John of Austria, son of Philip IV., of the painter’s beautiful only daughter Maria Rosa. But these assertions have not availed to displace the earlier and well-authenticated statement that Ribera died peaceably and wealthy in Naples in 1656. His own signature on his pictures is constantly “ Jusepe de Ribera, Espafiol.” His daughter, so far from being disgraced by an abduction, married a Spanish nobIeman who became a minister of the viceroy.</p><p>The pictorial· style of Spagnoletto is extremely powerful. In bis earlier style, founded (as we have seen) sometimes on Caravaggio and sometimes on the wholly diverse method of Correggio, the study of Spanish and Venetian masters can likewise be traced. Along with his massive and predominating shadows, he retained from first to last great strength of local colouring. His forms, though ordinary and partly gross, are correct; the impression of his works gloomy and startling. He delighted in subjects of horror. Salvator Rosa and Luca Giordano were his most distinguished pupils; also Giovanni Do, Enrico Fiammingo, Michelangelo Fracanzani, and Aniello Falcone, who was the first considerable painter of battle-pieces. Among Ribera’s principal works should be named “ St Januarius Emerging from the Furnace,” in the cathedral of Naples; the “ Descent from the Cross,” in the Neapolitan Certosa, generally regarded as his masterpiece; the “ Adoration of the Shepherds ” (a Iatc work, 1650), now in the Louvre; the “ Martyrdom of St Bartholomew,” in the museum of Madrid; the “ Pietà,” in the sacristy of S. Martino, Naples. His mythologie subjects are generally unpleasant—such as the “ Silenus,” in the Studj Gallery of Naples, and “ Venus Lamenting over Adonis,” in the Corsini Gallery of Rome. The Louvre contains altogether twenty-five of his paintings; the National Gallery, London, two—one of them, a “ Peità,” being an excellent though not exactly a leading specimen. He executed several fine male portraits; among others his own likeness, now in the collection at Alton Towers. He also produced twenty-six etchings, ably treated. For the use of his pupils, he drew a number of elementary designs, which in 1650 were etched by Francisco Fernandez, and which continued much in vogue for a long while among Spanish and French painters and students.</p><p>Besides the work of Dominici already referred to (1840-46), the <hi rend="italic">Diccionario Historico</hi>  of Cean Bermudez is a principal. authority regarding Ribera and his works; also E. dc Lalaing, “ Ribera ” (in <hi rend="italic">Histoire de quatre grands peintres),</hi>  1888.    (W. M. R.)</p><p>RIBOT<hi rend="sub">1</hi> ALEXANDRE FÉLIX JOSEPH (1842-    ), French</p><p>statesman, was born at St Omer on 7th February 1842. After a brilliant career at the university of Paris, where he was <hi rend="italic">lauréat</hi>  of the faculty of law, he rapidly made his mark at the bar. He was secretary of the conference of advocates and one of the founders of the <hi rend="italic">Société de législation comparée.</hi>  During 1875 and 1876 he was successively director of criminal affairs and secretary-general at the ministry of justice. In 1877 he made his entry into political life by the conspicuous part he played on the committee of legal resistance during the Broglie ministry, and in the following year he was returned to the chamber as a moderate republican member for Boulogne, in his native department of Pas-de-Calais. His impassioned yet reasoned eloquence gave him an influence which was increased by his articles in the <hi rend="italic">Parlement</hi>  in which he opposed violent measures against the unauthorized congregations. He devoted himself especially to financial questions, and in 1882 was reporter of the budget. He became one of the most prominent republican opponents of the Radical party, distinguishing himself by his attacks on the short-lived Gambetta ministry. He refused to vote the credits demanded by the Ferry cabinet for the Tongking expedition, and shared with M. Clémenceau in the overthrow of the ministry in 1885. At the general election of that year he was one of the victims of the Republican rout in the Pas-de-Calais, and did not re-enter the chamber till 1887. After 1889 he sat for St Omer. His fear of the Boulangist movement converted him to the policy of “ Republican Concentration,” and he entered office in 1890 as foreign minister in the Freycinet cabinet. He had an intimate acquaintance and sympathy with English institutions, and two of his published works—an address, <hi rend="italic">Biographie de Lord Erskine </hi>(1866), and <hi rend="italic">Élude sur Facte du $ avril 1873 pour F établissement .d'une cour suprême de justice en Angleterre</hi>  (1874)—deal with English questions; he also gave a fresh and highly important direction to French policy by the understanding with Russia, which was declared to· the world by the visit of the French fleet to Cronstadt in 1891, and which subsequently ripened into a formal treaty of alliance. He retained bis post in the Loubet ministry (February-November 1892), and on its defeat· became himself president of the council, retaining the direction of foreign affairs. The government resigned in March 1893 on the refusal of the chamber to accept the Senate’s amendments’ to the budget. On the election of Félix Faure as president of the Republic in January 1895, M. Ribot again became premier-and minister of finance. On the 10th of June he was able to make the first official announcement of a definite alliance with Russia. On the 30th of October the government was defeated on the question of the Chemin de fer du Sud, and resigned office. The real reason of its fall was the mismanagement of the Madagascar expedition, the .cost of which in men and money exceeded all expectations, and the alarming social conditions at home, as indicated by- the strike at Carmaux. After the fall of the Méline ministry in 1898 M. Ribot tried in vain to form a cabinet of “ conciliation.” He was elected, at the end of 1898, president of the important commission on education, in which he advocated the adoption of a modern system of education. The policy of the Waldeck-Rousscau ministry on the religious teaching congregations broke up the Republican party, and M. Ribot was among the scceders; but at the general election of 1902, though he himself secured re-election, his policy suffered a severe check. He actively opposed the policy of the Combes ministry and denounced the alliance with M. Jaurès, and on the 13th of January 1905 he was one of the leaders of the opposition which brought about the fall of the cabinet. Although he had been most violent ;in denouncing the anti-clerical policy of the Combes cabinet, he now announced his willingness to· recognize a new régime to replace the Concordat, and gave the government his support in the establishment of the <hi rend="italic">Associations Cultuedes</hi>, while he secured some mitigation of the severities attending the separation. He was re-elected deputy for St Omer in 1906. In the same year he became a member of the French Academy in succession to the duc d'Audiffret-Pasquier; he was already a member of the Academy of Moral and Political Science. In justification of his policy in opposition he published in 190$ two volumes of his <hi rend="italic">Discours politiques.</hi></p><p>RIBOT, THÉODULE (1823-1891), French painter, was bom at Breteuil, in Eure, in 1823, and died at Bois ColomBes, near Paris, in September 1891. A pupil nominally of Glaize, but more really of Ribera, of the great Flemings .and of Chardin, Théodule Ribot had yet conspicuously his own noble and personal vision, his own intensity of feeling and rich sobriety of performance. Beginning to work seriously at art when he was no longer extremely young, and dying before he was extremely oId, Ribot crowded into some thirty or thirty-five years of active practice very varied achievements; and he worked in at least three mediums, oil paint, pencil or crayon draughtsmanship and the needle of the etcher. His drawings were sometimes “ complete in themselves,” and sometimes fragmentary but powerful preparations for painted canvases. The etchings, of which there are only about a couple of dozen, are of the middle period of his practice; they show a diversity of method as well as of theme; the work in the w'ell-nigh Velazquez-Iike “ Prière ”—a group of girl children—contrasting strongly with that process almost of outline alone, w'hich he employed in the brilliant little group of prints which record his vision of the character and humours of cooks and kitchen-boys. In etching, the method varied with the theme—not with the period. It is quite otherwise W’ith the paintings. Here the earlier work, irrespective of its subject, is the drier</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>