<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>latter, in which thc Apocalyptist looks forward prophetically to the issue, the
                assurance held out is of ultimate victory, but of victory through death or
                martyrdom. In the former (Jewish or Christian-Jewish fragment) the sealing seemed to
                have carried with it the assurance of deliverance from physical death, as in Ezek.
                ix. 4 sqq. But in its <hi rend="italic">new</hi> context this meaning can hardly be
                retained. Not improbably the scaling means to our author the preservation not from
                death, but through death from unfaithfulness, and the number 144,000 would signify
                mystically the entire body of true Christians, which formed the true people of
                God,</p>
            <p>Chapter vii., then, interrupts the development of the author’s plan, but the
                interruption is deliberate. He wishes to encourage the persecuted church not only to
                face without fear, but also to meet with triumphant assurance the onset of those
                evils which would bring panic and despair on the unbelieving world.</p>
            <p>ww.-fx.—These chapters, though presenting some minor difficulties, do not call for
                discussion here. They recount the six partial judgments which followed the opening
                of the seventh seal and the blasts of the six trumpets.</p>
            <p>x.-xf. <hi rend="italic">1-1 d.—</hi>This section bristles with difficulties. Chapter
                x. forms an introduction to xi. 1-13. In it the prophet receives a new commission,
                x. 11 : “ Thou must prophesy again over many peoples and nations and tongues and
                kings.” This new commission explains his departure from the plan pursued in
                the earlier chapters of developing the seventh in each series into a new series of
                seven. The seer has a vision of the seven thunders, but these he is bidden to seal
                and not commit to writing. Hc is instead to write down the new book of prophecies.
                The end is at hand. It is noteworthy that in the earlier visions it was Christ who
                spoke to the seer. Here and in the later visions, especially those drawn from
                foreign sources, it is an angel.</p>
            <p>In xi. 1-13 we have a characteristic illustration of our author’s dependence on*
                traditional materials and his free adaptation of them to meanings other than
                originally belonged to them. For it is generally agreed among critics that xi. 1-13
                is borrowed from Jewish sources, and that this fragment really consists of two
                smaller fragments, xi. 1-2 and xi. 3-13. The former oracle referred originally to
                the actual. Temple, and contained a prediction of the preservation of the Temple. It
                must have been written before <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> 70 and probably by a
                    Zealot.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> But our author could not have taken it in this
                literal sense if he wrote after<hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> 70 or even anterior to
                that date, owing to the explicit declaration of Christ as to the coming destruction
                of Jerusalem. The passage, then, must have a spiritual meaning, and its purpose is
                the encouragement of the faithful by the assurance of their deliverance not
                necessarily from physical death but from the dominion of the evil one. In xi. 3-13
                we have another Jewish fragment of a very enigmatic character. Bousset has
                shown with much probability that it is part of the Antichrist legend. The prophecy
                of the two witnesses and their martyrdom belongs to this tradition. The fragment was
                apparently written before <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> 70, since it speaks of the
                fall of only a tenth of thc city, xi. 13.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The significance of
                this fragment in our author’s use of it is similar to that of xi. 1-2. The details
                defy at present any clear interpretation, but the incorporation of the fragment may
                be due in general to the emphasis it lays on the faithful witness, martyrdom and
                resurrection of the saints.</p>
            <p>xf. <hi rend="italic">14-19.—</hi>The seventh trumpet, xi. 15, ushers in the third
                woe, xi. 14. Its contents are given in xii.-xx. In xi. 15-19 the seer hears great
                voices in heaven singing a triumphal song in anticipation of the victory that is
                speedily to be achieved. This song forms a prelude to the chapters that follow.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><hi rend="italic">xii.—</hi>This is the most difficult chapter in the book. Its main
                intention in its present context is apparently to explain Satan’s dominion over the
                world and thc bitterness of his rage against the church and against Christ. Christ,
                indeed, escapes him and likewise the Jewish Christians (“ the woman,” xii. 16) but “
                the rest of her seed,” xii. 17 (the Gentile Christians?), are exposed to his fury.
                But his time is at hand; together with his hosts he has been cast down from heaven,
                and on the earth he <hi rend="sup">li</hi> hath but a short time.” The attribution
                of the seven heads and ten horns to the dragon, xii. 3, points forward to Rome,
                which is regarded as a temporary incarnation of Satan, xiii. 1, xvii. 3.</p>
            <p>But, though a few of the leading thoughts of this chapter may be obvious, we are
                plunged into problems that all but defy solution when we essay to discover its
                origin or interpret its details. Most scholars are agreed that this chapter is not,
                except in the case of a few sentences, the work of our author. In other words, it
                has been taken over from pre-existing material— either Christian or Jewish—and the
                materials of which it is composed are ultimately derived from non-Jewish
                sources— either Babylonian, Greek or Egyptian—and bore therein very different
                meanings from those which belong to them in their present connexion. Furthermore,
                the materials are fragmentary and the order irregular.</p>
            <p>(<hi rend="italic">a</hi>) First of all, the chapter is not the free creation of a
                Christian writer. Such an one could never have so represented the life of Christ—a
                child persecuted by a dragon and carried off to God’s throne. No mention of Christ’s
                earthly life and crucifixion. Furthermore, the victory over Satan is ascribed
                to Michael. Again, a Christian could not represent Christ as the son of the wife of
                the sun-god; for such is the natural interpretation of the woman crowned with the
                twelve stars and with her feet upon the moon. Finally, even if " the woman ” who is
                the mother of Christ be taken to be the ideal Israel in the beginning of the
                chapter, at its close she is clearly the Christian community founded by Him. We
                conclude, therefore, that the present chapter is not the work of our author. There
                are, however, traces of his hand. Thus 7-12, which is really a Jewish fragment
                recounting the victory of Michael over Satan, has to a certain degree been adapted
                to a Christian environment by the insertion of the 10b-11.</p>
            <p>(<hi rend="italic">b</hi>) The order is not original. The flight of the woman is
                mentioned in verse 6 to a place of refuge prepared for her by God. Then comes an
                account of the casting down of Satan from heaven. Then again in 13-16 the flight of
                the woman is described. This fact has been variously accounted for by different
                critics. Wellhausen regards 1-6 and 7-14 as doublets, and differentiates two actions
                in the original account which are here confused. Spitta takes verse 6 to be an
                addition of the redactor, which describes prolepticafly what follows, while
                Gunkel sees in 6 and 7-16 parallel accounts. In any case we should probably agree
                with the contention of J. Weiss, supported by Bousset in the second edition of his
                commentary, that 7-12 is a fragment of a Jewish apocalypse, of which iob-n is an
                addition of our author. Next that 6 is a doublet of 13 sqq. What then is to be made
                of 1-5, 13-17? Different explanations have been offered. Gunkel@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >3</hi> traces it to a Babylonian origin. He urges that an adequate explanation
                is impossible on thc assumption of a Jewish or Christian origin. At the base of this
                account lies the Babylonian myth of the birth of the sun-god Marduk, his escape from
                the dragon who knows him to be his destined destroyer, and the persecution of
                Marduk’s mother by the dragon. But GunkeFs explanation is an attempt to account for
                    one<hi rend="italic">ignotum per ignotius;</hi> for hitherto no trace of the
                myth of the sun-god’s birth and persecution and the flight into the wilderness has
                been found in Babylonian mythology. Moreover, Gunkel no longer lays emphasis on thc
                Babylonian, but merely on the mythical origin of the details. A more satisfactory
                explanation has been offered by Dieterich <hi rend="italic">(Abraxas, </hi>117
                sqq.), who finds in this chapter an adaptation of the birth of Apollo and the
                attempt of the dragon Pytho to kill his mother</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The Zealots occupied the inner court of the Temple during
                its siege by the Romans.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The. linguistic evidence, as Bousset has pointed out,
                confirms the critical conclusion that xi. 1-13 were independent sources. For whereas
                in ix.-x. the verb almost regularly begins the sentence and object follows the verb,
                in xi. 1-13 the object frequently precedes the verb and the subject nearly always.
                The order of the genitive in xi, 4 is elsewhere unknown in the AqocaIypse, and in
                xi. 2, 3 the construction of δώόραι followed by Kaiinstead of infinitive or<hi
                    rend="italic">ϊνα</hi> is unique in this book.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p><hi rend="italic"/>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi><hi rend="italic"> Schöpfung und
                    Chaos</hi> § 3, <hi rend="italic">Religionsgesch. Verstandniss d. N.T., </hi>54
                sqq.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
