<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the Incorporated Law Society in 1902. They may be found in the <hi rend="italic">Annual Practice.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Retainer of Debt.—</hi>In connexion with the administration of an estate under a will, it is the right of the personal representative—whether executor or administrator—of a deceased person to retain legal assets which have come into his hands towards the payment of a debt due to himself as against creditors of an equal degree, and this even though his debt is barred by the Statutes of Limitation. The privilege arose in all probability from the inability of the representative to sue himself, though it has been suggested that it is merely a corollary to the right of the representative to prefer one creditor to another of equal degree.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  The principle of retainer is not looked upon with favour by courts of equity, and consequently it has long been the rule that there is no right to retain out of equitable assets. It was thought that the effect of the Land Transfer Act 1897 was to make all the assets of the deceased legal assets, and so extend the privilege to reality which had till then been exempt; this view, however, has been repudiated by the courts of equity, and it must now be taken that there is still no right to retain out of real estate.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  It is a rule of the probate division to require a creditor administrator, to whom letters of administration are granted, to enter into a bond with two sureties not to prefer himself. This course, however, is not followed where administration is granted to a person as next of kin who happens also to be a creditor.</p><p>The privilege is not lost by judgment for an account being given in a suit by other creditors for the administration of assets, and the representative may retain out of assets which come to his hand subsequent to such judgment. On the other hand, the appointment of a receiver deprives the representative of his right except as regards assets which come to his hands prior to the appointment of the receiver.</p><p>RETALIATION, repayment of like with like, especially the return of hostile action, injuries or wrongs by similar action or injury, as in the primitive theory of punishment, an “ eye for an eye,” “ tooth for a tooth.” The Late Lat. <hi rend="italic">retaliare</hi>  was formed from <hi rend="italic">lalis,</hi>  such as, of the same quality as ; and this source also gave <hi rend="italic">talio, talionis,</hi>  the name of this type of punishment. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Punishment, Theory of,</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Roman Law, § </hi><hi rend="italic">The Twelve Tables.) </hi>A special form of retaliation is familiar in the imposition of differential import duties against the goods of a particular country (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Tariees</hi>  and <hi rend="smallcaps">Protection).</hi></p><p>RETENE (methyl isopropyl phenanthrene), CisH<hi rend="sub">18</hi>, a hydrocarbon present in the coal-tar fraction, boiling above 360° C.; it also occurs in the tars obtained by the distillation of resinous woods. It crystallizes in large plates, which melt at 98-5° C. and boil at 390° C. It is readily soluble in warm ether and in hot glacial acetic acid. Sodium and boiling amyl alcohol reduce it to a tetrahydroretene, Jwhilst if it be heated with phosphorus and hydriodic acid to 260° C. a dodecahydride is formed. Chromic acid oxidizes it to retene quinone, phthalic acid and acetic acid. It forms a picrate which melts at 123-124° C.</p><p>RETFORD (officially <hi rend="smallcaps">East Retford),.</hi>  a market town and municipal borough in the Bassctlaw parliamentary division of Nottinghamshire, England, 138I m. N. by W. from London by the Great Northern railway, the station being a junction with the Great Central railway. Pop. (1901) 12,340. The church of St Swithin dates from the 13th century, but was rebuilt in 1658 by a brief granted by Richard Cromwell. Modern buildings are the town hall, the corn exchange, the court house, and the covered markets. There is a large trade in corn and cheese, and the town possesses iron foundries, paper and corn mills, and india-rubber works. The town is governed by a mayor, 6 aldermen, and. 18 councillors. Area, 4656 acres.</p><p>The situation of Retford <hi rend="italic">CRedforde, Raiford),</hi>  near one of the Roman roads and on the river Idle, where there was possibly a ford, may account for its origin. In 1086 the archbishop of York owned a mill at Retford, and Roger de Busli had rights here. Retford was a borough by prescription, and was in the hands of the crown when, in 1276, Edward I. granted it to the burgesses in fee-farm with the right of electing bailiffs. This charter was confirmed by Edward III., Henry VI. and Elizabeth. In 1607 lames I. granted a. charter of incorporation to the bailiffs and burgesses, under which thc town was governed until 1835, when it was rcincorporated under a mayor. East Retford returned two members to parliament in 1315, and again from 1572 till 1885, when it was disfranchised. Henry III. granted the burgesses an eight-days’ fair at Holy Trinity, altered by Edward II. to St Gregory. Edward III. granted a six-days’ fair at St Margaret, and Henry VI. a four-days’ fair at St Matthew. Fairs are now held in March, June, July and December. The market held on Saturdays by prescription was sanctioned by Edward IIL and still exists.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>    Per Jessel, M.R.<hi rend="italic">Talbot</hi>  v. <hi rend="italic">Frere</hi>  (1879), L.R. 9. C.D. 568, 574.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">     In re Williams; Holder</hi>  v. <hi rend="italic">Williams</hi>  (1904), 1 Ch. 52.</p><lb/><p>RETHEL, ALFRED (1816-1859), German historical painter, was born at Aix-la-Chapelle in 1816. He very early showed an interest in art, and at the age of thirteen he executed a drawing which procured his admission to the academy of Düsseldorf. Here he studied for several years, and produced, among other works, a figure of St Boniface which attracted much attention. At the age of twenty he removed to Frankfort, and was selected to decorate the walls of the imperial hall in the Römer with figures of famous men. At the same period he produced a series of designs illustrative of Old Testament history. Four years later he was the successful competitor for the work of ornamenting the restored council house of his native city with frescoes depicting prominent events in the career of Charlemagne, but the execution of this work was delayed for some six years. Meanwhile Rethel occupied himself with the production of easel pictures and of drawings; and in 1842 he began a striking series of designs dealing with the “ Crossing of the Alps by Hannibal,” in which the weird power which animates his later art becomes first apparent. In 1844 Rethel visited Rome, executing, along with other subjects, an altar-piece for one of the churches of his native land. In 1846 he returned to Aix, and commenced his Charlemagne frescoes. But mental derangement, remotely attributable, it is believed, to an accident from which he suffered in childhood, began to manifest itself. While he hovered between madness and sanity, Rethel produced some of the most striking, individual and impressive of his works. Strange legends are told of the effect produced by some of his weird subjects. He painted “ Nemesis pursuing a AIurderer ”—a flat stretch of landscape, with a slaughtered body, while in front is the assassin speeding away into the darkness, and above an angel-of vengeance. The picture, so the story goes, was won in a lottery at Frankfort by a personage of high rank, who had been guilty of an undiscovered crime, and the contemplation of his prize drove him mad. Another design which Rethel executed was “ Death the Avenger,” a skeleton appearing at a masked ball, scraping daintily, like a violinist, upon two human bones. The drawing haunted the memory of his artist friends and disturbed their dreams; and, in expiation, he produced his pathetic design of “ Death the Friend.” Rethel also executed a powerful series of drawings—“ The Dance of Death ”—suggested by the Belgian insurrections of 1848. It is by such designs as these, executed in a technique founded upon that of Durer, and animated by an imagination akin to that of the elder master, that Rethel is most widely known. He died at Düsseldorf on the ist of December 1859.</p><p>His picture of “ Peter and John at the Beautiful Gate of the Temple,” is preserved in the Lelpzig Museum, and his “ St Boniface ” and several of his cartoons for the frescoes at Aix in the Berlin National Gallery. His Life, by Wolfgang Müller von Königswinter, was published in 1861. See also <hi rend="italic">Art Journal, </hi>November 1865.</p><p>RETHEL, a town of N. France, capital of an arrondissement in the department of Ardennes, on the right bank of the Aisne and the Ardennes canal, 31 m. S.W. of Mézières by rail. Pop. (1906) 5254. The church of St Nicholas was formed by the amalgamation of two churches, the oldest of which dates from the 13th century. Rethel has a subprefecture, a tribunal of first instance, a board of trade arbitration, a chamber of arts and manufactures and a school of agriculture, and carries on</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>