<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:10:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>12th July. As an administrator and legislator he showed an ability not inferior to that which in his earlier years he had manifested as a warrior and a general. He obtained from the estates a settlement of the succession, reformed abuses in the feudal law, regulated the courts, providing equal justice for poor and rich, and framed strict Acts against sedition. He also encouraged trade, especially shipbuilding, foreseeing its future importance to Scotland. Never off his guard, amongst his most anxious legislative provisions are those relating to the defence of the kingdom, —arming all able-bodied men, prohibiting exports of arms, fortifying the towns and castles on the borders, arranging signals to give notice of invasion. Though attacked by leprosy contracted in his campaigns, he remained active to the last,—a monarch such as occurs only once in many centuries, brave, liberal, wise, and pious, like the English Alfred, the darling of the nation he had delivered. (For fuller details, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert the Bruce,</hi> vol. xx. p. 594 <hi rend="italic">sqj) </hi>The wise provision that Bruce made for the regency secured the peaceful succession of his son David II. (1329- 70), who was the first Scottish king anointed at his coronation,—a privilege conceded to Bruce in a bull which reached Scotland after his death. According to the ideas of the age this placed the Scottish king on an equality with the sovereigns of Europe. The War of Independence quickened the sentiment of Scottish nationality, and left the country poorer in wealth but richer in spirit. The memories of Wallace and of Bruce educated the people and produced in the next generation their earliest literature. England, unconscious of the benefit, gained by its own defeat. But for the resistance of the Scots it might have become earlier than France a centralized feudal monarchy. The distinct character of the Scots—a blend of the Celt, Saxon, Norseman, and Norman—strengthened by variety the collective force of Britain. The loss which must be balanced against the gain was the bitter hatred between two races of kindred origin within one narrow isle, which for centuries retarded the progress of both, especially of the smaller kingdom.</p><p>The almost contemporaneous reigns of David II. and Edvard III. reversed the position of the two countries : Scotland had now one of its feeblest and England one of its most powerful kings. Had not the love of liberty become the life-blood of both nobles and commons in Scot- land it must have succumbed in the desperate struggle. After the death of Robert, Randolph, earl of Moray, governed with wisdom and vigour for three years. On his death the estates chose Donald, earl of Mar, another nephew of Bruce, whom he had passed over, foreseeing his incapacity. Encouraged by the divisions of the nobles, Edward, son of John Baliol, with the barons who had lost them land by espousing the English side, suddenly landed at Kinghorn. Nine days after his election, Mar was met and worsted by Balid on Dupplin Muir (11th August 1332), where Mar himself and many nobles were slain. Baliol was crowned at Score; but Perth was immediately retaken, and Baliol, having been defeated at Annan by the young earl of Moray, left Scotland Next year Edward came with a large army to his support and defeated at Halidon Hill (20th July 1333), chiefly through the skill of the archers, the Scots led by Archbald Douglas, lord of Galloway, who was now regent. Berwck capitulated and Baliol surrendered it to England, pledgng in addition the castles of the Lothians, including Edinburgh and Linlithgow, in security for an annual tribute of £2100. Like his grandfather, Edward III. made a new ordinance for the government of Scotland, but his officers never obtained possession of their posts. Meantime David and his queen fled to France, where they remained seven years. Fortunately for Scotland a new race of patriotic leader appeared : Moray of Bothwell handed down the</p><p>traditions of Wallace and Bruce, while Robert the Steward, Douglas the knight of Liddesdale, and Sir Alexander Ramsay of Dalhousie sustained the fame of Bruce, Randolph, and Douglas. The attraction of a French campaign with the crown of France as prize prevented Edward from ever using his whole force against Scotland, and a French fleet made a diversion by attacking the Channel Islands and threatening the Isle of Wight. Edward retaliated by assuming the title of king of France, and after two years’ preparation invaded that country from Flanders. The armies met at Vironfosse (26th September 1339), where David of Scotland was present. Never was the pomp of chivalry seen in greater splendour, but the first act of the Hundred Years’ War, which seemed destined to make French and English eternal enemies and French and Scots perpetual allies, passed without a blow.</p><p>Two years later the recovery of the Scottish castles and the repulse of Salisbury’s attempt on Dunbar made it safe for David to return to Scotland, which Baliol had abandoned. Though scarcely eighteen, he assumed the government (30th March 1342). Before his arrival Edinburgh had fallen, and next year Roxburgh was taken by Sir Alexander Ramsay, whom David unfortunately rewarded by the sheriffdom of Teviotdale, which the knight of Liddesdale claimed, and Ramsay, seized by treachery, was starved to death at the Hermitage by the knight of Liddesdale, who entered into correspondence with the English king, and dishonoured his name of the “ Flower of Chivalry.” Bullock, an ecclesiastic who had risen to the office of chamberlain under Baliol and transferred his services to David, met the same fate at the hands of the king on a suspicion of treason. Other signs of weak government were not wanting. On the conclusion of a brief truce, David, tempted by Edward’s absence, invaded England in spite of the defection of some of his chief nobles, and was defeated at Neville’s Cross (17th October 1346) near Durham by the archbishop of York and the northern barons, the king and several of his nobles being taken prisoners. The rigour of David’s captivity (which lasted eleven years) was relaxed so far as to allow him to return frequently to Scotland and try to persuade the people to raise his ransom, which the English king urgently required. Though Baliol was still acknowledged as nominal king by Edward, he resided in Galloway, while Robert the Steward, elected regent in the name of David, really governed. At length by the treaty of Newcastle (13th July 1354) David’s ransom was agreed on, sufficient hostages being taken for its payment. Next year the French king resumed the Scottish war by sending Eugène de Garancière with men, money, and arms. Several border engagements followed, but Edward, advancing to the frontier, took Berwick, and obtained from his puppet Baliol an absolute surrender of the Scottish kingdom for an annuity. He ravaged the Lothians in the raid called the Burnt Candlemas, but failed really to reduce the country. Edward’s victory over the French at Poitiers, in which many Scots were slain, forced the Scottish parliament to grant the terms dictated by the English king. Peace was finally concluded by the treaty of Berwick (3d October 1357), and confirmed at Scone,—the ransom being raised and the condition as to hostages made more severe. David at once returned to Scotland. But his sympathies had become English ; he revisited that country almost every year, and it required all the strength of the Scottish estates to prevent the son of Bruce from making a surrender of his kingdom more ignominious than Baliol's. The enormous ransom pressed hard on so poor a country. An attempt to induce France to resume the war failed, and David, like a debtor dealing with a money-lender, had to renew his bills at usury. Negotiations for this purpose</p></body></text></TEI>