<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:10:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The first ten members are elected for four years, which is also the financial period. There is a ministry with five departments—for the prince’s household, domestic affairs, finance, churches and schools, and justice. The budget for each year in the period 1884-87 estimated the income at £112,475 and the expenditure at £1000 less. The public debt in 1885 was £199,625. The troops of Schwarzburg-Sondershausen have been incorporated with the Prussian army by convention since 1867. The principality has one vote in the Reichstag and one in the federal council.</p><p>The house of Schwarzburg is one of the oldest and noblest in Germany ; and tradition traces its descent from Witikind and the kings of the Franks. Its historical ancestors were the counts of Käfernburg, from whom the counts of Schwarzburg sprang about the beginning of the 13th century. The name Giinther became the distinctive name for the members of this house (corresponding to Heinrich in the Reuss family), the various Günthers being at first distinguished by numbers and afterwards by prefixed names. Various subdivisions and collateral lines were formed, but by 1599 all were extinct but the present two. Count Günther XL., who died in 1552, was the last common ancestor of both lines. Schwarzburg-Sondershausen is the senior line, although its possessions are the smaller. In 1697 the count was raised to the dignity of imperial prince by the emperor Leopold I. The prince had to pay 7000 thalers to the elector of Saxony and 3500 to the duke of Saxe-Weimar, and numerous disputes arose in connexion with the superiorities thus indicated. In 1807 Schwarzburg-Sondershausen entered the Confederation of the Rhine and became a sovereign state. In 1816 it joined the German League, and redeemed with</p><p>portions of its territory all rights of superiority claimed by Prussia, Its domestic government has gradually, though not very quickly, improved since that time,—the oppressive game-laws in particular having been abolished. A treaty of mutual succession was made between the two families in 1713.</p><p>SCHWARZENBERG, <hi rend="smallcaps">Karl Philipp, Prince of</hi> (1771-</p><p>1820), Austrian field-marshal, was born on 15th April 1771 at Vienna. He fought in 1789 under Lacy with distinction against the Turks and became major in 1792. In the French campaign of 1793 he held command of a portion of the advanced guard under the duke of Coburg, and in 1794 his impetuous charge at the head of a cavalry regiment greatly contributed to the victory of Cateau- Cambrésis. After the battle of Würzburg in September 1796 he was raised to the rank of major-general, and in 1799 to that of field-marshal in command of a division. At the defeat of Hohenlinden in 1800 his promptitude and courage saved those under his command from being surrounded and taken prisoners. In the war of 1805 he held command of a division under General Mack, and when Ulm capitulated to Napoleon in October he cut his way through the hostile lines with some cavalry regiments. At the special request of the emperor Alexander he undertook an embassy to St Petersburg in 1808, but two days before the battle of Wagram he arrived in the camp and assumed command as general of the cavalry. After the peace of Vienna he was sent to Paris to negotiate a marriage between Napoleon and the duchess Maria Louisa. From this time he secured Napoleon’s special confidence and esteem, and at his request took command of the Austrian auxiliary corps in the Russian campaign. In August he received the command of the seventh or Saxon army corps ; after gaining some slight advantages over the Russians, he was compelled to retreat before superior forces to the duchy of Warsaw, where, according to instructions from Napoleon, he remained for some months inactive at Pultusk. In 1813 he was appointed commander-in-chief of the allied forces, and, after defeating·Napoleon at Leipsic in October, carried the campaign to a successful issue by entering Paris in March 1814. On the conclusion of the war he became president of the Aulic Council. He died from paralysis at Leipsic on 15th October 1820.</p><p>See Prokesch-Osten, <hi rend="italic">Denkwürdigkeiten aus dem Leben des Feldmarschall's Fürsten Schwarzenberg,</hi> Vienna, 1823 ; Berger, <hi rend="italic">Das Fürstenhaus Schwarzenberg,</hi> Vienna, 1866.</p><p>SCHWEGLER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert</hi> (1819-1857), historical, philosophical, and theological writer, one of the first and most distinguished of the pupils of F. C. Baur and of the <hi rend="italic">dei minores</hi> of the Tübingen school. He was born at Michel-</p><p>bach in Würtemberg on 10th February 1819, the son of a country clergyman, and entered the university of Tübingen· in 1836 as a student of theology, though with a predominant liking for classical philology. Under Baur’s influence he devoted himself to the study of ecclesiastical history, and his first work was <hi rend="italic">Der Montanismus u. die christliche Kirche des 2ten Jahrhunderts</hi> (1841), in which he was the first to point out that Montanism was much more than an isolated outbreak of eccentric fanaticism in the early church, though he introduced fresh misconceptions by connecting it with Ebionitism as he conceived the latter. This work, with other essays, brought Schwegler into conflict with the authorities of the church, in consequence of which he gave up theology as his professional study and chose that of philosophy. In 1843 he commenced in the Tübingen university the career of a teacher <hi rend="italic">(privat-docent)</hi> of philosophy and classical philology, and in 1848 was made extraordinary professor of the latter subject and soon after ordinary professor of history. His death took place on 5th January 1857.</p><p>His principal theological work was <hi rend="italic">Das nachapostolische Zeitalter </hi>(2 vols., 1846). It was this hook which first put before the world, with Schwegler’s characteristic boldness and clearness, the results of the critical labours of the earlier Tübingen school in relation to the first development of Christianity. Carl Schwarz says of it, “ This work—full though it was of youthful exaggerations and provocations, partisan as it was in its line of argument, untrue and abstract as its contrast of Paulinism and Petrinism was, and arbitrary as was its use of those party names—produced nevertheless by its masterly literary form (which reminds us of Strauss), and by its easy handling and presentation of all the important data, a powerful impression, and, although in many points of detail it is out of date, it may still be regarded as one of the ‘ standard works ’ of the school.” Schwegler published also an edition of the <hi rend="italic">Clementine Homilies</hi> (1847), and of Eusebius’s <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi> (1852). In the department of philosophy we have an edition of the <hi rend="italic">Metaphysics</hi> of Aristotle, with a translation and commentary (4 vols., 1847-48), the well-known sketch of the <hi rend="italic">History of Philosophy </hi>(1848), and a posthumous <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Gricch. Philosophie</hi> (1859). In history he commenced a <hi rend="italic">Römische Geschichte</hi> (vols. i.-iii., 1853- 58, 2d ed., 1869), which he brought down only to the laws of Licinius.</p><p>SCHWEIDNITZ, a manufacturing and trading town of Lower Silesia in Prussia, is picturesquely situated on the left bank of the Weistritz, 28 miles south-west of Breslau. Well built, with wide streets, the town contains several old churches (one of which has a tower 338 feet high) and an ancient town-house with a tower 130 feet high. The surrounding country is fertile and highly cultivated, and the large quantities of flax and hemp there raised encourage an active weaving industry in the town. Beetroot for sugar, grain, and fruit are also grown. The manufacture of furniture, leather gloves, machinery and tools, carriages, nuts and screws, needles, and other hardware goods is carried on. The beer of Schweidnitz has long been famous under the name of  “Schwarze Schöps,” and in the 16th century it was exported as far as Italy. Schweidnitz is the chief grain market of the district. The population in 1885 was 23,775 (an increase of 6 per cent. since 1880); in 1816 it was 10,046.</p><p>Schweidnitz, dating from about the 11th century, received town rights in 1250. About 1278 it became the capital of a principality, with an area of 935 square miles, which belonged to Bohemia from 1353 till 1741, when it passed into the possession of Prussia. The “ Pölerei of Schweidnitz ” is the name given to the riotous revolt of the town, in 1520-22, against a royal edict depriving it of the right of coining its own money. The town was four times besieged and taken in the Seven Years’ War ; and in 1807 it was captured by the French, who demolished the fortifications. In 1816 new works were raised, but in 1864 they were converted into a public park.</p><p>SCHWEINFURT, a manufacturing town of Lower Franconia in Bavaria, is situated on the right bank of the Main, 22 miles north-east of Würzburg. The Renaissance town-house in the spacious market-place dates from 1570 ;</p></body></text></TEI>