<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:10:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Henry I., who had lost his only son by the shipwreck of the “White Ship.” Soon after a rising of Scottish Celts under a natural son of Alexander and Angus, a grandson of the mormaer of Moray, was defeated at Stracathro (Forfar) by David’s troops in his absence in England, and four years later another under Wimund, who pretended to be Malcolm MacHeth, a chief in Ross, aided by Somerled of Argyll, who had acquired some of the adjacent isles, was put down by Wimund’s capture. The death of Henry I. and the claim of Stephen to the English throne led to the invasion of England by David, in support of Matilda, with an army drawn from all parts of his kingdom, —the men of Galloway, Cumbria, Teviotdale, Lothian, Lennox, the Isles, Scotia (the country south of the Forth or Scots Water), and Moray. Their defeat at the battle of the Standard at Cuton Moor (1138) near Northallerton by the barons of northern England was due to the want of discipline of the men of Galloway, and, though signal, was not decisive. At Carlisle peace was made on condition that David’s son Henry should hold Northumberland as an earldom under Stephen, with the exception of the castles of Bamborough and Newcastle. David gave hostages, but retained Carlisle and Cumberland without any condition of homage. Two years later, when Matilda seized London, David joined her ; but she was unable to maintain her advantage. David was forced to return to Scotland, and did not again engage in active hostilities against Stephen. His death was preceded by that of his only son ; but his power was so firm that he procured the acknowledgment of his grandson Malcolm, a boy of twelve, as successor to the Scottish crown, while William, his younger grandson, succeeded to Northumberland and the English fiefs his father had held.</p><p>The comparative peace of his last twelve years gave David opportunity for the ecclesiastical and civil organization of the kingdom. He found three and left nine bishoprics, adding to St Andrews, Moray, and Dunkeld the new sees of Glasgow, Brechin, Dunblane, Aberdeen (transferred from Mortlach), Ross, and Caithness. Closely connected with their establishment was the suppression of the Celtic Culdees at Dunkeld. St Andrews, and Loch Leven, and perhaps also at Dunblane and Dornoch, where canons regular of St Augustine became the chapters of the bishop. The abbeys, chiefly Cistercian, which he founded were Holyrood, Newbattle, Melrose, Jedburgh, Kelso, Cambuskenneth, Urquhart, and Kinloss. He added to the endowments of his father and mother at Dunfermline, and so lessened the crown lands that James I. called him “ a sore saint for the crown.” The division into dioceses stimulated the formation of parishes endowed by the bishops or by the lords of the manor ; but the first steps of the parochial division of Scotland are obscure. The diocesan episcopate now included the whole of Scotland except what was held by the Norsemen, who had bishops of their own for the Orkneys and the western isles, subject to the metropolitan of Drontheim. It preceded the civil division into sheriffdoms, which also began in this reign, but took a longer period to complete. The Celtic chiefs in the north and in Galloway were as yet too powerful to allow royal officers to hold courts within their territory, and regalities with the full rights of the crown in matters of justice were more lavishly granted in Scotland than in England, where they were confined to the few palatine earls or bishops on the border. The feudal system in Scotland, erroneously antedated to the reign of Malcolm II. or Malcolm Canmore, really took root in that of David. The king administered justice in person. The great judicial officer of state, the justiciar, who went circuits in the king’s name, appears either in this or the preceding reign <hi rend="italic">; so </hi>also do the seneschal or steward of the royal household</p><p>and the chamberlain who collected the royal revenues. The tenure of land by charter, of which there are a few examples by Edgar in favour of Durham and by Alexander I. in favour of Scone, now became common. The charters of David to the abbey of Holyrood, to Robert Bruce of Annandale, and others are in the regular style of the Norman chancery. There are also instances of subordinate grants by subjects, which the king confirms. Though no charter to a burgh is extant, David refers to Edinburgh, Perth, and Stirling as his burghs. The inquest in favour of the see of Glasgow is, by the verdict of those best acquainted with the facts, similar to the Norman inquest. The laws of the four burghs of Lothian—Berwick, Roxburgh, Edinburgh, and Stirling—are records of customs existing in this reign, while a variety of other laws called assizes, chiefly relating to tolls and matters of criminal jurisprudence, were the legislative acts of the king, assisted by the council of his great nobles. The beginning of the feudal system in Scotland was invigorated by the personal character of David. The absence of any large body of settled Celtic or Saxon customs gave full play to its assimilative influence. In the reigns which followed Scotland became a purer example of a feudal state than England, where a large number of Teutonic customs contributed to form the common law. A few of these found their way into Scotland, chiefly through the burghs or the medium of Norman charters, in which they had been incorporated. But the Scottish common law was in the main derived from the Roman code through the canon law, and not from Anglo- Saxon customs. Though never canonized by the church, this great monarch, for his faithful administration of justice and the purity of his domestic life, was deemed a saint by the people.</p><p>David’s grandson and successor Malcolm IV. (1154-65), called “ The Maiden,” died too young to leave a permanent impression. A rising by Somerled, lord of the Isles, and the sons of Malcolm MacHeth, mormaer of Moray, was suppressed in the early years of his reign, and peace was made with Somerled in 1158. A treaty by which Malcolm surrendered Northumberland and Cumberland to Henry II., and his following that king (who knighted him at Tours) in an expedition to Toulouse, led to the revolt of the earl of Strathearn with five other chiefs. This brought him suddenly home. An attempt to take him by surprise at Perth failed, and next year he succeeded in reducing Moray and Galloway, whose earl, Fergus, had also taken advantage of his absence. Moray was occupied by foreign settlers (1160), amongst whom, besides Norman barons, were Flemings,—a race fitted to civilize a new country by their industry. It is to this settlement that the permanent subjection of Moray to the Scottish kings, and perhaps the peculiar dialect and character of the inhabitants of that part of Scotland, were due. Four years later Somerled again attacked the west coast, but was defeated and slain at Renfrew, when the isles south of Ardnamurchan, which he had won from Godred the Black, son of Olaf, king of Man, were divided amongst his sons Dugall, Reginald, and Angus. Next year (1165) the young king himself died at Jedburgh. "While he was reproached for yielding too much to the powerful English monarch, his service abroad enabled him to obtain the necessary experience to contend with the Celtic chiefs. The reduction of Galloway and Moray more than compensated for the loss of the earldoms in northern England, the possession of which by the Scottish king must have been precarious. Before his death Bute had been taken by the steward of Scotland,—the first footing the Scotch got on the larger isles, but it was afterwards recovered by the Norwegian king Haco and restored to Ruari, a descendant of Reginald.</p><p>Malcolm, dying childless—though he had an illegitimate</p></body></text></TEI>