<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0181.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0175-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCUDDING</label>,
the movement by which a ſhip is carried precipitately before a tempeſt. As a ſhip flies with amazing rapidity through the water whenever this expedient is put in practice, it is never attempted in a contrary wind, unleſs when her condition renders her incapable of ſuſtaining the mutual effort of the wind and waves any longer on her ſide, without being expoſed to the moſt imminent danger of being overſet.</p><p>A ſhip either ſcuds with a ſail extended on her foremaſt, or, if the ſtorm is exceſſive, without any ſail: which, in the ſea-phraſe, is called <hi rend="italic">ſcudding under bare poles.</hi> In ſloops and ſchooners, and other ſmall veſſels; the ſail employed for this purpoſe is called the <hi rend="italic">ſquare-</hi> ſ <hi rend="italic">ail.</hi> In large ſhips, it is either the foreſail at large, reefed, or with its gooſe-wings-extended, according to the degree of the tempeſt; or it is the fore-top fail, cloſe reefed, and lowered on the cap; which laſt is particularly uſed when the ſea runs ſo high as to becalm the foreſail occaſionally, a circumſtance which expoſes the ſhip to the danger of broaching-to. The principal hazards incident to ſcudding are generally, a pooping ſea; the difficulty of fleering, which expoſes the veffel perpetually to the riſk of broaching-to; and the want of ſufficient ſea-room. A ſea ſtriking the ſhip violently on the ſtern may daſh it inwards, by which ſhe muſt inevitably founder. In broaching-to (that is, inclining ſuddenly to windward), ſhe is threatened with being immediately overturned; and, for want of ſea- room, ſhe is endangered by ſhipwreck on a lee-ſhore, a circumſtance too dreadful to require explanation.</p></div></body></text></TEI>