<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196363_0204.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0198-04"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SEAMANSHIP</label></p>
                <p>BY this word we expreſs that noble art, or, more purely, the qualifications which
                    enable a man to exerciſe the noble art of working a ſhip. A <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >seaman,</hi> in the language of the profeſſion, is not merely a mariner
                    or labourer on board a ſhip, but a man who underſtands the ſtructure of this
                    wonderful machine, and every ſubordinate part of its mechaniſm, ſo as to enable
                    him to employ it to the beſt advantage for puſhing her forward in a particular
                    direction, and for avoiding the numberleſs dangers to which ſhe is expoſed by
                    the violence of the winds and waves. He alſo knows what courſes can be held by
                    the ſhip, according to the wind that blows, and what cannot, and which of theſe
                    is moſt conducive to her progreſs in her intended voyage; and he muſt be able to
                    perform every part of the neceſſary operation with his own hands. As the ſea-men
                    expreſs it, he muſt be able “to hand, reef, and ſteer.”</p>
                <p>We are juſtified in calling it a <hi rend="italic">noble art,</hi> not only by
                    its importance, which it is quite needleſs to amplify or embelliſh, but by its
                    immenſe extent and difficulty, and the prodigious number and variety of
                    principles on which it is founded—all of which muſt be poſſeſſed in ſuch a
                    manner that they ſhall offer themſelves without reflection in an inſtant,
                    otherwiſe the pretended ſeaman is but a lubber, and cannot be truſted on his
                    watch.</p>
                <p>The art is practiſed by perſons without what we call <hi rend="italic"
                        >education,</hi> and in the humbler walks of life, and therefore it ſuffers
                    in the eſtimation of the careleſs ſpectator. It is thought little of, becauſe
                    little attention is<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0205.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0199"/> paid to it. But if multiplicity, variety, and
                    intricacy of principles, and a ſyſtematic knowledge of theſe principles, intitle
                    any art to the appellation of <hi rend="italic">ſcientific</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">liberal,</hi> ſeamanſhip claims theſe epithets in an eminent
                    degree. We are amuſed with the pedantry of the ſea- man, which appears in his
                    whole language. Indeed it is the only pedantry that amuſes. A ſcholar, a
                    ſoldier, a lawyer, nay, even the elegant courtier, would diſguſt us, were he to
                    make the thouſandth part of the alluſions to his profeſſion that is well
                    received from the jolly ſea- man; and we do the ſeaman no more than juſtice. His
                    profeſſion muſt engroſs his whole mind, otherwiſe he can never learn it. He
                    poſſeſſes a prodigious deal of knowledge; but the honeſt tar cannot tell what he
                    knows, or rather what he feels, for his ſcience is really at his fingers ends.
                    We can ſay with confidence, that if a perſon of education, verſed in mechanics,
                    and acquainted with the ſtructure of a ſhip, were to obſerve with attention the
                    movements which are made on board a firſt or ſecond rate ſhip of war during a
                    ſhifting ſtorm, under the direction of an intelligent officer, he would be rapt
                    in admiration.</p>
                <p>What a pity it is that an art ſo important, ſo difficult, and ſo intimately
                    connected with the invariable laws of mechanical nature, ſhould be ſo held by
                    its poſſeſſors, that it cannot improve, but muſt die with each individual.
                    Having no advantages of previous education, they cannot arrange their thoughts;
                    they can hardly be ſaid to think. They can far leſs expreſs or communicate to
                    others the intuitive knowledge which they poſſeſs; and their art, acquired by
                    habit alone, is little different from an inſtinct. We are as little intitled to
                    expect improvement here as in the architecture of the bee or the beaver. The
                    ſpecies (pardon the alluſion ye generous hearts of oak) cannot improve. Yet a
                    ſhip is a machine. We know the forces which act on it, and we know the reſults
                    of its conſtruction— all theſe are as fixed as the laws of motion. What hinders
                    this to be reduced to a ſet of practical maxims, as well founded and as
                    logically deduced as the working oſ a ſteam engine or a cotton mill. The ſtoker
                    or the ſpinner acts only with his hands, and may “whiſtle as he works for want
                    of thought;” but the mechaniſt, the engineer, thinks for him, improves his
                    machine, and directs him to a better practice. May not the rough ſea- man look
                    for the ſame aſſiſtance; and may not the ingenious ſpeculatiſt in his cloſet
                    unravel the intricate thread of mechaniſm which connects all the manual
                    operations with the unchangeable laws of nature, and both furniſh the ſeaman
                    with a better machine and direct him to a more dexterous uſe of it?</p>
                <p>We cannot help thinking that much may be done; nay, we may ſay that much has been
                    done. We think highly of the progreſſive labours of Renaud, Pitot, Bouguer, Du
                    Hamel, Groignard, Bernoulli, Euler, Romme, and others; and are both ſurpriſed
                    and ſorry that Britain has contributed ſo little in theſe attempts. Gordon is
                    the only one of our countrymen who has given a profeſſedly ſcientific treatiſe
                    on a ſmall branch of the ſubject. The government of France has always been
                    ſtrongly impreſſed with the notion of great improvements being attainable by
                    ſyſtematic ſtudy of this art; and we are indebted to the endeavours of that
                    ingenious nation for any thing of practical importance that has</p>
                <p>been obtained. M. Bouguer was profeſſor of hydrology at one of the marine
                    academies of France, and was enjoined, as part of his duty, to compoſe
                    diſſertations both on the conſtruction and the working of ſhipa. His <hi
                        rend="italic">Traité du Navire,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Manœuvre des
                        Vaisseaux,</hi> are undoubtedly very valuable performances: So are thoſe of
                    Euler and Bernoulli, conſidered as mathematical differtations, and they are
                    wonderful works of genius, conſidered as the productions of perſons who hardly
                    ever ſaw a ſhip, and were totally unacquainted with the profeſſion of a ſeaman.
                    In this reſpect Bouguer had great ſuperiority, having always lived at a
                    ſea-port, and having made many very long voyages. His treadles therefore are
                    infinitely better accommodated to the demands of the ſeaman, and more directly
                    inſtructive; but ſtill the author is more a mathematician than an artiſt, and
                    his performance is intelligible only to mathematicians. It is true, the
                    academical education of the young gentlemen of the French navy is ſuch, that a
                    great number of them may acquire the preparatory knowledge that is neceſſary;
                    and we are well informed that, in this reſpect, the officers of the Britiſh navy
                    are greatly inferior to them.</p>
                <p>But this very circumſtance has furniſhed to many perſons an argument againſt the
                    utility of thoſe performances. It is ſaid that, “notwithſtanding this ſuperior
                    mathematical education, and the poſſeſſion of thoſe boaſted performances of M.
                    Bouguer, the French are greatly inferior, in point of ſeamanſhip, to our
                    countrymen, who have not a page in their language to inſtruct them, and who
                    could not peruſe it if they had it. "Nay, ſo little do the French themſelves
                    ſeem ſenſible of the advantage of theſe publications, that no perſon among them
                    has attempted to make a familiar abridgement oſ them, written in a way fitted to
                    attract attention; and they ſtill remain neglected in their original abſtruſe
                    and unintereſting form.</p>
                <p>We wiſh that we could give a ſatisfactory anſwer to this obſervation. It is juſt,
                    and it is important. Theſe very ingenious and learned diſſertations are by no
                    means ſo uſeful as we ſhould expect. They are large books, and appear to contain
                    much; and as their plan is logical, it ſeems to occupy the whole ſubject, and
                    therefore to have done almoſt all that can be done. But, alas! they have only
                    opened the ſubject, and the ſtudy is yet in its infancy. The whole ſcience of
                    the art muſt proceed on the knowledge of the impulſions of the wind and water.
                    Theſe are the forces which act on the machine; and its motions, which are the
                    ultimatum of our reſearch, whether as an end to be obtained or as a thing to be
                    prevented, muſt depend on theſe forces. Now it is with reſpect to this
                    fundamental point that we are as yet almoſt totally in the dark. And, in the
                    performances of M. Bouguer, as alſo in thoſe of the other authors we have named,
                    the theory of theſe forces, by which their quantity and the direction of their
                    action are aſcertained, is altogether erroneous; and its reſults deviate ſo
                    enormouſly from what is obſerved in the motions of a, ſhip, that the perſon who
                    ſhould direct the operations on ſhipboard, in conformity to the maxims deducible
                    from M. Bouguer’s propoſitions, would be baffled in moſt oſ his attempts, and be
                    in danger of loſing the ſhip. The whole proceeds on the ſuppoſed truth of that
                    theory which ſtates the impulſe of a fluid<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0206.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0200"/> to be in the proportion of the ſquare of the
                    fine of the angle of incidence; and that its action on any ſmall portion, ſuch
                    as a ſquare foot of the ſails or hull, is the ſame as if that portion were
                    detached from the reſt, and were expoſed, single and alone, to the wind or water
                    in the same angle. But we have ſhown, in the article RESISTANCE <hi
                        rend="italic">of Fluids,</hi> both from theory and experience, that both of
                    theſe principles are erroneous, and this to a very great degree, in caſes which
                    occur moſt frequently in practice, that is, in the ſmall angles of inclination.
                    When the wind falls nearly perpendicular on the ſails, theory is not very
                    erroneous; but in theſe caſes, the circumſtances of the ſhip’s ſituation are
                    generally ſuch that the practice is eaſy, occurring aimoſt without thought; and
                    in this caſe, too, even conſiderable deviations from the very beſt practice are
                    of no great moment. The intereſting caſes, where the intended movement requires
                    or depends upon very oblique actions of the wind on the ſails, and its
                    practicability or impracticability depends on a very ſmall variation of this
                    obliquity; a miſtake of the force, either as to intenſity or direction, produces
                    a mighty effect on the resulting motion. This is the caſe in ſailing to
                    windward; the most important of all the general problems of ſeamanſhip. The trim
                    of the ſails, and the courſe of the ſhip, ſo as to gain moſt on the wind, are
                    very nice things; that is, they are confined within very narrow limits, and a
                    ſmall miſtake produces a very conſiderable effect. The ſame thing obtains in
                    many of the nice problems of tacking, box-hauling, wearing after lying-to in a
                    ſtorm, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The error in the ſecond aſſertion of the theory is ſtill greater, and the action
                    on one part of the ſail or hull is ſo greatly modified by its action on another
                    adjoining part, that a ſtay-ſail is often ſeen hanging like a looſe rag, altho’
                    there is nothing between it and the wind; and this merely becauſe a great ſail
                    in its neighbourhood ſends off a lateral ſtream of wind, which completely
                    hinders the wind from getting at it. Till the theory of the action of fluids be
                    eſtabliſhed, therefore, we cannot tell what are the forces which are acting on
                    every point of the ſail and hull: Therefore we cannot tell either the mean
                    intenſity or direction of the whole force which acts on any particular ſail, nor
                    the intenſity and mean direction of the reſiſtance to the hull; circumſtances
                    abſolutely neceſſary for enabling us to ſay what will be their energy in
                    producing a rotation round any particular axis. In like manner, we cannot, by
                    ſuch a computation, find the ſpontaneous axis of converſion (ſee <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Rotation),</hi> or the velocity of ſuch converſion. In
                    ſhort, we cannot pronounce with tolerable confidence <hi rend="italic">à
                        priori</hi> what will be the motions in any caſe, or what diſpoſitions of
                    the ſails will produce the movement we wiſh to perform. The experienced ſeaman
                    learns by habit the general effects of every diſpoſition of the ſails; and
                    though his knowledge is far from being accurate, it ſeldom leads him into any
                    very blundering operation. Perhaps he ſeldom makes the beſt adjuſtment poſſible,
                    but ſeldomer ſtill does he deviate very far from <hi rend="italic">it</hi>; and
                    in the moſt general and important problems, ſuch as working to windward, the
                    reſult of much experience and many corrections has ſettled a trim of the ſails,
                    which is certainly not far from the truth, but (it muſt ſee acknowledged)
                    deviates widely and uniformly from</p>
                <p>the theories of the mathematician’s clofet. The honest tar, therefore, muſt be
                    indulged in his joke on the uſeleſs labours of the mathematician, who can
                    neither hand, reef, nor ſteer.</p>
                <p>After this account of the theoretical performances in the art of ſeamanſhip, and
                    what we have ſaid in another place on the ſmall hopes we entertain of ſeeing a
                    perfect theory of the impulſe of fluids, it will not be expected that we enter
                    very minutely on the ſubject in this place; nor is it our intention. But let it
                    be obſerved, that the theory is defective in one point only; and although this
                    is a moſt important point, and the errors in it deſtroy the conduirons of the
                    chief propoſitions, the reaſonings remain in full force, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> is preciſely ſuch as is ſtated in the
                    theory. The <hi rend="italic">principles</hi> of the art are therefore to be
                    found in theſe treatiſes; but falſe inferences have been drawn, by computing
                    from erroneous quantities. The rules and the practice of the computation,
                    however, are ſtill beyond controverſy: Nay, ſince the proceſs of inveſtigation
                    is legitimate, we may make uſe of it in order to diſcover the very circumſtance
                    in which we are at preſent miſtaken; for by converting the propoſition, inſtead
                    of finding the motions by means of the ſuppoſed forces, combined with the known
                    mechaniſm, we may diſcover the forces by means of this mechaniſm and the
                    obſerved motions.</p>
                <p>We ſhall therefore in this place give a very general view of the movements of a
                    ſhip under ſail, ſhowing how they are produced and modified by the action of the
                    wind on her ſails, the water on her rudder and on her bows. We ſhall not attempt
                    a preciſe determination of any of theſe movements; but we ſhall ſay enough to
                    enable the curious landſman to underſtand how this mighty machine is managed
                    amidſt the fury of the winds and waves: and, what is more to our wiſh, we hope
                    to enable the uninſtructed but thinking ſeaman to generaliſe that knowledge
                    which poſſeſſes; to claſs his ideas, and give them a ſort of rational ſyſtem;
                    and even to improve his practice, by making him ſensible of the immediate
                    operation of every thing he does, and in what manner it contributes to produce
                    the movement which he has in view.</p>
                <p>A ſhip may be conſidered at preſent as a maſs of inert matter in free ſpace, at
                    liberty to move in every direction, according to the forces which impel or
                    refill her: and when ſhe is in actual motion, in the direction of her courſe, we
                    may ſtill conſider her as at reſt in abſolute ſpace, but expoſed to the irnpulſe
                    of a current of water moving equally faſt in the oppoſite direction: for in both
                    caſes the preſſure of the water on her bows is the ſame; and we know that it is
                    poſſible, and frequently happens in currents, that the impulſe of the wind on
                    her ſails, and that of the water on her bows, balance each other ſo preciſely,
                    that ſhe not only does not ſtir from the place, but alſo remains ſteadily in the
                    ſame poſition, with her head directed to the ſame point of the compaſs. This
                    ſtate of things is eaſily conceived by any perſon accuſtomed to conſider
                    mechanical ſubjects, and every ſeaman of experience has obſerved it. It is of
                    importance to conſider it in this point of view, becauſe it gives us the moſt
                    familiar notion of the manner in which theſe forces of the wind and water are
                    ſet in opposition, and made to balance or not to balance<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0207.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0201"/> each other by
                    the intervention of the ſhip, in the ſame manner as the goods and the weights
                    balance each other in the ſcales by the intervention of a beam or ſteel-
                    yard.</p>
                <p>When a ſhip proceeds ſteadily in her courſe, without changing her rate of
                    ſailing, or varying the direction of her head, we muſt in the firſt place
                    conceive the accumulated impulſes of the wind on all her ſails as preciſely
                    equal and directly oppoſite to the impulſe of the water on her bows. In the next
                    place, becauſe the ſhip does not change the direction of her keel, ſhe reſembles
                    the balanced ſteelyard, in which the energies of the two weights, which tend to
                    produce rotations in oppoſite directions, and thus to change the poſition of the
                    beam, mutually balance each other round the fulcrum; ſo the energies of the
                    actions of the wind on the different ſails balance the energies of the water on
                    the different parts of the hull.</p>
                <p>The ſeaman has two principal taſks to perform. The firſt is to keep the ſhip
                    ſteadily in that courſe which will bring her fartheſt on in the line of her
                    intended voyage. This is frequently very different from that line, and the
                    choice of the beſt courſe is ſometimes a matter of conſiderable difficulty. It
                    is ſometimes poſſible to ſhape the courſe precisely along the line of the
                    voyage; and yet the intelligent ſeaman knows that he will arrive ſooner, or with
                    greater ſafety, at his port, by taking a different courſe; becauſe he will gain
                    more by increaſing his ſpeed than he loſes by increaſing the diſtance. Some
                    principle muſt direct him in the ſelection of this courſe. This we muſt attempt
                    to lay before the reader.</p>
                <p>Having choſen ſuch a courſe as he thinks moſt advantageous, he muſt ſet ſuch a
                    quantity of ſail as the ſtrength of the wind will allow him to carry with ſafety
                    and effect, and muſt trim the ſails properly, or ſo adjuſt their poſitions to
                    the direction of the wind, that they may have the greateſt poſſible tendency to
                    impel the ſhip in the line of her courſe, and to keep her ſteadily in that
                    direction.</p>
                <p>His other taſk is to produce any deviations which he ſees proper from the preſent
                    courſe of the ſhip; and to produce theſe in the moſt certain, the ſafeſt, and
                    the moſt expeditious manner. It is chiefly in this movement that the mechanical
                    nature of a ſhip comes into view, and it is here that the ſuperior addreſs and
                    reſource of an expert ſeaman is to be perceived.</p>
                <p>Under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Sailing</hi> ſome notice has been taken of
                    the firſt taſk of the ſeaman, and it was there ſhown how a ſhip, after having
                    taken up her anchor and fitted her ſails, accelerates her motion, by degrees
                    which continually diminiſh, till the increaſing reſiſtance of the water becomes
                    preciſely equal to the diminiſhed impulſe of the wind, and then the motion
                    continues uniformly the ſame ſo long as the wind continues to blow with the ſame
                    force and in the ſame direction.</p>
                <p>It is perfectly conſonant to experience that the impulſe of fluids is in the
                    duplicate ratio of the relative velocity. Let it be ſuppoſed that when water
                    moves one foot per ſecond its perpendicular preſſure or impulſe on a ſquare foot
                    is <hi rend="italic">m</hi> pounds. Then, if it be moving with the velocity V
                    eſtimated in feet per ſecond, its perpendicular impulſe on a ſurface S,
                    containing any number of ſquare feet, muſt be <hi rend="italic">m</hi> SV <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>In like manner, the impulſe of air on the ſame ſurface may be repreſented by nSV
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>; and the proportion of the impulſe of theſe
                    two fluids will be that of m to n <hi rend="italic">.</hi> We may expreſs this
                    by the ratio of q to I, making <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> / <hi
                        rend="subscript"> n</hi> = q.</p>
                <p>M. Bouguer’s computations and tables are on the ſuppoſition that the impulſe of
                    ſea-water moving one foot per ſecond is 23 ounces on a ſquare foot, and that the
                    impulſe of the wind is the ſame when it blows at the rate of 24 feet per ſecond.
                    Theſe meaſures are all French. They by no means agree with the experiments of
                    others; and what we have already ſaid, when treating of the <hi
                        rend="italic smallcaps"> Resistance</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">of Fluids,</hi> is enough to ſhow us that nothing like preciſe
                    meaſures can be expected. It was ſhown as the reſult of a rational
                    inveſtigation, and confirmed by the experiments oſ Buat and others, that the
                    impulſions and reſiſtances at the ſame ſurface, with the ſame obliquity of
                    incidence and the ſame velocity of motion, are different according to the form
                    and ſituation of the adjoining parts. Thus the total reſiſtance of a thin board
                    is greater than that of a long priſm, having this board for its front or bow,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>We are greatly at a loſs what to give as abſolute meaſures of theſe
                    impulſions.</p>
                <p>1. With reſpect to water. The experiments of the French academy on a priſm two
                    feet broad and deep and four feet long, indicate a reſiſtance of 0,973 pounds
                    avoirdupois to a ſquare foot, moving with the velocity of one foot per ſecond at
                    the ſurface of ſtill water.</p>
                <p>Mr Buat’s experiments on a ſquare foot wholly immerſed in a ſtream were as
                    follows:</p>
                <p>A ſquare foot as a thin plate - 1,81 pounds.</p>
                <p>Ditto as the front of a box one foot long - 1,42</p>
                <p>Ditto as the front of a box three feet long - 1,29</p>
                <p>The reſiſtance of ſea-water is about <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 25</hi> greater.</p>
                <p>2. With reſpect to air, the varieties are as great.</p>
                <p>The reſiſtance of a ſquare foot to air moving with the velocity of one foot per
                    ſecond appears from Mr Robins’s experiments on 16 ſquare inches to be on a
                    ſquare foot - 0,001596 pounds,</p>
                <p>Chevalier Borda’s on 16 inches - 0,001757</p>
                <p>on 81 inches - 0,002042</p>
                <p>Mr Rouſe’s on large ſurfaces - 0,002291</p>
                <p>Preciſe meaſures are not to be expected, nor are they neceſſary in this inquiry.
                    Here we are chiefly intereſted in their proportions, as they may be varied by
                    their mode of action in the different circumſtances of obliquity and
                    velocity.</p>
                <p>We begin by recurring to the fundamental propoſition concerning the impulſe of
                    fluids, viz. that the abſolute preſſure is always in a direction perpendicular
                    to the impelled ſurface, whatever may be the direction of the ſtream of fluid.
                    We muſt therefore illuſtrate the doctrine, by always ſuppoſing a flat ſurface of
                    fail ſtretched on a yard, which can be braced about in any direction, and giving
                    this ſail ſuch a poſition and ſuch an extent of ſurface that the impulſe on it
                    may be the ſame both as to direction and intenſity with that on the real ſails.
                    Thus the conſideration is greatly Amplified. The direction of the impulſe is
                    therefore perpendicular to the yard. Its intenſity depends on the ve-<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0208.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0202"/> locity with
                    which the wind meets the ſail, and the obliquity of its ſtroke. We ſhall adopt
                    the constructions founded on the common doctrine, that the impulſe is as the
                    square of the fine of the inclination, becauſe they arc simple; whereas, if we
                    were to introduce the values of the oblique impulſes, ſuch as they have been
                    obſerved in the excellent experiments of the Academy of Paris, the conſtructions
                    would be complicated in the extreme, and we could hardly draw any conſequences
                    which would be intelligible to any but expert mathematicians. The concluſions
                    will be erroneous, not in kind but in quantity only; and we ſhall point out the
                    neceſſary corrections, ſo that the final reſults will be found not very
                    different from real obſervation.</p>
                <p>If a ſhip were a round cylindrical body like a flat tub, floating on its bottom,
                    and fitted with a mast and ſail in the centre, ſhe would always ſail in a
                    direction perpendicular to the yard. This is evident. But ſhe is an oblong body,
                    and may be compared to a cheſt, whoſe length greatly exceeds its breadth. She is
                    ſo ſhaped, that a moderate force will puſh her through the water with the head
                    or ſtern foremoſt; but it requires a very great force to puſh her ſidewiſe with
                    the fame velocity. A fine failing ſhip of war will require about 12 times as
                    much force to puſh her ſidewiſe as to puſh her head foremoſt. In this respect
                    therefore ſhe will very much resemble a cheſt whoſe length is 12 times its
                    breadth; and whatever be the proportion of these reſiſtances in different ſhips,
                    we may always subſtitute a box which ſhall have the ſame reſiſtances headwiſe
                    and ſidewiſe.</p>
                <p>Let EFGH (fig. 1.) be the horizontal ſection of ſuch a box, and AB its middle
                    line, and C its centre. In whatever direction this box may chance to move, the
                    direction of the whole reſiſtance on its two ſides will paſs through C. For as
                    the whole ſtream has one inclination to the side EF, the equivalent of the equal
                    impulſes on every part will be in a line perpendicular to the middle of EF. For
                    the ſame reaſon, it will be in a line perpendicular to the middle of FG. Theſe
                    perpendiculars muſt croſs in C. Suppoſe a maſt erected at C, and YC y to be a
                    yard hoiſted on it carrying a ſail. Let the yard be firſt conceived as braced
                    right athwart at right angles to the keel, as repreſented by Y'y'. Then,
                    whatever be the direction of the wind abaft this ſail, it will impel the veſſel
                    in the direction CB. But if the ſail has the oblique poſition Yy, the impulſe
                    will be in the direction CD perpendicular to CY, and will both puſh the veſſel
                    ahead and ſidewiſe: For the impulſe CD is equivalent to the two impulſes CK and
                    CI (the ſides of a rectangle of which CD is the diagonal). The force CI puſhes
                    the veſſel ahead, and CK puſhes her ſidewiſe. She muſt therefore take ſome
                    intermediate direction <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi> ſuch that the reſiſtance of
                    the water to the plane FG is to its reſiſtance to the plane EF as CI to CK.</p>
                <p>The angle <hi rend="italic">b</hi> CB between the real courſe and the direction
                    of the head is called the <hi rend="smallcaps">Leeway</hi>; and in the courſe of
                    this diſſertation we ſhall expreſs it by the ſymbol <hi rend="italic">X.</hi> It
                    evidently depends on the ſhape of the veſſel and on the poſition of the yard. An
                    accurate knowledge of the quantity of leeway, correſponding to different
                    circumſtances of obliquity of impulſe, extent of ſurface, &amp;c. is of the
                    utmoſt importance in the practice</p>
                <p>of navigation; and even an approximation is valuable. The ſubject is ſo very
                    difficult that this muſt content us for the preſent.</p>
                <p>Let V be the velocity of the ſhip in the direction C <hi rend="italic">b,</hi>
                    and let the ſurfaces FG and FE be called A' and B'. Then the reſiſtance to the
                    lateral motion is <hi rend="italic">m</hi> V <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × B'
                    × sine <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, <hi rend="italic">b</hi> CB, and that to
                    the direct motion is mV <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × A' × sine <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, bCK, or mV <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × A' ×
                    coſ. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> bCB. Therefore these reſiſtances are in the
                    proportion of B' × ſine <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, V to A' × coſ. <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, x (repreſenting the angle of leeway <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> CB by the ſymbol x).</p>
                <p>Therefore we have CI : CK, or CI : ID= A'.</p>
                <p>coſ. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> x : B' ∙ sine <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    x, = A':B' ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> sine^2x</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                        cos.^2x</hi> = A : B ∙ tangent <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> x <hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p>Let the angle YCB, to which the yard is braced up, be called the <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Trim</hi> of the sails, and expreſſed by the ſymbol <hi
                        rend="italic">b.</hi> This is the complement of the angle DCI. Now CI : ID =
                    rad.: tan. DCI, = 1 : tan, DCI, = I : cotan. <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Therefore
                    we have finally 1 : cotan, <hi rend="italic">b = A :</hi> B' ∙ tan. <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> x, and A' ∙ cotan. <hi rend="italic">b</hi> = B'
                    ∙ tangent <hi rend="superscript"> 2x</hi>, and tan. <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> x = <hi rend="superscript"> A</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> B</hi>
                    cot. <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> This equation evidently aſcertains the mutual
                    relation between the trim of the sails and the leeway in every case where we can
                    tell the proportion between the reſiſtances to the direct and broadſide motions
                    of the ſhip, and where this proportion does not change by the obliquity of the
                    courſe. Thus, ſuppoſe the yard braced up to an angle of 30⁰ with the keel. Then
                    cotan. 30⁰ = 1,732 very nearly. Suppoſe also that the reſiſtance ſidewiſe is 12
                    times greater than the reſiſtance headwiſe. This gives A' = I and B' = 12.
                    Therefore 1,732 = 12 × tangent <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> x, and tangent <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> x = <hi rend="superscript"> 1,732</hi> / <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 12</hi> = 0,14434, and tan. x = 0,3799, and x <hi
                        rend="italic">=</hi> 20 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 48', very nearly two
                    points of leeway.</p>
                <p>This computation, or rather the equation which gives room for it, ſuppoſes the
                    reſiſtances proportional to the ſquares of the sines of incidence. The
                    experiments of the Academy of Paris, of which an abſtract is given in the
                    article <hi rend="italic">RESISTANCE of Fluids,</hi> show that this ſuppoſition
                    is not far from the truth when the angle of incidence is great. In this preſent
                    case the angle of incidence on the front FG is about 70⁰, and the experiments
                    juſt now mentioned ſhow that the real reſiſtances exceed the theoretical ones
                    only <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 180</hi> But the
                    angle of incidence on EF is only 20⁰ 48'. Experiment ſhows that in this
                    inclination the reſiſtance is almoſt quadruple of the theoretical reſiſtances.
                    Therefore the lateral reſiſtance is assumed much too ſmall in the preſent
                    inſtance. Therefore a much ſmaller leeway will ſuffice for producing a lateral
                    reſiſtance which will balance the lateral impulſe CK, ariſing from the obliquity
                    of the ſail, viz. 30⁰. The matter of fact is, that a pretty good ſailing ſhip,
                    with her ſails braced to this angle at a medium, will not make above five or six
                    degrees leeway in ſmooth water and eaſy weather; and yet in this ſituation the
                    hull and rigging preſent a very great ſurface to the wind, in the most improper
                    poſitions, ſo as to have a very great effect in increaſing her leeway. And if we
                    compute the reſiſtances for this leeway of six degrees by the actual experiments
                    of the French Academy on that angle, we ſhall find the result not far<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0209.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0203"/> from the
                    truth; that is, the direct and lateral reſiſtances will be nearly in the
                    proportion of CI to ID.</p>
                <p>It reſults from this view of the matter, that the leeway is in general much
                    ſmaller than what the uſual theory aſſigns.</p>
                <p>We alſo ſee, that according to whatever law the reſiſtances change by a change of
                    inclination, the leeway remains the ſame while the trim of the sails is the
                    ſame. The leeway depends only on the direction of the impulſe of the wind; and
                    this depends ſolely on the poſition of the ſails with reſpect to the keel,
                    whatever may be the direction of the wind. This is a very important obſervation,
                    and will be frequently referred to in the progreſs of the preſent inveſtigation.
                    Note, however, that we are here conſidering only the action on the ſails, and on
                    the ſame ſails. We are not conſidering the action of the wind on the hull and
                    rigging. This may be very conſiderable; and it is always in a lee direction, and
                    augments the leeway; and its influence mult be ſo much the more ſenſible as it
                    bears a greater proportion to the impulſe on the ſails. A ſhip under courtes, or
                    cloſe-reefed topſails and courtes, muſt make more leeway than when under all her
                    canvas trimmed to the ſame angle. But to introduce this additional cauſe of
                    deviation here would render the inveſtigation too complicated to be of any
                    uſe.</p>
                <p>This doctrine will be conſiderably illuſtrated by attending to the manner in
                    which a lighter is tracked along a canal, or ſwings to its anchor in a ſtream.
                    The track rope is made faſt to ſome ſtaple or bolt E on the deck (fig. 2.), and
                    is paffed between two of the timber- heads of the bow at D, and laid hold of at
                    F on ſhore. The men or cattle walk along the path FG, the rope keeps extended in
                    the direction DF, and the lighter arranges itſelf in an oblique poſition AB, and
                    is thus dragged along in the direction <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi> parallel to
                    the ſide of the canal. Or, if the canal has a current in the oppoſite direction
                        <hi rend="italic">ba,</hi> the lighter may be kept ſteady in its place by
                    the rope DF made faſt to a poſt at F. In this caſe, it is always obſerved that
                    the lighter ſwings in a poſition AB, which is oblique to the ſtream <hi
                        rend="italic">ab</hi> Now the force which retains it in this poſition, and
                    which preciſely balances the action of the ſtream, is certainly exerted in the
                    direction DF; and the lighter would be held in the ſame manner if the rope were
                    made faſt at C amidſhip, without any dependence on the timberheads at D; and it
                    would ſtill be held in the ſame poſition, if, inſtead of the single rope CF, it
                    were riding by two ropes CG and CH, of which CH is in a direction right ahead,
                    but oblique to the ſtream, and the other CG is perpendicular to CH or AB. And,
                    drawing DI and DK perpendicular to AB and CG, the ſtrain on the rope CH is to
                    that on the rope CG as CI to CK. The action of the rope in these caſes is
                    preciſely analogous to that of the ſail <hi rend="italic">y</hi> Y; and the
                    obliquity of the keel to the direction of the motion, or to the direction oſ the
                    ſtream, is analogous to the leeway. All this muſt be evident to any perſon
                    accuſtomed to mechanical diſquiſitions.</p>
                <p>A moſt important uſe may be made of this illuſtration. If an accurate model be
                    made of a ſhip, and if it be placed in a ſtream of water, and ridden in this
                    manner by a rope made faſt at any point D of the bow, it will arrange itſelf in
                    ſome determined poſition AB. There will be a certain obliquity to the ſtream,
                    meaſured by the angle <hi rend="italic">Bob;</hi> and there will be a
                    correſponding obliquity of the rope, meaſured by the angle FCB. Let yCY be
                    perpendicular to CF. Then CY will be the poſition of the yard, or trim of the
                    ſails corresponding to the leeway <hi rend="italic">b</hi> CB. Then, if we ſhift
                    the rope to a point of the bow diſtant from D by a ſmall quantity, we ſhall
                    obtain a new poſition of the ſhip, both with reſpect to the ſtream and the rope;
                    and in this way may be obtained the relation between the poſition of the ſails
                    and the leeway, independent of all theory, and ſuſceptible of great accuracy;
                    and this may be done with a variety of models ſuited to the moſt uſual forms of
                    ſhips.</p>
                <p>In farther thinking on this ſubject, we are perſuaded that theſe experiments,
                    inſtead of being made on models, may with equal eaſe be made on a ſhip of any
                    ſize. Let the ſhip ride in a ſtream at a mooring D (fig. 3.) by means of a ſhort
                    hawter BCD from her bow, having a ſpring AC on it carried out from her quarter.
                    She will ſwing to her moorings, till ſhe ranges herſelf in a certain poſition AB
                    with reſpect to the direction <hi rend="italic">a b</hi> of the ſtream; and the
                    direction of the hawſer DC will point to ſome point E of the line of the keel.
                    Now, it is plain to any perſon acquainted with mechanical diſquiſitions, that
                    the deviation BE <hi rend="italic">b</hi> is preciſely the leeway that the ſhip
                    will make when the average poſition of the ſails is that of the line GEH
                    perpendicular to ED; at leaſt this will give the leeway which is produced by the
                    ſails alone. By heaving on the ſpring, the knot C may be brought into any other
                    poſition we pleaſe; and for every new poſition of the knot the ſhip will take a
                    new poſition with reſpect to the ſtream and to the hawſer. And we perſiſt in
                    ſaying, that more information will be got by this train of experiments than from
                    any mathematical theory: for all theories of the impulſes of fluids muſt proceed
                    on phyſical poſtulates with reſpect to the motions of the filaments, which are
                    exceedingly conjectural.</p>
                <p>And it muſt now be farther obſerved, that the ſubſtitution which we have made of
                    an oblong parallelopiped for a ſhip, although well ſuited to give us clear
                    notions of the ſubject, is of ſmall uſe in practice: for it is next to
                    impoſſible (even granting the theory of oblique impulſions) to make this
                    ſubſtitution. A ſhip is of a form which is not reducible to equations; and
                    therefore the action of the water on her bow or broadſide can only be had by a
                    moſt laborious and intricate calculation for almoſt every ſquare foot of its
                    ſurface. (See <hi rend="italic">Bezout's Cours de Mathem.</hi> vol. 5. p. 72,
                    &amp;c.) And this muſt be different for every ſhip. But, which is more
                    unlucky, when we have got a parallelopiped which will have the ſame proportion
                    of direct and lateral reſiſtance for a particular angle of leeway, it will not
                    anſwer for another leeway of the ſame ſhip; for when the leeway changes, the
                    figure actually expoſed to the action of the water changes alſo. When the leeway
                    is increated, more of the lee-quarter is acted on by the water, and a part of
                    the weather-bow is now removed from its action. Another parallelopiped muſt
                    therefore be diſcovered, whoſ reſiſtances ſhall ſuit this new poſition of the
                    keel with reſpect to the real courte of the ſhip.</p>
                <p>We therefore beg leaveto recommend this train of experiments to the notice of the
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Association for the Improvement of Naval
                        Architecture</hi> as a very promiſing method for ascertaining this important
                    point. And<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0210.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0204"/> we
                    proceed, in the next place, to aſcertain the relation between the velocity of
                    the ſhip and that of the wind, modified as they may be by the trim of the ſails
                    and the obliquity of the impulſe.</p>
                <p>Let AB (fig. 4, 5, and 6.) repreſent the horizontal ſection of a ſhip. In place
                    of all the drawing ſails, that is, the ſails which are really filled, we can
                    always ſubſtitute one ſail of equal extent, trimmed to the ſame angle with the
                    keel. This being ſuppoſed attached to the yard DCD, let this yard be firſt of
                    all at right angles to the keel, as repreſented in fig. 4. Let the wind blow in
                    the direction WC,and let CE (in the direction WC continued) repreſent the
                    velocity V of the wind. Let CF be the velocity <hi rend="italic">v</hi> of the
                    ſhip. It muſt alſo be in the direction of the ſhip’s motion, becauſe when the
                    ſail is at right angles to the keel, the abſolute impulſe on the ſail is in the
                    direction of the keel, and there is no lateral impulſe, and conſequently no
                    leeway. Draw EF, and complete the parallelogram CFE <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>
                    producing <hi rend="italic">e</hi> C through the centre of the yard to w <hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi> Then wC will be the relative or apparent direction of
                    the wind, and C <hi rend="italic">e</hi> or FE will be its apparent or relative
                    velocity: For if the line C <hi rend="italic">e</hi> be carried along CF,
                    keeping always parallel to its firſt poſition, and if a particle of air move
                    uniformly along CE (a fixed line in abſolute ſpace) in the ſame time, this
                    particle will always be found in that point of CE where it is interſected at
                    that inſtant by the moving line C <hi rend="italic">e</hi>; ſo that if C <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> were a tube, the particle of air, which really moves in
                    the line CE, would always be found in the tube Ce. While CE is the real
                    direction of the wind, C <hi rend="italic">e</hi> will be the poſition of the
                    vane at the maſt head, which will therefore mark the apparent direction of the
                    wind, or its motion relative to the moving ſhip.</p>
                <p>We may conceive this in another way. Suppoſe a cannon-ſhot fired in the direction
                    CE at the paſſing ſhip, and that it paſſes through the maſt at C with the
                    velocity of the wind. It will not paſs through the off- ſide of the ſhip at P,
                    in the line CE: for while the ſhot moves from C to P, the point P has gone
                    forward, and the point <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is now in the place where P was
                    when the ſhot paſſed through the maſt. The ſhot will therefore paſs through the
                    ſhip’s ſide in the point <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> and a perſon on board feeing
                    it paſs through C and p will ſay that its motion was in the line C <hi
                        rend="italic">p.</hi></p>
                <p>Thus it happens, that when a ſhip is in motion the apparent direction of the wind
                    is always ahead of its real direction. The line wC is always found within the
                    angle WCB. It is eaſy to ſee from the conſtruction, that the difference between
                    the real and apparent directions of the wind is ſo much the more remarkable as
                    the velocity of the ſhip is greater: For the angle WCw or EC e depends on the
                    magnitude of Ee or CF, in proportion to CE. Perſons not much accuſtomed to
                    attend to theſe matters are apt to think all attention to this difference to be
                    nothing but affectation of nicety. They have no notion that the velocity of a
                    ſhip can have any ſenſible proportion to that of the wind. “Swift as the wind”
                    is a proverbial expreſſion; yet the velocity of a ſhip always bears a very
                    ſenſible proportion to that of the wind, and even very frequently exceeds it. We
                    may form a pretty exact notion of the velocity of the wind by obſerving the
                    ſhadows of the ſummer clouds flying along the face of a country, and it may be
                    very well meaſured by this method. The motion of ſuch clouds cannot be very
                    different from that of the air below; and when the preſſure of the wind on a
                    flat ſurface, while blowing with a velocity meaſured in this way, is compared
                    with its preſſure when its velocity is meaſured by more unexceptionable methods,
                    they are found to agree with all deſirable accuracy. Now obſervations of this
                    kind frequently repeated, ſhow that what we call a pleaſant briſk gale blows at
                    the rate of about 10 miles an hour, or about 15 feet in a ſecond, and exerts a
                    preſſure of half a pound on a ſquare foot Mr Smeaton has frequently obſerved the
                    ſails of a windmill, driven by ſuch a wind, moving falter, nay much faſter,
                    towards their extremities, ſo that the ſail, inſtead of being preſſed to the
                    frames on the arms, was taken aback, and fluttering on them. Nay, we know that a
                    good ſhip, with all her ſails ſet and the wind on the beam, will in ſuch a
                    ſituation ſail above 10 knots an hour in ſmooth water. There is an obſervation
                    made by every experienced ſeaman, which ſhows this difference between the real
                    and apparent directions of the wind very diſtinctly. When a ſhip that is ſailing
                    briſkly with the wind on the beam tacks about, and then ſails equally well on
                    the other tack, the wind always appears to have ſhifted and come more ahead.
                    This is familiar to all ſeamen. The ſeaman judges of the direction of the wind
                    by the poſition of the ſhip’s vanes. Suppoſe the ſhip foiling due weſt on the
                    ſtarboard tack, with the wind apparently N. N. W. the vane pointing S. S. E. If
                    the ſhip puts about, and ſtands due eaſt on the larboard tack, the vane will be
                    found no longer to point S. S. E. but perhaps S. S.W. the wind appearing N. N.E.
                    and the ſhip muſt be nearly cloſe- hauled in order to make an eaſt courſe. The
                    wind appears to have ſhifted four points. If the ſhip tacks again, the wind
                    returns to its old quarter. We have often obſerved a greater difference than
                    this. The celebrated aſtronomer Dr Bradley, taking the amuſement of ſailing in a
                    pinnace on the river Thames, obſerved this, and was ſurpriſed at it, imagining
                    that the change of wind was owing to the approaching to or retiring from the
                    ſhore. The boatmen told him that it always happened at ſea, and explained it to
                    him in the beſt manner they were able. The explanation ſtruck him, and ſet him a
                    muſing on an aſtrononfical phenomenon which he had been puzzled by for ſome
                    years, and which he called <hi rend="smallcaps">the aberration of the fixed
                        stars.</hi> Every ſtar changes its place a ſmall matter for half a year, and
                    returns to it at the completion of the year. He compared the ſtream of light
                    from the ſtar to the wind, and the teleſcope of the aſtronomer to the ſhip’s
                    vane, while the earth was like the ſhip, moving in oppoſite directions when in
                    the oppoſite points of its orbit. The teleſcope muſt always be pointed ahead of
                    the real direction of the ſtar, in the ſame manner as the vane is always in a
                    direction ahead of the wind; and thus he aſcertained the progreſſive motion of
                    light, and diſcovered the proportion of its velocity to the velocity of the
                    earth in its orbit, by obſerving the deviation which was neceſſarily given to
                    the teleſcope. Obſerving that the light ſhifted its direction about 40", he
                    concluded its velocity to be about 11,000 times greater than that of the earth;
                    juſt as the intelligent ſeaman would conclude from this apparent ſhifting of the
                    wind, that the velocity of the wind is about triple that of the ſhip. This is
                    indeed the beſt method<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0211.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0205"/> for diſcovering the velocity of the wind. Let
                    the direction of the vane at the mast-head be very accurately noticed on both
                    tacks, and let the velocity of the ſhip be alſo accurately meaſured. The angle
                    between the directions of the ſhip’s head on theſe different tacks being halved,
                    will give the real direction of the wind, which muſt be compared with the
                    poſition of the vane in order to determine the angle contained between the real
                    and apparent directions of the wind or the angle EC <hi rend="italic">e;</hi> or
                    half of the obſerved ſhifting of the wind will ſhow the inclination of its true
                    and apparent directions. This being found, the proportion of EC to FC (fig. 6.)
                    is eaſily meaſured.</p>
                <p>We have been very particular on this point, becauſe ſince the mutual actions of
                    bodies depend on their relative motions only, we ſhould make prodigious miſtakes
                    if we eſtimated the action of the wind by its real direction and velocity, when
                    they differ ſo much from the relative or apparent.</p>
                <p>We now reſume the inveſtigation of the velocity of the ſhip (fig. 4. ), having
                    its sail at right angles to the keel, and the wind blowing in the direction and
                    with, the velocity CE, while the ſhip proceeds in the direction of the keel with
                    the velocity CF. Produce Ee, which is parallel to BC, till it meet the yard in
                        <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> and draw FG perpendicular to E <hi rend="italic"
                        >g.</hi> Let <hi rend="italic">a</hi> repreſent the angle WCD, contained
                    between the sail and the real direction of the wind, and let <hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi> be the angle of trim DCB. CE the velocity of the wind was expreſſed
                    by V, and CF the velocity of the ſhip by <hi rend="italic">v.</hi></p>
                <p>The abſolute impulſe on the ſail is (by the uſual theory) proportional to the
                    ſquare of the relative velocity, and to the ſquare of the sine of the angle of
                    incidence; that is, to FE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × sin. <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> wCD. Now the angle GFE = <hi rend="italic">w</hi>
                    C D, and EG is equal to FE × sin. GFE; and EG is equal to E <hi rend="italic"
                        >g</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">— g</hi> G. But E <hi rend="italic">g = z</hi> EC × sin. ECg —
                    V × sin. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> G — CF, = <hi
                        rend="italic">v.</hi> Therefore EG = VX sin. <hi rend="italic">a—ν,</hi> and
                    the impulſe is proportional to V × sin. <hi rend="italic">a — v</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">.</hi> If S repreſent the ſurface of the ſail, the impulſe, in
                    pounds, will be <hi rend="italic">n</hi> S (V × ſin. <hi rend="italic">a—v)</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Let A be the ſurface which, when it meets the water perpendicularly with the
                    velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> will ſuſtain the same preſſure or reſiſtance
                    which the bows of the ſhip actually meets with. This impulſe, in pounds, will be
                    mAv <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Therefore, becauſe we are conſidering the
                    ſhip’s motion as in a ſtate of uniformity, the two preſſures balance each other;
                    and therefore <hi rend="italic">mAv</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">— nS</hi> (V × ſin. <hi rend="italic">a—v</hi>) <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and m/n Av <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — S (V
                    × ſin. <hi rend="italic">a—v)</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">;</hi></p>
                <p>therefore <hi rend="italic">—</hi> √ <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> / <hi
                        rend="subscript"> n</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">× ν =</hi> √ <hi rend="italic">s</hi> × V × ſin. <hi
                        rend="italic">a—v</hi> √S,</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">n</hi></p>
                <p>√ S <hi rend="underline">×v×</hi> sin. <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">V × ſin. a V'× ſin.</hi> a and <hi rend="italic">v _ ∕m
                        .</hi> ∕m A , = *A +</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">√V</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> a+</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">√S</hi> √ 7s <hi rend="superscript"> +</hi> i^s <hi
                        rend="superscript"> +1</hi> ∙</p>
                <p>We ſee, in the firſt place, that the velocity of the ſhip is <hi rend="italic"
                        >(caeteris paribus)</hi> proportional to the velocity of the wind, and to
                    the ſine of its incidence on the ſail jointly; for while the ſurface of the ſail
                    S and the equivalent ſurface for the bows remains the ſame, <hi rend="italic"
                        >v</hi> increaſes or diminiſhes at the ſame rate with V ·sin. <hi
                        rend="italic">a —</hi> When the wind is right aſtern, the sine of a is
                    unity,</p>
                <p>V and then the ſhip’s velocity is ∕% A</p>
                <p>√ r⅛-+ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ∙_</p>
                <p>Note, that the denominator of this fraction is a common number; for <hi
                        rend="italic">m</hi> and <hi rend="italic">n</hi> are numbers, and A and S
                    being quantities of one kind, <hi rend="superscript"> A</hi> / <hi
                        rend="subscript"> S</hi> is alſo a number.</p>
                <p>It muſt alſo be carefully attended to, that S expreſſes a quantity of ſail
                    actually receiving wind with the inclination <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> It will
                    not always be true, therefore, that the velocity will increaſe as the wind is
                    more abaft, becauſe some ſails will then becalm others. This obſervation is not,
                    however, of great importance; for it is very unuſual to put a ſhip in the
                    ſituation conſidered hitherto; that is, with the yards ſquare, unless ſhe be
                    right before the wind.</p>
                <p>If we would diſcover the relation between the velocity and the quantity of ſail
                    in this simple case of the wind right aft, obſerve that the equation <hi
                        rend="italic">ν =</hi></p>
                <p>—0 + <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">n</hi> 0</p>
                <p>gives us ∕ <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> τ'4-Dc: V, and ∕ <hi
                        rend="superscript underline"> rn</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">v^zDJ— ν,</hi> ν Vs^ <hi rend="italic">nS</hi></p>
                <p>and »=v∑L^ζ*, and -1 <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi>; and becauſe</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">n S m</hi> A ( V — <hi rend="italic">ν j</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">n</hi> and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and A are conſtant
                    quantities, S is proportional to —or the ſurface of ſail is proportional</p>
                <p>( V—v) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, to the ſquare of the ſhip’s velocity
                    directly, and to the ſquare of the relative velocity inverſely. Thus, if a ſhip
                    be ſailing with of the velocity of the wind, and we would have her ſail with <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> of it, we muſt
                    quadruple the ſails. This is more eaſily ſeen in another way. The velocity of
                    the ſhip is proportional to the velocity of the wind; and therefore the relative
                    velocity is alſo proportional to that of the wind, and the impulſe of the wind
                    is as the ſquare of the relative velocity. Therefore, in order to increaſe the
                    relative velocity by an increaſe of ſail only, we muſt make this increaſe of
                    ſail in the duplicate proportion of the increaſe of velocity.</p>
                <p>Let us, in the next place, conſider the motion of a ſhip whole ſails ſtand
                    oblique to the keel.</p>
                <p>The conſtruction for this purpoſe differs a little from the former, becauſe, when
                    the ſails are trimmed to any oblique poſition DCB (fig. 5 and 6.), there muſt be
                    a deviation from the direction of the keel, or a leeway BC <hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi>. Call this <hi rend="italic">X.</hi> Let CF be the velocity of the
                    ſhip. Draw, as before, E <hi rend="italic">g</hi> perpendicular to the yard, and
                    FG perpendicular to E <hi rend="italic">g</hi>; alſo draw FH perpendicular to
                    the yard: then, as before, EG, which is in the ſubduplicate ratio of the impulſe
                    on the ſail, is equal to Eg — Gy. Now Eg is, as before, = V × ſin. <hi
                        rend="italic">a,</hi> and G <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is equal to FH, which
                    is = CF × ſin. FCH, or <hi rend="italic">— v ×</hi> ſin. (b+x). Therefore we
                    have the impulſe = n S (V ∙ ſin. <hi rend="italic">a—v</hi> ∙ ſin. (b+x)) <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>This expreſſion of the impulſe is perfectly ſimilar to that in the former caſe,
                    its only difference conſiſting in the ſubductive part, which is here <hi
                        rend="italic">v</hi> × ſin. <hi rend="italic">b</hi> + <hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi> inſtead of <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> But it expreſſes the ſame thing
                    as before, viz. the diminution of the impulſe. The impulſe being reckoned ſolely
                    in the direction perpendicular to the ſail,<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0212.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0206"/> it is
                    diminlſhed ſolely by the sail withdrawing itſelf <hi rend="italic">in that
                        direction</hi> from the wind; and as <hi rend="italic">g</hi> E may be
                    considered as the real impulſive motion of the wind, GE must be conſidered as
                    the relative and effective impulſive motion. The impulſe would have been the
                    ſame had the ſhip been at rest, and had the wind met it perpendicularly with the
                    velocity GE.</p>
                <p>We muſt now show the connection between this impulſe and the motion of the ſhip.
                    The sail, and consequently the ſhip, is preſſed by the wind in the direction CI
                    perpendicular to the ſail or yard with the force which we have just now
                    determined. This (in the ſtate of uniform motion) must be equal and oppoſite to
                    the action of the water. Draw IL at right angles to the keel. The impulſe in the
                    direction CI (which we may meaſure by CI) is equivalent to the impulſes CL and
                    LI. By the firſt the ſhip is impelled right forward, and by the second ſhe is
                    driven ſidewiſe. Therefore we must have a leeway, and a lateral as well as a
                    direct reſiſtance. We ſuppoſe the form of the ſhip to be known, and therefore
                    the proportion is known, or diſcoverable, between the direct and lateral
                    reſiſtances correſponding to every angle <hi rend="italic">x</hi> of leeway. Let
                    A be the ſurface whoſe perpendicular reſiſtance is equal to the direct
                    reſiſtance of the ſhip correſponding to the leeway x, that is, whoſe reſiſtance
                    is equal to the reſiſtance really felt by the ſhip’s bows in the direction of
                    the keel when ſhe is sailing with this leeway; and let B in like manner be the
                    ſurface whoſe perpendicular reſiſtance is equal to the actual reſiſtance to the
                    ſhip’s motion in the direction LI, perpendicular to the keel. (N. <hi
                        rend="italic">B.</hi> This is not equivalent to A' and B' adapted to the
                    rectangular box, but to A' · coſ. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> x and B' · sin.
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> x.) We have therefore A : B = CL : LI, and LI
                    = <hi rend="superscript"> CL∙B</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> A.</hi> Also,
                    becauſe CI= √CL <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +LI <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi>, we have A : √A <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> + B <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = CL : CI, and CI = <hi rend="superscript">
                        CLV</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">^ +</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript underline"> B</hi>
                    <hi rend="underline">\</hi> The resistance in the direction LC is properly
                    meaſured by <hi rend="italic">mAv</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">,</hi> as has been already obſerved. Therefore the reſiſtance
                    in the direction IC muſt be expreſſed by <hi rend="italic">m</hi> √ <hi
                        rend="italic">A</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> + B <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∙ <hi
                        rend="italic">v</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">;</hi> or (making C the surface which is equal to √Α <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +B <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> and which will
                    therefore have the ſame perpendicular reſiſtance to the water having the
                    velocity v) it may be expreſſed by <hi rend="italic">m</hi> C <hi rend="italic"
                        >ν</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p>Therefore, becauſe there is an equilibrium between the impulſe and reſiſtance, we
                    have mCv <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = nS (V∙ ſin. <hi rend="italic">a —
                        v</hi> ∙ sin. <hi rend="italic">b</hi> + x) <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    and <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> C <hi
                        rend="italic">v</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">, or qCν</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">=</hi> S (V∙ sin. <hi rend="italic">a—v ∙</hi> sin. b + x) <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and √ <hi rend="italic">q</hi> √ <hi
                        rend="italic">Cν =</hi> √ <hi rend="italic">S</hi> (V ∙ ſin. <hi
                        rend="italic">a—v</hi> · ſin. b+x).</p>
                <p>y S·V∙sin. <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p>
                <p>Therefore v = ——^y— =</p>
                <p>√q√C+√S·sin. <hi rend="italic">b+x</hi></p>
                <p>V·sin. a Sin. <hi rend="italic">a</hi></p>
                <p>√C Z^i~^, = V √C ⅜∕y Ç/g- + ſin. b+ <hi rend="italic">x</hi> √5 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> ^&amp;gt;^g+fin.</p>
                <p>Obſerve that the quantity wſhich is the coefficient of V in this equation is a
                    common number; for ſin. <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is a number, being a decimal
                    fraction of the radius 1. Sin. <hi rend="italic">b + x</hi> is alſo a number,
                    for the ſame reaſon. And since <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and n were numbers of
                    pounds, <hi rend="superscript"> m</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> Or <hi
                        rend="italic">q</hi> is a common number. And becauſe C and S are ſurfaces,
                    or quantities of one kind, <hi rend="superscript"> C</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"
                        > S</hi> is alſo a common number.</p>
                <p>This is the simpleſt expreſſion that we can think of for the velocity acquired by
                    the ſhip, though it muſt be acknowledged to be too complex to be of very prompt
                    uſe. Its complication ariſes from the neceſſity of introducing the leeway x <hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi> This affects the whole of the denominator; for the
                    ſurface C depends on it, becauſe C is = √A <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + B
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> and A and B are analogous to A'coſ. <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and B'sin. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">x.</hi></p>
                <p>But we can deduce ſome important conſequences from this theorem.</p>
                <p>While the ſurface S of the ſail actually filled by the wind remains the same, and
                    the angle DCB, which in future we ſhall call the <hi rend="smallcaps">Trim</hi>
                    of the sails, alſo remains the same, both the leeway <hi rend="italic">x</hi>
                    and the ſubſtituted ſurface C remains the ſame. The denominator is therefore
                    constant; and the velocity of the ſhip is proportional to √S ∙ V ∙ ſin. a; that
                    is, directly as the velocity of the wind, directly as the abſolute inclination
                    of the wind to the yard, and directly as the ſquare root of the ſurface of the
                    sails.</p>
                <p>We alſo learn from the conſtruction of the figure that FG parallel to the yard
                    cuts CE in a given ratio. For CF is in a conſtant ratio to Eg, as has been juſt
                    now demonſtrated. And the angle DCF is conſtant. Therefore CF ∙ sin. <hi
                        rend="italic">b,</hi> or FH or Gg, is proportional to E <hi rend="italic"
                        >g,</hi> and OC to EC, or EC is cut in one proportion, whatever may be the
                    angle ECD, ſo long as the angle DCF is conſtant.</p>
                <p>We alſo ſee that it is very poſſible for the velocity of the ſhip on an oblique
                    courſe to exceed that of the wind. This will be the caſe when the number</p>
                <p>ſin. <hi rend="italic">a exceeds</hi> unity, or when ſin. a / √ <hi rend="italic"
                        >q</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript"> C</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> S</hi> + sin. b + x</p>
                <p>∕ C~</p>
                <p>exceeds unity, or when sin. a. is greater than √q <hi rend="superscript"> C</hi>
                    / <hi rend="subscript"> S</hi> — + sin. b + x. Now this may eaſily be by
                    ſufficiently enlarging S and diminiſhing b + x. It is indeed frequently ſeen in
                    fine sailers with all their sails ſet and not hauled too near the wind.</p>
                <p>We remarked above that the angle of leeway <hi rend="italic">x</hi> affects the
                    whole denominator of the fraction which expreſſes the velocity. Let it be
                    obſerved that the angle ICL is the complement of LCD, or of b <hi rend="italic"
                        >.</hi> Therefore CL: LI, or A : B = 1 : tan. ICL, = 1: cot. <hi
                        rend="italic">b,</hi> and B = A ∙ cotan. <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Now A is
                    equivalent to A' · Coſi <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> and thus <hi rend="italic">b</hi> becomes a function
                    of x <hi rend="italic">.</hi> C is evidently ſo, being = √ <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >A</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2+</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">B</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">∙</hi> Therefore before the value of this fraction can be
                    obtained, we muſt be able to compute, by our knowledge of the form of the ſhip,
                    the value of A for every angle x of leeway. This can be done only by reſolving
                    her bows into a great number of elementary planes, and computing the impulſes on
                    each and adding them into one ſum. The computation is of immenſe labour, as may
                    be ſeen by one example given by Bouguer. When the leeway is but small, not
                    exceeding ten degrees, the ſubſtitution of the rectangular priſm of one
                    determined form is abundantly exact for all leeways contained within this limit;
                    and we ſhall ſoon ſee rea-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0213.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0207"/> son for being contented with this approximation.
                    We may now make uſe of the formula expreſſing the velocity for ſolving the chief
                    problems in this part of the ſeaman’s taſk.</p>
                <p>And first let it be required to determine the beſt poſition of the ſail for
                    ſtanding on a given courſe <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi> when CE the direction and
                    velocity of the wind, and its angle with the courſe WCF, are given. This problem
                    has exerciſed the talents of the mathematicians ever ſince the days oſ Newton.
                    In the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics</hi> we give the ſolution of one
                    very nearly related to it, namely, to determine the poſition of the ſail which
                    would produce the greateſt impulſe in the direction of the courſe. The ſolution
                    was to place the yard CD in ſuch a poſition that the tangent of the angle FCD
                    may be one half of the tangent of the angle DCW. This will indeed be the beſt
                    poſition of the ſail for beginning the motion; but as ſoon as the ſhip begins to
                    move in the direction CF, the effective impulſe of the wind is diminiſhed, and
                    alſo its inclination to the ſail. The angle DC w diminiſhes: continually as the
                    ſhip accelerates; for CF is now accompanied by its equal <hi rend="italic"
                        >e</hi> E, and by an angle ECe or WC <hi rend="italic">w.</hi> CF increaſes,
                    and the impulſe on the sail diminiſhes, till an equilibrium obtains between the
                    reſiſtance of the water and the impulſe of the wind. The impulſe is now meaſured
                    by Ce <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × sin. <hi rend="italic superscript">
                        2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">e</hi> CD inſtead of CE <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> × sin.
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ECD, that is, by EG <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> inſtead of Eg <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>This introduction of the relative motion oſ the wind renders the actual ſolution
                    of the problem extremely difficult. It is very eaſily expreſſed geometrically:
                    Divide the angle <hi rend="italic">w</hi> CF in ſuch a manner that the tangent
                    of DCF may be half of the tangent of DCw, and the problem may be conſtructed
                    geometrically as follows.</p>
                <p>Let WCF (fig. 7.) be the angle between the ſail and courſe. Round the centre C
                    deſcribe the circle WDFY; produce WC to Q, ſo that CQ = <hi rend="superscript">
                        1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> W C, and draw QY parallel to CF
                    cutting the circle in Y; biſect the arch WY in D, and draw DC. DC is the proper
                    poſition of the yard.</p>
                <p>Draw the chord WY, cutting CD in V and CF in T; draw the tangent PD cutting CF in
                    S and CY in R.</p>
                <p>It is evident that WY, PR, are both perpendicular to CD, and are biſected in V
                    and D; therefore (by reaſon of the parallels QY, CF) 4 : 3 = QW : CW, = YW : TW,
                    = RP : SP. Therefore PD : PS = 2 : 3, and PD : DS = 2 : 1. <hi rend="italic">E.
                        D.</hi> But this diviſion cannot be made to the beſt advantage till the ſhip
                    has attained its greateſt velocity, and the angle wCF has been produced.</p>
                <p>We muſt conſider all the three angles, a, <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">x</hi> as variable in the equation which expreiſes the value
                    of <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> and we muſt make the fluxion of this equation = o;
                    then, by means of the equation B = A· cotan. <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> w,e muſt
                    obtain the value of <hi rend="italic">b</hi> and of <hi rend="italic">b</hi> in
                    terms of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and x. With reſpect to a, observe, that if we
                    make the angle WCF = p, we have p = <hi rend="italic">a+ b + x;</hi> and p being
                    a constant quantity, we have <hi rend="italic">a + b + x = 0.</hi> Subſtituting
                    for a, <hi rend="italic">b, a,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> their values
                    in terms of <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> in the
                    fluxionary equation = 0 <hi rend="italic">,</hi> we readily obtain <hi
                        rend="italic">x,</hi> and then <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">b,</hi> which ſolves the problem.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Let it be required, in the next place, to determine the courſe
                        and the trim of the sails moſt proper for plying to windward.</hi></p>
                <p>In fig. 6. draw FP perpendicular to WC. CF is the motion of the ſhip; but it is
                    only by the motion CP that ſhe gains to windward. Now CP is = CF × coſin. WGF,
                    or <hi rend="italic">ν</hi> coſin. (a+ b + x). This muſt be rendered a maximum,
                    as follows.</p>
                <p>By means of the equation which expreſſes the value of <hi rend="italic">v</hi>
                    and the equation B = A · cotan. <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> we exterminate the
                    quantities <hi rend="italic">v</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b;</hi> we then take
                    the fluxion of the quantity into which the expreſſion <hi rend="italic">v</hi> ·
                    coſ. ( a + b + x) is changed by this operation. Making this fluxion = 0, we get
                    the equation which muſt ſolve the problem. This equation will contain the two
                    variable quantities <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and x with their fluxions; then
                    make the coefficient of x equal to o <hi rend="italic">,</hi> alſo the
                    coefficient of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> equal to o <hi rend="italic">.</hi> This
                    will give two equations which will determine <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">x,</hi> and from this we get <hi rend="italic">b = p — a
                        —x.</hi></p>
                <p>Should it be required, in the third place, to find the beſt courſe and trim of
                    the ſails for getting away from a given line of coaſt CM (fig. 6.), the proceſs
                    perfectly reſembles this laſt, which is in fact getting away from a line of
                    coaſt which makes a right angle with the wind. Therefore, in place of the angle
                    WCF, we muſt substitute the angle WCM c± WCF. Call this angle <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.</hi> We muſt make <hi rend="italic">v</hi> · coſ. <hi rend="italic">(e =
                        a = b =x)</hi> a maximum. The analytical proceſs is the ſame as the former,
                    only e is here a conſtant quantity.</p>
                <p>Theſe are the three principal problems which can be ſolved by means of the
                    knowledge that we have obtained of the motion of the ſhip when impelled by an
                    oblique ſail, and therefore making leeway; and they may be conſidered as an
                    abſtract of this part of M. Bouguer’s work. We have only pointed out the proceſs
                    for this ſolution, and have even omitted ſome things taken notice of by M.
                    Bezout in his very elegant compendium. Our reaſons will appear as we go on. The
                    learned reader will readily ſee the extreme difficulty of the ſubject, and the
                    immenſe calculations which are neceſſary even in the ſimpleſt cases, and will
                    grant that it is out of the power of any but an expert analyſt to derive any uſe
                    from them; but the mathematician can calculate tables for the uſe of the
                    practical ſeaman. Thus he can calculate the best poſition of the ſails for
                    advancing in a courſe 90 <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> from the wind, and the
                    velocity in that courſe; then for 85, 80⁰, 75⁰, &amp;c. M. Bouguer has given
                    a table of this kind; but to avoid the immenſe difficulty of the proceſs, he has
                    adapted it to the apparent direction of the wind. We have inſerted a few of his
                    numbers, ſuited to ſuch caſes as can be of ſervice, namely, when all the ſails
                    draw, or none stand in the way of others. Column 1st is the apparent angle of
                    the wind and courſe; column 2d is the correſponding angle of the ſails and keel;
                    and column, 3d is the apparent angle of the ſails and wind.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1 </cell>
                        <cell> 2 </cell>
                        <cell> 3 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> wCF </cell>
                        <cell> DCB </cell>
                        <cell> wCD </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1043⁰ 53' </cell>
                        <cell> 42⁰ 30' </cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">61</hi> ⁰ <hi rend="italic">23'</hi>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 99 13 </cell>
                        <cell> 40 — </cell>
                        <cell> 59 13 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 94 25 </cell>
                        <cell> 37 30 </cell>
                        <cell> 56 55 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 89 28 </cell>
                        <cell> 35 — </cell>
                        <cell> 54 28 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 84 23 </cell>
                        <cell> 32 30 </cell>
                        <cell> 51 53 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 79 06 </cell>
                        <cell> 30 — </cell>
                        <cell> 49 06 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 73 39 </cell>
                        <cell> 27 30 </cell>
                        <cell> 46 09 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 68 — </cell>
                        <cell> 25 — </cell>
                        <cell> 43 — </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>

                <pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0214.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0208"/>
                <p>In all theſe numbers we have the tangent of wCD double of the tangent of DCF.</p>
                <p>But this is really doing but little for the ſeaman. The apparent direction of the
                    wind is unknown to him till the ſhip is sailing with uniform velocity; and he is
                    ſtill uninformed as to the leeway. It is, however, of fervice to him to know,
                    for inſtance, that when the angle of the vanes and yards is 56 degrees, the yard
                    ſhould be Braced up to 37⁰ 30', amp;c.</p>
                <p>But here occurs a new difficulty. By the conſtruction of a ſquare-rigged ſhip it
                    is impoſſible to give the yards that inclination to the keel which the
                    calculation requires. Few ſhips can have their yards braced up to 37⁰ 30'; and
                    yet this is required in order to have an incidence of 56⁰, and to hold a courſe
                    94⁰ 25' from the apparent direction of the wind, that is, with the wind
                    apparently 4⁰ 25' abaft the beam. A good ſailing ſhip in this poſition may
                    acquire a velocity even exceeding that of the wind. Let us ſuppoſe it only one
                    half of this velocity. We ſhall find that the angle WCw is in this caſe about
                    29⁰, and the ſhip is nearly going 123⁰ from the wind, with the wind almoſt
                    perpendicular to the sail; therefore this utmoſt bracing up of the sails is only
                    giving them the poſition ſuited to a wind broad on the quarter. It is impoſſible
                    therefore to comply with the demand of the mathematician, and the ſeaman muſt be
                    contented to employ a leſs favourable diſpoſition of his ſails in all caſes
                    where his courſe does not lie at leaſt eleven points from the wind.</p>
                <p>Let us see whether this reſtriction, ariſing from neceſſity, leaves any thing in
                    our choice, and makes one courſe preferable to another. We ſee that there are a
                    prodigious number of courtes, and theſe the moſt uſual and the moſt important,
                    which <hi rend="italic">we</hi> muſt hold with one trim of the ſails; in
                    particular, ſailing with the wind on the beam, and all cates of plying to
                    windward, muſt be performed with this unfavourable trim of the ſails. We are
                    certain that the ſmaller we make the angle of incidence, real or apparent, the
                    ſmaller will be the velocity of the ſhip; but it may happen that we ſhall gain
                    more to windward, or get ſooner away from a lee-coaſt, or any object of danger,
                    by ſailing ſlowly on one courſe than by ſailing quickly on another</p>
                <p>We have ſeen that while the trim of the ſails remains the ſame, the leeway and
                    the angle of the yard and courſe remains the ſame, and that the velocity of the
                    ſhip is as the sine of the angle of real incidence, that is, as the ſine of the
                    angle of the ſail and the real direction of the wind.</p>
                <p>Let the ſhip AB (fig. 8.) hold the courſe CF, with the wind blowing in the
                    direction WC, and having her yards DCD braced up to the ſmalleſt angle BCD which
                    the rigging can admit. Let CF be to CE as the velocity of the ſhip to the
                    velocity of the wind; join FE and draw C <hi rend="italic">w</hi> parallel to
                    EF; it is evident that FE is the relative motion of the wind, and wCD is the
                    relative incidence on the ſail. Draw FO parallel to the yard DC, and deſcribe a
                    circle through the points COF; then we ſay that if the ſhip, with the ſame wind
                    and the ſame trim of the ſame drawing ſails, be made to ſail on any other courte
                    Cf, her velocity along CF is to the velocity along C <hi rend="italic">f</hi> as
                    CF is to C <hi rend="italic">f</hi>; or, in other words, the ſhip will employ
                    the ſame time in going from C to any point of the circumference CFO.</p>
                <p>Join <hi rend="italic">fO</hi>. Then, becauſe the angles CFO, <hi rend="italic"
                        >cfO</hi> are on</p>
                <p>the ſame chord CO, they are equal, and fO is parallel to <hi rend="italic">d</hi>
                    C <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> the new poſition of the yard correſponding to the
                    new poſition of the keel <hi rend="italic">a b,</hi> making the angle <hi
                        rend="italic">dCb</hi> = DCB. Alſo, by the nature of the circle, the line CF
                    is to <hi rend="italic">Cf</hi> as the ſine of the angle COF to the ſine of the
                    angle COf, that is (on account of the parallels CD, OF and C <hi rend="italic"
                        >d,</hi> Of), as the ſine of WCD to the ſine of <hi rend="italic">WCd.</hi>
                    But when the trim of the ſails remains the ſame, the velocity of the ſhip is as
                    the ſine of the angle of the ſail with the direction of the wind; therefore CF
                    is to Cfas the velocity on CF to that on <hi rend="italic">Cſ,</hi> and the
                    propoſition is demonstrated.</p>
                <p>Let it now be required to determine the beſt courſe for avoiding a rock R lying
                    in the direction CR, or for withdrawing as faſt as poſſible from a line of coaſt
                    PQ. Draw CM through R, or parallel to PQ, and let <hi rend="italic">m</hi> be
                    the middle of the arch CmM. It is plain that <hi rend="italic">m</hi> is the
                    moſt remote from CM of any point of the arch <hi rend="italic">Cm</hi> M, and
                    therefore the ſhip will recede farther from the coaſt PQ in any given time by
                    holding the courſe C <hi rend="italic">m</hi> than by any other courſe.</p>
                <p>This courſe is eaſily determined; for the arch C <hi rend="italic">m</hi> M =
                    360⁰ — (arch CO + arch OM), and the arch CO is the meaſure of twice the angle
                    CFO, or twice the angle DCB, or twice <hi rend="italic">b + x,</hi> and the arch
                    OM meaſures twice the angle ECM.</p>
                <p>Thus, ſuppoſe the ſharpeſt poſſible trim of the ſails to be 35⁰, and the observed
                    angle ECM to be 70⁰; then CO + OM is 700 + 1400 or 210⁰. This being taken from
                    360⁰, leaves 150⁰, of which the half Mm is 75⁰, and the angle MC <hi
                        rend="italic">m</hi> is 37⁰ 30'. This added to ECM makes EC <hi
                        rend="italic">m</hi> 107⁰ 30', leaving <hi rend="smallcaps">WCm</hi> = 72⁰
                    30', and the ſhip muſt hold a courſe making an angle of 72⁰ 30' with the real
                    direction of the wind, and WCD will be 37⁰ 30'.</p>
                <p>This ſuppoſes no leeway. But if we know that under all the ſail which the ſhip
                    can carry with ſafety and advantage ſhe makes 5 degrees of leeway, the angle DCm
                    of the ſail and courſe, or <hi rend="italic">b + x,</hi> is 40⁰. Then CO + OM =
                    220⁰, which being taken from 360⁰ leaves 140⁰, of which the half is 70⁰, = M <hi
                        rend="italic">m,</hi> and the angle MC <hi rend="italic">m =</hi> 35⁰ and EC
                        <hi rend="italic">m =</hi> 105⁰, and WC m <hi rend="italic">= 75</hi> ⁰ and
                    the ſhip muſt lie with her head 70⁰ from the wind, making <hi rend="italic"
                        >5</hi> degrees of leeway, and the angle WCD is 35⁰.</p>
                <p>The general rule for the poſition of the ſhip is, <hi rend="italic">that the line
                        on shipboard which bisects the angle</hi> b + x <hi rend="italic">may also
                        bisect the angle</hi> WCM, or make the angle between the courſe and the line
                    from which we wiſh to withdraw equal to the angle between the ſail and the real
                    direction of the wind.</p>
                <p>It is plain that this problem includes that of plying to windward. We have only
                    to ſuppoſe ECM to be 90⁰; then, taking our example in the ſame ſhip, with the
                    ſame trim and the ſame leeway, we have <hi rend="italic">b +</hi> x = 40⁰. This
                    taken from 90⁰ leaves 50⁰ and WCn = 90 — 25 = 65, and the ſhip’s head muſt lie
                    60⁰ from the wind, and the yard muſt be 25⁰ from it.</p>
                <p>It muſt be obſerved here, that it is not always eligible to ſelect the courſe
                    which will remove the ſhip faſteſt from the given line CM; it may be more
                    prudent to remove from it more ſecurely though more ſlowly. In ſuch cates the
                    procedure is very ſimple, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> to ſhape the courſe as
                    near the wind as is poſſible.</p>
                <p>The reader will alſo eaſily tee that the propriety of theſe practices is confined
                    to thoſe courtes only where the practicable trim of the ſails is not
                    ſuſſiciently ſharp.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0215.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0209"/> Whenever the courſe lies ſo far from the wind
                    that it is poſſible to make the tangent of the apparent angle of the wind and
                    sail double the tangent of the sail and courſe, it ſhould be done.</p>
                <p>Theſe are the chief practical conſequences which can be deduced from the theory.
                    But we ſhould conſider how far this adjuſtment of the ſails and courſe can be
                    performed. And here occur difficulties ſo great as to make it almoſt
                    impracticable. We have always ſuppoſed the poſition of the ſurface of the ſail
                    to be distinctly obſervable and meaſurable; but this can hardly be affirmed even
                    with reſpect to a ſail ſtretched on a yard. Here we ſuppoſed the ſurface of the
                    ſail to have the ſame inclination to the keel that the yard has. This is by no
                    means the caſe; the ſail affirmes a concave form, of which it is almoſt
                    impoſſible to aſſign the direction of the mean impulſe. We believe that this is
                    always conſiderably to leeward of a perpendicular to the yard, lying between CI
                    and CE (fig. 6.). This is of ſome advantage, being equivalent to a ſharper trim.
                    We cannot affirm this, however, with any confidence, becauſe it renders the
                    impulſe on the weather-leech of the ſail ſo exceedingly feeble as hardly to have
                    any effect. In ſailing cloſe to the wind the ſhip is kept ſo near that the
                    weather-leech of the ſail is almoſt ready to receive the wind edgewiſe, and to
                    flutter or driver. The moſt effective or drawing ſails with a ſidewind,
                    eſpecially when plying to windward, are the ſtayſails. We believe that it is
                    impoſſible to ſay, with any thing approaching to preciſion, what is the poſition
                    of the general ſurface of a ſtayſail, or to calculate the intenſity and
                    direction of the general impulſe; and we affirm with confidence that no man can
                    pronounce on theſe points with any exactneſs. If we can gueſs within a third or
                    a fourth part of the truth, it is all we can pretend to; and after all, it is
                    but a gueſs. Add to this, the ſails coming in the way of each other, and either
                    becalming them or ſending the wind upon them in a direction widely different
                    from that of its free motion. All theſe points we think beyond our power of
                    calculation, and therefore that it is in vain to give the ſeaman mathematical
                    rules, or even tables of adjuſtment ready calculated; ſince he can neither
                    produce that medium poſition of his ſails that is required, nor tell what is the
                    poſition which he employs.</p>
                <p>This is one of the principal reaſons why ſo little advantage has been derived
                    from the very ingenious and promiſing diſquiſitions of Bouguer and other
                    mathematicians, and has made us omit the actual ſolution of the chief problems,
                    contenting ourſelves with pointing out the proceſs to ſuch readers as have a
                    reliſh for theſe analytical operations.</p>
                <p>But there is another principal reaſon for the ſmall progreſs which has been made
                    in the theory of ſeaman- ſhip: This is the errors of the theory itſelf, which
                    ſuppoſes the impulſions of a fluid to be in the duplicate ratio of the ſine of
                    incidence. The moſt careful compariſon which has been made between the reſults
                    of this theory and matter of fact is to be ſeen in the experiments made by the
                    members of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, mentioned in the article
                    RESISTANCE <hi rend="italic">of Fluids.</hi> We ſubjoin another abſtract of them
                    in the following table; where col. 1ſt gives the angle of incidence; col. 2d
                    gives the impulſions really obſerved; col. 3d the impulſes, had they followed
                    the duplicate</p>
                <p>ratio of the ſines; and col 4th the impulſes, if they were in the ſimple ratio of
                    the ſines.</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Angle</p><p>of</p><p>Incid.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Impulsion</p><p>obſerved.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Impulſe</p><p>as</p><p>Sine <hi rend="superscript">
                            2</hi>.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Impulse</p><p>as</p><p>Sine.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 90 </cell>
                        <cell> 10OO </cell>
                        <cell> 10OO </cell>
                        <cell> 10OO </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 84 </cell>
                        <cell> 989 </cell>
                        <cell> 989 </cell>
                        <cell> 995 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 78 </cell>
                        <cell> 958 </cell>
                        <cell> 957 </cell>
                        <cell> 978 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 72 </cell>
                        <cell> 908 </cell>
                        <cell> 905 </cell>
                        <cell> 951 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 66 </cell>
                        <cell> 845 </cell>
                        <cell> 835 </cell>
                        <cell> 914 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 60 </cell>
                        <cell> 771 </cell>
                        <cell> 750 </cell>
                        <cell> 866 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 54 </cell>
                        <cell> 693 </cell>
                        <cell> 655 </cell>
                        <cell> 809 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 48 </cell>
                        <cell> 615 </cell>
                        <cell> 552 </cell>
                        <cell> 743 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 42 </cell>
                        <cell> 543 </cell>
                        <cell> 448 </cell>
                        <cell> 669 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> 480 </cell>
                        <cell> 346 </cell>
                        <cell> 587 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 30 </cell>
                        <cell> 440 </cell>
                        <cell> 250 </cell>
                        <cell> 500 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 24 </cell>
                        <cell> 424 </cell>
                        <cell> 165 </cell>
                        <cell> 407 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 18 </cell>
                        <cell> 414 </cell>
                        <cell> 96 </cell>
                        <cell> 309 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 12 </cell>
                        <cell> 406 </cell>
                        <cell> 43 </cell>
                        <cell> 208 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 6 </cell>
                        <cell> 400 </cell>
                        <cell> 11 </cell>
                        <cell> 105 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Here we ſee an enormous difference in the great obliquities. When the angle of
                    incidence is only ſix degrees, the obſerved impulſe is forty times greater than
                    the theoretical impulſe; at 12⁰ it is ten times greater; at 18⁰ it is more than
                    four times greater; and at 24⁰ it is almoſt three times greater.</p>
                <p>No wonder then that the deductions from this theory are ſo uſeleſs and ſo unlike
                    what we familiarly obſerve. We took notice of this when we were conſidering the
                    leeway of a rectangular box, and thus ſaw a reaſon for admitting an incomparably
                    ſmaller leeway than what would reſult from the laborious computations neceſſary
                    by the theory. This error in theory has as great an influence on the impulſions
                    of air when acting obliquely on a ſail; and the experiments of Mr Robins and of
                    the Chevalier Borda on the oblique impulſions of air are perfectly conformable
                    (as far as they go) to thoſe of the academicians on water. The oblique
                    impulſions of the wind are therefore much more efficacious for preſſing the ſhip
                    in the direction of her courſe than the theory allows us to ſuppoſe; and the
                    progreſs of a ſhip plying to windward is much greater, both becauſe the oblique
                    impulſes of the wind are more effective, and becauſe the leeway is much ſmaller,
                    than we ſuppoſe. Were not this the caſe, it would be impoſſible for a
                    ſquare-rigged ſhip to get to windward. The impulse on her fails when
                    cloſe-hauled would be ſo trifling that ſhe would not have a third part of the
                    velocity which we ſee her acquire: and this trifling velocity would be waſted in
                    leeway; for we have ſeen that the diminution of the oblique impulſes of the
                    water is accompanied by an increaſe of leeway. But we ſee that in the great
                    obliquities the impulſions continue to be very conſiderable, and that even an
                    incidence of ſix degrees gives an impulſe as great as the theory allows to an
                    incidence of 40. We may therefore, on all occaſions, keep the yards more ſquare;
                    and the loſs which we ſuſtain by the diminution of the very oblique impulſe will
                    be more than compenſated by its more favourable direction with reſpect to the
                    ſhip’s keel. Let us take an example of this. Suppoſe the wind about two points
                    before the beam, making an angle of 68⁰ with the keel. The theory aſſigns 43⁰
                    for the inclination of the wind to<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0216.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0210"/> the fall, and 25⁰ for the trim of the ſail. The
                    perpendicular impulſe bceing ſuppoſed 1000, the theoretical impulſe for 43⁰ is
                    465. This reduced in the proportion of radius to the ſine of 25⁰, gives the
                    impulſe in the direction of the courſe only 197.</p>
                <p>But if we eaſe off the lee-braces till the yard makes an angle of 50⁰ with the
                    keel, and allows the wind an incidence of no more than 18⁰, we have the
                    experimented impulſe 414, which, when reduced in the proportion of radius to the
                    fine of 50⁰, gives an effective impulſe 317. In like manner, the trim 56⁰, with
                    the incidence 12⁰, gives an effective impulſe 337; and the trim 62⁰, with the
                    incidence only 6⁰, gives 353.</p>
                <p>Hence it would at firſt ſight appear that the angle DCB of 62⁰ and WCD of 6⁰
                    would be better for holding a courſe within ſix points of the wind than any more
                    oblique poſition of the ſails; but it will only give a greater initial impulſe.
                    As the ſhip accelerates, the wind apparently comes ahead, and we muſt continue
                    to brace up as the ſhip freſhens her way. It is not unuſual for her to acquire
                    half or two thirds of the velocity of the wind; in which caſe the wind comes
                    apparently ahead more than two points, when the yards muſt be braced up to 35⁰,
                    and this allows an impulſe no greater than about 7⁰. Now this is very frequently
                    obſerved in good ſhips, which in a briſk gale and ſmooth water will go five or
                    ſix knots cloſe-hauled, the ſhip’s head ſix points from the wind, and the ſails
                    no more than juſt full, but ready to ſhiver by the ſmalleſt luff. All this would
                    be impoſſible by the uſual theory; and in this reſpect theſe experiments of the
                    French academy give a fine illuſtration of the ſeaman’s practice. They account
                    for what we ſhould otherwiſe be much puzzled to explain; and the great progreſs
                    which is made by a ſhip cloſe-hauled being perfectly agreeable to what we ſhould
                    expect from the law of oblique impulſion deducible ſrom theſe ſo often mentioned
                    experiments, while it is totally incompatible with the common theory, ſhould
                    make us abandon the theory without heſitation, and ſtrenuouſly ſet about the
                    eſtabliſhment of another, founded entirely on experiments. For this purpoſe the
                    experiments ſhould be made on the oblique impulſions of air on as great a ſcale
                    as poſſible, and in as great a variety of circumſtances, ſo as to furniſh a
                    ſeries of impulſions for all angles of obliquity. We have but four or five
                    experiments on this ſubject, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> two by Mr Robins and
                    two or three by the Chevalier Borda. Having thus gotten a ſeries of impulſions,
                    it is very practicable to raiſe on this foundation a practical inſtſtute, and to
                    give a table of the velocities of a ſhip ſuited to every angle of inclination
                    and of trim; for nothing is more certain than the reſolution of the impulſe
                    perpendicular to the ſail into a force in the direction of the keel, and a
                    lateral force.</p>
                <p>We are alſo diſpoſed to think that experiments might be made on a model very
                    nicely rigged with ſails, and trimmed in every different degree, which would
                    point out the mean direction of the impulſe on the ſails, and the comparative
                    force of theſe impulſes in different directions of the wind. The method would be
                    very ſimilar to that for examining the impulſe of the water on the hull. If this
                    can alſo be aſcertained experimentally, the intelligent reader will eaſily ſee
                    that the whole motion of a ſhip under ſail may be determined for every caſe.
                    Tables may then be conſtructed by calculation,</p>
                <p>or by graphical operations, which will give the velocities of a ſhip in every
                    different courſe, and correſponding to every trim of ſail. And let it be here
                    obſerved, that the trim of the ſail is not to be eſtimated in degrees of
                    inclination of the yards; becauſe, as we have already remarked, we cannot
                    obſerve nor adjuſt the lateen ſails in this way. But, in making the experiments
                    for aſcertaining the impulſe, the exact poſition of the tacks and ſheets of the
                    ſails are to be noted; and this combination of adjuſtments is to paſs by the
                    name of a certain trim. Thus that trim of all the ſails may be called 40, whoſe
                    direction is experimentally found equivalent to a flat ſurface trimmed to the
                    obliquity 40⁰.</p>
                <p>Having done this, we may conſtruct a figure for each trim ſimilar to fig. 8.
                    where, inſtead of a circle, we ſhall have a curve COM'F', whoſe chords CF', <hi
                        rend="italic">cf',</hi> amp;c. are proportional to the velocities in theſe
                    courſes; and by means of this curve we can find the point m', which is moſt
                    remote from any line CM from which we wiſh to withdraw: and thus we may ſolve
                    all the principal problems of the art.</p>
                <p>We hope that it will not be accounted preſumption in us to expect more
                    improvement from a theory founded on judicious experiments only, than from a
                    theory of the impulſe of fluids, which is found ſo inconſiſtent with
                    obſervation, and of whoſe fallacy all its authors, from Newton to D’Alembert,
                    entertained ſtrong ſuſpicions. Again, we beg leave to recommend this view of the
                    ſubject to the attention of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Society for. the
                        Improvement of Naval Architecture.</hi> Should theſe patriotic gentlemen
                    entertain a favourable opinion of the plan, and honour us with their
                    correſpondence, we will cheerfully impart to them our notions of the way in
                    which both theſe trains of experiments may be proſecuted with ſucceſs, and
                    reſults obtained in which we may confide; and we content ourſelves at preſent
                    with offering to the public theſe hints, which are not the ſpeculations of a man
                    of mere ſcience, but of one who, with a competent knowledge of the laws of
                    mechanical nature, has the experience of ſeveral years ſervice in the royal
                    navy, where the art of working of ſhips was a favourite object of his ſcientific
                    attention.</p>
                <p>With theſe obſervations we conclude our diſcuſſion of the firſt part of the
                    ſeaman’s taſk, and now proceed to conſider the means that are employed to
                    prevent or to produce any deviations from the uniform rectilineal courſe which
                    has been ſelected.</p>
                <p>Here the ſhip is to be conſidered as a body in free ſpace, convertible round her
                    centre of inertia. For whatever may be the point round which ſhe turns, this
                    motion may always be conſidered as compounded of a rotation round an axis
                    paſſing through her centre of gravity or inertia. She is impelled by the wind
                    and by the water acting on many ſurfaces differently inclined to each other, and
                    the impulſe on each is perpendicular to the ſurface. In order therefore that ſhe
                    may continue ſteadily in one courſe, it is not only neceſſary that the impelling
                    forces, eſtimated in their mean direction, be equal and oppoſite to the
                    reſiſting forces eſtimated in their mean direction; but alſo that theſe two
                    directions may paſs through one point, otherwiſe ſhe will be affected as a log
                    of wood is when puſhed in oppoſite directions by two forces, which are equal
                    indeed, but are applied to different parts of the log. A ſhip muſt<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0217.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0211"/> be conſidered
                    as a lever, acted on in different parts by forces in different directions, and
                    the whole balancing each other round that point or axis where the equivalent of
                    all the reſiſting forces paſſes. This may be conſidered as a point ſupported by
                    this reſiſting force, and as a fort of fulcrum: therefore, in order that the
                    ſhip may maintain her poſition, the energies or momenta of all the impelling
                    forces round this point muſt balance each other.</p>
                <p>When a ſhip fails right afore the wind, with her yards ſquare, it is evident that
                    the impulſes on each ſide of the keel are equal, as alſo their mechanical <hi
                        rend="italic">momenta</hi> round any axis paſſing perpendicularly through
                    the keel. So are the actions of the water on her bows. But when ſhe ſails on an
                    oblique courſe, with her yards braced up on either ſide, ſhe ſuſtains a preſſure
                    in the direction CI (fig. 5.) perpendicular to the ſail. This, by giving her a
                    lateral preſſure LI, as well as a preſſure CL ahead, cauſes her to make leeway,
                    and to move in a line C <hi rend="italic">b</hi> inclined to CB. By this means
                    the balance of action on the two bows is deſtroyed; the general impulſe on the
                    lee-bow is increaſed; and that on the weather-bow is diminiſhed. The combined
                    impulſe is therefore no longer in the direction BC, but (in the ſtate of uniform
                    motion) in the direction IC.</p>
                <p>Suppoſe that in an inſtant the whole ſails are annihilated and the impelling
                    preſſure CI, which preciſely balanced the reſiſting preſſure on the bows,
                    removed. The ſhip tends, by her inertia, to proceed in the direction C <hi
                        rend="italic">b.</hi> This tendency produces a continuation of the
                    reſiſtance in the oppoſite direction IC, which is not directly oppoſed to the
                    tendency of the ſhip in the direction C <hi rend="italic">b;</hi> therefore the
                    ſhip’s head would immediately come up to the wind. The experienced ſeaman will
                    recollect ſomething like this when the ſails are ſuddenly lowered when coming to
                    anchor. It does not happen ſolely from the obliquity of the action on the bows:
                    It would happen to the parallelopiped of fig. 2. which was ſuſtaining a lateral
                    impulſion B ∙ sin. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> and a direct impulsion A∙ cos. <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">x.</hi> Theſe are continued for a moment after the
                    annihilation of the ſail; but being no longer oppoſed by a force in the
                    direction CD, but by a force in the direction C <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> the
                    force B ∙ sin. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">x</hi> muſt prevail, and the body is not only retarded in its
                    motion, but its head turns towards the wind. But this effect of the leeway is
                    greatly increaſed by the curved form of the ſhip’s bows. This occaſions the
                    centre of effort of all the impulſions of the water on the lee ſide of the ſhip
                    to be very far forward, and this ſo much the more remarkably as ſhe is ſharper
                    afore. It is in general not much abaft the foremaſt. Now the centre of the
                    ſhip’s tendency to continue her motion is the ſame with her centre of gravity,
                    and this is generally but a little before the mainmaſt. She is therefore in the
                    ſame condition nearly as if ſhe were puſhed at the mainmaſt in a direction
                    parallel to C <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> and at the foremaſt by a force parallel
                    to IC. The evident conſequence of this is a tendency to come up to the wind.
                    This is independent of all ſituation of the ſails, provided only that they have
                    been trimmed obliquely.</p>
                <p>This tendency of the ſhip’s head to windward is called <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >griping</hi> in the ſeaman’s language, and is greateſt in ſhips which are
                    ſharp forward, as we have ſaid already. This circumſtance is eaſily underſtood.
                    Whatever is the direction of the ſhip’s motion, the abſolute impulſe on that
                    part of the bow immediately contiguous to B is perpendicular to that very part
                    of the ſurface. The more acute, therefore, that the angle of the bow is, the
                    more will the impulſe on that part be perpendicular to the keel, and the greater
                    will be its energy to turn the head to windward.</p>
                <p>Thus we are enabled to underſtand or to ſee the propriety of the diſpoſition of
                    the ſails of a ſhip. We fee her crowded with ſails forward, and even many ſails
                    extended far before her bow, ſuch as the ſpritſail, the bowſprit topſail, the
                    fore-topmaſt ſtaylarl, the jib, and flying jib. The ſails abaft are
                    comparatively ſmaller. The ſails on the mizenmaſt are much smaller than those on
                    the foremast. All the ſtayſails hoiſted on the mainmaſt may be conſidered as
                    headſails, becauſe their centres of effort are conſiderably before the centre of
                    gravity of the ſhip; and notwithſtanding this diſpoſition, it generally requires
                    a ſmall action of the rudder to counteract the windward tendency of the lee-bow.
                    This is conſidered as a good quality when moderate; becauſe it enables the
                    ſeaman to throw the ſails aback, and flop the ſhip’s way in a moment, if ſhe be
                    in danger from any thing ahead; and the ſhip which does not carry a little of a
                    weather helm, is always a dull ſailer.</p>
                <p>In order to judge ſomewhat morc accurately of the action of the water and ſails,
                    suppoſe the ſhip AB (fig. 9.) to have its ſails on the mizenmaſt D, the mainmaſt
                    E, and foremaſt F, braced up or trimmed alike, and that the three lines D <hi
                        rend="italic">i,</hi> Et, Ff, perpendicular to the ſails, are in the
                    proportion of the impulſes on the ſails. The ſhip is driven ahead and to
                    leeward, and moves in the path <hi rend="italic">a</hi> C <hi rend="italic"
                        >b.</hi> This path is ſo inclined to the line of the keel that the medium
                    direction of the reſiſtance of the water is parallel to the direction of the
                    impulſe. A line CI may be drawn parallel to the lines Di, E <hi rend="italic"
                        >e,</hi> Ff, and equal to their ſum: and it may be drawn from ſuch a point
                    C, that the actions on all the parts of the hull between C and B may balance the
                        <hi rend="italic">momenta</hi> of all the actions on the hull between C and
                    A. This point may juſtly be called the <hi rend="italic">centre of effort,</hi>
                    or the <hi rend="italic">centre oſ resistance.</hi> We cannot determine this
                    point for want of a proper theory of the reſiſtance of fluids. Nay, although
                    experiments like thoſe of the Pariſian academy ſhould give us the most perfect
                    knowledge of the intenſity of the oblique impulſes on a ſquare foot, we ſhould
                    hardly be benefited by them: for the action of the water on a ſquare foot of the
                    hull at <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> for inſtance, is ſo modified by the
                    intervention of the ſtream of water which has ſtruck the hull about B, and
                    glided along the bow B <hi rend="italic">op,</hi> that the preſſure on p is
                    totally different from what it would have been were it a ſquare foot or ſurface
                    detached from the reſt, and preſented in the ſame poſition to the water moving
                    in the direction <hi rend="italic">bC.</hi> For it is found, that the
                    resiſtances given to planes joined ſo as to form a wedge, or to curved ſurfaces,
                    are widely different from the accumulated reſiſtances, calculated for their
                    ſeparate parts, agreeably to the experiments of the academy on ſingle ſurfaces.
                    We therefore do not attempt to aſcertain the point C by theory; but it may be
                    accurately determined by the experiments which we have ſo ſtrongly recommended;
                    and we offer this as an additional inducement for proſecuting them.</p>
                <p>Draw through C a line perpendicular to CI, that is, parallel to the ſails; and
                    let the lines of impulſe of the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0218.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0212"/> three sails cut it in the points i, k, and m.
                    This line i m maybe considered as a lever, moveable round C, and acted on at the
                    points <hi rend="italic">i, k,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> by three
                    forces. The rotatory momentum of the ſails on the mizenmaſt is D <hi
                        rend="italic">i</hi> × iC; that of the ſails on the mainmaſt is E <hi
                        rend="italic">e × k</hi> C; and the momentum of the ſails on the fore- maſt
                    is Ff <hi rend="italic">× m</hi> C. The two firſt tend to preſs forward the arm
                    Ci, and then to turn the ſhip’s head towards the wind. The action of the ſails
                    on the foremaſt tends to pull the arm Cm forward, and produce a contrary
                    rotation. If the ſhip under theſe three ſails keeps ſteadily in her courſe,
                    without the aid of the rudder, we muſt have Di <hi rend="italic">×</hi> iC + Ee
                        <hi rend="italic">× k</hi> C = F <hi rend="italic">ſ × m</hi> C. This is
                    very poſſible, and is often ſeen in a ſhip under her mizen-topſail,
                    main-topsail, and fore-top sail, all parallel to one another, and their ſurfaces
                    duly proportioned by reefing. If more ſails are ſet, we muſt always have a
                    ſimilar equilibrium. A certain number of them will have their efforts directed
                    from the larboard arm of the lever <hi rend="italic">im</hi> lying to lee-ward
                    ol CI, and a certain number will have their efforts directed from the ſtarboard
                    arm lying to windward of CI. The ſum of the products of each of the firſt ſet,
                    by their diſtances from C, muſt be equal to the ſum of the ſimilar products of
                    the other ſet. As this equilibrium is all that is neceſſary for preſerving the
                    ſhip’s poſition, and the ceſſation of it is immediately followed by a
                    converſion; and as theſe ſtates of the ſhip may be had by means of the three
                    ſquare ſails only, when their ſurfaces are properly proportioned—it is plain
                    that every movement may be executed and explained by their means. This will
                    greatly simplify our future diſcuſſions. We ſhall therefore ſuppoſe in future
                    that there are only the three topſails ſet, and that their ſurfaces are ſo
                    adjuſted by reefing, that their actions exactly balance each other round that
                    point C of the middle line AB, where the actions of the water on the different
                    parts of her botttom in like manner balance each other. This point C may be
                    differently ſituated in the ſhip according to the leeway ſhe makes, depending on
                    the trim of the ſails; and therefore although a certain proportion of the three
                    ſurfaces may balance each other in one ſtate of leeway, they may happen not to
                    do ſo in another ſtate. But the equilibrium is evidently attainable in every
                    cafe, and we therefore ſhall always ſuppoſe it.</p>
                <p>It muſt now be obſerved, that when this equilibrium is dcſtroyed, as, for
                    example, by turning the edge of the mizen topſail to the wind, which the ſeamen
                    call shiver <hi rend="italic">ing</hi> the mizen-topſail, and which may be
                    conſidered as equivalent to the removing the mizen-topſail entirely, it does not
                    follow that the ſhip will round the point C, this point remaining fixed. The
                    ſhip muſt be conſidered as a free body, ſtill acted on by a number of forces,
                    which no longer balance each other; and ſhe muſt thereſore <hi rend="italic"
                        >begin</hi> to turn round a ſpontaneous axis of converſion, which muſt be
                    determined in the way ſet forth in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Rotation.</hi> It is of importance to point out in general where this axis
                    is ſituated, Therefore let G (fig. 10.) be the centre of gravity of the ſhip.
                    Draw the line <hi rend="italic">q</hi> G <hi rend="italic">v</hi> parallel to
                    the yards, cutting D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> in <hi rend="italic">q,</hi> E <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> in r, CT in t, and Ff in <hi rend="italic">v.</hi>
                    While the three sails are ſet, the line q <hi rend="italic">v</hi> may be
                    conſidered as a lever acted on by four forces, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> D <hi
                        rend="italic">d,</hi> impelling the lever forward perpendicularly in the
                    point <hi rend="italic">q;</hi> E <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> impelling it forward
                    in the point <hi rend="italic">r;</hi> Ff, impelling it for</p>
                <p>ward in the point <hi rend="italic">ν;</hi> and CI, impelling it backward in the
                    point <hi rend="italic">t.</hi> Theſe forces balance each other both in respect
                    of progreſſive motion and of rotatory energy; for CI was taken equal to the ſum
                    of Dd <hi rend="italic">,</hi> E <hi rend="italic">e,</hi> and Ff; ſo that no
                    acceleration or retardation of the ſhip’s progreſs in her courſe is
                    ſuppoſed.</p>
                <p>But by taking away the mizen-topſail, both the equilibriums are destroyed. A part
                    D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> of the accelerating force is taken away; and yet the
                    ſhip, by her inertia or inherent force, tends, for a moment, to proceed in the
                    direction C <hi rend="italic">p</hi> with her former velocity; and by this
                    tendency exerts for a moment the ſame preſſure CI on the water, and ſuſtains the
                    ſame reſiſtance IC. She muſt therefore be retarded in her motion by the exceſs
                    of the reſiſtance IC over the remaining impelling forces E <hi rend="italic"
                        >e</hi> and F <hi rend="italic">f,</hi> that is, by a force equal and
                    oppoſite to Dd <hi rend="italic">.</hi> She will therefore be retarded in the
                    ſame manner as if the mizeu-topſail were ſtill ſet, and a force equal and
                    oppoſite to its action were applied to G the centre of gravity, and ſhe would
                    ſoon acquire a ſmaller velocity, which would again bring all things into
                    equilibrium; and ſhe would stand on in the ſame courſe, without changing either
                    her leeway or the poſition of her head.</p>
                <p>But the equilibrium of the lever is alſo deſtroyed. It is now acted on by three
                    forces only, viz. E <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and Ff <hi rend="italic">,</hi>
                    impelling it forward in the points r and <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> and IC
                    impelling it backward in the point <hi rend="italic">t.</hi> Make r <hi
                        rend="italic">v : ro =</hi> Ee + Ff : Ff, and make <hi rend="italic">op</hi>
                    parallel to CI and equal to Ee + Ff. Then we know, from the common principles of
                    mechanics, that the force <hi rend="italic">op</hi> acting at o will have the
                    ſame momentum or energy to turn the lever round <hi rend="italic">any</hi> point
                    whatever as the two forces Ee and Ff applied at r and <hi rend="italic">v;</hi>
                    and now the lever is acted on by two forces, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> IC,
                    urging it backwards in the point <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >op</hi> urging it forwards in the point <hi rend="italic">o.</hi> It muſt
                    therefore turn round like a floating log, which gets two blows in oppoſite
                    directions, If we now make IC — <hi rend="italic">op : op = to : tx,</hi> or IC
                    — <hi rend="italic">op:</hi> IC = <hi rend="italic">to : ox,</hi> and apply to
                    the point <hi rend="italic">x</hi> a force equal to IC — <hi rend="italic"
                        >op</hi> in the direction IC; we know, by the common principles of
                    mechanics, that this force IC — op will produce the ſame rotation round any
                    point as the two forces IC and <hi rend="italic">op</hi> applied in their proper
                    directions at <hi rend="italic">t</hi> and <hi rend="italic">o.</hi> Let us
                    examine the ſituation of the point <hi rend="italic">x.</hi></p>
                <p>The force IC — <hi rend="italic">op</hi> is evidently = Dd, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >op</hi> is = Ee + Ff. Therefore <hi rend="italic">ot : tx = Dd : op.</hi>
                    But because, when all the ſails were filled, there was an equilibrium round C,
                    and thereſore round <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> and becauſe the force <hi
                        rend="italic">op</hi> acting at <hi rend="italic">o</hi> is equivalent to E
                        <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and Ff acting at <hi rend="italic">r</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">v,</hi> we muſt ſtill have the equilibrium; and therefore we
                    have the momentum D <hi rend="italic">d × qt = op × ot.</hi> Therefore <hi
                        rend="italic">ot : tq = Dd : op,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tq = tx.</hi>
                    Therefore the point <hi rend="italic">x</hi> is the ſame with the point <hi
                        rend="italic">q.</hi></p>
                <p>Therefore, when we ſhiver the mizen-topſail, the rotation of the ſhip is the ſame
                    as if the ſhip were at reſt, and a force equal and oppoſite to the action of the
                    mizen-topſail were applied at <hi rend="italic">q</hi> or at D, or at any point
                    in the line Dq.</p>
                <p>This might have been ſhown in another and ſhorter way. Suppoſe all ſails filled,
                    the ſhip is in equilibrio. This will be diſturbed by applying to D a force
                    oppoſite to D <hi rend="italic">d;</hi> and if the force be alſo equal to D <hi
                        rend="italic">d,</hi> it is evident that theſe two forces deſtroy each
                    other, and that this application of the force <hi rend="italic">d</hi> D is
                    equivalent to<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0219.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0213"/>
                    the taking away of the mizen-topſail. But we choſe to give the whole mechanical
                    inveſtigation; becauſe it gave us an opportunity of pointing out to the reader,
                    in a case of very eaſy comprcheiiſion, the preciſe manner in which the ſhip is
                    acted on by the different sails and by the water, and what ſhare each of them
                    has in the motion ultimately produced. We ſhall not repeat this manner of
                    procedure in other cases, becauſe a little reflection on the part of the reader
                    will now enable him to trace the <hi rend="italic">modus operandi</hi> through
                    all its ſteps.</p>
                <p>We now see that, in reſpect both of progreſſive motion and of converſion, the
                    ſhip is affected by shivering the sail D, in the same manner as if a force equal
                    and oppoſite to D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> were applied at D, or at any point in
                    the line D <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> We must now have recourse to the principles
                    established under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Rotation.</hi></p>
                <p>Let p repreſent a particle of matter, r its radius vector, or its diſtance p G
                    from an axis paſſing through the centre of gravity G, and let M repreſent the
                    whole quantity of matter of the ſhip. Then its momentum of inertia is = Sp <hi
                        rend="italic">×</hi> r <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">(See</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Rotation,</hi> n⁰ 18.) The ſhip, impelled in the point D by
                    a force in the direction <hi rend="italic">dD,</hi> will begin to turn round a
                    ſpontaneous vertical axis, paſſing through a point S of the line <hi
                        rend="italic">q</hi> G, which is drawn through the centre of gravity G,
                    perpendicular to the direction <hi rend="italic">d</hi> D of the external force,
                    and the diſtance GS of this axis from the centre of gravity is = <hi
                        rend="italic">L —</hi> — (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Rotation,</hi> n⁰ 96.),
                    and it is M ∙ Gq and it is taken on the oppoſite side of G from y, that is, S
                    and <hi rend="italic">q</hi> are on oppoſite ſides of G.</p>
                <p>Let us expreſs the external force by the ſymbol F. It is equivalent to a certain
                    number of pounds, being the preſſure of the wind moving with the velocity V and
                    inclination a on the surface of the ſail D; and may therefore be computed either
                    by the theoretical or experimental law of oblique impulſes. Having obtained
                    this, we can aſcertain the angular velocity of the rotation and the abſolute
                    velocity of any given point of the ſhip by means of the theorems eſtabliſhed in
                    the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Rotation.</hi></p>
                <p>But before we proceed to this inveſtigation, we ſhall conſider the action of the
                    rudder, which operates preciſely in the ſame manner. Let the ſhip AB (fig. 11.)
                    have her rudder in the poſition AD, the helm being hard a-ſtarboard, while the
                    ſhip sailing on the ſtarboard tack, and making leeway, keeps on the courſe <hi
                        rend="italic">ab.</hi> The lee ſurface of the rudder meets the water
                    obliquely. The very foot of the rudder meets it in the direction DE parallel to
                        <hi rend="italic">ab.</hi> The parts farther up meet it with various
                    obliquities, and with various velocities, as it glides round the bottom of the
                    ſhip and falls into the wake. It is abſolutely impoſſible to calculate the
                    accumulated impulſe. We ſhall not be far miſtaken in the deflection of each
                    contiguous filament, as it quits the bottom and glides along the rudder; but we
                    neither know the velocity of theſe filaments, nor the deflection and velocity of
                    the filaments gliding without them. We therefore imagine that all computations
                    on this ſubject are in vain. But it is enough for our purpoſe that we know the
                    direction of the abſolute preſſure which they exert on its ſurface. It is in the
                    direction D <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> perpendicular to that ſurface. We alſo may
                    be confident that this preſſure is very considerable, in proportion to the
                    action of the water on the ſhip’s bows, or of the wind on the ſails; and we may
                    ſuppoſe it to be nearly in the proportion of the ſquare of the velocity of the
                    ſhip in her courſe; but we cannot affirm it to be accurately in that proportion,
                    for reaſons that will readilv occur to one who conſiders the way in which the
                    water falls in behind the ſhip.</p>
                <p>It is obſerved, however, that a fine ſailer always ſteers well, and that all
                    movements by means of the rudder are performed with great rapidity when the
                    velocity of the ſhip is great. We ſhall ſee by and bv, that the ſpeed with which
                    the ſhip performs the angular movements is in the proportion of her progreſſive
                    velocity: For we ſhall ſee that the ſquares of the times of performing the
                    evolution are as the impulſes inverſely, which are as the ſquares of the
                    velocities. There is perhaps no force which acts on a ſhip that can be more
                    accurately determined by experiment than this. Let the ſhip ride in a ſtream or
                    tideway whoſe velocity is accurately meaſured; and let her ride from two
                    moorings, ſo that her bow may be a fixed point. Let a ſmall tow-line be laid out
                    from her item or quarter at right angles to the keel, and connected with ſome
                    apparatus fitted up on ſhore or on board another ſhip, by which the ſtrain on it
                    may be accurately meaſured; a person conversant with mechanics will ſee many
                    ways in which this can be done. Perhaps the following may be as good as any: Let
                    the end of the tow-line be fixed to ſome point as high out of the water as the
                    point of the ſhip from which it is given out, and let this be very high. Let a
                    block with a hook be on the rope, and a conſiderable weight hung on this hook.
                    Things being thus prepared, put down the helm to a certain angle, ſo as to cauſe
                    the ſhip to ſheer off from the point to which the far end of the tow-line is
                    attached. This will ſtretch the rope, and raiſe the weight out of the water. Now
                    heave upon the rope, to bring the ſhip back again to her former poſition, with
                    her keel in the direction of the ſtream. When this poſition is attained, note
                    carefully the form of the rope, that is, the angle which its two parts make with
                    the horizon. Call this angle <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> Every perſon acquainted
                    with theſe ſubjects knows that the horizontal ſtrain is equal to half the weight
                    multiplied by the cotangent of a <hi rend="italic">,</hi> or that 2 is to the
                    cotangent of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> as the weight to the horizontal ſtrain.
                    Now it is this ſtrain which balances and therefore meaſures the action of the
                    rudder, or D <hi rend="italic">e</hi> in fig. 11. Therefore, to have the
                    abſolute impulſe D <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> we muſt increaſe D <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> in the proportion of radius to the ſecant of the angle
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi> which the rudder makes with the keel. In a great
                    ſhip ſailing six miles in an hour, the impulſe on the rudder inclined 30⁰ to the
                    keel is not leſs than 3000 pounds. The ſurface of the rudder of ſuch a ſhip
                    contains near 80 ſquare feet. It is not, however, very neceſſary to know this
                    abſolute impulſe D <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> becauſe it is its part D <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> alone which meaſures the energy of the rudder in
                    producing a conversion. Such experiments, made with various poſitions of the
                    rudder, will give its energies correſponding to theſe poſitions, and will ſettle
                    that long diſputed point which is the belt poſition for turning a ſhip. On the
                    hypotheſis that the impulſions of fluids are in the duplicate ratio of the sines
                    of incidence, there can be no doubt that it ſhould make an angle of 54⁰ 44' with
                    the keel. But the form of a large ſhip will not admit of this, becauſe a tiller
                    of a length ſufficient for managing the rudder in sailing<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0220.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0214"/> with great
                    velocity has not room to deviate above 30⁰ from the direction of the keel; and
                    in this poſition of the rudder the mean obliquity of the filaments of water to
                    its ſurface cannot exceed 40⁰ or 45⁰. A greater angle would not be of much
                    ſervice, for it is never for want of a proper obliquity that the rudder sails of
                    producing a conversion.</p>
                <p>A ſhip miſſes stays in rough weather for want of a Sufficient progreſſive
                    velocity, and becauſe her bows are beat off by the waves: and there is ſeldom
                    any difficulty in wearing the ſhip, if ſhe has any progreſſive motion. It is,
                    however, always deſirable to give the rudder as much influence as poſſible. Its
                    ſurface ſhould be enlarged (eſpecially below) as much as can be done
                    consiſtently with its ſtrength and with the power of the steerſmen to manage it;
                    and it ſhould be put in the moſt favourable ſituation for the water to get at it
                    with great velocity; and it ſhould be placed as far from the axis of the ſhip’s
                    motion as poſſible. Theſe points are obtained by making the ſtern-poſt very
                    upright, as has always been done in the French dockyards. The Britiſh ſhips have
                    a much greater rake; but our builders are gradually adopting the French forms,
                    experience having taught us that their ſhips, when in our posseſſion, are much
                    more obedient to the helm than our own.— In order to afcertain the motion
                    produced by the action of the rudder, draw from the centre of gravity a line <hi
                        rend="italic">Gq</hi> perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">Dd</hi> (Dd being
                    drawn thro’ the centre of effort of the rudder). Then, as in the conſideration
                    of the action of the sails, we may conceive the line <hi rend="italic">q</hi> G
                    as a lever connected with the ſhip, and impelled by a force D <hi rend="italic"
                        >A</hi> acting perpendicularly at <hi rend="italic">q.</hi> The consequence
                    of this will be, an incipient converſion of the ſhip about a vertical axis
                    paſſing through ſome point S in the line <hi rend="italic">q</hi> G, lying on
                    the other side of G from <hi rend="italic">q;</hi> and we have, as in the former
                    caſe, GS = M ∙ Gy</p>
                <p>Thus the action and effects of the ſails and of the rudder are perfectly ſimilar,
                    and are to be conſidered in the same manner. We fee that the action of the
                    rudder, though of a ſmall ſurface in compariſon of the ſails, must be very
                    great: For the impulſe of water is many hundred times greater than that of the
                    wind; and the arm qG of the lever, by which it acts, is incomparably greater
                    than that by which any of the impulsions on the ſails produces its effect;
                    accordingly the ſhip yields much more rapidly to its action than ſhe does to the
                    lateral impulſe of a ſail.</p>
                <p>Obſerve here, that if G were a fixed or ſupported axis, it would be the ſame
                    thing whether the abſolute force D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> of the rudder acts
                    in the direction D <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> or its tranſverſe part D <hi
                        rend="italic">e</hi> acts in the direction De, both would produce the ſame
                    rotation; but it is not ſo in a free body. The force D <hi rend="italic">d</hi>
                    both tends to retard the ſhip’s motion and to produce a rotation: It retards it
                    as much as if the ſame force D <hi rend="italic">d</hi> had been immediately
                    applied to the centre. And thus the real motion of the ſhip is compounded of a
                    motion of the centre in a direction parallel to <hi rend="italic">Dd,</hi> and
                    of a motion round the centre. Theſe two constitute the motion round 8.</p>
                <p>As the effects of the action of the rudder are both more remarkable and somewhat
                    more simple than thoſe of the ſails, we ſhall employ them as an example of the
                    mechaniſm of the motions of converſion in general; and as we muſt content
                    ourſelves in a work like this with what is very general, we ſhall simplify the
                    inveſtigation by attending only to the motion of converſion. We can get an
                    accurate notion of the whole motion, if wanted for any purpoſe, by combining the
                    progreſſive or retrograde motion parallel to Dd with the motion of rotation
                    which we are about to determine.</p>
                <p>In this caſe, then, we obſerve, in the firſt place, that the Db ∙ qG; angular
                    velocity (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Rotation,</hi> n <hi rend="superscript">
                        o</hi> 22.) is</p>
                <p>and, as was ſhown in that article, this velocity of rotation increaſes in the
                    proportion of the time of the forces uniform action, and the rotation would be
                    uniformly accelerated if the forces did really act uniformly. This, however,
                    cannot be the caſe, becauſe, by the ſhip’s change of poſition and change of
                    progreſſive velocity, the direction and intenſity of the impelling force is
                    continually changing. But if two ſhips are performing ſimilar evolutions, it is
                    obvious that the changes of force are ſimilar in ſimilar parts of the evolution.
                    Therefore the conſideration of the momentary evolution is ſufficient for
                    enabling us to compare the motions of ſhips actuated by ſimilar forces, which is
                    all we have in view at preſent.</p>
                <p>The velocity <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> generated in any time <hi rend="italic"
                        >t</hi> by the continuance of an invariable momentary acceleration (which is
                    all that we mean by ſaying that it is produced by the action of a constant
                    accelerating force), is as the acceleration and the time jointly. Now what we
                    call the <hi rend="italic">angular velocity</hi> is nothing but this momentary
                    acceleration. Therefore the velocity <hi rend="italic">v</hi> generated in the
                    time</p>
                <p>F ∙ qG</p>
                <p>" <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> v <hi rend="superscript"> 777</hi> ''</p>
                <p>The expreſſioivof the angular velocity is alſo the expreſſion of the velocity <hi
                        rend="italic">v</hi> of a point ſituated at the distance 1 from the axis
                    G.</p>
                <p>Let z be the ſpace or arch of revolution deſcribed in the time <hi rend="italic"
                        >t</hi> by this point, whoſe diſtance from G is</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">f∙qg</hi></p>
                <p>= 1. Then z = <hi rend="italic">ν t = jy</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">^ tt</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> and taking the F ∙ qG</p>
                <p>fluent z = — t <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">.</hi> This arch meaſures the whole</p>
                <p>A*</p>
                <p>angle of rotation accompliſhed in the time <hi rend="italic">t.</hi> Theſe are
                    therefore as the ſquares of the times from the beginning of the rotation.</p>
                <p>Thoſe evolutions are equal which are meaſured by equal arches. Thus two motions
                    of 45 degrees each are equal. Therefore becauſe <hi rend="italic">z</hi> is the
                    ſame in both,</p>
                <p>F∙q G</p>
                <p>the quantity <hi rend="italic">~Γ t</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> is a constant quantity, and t <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> is F ∙ <hi rend="italic">q</hi> G</p>
                <p>reciprocally proportional <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> θyy <hi rend="subscript"
                        > r</hi> * ’ or is proportional</p>
                <p>to <hi rend="italic">ſMy y</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t</hi> is proportional to ∖
                    That</p>
                <p>F∙qG √F∙qG</p>
                <p>is to ſay, the times of the ſimilar evolutions of two ſhips are as the ſquare
                    root of the momentum of inertia directly, and as the ſquare root of the momentum
                    of the rudder or ſail inverſely. This will enable us to make the compariſon
                    eaſily. Let us ſuppoſe the ships perfectly ſimilar in form and rigging, and to
                    differ only in length L and l : SP ∙ R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> is to Spr
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> as L <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> to l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 5</hi>.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0221.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0215"/> For the ſimilar particles P and <hi
                        rend="italic">p</hi> contain quantities of matter which are as the cubes of
                    their lineal dimenſions, that is, as L <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> to Z <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 3</hi>. And becauſe the particles are ſimilarly
                    ſituated, R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> is to r <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> as L <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> to Z <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi>. Therefore P ∙ R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: <hi rend="italic">p
                        ∙ r</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">—</hi> L <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi>: l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 5</hi>. Now F is to <hi rend="italic">f</hi> as L <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi> to l <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. For the
                    ſurfaces of the ſimilar rudders or ſails are as thc ſquares of their lineal
                    dimenſions, that is, as L <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> to l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. And, laſtly, G <hi rend="italic">q</hi> is to
                        <hi rend="italic">gq</hi> as L to Z, and therefore F <hi rend="italic"
                        >∙</hi> Gq : f <hi rend="italic">∙</hi> gq = L <hi rend="superscript">
                        3</hi>: l <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi>. Therefore we have T <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>:</p>
                <p>∕P∙R <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> S <hi rend="italic">p∙r</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> L <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi> l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 5</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">t</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">=</hi>: Sp <hi rend="italic">∙r</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> = <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi>- <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 3</hi>: 7T= L <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>: l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and T:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">F∙Gq</hi> f∙gq</p>
                <p>t = L : l.</p>
                <p>Therefore the times of performing ſimilar evolutions with ſimilar ſhips are
                    proportional to the lengths of the ſhips when both are ſailing equally faſt; and
                    ſince the evolutions are ſimilar, and the forces vary ſimilarly in their
                    different parts, what is here demonstrated of the ſmalleſt incipient evolutions
                    is true of the whole. They therefore not only deſcribe equal angles of
                    revolution, but alſo ſimilar curves.</p>
                <p>A ſmall ſhip, therefore, works in leſs time and in leſs room than a great ſhip,
                    and this in the proportion of its length. This is a great advantage in all
                    cafes, particularly in wearing, in order to ſail on the other tack cloſe-hauled.
                    In this cafe ſhe will always be to windward and ahead of the large ſhip, when
                    both are got on the other tack. It would appear at firſt fight that the large
                    ſhip will have the advantage in tacking. Indeed the large ſhip is farther to
                    windward when again trimmed on the other tack than the ſmall ſhip when ſhe is
                    juſt trimmed on the other tack. But this happened before the large ſhip had
                    completed her evolution, and the ſmall ſhip, in the mean time, has been going
                    forward on the other tack, and going to windward. She will therefore be before
                    the large ſhip’s beam, and perhaps as far to windward.</p>
                <p>We have ſeen that the velocity of rotation is proportional, <hi rend="italic"
                        >coeteris paribus,</hi> to F × G <hi rend="italic">q.</hi> F means the
                    abſolute impulſe on the rudder or ſail, and is always perpendicular to its
                    ſurface. This abſolute impulſe on a ſail depends on the obliquity of the wind to
                    its ſurface. The uſual theory ſays, that it is as the ſquare of the ſine of
                    incidence: but we find this not true. We muſt content ourſelves with expreſſing
                    it by ſome as yet unknown function φ of the angle of incidence <hi rend="italic"
                        >a,</hi> and call it φa; and if S be the ſurface of the ſail, and V the
                    velocity of the wind, the abſolute impulſe is <hi rend="italic">nV</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> S × φ <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> This acts
                    (in the caſe of the mizen-topſail, fig. 10.) by the lever <hi rend="italic"
                        >q</hi> G, which is equal to DG × coſ. DGq, and DGq is equal to the angle of
                    the yard and keel; which angle we formerly called <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                    Therefore its energy in producing a rotation is nV <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> S × φa × DG <hi rend="italic">×</hi> coſ. <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                    Leaving out the confiant quantities n, V <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, S, and
                    DG, its energy is proportional to φa <hi rend="italic">× coſ. b.</hi> In order,
                    therefore, that any ſail may have the greateſt power to produce a rotation round
                    G, it mult be ſo trimmed that <hi rend="italic">φa</hi> × coſ. <hi rend="italic"
                        >b</hi> may be a maximum. Thus, if we would trim the ſails on the foremaſt,
                    ſo as to pay the ſhip off from the wind right ahead with the greateſt effect,
                    and if we take the experiments of the French academicians as proper meaſures of
                    the oblique impulſes of the wind on the ſail, we will brace up. the yard to an
                    angle of 48 degrees with the keel. The impulſe corre- ponding to 48° is 615 <hi
                        rend="italic">,</hi> and the cosine of 48⁰ is 669.</p>
                <p>Theſe give a product of 411435. If we brace the ſail to 54.44, the angle aſſigned
                    by the theory, the effective impulſe is 405274. If we make the angle 45⁰, the
                    impulſe is 408774. It appears then that 48⁰ is preferable to either of the
                    others. But the difference is inconſiderable, as in all caſes of maximum a ſmall
                    deviation from the beſt poſition is not very detrimental. But the difference
                    between the theory and this experimental meaſure will be very great when the
                    impulſes of the wind are of neceſſity very oblique. Thus, in tacking ſhip, as
                    ſoon as the headſails are taken aback, they ſerve to aid the evolution, as is
                    evident: But if we were now to adopt the maxim inculcated by the theory, we
                    ſhould immediately round in the weather-braces, ſo as to increase the impulſe on
                    the ſail, becauſe it is then very ſmall; and although we by this means make yard
                    more ſquare, and therefore diminiſh the rotatory momentum of this impulſe, yet
                    the impulſe is more increaſed (by the theory) than its vertical lever is
                    diminiſhed.— Let us examine this a little more particularly, becauſe it is
                    reckoned one of the niceſt points of ſeamanſhip to aid the ſhip’s coining round
                    by means of the headſails; and experienced seamen differ in their practice in
                    this manœuvre. Suppoſe the yard braced up to 40⁰, which is as much as can be
                    uſually done, and that the ſail ſhivers (the bowlines are uſually let go when
                    the helm is put down), the ſail immediately takes aback, and in a moment we may
                    ſuppoſe an incidence of 6 degrees. The impulſe correſponding to this is 400 (by
                    experiment), and the coſine of 40⁰ is 766. This gives 306400 for the effective
                    impulſe. To proceed according to the theory, we ſhould brace the yard to 70⁰,
                    which would give the wind (now 34⁰ on the weather-bow) an incidence of nearly
                    36⁰, and the ſail an inclination of 20⁰ to the intended motion, which is
                    perpendicular to the keel. For the tangent of 20⁰ is about <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> of the tangent of
                    36⁰. Let us now ſee what effective impulſe the experimental law of oblique
                    impulſions will give for this adjuſtment of the ſails. The experimental impulſe
                    for 36⁰ is 480; the coſine of 70⁰ is 342; the product is 164160, not much
                    exceeding the half of the former. Nay; the impulſe for 36⁰, calculated by the
                    theory, would have been only 346, and the effective impulſe only 118332. And it
                    muſt be farther obſerved, that this theoretical adjuſtment would tend greatly to
                    check the evolution, and in moſt caſes would entirely mar it, by checking the
                    ſhip’s motion ahead, and conſequently the action of the rudder, which is the
                    moſt powerful agent in the evolution; for here would be a great impulſe directed
                    almoſt aſtern.</p>
                <p>We were juſtifiable, therefore, in ſaying, in the beginning of this article, that
                    a ſeaman would frequently find himſelf baffled if he were to work a ſhip
                    according to the rules deduced from M. Bouguer’s work; and we ſee by this
                    inſtance of what importance it is to have the oblique impulſions of fluids
                    ascertained experimentally The practice of the moſt experienced ſeaman is
                    directly the oppoſite to this theoretical maxim, and its ſuccess greatly
                    confirms the uſefulneſs of theſe experiments of the academicians ſo often
                    praiſed by us.</p>
                <p>We return again to the general consideration of the F <hi rend="italic">×
                    qG</hi></p>
                <p>rotatory motion. We found the velocity <hi rend="italic">v — —</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ſp</hi> r∙ ∙</p>
                <p>It is therefore proportional, <hi rend="italic">coeteris paribus,</hi> to <hi
                        rend="italic">q</hi> G. We have ſeen in what manner g G depends on the
                        poſi-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0222.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0216"/> tion
                    and situation of the sail or rudder when the point G is fixed. But it alſo
                    depends on the position of G. With reſpect to the action of the rudder, it is
                    evident that it is ſo much the more powerful as it is more remote from G. The
                    diſtance from G may be increaſed either by moving the rudder farther aft or G
                    farther forward And as it is of the utmoſt importance that a ship anſwer her
                    helm with the greateſt promptitude, those circumſtances have been attended to
                    which diſtinguiſhed fine ſteering ſhips from ſuch as had not this quality; and
                    it is in a great meaſure to be aſcribed to this, that, in the gradual
                    improvement of naval architecture, the centre of gravity has been placed far
                    forward. Perhaps the notion of a centre of gravity did not come into the
                    thoughts of the rude builders in early times; but they obſerved that thoſe boats
                    and ſhips ſteered beſt which had their extreme breadth before the middle point,
                    and conſequently the bows not ſo acute as the ſtern. This is ſo contrary to what
                    one would expect, that it attracted attention more forcibly; and, being ſomewhat
                    myſterious, it might prompt to attempts of improvement, by exceeding in this
                    ſingular maxim. We believe that it has been carried as far as is compatible with
                    other eſſential requisites in a ſhip.</p>
                <p>We believe that this is the chief circumſtance in what is called the trim of a
                    ſhip; and it were greatly to be wiſhed that the beſt place for the centre of
                    gravity could be accurately aſcertained. A practice prevails, which is the
                    oppoſite of what we are now advancing. It is uſual to load a ſhip ſo that her
                    keel is not horizontal, but lower abaft. This is found to improve her ſteerage.
                    The reaſon of this is obvious. It increaſes the acting ſurface of the rudder,
                    and allows the water to come at it with much greater freedom and regularity; and
                    it generally diminishes the griping of the ſhip forward, by removing a part of
                    the bows out of the water. It has not always this effect; for the form of the
                    harping aloft is frequently ſuch, that the tendency to gripe is diminiſhed by
                    immerſing more of the bow in the water.</p>
                <p>But waving theſe circumſtances, and attending only to the rotatory energy of the
                    rudder, we ſee that it is of advantage to carry the centre of gravity forward.
                    The ſame advantage is gained to the action of the after sails. But, on the other
                    hand, the action of the head ſails is diminiſhed by it; and we may call every
                    sail a headſail whoſe centre of gravity is before the centre ot gravity of the
                    ſhip; that is, all the sails hoiſted on the bowſprit and foremaſt, and the
                    ſtayſails hoiſted on the mainmaſt; for the centre of gravity is ſeldom far
                    before the mainmast.</p>
                <p>Suppoſe that when the rudder is put into the position AD (fig. 11.), the centre
                    of gravity could be ſhifted to g, ſo as to increaſe <hi rend="italic">q</hi> G,
                    and that this is done without increaſing the ſum of the products pr <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">.</hi> It is obvious that the velocity of convection will be
                    increaſed in the proportion of <hi rend="italic">q</hi> G to <hi rend="italic"
                        >qg.</hi> This is very poſſible, by bringing to that ſide of the ſhip parts
                    of her loading which were ſituated at a diſtance from G on the other ſide. Nay,
                    we can make this change in ſuch a manner that Spr <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    ſhall even be leſs than it was before, by taking care that every thing which we
                    ſhift ſhall be nearer to <hi rend="italic">g</hi> than it was formerly to G.
                    Suppoſe it all placed in one ſpot <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> and that <hi
                        rend="italic">m</hi> is the quantity of matter ſo ſhifted, while M is the
                    quantity of matter in the whole ſhip.</p>
                <p>It is only neceſſary that <hi rend="italic">m ∙ g</hi> G <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> ſhall be leſs than the ſum of the products <hi rend="italic">pr</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> correſponding to the matter which has been
                    ſhifted. Now, although the matter which is eaſily moveable is generally very
                    final) in companion to the whole matter of the ſhip, and therefore can make but
                    a ſmall change in the place of the centre of gravity, it may frequently be
                    brought from places ſo remote, that it may occaſion a very senſible diminution
                    of the quantity Spr <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">,</hi> which expreſſes the whole momentum of inertia.</p>
                <p>This explains a practice of the ſeamen in ſmall wherries or ſkiffs, who in
                    putting about are accuſtomed to place themselves to leeward of the maſt. They
                    even find that they can aid the quick motions of theſe light boats by the way in
                    which they reft on their two feet, ſometimes leaning all on one loot, and
                    ſometimes on the other. And we have often ſeen this evolution very ſenſibly
                    accelerated in a ſhip of war, by the crew running ſuddenly, as the helm is put
                    down, to the lee-bow. And we have heard it aſſerted by very expert ſeamen, that
                    after all attempts to wear ſhip (alter lying-to in a ſtorm) have failed, they
                    have ſucceeded by the crew collecting themſelves near the weather fore-ſhrouds
                    the moment the helm was put down. It muſt be agreeable to the reflecting ſeaman
                    to ſee this practice ſupported by undoubted mechanical principles.</p>
                <p>It will appear paradoxical to ſay that the evolution may. be accelerated even by
                    an addition of matter to the ſhip; and though it is only a piece of curioſity,
                    our readers may wiſh to be made ſenſible of it. Let <hi rend="italic">m</hi> be
                    the addition, placed in ſome point <hi rend="italic">m</hi> lying beyond G from
                        <hi rend="italic">q.</hi> Let S be the ſpontaneous centre of convection
                    before the addition. Let <hi rend="italic">v</hi> be the velocity of rotation
                    round <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> that is, the velocity of a point whoſe diſtance
                    from <hi rend="italic">g</hi> is I, and let p be the radius vector, or diſtance
                    of a particle from g. We have <hi rend="smallcaps">(Rotation,</hi> n⁰ 22.) v
                    =</p>
                <p>F ∙ <hi rend="italic">qg</hi></p>
                <p>— — . But we know <hi rend="smallcaps">(Rotation,</hi> n⁰ 23.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sp</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> + m ∙ <hi rend="italic">mg</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>that Spρ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">— Spr</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi> + M ∙ G <hi rend="italic">g</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">.</hi> Therefore <hi rend="italic">v</hi> = s</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Spr</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">+ M</hi> ∙ Gg <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + m ∙ mg2 Let us
                    determine G <hi rend="italic">g</hi></p>
                <p>Spr <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> M + M ∙ Gg <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + m
                    ∙ <hi rend="italic">mg</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>and <hi rend="italic">mg</hi> and <hi rend="italic">qg.</hi></p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">m</hi> G be called z. Then, by the nature of the</p>
                <p>centre of gravity, M + m : M = <hi rend="italic">Gm : gm — z : gm,</hi> and gm
                    =</p>
                <p>M</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">gm</hi> = —- z, and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> ∙ <hi
                        rend="italic">gm</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">= —z</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>. In</p>
                <p>M+ <hi rend="italic">m</hi> M + m <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>M <hi rend="italic">m</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>like manner, M ∙ Gg <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>- — z <hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi>. Now <hi rend="italic">m</hi> M <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> +</p>
                <p>M <hi rend="italic">gm</hi></p>
                <p>M <hi rend="italic">m</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> — Mm × M + <hi rend="italic">m.</hi> Therefore M
                    ∙ Gg <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + <hi rend="italic">m</hi> ∙ <hi
                        rend="italic">gm</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>Mm × (M + m)z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, M <hi rend="italic">m</hi> = <hi
                        rend="underline">—</hi>- — z <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> = ——- z <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Let <hi rend="italic">n</hi> be =</p>
                <p>M + m <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> M + m</p>
                <p>— , then MG <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + m ∙ <hi rend="italic">gm</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">=</hi> Mnz <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>. Alſo Gg =</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">M + m</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">nz,</hi> being = ———z. Let qG be called <hi rend="italic"
                        >c</hi>: then</p>
                <p>M + n</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">qg — c + nz.</hi> Alſo let SG be called <hi rend="italic"
                        >e.</hi></p>
                <p>We have now for the expreſſion of the velocity <hi rend="italic">ν =</hi> F (c +
                        <hi rend="italic">nz)</hi> F <hi rend="italic">c + nz</hi></p>
                <p>Spr <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + Mnz <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> or v =
                        <hi rend="superscript"> F</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> M</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">∙ But</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">M +</hi> nz <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi><pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0223.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0217"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">ſpr</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> (Rotation,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">n⁰ 30 ) lt; =</hi> ce. <hi rend="italic">Therefore, finally,
                        v</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> =</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript smallcaps"> F</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> /</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps"> M</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">× c + nz/ce + nz</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> 2</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">. Had there been no addition of matter Mce +</hi> nz <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>made, we ſhould have had <hi rend="italic">v =</hi>
                    <hi rend="superscript"> F</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> M</hi> × —. It remains to
                    M <hi rend="italic">ce</hi> ſhow, that z may be ſo taken that <hi
                        rend="superscript"> c</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> ce</hi> may be leſs than
                    c + nz / ce + nz <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>—-——,. Now, if <hi rend="italic">c</hi> be to z as <hi rend="italic">ce</hi> to z
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> that is, if z be taken equal to e, the two
                    fractions will be equal. But if z be leſs than r, that is, if the additional
                    matter is placed anywhere between S and G, the complex fraction will be greater
                    than the fraction <hi rend="superscript"> c</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                    ce</hi>, and the velocity of rotation will be increaſed. There is a particular
                    diſtance which will make it the greateſt poſſible, namely, when z is made = —
                    (√c <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + <hi rend="italic">nce - c),</hi> as will
                    easily be found by treating the fraction c + nz , with <hi rend="italic">ce</hi>
                    + nz <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></p>
                <p>z, conſidered as the variable quantity, for a maximum. In what we have been
                    saying on this ſubject, we have conſidered the rotation only in as much as it is
                    performed round the centre of gravity, although in every moment it is really
                    performed round a ſpontaneous axis lying beyond that centre. This was done
                    becauſe it afforded an eaſy inveſtigation, and any angular motion round the
                    centre of gravity is equal to the angular motion round any other point.
                    Therefore the extent and the time of the evolution are accurately defined.— From
                    obſerving that the energy of the force F is proportional to <hi rend="italic"
                        >q</hi> G, an inattentive reader will be apt to conceive the centre of
                    gravity as the centre of motion, and the rotation as taking place became the
                    momenta of the ſails and rudder, on the oppoſite ſides of the centre of gravity,
                    do not balance each other. But we must always keep in mind that this is not the
                    cauſe of the rotation. The cauſe is the want of equilibrium round the point C
                    (fig. 10.), where the actions of the water balance each other. During the
                    evolution, which conſiſts of a rotation combined with a progressive motion, this
                    point C is continually ſhifting, and the unbalanced momenta which continue the
                    rotation always reſpect the momentary ſituation of the point C. It is
                    nevertheleſs always true that the energy of a force F is proportional coe <hi
                        rend="italic">teris paribus)</hi> to <hi rend="italic">q</hi> G, and the
                    rotation is always made in the same direction as if the point G were really the
                    centre of converſion. Therefore the mainſail acts always (when oblique) by
                    puſhing the stern away from the wind, although it ſhould ſometimes act on a
                    point of the vertical lever through C, which is a head of C.</p>
                <p>Theſe obſervations on the effects of the sails and rudder in producing a
                    converſion, are ſufficient for enabling us to explain any case of their action
                    which may occur. We have not conſidered the effects which they tend to produce
                    by inclining the ſhip round a horizontal axis, viz. the motions of rolling and
                    pitching. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rolling</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Pitching.</hi> To treat this ſubject properly would lead us into the whole
                    doctrine of the equilibrium of floating bodies, and it would rather lead to
                    maxims of conſtruction than to maxims of manœuvre. M. Bouguer’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Traité du Navire</hi> and Euler’s <hi rend="italic">Scientia
                        Navalis</hi> are excellent performances on this ſubject,</p>
                <p>and we are not here obliged to have recourſe to any erroneous theory.</p>
                <p>It is eaſy to fee that the lateral preſſure both of the wind on the sails and of
                    the water on the rudder tends to incline the ſhip to one side. The s\ails alſo
                    tend to press the ſhip’s bows into the water, and, if ſhe were kept from
                    advancing, would preſs them down conſiderably. But by the ſhip’s motion, and the
                    prominent form of her bows, the resiſtance of the water to the fore part of the
                    ſhip produces a force which is directed upwards. The sails alſo have a ſmall
                    tendency to raise the ſhip, for they conſtitute a ſurface which in general
                    ſeparates from the plumb-line below. This is remarkably the case in the
                    staysails, particularly the jib and fore-topmaſt ſtayſail. And this helps
                    greatly to ſoften the plunges of the ſhip’s bows into the head leas. The upward
                    preſſure alſo of the water on her bows, which we juſt now mentioned, has a great
                    effect in oppoſing the immerſion of the bows which the sails produce by acting
                    on the long levers furnished by the mails. M. Bouguer gives the name of <hi
                        rend="italic">point velique</hi> to the point V (fig. 12.) of the mail,
                    where it is cut by the line CV, which marks the mean place and direction of the
                    whole impulſe of the water on the bows. And he obſerves, that if the mean
                    direction of all the actions of the wind on the ſails be made to paſs alſo
                    through this point, there will be a perfect equilibrium, and the ſhip will have
                    no tendency to plunge into the water or to rise out of it; for the whole action
                    of the water on the bows, in the direction CV, is equivalent to, and may be
                    reſolved into the action CE, by which the progreſſive motion is reſiſted, and
                    the vertical action CD, by which the ſhip is raiſed above the water. The force
                    CE must be oppoſed by an equal force. VD, exerted by the wind on the ſails, and
                    the force CD is oppoſed by the weight of the ſhip. If the mean effort of the
                    ſails</p>
                <p>paſſes above the point V, the ſhip’s bows will be preſſed into the water; and if
                    it paſs below V, her ſtern will be preſſed down. But, by the union of theſe
                    forces, ſhe will rise and fall with the ſea, keeping always in a parallel
                    poſition. We apprehend that it is of very little moment to attend to the
                    ſituation of this point. Except when the ſhip is right afore the wind, it is a
                    thouſand chances to one that the line CV of mean reliſtance does not paſs
                    through any maſt; and the fact is, that the ſhip cannot be in a ſtate of uniform
                    motion on any other condition but the perfect union of the line of mean action
                    of the ſails, and the line of mean action of the reſiſtance. But its place
                    ſhifts by every change of leeway or of trim; and it is impoſſible to keep theſe
                    lines in one constant point of interſection for a moment, on account of the
                    inceſſant changes of the ſurface of the water on which ſhe floats. M. Bouguer’s
                    obſervations on this point are, however, very ingenious and original.</p>
                <p>We conclude this diſſertation, by deſcribing ſome of the chief movements or
                    evolutions. What we have ſaid hitherto is intended for the instruction of the
                    artist, by making him ſenſible of the mechanical procedure, The deſcription is
                    rather meant for the amuſement of the landsman, enabling him to understand
                    operations that are familiar to the ſeaman. The latter will perhaps ſmile at the
                    awkward account given of his business by one who cannot hand, reef, nor
                    steer.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">To tack Ship.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> ſhip muſt firſt of all be kept full, that is,
                        with<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0224.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0218"/> a
                    very ſenſible angle of incidence on the sails, and by no means hugging the wind.
                    For as this evolution is chiefly performed by the rudder, it is neceſſary to
                    give the ſhip a good velocity. When the ſhip is obſerved to luff up of herſelf,
                    that moment is to be catched for beginning the evolution, becauſe ſhe will by
                    her inherent force continue this motion. The helm is then put down. When the
                    officer calls out Helm’s a lee, the foreſheet, fore-top bowline, jib, and flag
                    sail ſheets forward are let go. The jib is frequently hauled down. Thus the
                    obſtacles to the ſhip’s head coming up to the wind by the action of the rudder
                    are removed. If the mainſail is ſet, it is not unuſual to clue up the weather
                    side, which may be conſidered as a headſail, becauſe it is before the centre of
                    gravity. The mizen muſt be hauled out, and even the ſail braced to windward. Its
                    power in paying off the ſtern from the wind conſpires with the action of the
                    rudder. It is really an aerial rudder. The ſails are immediately taken aback. In
                    this ſtate the effect of the mizen-topſail would be to obſtruct the movement, by
                    preſſing the ſtern the contrary way to what it did before. It is therefore
                    either immediately braced about ſharp on the other tack, or lowered. Bracing it
                    about evidently tends to pay round the ſtern from the wind, and thus aſſiſt in
                    bringing the head up to the wind. But in this poſition it checks the progreſſive
                    motion of the ſhip, on which the evolution chiefly depends. For a rapid
                    evolution, therefore, it is as well to lower the mizen-topſail. Meantime, the
                    headſails are all aback, and the action of the wind on them tends greatly to pay
                    the ſhip round. To increaſe this effect, it is not unuſual to haul the fore-top
                    bowline again. The ſails on the mainmaſt are now almoſt becalmed; and therefore
                    when the wind is right ahead, or a little before, the mainſail is hauled round
                    and braced up ſharp on the other tack with all expedition. The ſtayſail ſheets
                    are now ſhifted over to their places for the other tack. The ſhip is now
                    entirely under the power of the headſails and of the rudder, and their actions
                    conſpire to promote the converſion. The ſhip has acquired an angular motion, and
                    will preſerve it, ſo that now the evolution is ſecured, and ſhe falls off apace
                    from the wind on the other tack. The farther action of the rudder is therefore
                    unneceſſary, and would even be prejudicial, by cauſing the ſhip to fall off too
                    much from the wind before the ſails can be ſhifted and trimmed for ſailing on
                    the other tack. It is therefore proper to right the helm when the wind is right
                    ahead, that is, to bring the rudder into the direction of the keel. The ſhip
                    continues her converſion by her inherent force and the action of the
                    headſails.</p>
                <p>When the ſhip has fallen off about four points from the wind, the headſails are
                    hauled round, and trimmed ſharp on the other tack with all expedition; and
                    although this operation was begun with the wind four points on the bow, it will
                    be ſix before the ſails are braced up, and therefore the headſails will
                    immediately fill. The after-ſails have filled already, while the headſails were
                    inactive, and therefore immediately check the farther falling off from the wind.
                    All fails now draw, for the ſtayſail ſheets have been ſhifted over while they
                    were becalmed or ſhaking in the wind. The ſhip now gathers way, and will obey
                    the smallest motion of the helm to bring her cloſe to the wind.</p>
                <p>We have here ſuppoſed, that during all this operation the ſhip preſerves her
                    progreſſive motion. She</p>
                <p>muſt therefore have deſcribed a curve line, advancing all the while to windward.
                    Fig. 13. is a repreſentation of this evolution when it is performed in the
                    completeſt manner. The ſhip Handing on the courſe E <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>
                    with the wind blowing in the direction WF, has her helm put hard a-lee when she
                    is in the poſition A. She immediately deviates from her courſe, and deſcribing a
                    curve, comes to the poſition B, with the wind blowing in the direction WF of the
                    yards, and the ſquare-ſails now ſhiver. The mizen-topſail is here repreſented
                    braced ſharp on the other tack, by which its tendency to aid the angular motion
                    (while it checks the progreſſive motion) is diſtinctly ſeen. The main and fore-
                    ſails are now ſhivering, and immediately after are taken aback. The effect of
                    this on the headſails is diſtinctly ſeen to be favourable to the converſion, by
                    puſhing the point F in the direction Fi; but for the ſame reaſon it continues to
                    retard the progreſſive motion. When the ſhip has attained to the poſition C, the
                    mainſail is hauled round and trimmed for the other tack. The impulſe in the
                    direction F <hi rend="italic">i</hi> ſtill aids the converſion and retards the
                    progreſſive motion. When the ſhip has attained a poſition between C and D, ſuch
                    that the main and mizen topſail yards are in the direction of the wind, there is
                    nothing to counteract the force of the headſails to pay the ſhip’s head off from
                    the wind. Nay, during the progreſs of the ſhip to this intermediate poſition, if
                    any wind gets at the main or mizen topſails, it acts on their anterior ſurfaces,
                    and impels the after parts of the ſhip away from the curve <hi rend="italic"
                        >abcd,</hi> and thus aids the revolution. We have therefore ſaid, that when
                    once the ſails are taken fully aback, and particularly when the wind is brought
                    right ahead, it is ſcarce poſſible for the evolution to ſail; as ſoon therefore
                    as the maintopſail (trimmed for the other tack) ſhivers, we are certain that the
                    headſails will be filled by the time they are hauled round and trimmed. The
                    ſtayſails are filled before this, becauſe their ſheets have been ſhifted, and
                    they ſtand much ſharper than the ſquare-ſails; and thus every thing tends to
                    check the falling off from the wind on the other tack, and this no ſooner than
                    it ſhould be done. The ſhip immediately gathers way, and holds on in her new
                    courſe dG.</p>
                <p>But it frequently happens, that in this converſion the ſhip loses her whole
                    progreſſive motion. This sometimes happens while the ſails are ſhivering before
                    they are taken fully aback. It is evident, that in this caſe there is little
                    hopes of aucceſs, for the ſhip now lies like a log, and neither ſails nor rudder
                    have any action.. The ſhip drives to leeward like a log, and the water acting on
                    the lee-ſide of the rudder checks a little the driving of the ſtern. The head
                    therefore falls off again, and by and by the ſails fill, and the ſhip continues
                    on her former tack. This is called <hi rend="smallcaps">missing stays,</hi> and
                    it is generally owing to the ship's having too little velocity at the beginning
                    of the evolution. Hence the propriety of keeping the sails well filled for ſome
                    little time before. Rough weather, too, by raiſing a wave which beats violently
                    on the weather-bow, frequently checks the firſt luffing of the ſhip, and beats
                    her off again.</p>
                <p>If the ſhip loses all her motion after the headſails have been fully taken aback,
                    and before we have brought the wind right ahead, the evolution becomes
                    uncertain, but by no means deſperate; for the action<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196363_0225.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0219"/> of the wind
                    on the headſails will presently give her ſtern-way. Suppoſe this to happen when
                    the ſhip is in the poſition C, Bring the helm over hard to windward, ſo that the
                    rudder ſhall have the poſition repreſented by the ſmall dotted line <hi
                        rend="italic">of.</hi> It is evident, that the resiſtance of the water to
                    the ſtern-way of the rudder acts in a favourable direction, puſhing the ſtern
                    outwards. In the mean time, the action of the wind on the headſails pushes the
                    head in the oppoſite direction. Theſe actions conſpire therefore in promoting
                    the evolution; and if the wind is right ahead, it cannot fail, but may even be
                    completed ſpeedily, becauſe the ſhip gathers ſtern-way, and the action of the
                    rudder becomes very powerful; and as ſoon as the wind comes on the formerly
                    lee-bow, the action of the water on the now lee-quarter will greatly accelerate
                    the converſion. When the wind therefore has once been brought nearly right
                    ahead, there is no risk of being baffled.</p>
                <p>But ſhould the ſhip have loſt all her head-way conſiderably before this, the
                    evolution is very uncertain: for the action of the water on the rudder may not
                    be nearly equal to its contrary action on the lee-quarter; in which caſe, the
                    action of the wind on the headſails may not be ſuſſicient to make up the
                    difference. When this is obſerved, when the ſhip goes aſtern without changing
                    her poſition, we muſt immediately throw the headſails completely aback, and put
                    the helm down again, which will pay off the ſhip’s head from the wind enough to
                    enable us to fill the ſails again on the ſame tack, to try our fortune again; or
                    we muſt <hi rend="smallcaps">boxhaul</hi> the ſhip, in the manner to be
                    deſcribed by and by.</p>
                <p>Such is the ordinary proceſs of tacking ſhip; a proceſs in which all the
                    different modes of action of the rudder and sails are employed. To execute this
                    evolution in the moſt expeditious manner, and ſo as to gain as much on the wind
                    as poſſible, is conſidered as the teſt of an expert ſeaman. We have deſcribed
                    the proceſs which is beſt calculated for <hi rend="italic">ensuring</hi> the
                    movement. But if the ſhip be ſailing very briſkly in ſmooth water, ſo that there
                    is no danger of miſſing ſtays, we may gain more to windward conſiderably by
                    keeping faſt the fore-top bowline and the jib and ſtay-ſail ſheets till the
                    ſquare-ſails are all ſhivering: For theſe ſails, continuing to draw with
                    conſiderable force, and balancing each other tolerably fore and aft, keep up the
                    ſhip’s velocity very much, and thus maintain the power of the rudder. If we now
                    let all fly when the ſquare-ſails are ſhivering, the ſhip may be conſidered as
                    without ſails, but expoſed to the action oſ the water on the lee-bow; from which
                    ariſes a ſtrong preſſure of the bow to windward, which conſpires with the action
                    of the rudder to aid the converſion. It evidently leaves all that tendency of
                    the bow to windward which ariſes from leeway, and even what was counteracted by
                    the formerly unbalanced action of theſe head-ſtayſails. This method lengthens
                    the whole time of the evolution, but it advances the ſhip to windward. Obſerve,
                    too, that keeping faſt the fore-top bowline till the ſail ſhivers, and then
                    letting it go, insures the taking aback of that ſail, and thus inſtantly
                    produces an action that is favourable to the evolution.</p>
                <p>The moſt expert ſeamen, however, differ among themſelves with reſpect to theſe
                    two methods, and the firſt is the moſt generally practiſed in the Britiſh navy,
                    becauſe the leaſt liable to fail. The forces which oppoſe the conversion are
                    ſooner removed, and the production of a favourable action by the backing of the
                    fore-topſail is alſo ſooner obtained, by letting go the fore-top bowline at the
                    firſt.</p>
                <p>Having entered ſo minutely into the deſcription and rationale of this evolution,
                    we have ſufficiently turned the reader’s attention to the different actions
                    which cooperate in producing the motions of converſion. We ſhall therefore be
                    very brief in our deſcription of the other evolutions.</p>
                <p>To wear Ship.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">When</hi> the ſeaman ſees that his ſhip will not go a bout
                    head to wind, but will miſs ſtays, he muſt change his tack the other way; that
                    is, by turning her head away from the wind, going a little way before the wind,
                    and then hauling the wind on the other tack. This is called <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >wearing</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">veεring</hi> ſhip. It is moſt
                    neceſſary in ſtormy weather with little sail, or in very faint breezes, or in a
                    diſabled ſhip.</p>
                <p>The proceſs is exceedingly ſimple; and the mere narration of the procedure is
                    ſufficient for ſhowing the propriety of e,very part of it.</p>
                <p>Watch for the moment of the ſhip’s falling off, and then haul up the mainſail and
                    mizen, and ſhiver the mizen-topſail, and put the helm a-weather. When the ſhip
                    falls off ſenſibly (and not before), let go the bowlines. Eaſe away the
                    fore-ſheet, raiſe the fore-tack, and gather aft the weather fore-ſheet, as the
                    lee-ſheet is eaſed away. Round in the weather-braces of the fore and main maſts,
                    and keep the yards nearly biſecting the angle of the wind and keel, ſo that when
                    the ſhip is before the wind the yards may be ſquare. It may even be of advantage
                    to round in the weather-braces of the main-topſail more than thoſe of the
                    headſails; for the mainmaſt is abaft the centre of gravity. All this while the
                    mizen-topſail muſt be kept ſhivering, by rounding in the weather-braces as the
                    ſhip pays off from the wind. Then the main-topſail will be braced up for the
                    other tack by the time that we have brought the wind on the weather-quarter.
                    After this it will be full, and will aid the evolution. When the wind is right
                    aft, ſhift the jib and ſtay-ſail ſheets. The evolution now goes on with great
                    rapidity; therefore briskly haul on board the fore and main tacks, and haul out
                    the mizen, and let the mizen-ſtayſail as ſoon as they will take the wind the
                    right way. We muſt now check the great rapidity with which the ſhip comes to the
                    wind on the other tack, by righting the helm before we bring the wind on the
                    beam; and all muſt be trimmed ſharp fore and aft by this time, that the
                    headſails may take and check the coming-to. All being trimmed, ſtand on cloſe by
                    the wind.</p>
                <p>We cannot help loſing a great deal oſ ground in this movement. Therefore, though
                    it be very ſimple, it requires much attention and rapid execution to do it with
                    as little loſs oſ ground as poſſible. One is apt to imagine at firſt that it
                    would be better to keep the headſails braced up on the former tack, or at leaſt
                    not to round in the weather-braces ſo much as is here directed. When the ſhip is
                    right afore the wind, we ſhould expect assiſtance from the obliquity of the
                    headſails; but the rudder being the principal agent in the evolution, it is
                    found that more is gained by increaſing the ſhip’s velocity, than by a smaller
                    impulſe on the<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0226.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0220"/>
                    headſails more ſavourably directed. Experienced seamen differ, however, in their
                    practice in reſpect of this particular.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">To boxhaul a Ship.</hi></p>
                <p>This is a proceſs performed only in critical situations, as when a rock, a ſhip,
                    or ſome danger, is ſuddenly ſeen right ahead, or when a ſhip miſſes ſtays. It
                    requires the moſt rapid execution.</p>
                <p>The ſhip being cloſe-hauled on a wind, haul up the mainſail and mizen, and ſhiver
                    the topſails, and put the helm hard a-lee altogether. Raiſe the fore-tack, let
                    go the head bowlines, and brace about the headſails ſharp on the other tack. The
                    ſhip will quickly loſe her way, get ſtern-way, and then fall off, by the joint
                    action of the headſails and of the inverted rudder. When ſhe has lallen off
                    eight points, brace the after- ſails ſquare, which have hitherto been kept
                    ſhivering. This will at firſt increaſe the power of the rudder, by increaſing
                    the ſtern-way, and at the ſame time it makes no oppoſition to the conversion
                    which is going on. The continuation of her circular motion will preſently cauſe
                    them to take the wind on their after ſurfaces. This will check the ſtern-way,
                    ſtop it, and give the ſhip a little head-way. Now ſhift the helm, ſo that the
                    rudder may again act in conjunction with the headſails in paying her off from
                    the wind. This is the critical part of the evolution, becauſe the ſhip has
                    little or no way through the water, and will frequently remain long in this
                    poſition. But as there are no counteracting forces, the ſhip continues to fall
                    off. Then the weather-braces of the after-ſails may be gently rounded in, ſo
                    that the wind acting on their hinder ſurfaces may both puſh the ſhip a little
                    ahead and her ſtern laterally in conjunction with the rudder. Thus the wind is
                    brought upon the quarter, and the headſails ſhiver. By this time the ſhip has
                    acquired ſome headway. A continuation of the rotation would now ſill the
                    headſails, and their action would be contrary to the intended evolution. They
                    are therefore immediately braced the other way, nearly ſquare, and the evolution
                    is now completed in the ſame manner with wearing ſhip.</p>
                <p>Some ſeamen brace all the ſails aback the moment that the helm is put hard a-lee,
                    but the after-ſails no more aback than just to ſquare the yards. This quickly
                    gives the ſhip ſtern-way, and brings the rudder into action in its inverted
                    direction; and they think that the evolution is accelerated by this method.</p>
                <p>There is another problem of ſeamanſhip deſerving of our attention, which cannot
                    properly be called an evolution. This is lying-to. This is done in general by
                    laying ſome ſails aback, ſo as to ſtop the head-way produced by others. But
                    there is a conſiderable addreſs neceſſary for doing this in ſuch a way that the
                    ſhip ſhall lie eaſily, and under command, ready to proceed in her courſe, and
                    eaſily brought under weigh.</p>
                <p>To bring-to with the fore or main-topſail to the maſt, br ace that ſail ſharp
                    aback, haul out the mizen, and clap the helm hard a-lee.</p>
                <p>Suppoſe the fore topſail to be aback; the other ſails ſhoot the ſhip ahead, and
                    the lee helm makes the ſhip come up to the wind, which makes it come more
                    perpendicularly on the ſail which is aback. Then its impulſe ſoon exceeds thoſe
                    on the other ſails, which are now ſhivering, or almoſt ſhivering. The ſhip
                    ſtands ſtill</p>
                <p>awhile, and then rails off, ſo as to ſill the after-ſails, which again ſhoot her
                    ahead, and the proceſs is thus repeated. A ſhip lying-to in this way goes a good
                    deal ahead and alſo to leeward. If the main-topſail be aback, the ſhip ſhoots
                    ahead, and comes up till the diminiſhed impulſe of the drawing ſails in the
                    direction of the keel is balanced by the increaſed impulſe on the main-topſail.
                    She lies a long while in this poſition, driving ſlowly to leeward; and ſhe at
                    laſt falls off by the beating of the water on her weather-bow. She falls off but
                    little, and ſoon comes up again.</p>
                <p>Thus a ſhip lying-to is riot like a mere log, but has a certain motion which
                    keeps her under command. To get under weigh again, we muſt watch the time of
                    falling off; and when this is juſt about to finiſh, brace about briſkly, and
                    fill the ſail which was aback. To aid this operation, the jib and fore-topmaſt
                    ſtayſail may be hoiſted, and the mizen brailed up: or, when the intended courſe
                    is before the wind or large, back the fore- topſail ſharp, ſhiver the main and
                    mizen topſail, brail up the mizen, and hoiſt the jib and fore-topmaſt ſtay-
                    ſails altogether.</p>
                <p>In a ſtorm with a contrary wind, or on a lee ſhore, a ſhip is obliged to lie-to
                    under a very low ſail. Some sail is abſolutely neceſſary, in order to keep the
                    ſhip ſteadily down, otherwiſe ſhe would kick about like a cork, and roll ſo deep
                    as to ſtrain and work herſelf to pieces. Different ſhips behave beſt under
                    different ſails. In a very violent gale, the three lower ſtayſails are in
                    general well adapted for keeping her ſteady, and diſtributing the ſtrain. This
                    mode ſeems alſo well adapted for wearing, which may be done by hauling down the
                    mizen-ſtayſail. Under whatever ſail the ſhip is brought- to in a ſtorm, it is
                    always with a fitted ſail, and never with one laid aback. The helm is laſhed
                    down hard a-lee; therefore the ſhip ſhoots ahead, and comes up till the ſea on
                    her weather-bow beats her off again. Getting under weigh is generally difficult;
                    becauſe the ſhip and rigging are lofty abaft, and hinder her from falling off
                    readily when the helm is put hard a-weather. We muſt watch the falling off, and
                    aſſiſt the ſhip by ſome ſmall headſail. Sometimes the crew get up ou the weather
                    ſore-ſhrouds in a crowd, and thus preſent a ſurface to the wind.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">These</hi> examples of the three chief evolutions will
                    enable thoſe who are not ſeamen to underſtand the propriety of the different
                    ſteps, and alſo to underſtand the other evolutions as they are deſcribed by
                    practical authors. We are not acquainted with any performance in our language
                    where the whole are conſidered in a connected and ſyſtematic manner. There is a
                    book on this ſubject in French, called <hi rend="italic">Le Manœuvrier</hi>, by
                    M. Bourde de Ville-Huet, which is in great reputation in France. A tranſlation
                    into Engliſh was publiſhed ſome years ago, laid to be the performance of the
                    Chevalier de Sauſeuil a French officer. But this appears to be a bookſeller’s
                    puff; for it is undoubtedly the work of ſome perſon who did not underſtand
                    either the French language, or the ſubject, or the mathematical principles which
                    are employed in the ſcientiſic part. The blunders are not ſuch as could poſſibly
                    be made by a Frenchman not verſant in the Engliſh language, but natural for an
                    Engliſhman ignorant of French. No French. gentleman or officer would have
                    tranſlated a work of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0227.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0221"/> this kind (which he profeſſes to think ſo highly
                    of) to ſerve the rivals and foes of his country. But indeed it can do no great
                    harm in this way; for the ſcientific part of it is abſolutely unintelligible for
                    want of ſcience in the translator; and the practical part is full of blunders
                    for want of knowledge of the French language.</p>
                <p>We offer this account of the ſubject with all proper reſpect and diſſidence. We
                    do not profeſs to teach: but by pointing out the defects of the celebrated
                    works</p>
                <p>of M. Bouguer, and the courſe which may be taken to remove them, while we
                    preſerve much valuable knowledge which they contain, we may perhaps excite ſome
                    perſons to apply to this ſubject, who, by a combination of what is juſt in M.
                    Bouguer’s theory, with an experimental doctrine of the impulſes of fluids, may
                    produce a treatiſe of ſeamanſhip which will not be confined to the libraries of
                    mathematicians, but become a manual for ſeamen by profeſſion.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
