<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0181.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0175-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCULPTURE</label>
Is the art of carving wood or hewing ſtone into images. It is an art of the moſt remote antiquity, being practiſed, as there is reaſon to believe, before the general deluge. We are induced to aſſign to it this early origin, by conſidering the expedients by which, in the firſt ſtages of ſociety, men have everywhere ſupplied the place of alphabetic characters. Theſe, it is univerſally known, have been picture-writing, ſuch as that of the Mexicans, which, in the progreſs of refinement and knowledge, was gradually improved into the hieroglyphics of the Egyptians and other ancient nations. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Hieroglyphics.</hi></p><p>That mankind ſhould have lived near 1700 years, from the creation of the world to the flood of Noah, without falling upon any method to make their conceptions permanent, or to communicate them to a diſtance, is extremely improbable; eſpecially when we call to mind that ſuch methods of writing have been found, in modern times, among people much leſs enlightened than thoſe muſt have been who were capable of building ſuch a veſſel as the ark. But if the antediluvians were acquainted with any kind of writing, there can be little doubt of its being hieroglyphical writing. Mr Bryant has proved that the Chaldeans were poſſeffed of that art before the Egyptians; and Beroſus<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Apud Syncellum, p. 37.</p></note> * informs us, that a delineation of all the monſtrous forms which inhabited the chaos, when this earth was in that ſtate, was to be ſeen in the temple of Belus in Babylon. This delineation, as he deſcribes it, muſt have been a hiſtory in hieroglyphical characters; for it conſiſted of human figures with wings, with two heads, and ſome with the horns and legs of goats. This is exactly ſimilar to the hieroglyphical writing of the Egyptians; and it was preſerved, our author fays, both in drawings and <hi rend="italic">engravings</hi> in the temple of the god of Babylon. As Chaldee was the firſt peopled region of the earth after the flood, and as it appears from Pliny<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>† Hist. Nat. lib. 7. cap. 56.</p></note> †, as well as from Beroſus, that the art of engraving upon bricks baked in the fun was there carried to a conſiderable degree of perfection at a very early period, the probability cer-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0182.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0176"/>
tainly is, that the Chaldeans derived the art of hieroglyphical writing, and conſequently the rudiments of the art of ſculpture, from their antediluvian anceſtors.</p><p>It is generally thought that ſculptore had its origin from idolatry, as it was found neceſſary to place before the people the images of their gods to enliven the fervour of their devotion: but this is probably a miſtake. The worſhip of the heavenly bodies, as the only gods of the heathen nations, prevailed ſo long before the deification of dead men was thought of (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Polytheism),</hi> that we cannot ſuppoſe mankind to have been, during all that time, ignorant of the art of hieroglyphical writing. But the deification of departed heroes undoubtedly gave riſe to the almoſt univerſal practice of repreſenting the gods by images of a human form; and therefore we muſt conclude, that the elements of ſculpture were known before that art was employed to enliven the devotion of idolatrous worſhippers. The pyramids and obeliſks of Egypt, which were probably temples, or rather altars, dedicated to the ſun (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Pyramid),</hi> were covered from top to bottom with hieroglyphical emblems of men, beaſts, birds, fiſhes, and reptiles, at a period prior to that in which there is any unexceptionable evidence that mere ſtatue-worſhip prevailed even in that nurſery of idolatry.</p><p>But though it appears thus evident that picture- writing was the firſt employment of the ſculptor, we are far from imagining that idolatrous worſhip did not contribute to carry his art to that perfection which it attained in ſome of the nations of antiquity. Even in the dark ages of Europe, when the other fine arts were almoſt extinguiſhed, the mummery of the church of Rome, and the veneration which ſhe taught for her ſaints and martyrs, preſerved among the Italians ſome veſtiges of the ſiſter-arts of ſculpture and painting; and therefore, as human nature is everywhere the ſame, it is reaſonable to believe that a ſimilar veneration for heroes and demigods would, among the ancient nations, have a ſimilar effect. But if this be ſo, the preſumption is, that the Chaldeans were the firſt who invented the art of hewing blocks of wood and ſtone into the figures of men and other animals; for the Chaldeans were unqueſtionably the firſt idolaters, and their early progreſs in ſculpture is confirmed by the united teſtimonies of Beroſus, Alexander Polyhiſtor, Apollodorus, and Pliny; not to mention the eaſtern tradition, that the father of Abraham was a ſtatuary.</p><p>Againſt this concluſion Mr Bromley, in his late Hiſtory of the Fine Arts, has urged ſome plauſible arguments. In ſtating theſe he profeſſes not to be original, or to derive his information from the fountain-head of antiquity. He adopts, as he tells us, the theory of a French writer, who maintains, that in the year of the world 1949, about 300 years after the deluge, the Scythians under Brouma, a deſcendant of Magog the ſon of Japhet, extended their conqueſts over the greater part of Aſia. According to this ſyſtem, Brouma was not only the civilizer of India, and the author of the braminical doctrines, but alſo diffuſed the principles of the Scythian mythology over Egypt, Phcenicia, Greece, and the continent of Aſia.</p><p>Of theſe principles Mr Bromley has given us no diſtinct enumeration: the account which he gives of them is not to be found in one place, but to be collected from a variety of diſtant paſſages. In attempting therefore</p><p>to preſent the ſubſtance of his ſcattered hints in one view, we will not be confident that we have omitted none of them. The ox, ſays he, was the Scythian emblem of the generator of animal life, and hence it became the principal divinity of the Arabians. The ſerpent was the ſymbol of the ſource of intelligent nature. Theſe were the common points of union in all the firſt religions of the earth. From Egypt the Iſraelites carried with them a religious veneration for the ox and the ſerpent. Their veneration for the ox appeared ſoon after they marched into the wilderneſs, when in the abſence of Moſes they called upon Aaron to make them gods which ſhould go before them. The idea of having an idol to go before them, ſays our author, was completely Scythian; for ſo the Scythians acted in all their progreſs through Aſia, with this difference, that their idol was a living animal. The Iſraelites having gained their favourite god, which was an ox (not a calf as it is rendered in the book of Exodus), next proceeded to hold a feſtival, which was to be accompanied with dancing; a species of gaiety common in the feſtivals which were held in adoration of the emblematic <hi rend="italic">Urotal</hi> or ox in that very part of Arabia near Mount Sinai where this event took place. It is mentioned too as a curious and important fact, that the ox which was revered in Arabia was called <hi rend="italic">Adonai.</hi> Accordingly Aaron announcing the feaſt to the ox or golden calf, ſpeaks thus, <hi rend="italic">tomorrow is a fea</hi> ſ <hi rend="italic">t to Adonai,</hi> which is in our tranſlation rendered <hi rend="italic">to the Lord.</hi> In the time of Jeroboam we read of the golden calves ſet up as objects of worſhip at Bethel and Dan. Nor was the reverence paid to the ox confined to Scythia, to Egypt, and to Aſia; it extended much farther. The ancient Cimbri, as the Scythians did, carried an ox of bronze before them on all their expeditions. Mr Bromley alſo informs us, that as great reſpect was paid to the living ox among the Greeks as was offered to its ſymbol among other nations.</p><p>The emblem of the ſerpent, continues Mr Bromley, was marked yet more decidedly by the expreſs direction of the Almighty. That animal had ever been conſidered as emblematic of the ſupreme generating power of intelligent life: And was that idea, ſays he, diſcouraged, ſo far as it went to be a ſign or ſymbol of life, when God ſaid to Moſes, “Make thee a brazen ſerpent, and ſet it upon a pole, and it ſhall Come to paſs that every one who is bitten, when he looketh upon it, ſhall live.” In Egypt the ſerpent ſurrounded their Iſis and Oſiris, the diadems of their princes, and the bonnets of their prieſts. The ſerpent made a diſtinguiſhed figure in Grecian ſculpture. The fable of Echidne, the mother of the Scythians, gave her figure terminating as a ſerpent to ail the founders of ſtates in Greece; from which their earlieſt ſculptors repreſented in that form the Titan princes, Cecrops, Draco, and even Ericthonius. Beſides the ſpear of the image of Minerva, which Phidias made for the citadel of Athens, he placed a ſerpent, which was ſuppoſed to guard that goddeſs.</p><p>The ſerpent was combined with many other figures. It ſometimes was coiled round an egg as an emblem of the creation; ſometimes round a trident, to ſhow its power over the ſea; ſometimes it encircled a flambeau, to repreſent life and death.</p><p>In Egypt, as well as in Scythia and India, the di-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0183.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0177"/>
vinity was represented on the leaves of the tamara or lotus. Pan was worshipped as a god in that country, as well as over the eaſt. Their ſphinxes, and all their combined figures of animal creation, took their origin from the mother of the Scythians, who brought forth an offspring that was half a woman and half a ſerpent. Their pyramids and obeliſks aroſe from the idea of flame; the firſt emblem of the ſupreme principle, introduced by the Scythians, and which even the influence of Zoroaſter and the Magi could not remove.</p><p>We are told that the Bacchus of the Greeks is derived from the Brouma of the Indians; that both are repreſented as ſeated on a ſwan ſwimming over the waves, to indicate that each was the god of humid nature, not the god of wine, but the god of waters. The mitre of Bacchus was ſhaped like half an egg; an emblem taken from this circumſtance, that at the creation the egg from which all things ſprung was divided in the middle. Pan alſo was revered among the Scythians; and from that people were derived all the emblems by which the Greeks repreſented this divinity.</p><p>It would be tedious to follow our author through the whole of this ſubject; and were we to ſubmit to the labour of collecting and arranging his ſcattered materials, we ſhould still view his ſyſtem with ſome degree of ſuſpicion. It is drawn, as he informs us, from the work of M. D’Ancarville, intitled, <hi rend="italic">Recherches ſur l'Origine, l'Esprit, et les Progres, des Arts de la Grece.</hi></p><p>To form concluſions concerning the origin of nations, the riſe and progreſs of the arts and ſciences, without the aid of hiſtorical evidence, by analogies which are ſometimes accidental, and often fanciful, is a mode of reaſoning which cannot readily be admitted. There may indeed, we acknowledge, be reſemblances in the religion, language, manners, and customs, of different nations, ſo ſtriking and ſo numerous, that to doubt of their being deſcended from the ſame ſtock would ſavour of ſcepticiſm. But hiſtorical theories muff not be adopted raſhly. We muſt be certain that the evidence is credible and ſatisfactory before we proceed to deduce any concluſions. We muſt firſt know whether the Scythian hiſtory itſelf be authentic, before we make any compariſon with the hiſtory of other nations. But what is called the Scythian hiſtory, every man of learning knows to be a collection of fables. Herodotus and Juſtin are the two ancient writers from whom we have the fulleſt account of that warlike nation; but theſe two hiſtorians contradict each other, and both write what cannot be believed of the ſame people at the ſame period of their progreſs. Juſtin tells us, that there was a long and violent conteſt between the Scythians and Egyptians about the antiquity of their reſpective nations; and after ſtating the arguments on each ſide of the queſtion, which, as he gives them<note anchored="true" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Lib. II. cap. 1.</p></note> *, are nothing to the purpoſe, he decides in favour of the claim of the Scythians. Herodotus was too partial to the Egyptians, not to give them the palm of antiquity: and he was probably in the right; for Juſtin deſcribes his moſt ancient of nations, even in the time of Darius Hyſtaſpes, as ignorant of all the arts of civil life. “They occupied their land in common (ſays he), and cultivated none of it. They had no houſes nor fettled habitations, but wandered with their cattle from deſert to deſert. In theſe rambles they carried their wives and children in tumbrels covered with the ſkins of beaſts, which ſerved as houſes to protect them from the ſtorms of winter. They were without laws, governed by the dictates of natural equity. They coveted not gold or ſilver like the reft of mankind, and lived upon milk and honey. Though they were expoſed to extreme cold, and had abundance of flocks, they knew not how to make garments of wool, but clothed themſelves in the ſkins of wild beaſts<note anchored="true" n="4" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>‡Lib. 2. cap. 2.</p></note> ‡.” This is the moſt favourable account which any ancient writer gives of the Scythians. By Strabo<note anchored="true" n="5" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>§ Lib. 7.</p></note> § and Herodotus<note anchored="true" n="6" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>‖ Lib. 4. cap. 62.</p></note> ‖ they are repreſented as the moſt ſavage of mortals, delighting in war and bloodſhed, cutting the throats of all ſtrangers who came among them, eating their fleſh, and making cups and pots of their ſkulls. Is it conceivable that such ſavages could be ſculptors; or that, even ſuppoſing their manners to have been ſuch as Juſtin repreſents them, a people ſo simple and ignorant could have impoſed their mythology upon the Chaldeans, Phenicians, and Egyptians, whom we know by the moſt incontrovertible evidence to have been great and poliſhed nations ſo early as in the days of Abraham? No! We could as ſoon admit other novelties of more importance, with which the French of the preſent age pretend to enlighten the world, as this origin aſſigned by Mr Bromley to the art of ſculpture, unleſs ſupported by better authority than that of D’Ancarville.</p><p>The inference of our author from the name of the ſacred ox in Arabia, and from the dancing and gaiety which were common in the religious feſtivals of the Arabians, appears to us to be very haſtily drawn. At the early period of the departure of the Iſraelites from Egypt, the language of the Hebrews, Egyptians, and Arabians, differed not more from each other than do the different dialects of the Greek tongue which are found in the poems of Homer (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Philology,</hi> Sect. III.); and it is certain, that for many years after the formation of the golden-calf, the Hebrews were ſtrangers to every ſpecies of idolatry but that which they had brought with them from their houſe of bondage. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Remphan.</hi></p><p>Taking for granted therefore that the Scythians did not impoſe their mythology upon the eaſtern nations, and that the art of ſculpture, as well as hieroglyphic writing and idolatrous worſhip, prevailed firſt among the Chaldeans, we ſhall endeavour to trace the progreſs of this art through ſome other nations of antiquity, till we bring it to Greece, where it was carried to the higheſt perfection to which it has yet attained.</p><p>The firſt intimation that we have of the art of ſculpture is in the book of Geneſis, where we are informed, that when Jacob, by the divine command, was returning to Canaan, his wife Rachel carried along with her the teraphim or idols of her father. Theſe we are aſſured were ſmall, since Rachel found it ſo easy to conceal them from her father, notwithſtanding his anxious ſearch. We are ignorant, however, how theſe images were made, or of wſhat materials they were compoſed. The firſt perſon mentioned as an artiſt of eminence is Bezaleel, who formed the cherubims which covered the mercy-feat.</p><p>The Egyptians alſo cultivated the art of ſculpture; but there were two circumſtances that obſtructed its progreſs, 1. The perſons of the Egyptians were not poſſeſſed of the graces of form, of elegance, or of ſymmetry; and of conſequence they had no perfect ſtandard<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0184.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0178"/>
to model their taſte. They reſembled the Chineſe in the caſt of their face, in their great bellies, and in the clumſy rounding of their contours. 2. They were reſtrained by their laws to the principles and practices of their anceſtors, and were not permitted to introduce any innovations. Their ſtatues were always formed in the ſame ſtiff attitude, with the arms hanging perpendicular ly down the ſides. What perfection were they capable of who knew no other attitude than that of chairmen? So far were they from attempting any improvements, that in the time of Adrian the art continued in the fame rude ſtate as at firſt; and when their ſlaviſh adulation for that emperor induced them to place the ſtatue of his favourite Antinous among the objects of their worſhip, the ſame inanimate ſtiffneſs in the attitude of the body and poſitionof the arms was obſerved. We believe it will ſcarcely be neceſſary to inform our readers that the Egyptian ſtatue juſt now mentioned is very different from the celebrated ſtatue of Antinous, of which ſo many moulds have been taken that imitations of it are now to be met with almoſt in every cabinet in Europe.</p><p>Notwithſtanding the attachment of the Egyptians to ancient uſages, Winkelman thinks he has diſcovered two different ſtyles of ſculpture which prevailed at different periods, The firſt of theſe ends with the conqueſt of Egypt by Cambvſes. The ſecond begins at that time, and extends beyond the reign of Alexander the Great. In the firſt ſtyle, the lines which form the contour are ſtraight and projecting a little; the poſition is ſtiff and unnatural: In ſitting figures the legs are parallel, the feet ſqueezed together, and the arms fixed to the ſides; but in the figures oſ women the left arm is folded acroſs the breaſt; the bones and muſcles are faintly diſcernible; the eyes are flat and looking obliquely, and the eyebrows ſunk; features which deſtroy entirely the beauty of the head; the cheek-bones are high, the chin ſmall and piked; the ears are generally placed higher than in nature, and the feet are too large and flat. In ſhort, if we are to look for any model in the ſtatues of Egypt, it is not for the model of beauty but of deformity. The ſtatues of men are naked, only they have a ſhort apron, and a few folds of drapery ſurrounding their waiſt: The veſtments of women are only diſtinguiſhable by the border, which riſes a little above the ſurface of the ſtatue. In this age it is evident the Egyptians knew little of drapery.</p><p>Of the ſecond ſtyle of ſculpture practiſed among the Egyptians, Winkelman thinks he has found ſpecimens in the two figures of baſaltes in the Capitol, and in another figure at Villa Albani, the head of which has been renewed. The two firſt of theſe, he remarks, bear viſible traces of the former ſtyle, which appear eſpecially in the form oſ the mouth and ſhortneſs of the chin. The hands poſſeſs more elegance; and the feet are placed at a greater diſtance from one another, than was cuſtomary in more ancient times. In the firſt and third figures the arms hang down cloſe to the ſides. In the ſecond they hang more freely. Winkelman ſuſpects that theſe three ſtatues have been made after the conqueſt of Egypt by the Greeks. They are clothed with a tunic, a robe, and a mantle. The tunic, which is puckered into many folds, deſcends from the neck to the ground. The robe in the firſt and third ſtatues items cloſe to the body, and is only perceptible by</p><p>ſome little folds. It is tied under the breaſt, and covered by the mantle, the two buttons of which are placed under the epaulet.</p><p>The Antinous of thc Capitol is compoſed of two pieces, which are joined under the haunches. But as all the Egyptian ſtatues which now remain have been hewn out of one block, we muſt believe that Diodorus, in ſaying the ſtone was divided, and each half finiſhed by a ſeparate artizan, ſpoke only of a coloſſus. The ſame author informs us, that the Egyptians divided the human body into 24 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> parts; but it is to be regretted that he has not given a more minute detail of that diviſion.</p><p>The Egyptian ſtatues were not only formed by the chiſel, they were alſo poliſhed with great care. Even thoſe on the ſummit of an obeliſk, which could only be viewed at a diſtance, were finiſhed with as much labour and care as if they had admitted a cloſe inſpection. As they are generally executed in granite or baſaltes, ſtones of a very hard texture, it is impoſſible not to admire the indefatigable patience of the artiſts.</p><p>The eye was often of different materials from the reſt of the ſtatue; ſometimes it was compoſed of a precious ſtone or metal. We are aſſured that the valuable diamond of the empreſs of Ruſſia, the largeſt and moſt beautiful hitherto known, formed one of the eyes of the famous ſtatue of Scheringham in the temple of Brama.</p><p>Thoſe Egyptian ſtatues which ſtill remain are compoſed of wood or baked earth: and the ſtatues of earth are covered with green enamel.</p><p>The Phenicians poſſeſſed both a character and ſituation highly favourable to the cultivation of ſtatuary. They had beautiful models in their own perſons, and their induſtrious character qualified them to attain perfection in every art for which they had a taſte. Their ſituation raiſed a ſpirit of commerce, and commerce induced them to cultivate the arts. Their temples ſhone with ſtatues and columns of gold, and a profuſion of emeralds was everywhere ſcattered. All the great works of the Phenicians have been unfortunately deſtroyed; but many of the Carthaginian medals are ſtill preſerved, ten of which are depoſited in the cabinet of the grand duke of Florence. But though the Carthaginians were a colony of Phenicians, we cannot from their works judge of the merit of their anceſtors.</p><p>The Perſians made no diſtinguiſhed figure in the arts of deſign. They were indeed ſenſible to the charms of beauty, but they did not ſtudy to imitate them. Their dreſs, which conſiſted of long flowing robes concealing the whole perſon, prevented them from attending to the beauties of form. Their religion, too, which taught them to worſhip the divinity in the emblem of fire, and that it was impious to repreſent him under a human form, ſeemed almoſt to prohibit the exerciſe of this art, by taking away thoſe motives which alone could give it dignity and value; and as it was not cuſtomary among them to raiſe ſtatues to great men, it was impoſſible that ſtatuary could flouriſh in Perſia.</p><p>The Etrurians or ancient Tuſcans, in the opinion of Winkelman, carried this art to ſome degree of perfection at an earlier period than the Greeks. It is ſaid to have been introduced before the ſiege of Troy by Dedalus, who, in order to eſcape the reſentment of Minos king of Crete, took refuge in Sicily, from whence he<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0185.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0179"/>
paſſed into Italy, where he left many monuments of his art. Pauſanias and Diodorus Siculus inform us, that ſome works aſcribed to him were to be ſeen when they wrote, and that theſe poſſeſſed that character of majeſty which afterwards diſtinguiſhed the labours of Etruria.</p><p>A character ſtrongly marked forms the chief diſtinction in thoſe productions of Etruria which have descended to us. Their ſtyle was indeed harſh and overcharged; a fault alſo committed by Michael Angelo the celebrated painter of modern Etruria; for it is not to be ſuppoſed that a people of ſuch rude manners as the Etrurians could communicate to their works that vividneſs and beauty which the elegance of Grecian manners inſpired. On the other hand, there are many of the Tuſcan ſtatues which bear ſo cloſe a reſemblance to thoſe of Greece, that antiquarians have thought it probable that they were conveyed from that country or Magna Græcia into Etruria about the time of the Roman conqueſt, when Italy was adorned with the ſpoils of Greece.</p><p>Among the monuments of Etrurian art two different ſtyles have been obſerved. In the firſt the lines are ſtraight, the attitude ſtiff, and no idea of beauty appears in the formation of the head. The contour is not well rounded, and the figure is too ſlender. The head is oval, the chin piked, the eyes flat, and looking aſquint.</p><p>Theſe are the defects of an art in a ſtate of infancy, which an accompliſhed maſter could never fall into, and are equally conſpicuous in Gothic ſtatues as in the productions of the ancient natives of Florence. They reſemble the ſtyle of the Egyptians ſo much, that one is almoſt induced to ſuppoſe that there had once been a communication between theſe two nations; but others think that this ſtyle was introduced by Dedalus.</p><p>Winkelman ſuppoſes that the ſecond epoch of this art commenced in Etruria, about the time at which it had reached its greateſt perfection in Greece, in the age of Phidias; but this conjecture is not ſupported by any proofs. To deſcribe the ſecond ſtyle of ſculpture among the Etrurians, is almoſt the ſame as to deſcribe the ſtyle of Michael Angelo and his numerous imitators. The joints are ſtrongly marked, the muſcles raiſed, the bones diſtinguiſhable; but the whole mien harſh. In deſigning the bone of the leg, and the reparation of the muſcles of the calf, there is an elevation and ſtrength above life. The ſtatues of the gods are deſigned with more delicacy. In forming them, the artiſts were anxious to ſhow that they could exerciſe their power without that violent diſtenſion of the muſcles which is neceſſary in the exertions of beings merely human; but in general their attitudes are unnatural, and the actions ſtrained. If a ſtatue, for inſtance, hold any thing with its fore-fingers, the reſt are ſtretched out in a ſtiff poſition.</p><p>According to ancient hiſtory, the Greeks did not emerge from the ſavage ſtate till a long time after the Egyptians, Chaldeans, and Indians, had arrived at a conſiderable degree of civilization. The original rude inhabitants of Greece were civilized by colonies which arrived among them, at different times, from Egypt and Phenicia. Theſe brought along with them the religion, the letters, and the arts of their parent coun</p><p>tries: and if ſculpture had its origin froth the worſhip of idols, there is reaſon to believe that it was one of the arts which were thus imported; for that the gods of Greece were of Egyptian and Phenician extraction is a fact incontrovertible; (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Mysteries, Mythology, Philology,</hi> ſect. 7. <hi rend="smallcaps">Philosophy,</hi> n⁰ 19, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Titan.)</hi> The original ſtatues of the gods, however, were very rude. The earlieſt objects of idolatrous worſhip have everywhere been the heavenly bodies; and the ſymbols conſecrated to them were generally pillars of a conical or pyramidal figure. It was not till hero-worſhip was engrafted on the planetary, that the ſculptor thought of giving to the ſacred ſtatue any part of the human form (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Polytheism,</hi> n⁰ 19, 23); and it appears to have been about the era of their revolution in idolatry that the art of ſculpture was introduced among the Greeks. The firſt repreſentations of their gods were round ſtones placed upon cubes or pillars; and theſe ſtones they afterwards formed roughly, ſo as to give them ſomething of the appearance of a head. Agreeable to this deſcription was a Jupiter, which Pauſanias ſaw in Tegeum, in Arcadia. Theſe repreſentations were called <hi rend="italic">Hermes;</hi> not that they repreſented Mercury, but from the word <hi rend="italic">herma,</hi> which ſignified a rough ſtone. It is the name which Homer gives to the ſtones which were uſed to fix veſſels to the ſhore. Pauſanias ſaw at Pheres 30 deities made of unformed blocks or cubical ſtones. The Lacedemonians repreſented Caſtor and Pollux by two parallel poſts; and a tranſverſe beam was added, to expreſs their mutual affection.</p><p>If the Greeks derived from foreign nations the rudiments of the arts, it muſt redound much to their honour, that in a few centuries they carried them to ſuch wonderful perfection as entirely to eclipſe the fame of their maſters. It is by tracing the progreſs of ſculpture among them that we are to ſtudy the hiſtory of this art; and we ſhall ſee its origin and ſucceſſive improvements correſpond with nature, which always operates ſlowly and gradually.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">View of Grecian Sculpture.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> great ſuperiority of the Greeks in the art of ſculpture may be aſcribed to a variety of cauſes. The influence of climate over the human body is ſo ſtriking, that it muſt have fixed the attention of every thinking man who has reflected on the ſubject. The violent heats of the torrid zone, and the exceſſive cold of the polar regions, are unfavourable to beauty. It is only in the mild climates of the temperate regions that it appears in its moſt attractive charms. Perhaps no country in the world enjoys a more ſerene air, leſs tainted with miſts and vapours, or poſſeſſes in a higher degree that mild and genial warmth which can unfold and expand the human body into all the ſymmetry of muſcular ſtrength, and all the delicacies of female beauty in greater perfection, than the happy climate of Greece; and never was there any people that had a greater taſte for beauty, or were more anxious to improve it. Of the four wiſhes of Simonides, the ſecond was to have a handſome figure. The love of beauty was ſo great among the Lacedemonian women, that they kept in their chambers the ſtatues of Nereus, of Narciſſus, of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0186.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0180"/>
Hyacinthus, and of Caſtor and Pollux; hoping that by often contemplating them they might have beautiful children.</p><p>There was a variety of circumſtances in the noble and virtuous freedom of the Grecian manners that rendered theſe models of beauty peculiarly ſubſervient to the cultivation of the fine arts. There were no tyrannical laws, as among the Egyptians, to check their progreſs. They had the beſt opportunities to ſtudy them in the public places, where the youth, who needed no other vail than chaſtity and purity of manners, performed their various exerciſes quite naked. They had the ſtrongeſt motives to cultivate ſculpture, for a ſtatue was the higheſt honour which public merit could attain. It was an honour ambitiouſly ſought, and granted only to thoſe who had diſtinguiſhed themſelves in the eyes of their fellow citizens. As the G reeks preferred natural qualities to acquired accompliſhments, they decreed the firſt rewards to thoſe who excelled in agility and ſtrength of body. Statues were often raiſed to wreſtlers. Even the moſt eminent men of Greece, in their youth, fought renown in gymnaſtic exerciſes. Chryſippus and Cleanthes diſtinguiſhed themſelves in the public games before they were known as philoſophers. Plato appeared as a wreſtler both at the Iſthmian and Pythian games; and Pythagoras carried off the prize at Elis, (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Pythagoras.)</hi> The paſſion by which they were inſpired was the ambition of having their ſtatues erected in the moſt ſacred place of Greece, to be ſeen and admired by the whole people. The number of ſtatues erected on different occaſions was immenſe; of courſe the number of artiſts muſt have been great, their emulation ardent, and their progreſs rapid.</p><p>As moſt of their ſtatues were decreed for thoſe who vanquiſhed in the public games, the artiſts had the opportunity of ſeeing excellent models; for thoſe who ſurpaſſed in running, boxing, and wreſtling, muſt in general have been well formed, yet would exhibit different kinds of beauty.</p><p>The high eſtimation in which ſculptors were held was very favourable to their art. Socrates declared the artiſts the only wiſe men. An artiſt could be a legiſlator, a commander of armies, and might hope to have his ſtatue placed beſide thoſe of Miltiades and Themiſtocles, or thoſe of the gods themſelves. Beſides, the honour and ſucceſs of an artiſt did not depend on the caprice of pride or of ignorance. The productions of art were eſtimated and rewarded by the greateſt ſages in the general aſſembly of Greece, and the ſculptor who had executed his work with ability and taſte was confident of obtaining immortality.</p><p>It was the opinion of Winkelman, that liberty was highly favourable to this art; but, though liberty is abſolutely neceſſary to the advancement <hi rend="italic">of</hi> ſcience, it may be doubted whether the fine arts owe their improvement to it. Sculpture flouriſhed moſt in Greece, when Pericles exerciſed the power of a king; and in the reign of Alexander, when Greece was conquered. It attained no perfection in Rome till Auguſtus had enſlaved the Romans. It revived in Italy under the patronage of the family of Medici, and in France under the deſpotic rule of Louis XIV. It is the love of beauty, luxury, wealth, or the patronage of a powerful individual, that promotes the progreſs of this art.</p><p>It will now be proper to give a particular account of the ideas which the Greeks entertained concerning the ſtandard of beauty in the different parts of the human body. And with reſpect to the head, the profile which they chiefly admired is peculiar to dignified beauty. It conſiſts in a line almoſt ſtraight, or marked by ſuch ſlight and gentle inflections as are ſcarcely diſtinguiſhable from a ſtraight line. In the figures of women and young perſons, the forehead and noſe form a line approaching to a perpendicular.</p><p>Ancient writers, as well as artiſts, aſſure us that the Greeks reckoned a ſmall forehead a mark of beauty, and a high forehead a deformity. From the ſame idea, the Circaſſians wore their hair hanging down over their foreheads almoſt to their eyebrows. To give an oval form to the countenance, it is neceſſary that the hair ſhould cover the forehead, and thus make a curve about the temples; otherwiſe the face, which terminates in an oval form in the inferior part, will be angular in the higher part, and the proportion will be deſtroyed. This rounding of the forehead may be ſeen in all handſome perſons, in all the heads of ideal beauty in ancient ſtatues, and eſpecially in thoſe of youth. It has been overlooked, however, by modern ſtatuaries. Bernini, who modelled a ſtatue of Louis XIV. in his youth, turned back the hair from the forehead.</p><p>It is generally agreed that large eyes are beautiful; but their ſize is of leſs importance in ſculpture than their form, and the manner in which they are enchaſed. In ideal beauty, the eyes are always ſunk deeper than they are in nature, and conſequently the eyebrows have a greater projection. But in large ſtatues, placed, at a certain diſtance, the eyes, which are of the ſame colour with the reſt of the head, would have little effect if they were not ſunk. By deepening the cavity of the eye, the ſtatuary increaſes the light and ſhade, and thus gives the head more life and expreſſion. The ſame practice is uſed in ſmall ſtatues. The eye is a characteriſtic feature in the heads of the different deities. In the ſtatues of Apollo, Jupiter, and Juno, the eye is large and round. In thoſe of Pallas they are alſo large; but by lowering the eyelids, the virgin air and expreſſion of modeſty are delicately marked. Venus has ſmall eyes, and the lower eyelid being raiſed a little, gives them a languiſhing look and an enchanting ſweetneſs. It is only neceſſary to ſee the Venus de Medicis to be convinced that large eyes are not eſſential to beauty, eſpecially if we compare her ſmall eyes with thoſe which reſemble them in nature. The beauty of the eyebrows conſiſts in the fineneſs of the hair, and in the ſharpneſs of the bone which covers them; and maſters of the art conſidered the joining of the eyebrows as a deformity, though it is ſometimes to be met with in ancient ſtatues.</p><p>The beauty of the mouth is peculiarly neceſſary to conſtitute a fine face. The lower lip muſt be fuller than the upper, in order to give an elegant rounding to the chin. The teeth ſeldom appear, except in laughing ſatyrs. In human figures the lips are generally cloſe, and a little opened in the figures of the gods. The lips of Venus are half open.</p><p>In figures of ideal beauty, the Grecian artiſts never interrupted the rounding of the chin by introducing a dimple: for this they conſidered not as a mark of beauty, and only to be admitted to diſtinguiſh individuals. The dimple indeed appears in ſome ancient ſtatues, but<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0187.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0181"/>
antiquaries ſuſpect it to be the work of a modern hand. It is ſuſpected alſo, that the dimple which is ſometimes found on the cheeks of ancient ſtatues is a modern innovation.</p><p>No part of the head was executed by the ancients with mare care than the ears, though little attention has been given to them by modern artiſts. This character is ſo decisive, that if we obſerve in any ſtatue that the ears are not highly finiſhed, but only roughly marked, we may conclude with certainty that we are examining a modern production. The ancients were very attentive to copy the preciſe form of the ear in taking likeneſſes. Thus, where we meet with a head the ears of which have a very large interior opening, we know it to be the head of Marcus Aurelius.</p><p>The manner in which the ancient artiſts formed the hair alſo enables us to diſtinguiſh their works from thoſe of the moderns. On hard and coarſe ſtones the hair was ſhort, and appeared as if it had been combed with a wide comb; for that kind of ſtone was difficult to work, and could not without immenſe labour be formed into curled and flowing hair. But the figures executed in marble in the moſt flouriſhing period of the art have the hair curled and flowing; at leaſt where the head was not intended to be an exact reſemblance, for then the artiſt conformed to his model. In the heads of women, the hair was thrown back, and tied behind in a waving manner, leaving conſiderable intervals; which gives the agreeable variety of light and ſhade, and produces the effects of the claro-obſcuro. The hair of the Amazons is diſpoſed in this manner. Apollo and Bacchus have their hair falling down their ſhoulders; and young perſons, till they arrived at manhood, wore their hair long. The colour of the hair which was reckoned moſt beautiful, was fair; and this they gave without diſtinction to the moſt beautiful of their gods, Apollo and Bacchus, and likewiſe to their moſt illuſtrious heroes.</p><p>Although the ravages of time have preſerved but few of the hands or feet of ancient ſtatues, it is evident from what remains how anxious the Grecian artiſts were to give every perfection to theſe parts. The hands of young perſons were moderately plump, with little cavities or dimples at the joints of the fingers. The fingers tapered very gently from the root to the point, like well-proportioned columns, and the joints were ſcarcely perceptible. The terminating joint was not bent, as it commonly appears in modern ſtatues.</p><p>In the figures of young men the joints of the knee are faintly marked. The knee unites the leg to the thigh without making any remarkable projections or cavities. The moſt beautiful legs and beſt-turned knees, according to Winkelman, are preſerved in the Apollo Saurocthones, in the Villa Borgheſe; in the Apollo which has a ſwan at its feet; and in the Bacchus of Villa Medicis. The ſame able connoiſſeur remarks, it is rare to meet with beautiful knees in young perſons, or in the elegant repreſentations of art. As the ancients did not cover the feet as we do, they gave to them the moſt beautiful turning, and ſtudied the form of them with the moſt ſcrupulous attention.</p><p>The breaſts of men were large and elevated. The breaſts of women did not poſſeſs much amplitude. The figures of the deities have always the breaſts of a virgin, the beauty of which the ancients made to conſiſt in a gentle elevation So anxious were the women to reſemble this ſtandard, that they uſed ſeveral arts to reſtrain the growth of their breaſts. The breaſts of the nymphs and goddeſſes were never repreſented ſwelling, becauſe that is peculiar to thoſe women who ſuckle. The paps of Venus contract and end in a point, this being conſidered as an eſſential characteriſtic of perfect beauty. Some of the moderns have tranſgreſſed theſe rules, and have fallen into great improprieties.</p><p>The lower part of the body in the ſtatues of men was formed like that of the living body after a profound ſleep and good digeſtion. The navel was conſiderably iunk, eſpecially in female ſtatues.</p><p>As beauty never appears in equal perfection in every part of the ſame individual, perfect or ideal beauty can only be produced by ſelecting the moſt beautiful parts from different models; but this muſt be done with ſuch judgment and care, that theſe detached beauties when united may form the moſt exact ſymmetry. Yet the ancients ſometimes confined themſelves to one individual, even in the moſt flouriſhing age Theodorus, whom Socrates and his diſciples viſited, ſerved as a model to the artiſts of his time. Phryne alſo appears to have been a model to the painters and ſculptors But Socrates, in his converſation with Parrhaſius, ſays, that when a perfect beauty was to be produced, the artiſts joined together the moſt ſtriking beauties which could be collected from the fineſt figures. We know that Zeuxis, when he was going to paint Helen, united in one picture all the beauties of the moſt handſome women of Crotona.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> Grecian ſculptors, who repreſented with ſuch ſucceſs the moſt perfect beauty of the human form, were not regardleſs of the drapery of their ſtatues. They clothed their figures in the moſt proper ſtuff, which they wrought into that ſhape which was beſt calculated to give effect to their deſign.</p><p>The veſtments of women in Greece generally conſiſted of linen cloth, or ſome other light fluff, and in latter times of ſilk and ſometimes of woollen cloth. They had alſo garments embroidered with gold. In the works of ſculpture, as well as in thoſe of painting, one may diſtinguiſh the linen by its transparency and ſmall united folds. The other light ſtuffs which were worn by the women<note anchored="true" n="7" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> @@@(a)</hi> <hi rend="italic">Men ſometimes wore cotton, but all who did ſo were reckoned effeminate.</hi></p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> were generally of cotton produced in the iſle of Cos; and theſe the art of ſtatuary was able to diſtinguiſh from the linen veſtments. The cotton cloth was ſometimes ſtriped, and ſometimes embelliſhed with a profuſion of flowers. Silk was alſo employed; but whether it was known in Greece before the time of the Roman emperors cannot eaſily be determined. In paintings, it is diſtinguiſhable by changing its colour in different lights to red, violet, and ſky-blue. There were two ſorts of purple; that which the Greeks called the <hi rend="italic">colour oſ the sea,</hi> and Tyrian purple, which reſembled lac. Woollen garments are eaſily known by<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0188.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0182"/>
the amplitude of their folds. Beſides theſe, cloth of gold ſometimes compoſed their drapery: but it was not like the modern fabric, conſiſting of a thread of gold or of ſilver ſpun with a thread of ſilk; it was compoſed of gold or ſilver alone, without any mixture.</p><p>The veſtments of the Greeks, which deſerve particular attention, are the tunic, the robe, and the mantle.</p><p>The tunic was that part of the dreſs which was next to the body. It may be ſeen in ſleeping figures, or in thoſe in diſhaille; as in the Flora Farneſe, and in the ſtatues of the Amazons in the Capitol. The youngeſt of the daughters of Niobe, who throws herſelf at her mother’s ſide, is clothed only with a tunic. It was of linen, or ſome other light ſtuff, without ſleeves, fixed to the ſhoulders by a button, ſo as to cover the whole breaſt. None but the tunics of the goddeſs Ceres and comedians have long ſtraight ſleeves.</p><p>The robes of women commonly conſiſted of two long pieces of woollen cloth, without any particular form, attached to the ſhoulders by a great many buttons, and ſometimes by a claſp. They had ſtraight ſleeves which came down to the wriſts. The young girls, as well as the women, faſtened their robe to their ſide by a cincture, in the ſame way as the high-prieſt of the Jews faſtened his, as it is ſtill done in many parts of Greece. The cincture formed on the ſide a knot of ribbons ſometimes reſembling a roſe in ſhape, which has been particularly remarked in the two beautiful daughters of Niobe. In the younger of theſe the cincture is ſeen paſſing over the ſhoulders and the back. Venus has two cinctures, the one paſſing over the ſhoulder, and the other ſurrounding the waiſt. The latter is called <hi rend="italic">ceſlus</hi> by the poets.</p><p>The mantle was called <hi rend="italic">peplon</hi> by the Greeks, which ſignifies properly the mantle of Pallas. The name was afterwards applied to the mantles of the other gods, as well as to thoſe of men. This part of the dreſs was not ſquare, as ſome have imagined, but of a roundiſh form. The ancients indeed ſpeak in general of ſquare mantles, but they received this ſhape from four taſſels which were affixed to them; two of theſe were viſible, and two were concealed under the mantle. The mantle was brought under the right arm, and over the left ſhoulder; ſometimes it was attached to the ſhoulder by two buttons, as may be ſeen in the beautiful ſtatue oſ Leucothoe at Villa Albani.</p><p>The colour of veſtments peculiar to certain ſtatues is too curious to be omitted. To begin with the figures of the gods. — The drapery of Jupiter was red, that of Neptune is ſuppoſed by Winkelman to have been ſea-green. The ſame colour alſo belonged to the Nereids and Nymphs. The mantle of Apollo was blue or violet. Bacchus was dreſſed in white. Martianus Capella aſſigns green to Cybele. Juno’s veſtments were ſky-blue, ſhe ſometimes had a white veil. Pallas was robed in a flame-coloured mantle. In a painting of Herculaneum, Venus is in flowing drapery of a golden yellow. Kings were arrayed in purple; prieſts in white; and conquerors ſometimes in ſea-green.</p><p>With reſpect to the head, women generally wore no covering but their hair; when they wiſhed to cover their head, they uſed the corner of their mantle. — Sometimes we meet with veils of a fine tranſparent texture. Old women wore a kind of bonnet upon their head, an example of which may be ſeen in a ſtatue in the Capitol, called the Praefica, but Winkelman thinks it is a ſtatue of Hecuba.</p><p>The covering of the feet conſiſted of ſhoes or ſandals. The ſandals were generally an inch thick, and compoſed of more than one ſole of cork. Thoſe of Pallas in Villa Albani has two ſoles, and other ſtatues had no leſs than five.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Winkelman</hi> has aſſigned four different ſtyles to this art. The <hi rend="italic">ancient</hi> ſtyle, which continued until the time of Phidias; the <hi rend="italic">grand</hi> ſtyle, formed by that celebrated ſtatuary; the <hi rend="italic">beautiful,</hi> introduced by Praxiteles, Apelles, and Lyſippus; and the <hi rend="italic">imitative</hi> ſtyle, practiſed by thoſe artiſts who copied the works of the ancient maſters.</p><p>The moſt authentic monuments of the ancient ſtyle are medals, containing an inſcription, which leads us back to very diſtant times. The writing is from right to left in the Hebrew manner; a uſage which was abandoned before the time of Herodotus. The ſtatue of Agamemnon at Elis, which was made by Ornatas, has an inſcription from right to left. This artiſan flouriſhed 50 years before Phidias; it is in the intervening period therefore between theſe two artiſts, that we are to look for the ceſſation of this practice. The ſtatues formed in the ancient ſtyle were neither diſtinguiſhed by beauty of ſhape nor by proportion, but bore a cloſe reſemblance to thoſe of the Egyptians and Etrurians<note anchored="true" n="8" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> This is a proof additional to thoſe that will be found in the articles to which we have referred, that the Greeks received the rudiments of the art of ſculpture from the nations to which they were confeſſedly indebted for the elements of ſcience.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi>; the eyes were long and flat; the ſection of the mouth not horizontal; the chin was pointed; the curls of the hair were ranged in little rings, and reſembled grains incloſed in a heap of raiſins. What was ſtill worſe, it was impoſſible by inſpecting the head to diſtinguiſh the ſex.</p><p>The characters of this ancient ſtyle were theſe: The deſigning was energetic, but harſh; it was animated, but without gracefulneſs; and the violence of the expreſſion deprived the whole figure of beauty.</p><p>The grand ſtyle was brought to perfection by Phidias, Polycletus, Scopas, Alcamenes, Myron, and other illuſtrious artiſts. It is probable, from ſome paſſages of ancient writers, that in this ſtyle were preſerved ſome characters of the ancient manner, ſuch as the ſtraight lines, the ſquares and angles. The ancient maſters, ſuch as Polycletus, being the legiſlators of proportions, lays Winkelman, and of conſequence thinking they had a right to diſtribute the meaſures and dimenſions of the parts of the human body, have undoubtedly ſacrificed ſome degree of the form of beauty to a grandeur which is harſh, in compariſon of the flowing contours and graceful forms of their ſucceſſors.— The moſt conſiderable monuments of the grand ſtyle are the ſtatues of Niobe and her daughters, and a fi-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0189.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0183"/>
gure of Pallas, to be ſeen in Villa Albani; which, however, muſt not be confounded with the ſtatue which is modelled according to the firſt ſtyle, and is alſo found in the ſame place. The head poſſeſſes all the characters of dignified beauty, at the ſame time exhibiting the rigidneſs of the ancient ſtyle. The face is defective in gracefulneſs; yet it is evident how eaſy it would have been to give the features more roundneſs and grace. The figures of Niobe and her daughters have not, in the opinion of Winkelman, that auſterity of appearance which marks the age of the ſtatue of Pallas. They are characterized by grandeur and ſimplicity: ſo ſimple are the forms, that they do not appear to be the tedious productions of art, but to have been created by an inſtantaneous effort of nature.</p><p>The third ſtyle was the graceful or beautiful. Lyſippus was perhaps the artiſt who introduced this ſtyle. Being more converſant than his predeceſſors with the ſweet, the pure, the flowing, and the beautiful lines of nature, he avoided the ſquare forms which the maſters of the ſecond ſtyle had too much employed. He was of opinion that the uſe of the art was rather to pleaſe than to aſtoniſh, and that the aim of the aitiſt ſhould be to raiſe admiration by giving delight. The artiſts who cultivated this ſtyle did not, however, neglect to ſtudy the ſublime works oſ their predeceſſors. They knew that grace is conſiſtent with the moſt dignified beauty, and that it poſſeſſes charms which muſt ever pleaſe: they knew alſo that theſe charms are enhanced by dignity. Grace is infuled into all the movements and attitudes of their ſtatues, and it appears in the delicate turns of the hair, and even in the adjuſting of the drapery. Every ſort of grace was well known to the ancients; and great as the ravages of time have been amongſt the works of art, ſpecimens are ſtill preſerved, in which can be diſtinguiſhed <hi rend="italic">dignified</hi> beauty, <hi rend="italic">attractive</hi> beauty, and a beauty <hi rend="italic">peculiar to infants. A</hi> ſpecimen of dignified beauty may be ſeen in the ſtatue of one of the muſes in the palace of Barberini at Rome; and in the garden of the pope, on the Quirinal is a ſtatue of another muſe, which affords a fine inſtance of attractive beauty. Winkelman ſays that the moſt excellent model of infant beauty which antiquity has tranſmitted to us is a ſatyr of a year old, which is preſerved, though a little mutilated, in Villa Albani.</p><p>The great reputation of Praxiteles and Apelles raiſed an ardent emulation in their ſucceſſors, who deſpairing to ſurpaſs ſuch illuſtrious maſters, were ſatisfied with imitating their works. But it is well known that a mere imitator is always inferior to the maſter whom he attempts to copy. When no original genius appears, the art muſt therefore decline.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Clay</hi> was the firſt material which was employed in ſtatuary. An inſtance of this may be ſeen in a figure of Alcamenes in bas-relief in Villa Albani. The ancients uſed their fingers, and eſpecially their nails, to render certain parts more delicate and lively: hence aroſe the phraſe <hi rend="italic">ad unguem factus homo,</hi> “an accompliſhed man.” It was the opinion of count Caylus that the ancients did not uſe models in forming their ſtatues. But to diſprove this, it is only neceſſary to mention an engraving on a ſtone in the cabinet of Stoſch, which repreſents Prometheus engraving the figure of a man, with a plummet is his hand to meaſure the proportions of his</p><p>model. The ancients as well as the moderns made works in plaſter; but no ſpecimens remain except ſome figures in bas-relief, of which the moſt beautiful were found at Baia.</p><p>The works made oſ ivory and ſilver were generally of a ſmall ſize. Sometimes, however, ſtatues of a prodigious ſize were formed of gold and ivory. The coloſſal Minerva of Phidias, which was compoſed of theſe materials, was 26 cubits high. It is indeed ſcarcely poſſible to believe that ſtatues of ſuch a ſize could entirely conſiſt oſ gold and ivory. The quantity of ivory neceſſary to a coloſſal ſtatue is beyond conception. M. de Pauw calculates that the ſtatue of Jupiter Olympus, which was 54 feet high, would confirme the teeth of 300 elephants.</p><p>The Greeks generally hewed their marble ſtatues out oſ one block, though they after worked the heads ſeparately, and ſometimes the arms. The heads of the famous group of Niobe and her daughters have been adapted to their bodies after being ſeparately finiſhed. It is proved by a large figure representing a river, which is preſerved in Villa Albani, that the ancients firſt hewed their ſtatues roughly before they attempted to finiſh any part. When the ſtatue had received its perfect figure, they next proceeded to poliſh it with pumice- ſtone, and again carefully retouched every part with the chiſel.</p><p>The ancients, when they employed porphyry, uſually made the head and extremities of marble. It is true, that at Venice there are four figures entirely compoſed oſ porphyry; but theſe are the productions of the Greeks oſ the middle age. They alſo made ſtatues of baſaltes and alabaſter.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Without</hi> expreſſion, geſture, and attitude, no figure can be beautiful, becauſe in theſe the graces always reſide It was for this reaſon that the graces are always repreſented as the companions of Venus.</p><p>The expreſſion of tranquillity was frequent in Grecian ſtatues, becauſe, according to Plato, that was conſidered as the middle ſtate of the ſoul between pleaſure and pain. Experience too ſhows that in general the moſt beautiful perſons are endowed with the ſweeteſt and moſt engaging manner. Without a ſedate\ tranquillity dignified beauty could not exiſt. It is in this tranquillity, therefore, that we muſt look for the complete diſplay of genius.</p><p>The moſt elevated ſpecies of tranquillity and repoſe was ſtudied in the figures of the gods. The father of the gods, and even inferior divinities, are repreſented without emotion or reſentment. It is thus that Homer paints Jupiter ſhaking Olympus by the motion of his hair and his eyebrows.</p><p>Shakes his ambroſial curls, and gives the nod,</p><p>The ſtamp of fate and ſanction of the god.</p><p>Jupiter is not always exhibited in this tranquil ſtate. In a bas-relief belonging to the Marquis Rondini he appears ſeated on an arm-chair with a melancholy aſρect, The Apollo of the Vatican repreſents the god in a fit of rage againſt the ſerpent Python, which he kills at a blow. The artiſt, adopting the opinion of the poets, has made the noſe the feat of anger, and the lips the feat of diſdain.</p><p>To expreſs the action of a hero, the Grecian ſculptors<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0190.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0184"/>
delineated the countenance of a noble virtuous character repreſſing his groans, and allowing no expression of pain to appear. In deſcribing the actions of a hero the poet has much more liberty than the artiſt. The poet can paint them ſuch as they were before men were taught to ſubdue their paſſions by the reſtraints of law, or the refined cuſtoms of ſocial life. But the artiſt, obliged to ſelect the moſt beautiful forms, is reduced to the neceſſity of giving ſuch an expreſſion of the paſſions as may not ſhock our feelings and diſguſt us with his production. The truth of theſe remarks will be acknowledged by thoſe who have ſeen two of the moſt beautiful monuments of antiquity; one of which repreſents the fear of death, the other the moſt violent pains and ſufferings. The daughters of Niobe, againſt whom Diana has diſcharged her fatal arrows, are exhibited in that ſtate of ſtupefaction which we imagine muſt take place when the certain proſpect of death deprives the ſoul of all ſenſibility. The fable preſents us an image ot that ſtupor which Eſchylus deſcribes as ſeizing the Niobe when they were transformed into a rock. The other monument referred to is the image of Laocoon, which exhibits the moſt agonizing pain that can affect the muſcles, the nerves, and the veins. The ſufferings of the body and the elevation of the ſoul are expreſſed in every member with equal energy, and form the moſt ſublime contraſt imaginable. Laocoon appears to ſuffer with ſuch fortitude, that, whilſt his lamentable ſituation pierces the heart, the whole figure fills us with an ambitious deſire of imitating his conſtancy and magnanimity in the pains and ſufferings that may fall to our lot.</p><p>Philoctetes is introduced by the poets ſhedding tears, uttering complaints, and rending the air with his groans and cries; but the artiſt exhibits him filent and bearing his pains with dignity. The Ajax of the celebrated painter Timomachus is not drawn in the act of deſtroying the ſheep which he took for the Grecian chiefs, but in the moments of reflection which ſucceeded that frenzy. So far did the Greeks carry their love of calmneſs and ſlow movements, that they thought a quick ſtep always announced ruſticity of manners. Demoſthenes reproaches Nicobulus for this very thing; and from the words he makes uſe of, it appears, that to ſpeak with inſolence and to walk haſtily were reckoned ſynonymous.</p><p>In the figures of women, the artiſts have conformed to the principle obſerved in all the ancient tragedies, and recommended by Ariſtotle, never to make women ſhow too much intrepidity or exceſſive cruelty. Conformable to this maxim, Clytemneſtra is repreſented at a little diſtance from the fatal ſpot, watching the murderer, but without taking any part with him. In a painting of Timomachus repreſenting Medea and her children, when Medea lifts up the dagger they ſmile in her face, and her fury is immediately melted into compaſſion for the innocent victims. In another repreſentation of the ſame ſubject, Medea appears heſitating and indeciſive. Guided by the ſame maxims, the artiſts of moſt refined taſte were careful to avoid all deformity, chooſing rather to recede from truth than from their accuſtomed reſpect for beauty, as may be ſeen in ſeveral figures of Hecuba. Sometimes, however, ſhe appears in the decrepitude of age, her face furrowed with wrinkles, and her breaſts hanging down.</p><p>Illuſtrious men, and thoſe inverted with offices of dignity, are repreſented with a noble aſſurance and firm aſpect. The ſtatues of the Roman emperors reſemble thoſe of heroes, and are far removed from every ſpecies of flattery, in the geſture, in the attitude, and action. They never appear with haughty looks, or with the ſplendor of royalty; no figure is ever ſeen preſenting any thing to them with bended knee, except captives; and none addreſſes them with an inclination of the head. In modern works too little attention has been paid to the ancient <hi rend="italic">coſlume.</hi> Winkelman mentions a bas-relief, which was lately executed at Rome for the fountain of Trevi, repreſenting an architect in the act of preſenting the plan of an aqueduct to Marcus Agrippa. The modern ſculptor, not content with giving a long beard to that illuſtrious Roman, contrary to all the ancient marble ſtatues as well as medals which remain, exhibits the architect on his knees.</p><p>In general, it was an eſtabliſhed principle to baniſh all violent paſſions from public monuments. This will ſerve as a deciſive mark to diſtinguiſh the true antique from ſuppoſititious works. A medal has been found exhibiting two Aſſyrians, a man and woman tearing their hair, with this inſcription, <hi rend="smallcaps">Assyria. et. pAlaestina. in. potest, P</hi>. R. REDAC. s. c. The forgery of this medal is manifeſt from the word <hi rend="italic">Palaestina,</hi> which is not to be found in any ancient Roman medal with a Latin inſcription. Beſides, the violent action of tearing the hair does not ſuit any ſymbolical figure. This extravagant ſtyle, which was called by the ancients <hi rend="italic">parenthyrsis</hi> has been imitated by moſt of the modern artiſts. Their figures reſemble comedians on the ancient theatres, who, in order to ſuit the diſtant ſpectators, put on painted maſks, employed exaggerated geſtures, and far overleaped the bounds of nature. This ſtyle has been reduced into a theory in a treatiſe on the paſſions compoſed by Le Brun. The deſigns which accompany that work exhibit the paſſions in the very higheſt degree, approaching even to frenzy: but theſe are calculated to vitiate the taſte, eſpecially of the young; for the ardour of youth prompts them rather to ſeize the extremity than the middle; and it will be difficult for that artiſt who has formed his taſte from ſuch empaſſioned models ever to acquire that noble ſimplicity and ſedate grandeur “which diſtinguiſhed the works of ancient taſte.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Proportion</hi> is the baſis of beauty, and there can be no beauty without it; on the contrary, proportion may exiſt where there is little beauty. Experience every day teaches us that knowledge is diſtinct from taſte; and proportion, therefore, which is founded on knowledge, may be ſtrictly obſerved in any figure, and yet the figure have no pretenſions to beauty. The ancients conſidering ideal beauty as the moſt perfect, have frequently employed it in preference to the beauty of nature.</p><p>The body conſiſts of three parts as well as the members. The three parts of the body are the trunk, the thighs, and the legs. The inferior part of the body are the thighs, the legs, and the feet. The arms alſo conſiſt of three parts. Theſe three parts muſt bear a certain proportion to the whole as well as to one another. In a well formed man the head and body muſt be proportioned to the thighs, the legs, and the feet, in the ſame manner as the thighs are proportioned to the legs and the feet, or the arms to the hands. The face<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0191.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0185"/>
alſo conſiſts of three parts, that is, three times the length of the noſe; but the head is not four times the length of the noſe, as ſome writers have aſſerted. From the place where the hair begins to the crown of the head are only three-fourths of the length of the noſe, or that part is to the noſe as 9 to 12.</p><p>It is probable that the Grecian, as well as Egyptian artiſts, have determined the great and ſmall proportions by fixed rules; that they have eſtabliſhed a poſitive meaſure for the dimenſions of length, breadth, and circumference. This ſuppoſition alone can enable us to account for the great conformity which we meet with in ancient ſtatues. Winkelman thinks that the foot was the meaſure which the ancients uſed in all their great dimenſions, and that it was by the length of it that they regulated the meaſure of their figures, by giving to them ſix times that length. This in fact is the length which Vitruvius aſſigns, <hi rend="italic">Pes vero altitudinis corporis ſextae,</hi> 1. 3. cap. 1. That celebrated antiquary thinks the foot is a more determinate meaſure than the head or the face, the parts from which modern painters and ſculptors too often take their proportions. This proportion of the foot to the body, which has appeared ſtrange and incomprehenſible to the learned Huetius, and has been entirely rejected by Perrault, is however founded upon experience. After meaſuring with great care a vaſt number of figures, Winkelman found this proportion obſerved not only in Egyptian ſtatues, but alſo in thoſe of Greece. This fact may be determined by an inſpection of thoſe ſtatues the feet of which are perfect. One may be fully convinced of it by examining ſome divine figures, in which the artiſts have made ſome parts beyond their natural dimenſions. In the Apollo Belvidere, which is a little more than ſeven heads high, the foot is three Roman inches longer than the head. The head of the Venus de Medicis is very ſmall, and the height of the ſtatue is ſeven heads and a half: the foot is three inches and a half longer than the head, or preciſely the ſixth part of the length of the whole ſtatue.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Practice</hi> of <hi rend="smallcaps">Sculpture.</hi></p><p>W <hi rend="smallcaps">e</hi> have been thus minute in our account of the Grecian ſculpture, becauſe it is the opinion of the ableſt critics that modern artiſts have been more or leſs eminent as they have ſtudied with the greater or leſs attention the models left us by that ingenious people: Winkelman goes ſo far as to contend that the muſt finiſhed works of the Grecian matters ought to be ſtudied in preference even to the works of nature. This appears to be paradoxical; but the reaſon aſſigned by the Abbe for his opinion is, that the faireſt lines of beauty are more eaſily diſcovered, and make a more ſtriking and powerful impreſſion, by their reunion in theſe ſublime copies, than when they are ſcattered far and wide in the original. Allowing, therefore, the ſtudy of nature the high degree of merit it ſo juſtly claims, it muſt nevertheleſs be granted, that it leads to true beauty by a much more tedious, laborious, and difficult path, than the ſtudy of the <hi rend="italic">antique,</hi> which preſents immediately to the artiſt’s view the object of his reſearches, and combines in a clear and ſtrong point of light the various rays of beauty that are diſperſed through the wide domain of nature.</p><p>As ſoon as the artiſt has laid this excellent founda</p><p>tion, acquired an intimate degree of familiarity with the beauties of the Grecian ſtatues, and formed his taſte after the admirable models they exhibit, he may then proceed with advantage and aſſurance to the imitation of nature. The ideas he has already formed of the perfection of nature, by obſerving her diſperſed beauties combined and collected in the compoſitions of the ancient artiſts, will enable him to acquire with facility, and to employ with advantage, the detached and partial ideas of beauty which will be exhibited to his view in a ſurvey of nature in her actual ſtate. When he diſcovers theſe partial beauties, he will be capable of combining them with thoſe perfect forms of beauty with which he is already acquainted. In a word, by having always preſent to his mind the noble models already mentioned, he will be in ſome meaſure his own oracle, and will draw rules from his own mind.</p><p>There are, however, two ways of imitating nature. In the one a ſingle object occupies the artiſt, who endeavours to repreſent it with preciſion and truth; in the other, certain lines and features are taken from a variety of objects, and combined and blended into one regular whole. All kinds of copies belong to the firſt kind of imitation; and productions of this kind muſt be executed neceſſarily in the Dutch manner, that is to ſay, with high finiſhing, and little or no invention. But the ſecond kind of imitation leads directly to the inveſtigation and diſcovery of true beauty, of that beauty whoſe idea is connate with the human mind, and is only to be found there in its higheſt perfection. This is the kind of imitation in which the Greeks excelled, and in which men of genius excite the young artiſts to excel after their example, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> by ſtudying nature as they did.</p><p>After having ſtudied in the productions of the Grecian maſters their choice and expreſſion of ſelect nature, their ſublime and graceful contours, their noble draperies, together with that ſedate grandeur and admirable ſimplicity that conſtitute their chief merit, the curious artiſts will do well to ſtudy the manual and mechanical part of their operations, as this is abſolutely neceſſary to the ſucceſsful imitation of their excellent manner.</p><p>It is certain that the ancients almoſt always formed their firſt models in wax: to this modern artiſts have ſubſtituted clay, or ſome ſuch compoſition: they prefer clay before wax in the carnations, on account of the yielding nature of the latter, and its flicking in ſome meaſure to every thing it touches. We muſt not, however, imagine from hence that the method of forming models of wet clay was either unknown or neglected among the Greeks; on the contrary, it was in Greece that models of this kind were invented. Their author was Dibutades of Sicyon; and it is well known that Arceſilas, the friend of Lucullus, obtained a higher degree of reputation by his clay models than by all his other productions. Indeed, if clay could be made to preſerve its original moiſture, it would undoubtedly be the fitteſt ſubſtance for the models of the ſculptor; but when it is placed either in the fire or left to dry imperceptibly in the air, its ſolid parts grow more compact, and the figure loſing thus a part of its dimenſions, is neceſſarily reduced to a ſmaller volume. This diminution would be of no conſequence did it equally affect the whole figure, ſo as to preſerve its proportions en-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0192.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0186"/>
tire. But this is not the caſe: for the ſmaller parts of the figure dry ſooner than the larger; and thus loſing more of their dimenſions in the ſame ſpace of time than the latter do, the ſymmetry and proportions of the figure inevitably ſuffer. This inconveniency does not take place in thoſe models that are made in wax. It is indeed extremely difficult, in the ordinary method of working the wax, to give it that degree of ſmoothneſs that is neceſſary to repreſent the ſoftneſs of the carnations or fleſhy parts of the body. This inconvenience may, however, be remedied, by forming the model firſt in clay, then moulding it in plaſter, and laſtly caſting it in wax. And, indeed, clay is ſeldom uſed but as a mould in which to caſt a figure of plaſter, ſtucco, or wax, to ſerve henceforth for a model by which the meaſures and proportions of the ſtatue are to be adjuſted. In making waxen models, it is common to put half a pound of colophony to a pound of wax; and ſome add turpentine, melting the whole with oil of olives.</p><p>So much for the firſt or preparatory ſteps in this procedure. It remains to conſider the manner of working the marble after the model ſo prepared; and the method here followed by the Greeks ſeems to have been extremely different from that which is generally obſerved by modern artiſts. In the ancient ſtatues we find the moſt ſtriking proofs of the freedom and boldneſs that accompanied each ſtroke of the chiſel, and which reſulted from the artiſt's being perfectly ſure of the accuracy of his idea, and the preciſion and ſteadineſs of his hand: the moſt minute parts of the figure carry theſe marks of aſſurance and freedom; no indication of timorouſneſs or diffidence appear; nothing that can induce us to fancy that the artiſt had occaſion to correct any of his ſtrokes. It is difficult to find, even in the ſecond-rate productions of the Grecian artiſts, any mark of a falſe ſtroke or a random touch. This firmneſs and preciſion of the Grecian chiſel were certainly derived from a more determined and perfect ſet of rules than thoſe which are obſerved in modern times.</p><p>The method generally obſerved by the modern ſculptor is as follows: Firſt, out of a great block of marble he ſaws another of the ſize required, which is performed with a ſmooth ſteel ſaw, without teeth, caſting water and ſand thereon from time to time; then he faſhions it, by taking off what is ſuperfluous with a ſteel point and a heavy hammer of ſoft iron; after this, bringing it near the meaſure required, he reduces it ſtill nearer with another finer point; he then uſes a flat cutting inſtrument, having notches in its edge; and then a chiſel to take off the ſcratches which the former has left; till, at length, taking raſps of different degrees of fineneſs, by degrees he brings his work into a condition for poliſhing.</p><p>After this, having ſtudied his model with all poſſible attention, he draws upon this model horizontal and perpendicular lines which interſect each other at right angles. He afterwards copies theſe lines upon his marble, as the painter makes uſe of ſuch tranſverſal lines to copy a picture, or to reduce it to a ſmaller ſize. Theſe traniverſal lines or ſquares, drawn in an equal number upon the marble and upon the model, in a manner proportioned to their reſpective dimenſions, exhibit accurate meaſures of the ſurfaces upon which the artiſt is to work; but cannot determine, with equal preciſion, the depths that arc proportioned to theſe ſurfaces.—</p><p>The ſculptor, indeed, may determine theſe depths by obſerving the relation they bear to his model; but as his eye is the only guide he has to follow in this eſtimate, he is always more or leſs expoſed to error, or at leaſt to doubt. He is never ſure that the cavities made by his chiſel are exact; a degree of uncertainty accompanies each ſtroke; nor can he be aſſured that it has carried away neither too much nor too little of his marble. It is equally difficult to determine, by ſuch lines as have already been mentioned, the external and internal contours of the figure, or to transfer them from the model to the marble. By the internal contour is underſtood that which is deſcribed by the parts which approach towards the centre, and which are not marked in a ſtriking manner.</p><p>It is farther to be noticed, that in a complicated and laborious work, which an artiſt cannot execute without aſſiſtance, he is often obliged to make uſe of foreign hands, that have not the talents or dexterity that are neceſſary to finiſh his plan. A ſingle ſtroke of the chiſel that goes too deep is a defect not to be repaired; and ſuch a ſtroke may eaſily happen, where the depths are ſo imperfectly determined. Defects of this kind are inevitable, if the ſculptor, in chipping his marble, begins by forming the depths that are requiſite in the figure he deſigns to repreſent. Nothing is more liable to error than this manner of proceeding. The cautious artiſt ought, on the contrary, to form theſe depths gradually, by little and little, with the utmoſt circumſpection and care; and the determining of them with preciſion ought to be conſidered as the laſt part of his work, and as the finiſhing touches of his chiſel.</p><p>The various inconveniences attending this method determined ſeveral eminent artiſts to look out for one that would be liable to leſs uncertainty, and productive of fewer errors. The French academy of painting at Rome hit upon a method of copying the ancient ſtatues, which ſome ſculptors have employed with ſucceſs, even in the figures which they finiſhed alter models in clay or wax. This method is as follows. The ſtatue that is to be copied is incloſed in a frame that fits it exactly. The upper part of this frame is divided into a certain number of equal parts, and to each of theſe parts a thread is fixed with a piece of lead at the end of it. Theſe threads, which hang freely, ſhow what parts of the ſtatue are moſt removed from the centre with much more perſpicuity and preciſion than the lines which are drawn upon its ſurface, and which paſs equally over the higher and hollow parts of the block: they alſo give the artiſt a tolerable rule to meaſure the more ſtriking variations of height and depth, and thus render him more bold and determined in the execution of his plan.</p><p>But even this method is not without its defects: for as it is impoſſible, by the means of a ſtraight line, to determine with preciſion the procedure of a curve, the artiſt has, in this method, no certain rule to guide him in his contours; and as often as the line which he is to deſcribe deviates from the direction of the plumb line, which is his main guide, he muſt neceſſarily find himſelf at a loſs, and be obliged to have recourſe to conjecture.</p><p>It is alſo evident, that this method affords no certain rule to determine exactly the proportion which the various parts of the figure ought to bear to each other, conſidered in their mutual relation and connections. The artiſt, indeed, endeavours to ſupply this defect by<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0193.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0187"/>
interſecting the plumb-lines by horizontal ones. This recourſe has, nevertheleſs, its inconveniences, ſince the ſquares formed by tranſverſal lines, that are at a diſtance from the figure (though they be exactly equal), yet repreſent the parts of the figure as greater or ſmaller, according as they are more or leſs removed from our poſition or point of view. But, notwithſtanding theſe inconveniences, the method now under conſideration is certainly the beſt that has hitherto been employed: it is</p><p>more practicable and ſure than any other we know, though it appears, from the remarks we have now been making, that it does not exhibit a ſure and univerſal criterion to a ſculptor who executes after a model.</p><p>To poliſh the ſtatue, or make the parts of it ſmooth and ſleek, they uſe pumice-ſtone and ſmelt; then tripoli; and when a ſtill greater luſtre is required, they uſe burnt ſtraw. For the <hi rend="italic">Casting of Statues,</hi> ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">FounderY</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">PLASTER oſ Paris.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>