<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0110.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0104-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCRIMZEOR</label>
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Scrimgeour</hi> (Henry), an eminent reſtorer of learning, was born at Dundee in the year 1506. He traced his deſcent from the ancient family of the Scrimzeours of Didupe, who obtained the office of hereditary ſtandard-bearers to the kings of Scotland in 1057.</p><p>At the grammar ſchool of Dundee our author acquired the Greek and Latin languages to an uncommon degree of perfection, and that in a ſhorter ſpace of time than many ſcholars before him. At the univerſity of St Andrew’s his ſucceſsful application to philoſophy gained him great applauſe. The next ſcene of his ſtudies was the univerſity of Paris, and their more particular object the civil law. Two of the moſt famous civilians of that age, Eguinard Baron and Francis Duaren<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> “Francis Duaren was the firſt of the French civilians who purged the chair in the civil law ſchools from the barbariſms of the Gloſſaries, in order to introduce the pure ſources of the ancient jurisprudence. As he did not deſire to ſhare that glory with any one, he looked with an envious eye on the reputation of his colleague Eguinard Baron, who alſo mixed good literature with the knowledge of the law. This jealouſy put him upon compoſing a work, wherein he endeavoured to leſſen the eſteem that people had for his colleague The maxim, " <hi rend="italic">Paſcitur in vivis livor; post ſata quieſcit,"</hi> was verified remarkably in him; for after the death of Baron, he ſhowed himſelf moſt zealous to eternize his memory, and was at the expence of a monument to the honour of the deceaſed.” From the Tranſlation of Bayle’s Dict. of 1710, p. 1143-4.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a),</hi> were then giving their lectures to crowded circles at Bourges. The fame of theſe profeſſors occaſioned his removal from Paris; and for a conſiderable time he proſecuted his ſtudies under their direction.</p><p>At Bourges he had an opportunity of becoming acquainted with the celebrated James Amiot, Greek profeſſor in that city, well known in the learned world by his tranſlation of Plutarch’s Lives, and diſtinguiſhed afterwards by his advancement to great honours in the church, and finally to the rank of cardinal.</p><p>Through the recommendation of this eminent perſon, Mr Scrimzeor engaged in the education of two young gentlemen of the name of Bucherel, whom he inſtructed in the belles lettres, and other branches of literature, calculated to accompliſh them for their ſtation in life.</p><p>This connection introduced him to Bernard Bornetel biſhop of Rennes, a perſon famed in the political world for having ſerved the ſtate in many honourable embaſſies. Accepting an invitation from this prelate to accompany him to Italy, Mr Scrimzeor greatly enlarged the ſphere of his literary acquaintance, by his converſation and connection with moſt of the diſtinguiſhed ſcholars of that country. The death of Francis Spira<note anchored="true" n="2" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> Francis Spira was a lawyer of great reputation at Cistadella in the Venetian ſtate, at the beginning of the 10th century. He had imbibed the principles of the Reformation, and was accuſed before John de la Caſa, archbiſhop of Benevento, the pope’s nuncio at Venice. He made ſome conceſſions, and aſked pardon of the papal miniſter for his errors. But the nuncio infilled upon a public recantation. Spira was exceedingly averſe to this meaſure; but at the preſſing inſtances of his wife and his friends, who repreſented to him that he muſt loſe his practice and ruin his affairs by perſiſting againſt it, he at laſt complied. Shortly after he fell into a deep melancholy, loſt his health, and was removed to Padua for the advice of phyſicians and divines; but his diſorders augmented. The recantation, which he ſaid he had made from cowardice and intereſt, filled his mind with continual horror and remorſe; inſomuch that he ſometimes imagined that he felt the torments of the damned. No means being found to reſtore either his health or his peace of mind, in 1548 he fell a victim to his miſerable ſituation. See Collyer’s Dict.—Spira.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> happened during his viſit at Padua; and as the character and conduct of this remarkable perſon at that time engaged the attention of the world, Mr Scrimzeor is ſaid to have collected memoirs of him in a publication entitled, “The Life of Francis Spira, by Henry of Scotland.” This performance, however, does not appear in the catalogue of his works.</p><p>After he had ſtored his mind with the literature of foreign countries, and ſatisfied his curioſity as a travel-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0111.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0105"/>
ler, it was his intention to have reviſited Scotland. He might without vanity have entertained hopes, that the various knowledge which he had treaſured would have won him a partial reception among his countrymen. An ambition of being uſefully diſtinguiſhed among them as a man of letters is juſtly fuppoſed the principal motive of his deſire to return: but the moſt ſanguine projects of life are often ſtrangely diverted by accident, or rather perhaps are inviſibly turned by Providence, from their purpoſed courſe. Mr Scrimzeor, on his journey homewards, was to paſs through Geneva. His fame had long forerun his footſteps. The ſyndics and other magiſtrates, upon his arrival, requeſted him to ſet up the profeſſion of philoſophy in that city; promiſing a compenſation ſuitable to the exertion of his talents. He accepted the propoſal, and eſtabliſhed the philoſophical chair.</p><p>After he had taught for ſome time at Geneva, a fire broke out in his neighbourhood, by which his houſe was confirmed, and he himſelf reduced to great diſtreſs. His late pupils, the Bucherels, had not forgotten their obligations to him, and ſent a conſiderable ſum of money to his relief.</p><p>At this time flouriſhed at Augſburg that famous mercantile family<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(c) They were ennobled by the emperor in 1510, under the title of Barons of Kirkberg and Weiſſenborn.</p></note> (c), the Fuggers. Ulric Fugger was then its repreſentative; a man poſſeſſed of prodigious wealth, paſſionately fond of literature, a great collector of books and manuſcripts, and a munificent patron of learned men. Being informed by means of his literary correſpondence of the misfortune which had befallen Mr Scrimzeor in the burning of his houſe, he immediately ſent him a preſſing invitation to accept an aſylum beneath his roof till his affairs could be re-eſtabliſhed. Mr Scrimzeor, gladly availing himſelf of ſuch a hoſpitable kindneſs, loſt no time in going to Germany.</p><p>Whilſt reſiding at Augſhurg with Mr Fugger, he was much employed in augmenting his patron’s library by vaſt collections, purchaſed from every corner of Europe. Manuſcripts of the Greek and Latin authors were then of ineſtimable value, and ſeem to have been more particularly the object of Mr Scrimzeor’s reſearches.</p><p>He did not lead a life of yawning indolence amidſt theſe treaſures, and, like a mere unfeeling collector, leave them unenjoyed. As librarian, he was not contented to act the part of a black eunuch to his literary ſeraglio. He ſeems to have forgotten that he was not its Grand Sultan, and accordingly ranged at will among ſurrounding beauties. He compoſed many works of great learning and ingenuity, whilſt he continued in a ſituation io peculiarly agreeable to the views and habits of a ſcholar.</p><p>When his manuſcripts were ready for the preſs, he was deſirous of returning to Geneva to print them. His patron, Fugger, recommended him for this purpoſe to the very learned Henry Stephens, one of his penſioners, and at that time one of the moſt celebrated printers in Europe.</p><p>Immediately on his arrival at Geneva, 1563, <hi rend="italic">he</hi> was earneſtly ſolicited by the magiſtrates to reſume the chair of philoſophy. Notwithſtanding his compliance, and in conſequence of it the dedication of much of his time to the ſtudy of phyſics, he, two years afterwards, inſtituted a courſe of lectures in the civil law, and had the honour of being its first founder and profeſſor at Geneva.</p><p>As ſoon as he was ſettled again in this city, he hoped, amidſt his other occupations, to proſecute the great object of his literary fame, the printing of his various works. But a ſuſpicion which Henry Stephens entertained, that it was his intention to ſet up a rival preſs at Geneva, occaſioned great diſſenſions between them. The reſult of the quarrel was, that the republic of letters, during Mr Scrimzeor’s life, was deprived of his valuable productions. They fell moſt of them at his death into the hands of Iſaac Caſaubon, who has been accuſed of publiſhing conſiderable portions of them as his own.</p><p>Some account of Mr Scrimzeor’s ſeveral performances will give an idea of his extenſive erudition.</p><p>He wrote critical and explanatory notes upon Athenæus’s<note anchored="true" n="4" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(d)</hi> Athenaeus was a grammarian of Naucrates in Egypt, and lived in the ſecond century. His Deipnoſophiſtae is a very curious and learned work, in 15 books. It is full of intereſting anecdotes and deſcriptions of ancient manners, and has preserved many relics of Grecian poetry not to be found elſewhere.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(d)</hi> <hi rend="italic">Deipnosophists,</hi> or Table-converſations of Philoſophers and Learned Men of Antiquity; having firſt collated ſeveral manuſcripts of his author. This work Caſaubon publiſhed at Leyden in 1600; but without diſtinguiſhing his own notes from thoſe of Scrimzeor.</p><p>A Commentary and Emendations of the Geography of Strabo were among our author’s literary remains. Theſe were publiſhed in Caſaubon’s Pariſian edition of Strabo, 1620. Henry Stephens, from an idea of juſtice due to Scrimzeor’s literary fame, notwithſtanding the violent animoſity which had ſubſiſted betwixt them, reproaches Caſaubon for adopting our Scottiſh critic’s lucubrations on Strabo without acknowledgment.— Dempſter aſſures us, that Scrimzeor, in his manuſcript letters, mentions his deſign of publiſhing this performance; whence, it is probable, that his work appeared to himſelf of conſiderable conſequence, and had taken up much of his attention. Although Caſaubon, in his ample notes exhibited at the foot of Strabo’s text, makes no confeſſion of having derived any thing from Scrimzeor, it muſt not be concealed, that in an epiſtle to Sir Peter Young, our critic’s nephew, through whom the Commentary and Emendations of Strabo came into his hands, Caſaubon acknowledges how very uſeful to him they might be made; for ſpeaking there of his intended edition of Strabo, he ſays, “It cannot be expreſſed how much aſſiſtance I may obtain from your notes of Scrimzeor.”</p><p>Edward Herriſon, a Scottiſh author, in his Commentary on Plutarch’s Book concerning the Inconſiſtencies of the Stoics, informs us, that Scrimzeor collated different manuſcripts of all the works of Plutarch. This undertaking appears ſufficient to have occupied half the life of an ordinary critic. Every one knows how voluminous an author was the philoſopher, the hiſtorian, and orator of Chaeronea. Whether our learned<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0112.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0106"/>
critic had meant to publiſh an edition of Plutarch’s works is not known; but ſuch an intention ſhould ſeem highly probable from this laborious enterpriſe of collating them.</p><p>The 10 books of Diogenes Laertius on the Lives, Opinions, and Apophthegms of the Plriloſophers, were collated from various manuſcripts by Scrimzeor. His corrected text of this author, with notes full of erudition, came alſo into Caſaubon’s poſſeſſion, and is ſuppoſed to have contributed much to the value of his edition of the Grecian Biographer, printed at Paris in 1593.</p><p>The works of Phornutus and Palaephatus were alſo among the collations of Mr Scrimzeor. To the latter of theſe authors he made ſuch conſiderable additions, that the work became partly his own. Theſe were two ancient authors who explain the fables of the heathen deities. The former wrote <hi rend="italic">De Natura Deorum, ſeu de Fabularum Poeticarum Allegoriis Speculatio,</hi> “On the Nature of the Gods, or the Allegorical Fictions of the Poets.” The latter entitled his book Απιςα, <hi rend="italic">Sive de falsis Narrationibus,</hi> “Things incredible, or concerning falſe Relations.” Theſe works were printed at Baſil, 1570; whether in Greek or Latin is uncertain. They have been publiſhed ſince in both languages.</p><p>The manuſcripts of them were for ſome time preſerved in the library of Sir Peter Young, after that of his uncle Scrimzeor, which was brought into Scotland in 1573, had been added to it. What became of this valuable bequeſt at the death of the former, is uncertain.</p><p>Our learned philologer left alſo behind him in manuſcript the orations of Demoſthenes, AEschines, and Cicero, and the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory of Euſebius, all carefully collated.</p><p>Among his literary remains was a collection of his Latin epiſtles. The men of letters in the 15th and 16th centuries ſeem to nave kept their republic, as it is called, more united and compact than it is at preſent, by an epiſtolary intercourſe in the Latin language, then the univerſal medium of literature and ſcience. This general ſpirit of communication could not but contribute greatly to the advancement of learning, as well as to the pleaſure, and, we may add, to the importance, of thoſe who were engaged in its purſuit. The intercourſe and union of enlightened men, able and diſpoſed to promote the happineſs of their fellow-creatures, cannot be too cloſe. From ſuch intellectual combination alone it is, that uniformity of religious, moral, and political principles, to its greateſt attainable degree, can ever be expected; or, in other words, the greateſt poſſible benefit derived from the cultivation of letters.</p><p>Of the many performances which had exerciſed his pen, it does not appear that any were immediately publiſhed by himſelf but his Tranſlation of Juſtinian’s Novels into Greek. This was printed at Paris in 1558, and again with Holoander’s Latin verſion at Antwerp in 1575. This work has been highly extolled, both for the purity of its language and the accuracy of its execution, and is likely, according to ſome reſpectable opinions, to hold its eſtimation as long as any uſe or memory of the civil law ſhall exiſt.</p><p>A Latin tranſlation of the <hi rend="italic">Basilica,</hi> or Baſilics, as they are called by our civilians, is the laſt we have to mention of this author’s performances. This is a collection of Roman Laws, which the eaſtern emperors Baſil and Leo who reigned in the fifth century, commanded to be tranſlated into Greek, and which preſerved their authority till the diſſolution of the eaſtern empire. The Baſilics comprehend the inſtitutes, digeſts, code, and novels, and ſome of the edicts of Juſtinian and other emperors. Of 60 original books, 41 only remain. Mr Scrimzeor collated them with various manuſcripts, probably before he commenced his tranſlation.</p><p>From the foregoing recital of the learned labours of this profound ſcholar and critic, it will be concluded, that almoſt the whole of his life, although long, was ſpent in his library, and that the biographer, having now terminated the catalogue of his writings, is probably not diſtant from the concluſion of his life. Different years have been aſſigned for the time of his death; but it appears moſt likely, from a compariſon of the different accounts of this event, that it happened very near the expiration of 1571, or at the beginning of the ſucceeding year, about the 66th year of his age. He died in the city of Geneva.</p><p>The characteriſtic features of Scrimzeor are few, but they are prominent and ſtriking, and remote poſterity may regard him with no inferior degree of reſpect. His induſtry and perſeverance in the purſuit of knowledge and erudition were equalled only by the exquiſite judgement which he diſplayed in his critical annotations and commentaries on the errors and obſcurities of ancient books and manuſcripts.</p><p>His acquiſitions in the Greek, Latin, and oriental languages, were reckoned much beyond thoſe of moſt of the profeſſed linguiſts of his time. The great Cujacius uſed to ſay, “That he never quitted Mr Scrimzeor’s converſation without having learned ſomething new.” But that which lent peculiar grace to ſuch ſuperiority, was the amiable modeſty which upon all occaſions was obſerved to accompany it. From the commendation given him by the illuſtrious civilian juſt mentioned, it will be concluded, that he did not brood, with a jealous reſerve, over unlocked treaſures of erudition; but that, conſcious of poſſeſſing ſtores too ample to be ſoon exhauſted, at the ſame time that he avoided an oſtentatious profuſion of them, he obliged and delighted his friends by a liberal communication. From the period at which he lived, conſidered with the nature and extent of his ſtudies, and his abilities in proſecuting them, he may deſervedly be ranked among thoſe eminent characters who have moſt ſucceſsfully contributed their exertions to the revival of letters in Europe.</p></div></body></text></TEI>