<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-s03-0639-01" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0665.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SELKIRK</label>, or Selcraig, Alexander (1676-1723), a sailor who is supposed to have been the prototype of Defoe’s “ Robinson Crusoe,” was the son of a shoemaker and tanner in Largo, Fifeshire, and was born in 1676. In his youth he displayed a quarrelsome and unruly disposition, and, having been summoned on 27th August 1695 before the kirk-session for his indecent behaviour in church, “ did not compear, being gone away to the seas.” At an early period he was engaged in buccaneer expeditions to the South Seas, and in 1703 joined the “Cinque Ports” galley as sailing master. The following year he had a dispute with the captain, and at his own request was in October put ashore on the island of Juan Fernandez, where, after a solitary residence of four years and four months, he was taken off by Captain Woods Rogers, commander of a privateer, who made him his mate and afterwards gave him the independent command of one of his prizes. He returned home in 1712; but in 1717 he eloped with a country girl and again went to sea. He died in 1723 while lieutenant on board the royal ship “ Weymouth.”</p><p>See Howell, <hi rend="italic">Life and Adventures of Alexander Selkirk,</hi> 1829. SELMA, a city of the United States, in Dallas county, Alabama, at the head of steamboat navigation of the Alabama river, occupies a plateau on the bluff of the right bank, 95 miles below Montgomery. It has cotton warehouses, railroad machine-shops, and various factories. The population was 6484 (3660 coloured) in 1870 and 7529 (4184 coloured) in 1880. Selma, which was strongly fortified during the Civil War and the seat of a Confederate arsenal (where 1800 men were employed), was captured by the Federal major-general J. H. Wilson on 2d April 1865.</p></div></body></text></TEI>