<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-s02-0470-01" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0492.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCOT</label>, Reginald (<hi rend="italic">c</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">. 1538-1599), was the son of Richard, third son of Sir John Scot of Scotshall, Smeeth (Kent), studied at Hart Hall in Oxford, and afterwards lived in studious retirement at Smeeth, dying in 1599. He was the author of a very remarkable book,</hi> <hi rend="italic">The Discoverie of Witchcraft,</hi> the object of which was to put an end to the cruel persecution of witches, by showing that “ there will be found among our <hi rend="italic">Witches</hi> only <hi rend="italic">two sorts</hi>; the <hi rend="italic">one sort</hi> being such by imputation, as so thought of by others (and</p><p>these are abused and not abusers), the <hi rend="italic">other</hi> by <hi rend="italic">acceptation,</hi> as being <hi rend="italic">willing</hi> so to be <hi rend="italic">accounted,</hi> and these be meer <hi rend="italic">Coseners."</hi> This thesis is worked out in sixteen books, with great learning and acuteness, in a spirit of righteous indignation against the witchmongers. Scot was far in advance of his time, and his book, of which the first edition appeared in 1584, was burned by order of King James I. The book is still interesting, not only as having anticipated Bekker by a century, but for the great mass of curious details as to every branch of so-called witchcraft which it contains. It also takes up natural magic and conjuring at considerable length (bk. xiii.), and contains an argument against “ alchymistry ” (bk. xiv.).</p><p>Scot also published in 1574 <hi rend="italic">A perfite Platforme of a Hoppe Garden</hi> (3d ed. 1578), which is noteworthy as having originated the cultivation of the hop in England. A second edition of the <hi rend="italic">Discoverie</hi> appeared in 1651 and a third in 1665 ; the latter contained nine new chapters, prefixed by an anonymous hand to bk. XV. of the <hi rend="italic">Discoverie,</hi> and the addition of a second book to the “Discourse concerning Angels and Spirits.”</p><p>See B. Nicholson’s <hi rend="italic">Scot's Discovery of Witchcraft,</hi> London, 1886.</p></div></body></text></TEI>