<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-s03-0726-05" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0752.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SHAD</label>, is the name given to certain migratory species of Herrings <hi rend="italic">(Clupea),</hi> which are distinguished from the herrings proper by the total absence of teeth in the jaws. Two species occur in Europe, much resembling each other,</p><p>—one commonly called Allis Shad (<hi rend="italic">Clupea alοsa),</hi> and the other known as Twaite Shad <hi rend="italic">(Clupea finta).</hi> Both are, like the majority of herrings, greenish on the back and bright silvery on the sides, but they are distinguished from the other European species of <hi rend="italic">Clupea</hi> by the presence of a large blackish blotch behind the gill-opening, which is succeeded by a series of several other similar spots along the middle of the side of the body. So closely allied are these two fishes that their distinctness can be proved only by an examination of the gill-apparatus, the allis shad having from sixty to eighty very fine and long gill-rakers along the concave edge of the first branchial arch, whilst the twaite shad possesses from twenty-one to twenty-seven stout and stiff gill rakers only. In their habits and geo</p><p>graphical distribution also the two shads are very similar. They inhabit the coasts of temperate Europe, the twaite shad being more numerous in the Mediterranean. While they are in salt water they live singly or in very small companies, but during May (the twaite shad some weeks later) they congregate, and in great numbers ascend large rivers, such as the Severn (and formerly the Thames), the Seine, the Rhine, the Nile, &amp;amp;c., in order to deposit their</p><pb xml:id="eb09-21-s03-0727" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0753.jp2"/><p>spawn,—sometimes traversing hundreds of miles, until their progress is arrested by some natural obstruction. A few weeks after they may be observed dropping down the river, lean and thoroughly exhausted, numbers floating dead on the surface, so that only a small proportion seem to regain the sea. Although millions of ova must be deposited by them in the upper reaches of a river, the fry does not seem to have been actually observed in fresh water, so that it seems probable that the young fish travel to the sea long before they have attained to any size.</p><p>On rivers in which these fishes make their periodical appearance they have become the object of a regular fishery, and their value increases in proportion to the distance from the sea at which they are caught. Thus they are much esteemed on the middle Rhine, where they are generally known as “Maifisch”; those caught on their return journey are worthless and uneatable. The allis shad is caught at a size from 15 to 24 inches, and is considered to be better flavoured than the twaite shad, which generally remains within smaller dimensions.</p><p>Other, but closely allied species, occur on the Atlantic coasts of North America, all surpassing the European species in importance as food-fishes and economic value, viz., the American Shad <hi rend="italic">(Clupea sapidissima),</hi> the Gaspereau or Ale-wife <hi rend="italic">(C. mattowocca),</hi> and the Menhaden <hi rend="italic">(C. menhaden).</hi> See Menhaden.</p></div></body></text></TEI>