<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0040-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0063.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>REGISTER</label> a record of facts, proceedings, acts, events, names,
                    &amp;c., entered regularly for reference in a volume kept for that purpose, also
                    the volume in which the entries are made. The Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                        >registre</hi> is taken from the Med. Lat. <hi rend="italic">registrum</hi>
                    for <hi rend="italic">registum,</hi> Late Lat. <hi rend="italic">regesta,</hi>
                    things recorded, hence list, catalogue, from <hi rend="italic">regerere,</hi> to
                    carry or bear back, to transcribe, enter on a roll. For the keeping of public
                    registers dealing with various subjects see Registration and the articles there
                    referred to, and for the records of baptisms, marriages and burials made by a
                    parish clergyman, see section <hi rend="italic">Parish Registers</hi> below. The
                    keeper of a register was, until the beginning of the 19th century, usually known
                    as a “ register,” but that title has in Great Britain now been superseded by “
                    registrar ”; it still survives in the Lord Clerk Register, an officer of state
                    in Scotland, nominally the official keeper of the national records, whose duties
                    are performed by the Deputy“ Clerk Register. In the United States the title is
                    still “ register.” The term “ register ” has also been applied to mechanical
                    contrivances for the automatic registration or recording of figures, &amp;c.
                    (see Cash Register), to a stop in an organ, to the compass of a voice or musical
                    instrument, and also to an apparatus for regulating the in- and outflow of air,
                    heat, steam, smoke or the like. Some of these instances of the application of
                    the term are apparently due to a confusion in etymology, with Lat. regere, to
                    rule, regulate.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Parish Registers</hi> were instituted in England by an
                    order of Thomas Cromwell, as vicegerent to Henry VIII., “ supreme hedd undre
                    Christ of the Church of Englande,” in September 1538. The idea appears to have
                    been of Spanish origin, Cardinal Ximenes having instituted, as archbishop of
                    Toledo, registers of baptisms in 1497. They included, under the above order,
                    baptisms, marriages and burials, which were to be recorded weekly. In 1597 it
                    was ordered by the Convocation of Canterbury that parchment books should be
                    provided for the registers and that transcripts should be made on parchment of
                    existing registers on paper, and this order was repeated in the 70th canon of
                    1603. The transcripts then made now usually represent the earliest registers. It
                    was further provided at both these dates that an annual transcript of the
                    register should be sent to the bishop for preservation in the diocesan registry,
                    which was the origin of the “ bishop’s transcripts.” The “ Directory for the
                    publique worship of God,” passed by parliament in 1645, provided for the date of
                    birth being also registered, and in August 1653, an Act of “ Bare-bones’
                    Parliament ” made a greater change, substituting civil “ parish registers ” <hi
                        rend="italic">(sic)</hi> for the clergy, and ordering them to record births,
                    banns, marriages and burials. The “ register ” was also to publish the banns and
                    a justice to perform the marriage. The register books were well kept under this
                    civil system, but at the Restoration the old system was resumed.</p>
               <p>A tax upon births, marriages and burials imposed in 1694 led to the clergy being
                    ordered to register all births, apart from baptisms, but the act soon expired
                    and births were not again registered till 1836. Lord Hardwicke's Marriage Act
                    (1754), by its rigid provisions, increased the registration of marriages by the
                    parochial clergy and prescribed a form of entry. In 1812 parish registers became
                    the subject of parliamentary enactment, owing to the discovery of their
                    deficiencies. Rose’s Act provided for their safer custody, for efficient
                    bishops, transcripts, and for uniformity of system. This act continued to
                    regulate the registers till their supersession for practical purposes, in 1837,
                    by civil registration under the act of 1836.</p>
               <p>In age, completeness and condition they vary much. A blue book on the subject
                    was published in 1833, but the returns it contains are often inaccurate. A few
                    begin even earlier than Cromwell’s order, the oldest being that of Tipton,
                    Staffs, (1513). Between 800 and 900, apparently, begin in 1538 or 1539. The
                    entries were originally made in Latin, but this usage died out early in the 17th
                    century: decay and the crabbed handwriting of the time render the earlier
                    registers extremely difficult to read. There is general agreement as to the
                    shocking neglect of these valuable records in the past, and the loss of volumes
                    appears to have continued even through the 19th century. Their custody is
                    legally vested in the parochial clergy and their wardens, but several proposals
                    have been made for their removal to central depositories. The fees for searching
                    them are determined by the act of 1836, which prescribes half a crown for each
                    certified extract, and sixpence a year for searching, with a shilling for the
                    first year.</p>
               <p>The condition of the “ bishops’ transcripts ” was, throughout, much worse than
                    that of the parish registers, there being no funds provided for their custody.
                    The report on Public Records in 1800 drew attention to their neglect, but, in
                    spite of the provisions in Rose’s Act (1812), little or nothing was done, and,
                    in spite of their importance as checking, and even sometimes supplementing
                    deficient parish registers, they remained “ unarranged, unindexed and
                    unconsultable.” Of recent years, however, some improvement has been made. It has
                    also been discovered that transcripts from “ peculiars ” exist in other than
                    episcopal registries.</p>
               <p>Outside the parochial registers, which alone were official in character, there
                    were, till 1754, irregular marriage registers, of which those of the Fleet
                    prison are the most famous, and also registers of private chapels in London.
                    Those of the Fleet and of Mayfair chapel were deposited with the
                    registrar-general, but not authenticated. The registers of dissenting chapels
                    remained unofficial till an act of 1840 validated a number which had been
                    authenticated, and was extended to many others in 1858. Useful information on
                    these registers, now mostly deposited with the registrar-general, will be found
                    in Sims’ <hi rend="italic">Manual,</hi> which also deals with those of private
                    chapels, of English settlements abroad preserved in London, and with English
                    Roman Catholic registers. These last, however, begin only under George II. and
                    are restricted to certain London chapels.</p>
               <p>The printing of parish registers has of late made much progress, but the field
                    is so vast that the rate is relatively slow. There is a Parish Register Society,
                    and a section of the Harleian Society engaged on the same work, as well as some
                    county societies and also one for Dublin. But</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0041" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0064.jp2"/>
               <p>so many have been issued privately or by individuals that reference should be
                    made to the lists in Marshall's <hi rend="italic">Genealogist's Guide</hi>
                    (1893) and Dr Cox’s <hi rend="italic">Parish Registers</hi> (1910), and even
                    this last is not perfect. The Huguenot Society has printed several registers of
                    the Protestant Refugees, and Mr Moens that of the London Dutch church. There are
                    also several registers of marriages alone now in print, such as that of St
                    Dunstan’s, Stepney, in 3 vols. Colonel Chester’s extensive MS. collection of
                    extracts from parish registers is now in the College of Arms, London, and the
                    parishes are indexed in Dr Marshall’s book. MS. extracts in the British Museum
                    are dealt with in Sims’ <hi rend="italic">Manual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Scotland registers of baptisms and marriages were instituted by the clergy in
                    1551, and burials were added by order of the Privy Council in 1616; but these
                    were very imperfectly kept, especially in rural parishes. Yet it was not till
                    1854 that civil registration was introduced, by act of parliament, in their
                    stead. Some 900 parish registers, beginning about 1563, have been deposited in
                    the Register House, Edinburgh, under acts of parliament which apply to all those
                    prior to 1819. Mr Hallen has printed the register of baptisms of Muthill
                    Episcopal Church.</p>
               <p>In Ireland, parish registers were confined to the now disestablished church,
                    which was that of a small minority, and were, as in Scotland, badly kept.
                    Although great inconvenience was caused by this system, civil registration of
                    marriages, when introduced in 1844, was only extended to Protestants, nor was it
                    till 1864 that universal civil registration was introduced, great difficulty
                    under the Old Age Pensions Act being now the result. No provision was made, as
                    in Scotland, for central custody of the registers, which, both Anglican and
                    Nonconformist, remain in their former repositories. Roman Catholic registers in
                    Ireland only began, apparently, to be kept in the 19th century.</p>
               <p>In France registers, but only of baptism, were first instituted in 1539. The
                    Council of Trent, however, made registers both of baptisms and of marriages a
                    law of the Catholic Church in 1563, and Louis XIV. imposed a tax on registered
                    baptislks and marriages in 1707.</p>
               <p>See Burn, <hi rend="italic">The History of Parish Registers</hi> (1829, 1862);
                    Sims, <hi rend="italic">Manual for the Genealogist</hi> (1856, 1888); Chester
                    Waters, <hi rend="italic">Parish Registers in England</hi> (1870, 1882, 1887);
                    Marshall, <hi rend="italic">Genealogist’s Guide</hi> (1893); A. M. Burke, <hi
                        rend="italic">Key to the Ancient Parish Registers</hi> (1908) ; J. C. Cox,
                        <hi rend="italic">Parish Registers of England</hi> (1910) ; W. D. Bruce, <hi
                        rend="italic">Account . . . of the Ecclesiastical Courts of Record</hi>
                    (1854) ; Bigland, <hi rend="italic">Observations on Parochial Registers</hi>
                    (1764); <hi rend="italic">Report of the Commissioners on the state of Registers
                        of Births, &amp;c.</hi> (1838); <hi rend="italic">Lists of N on-parochial
                        Registers and Records in the custody of the Registrar-General</hi> (1841);
                        <hi rend="italic">Report on Non-parochial Registers</hi> (1857); <hi
                        rend="italic">Detailed List of the old Parochial Registers of Scotland</hi>
                    (1872). (J. H. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
