<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0061-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0084.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RELIGION</label> . The origin of the Latin word <hi rend="italic"
                        >rZligio</hi> or <hi rend="italic">relligio</hi> has been the subject of
                    discussion since the time of Cicero. Two alternative derivations have been
                    given, viz. from <hi rend="italic">rëlëgere,</hi> to gather together, and <hi
                        rend="italic">rëligare,</hi> to bind back, fasten. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Relegere</hi> meant to gather together, collect, hence to go over a subject
                    again in thought, from <hi rend="italic">re</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >legere,</hi> to collect together, hence to read, collect at a glance. This
                    view is that given by Cicero <hi rend="italic">(Nat. Dear.</hi> ii. 28, 72). He
                    says: “ Qui omnia quae ad cultum deorum pertinerent diligenter retractarent et
                    tanquamrelegerent, sunt dicti religiosi ex relegendo,” “ men were called <hi
                        rend="sup">f</hi> religious ’ from <hi rend="italic">relegere,</hi> because
                    they reconsidered carefully and, as it were, went over again in thought all that
                    appertained to the worship of the gods.” He compares <hi rend="italic"
                        >elegantes</hi> from <hi rend="italic">eligere, diligentes</hi> from <hi
                        rend="italic">diligere,</hi> and continues, “ his enim in verbis omnibus
                    inest vis legendi eadem quae in religioso.” This view is supported by the form
                    of the word in the verse quoted by Gellius (iv. 9), “ religentem esse oportet,
                    rcligiosum nef as,” and by the use of the Greek <hi rend="italic">KKeyeiv,</hi>
                    to pay heed to, frequently with a negative, in the sense of the Latin <hi
                        rend="italic">negligere (nec-legere),</hi> cf. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Gcwp</hi> inrtp <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> ovk</hi></hi> <hi rend="italic">tikeyovres</hi> (Homer, <hi rend="italic">II.</hi> xvi. 388),
                    heeding not the visitation of the gods, or où <hi rend="italic">yàp</hi>
                    KuxXanres Atôs . . . <hi rend="italic">ä\eyovaw (Od.</hi> ix. 275). The
                    alternative derivation, from <hi rend="italic">religare,</hi> to fasten, bind,
                    is that adopted by Lactantius <hi rend="italic">(Inst.</hi> iv. 28), <hi
                        rend="sup">ii</hi> Vinculo pietatis obstricti, Dco rcligati sumus unde ipsa
                    religio nomen cepit. ” He quotes in support the line from Lucretius (i. 931), “
                    religionum nodis animos exsolvere.” Servius (on Virgil, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aen.</hi> viii. 349) and St Augustine <hi rend="italic">(Retract,</hi> i.
                    13) also take <hi rend="italic">religare</hi> as the source of the word. It is
                    one that has certainly coloured the meaning of the word, particularly in that
                    use which restricts</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0062" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0085.jp2"/>
               <p>it to the monastic life with its binding rules. It also has appealed to
                    Christian thought. Liddon <hi rend="italic">(Some Elements. of Religion,</hi>
                    Lecture I. 19) says: “ Lactantius may be wrong in his etymology, but he has
                    certainly seized the broad popular sense of the word when he connects it with
                    the idea of an obligation by which man is bound to an invisible God.” Archbishop
                    Trench <hi rend="italic">(Study of Words)</hi> supposed that when “ religion ”
                    became equivalent to the monastic life, and “ religious ” to a monk, the words
                    lost their original meaning, but the <hi rend="italic">Ancren Riwle <hi
                            rend="sub"> i</hi> ante</hi> 1225, and the <hi rend="italic">Cursor
                        Mundi</hi> use the words both in the general and the more particular sense
                    (see quotations in the <hi rend="italic">New English Dictionary),</hi> and both
                    meanings can be found in the <hi rend="italic">Imitatio Christi</hi> and in
                    Erasmus’s <hi rend="italic">Colloquia.</hi> (X.)</p>
               <p>The study of the forms of belief and worship belonging to different tribes,
                    nations or religious communities has only recently acquired a scientific
                    foundation. The Greek historians early directed their attention to the ideas and
                    customs of the peoples with whom they were brought into contact ; and Herodotus
                    has been called the “ first anthropologist of religion.” Theopompus described
                    the Persian dualism in the 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and when
                    Megasthenes was ambassador to the court of Chandragupta, 302 <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> he noted the religious usages of the middle
                    Ganges valley. The early Christian Fathers recorded many a valuable observation
                    of the Gentile faiths around them from varying points of view, sympathetic or
                    hostile; and Eusebius and Epiphanius, in the 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.,</hi> attributed to the librarian of Ptolemy Philadelphus the design
                    of collecting the sacred books of the Ethiopians, Indians, Persians, Elamites,
                    Babylonians, Assyrians, Romans, Phoenicians, Syrians and Greeks. The Mahommedan
                    BiruiiI (b. <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d,</hi> 973) compared the doctrines of the
                    Greeks, Christians, Jews, Manichaeans and Sufis with the philosophies and
                    religions of India. Akbar (1542-1605) gathered Brahmans and Zoroastrians, Jews,
                    Christians and Mahommedans at his court, and endeavoured to get translations of
                    their scriptures. In the next century the Persian author of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Dabistan</hi> exhibited the doctrines of no less than twelve
                    religions and their various sects. Meanwhile the scholars of the West had begun
                    to work. Thomas Hyde (1636-1703) studied the religion of the ancient Persians;
                    John Spencer (1630-1693) analysed the laws of the Hebrews; and Lord Herbert of
                    Cherbury <hi rend="italic">(De Religione Gentilium,</hi> 1645) endeavoured to
                    trace all religions back to five “ truly Catholic truths ” of primitive faith,
                    the first being the existence of God. The doctrine of a primeval revelation
                    survived in various forms for two centuries, and appeared as late as the <hi
                        rend="italic">Juventus Mundi</hi> of W. E. Gladstone (1868, p. 207 ff.).
                    David Hume, on the other hand, based his essay on <hi rend="italic">The Natural
                        History of Religion</hi> (1757) on the conception of the development of
                    human society from rude beginnings, and all modern study is frankly founded on
                    the general idea of Evolution. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="1"> This does not, of course, preclude the possibility
                        of degeneration in particular instances. </note>
               </p>
               <p>The materials at Hume’s command, however, were destined to vast and speedy
                    expansion. The Jesuit missionaries had already been at work in India and China,
                    and a brilliant band of English students, led by Sir William Jones ând H. T.
                    Colebrooke, began to make known the treasures of Sanskrit literature, which the
                    great scholars of Germany and France proceeded to develop. In Egypt the
                    discovery of the Rosetta stone placed the key to the hieroglyphics within
                    Western reach; and the decipherment of the cuneiform character enabled the
                    patient scholars of Europe tq recover the clues to the contents of the ancient
                    libraries of Babylonia and Assyria. With the aid of inscriptions the cults of
                    Greece and Rome have been largely reconstructed. Travellers and missionaries
                    reported the beliefs and usages of uncivilized tribes in every part of the
                    world, with the result that “ ethnography knows no race devoid of religion, but
                    only differences in the degree to which religious ideas have developed ”
                    (Ratzel, <hi rend="italic">History of Mankind,</hi> i. 40). Meanwhile philosophy
                    was at work on the problem of the religious consciousness. The great series of
                    ,German thinkers, Lessing, Herder, Kant, Hegel, Fichte, Schleiermacher and their</p>
               <p>successors, sought to explain religion by means of the phenomena of mind, and to
                    track it to its roots in the processes of thought and feeling. While ethnography
                    was gathering up the facts from every part of the globe, psychology began to
                    analyse the forms of belief, of action and emotion, to discover if possible the
                    key to the multitudinous variety which history revealed. From the historical and
                    linguistic side attention was first fixed upon the myth, and the publication of
                    the ancient hymns of the <hi rend="italic">Rig Veda</hi> led Max Müller to seek
                    in the common elements of Aryan thought for the secrets of primitive religion
                    (essay on <hi rend="italic">Comparative Mythology,</hi> 1856). The phenomena of
                    day and night, of sunshine and storm, and other aspects of nature, were invoked
                    by different interpreters to explain the conceptions of the gods, their origins
                    and their referions. Fresh materials were gathered at the same time out of
                    European folk-lore; the work begun by the brothers Grimm was continued by J. W.
                    E. Mannhardt, and a lower stratum of beliefs and rites began to emerge into view
                    beneath the poetic forms of the more developed mythologies. By such preliminary
                    labours the way was prepared for the new science of anthropology.</p>
               <p>Since the appearance of Dr E. B. Tylor’s classical treatise on <hi rend="italic"
                        >Primitive Culture</hi> (1871), the study of the origins of religion has
                    becn pursued with the utmost zeal. Comte had already described the primitive
                    form of the religious consciousness as that in which man conceives of all
                    external bodies as animated by a life analogous to his own <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Philos. Positive,</hi> tome v., 1841, p. 30). This has been since
                    designated as <hi rend="italic">polyzoism</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Panthelism</hi> or <hi rend="italic">panvitalism,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> Comte’s own term “
                        fetishism ” was most unfortunately, misleading (see Fetishism). Marett
                        proposed the termAnimatism,” <hi rend="italic">Folk Lore</hi> (1900), xi. p.
                        171. </note> and represents the obscure undifferentiated groundwork out of
                    which Tylor’s <hi rend="italic">Animism</hi> arises. Many are the clues by which
                    it has been sought to explain the secret of primitive religion. Hegel, before
                    the anthropological stage, found it in magic. Max Muller, building on philosophy
                    and mythology, affirmed that “ Religion consists in the perception of the
                    infinite under such manifestations as are able to influence the moral character
                    of man ” ( <hi rend="italic">Natural Religion,</hi> 1899, p. 188). Herbert
                    Spencer derived all religion from the worship of the dead <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Principles of Sociology,</hi> i.), like Grant Allen, and Lippert in
                    Germany. Mr Andrew Lang, on the other hand, supposes that belief in a supreme
                    being came first in order of evolution, but was afterwards thrust into the
                    background by belief in ghosts and lesser divinities <hi rend="italic">(Magic
                        and Religion,</hi> 1901, p. 224). <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="3"> See his treatise on <hi rend="italic">The Making of
                            Religion</hi> (1898), and Hartland’s article on “ The * High Gods ’ of
                        Australia,” <hi rend="italic">Folk Lore</hi> (1898), ix. p. 290. </note> Dr
                    Jevons finds the primitive form in totemism <hi rend="italic">(Introd. to the
                        History of Religion,</hi> 1896, chap. ix.). Mr J. G. Frazer regards religion
                    (see his definition quoted below) as superposed on an antecedent stage of magic.
                    In <hi rend="italic">The Tree of Life</hi> (1905), Mr E. Crawley interprets it
                    by the vital instinct, and connects its first manifestations with the processes
                    of the organic life. The VeteranWilhelm Wundt <hi rend="italic">(Mythus und
                        Religion,</hi> ii. 1906, p. 177) recurs to the primitive conceptions of the
                    soul as the source of all subsequent development. The origin of religion,
                    however, can never be determined archaeologically or historically; it must be
                    sought conjecturally through psychology. (J. E. C.)</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">A.</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Primitive ’Religion</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a point at which the History of Religion becomes in its predominant
                    aspect a History of Religions. The conditions that we describe by the
                    comprehensive term “ civilization ” occasion a specification and corresponding
                    differentiation of the life of societies; whence there result competing types of
                    culture, each instinct with the spirit of propagandism and, one might almost
                    say, of empire. It is an age of conscious selection as between ideal systems.
                    Instead of necessitating a wasteful and precarious elimination of inadequate
                    customs by the actual destruction of those who practise them—this being the
                    method of natural selection, which, like some Spanish Inquisition, abolishes the
                    heresÿ by wiping out the heretics one and all— progress now becomes possible
                    along the more direct and less</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0063" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0086.jp2"/>
               <p>painful path of conversion. The heretic, having developed powers of rational
                    choice, perceives his heresy, to wit, his want of adaptation to the moral
                    environment, and turning round embraces the new faith that is the passport to
                    survival.</p>
               <p>Far otherwise is it with man at the stage of savagery—the stage of petty groups
                    pursuing a self-centred life of inveterate custom, in an isolation almost as
                    complete as if they were marooned on separate atolls of the ocean. Progress, or
                    at all events change, does indeed take place, though very slowly, since the most
                    primitive savage we know of has his portion of human intelligence, looks after
                    and before, nay, in regard to the pressing needs of every day shows a quite
                    remarkable shrewdness and resource. Speaking generally, however, we must
                    pronounce him unprogressive, since, on the whole, unreflective in regard to his
                    ends. It is the price that must be paid for social discreteness and incoherency.
                    And the consequence of this atomism is not what a careless thinker might be led
                    to assume, extreme diversity, but, on the contrary, extreme homogeneity of
                    culture. It has been found unworkable, for instance, to classify the religions
                    of really primitive peoples under a plurality of heads, as becomes necessary the
                    moment that the presence of a distinctive basis of linked ideas testifies to the
                    individuality of this or that type of higher creed. Primitive religions are like
                    so many similar beads on a string; and the concern of the student of comparative
                    religion is at this stage mainly with the nature of the string, to wit, the
                    common conditions of soul and society that make, say, totemism, or taboo, very
                    much the same thing all the savage world over, when we seek to penetrate to its
                    essence.</p>
               <p>This fundamental homogeneity of primitive culture, however, must not be made the
                    excuse for a treatment at the hands of psychology and sociology that dispenses
                    with the study of details and trusts to an a priori method. By all means let
                    universal characterization be attempted—we are about to attempt one here, though
                    well aware of the difficulty in the present state of our knowledge—but they must
                    at least model themselves on the composite photograph rather than the
                    impressionist sketch. An enormous mass of material, mostly quite in the raw,
                    awaits reduction to order on the part of anthropological theorists, as yet a
                    small and ill-supported body of enthusiasts. Under these circumstances it would
                    be premature to expect agreement as to results. In regard to method, however,
                    there is little difference of opinion. Thus, whereas the popular writer abounds
                    in wide generalizations on the subject of primitive humanity, the expert has
                    hitherto for the most part deliberately restricted himself to departmental
                    investigations. Religion, for example, seems altogether too vast a theme for him
                    to embark on, and he usually prefers to deal with some single element or aspect.
                    Again, origins attract the <hi rend="italic">litterateur;</hi> he revels in
                    describing the transition from the pre-religious to the religious era. But the
                    expert, confining his attention to the known savage, finds him already
                    religious, nay, encumbered with religious survivals of all kinds; for him, then,
                    it suffices to describe things as they now are, or as they were in the
                    comparatively recent fore-time. Lastly, there are many who, being competent in
                    some other branch of science, but having small acquaintance with the scientific
                    study of human culture, are inclined to explain primitive ideas and institutions
                    from without, namely by reference to various external conditions of the mental
                    life of peoples, such as race, climate, food-supply and so on. The
                    anthropological expert, on the other hand, insists on making the primitive point
                    of view itself the be-all and end-all of his investigations. The inwardness of
                    savage religion—the meaning it has for those who practise it—constitutes its
                    essence and meaning likewise for him, who after all is a man and a brother, not
                    one who stands really outside.</p>
               <p>In what follows, then, we shall, indeed, venture to present a wholesale
                    appreciation of the religious idea as it is for primitive man in general; but
                    our account will respect the modern anthropological method that bids the student
                    keep closely to the actualities of the religious experience of savages, as it
                    can with reasonable accuracy be gathered from what they do and say.</p>
               <p>We have sought to render only the spirit of primitive religion, keeping clear
                    both of technicalities and of departmental investigations. These are left to the
                    separate articles bearing on the subject. There the reader will find the most
                    solid results of recent anthropological research. Here is he merely offered a
                    flimsy thread that, we hope, may guide him through the maze of facts, but alas!
                    is only too likely to break off short in his hand.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Definition of Primitive Religion.—</hi> In dealing with a
                    development of culture that has no immutable essence, but is intrinsically fluid
                    and changing, definition must consist either in a definition of type, which
                    indicates prevalence of relevant resemblance as between specimens more or less
                    divergent, or in exterior definition, which delimits the field of inquiry by
                    laying down within what extreme limits this divergence holds. Amongst the
                    numberless definitions of religion that have been suggested, those that have
                    been most frequently adopted for working purposes by anthropologists are Tylor’s
                    and Frazer’s. Dr E. B. Tylor in <hi rend="italic">Primitive Culture</hi> (i), i.
                    424, proposes as a “ minimum definition” of religion “ the belief in spiritual
                    beings.” Objections to this definition on the score of incompleteness are,
                    firstly, that, bcsides belief, practice must be reckoned with (since, as Dr W.
                    Robertson Smith has made clear in his <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the Religion
                        of the Semites,</hi> 18 sqq., ritual is in fact primary for primitive
                    religion, whilst dogma and myth are secondary); secondly, that the outlook of
                    such belief and practice is not exclusively towards the spiritual, unless this
                    term be widened until it mean next to nothing, but is likewise towards the
                    quasimaterial, as will be shown presently. The merit of this definition, on the
                    other hand, lies in its bilateral form, which calls attention to the need of
                    characterizing both the religious attitude and the religious object to which the
                    former has reference. The same form appears in Dr J. G. Frazer’s definition in
                        <hi rend="italic">The Golden Bough</hi> (2nd ed.), i. 63. He understands by
                    religion “ a propitiation or conciliation of powers superior to man which are
                    believed to direct and control the course of nature and of human life.” He goes
                    on to explain that by “ powers” he means “ conscious or personal agents.” It is
                    also to be noted that he is here definitely opposing religion to magic, which he
                    holds to be based on the (implicit) assumption “ that the course of nature is
                    determined, not by the passions or caprice of personal beings, but by the
                    operation of immutable laws acting mechanically.” His definition improves on
                    Tylor’s in so far as it makes worship integral to the religious attitude. By
                    regarding the object of religion as necessarily personal, however, he is led to
                    exclude much that the primitive man undoubtedly treats with awe and respect as
                    exerting a mystic effect on his life. Further, in maintaining that the powers
                    recognized by religion are always superior to man, he leaves unclassed a host of
                    practices that display a bargaining, or even a hectoring, spirit on the part of
                    those addressing them (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Prayer).</hi> Threatening or
                    beating a fetish cannot be brought under the head of magic, even if we adopt
                    Frazer’s principle <hi rend="italic">(op. cit.</hi> i. 64) that to constrain or
                    coerce a personal being is to treat him as an inanimate agent; for such a
                    principle is quite inapplicable to cases of mere terrorism, whilst it may be
                    doubted if it even renders the sense of the savage magician’s typical notion of
                    his <hi rend="italic">modus operandi,</hi> viz. as the bringing to bear of a
                    greater <hi rend="italic">mana</hi> or psychic influence (see below) on what has
                    less, and must therefore do as it is bidden. Such definitions, then, are to be
                    accepted; if at all, as definitions of type, selective designations of leading
                    but not strictly universal features. An encyclopaedic account, however, should
                    rest rather on an exterior definition which can serve as it were to pigeon-hole
                    the whole mass of significant facts. Such an exterior definition is suggested by
                    Mr E. Crawley in <hi rend="italic">The Tree of Life,</hi> 209, where he points
                    out that “ neither the Greek nor the Latin language has any comprehensive term
                    for religion, except in the one <hi rend="italic">lepa,</hi> and in the other
                        <hi rend="italic">sacra,</hi> words which are equivalent to ‘sacred.’ No
                    other term covers the whole of religious phenomena, and a survey of the complex
                    details of various worships results in showing that no other conception will
                    comprise the whole body of religious facts.” It may be added that we have here
                    no generalization imported from a</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0064" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0087.jp2"/>
               <p>higher level of culture, but an idea or blend of ideas familiar to primitive
                    thought. An important consequence of thus giving the study of primitive religion
                    the wide scope of a comparative hierology is that magic is no longer divorced
                    from religion, since the sacred will now be found to be coextensive with the
                    magico-religious, that largely undifferentiated plasm out of which religion and
                    magic slowly take separate shape as society comes more and more to contrast
                    legitimate with illicit modes of dealing with the sacred. We may define, then,
                    the religious object as the sacred, and the corresponding religious attitude as
                    consisting in such manifestation of feeling, thought and action in regard to the
                    sacred as is held to conduce to the welfare of the community or to that of
                    individuals considered as members of the community.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Aspects of the Nature of the Sacred.—</hi> To exhibit the
                    general character of the sacred as it exists for primitive religion it is
                    simplest to take stock of various aspects recognized by primitive thought as
                    expressed in language. If some, and not the least essential, of these aspects
                    are quasi-negative, it must be remembered that negations—witness the Unseen, the
                    Unknown, the Infinite of a more advanced theology—are well adapted to supply
                    that mystery on which the religious consciousness feeds with the slight basis of
                    conceptual support it needs, (i) <hi rend="italic">The sacred as the
                        forbidden.</hi> The primitive notion that perhaps comes nearest to our “
                    sacred,” whilst it immediately underlies the meanings of the Latin <hi
                        rend="italic">sacer</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sanctus,</hi> is that of a
                        <hi rend="italic">taboo,</hi> a Polynesian term for which equivalents can be
                    quoted from most savage vocabularies. The root idea seems to be that something
                    is marked off as to be shunned, with the added hint of a mystic sanction or
                    penalty enforcing the avoidance. Two derivative senses of a more positive import
                    call for special notice. On the one hand, since that which is tabooed is held to
                    punish the taboo-breaker by a sort of mystic infection, taboo comes to stand for
                    uncleanness and sin. On the other hand, since the isolation of the sacred, even
                    when originally conceived in the interest of the profane, may be interpreted as
                    self-protection on the part of the sacred as against defiling contact, taboo
                    takes on the connotation of ascetic virtue, purity, devotion, dignity and
                    blessedness. Primary and secondary senses of the term between them cover so much
                    ground that it is not surprising to find taboo used in Polynesia as a name for
                    the whole system of religion, founded as it largely is on prohibitions and
                    abstinences. (2) <hi rend="italic">The sacred as the mysterious.</hi> Another
                    quasinegative notion of more restricted distribution is that of the mysterious
                    or strange, as we have it expressed, for example, in the Siouan <hi
                        rend="italic">wakan,</hi> though possihly this is a derivative meaning.
                    Meanwhile, it is certain that what is strange, new or portentous is regularly
                    treated by all savages as sacred. (3) <hi rend="italic">The sacred as the
                        secret.</hi> The literal sense of the term <hi rend="italic">churinga,</hi>
                    applied by the Central Australians to their sacred objects, and likewise used
                    more abstractly to denote mystic power, as when a man is said to be “ full of
                        <hi rend="italic">Churinga,"</hi> is “ secret,” and is symptomatic of the
                    esotericism that is a striking mark of Australian, and indeed of all primitive,
                    religion, with its insistence on initiation, its exclusion of women, and its
                    strictly enforced reticence concerning traditional lore and proceedings. (4) <hi
                        rend="italic">The sacred as the potent.</hi> Passing on to positive
                    conceptions of the sacred, perhaps the most fundamental is that which identifies
                    the efficacy of sacredness with such mystic or magical power as is signified by
                    the <hi rend="italic">mana</hi> of the Pacific or <hi rend="italic">orenda</hi>
                    of the Hurons, terms for which analogies are forthcoming on all sides. Of <hi
                        rend="italic">mana</hi> Dr R. H. Codrington in <hi rend="italic">The
                        Melanesians,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>119 <hi rend="italic">n.,</hi> writes: “It essentially belongs to personal
                    beings to originate it, though it may act through the medium of water, or a
                    stone, or a bone. All Melanesian religion consists . . . in getting this <hi
                        rend="italic">mana</hi> for oneself, or getting it used for one’s benefit.”
                    E. Tregear’s <hi rend="italic">Maori-Polynesian Comparative Dictionary</hi>
                    shows how the word and its derivatives are used to express thought, memory,
                    emotion, desire, will—in short, psychic energy of all kinds. It also stands for
                    the vehicle of the magician’s energy—the spell; which would seem likewise to be
                    a meaning, perhaps the root-meaning, of <hi rend="italic">orenda</hi> (cf. J. N.
                    B. Hewitt, <hi rend="italic">American Anthropologist,</hi> N.S., iv. 40).
                    Whereas everything, perhaps, has some share of indwelling potency, whatever is
                    sacred manifests this potency in an extraordinary degree, as typically the
                    wonder-working leader of society, whose <hi rend="italic">mana</hi> consists in
                    his cunning and luck together. Altogether, in <hi rend="italic">mana</hi> we
                    have what is <hi rend="italic">par excellence</hi> the primitive religious idea
                    in its positive aspect, tahoo representing its negative side, since whatever has
                        <hi rend="italic">mana</hi> is taboo, and whatever is taboo has <hi
                        rend="italic">mana.</hi> (5) <hi rend="italic">The sacred as the
                        animate.</hi> The term “ animism,” which embodies Tylor’s classical theory
                    of primitive religion, is unfortunately somewhat ambiguous. If we take it
                    strictly to mean the belief in ghosts or spirits having the “ vaporous
                    materiality ” proper to the objects of dream or hallucination, it is certain
                    that the agency of such phantasms is not the sole cause to which all mystic
                    happenings are referred (though ghosts and spirits are everywhere believed in,
                    and appear to be endowed with greater predominance as religious synthesis
                    advances amongst primitive peoples). Thus there is good evidence to show that
                    many of the early gods, notahly those that are held to be especially well
                    disposed to man, are conceived rather in the shape of magnified nonnatural men
                    dwelling somewhere apart, such as the Mungan-ngaur of the Kurnai of S.E.
                    Australia (cf. A. Lang, <hi rend="italic">The Making of Religion <hi rend="sup">2</hi> , x.</hi> sqq.). Such anthropomorphism is with difficulty
                    reduced to the Tylorian animism. The term, however, will have to be used still
                    more vaguely, if it is to cover all attribution of personality, will or
                    vitality. This can be more simply brought under the notion of <hi rend="italic"
                        >mana.</hi> Meanwhile, since quasi-mechanical means are freely resorted to
                    in dealing with the sacred, as when a Maori chief snuffs up the sanctity his
                    fingers have acquired by touching his own sacred head that he may restore the
                    virtue to the part whence it was taken (R. Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Te Ika a
                        Maui,</hi> 165), or when uncleanness is removed as if it were a physical
                    secretion by washing, wiping and so forth, it is hard to say whether what we
                    should now call a “ material ” nature is not ascribed to the sacred, more
                    especially when its transmissihility after the manner of a contagion is the
                    trait that holds the attention. It is possible, however, that the savage always
                    distinguishes in a dim way between the material medium and the indwelling
                    principle of vital energy, examples of a pure fetishism, in the sense of the
                    cult of the purely material, recognized as such, being hard to find. (6) <hi
                        rend="italic">The sacred as the ancient.</hi> The prominence of the notion
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Alcheringa</hi> “ dreamtime,” or sacred past, in
                    Central Australian religion illustrates the essential connexion perceived by the
                    savage to lie between the sacred and the traditional. Ritualistic conservatism
                    may be instanced as a practical outcome of this feeling. Another development is
                    ancestor-worship, the organized cult of ancestors marking, however, a certain
                    stage of advance beyond the very primitive, though the dead are always sacred
                    and have <hi rend="italic">mana</hi> which the living may exploit for their own
                    advantage.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">The Activity of the Sacred.—</hi> The foregoing views of the
                    sacred, though starting from distinct conceptions, converge in a single complex
                    notion, as may be seen from the many-sided sense borne by such a term as <hi
                        rend="italic">wakan,</hi> which may stand not only for “ mystery,” but also
                    for “ power, sacred, ancient, grandeur, animate, immortal ” (W J McGee, <hi
                        rend="italic">15th Report of U. S. Bureau of Ethnology,</hi> 182). The
                    reason for this convergence is that, whereas there is found great difficulty in
                    characterizing the elusive nature of the sacred, its mode of manifesting itself
                    is recognized to be much the same in all its phases. Uniform characteristics are
                    the fecundity, ambiguity, relativity and transmissihility of its activity, (r)
                        <hi rend="italic">Fecundity.</hi> The mystic potency of the sabred is no
                    fixed quantity, but is big with possibilities of all sorts. The same sacred
                    person, object, act, will suffice for a variety of purposes. Even where a piece
                    of sympathetic magic appears to promise definite results, or when a departmental
                    god is recognized, there would seem to be room left for a more or less
                    indefinite expectancy. It must be re-membered that the meaning of a rite is for
                    the most part obscure</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0065" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0088.jp2"/>
               <p>to the participants, being overlaid by its traditional character, which but
                    guarantees a general efficacy. “ Blessings come, evils go,” may be said to be
                    the magico-religious formula implicit in all socially approved dealings with the
                    sacred, however specialized in semblance. (2) <hi rend="italic">Ambiguity.</hi>
                    Mystic potency, however, because of the very indefiniteness of its action, is a
                    two-edged sword. The sacred is not to be approached lightly. It will heal or
                    blast, according as it is handled with or without due circumspection. That which
                    is taboo, for instance, the person of the king, or woman’s blood, is poison or
                    medicine according as it is manipulated, being inherently just a potentiality
                    for wonder-working in any direction. Not but what primitive thought shows a
                    tendency to mark off a certain kind of mystic power as wholly bad by a special
                    name, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> the <hi rend="italic">arungquiltha of</hi>
                    Central Australia; and here, we may note, we come nearest to a conception of
                    magic as something other than religion, the trafficker in <hi rend="italic"
                        >arungquiltha</hi> being socially suspect, nay, liable to persecution, and
                    even death (as amongst the Arunta tribe, see Spencer and Gillen, <hi
                        rend="italic">Native Tribes of</hi> C. <hi rend="italic">Australia,</hi>
                    536), at the hands of his fellows. On the other hand, wholly beneficent powers
                    seem hardly to be recognized, unless we find them in beings such as Mungan-ngaur
                    (“ father-our” ), who derive an ethical character from their association with
                    the initiation ceremonies and the moral instruction given thereat (cf. Lang,
                    Z.c.). (3) <hi rend="italic">Relativity.</hi> So far we have tended to represent
                    the activity of the sacred as that of a universal force, somewhat in the style
                    of our “ electricity” or “ mind. ” It remains to add that this activity
                    manifests itself at numberless independent centres. These differ amongst
                    themselves in the degree of their energy. One spell is stronger than another,
                    one taboo more inviolable than another. Dr W. H. R. Rivers <hi rend="italic"
                        >{The Todas,</hi> 448) gives an interesting analysis of the grades of
                    sanctity apparent in Toda religion. The gods of the hill-tops come first. The
                    sacred buffaloes, their milk, their bells, the dairies and their vessels are on
                    a lower plane; whilst we may note that there are several grades amongst the
                    dairies, increase of sanctity going with elaboration of dairy ritual (cf. ibid.
                    232). Still lower is the dairyman, who is in no way divine, yet has sanctity as
                    one who maintains a condition of ceremonial purity. (4) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Transmissibility.</hi> If, however, this activity originates at certain
                    centres, it tends to spread therefrom in all directions. Dr F. B. Jevons (in <hi
                        rend="italic">An Introduction to the History of Religion,</hi> vii.)
                    distinguishes between “ things taboo,” which have the mystic contagion inherent
                    in them, and “ things tabooed,” to which the taboo-infection has been
                    transmitted. In the former class he places supernatural beings (including men
                    with <hi rend="italic">mana</hi> as well as ghosts and spirits), blood, new-born
                    children with their mothers, and corpses; which list might be considerably
                    extended, for instance, by the inclusion of natural portents, and animals and
                    plants such as are strikingly odd, dangerous or useful. Any one of these can
                    pass on its sacred quality to other persons and objects (as a corpse defiles the
                    mourner and his clothes), nay to actions, places and times as well (as a corpse
                    will likewise cause work to be tabooed, ground to be set apart, a holy season to
                    be observed). Such Iransmissibility is commonly explained by the association of
                    ideas, that becoming sacred which as it were reminds one of the sacred; though
                    it is important to add, firstly, that such association takes place under the
                    influence of a selective interest generated by strong religious feeling, and,
                    secondly, that this interest is primarily a collective product, being governed
                    by a social tradition which causes certain possibilities of ideal combination
                    alone to be realized, whilst it is the chief guarantee of the objectivity of
                    what they suggest.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">The Exploitation of the Sacred.</hi> A. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Methods.</hi> —It is hard to find terms general enough to cover dealings
                    with the sacred that range from the manipulation of an almost inanimate type of
                    power to intercourse modelled on that between man and man. Primitive religion,
                    however, resorts to either way of approach so indifferently as to prove that
                    there is little or no awareness of an inconsistency of attitude. The radical
                    contrast between mechanical and spiritual religion, though fundamental for
                    modern theology, is alien to the primitive point of view, and is therefore
                    inappropriate to the purposes of anthropological description. (1) <hi
                        rend="italic">Acquisition.</hi> Mystic power may be regarded as innate so
                    far as skill, luck or queerness are signs and conditions of its presence. On the
                    whole, however, savage society tends to regard it as something acquired, the
                    product of acts and abstinences having a traditional character for imparting
                    magico-religious virtue. An external symbol in the shape of a ceremony or
                    cult-object is of great assistance to the dim eye of primitive faith. Again, the
                    savage universe is no preserve of man, but is an open field wherein human and
                    non-human activities of all sorts compete on more or less equal terms, yet so
                    that a certain measure of predominance may be secured by a judicious combination
                    of forces. (2) <hi rend="italic">Concentration.</hi> Hence the magico-religious
                    society or individual practitioner piles ceremony on ceremony, name of power on
                    name of power, relic on relic, to consolidate the forces within reach and assume
                    direction thereof. The transmissihility of the sacred ensures the fusion of
                    powers drawn from all sources, however disparate. (3) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Induction.</hi> It is necessary, however, as it were to bring this force to
                    a head. This would appear to be the essential significance of sacrifice, where a
                    number of sacred operations and instruments are made to discharge their efficacy
                    into the victim as into a vat, so that a blessing-yielding, evil-neutralizing
                    force of highest attainable potency is obtained (see H. Hubert and M. Mauss, “
                    Essai sur la nature et la fonction du sacrifice” in <hi rend="italic">L' Année
                        sociologique,</hi> ii.). (4) <hi rend="italic">Renovation.</hi> An important
                        <hi rend="italic">motif</hi> in magico-religious ritual, which may not have
                    been without effect on the development of sacrifice, is, as Dr Frazer’s main
                    thesis in <hi rend="italic">The Golden Boiigh</hi> asserts, the imparting of
                    reproductive energy to animals, plants and man himself, its cessation being
                    suggested by such phenomena as old age and the fall of the year. To concentrate,
                    induce and renovate are, however, but aspects of one process of acquisition by
                    the transfusion of a transmissible energy. (5) <hi rend="italic">Demission.</hi>
                    Hubert and Mauss show in their penetrating analysis of sacrifice that after the
                    rite has been brought to its culminating point there follows as a pendant a
                    ceremony of re-entry into ordinary life, the idea of which is preserved in the
                    Christian formula <hi rend="italic">Ite, missa est.</hi> (6) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Insidation.</hi> Such deposition of sacredness is but an aspect of the
                    wider method that causes a ring-fence to be erected round the sacred to ward off
                    casual trespassers at once in their own interest and to prevent contamination.
                    We see here a natural outcome of religious awe supported by the spirit of
                    esotericism, and by a sense of the need for an expert handling of that which is
                    so potent for good or ill. (7) <hi rend="italic">Direction.</hi> This last
                    consideration brings to notice the fact that throughout magico-religious
                    practice of all kinds the human operator retains a certain control over the
                    issue. In the numberless transitions that, whilst connecting, separate the spell
                    and the prayer we observe as the accompaniment of every mood from extreme
                    imperiousness to extreme humility an abiding will and desire to help the action
                    out. Even “ Thy will be done ” preserves the echo of a direction, and, needless
                    to say, this is hardly a form of primitive address. At the bottom is the vague
                    feeling that it is man’s own self-directed mysterious energy that is at work,
                    however much it needs to be reinforced from without. Meanwhile, tradition
                    strictly prescribes the ways and means of such reinforcement, so that religion
                    becomes largely a matter of sacred lore; and the expert director of rites, who
                    is likewise usually at this stage the leader of society, comes more and more to
                    be needed as an intermediary between the lay portion of the community and the
                    sacred powers.</p>
               <p>B. <hi rend="italic">Results.</hi> —Hitherto our account of primitive religion
                    has had to move on somewhat abstract lines. His religion is, however, anything
                    but an abstraction to the savage, and stands rather for the whole of his
                    concrete life so far as it is penetrated by a spirit of earnest endeavour. The
                    end and result of primitive religion is, in a word, the consecration of life,
                    the stimulation of the will to live and to do. This bracing of the vital feeling
                    takes place by means of imaginative appeal to the great forces man perceives
                    stirring within him and about him, such appeal proving effective doubtless by
                    reason of the psychological law that to conceive strongly is</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0066" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0089.jp2"/>
               <p>to imitate. Meanwhile, that there shall be no clashing of conceptions to inhibit
                    the tendency of the idea of an acquired “ grace ” to realize itself in action,
                    is secured by the complete unanimity of public opinion, dominated as it is by an
                    inveterate custom. To appreciate the consecrating effect of religion on
                    primitive life we have only to look to the <hi rend="italic">churinga</hi>
                    -worship of the Central Australians (as described by Spencer and Gillen in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Native Tribes of Central Australia</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">The Northern Tribes of Central Australia).</hi> Contact with
                    these repositories of mystic'influence “makes them glad” <hi rend="italic">(Nat.
                        Tr.</hi> 165); it likewise makes them “ good,” so that they are no longer
                    greedy or selfish <hi rend="italic">(North. Tr.</hi> 266); it endows them with
                    second sight (ibid.); it gives them confidence and success in war <hi
                        rend="italic">(Nat. Tr.</hi> 135); in fact, there is no end to its
                    “strengthening” effects (ibid. <hi rend="italic">n</hi> .). Or, again, we may
                    note the earnestness and solemnity that characterize all their sacred
                    ceremonies. The inwardness of primitive religion is, however, non-existent for
                    those who observe it as uninitiated strangers; whilst, again, it evaporates as
                    soon as native custom breaks down under pressure of civilization, when only
                    fragments of meaningless superstition survive: wherefore do travesties of
                    primitive religion abound.</p>
               <p>It remains to consider shortly the consecration of life in relation to
                    particular categories and departments. (1) <hi rend="italic">Education.</hi>
                    Almost every tribe has its initiation ceremonies, and in many tribes adult life
                    may almost be described as a continuous initiation. The object of these rites is
                    primarily to impart mystic virtue to the novice, such virtue, in the eyes of the
                    primitive man, being always something more than social usefulness, amounting as
                    it does to a share in the tribal luck by means of association with all it holds
                    sacred. Incidentally the candidate is trained to perform his duties as a
                    tribesman, but religion presides over the course, demanding earnest endeavour of
                    an impressionable age. (2) <hi rend="italic">Government.</hi> Where society is
                    most primitive it is most democratic, as in Australia, and magico-religious
                    powers are possessed by the whole body of fully initiated males, age, however,
                    conferring increase of sacred lore and consequently of authority; whilst even at
                    this stage the experts tend to form an inner circle of rulers. The man with <hi
                        rend="italic">mana</hi> is bound to come to the top, both because his gifts
                    give him a start and because his success is taken as a sign that he has the
                    gift. A decisive “ moment ” in the evolution of chief ship is the recognition of
                    hereditary <hi rend="italic">mana,</hi> bound up as this is with the handing on
                    of ceremonies and cult-objects. Invested, as society grows more complex, with a
                    sanctity increasingly superior to that of the layman,, the priest-king becomes
                    the representative of the community as repository of its luck, whilst, as
                    controller of all sacred forces that bear thereon, he is, as Dr Frazer puts it,
                    “ dynamical centre of the universe” (The <hi rend="italic">Golden Bough</hi>
                    (2nd ed.), i. 233). Only when the holy man’s duty to preserve his holiness binds
                    him hand and foot in a network of taboos does his temporal power tend to devolve
                    on a deputy. (3) <hi rend="italic">Pood-supply.</hi> In accordance with the
                    principle of Renovation (see above), the root-idea of the application of
                    religion to economics is not the extorting of boons from an unwilling nature,
                    but rather the stimulation of the sources of life, so that all beings alike may
                    increase and multiply. (4) <hi rend="italic">Food-taking.</hi> Meanwhile, the
                    primitive meal is always more or less of a sacrament, and there are many
                    food-taboos, the significance of which is, however, not so much that certain
                    foods are unclean and poisonous as that they are of special virtue and must be
                    partaken of solemnly and with circumspection. (s) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kinship.</hi> It is hard to say whether the unit of primitive society is
                    the tribe or the group of kinsmen. Both are forms of union that are consolidated
                    by means of religious usages. Thus in Australia the initiation ceremonies,
                    concerned as they partly are with marriage, always an affair between the
                    kin-groups, are tribal, whilst the totemic rites are the prime concern of the
                    members of the totem clans. The significance of a common name and a common blood
                    is immensely enhanced by its association with mystic rights and duties, and the
                    pulse of brotherhood beats faster. (6) <hi rend="italic">The Family.</hi> Side
                    by side with the kin there is-always found the domestic group, but the latter
                    institution develops fully only as the former weakens, so that the one comes
                    largely to inherit the functions of the other, whilst the tribe too in its turn
                    hands over certain interests. Thus in process of time birth-rites,
                    marriage-rites, funeral-rites, not to mention subordinate ceremonies such as
                    those of name-giving and food-taking, become domestic sacraments. (7) <hi
                        rend="italic">Sex.</hi> Woman, for certain physiological reasons, is always
                    for primitive peoples hedged round with sanctity, whilst man does all he can to
                    inspire awe of his powers in woman by keeping religion largely in his own hands.
                    Theresult, so far as woman is concerned, is that, in company with those males
                    who are endowed with sacredness in a more than ordinary degree, she tends as a
                    sex to lose in freedom as much as she gains in respect. (8) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Personality.</hi> Every one has his modicum of innate <hi rend="italic"
                        >mana,</hi> or at least may develop it in himself by communicating with
                    powers that can be brought into answering relation by the proper means.
                    Nagualism, or the acquisition of a mystic guardian, is a widely distributed
                    custom, the essence of which probably consists in the procuring of a personal
                    name having potency. The exceptional man is recognized as having <hi
                        rend="italic">mana</hi> in a special degree, and a belief thus held at once
                    by others and by himself is bound to stimulate his individuality. The primitive
                    community is not so custom-bound that personality has no chance to make itself
                    felt, and the leader of men possessed of an inner fund of inspiration is the
                    wonderworker who encourages all forms of social advance.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Psychology of the Primitive Attitude towards the Sacred.—</hi>
                    We are on firmer ground when simply describing the phenomena of primitive
                    religion than when seeking to account for these in terms of natural law—in
                    whatever sense the conception of natural law be applicable to the facts of the
                    mental life of man. One thing is certain, namely, that savages stand on
                    virtually one footing with the civilized as regards the type of explanation
                    appropriate to their beliefs and practices. We have no right to refer to “
                    instincts ” in the case of primitive man, any more at any rate than we have in
                    our own case. A child of civilized parents brought up from the first amongst
                    savages is a savage, neither more nor less. Though race may count for something
                    in the matter of mental endowment—and at least it would seem to involve
                    differences in weight of brain—it clearly counts for much less than does <hi
                        rend="italic">milieu,</hi> to wit, that social environment of ideas and
                    institutions which depends so largely for its effectiveness on mechanical means
                    of tradition, such as the art of writing. The outstanding feature of the mental
                    life of savages known to psychologists as “ primitive credulity ” is doubtless
                    chiefly due to sheer want of diversity of suggestiveness in their intellectual
                    surroundings. Their notions stick fast because there are no competing notions to
                    dislodge them. Society suffers a sort of perpetual obsession, and remains
                    self-hypnotized as it were within a magic circle of traditional views. A rigid
                    orthodoxy is sustained by means of purblind imitation assisted by no little
                    persecution. Such changes as occur come about, not in consequence of a new
                    direction taken by conscious policy, but rather in the way that fashions in
                    dress alter amongst ourselves, by subconscious, hardly purposive drifting. The
                    crowd rather than the individual is the thinking unit. A proof is the mysterious
                    rapid extinction of savages the moment that their group-life is broken up; they
                    are individually so many lost sheep, without self-reliance or initiative. And
                    the thinking power of a crowd—that is, a mob, not a deliberative assembly— is of
                    a very low order, emotion of a “ panicky ” type driving it hither and thither
                    like a rudderless ship. However, as the students of mob-psychology have shown,
                    every crowd tends to have its <hi rend="italic">meneur,</hi> its mob-leader, the
                    man who sets the cheering or starts the running-away. So too, then, with the
                    primitive society. Grossly ignorant of all that falls outside “ the daily round,
                    the common task,” they are full of panicky fears in regard to this unknown, and
                    the primary attitude of society towards it is sheer avoidance, taboo. But the
                    mysterious has another face. To the mob the mob-leader is mysterious in his
                    power of bringing luck and salvation; to himself also he is a wonder, since he
                    wills, and lo ! things happen accordingly. He has</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0067" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0090.jp2"/>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">mana,</hi> power, and by means of this <hi rend="italic"
                        >mana,</hi> felt inwardly by himself, acknowledged by his fellows, he stems
                    the social impulse to run away from a mystery. Not without nervous dread—
                    witness the special taboo to which the leader of society is subject —he draws
                    near and strives to constrain, conciliate or cajole the awful forces with which
                    the life of the group is set about. He enters the Holy of Holies; the rest
                    remain without, and are more than half afraid of their mediator. In short, from
                    the standpoint of lay society, the manipulator of the sacred is himself sacred,
                    and shares in all the associations of sacred-ness. An anthropomorphism which is
                    specifically a “ mago-morphism ” renders the sacred powers increasingly one with
                    the governing element in society, and religion assumes an ethico-political
                    character, whilst correspondingly authority and law are invested with a deeper
                    meaning.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">The Abuse of the Sacred.—</hi> Lest our picture of primitive
                    religion appear too brightly coloured, a word must be said on the perversions to
                    which the exploitation of the sacred is liable. Envy, malice and
                    uncharitableness are found in primitive society, as elsewhere, and in their
                    behoof the mystic forces are not unfrequently unloosed by those who know how to
                    do so. To use the sacred to the detriment of the community, as does, for
                    instance, the expert who casts a spell, or utters a prayer, to his neighbour’s
                    hurt, is what primitive society understands by magic (cf. <hi rend="italic"
                        >arungquiltha,</hi> above), and anthropology has no business to attach any
                    other meaning to the word if it undertakes to interpret the primitive point of
                    view. On the other hand, if those in authority perpetrate in the name of what
                    their society holds sacred, and therefore with its full approval, acts that to
                    the modern mind are cruel, silly or revolting, it is bad science and bad ethics
                    to speak of vice and degradation, unless it can be shown that the community in
                    which these things occur is thereby brought nearer to elimination in the
                    struggle for existence. As a matter of fact, the earlier and more democratic
                    types of primitive society, uncontaminated by our civilization, do not present
                    many features to which the modern conscience can take exception, but display
                    rather the edifying spectacle of religious brotherhoods encouraging themselves
                    by mystical communion to common effort. With the evolution of rank, however, and
                    the concentration of magico-religious power in the hands of certain orders,
                    there is less solidarity and more individualism, or at all events more
                    opportunity for sectional interests to be pursued at other than critical times;
                    whereupon fraud and violence are apt to infect religion. Indeed, as the history
                    of the higher religions shows, religion tends in the end to break away from
                    secular government with its aristocratic traditions, and to revert to the more
                    democratic spirit of the primitive age, having by now obtained a clearer
                    consciousness of its purpose, yet nevertheless clinging to the inveterate forms
                    of human ritual as still adequate to symbolize the consecration of life—the
                    quickening of the will to face life earnestly.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.</hi> —The number of works dealing with
                    primitive religion is endless. The English reader who is more or less new to the
                    subject is recommended to begin with E. B. Tylor, <hi rend="italic">Primitive
                        Culture</hi> (4th ed., Lond. 1903), and then to proceed to J. G. Frazer, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Golden Bough</hi> (2nd ed., Lond. 1900). The latter
                    author’s <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the Early History of the Kingship</hi>
                    (Lond. 1905) may also be consulted. Only second in importance to the above are
                    W. Robertson Smith, <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the Religion of the
                        Semites</hi> (2nd ed., Lond. 1904); A. Lang, <hi rend="italic">Myth, Ritual
                        and Religion</hi> (2nd ed., Lond. 1899), and <hi rend="italic">Magic and
                        Religion</hi> (Lond. 1902); E. S. Hartland, <hi rend="italic">The Legend of
                        Perseus</hi> (Lond. 1894-1896) ; F. B. Jevons, <hi rend="italic">An
                        Introduction to the History of Religion</hi> (2nd ed., 1902); E. Crawley,
                        <hi rend="italic">The Mystic Rose</hi> (Lond. 1902), and <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Tree of Life</hi> (Lond. 1905). The two last-mentioned works perhaps
                    most nearly represent the views taken in the text, which are also developed by
                    the present writer in “ Pre-An i mist ic Religion,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Folk-Lore</hi> xi. (1900), “ From Spell to Prayer,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >Folk-Lore,</hi> xv. (1904), and “ Is Taboo a Negative Magic?” <hi
                        rend="italic">Anthropological Essays presented to E. B. Tylor</hi> (1907);
                    L. R. Farnell, <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Religion</hi> (1905), follows
                    similar lineç. The present writer owes something to Goblet d’Alviella, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hibbert Lectures</hi> (Lond. 1891), and more to H. Hubert and
                    M. Mauss, “ Essai sur la nature et la fonction du sacrifice,” <hi rend="italic"
                        >L'Année sociologique,</hi> ii. ; and “ Esquisse d’une théorie générale de
                    la magie,” ibid. vii. If the reader wish to keep pace with the output of
                    literature on this vast subject, he will find <hi rend="italic">L’Année
                        sociologique</hi> (1896 onwards) a wonderfully complete bibliographical
                    guide.</p>
               <p>Side by side with works of general theory, first-hand authorities should be
                    freely used. To make a selection from these is not easy, but the following at
                    least are very important: R. H. Codrington, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Melanesians</hi> (Oxford, 1891); W. B. Spencer and F. J. Gillen, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Native Tribes of Central Australia</hi> (Lond. 1899); <hi
                        rend="italic">The Northern Tribes of Central Australia</hi> (Lond. 1904); A.
                    W. Howitt, <hi rend="italic">The Native Tribes of South-Eastern Australia</hi>
                    (Lond. 1904); A. C. Haddon, <hi rend="italic">Reports of the Cambridge
                        Anthropological Expedition to Torres Straits</hi> (Cambridge, 1904, vol.
                    v.); A. B. Ellis, <hi rend="italic">The Tshi-Speaking Peoples OftheGotd
                        Coast</hi> (Lond. 1897); <hi rend="italic">The Ewe-Speaking Peoples of the
                        Slave Coast</hi> (Lond. 1890); <hi rend="italic">The Yoruba-Speaking Peoples
                        of the Slave Coast</hi> (Lond. 189a); Miss M. H. Kingsley, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Travels in West Africa</hi> (Lond. 1898), and <hi rend="italic">West
                        African Studies</hi> (Lond. 1899); A. C. Hollis, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Masai</hi> (1905); W. Crooke, <hi rend="italic">The North-West Provinces of
                        India</hi> (Lond. 1897;; W. H. R. Rivers, <hi rend="italic">The Todas</hi>
                    (1906). An immense amount of valuable evidence is to be obtained in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Reports of the Bureau of Ethnology,</hi> Smithsonian
                    Institution, Washington. See Nos. 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, n, 13, 14, 15, 16, 18, 19,
                    21, 22, 23, and specially J. O. Dorsey, <hi rend="italic">A Study of Siouan
                        Cults,</hi> in No. 11 ; A. C. Fletcher, <hi rend="italic">The Hako,</hi> in
                    No. 22; and M. C. Stevenson, <hi rend="italic">The Zuhi Indians,</hi> in No. 23.
                    Though dealing, primarily with a more advanced culture, T. J. M. de Groot, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Religious System of China</hi> (1892-1901), will be found
                    to throw much light on primitive ideas. Finally let it be repeated that there is
                    offered here no more than an introductory course of standard authorities
                    suitable for the English reader. (R. R. M.)</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">B.</hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">The Higher Religions</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Various phenomena associated with the religions of the lower culture will be
                    found discussed in the articles on <hi rend="smallcaps">Animism; Fetishism;
                        Magic; Mythology; Prayer; Ritual; Sacrifice;</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Totemism.</hi> In this article religions .are treated from the point of
                    view of morphology, and no attempt can be made in the allotted limits to connect
                    them with the phases of ritual, sociological or ethical development. See the
                    separate articles on each religious system, and the separate headings for
                    different forms of ritual.</p>
               <p>i. <hi rend="italic">Developments of Animism.—</hi> Animism is not, indeed,
                    itself a religion; it is Tatheraprimitive kind of philosophy which provides the
                    intellectual form for the interpretation alike of Man and of Nature. It implies
                    that the first great step has been taken for distinguishing between the material
                    objects—whether the conscious body, or the rocks, trees and animals—and the
                    powers that act in or through them. The Zufiis of New Mexico, U.S.A., supposed “
                    the sun, moon and stars, the sky, earth and sea, in all their phenomena and
                    elements, and all inanimate objects as well as plants, animals and men, to
                    belong to one great system of all-conscious and interrelated life, in which the
                    degrees of relationship seem to be determined largely, if not wholly, by the
                    degrees of resemblance.” <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="4"> F. H. Cushing, on “ Zuni Fetiches” in <hi rend="italic">Second Annual
                            Report of the Bureau of Ethnology,</hi> Washington, 1883, p. 9. </note>
                    If the earliest conception is that of an obscure undifferentiated animation (
                        <hi rend="italic">panvitalism),</hi> the analysis of the human person into
                    body and spirit with the corresponding doctrine of “ object-souls ” ( <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.</hi> the <hi rend="italic">tornait</hi> or “ invisible
                    rulers ” of every object among the Eskimo) <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="5"> Dr. Franz Boas, in the <hi rend="italic">Sixth
                            Annual Report of the Bureau of Ethnology,</hi> 1888, p. 591. </note>
                    constitutes an important development. Matter is no longer animated or
                    self-acting; it is subject to the will of an agent which can enter or quit it,
                    perhaps at its own pleasure, perhaps at the compulsion of another. The
                    transition has usually been effected ages before the higher religions come into
                    view; but it has left innumerable traces in language and custom. Thus the Vedic
                    hymns, which exhibit the deposits of so many stages of thought, are founded
                    ultimately on the conception of the animation of nature. The objects of the
                    visible world are themselves mighty to hurt or help. The springs and rivers, the
                    wind, the sun, fire, the Earth-Mother, the Sky-Father, are all active powers.
                    The animals, domesticated or wild, like the horse or cow, the guardian dog, the
                    bird of omen, naturally share the same life, and are approached with the same
                    invocation. The sacred energy is also discerned in the ritual implements, in the
                    stones for squeezing the soma-juice, and the sacrificial post to which animals
                    were bound; nay, it was even recognized in fabricated products like the plough
                    (the “ tearer ” or “ divider ”), the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0068" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0091.jp2"/>
               <p>tvar-car, the drum, quiver, bow and axe. The Earth-Mother and Sky-Father are to
                    be found again and again in religions, at various stages of development, as
                    co-ordinating conceptions which comprehend the universe. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="6"> The Japanese name is <hi
                            rend="italic">Ame-tsuchi,</hi> “ heaven and earth,” a translation of the
                        Chinese <hi rend="italic">ten-chi,</hi> Aston, <hi rend="italic">Shinto</hi>
                        (1905), p. 35. </note> Sometimes one is more prominent, sometimes the other.
                    In many cases the Sky has been already resolved into the visible firmament and
                    its lord and owner, like the Yoruban Olorun or the Finnic Ukko. The consort of
                    Ukko is <hi rend="italic">Maan-emö, “</hi> mother of the earth,” or <hi
                        rend="italic">maan ernanicl, “</hi> mistress of the earth.” But the rare
                    expression <hi rend="italic">maan-emd,</hi> “ Mother-earth,” still used in the
                    ancient lays, <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="7">
                        Castrén, <hi rend="italic">Finnische Mythologie,</hi> p. 86. </note> points
                    to the older type of belief in the animation of the productive soil. So the
                    Peruvians designated the Earth as Pacha-mama, “ mother of (all) things.” In
                    Egypt the relation was curiously reversed; the earth-god Keb was the husband of
                    Nut, the sky, represented sometimes as a woman, overarching the earth and
                    supported on hands and feet, sometimes as a gigantic cow, upheld on the
                    outstretched hands of Shu, the atmosphere. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="8"> Erman, <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Egyptian
                            Religion</hi> (1907), pp. 8, 12. </note> When earth and sky were still
                    unseparated, Shu thrust himself between them and raised Nut to the heights. So
                    in the New Zealand myth, Rangi and Papa, Sky and Earth, who once clave together
                    in the darkness, were rent asunder by the forest-god Tane-mahuta, who forced up
                    the sky far above him. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="9"> Sir George Grey, <hi rend="italic">Polynesian Mythology</hi> (1855),
                        pp. 1-4. </note> The most elaborate presentment of this mode of thought is
                    to be seen in the organized animism of the ancient state religion of China,
                    where the supreme power is lodged in the living sky (Tien). <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="10"> The English “Heaven”
                        has acquired a quasi-personal mean </note> Tien was originally the actual
                    firmament; In the <hi rend="italic">Shi-King</hi> it is addressed in prayer as “
                    great and wide,” as “ vast and distant ”; it is even “ blue ” (Pt. II. V. 6, s).
                    So it is the ancestor of all things; and Heaven and Earth are the father and
                    mother of the world. From the imperial point of view the sky bore the name of
                    Ti, “ ruler,” or Shang Ti, “ supreme ruler ” (emperor) ; and later commentators
                    readily took advantage of this to discriminate between the visible expanse and
                    the indwelling spirit, producing a kind of Theism. But the older conception
                    still holds its own. “ Why ” (says Edkins, <hi rend="italic">Religion in
                        China,</hi> 95), “ they have been often asked, should you speak of those
                    things which are dead matter, fashioned from nothing by the hand of God, as
                    living beings? And why not? they have replied. The Sky pours down rain and
                    sunshine; the Earth produces corn and grass. We see them in perpetual movement,
                    and we therefore say that they are living.” <hi rend="italic">Tien Ti, Fu
                        Mu,</hi> “ Heaven and Earth, Father and Mother,” are conjoined in common
                    speech, and are the supreme objects of imperial worship. The great altar to
                    Heaven, round in shape like the circuit of the sky, and white as the symbol of
                    the light principle (Yang), stands in the southern suburb of Peking in the
                    direction of light and heat. The altar to the Earth is dark and square, on the
                    north side of the city, the region of <hi rend="italic">yin,</hi> the principle
                    of cold and gloom. Associated with the Sky are tablets to the sun and moon, the
                    seven stars of the Great Bear, the five planets, the twenty-eight
                    constellations, and all the stars of heaven; tablets to clouds, rain, wind and
                    thunder being placed next to that of the moon. With the Earth are grouped the
                    tablets to the five lofty Mountains, the three Hills of perpetual peace and the
                    four Seas, the five celebrated Mountains and the four great Rivers. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="11"> Blodget, on “ The
                        Chinese Worship of Heaven and Earth,” <hi rend="italic">Joum. of the
                            American Oriental Society,</hi> xx. p. 58 ff. </note> The ancient ritual
                        <hi rend="italic">(Chow Li)</hi> carefully graded the right of sacrifice
                    from the viceroys of provinces down to the humblest district-superintendent who
                    offered to the spirits of his district, the hills, lakes and grains. With these
                    spirits ranged in feudal order in two vast groups beneath Heaven and Earth is
                    associated a third class, those of human beings. They are designated by the same
                    name, <hi rend="italic">shin</hi> ; and they are in-</p>
               <p>extricably mingled with the operations of nature. So in the Vedic hymns the
                    departed “ Fathers ” inhabit the three zones-of earth, air and sky; they are
                    invoked with the streams and mountains of this lower earth, as well as with the
                    dawns and the sky itself; even cosmic functions are ascribed to them; and they
                    adorn the heaven with stars. The Chinese conception of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Shin</hi> under the name of <hi rend="italic">Shin-to</hi> (Chinese <hi
                        rend="italic">tao)</hi> or “ spirits’-way ” profoundly influenced Japanese
                    thought from the 6th century <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> onwards; and the
                    great Shinto revival of the 18th century brought the doctrine again into
                    prominence. The Japanese <hi rend="italic">Kami</hi> are the “ higher ” powers,
                    the <hi rend="italic">superi,</hi> conceived as acting through nature on the one
                    hand and government on the other. Just as the emperor is <hi rend="italic"
                        >kami,</hi> and provincial officers of rank, so also mountains, rivers, the
                    sea, thunder, winds, and even animals like the tiger, wolf or fox, are all <hi
                        rend="italic">kami.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="12"> So the epithet <hi
                            rend="italic">'el</hi> might be applied in Hebrew to men of might, to
                        lofty cedars, or mountains of unusual height, as well as to the Supreme
                        Being. </note> The spirits of the dead also become <hi rend="italic"
                        >kami,</hi> of varying character and position; some reside in the temples
                    built in their honour; some hover near their tombs; but they are constantly
                    active, mingling in the vast multitude of agencies which makes every event in
                    the universe, in the language of Motowori (1730-1801), the act of the Kami. They
                    direct the changing seasons, the wind and the rain; and the good and bad
                    fortunes of individuals, families and states are due to them. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="13"> See E. M. Satow, “
                        Revival of Pure Shinto,” <hi rend="italic">Trans.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">As.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Soc. of Japan,</hi> vol. iii. pt. 1 (1875), Appendix, p.
                        26. </note> Everywhere from birth to death the entire life of man is
                    encompassed and guided by the Kami, which are sometimes reckoned at 8,000,000 in
                    number.</p>
               <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Transition to Polytheism.—</hi> In such ways does the
                    Poly-daemonism of early faith survive in the modern practice of religion. The
                    process of enrolling the spirits of the dead in the ranks of what may be more or
                    less definitely called “ gods ” may be seen in the popular usages of India at
                    the present day, or traced in the pages of the <hi rend="italic">Peking
                        Gazette</hi> under the direction of the Board of Rites, one of the most
                    ancient branches of Chinese administration. Whether the higher polytheisms were
                    produced in this fashion out of the cultus of the dead, may, however, be
                    doubted. Many influences have doubtless contributed, and different races have
                    followed different lines of development. No definite succession like the series
                    of ages marked by the use of stone, bronze and iron can be clearly marked. But
                    there must always have been some correspondence between the stages of social
                    advance (or, in certain cases, of degeneration) and the religious interpretation
                    of the world. The formation of clans and tribes, the transitions from the
                    hunting to the pastoral life, and from the pastoral to the agricultural—the
                    struggle with forest and swamp, the clearings for settlement, the protection of
                    the dwelling-place, the safety of flocks and herds, the production of corn,—the
                    migration of peoples, the founding of colonies, the processes of conquest,
                    fusion, and political union—have all reacted on the elaboration of the higher
                    polytheisms, before bards and poets, priesthoods and theological speculators,
                    began to systematize and regulate the relations of the gods. Certain phases of
                    thought may be more or less clearly indicated ; certain elements of race, of
                    local condition, of foreign contact, may be distinguished with more or less
                    historic probability; but no single key can explain all the wide diversity of
                    phenomena. Broadly speaking it may be said that a distinction may be drawn
                    between “ spirits ”” and “ gods,” but it is a distinction of degree rather than
                    of kind, obvious enough at the upper end, yet shading off into manifold
                    varieties of resemblance in the lower forms. Some writers, only recognize
                    friendly agencies as gods; but destructive powers like the volcano, or the lords
                    of the underworld, cannot be regarded as the protectors of the life of man, yet
                    they seem in many mythologies to attain the full personalised stature of gods
                    with definite names. Early Greek religion recognized a class of gods of Aversion
                    and Riddance, αποτρόπαιοι and άποπομπαιοι. Neither the spirit nor the god is
                    conceived as</p>
               <p>ing, and is usually employed as its equivalent, but, like the Jewish use <hi
                        rend="italic">(e.g.</hi> Luke xv. 18), tends to carry too definite religious
                    associations with it.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0069" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0092.jp2"/>
               <p>immaterial. They can take food, though the crudest form of this belief soon
                    passes into the more refined notion that they consume the impalpable essence of
                    the meals provided for them. The ancient Indian ritual for the sacrifice to the
                    Fathers required the officiating priest to turn away with bated breath that he
                    might not see the spirits engaged upon the rice-balls laid out for them. The
                    elastic impalpable stuff of the spirit-body is apparently capable of compression
                    or expansion, just as Athena can transform herself into a bird. The spirits can
                    pass swiftly through the air or the water; they can enter the stone or the tree,
                    the animal or the man. The spirit-land of the Ibo on the Lower Niger had its
                    rivers, forests or hills, its towns and roads, as upon earth: <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="14"> Leonard, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Lower Niger and its Tribes</hi> (1906), p. 186.
                    </note> the spirits of the Mordvinian mythology, created by Chkai, not only
                    resembled men, they even possessed the faculty of reproduction by
                    multiplication. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="15">
                        Mainof, “ Les Restes de la mythologie mordvine,” <hi rend="italic">Journal
                            de la Soc. Finno-Ougrienne,</hi> v. (1889), p. 102. </note> The Finns
                    ascribed a <hi rend="italic">haltia</hi> or genius to each object, which could,
                    however, guard other individuals of the same species. This is the beginning of
                    the species-god, and implies a step of thought comparable to the production in
                    language of general terms. These protecting spirits were free beings, having
                    form and shape, hut not individualized; while above them rose the higher deities
                    like the forest-god Tapio and his maiden Hillervo, protectress of herds, or Ahto
                    the water-god who gradually took the place of Vesi, the actual element
                    originally conceived as itself divine, and ruled over the spirits of lakes and
                    rivers, wells and springs. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="16"> Castrén, <hi rend="italic">Finn. Mythol.</hi> pp. 92 ff., 72.
                    </note> The Finns came to apply to the. upper gods the term Yumala which
                    originally denoted the living sky; the Samoyedes made the same use of Num, and
                    the Mongols of Tengri. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="17"> Ibid. pp. 7, 14, 17, 24. </note> Above the innumerable of the Gold
                    Coast rose</p>
               <p>Nyongmo, the Sky-god, giver of the sunshine and the rain. The Yoruba-Speaking
                    peoples generalized the spirits of mountain and hill into Oke, god of heights;
                    and the multitude of local sea-gods on the western half of the slave coast was
                    fused into one god of the Ocean, Olokun. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="18"> A. B. Ellis, <hi rend="italic">The Yoruba-Speaking
                            Peoples</hi> (1894), P- 289. </note> The Babylonian theology recognized
                    a <hi rend="italic">Zi</hi> or “ spirit ” in both men and gods, somewhat
                    resembling the Egyptian “ double ” or <hi rend="italic">ka</hi> ; spirits are
                    classed as spirits of heaven and spirits of earth; but the original identity of
                    gods and spirits may be inferred from the fact that the same sign stands before
                    the names of both. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="19">
                        Jastrow, <hi rend="italic">Religion of Babylonia and Assyria</hi> (1898), p.
                        181. The </note> Out of the vast mass of undifferentiated powers certain
                    functional deities appear; and the Kami of Japan to-day who preside over the
                    gilds and crafts of industry and agriculture, over the trees and grasses of the
                    field, the operations of the household, and even the kitchen-range, the
                    saucepan, the rice-pot, the well, the garden, the scarecrow and the privy, have
                    their counterparts in thé lists of ancient Rome, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Migitamenla</hi> over whose contents Tertullian and Augustine made merry.
                    The child was reared under the superintendence of <hi rend="italic">Educa</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Potina. Abeona</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Adeona</hi>
                    taught him to go out and in. <hi rend="italic">Cuba</hi> guarded him when he was
                    old enough to exchange a cradle for a bed. <hi rend="italic">Ossipaga</hi>
                    strengthened his hones; <hi rend="italic">Leväna</hi> helped him to get up, and
                        <hi rend="italic">Slalina</hi> to stand. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="20"> Zufiis applied the term ö-Ädt “
                        All-Life ” or ” the Beings ” to all supernatural beings, men, animals,
                        plants, and many objects in nature regarded as personal existences, as well
                        as to the higher anthropomorphic powers known as “ Finishers or Makers of
                        the Paths of Life," <hi rend="italic">Report of Bureau of Ethnol.</hi>
                        (1883), p. 11. On the distinction between “ gods ” and “ spirits,” cf. Ed.
                        Meyer, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. des Alterthums,</hi> 2nd ed. Band i. erste
                        Haelfte (1907), p. 97 ff. </note> There were 'powers ptotecting the
                    threshold, the door and the hinge: and the duties of the house, the farm, the
                    mill, had each its appointed guardian. But such powers were hardly persons. The
                    settler who went into the woods might know neither the name nor the sex .of the
                    indwelling <hi rend="italic">numen</hi> ; “si deus si dea,” “ sive mas sive
                    femina,” ran the old formulae. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="21"> Tert. <hi rend="italic">De Anima,</hi> 39 Aug. <hi
                            rend="italic">De Civ. Dei,</hi> iv. 11, &amp;c. </note> So the Baals of
                    the Semitic peoples constituted a group of powers fertilizing the land with
                    water-springs, the givers of com and wine and oil, out of which under Xonditions
                    of superior political development a high-god like the Tyrian Baal, the majestic
                    City-King, might he evolved. The Celts who saw the world peopled with the
                    spirits of trees and animals, rocks, mountains, springs and rivers, grouped them
                    in classes like the Dervonnae (oak-spirits), the Niskai (water-spirits), the
                    Proximae, the Matronae (earth-goddesses) <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="22"> On the Dei Certi and the Dei Incerti, see von
                        Domaszewski in the <hi rend="italic">Archivfur Religionswiss.,</hi> x.
                        (1907), pp. 1-17. </note> and the like. Below the small band of Teutonic
                    divinities were the elves of forest and field, the water-elves or nixes and
                    spirits of house and home. The Vedic deities of the nobler sort, the shining <hi
                        rend="italic">devas,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">asuras</hi> (the “ breathers
                    ” or living, perhaps to be identified with the Scandinavian <hi rend="italic"
                        >oesir)</hi> rose above a vast multitude of demonic powers, many of them
                    doubtless derived from the local customs and beliefs of the native races whom
                    the immigrant Aryans subdued. In the earliest literary record of Greek religion
                    Homer distinguishes between the and the δαίμων, the personalized god and the <hi
                        rend="italic">numen or</hi> divine power. In Homer the element of time is
                    definitely recognized. The gods are the “ Immortals.” They arc born, and their
                    parentage is known, but they do not die. Zeus is not self-existent in the sense
                    in which the Indian Brahmä is <hi rend="italic">svayambhu,</hi> but certain
                    questions have been by implication asked and answered, which the demonology of
                    the savage has not yet raised. But behind Homcr stretches the dim scene of
                    pre-Hellenic religion, and the conflict of elements “ Pelasgic,” oriental and
                    Hellenic, out of which the Homeric religion emerged; and beneath the Homeric
                    religion how many features of the religion of ghosts and nature-spirits survived
                    in popular usage and the lower cults! <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="23"> Cf. the groups of “ Mothers ” in modem India, of
                        various origins, Crooke, <hi rend="italic">Popular Religion and
                            Folklore</hi> (2), i. 111. </note> When Herodotus (ii. 53) tried to
                    trace the origin of the beliefs around him, he found his way back to an age
                    before Hesiod or Homer, when the gods were nameless. To that age the traditions
                    preserved at Dodona bore witness; and the designations of special groups like
                    the <hi rend="italic">Bcol</hi> μέγ <hi rend="italic">ιστοί, Beol μαλίχιοι,
                        Bcol</hi> πραξιδικαι, or, possibly, thé Venerable Goddesses <hi
                        rend="italic">(Bcai σ€μναΙ)</hi> of Athens, point to a mode of thought when
                    the divine Powers were not definitely individualized. They are just at the point
                    of transition from the ranks of spirits to the higher classes of the gods. As
                    they had no names, they had no relations. Nor had any images yet been made of
                    them. They were associated with hallowed trees, with sacred stones and pillars,
                    out of which came the square rough-hewn Hermae which were anointed with oil Hke
                    the sacred stone attributed by legend to Jacob at Bethel. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="24"> Cf. Andrew Lang, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Myth, Ritual and Religion</hi> ; and Miss Harrison, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Prolegomena to the Study OfGreek Religion.</hi>
                    </note> By what processes the Hellenic immigration introduced new deities and
                    the Greek pantheon was slowly formed, can only be conjecturally traced with the
                    help of archaeology. But Herodotus and Aeschylus were well aware that the
                    religion of Greece had not been uniformly the same; and the gods whom they knew
                    had been developed out of intercourse with other peoples and the succession of
                    races in the obscure and distant past.</p>
               <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Polytheism.—</hi> The lower and unprogressive religions
                    practically remain in the polydaemonistic stage, though not without occasionally
                    feehng the stimulus of contact with higher faiths, Hke some of the West African
                    peoples in the presence of the Mahommedan advance. Among the more progressive
                    races, on the other hand, continual processes of elevation and decline may be
                    observed, and the activities of the greater gods are constantly being enriched
                    with new functions. Personal or social experiences of the satisfaction of some
                    desire or escape from some danger are referred to some particular deity.
                    Elements of race-consciousness help to shape the outlook on nature or life: and
                    slight differences of linguistic use in the coining of descriptive terms
                    sometimes lead to the multipHcation of divine forms. Exacter observation of
                    nature; closer attention to its contrasts of life and death, or Hght and
                    darkness, or male and</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0070" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0093.jp2"/>
               <p>female; the distinction between its permanent objects, and its occasional or
                    recurring operations; the recognition that behind sudden manifestations of
                    power, like the thunder-storm, there are steady forces and continuous cosmic
                    agencies at work—lead to the graduaI rise of the higher deities. And from the
                    social side the development of law, the influence of city life, the formation of
                    priesthoods, the connexion of particular deities with the fortunes of dynasties
                    or the vicissitudes of nations, the processes of migration, of conquest and
                    political fusion, the deportations of vanquished peoples, even the sale of
                    slaves to distant lands and the growth of trade and travel, all contribute to
                    the processes which expand and modify different pantheons, and determine the
                    importance of particular deities. In the midst of the bewildering variety, where
                    aIl types co-exist together and act and react on each other, it is impossible to
                    do more than point out some obvious groups receiving their special forms chiefly
                    from the side (1) of nature, (2) of human life, and (3) from moral or
                    theological speculation. Divine persons, objects or powers, connected with
                    ritual, are not here considered, such as the Brahman priests who claimed to be
                        <hi rend="italic">manushyadeväh</hi> (human-gods), or the sacred soma-juice
                    which grew by strange analogies into a mysterious element, linking together
                    heaven and earth.</p>
               <p>I. On the side of Nature the lowest rank (1) seems to belong to what Usener has
                    designated “ momentary ” or “ occasional ” gods. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="25">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gotternamen,</hi> Bonn, 1896, p. 279 ff. But cp. Dr
                        FarnelVs essay “ On the Place of the Sonder-Gotter in Greek Polytheism,” in
                            <hi rend="italic">Anthropological Essays presented to Edward Burnett
                            Tylor</hi> (1907), p. 81. </note> They embody for the time being a vague
                    consciousness of the divine, which is concentrated for some single act into an
                    outward object, like a warrior’s spear or the thunderbolt, <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="26"> Ibid. pp. 285, 286. </note> or the
                    last sheaf of com into „ which the Corn-Mother has been driven. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="27"> Frazer, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Golden Bough</hi> (2), ii. 170-1. </note> (2) Above
                    these, to use again Useneris nomenclature, <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="28">
                        <hi rend="italic">Gdtternamen</hi> p. 75. </note> are the “ special ” or
                    functional ” gods, “ departmental gods,” as Mr Lang has called them. Such were
                    some of the deities of the <hi rend="italic">Indigitarnenta</hi> already
                    compared with the Japanese Kami. Among them, for example, were twelve deities of
                    ploughing and harvest operations, who were invoked with Tellus and Ceres. (3)
                    Another class may be seen in the species-deities previously named; the Samoan
                    gods which could become incarnate as a heron or an owl, did not die with
                    particular birds. A dead owl was not a dead god; he yet lived in all other owls.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="29"> Turner, <hi
                            rend="italic">Samoa,</hi> 1884, p. 21. </note>
               </p>
               <p>(4) The worship of trees, plants and animals is a particular phase of the wider
                    series of nature-cults, only named here because of its frequency and its obvious
                    survivals in some of the higher polytheisms, where, as in Egypt, the Apis bulls
                    were.worshipped; or where, as in Mesopotamia, the great gods are partly
                    symbolized by animal forms; or where, as in Israel, Yahweh might be represented
                    as a bull; or where, as in Greece, such epithets as Dendrites and Endendros
                    preserved traces of the association of Dionysus and Zeus with vegetation; while
                    sacred animals like the serpents of Aesculapius were preserved in the temples.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="30"> Cf. de Visser,
                            <hi rend="italic">Die nicht Menschen-Gestaltigen Götter der
                            Griechin</hi> (Leiden, 1903). </note>
               </p>
               <p>(5) The higher elemental gods sometimes, like the sun, as the Indian Surya, the
                    Egyptian Rê, the Babylonian Shamash (Samas), the Greek Helios, retain their
                    distinct connexion with the visible object. It was naturally more easy for a
                    relatively spiritual worship to gather round a god whose name did not
                    immediately suggest a familiar body. No one ever thought of confessing sin, for
                    instance, to a river. But the da*ily survey of the sun (occasionally also the
                    function of the moon as measurer of time), together with his importance for
                    life, secured him a high moral rank; and Rê, united with the Theban Ammon,
                    became (under the New Empire) the leading god of Egypt for a thousand years, “
                    He who hath made all, the sole One with many hands.” Other deities, like Zeus,
                    rise to the head of a monarchical polytheism, in which their physical base is
                    almost,</p>
               <p>if not quite, forgotten in cosmic and moral grandeur. The gods are often
                    arranged in groups, three, seven and twelve being frequent numbers. Egyptian
                    summaries recognized gods in the sky, on earth and in the water; gods of the
                    north and south, the east and west, gods of the field and the cities. Indian
                    theologians classified them in three zones, earth, air and sky. Babylonian
                    speculation embraced the world in a triad of divine powers, Anu the god of
                    heaven, Bel of earth and Ea of the deep; and these became the symbols of the
                    order of nature, the divine embodiments of physical law. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="31"> Jastrow, <hi rend="italic">Rel. of
                            Babylonia,</hi> p. 432. </note> Sometimes the number three is reached by
                    the distribution of the universe into sky, earth and UnderworId, and the gods of
                    death claim their place as the rulers of the world to come. Among these deities
                    all kinds of relationships are displayed; consorts must be provided for the
                    unwedded, and the family conception, as distinct from the regal, presents a
                    divine father, mother and child. The Ibani in Southern Nigeria recognized Adum
                    the father-god, Okoba the mother-god and Eberebo the son-god. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="32"> Leonard, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Lower Niger and its Tribes,</hi> p. 354. </note> In
                    Egypt, Osiris, Isis and Horus proved an influential type. Perhaps at a
                    relatively earIier stage maternity alone is emphatically asserted, as in the
                    figure of the Cretan Mother, productive without distinctly sexual character.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="33"> Cf. Farneil,
                            <hi rend="italic">Cults of Greece,</hi> iii. 295. </note> Or, again,
                    maternity disappears, while parenthood survives, and causation is embodied in a
                    universal “ Father of all that are and are to be,” like the Indian Brahma in the
                    days of Gotama the Buddha.” <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="34">
                        <hi rend="italic">Digha Nikaya,</hi> i. 18. </note>
               </p>
               <p>II. On the human side polytheism receives fresh groups in connexion with the
                    development of social institutions and national feeling. (1) In the family the
                    hearth-fire is the scene of the protecting care of deity; the gods of the
                    household watch over its welfare. Each Roman householder had his <hi
                        rend="italic">Genius,</hi> the women their <hi rend="italic">Junones.</hi>
                    These stood at a higher level than the “ occasional gods,” having permanent
                    functions of supervision. (2) From the household a scries of steps embodied the
                    divine power in higher forms for social and political ends. Hestia presided over
                    cities; there was even a common Hestia for all Greece. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >fravashi</hi> or ideal type, the genius of both men and gods in the Zend
                    Avesta (possibly connected originally with the cultus of the dead <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="35"> This is denied by
                        Tiele, <hi rend="italic">Religion im Altertum,</hi> tr. Gehrich, ii. (1898),
                        p. 259. </note> ), rises in successive ranks from the worshipper’s own
                    person through the household, the village, the district and the province, up to
                    the throne of Ahura himself. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="36"> Cf. <hi rend="italic">Yasna,</hi> 4xxi. <hi
                            rend="italic">iSfS.B.E.</hi> xxxi. p. 331 ; and Soderblom <hi rend="sup"
                            >t</hi> S essay in the <hi rend="italic">Rev. de Vhist. des
                            religions,</hi> xxxix. (1899), pp. 229, 373. </note> The Chinese Shin
                    were similarly organized; so (less elaborately) were the Japanese <hi
                        rend="italic">Kami</hi> ; <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="37"> Hirata’s morning prayer in the last century
                        included 800 myriads of celestial <hi rend="italic">kami,</hi> 800 myriads
                        of ancestral <hi rend="italic">kami,</hi> the 1500 myriads to whom are
                        consecrated the great and small temples in all provinces, all islands, and
                        all places of the great land of eight islands, &amp;c. </note> and the Roman
                        <hi rend="italic">lares,</hi> the old local land-gods, found their highest
                    co-ordinating term in the <hi rend="italic">Lares Augusti,</hi> just as the
                    Genius was extended to the legion and the colony, and finally to Rome itself.
                    (3) In the case of national deities the tie between god and people is peculiarly
                    close, as when Yahweh of Israel is pitted against Chemosh of Ammon (Judges xi.
                    24). The great gods of Greece, in their functions as “ saviours ” and
                    city-guardians, acquire new moral characters, and become really different gods,
                    though they retain the old names. Ashur rises into majestic sovereignty as the “
                    Ruler of all the gods,” the supreme religious form of Assyrian sway: when the
                    empire falls beneath the revived power of Babylon, he fades away and disappears.
                    (4) The earthly counterpart of the heavenly monarch is the divine king, who may
                    be traced back in Egypt, for example, to the remotest antiquity, <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="38"> Moret, <hi
                            rend="italic">Du caractère religieux de la royauté pharaonique</hi>
                        (1902). For instances in the lower culture see Frazer, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Golden Bough</hi> (2), i. 140 ff. </note> and who survives to-day among
                    the civilized powers in the emperor of Japan (anciently <hi rend="italic"
                        >Arahito-gami,</hi> “ incarnate Kami ”). “To the end of time,”</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0071" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0094.jp2"/>
               <p>said Motowori (18th century), “ the Mikado is the child of the Sun-goddess.” (5)
                    The dead hero (historical or mythic) signalizes his power by gracious saving
                    acts; and Heracles, Asclepius, Amphiaraus, and others pass into the ranks of the
                    gods, which are thus continually recruited from below.</p>
               <p>HI. A third great group rises out of the sentiments and affections of man, or
                    the moral energies which he secs working in human life. (1) The Vedic <hi
                        rend="italic">Craddhä,</hi> “ faith,” the Greek <hi rend="italic"
                        >Metameleia,</hi> “repentance,” <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="39"> Worshipped at Argos. Usener, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Gotternarnen,</hi> p. 366. </note> the Latin <hi rend="italic"
                        >Spes,</hi> and a band of other figures, represent the dispositions of the
                    heart; Nemesis and Nike and Concordia and their kin belong to a somewhat
                    different sphere, the divine powers avenging, conquering, harmonizing the
                    counterparts of the “ departmental ” gods in the field of moral agencies. (2)
                    Over these theological speculation erects a few lofty and impressive forms;
                    sometimes below the highest, like Vohu Mano, “ the Good Mind ” of Ahura Mazda;
                    or the Bodhisattva Avalokitccvara, who vowed not to enter into final peace till
                    every creature had received the saving truth; sometimes supreme, like Brahma or
                    Prajapati (“ lord of creatures ”) in the early Brahmanic theology; or Adi
                    Buddha, or the Zervan Akarana, “ boundless time,” of a kind of Persian
                    gnosticism; or the Geôs <hi rend="italic">νψιστος</hi> whose worship appears
                    among other syncretistic cults of the Roman empire.</p>
               <p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Order of Nature.—</hi> Polytheism is here on the way to
                    monotheism, and this tendency receives significant support from the recognition
                    of an order in nature which is the ground and framework of social ethics. Not
                    only does a sky-god like Varuna, or a sun-god like the Babylonian Shamash,
                    survey all human things, and take cognizance of the evil-doer, but the daily
                    course of the world is itself the expression of an intellectual and moral power.
                    In the Chinese combination of Heaven and Earth as the parents and nourishers of
                    all things, the energy and action lie with Tien, Earth being docile and
                    receptive. Tien is intelligent and all-observing, and its “ sincerity ” or
                    steadfastness, displayed in the courses of the sun and moon and the succession
                    of the seasons, becomes the basis of right human conduct, personal and social.
                    The “ way ” of Heaven, the “ course ” of Heaven, the “ lessons ” of Heaven, the
                    law or “ decree ” <hi rend="italic">(ming)</hi> of Heaven, are constantly cited
                    as the pattern for the emperor and his subjects. This conception is even
                    reflected in human nature: “ Heaven in giving birth to the multitude of the
                    people, to every faculty and relationship affixed its laws ” <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Shi King,</hi> III. iii. 6; cf. IV. iii. <hi rend="italic">2,</hi> tr.
                    Legge), and the “ Grand Unity ” forms the source of all moral order <hi
                        rend="italic">(Li Ki,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Sacred Books of lhe
                        East,</hi> xxvii. p. 387). Indian thought presented this Order in a
                    semi-personal form. The great elemental gods imposed their laws <hi
                        rend="italic">(dhaman, dharman, vrata)</hi> on the visible objects of
                    nature, the flow of rivers, the march of the heavenly bodies across the sky. But
                    the idea of Law was generalized in the figure of <hi rend="italic">Rita</hi>
                    (what is “ fitted ” or “ fixed or the “ course ” or “ path ” which is
                    traversed), whose Zend equivalent <hi rend="italic">asha</hi> shows that the
                    conception had been reached before the separation of the Eastern Aryans produced
                    the migrations into India and Iran. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="40"> Cf. Max Müller, <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the
                            Origin and Growth of Religion</hi> (Hibbert Lect., 1878), v., and the
                        Vedic treatises of Ludwig, Ber-gaigne and Wallis. </note> In the <hi
                        rend="italic">Rig Veda</hi> the gods (even those of storm) are again and
                    again described as “born from the Rita,” or born in it, according to it, or of
                    it. Even Heaven and Earth rejoice in the womb or lap of the Rita. In virtue of
                    the mystic identity between the cosmic phenomena and sacrifice, Rita may be also
                    viewed as the principle of the cultus; and from that sphere it passes into
                    conduct and acquires the meaning of morality and is equated with what is “
                    true.” The fundamental idea remains the same in the Zend Asha, its philological
                    counterpart, but it is applied with a difference. Its form is more personal, for
                    Asha is one of the six Holy Immortals round the throne of Ahura Mazda
                    (Auramazda). In the primeval conflict between the powers of good and evil, the
                    Bounteous Spirit chose Asha, the Righteous Order which</p>
               <p>knit the world together and maintained the stars. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="41">
                        <hi rend="italic">Yasna <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> xxx. 5; <hi rend="italic">Sacred Books of the East,</hi> xxxi. p. 30;
                        cf. pp. 44, 5b 248. </note> The immediacy of the relation between Ahura and
                    Asha is implied in the statements that Ahura created Asha and that he dwells in
                    the paths which proceed from Asha; and when he created the inspired word of
                    Reason, Asha consented with him in his deed. In its ritual form Asha becomes the
                    principle of sacrifice, and hence of holiness, first ritual and then moral. Like
                    Rita, it rises into an object of worship, and in its most exalted aspect <hi
                        rend="italic">(Asha vahisia,</hi> the “ best ” Asha, most excellent
                    righteousness) it is identified with Ahura himself, being fourth among his
                    sacred names <hi rend="italic">(Orrnazd Yasht,</hi> § 7; <hi rend="italic"
                        >S.B.E.</hi> xxiii. p. 25). Egyptian speculation, in like manner,
                    impersonated the conceptions of physical and moral order as two sides of a
                    fundamental unity in the goddess Maât. Derived from the verb <hi rend="italic"
                        >mä,</hi> “ to stretch out,” her name denoted the ideas of right and rule,
                    and covered the notions of order, law, justice and truth, which remained
                    steadfast and unalterable. Mythologically she was the daughter (or the eye) of
                    the sun-god Re; but she bçcame Lady of Heaven and Queen of Earth, and even Lady
                    of the land of the West, the mysterious habitation of the dead. Each of the
                    great gods was said to be lord or master of Maât; but from another point of view
                    she “ knew no lord or master,” and the particular quality of deity was expressed
                    in the phrase <hi rend="italic">anx em maät,</hi> “ living by Maât,” which was
                    applied to the gods of the physical world, the sun and moon, the days and hours,
                    as well as to the divine king. She was solemnly offered by the sovereign to his
                    god; and the deity replied by laying her within the heart of his worshipper “to
                    manifest her everlastingly before the gods.” So in the famous scene of the
                    weighing of the soul, which first appears pictorially under the New Empire, she
                    introduces the deceased before the forty-two assessors of the heavenly judge,
                    Osiris, and presides over the scale in which his actions and life are weighed.
                    From the zenith to the realm of the departed she is the “queen of all gods and
                    goddesses.” <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="42"> Cf.
                        Renouf, <hi rend="italic">Hibbert Lectures,</hi> p. 119; Brugsch, <hi
                            rend="italic">Rel. und Mythol.,</hi> p. 477; Wiedemann, <hi
                            rend="italic">Ann. du Musée Guirnet <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> x. p. 561; Budge, <hi rend="italic">Gods of Egypt,</hi> i. p. 416.
                    </note> The Hellenic polytheism of Homer and Hesiod is already at work upon
                    similar ideas, and a whole group of mythic personifications slowly rises into
                    view representing different phases of the same fundamental conception. Themis
                    (root 0e=Sanskr. <hi rend="italic">dha,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic"
                        >dhäman)</hi> appears in Homer as the embodiment of what is fit or right;
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="43"> Cf. AMs
                        UijLttaresOd. xvi. 403 ; cf. Apollo, <hi rend="italic">Horn. Hymn.</hi> 394.
                    </note> she convenes or dismisses assemblies, she even keeps order at the
                    banquet of the gods. Next, Hesiod supplies a significant biography. She is the
                    daughter of Ouranos and Gaia; and after Metis she becomes the bride of Zeus.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="44">
                        <hi rend="italic"/> @@@ <hi rend="italic">Theog.</hi> 135, 901. </note>
                    Pindar describes her as born in a golden car from the primeval Oceanus, source
                    of all things, to the sacred height of Olympus to be the consort of Zeus the
                    saviour; and she bears the same august epithet, as the symbol of social justice
                    and the refuge for the oppressed. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="45">
                        <hi rend="italic"/> @@@ <hi rend="italic">Fr.</hi> 6, 7 ; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Ol.</hi> viii. 29. </note> Law was thus the spouse of the sovereign of
                    the sky, but Aeschylus identified her with the Earth (worshipped at Athens as
                    Ge-Themis), not only the kindly Mother, but the goddess who bound herself by
                    fixed rules or laws of nature and life. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="46"> Farnell, however, supposes that Ge acquired the
                        cult-appellative through her prophetic character <hi rend="italic">(Cults of
                            the Greek States,</hi> iii. p. 12). The union of Zeus and Themis is,
                        then, a later equivalent of the marriage of Zeus and Earth (ibid. p. 14).
                    </note> For the cultus of the earth as the source of fertility was associated
                    with the maintenance of the family, with the operations of agricuiture and the
                    social order of marriage. So Themis became the mother of the seasons; the
                    regular sequence of blossom and fruit was her work; and Good Order, Justice and
                    Peace were her offspring. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="47"> Paus. v. 17; Hes. <hi rend="italic">Theog.</hi> 901 ; Pindar, <hi
                            rend="italic">Ol.</hi> xiii. 6; ix. 26. </note> By such conceptions the
                    Hellenic polytheism was moralized; the physical character of the greater gods
                    fell into the background, and the sculptor’s art came to the aid of the poet by
                    completely enduing them with personality.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0072" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0095.jp2"/>
               <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Transition lo Monotheism.—From</hi> the higher Polytheism
                    an easy step leads to some form of Monotheism. The transition may be effected in
                    various ways. Max Müller observed the Vedic poets addressing themselves to the
                    several objects of their devotion, as if each occupied the field alone. Varuna
                    or Indra was for the time being the only god within the worshipper’s view; and
                    to this mode of thought he gave the name Heno-theism. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="48"> Or Kathenotheism, a term which did
                        not succeed in gaining permanent support, <hi rend="italic">Hibbert
                            Lect.,</hi> p. 271. </note> It obviously reappears elsewhere, as it is
                    the natural attitude of prayer, and may be seen in the pious homage of the
                    pilgrims to the Virgin of Loretto or Einsiedeln. Pfleiderer employed the word to
                    denote a relative monotheism like that of the early religion of Israel, whose
                    teachers demanded that the nation should worship but one god, Yahweh, but did
                    not deny the existence of other gods for other peoples. Yet once again the term
                    has been applied to characterize a whole group of religions, like the
                    Indo-Germanic, which are ultimately founded on the unity of the divine nature in
                    a plurality of divine persons. A designation of such doubtful meaning it seems
                    better (with Chantepie de la Saussaye) to abandon. But the unifying process may
                    advance along different lines. The deities of different local centres may be
                    identified; many such combinations took place in Egypt, and Isis in late days
                    served to her votaries as the unitary principle which appeared in one figure
                    after another of whole pantheons. Again, the gods may be viewed as a collective
                    totality, like the “ All-gods ” of the Vedic poets, or as at Olympia where there
                    was a “ common altar for all the gods” (cf. the frequent Roman dedication in
                    later days, “ Jovi optimo maximo caeterisque dis immortalibus ”). Or the
                    relation between the inferior deities and the most exalted may be conceived
                    politically and explained by Tertullian’s formula, “ Imperium penes unum,
                    officia penes multos.” One particular god may be eminent enough, like Zeus, to
                    rise above all others, and supply cultivated thought with a name for the supreme
                    power; and this may be strengthened by the national motive as in the case of
                    Israel. Or philosophic theology may penetrate to an abstract conception of
                    deity, like the Babylonian <hi rend="italic">'iluth,</hi> or the Vedic <hi
                        rend="italic">devatva</hi> and <hi rend="italic">asuratva',</hi> and some
                    seer may have the courage and insight to formulate the principle that “ the
                    great <hi rend="italic">asuratva</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">devas</hi> is one
                    ” <hi rend="italic">(R.V.</hi> iii. 55. 1). “ The One with many names ” was
                    recognized alike in India and in Greece; “πολλών <hi rend="italic">ονομάτων
                        μορφή μία,”</hi> says Aeschylus, almost in the words of the Vedic poet.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="49">
                        <hi rend="italic">R. V.</hi> i. 164. 46, “ Men call him Indra, Mitra,
                        Varuna, Agni. . . . Poets name variously what is but one.” </note>
                    Historians have usually recognized only three monotheistic religions, Judaism,
                    Christianity and Islam. The Christian apologists of the 2nd century, however,
                    found plenty of testimony to their doctrine of the unity of God in the writings
                    of Greek poets and philosophers; it was a commonplace in the revival under the
                    Empire; and among the group of religions embraced under the name Buddhism more
                    than one form must be ranked as monotheistic. The idealist philosophy of the
                    Prajna Päramitä in the system of the “ Great Vehicle ” declared that “ every
                    phenomenon is the manifestation of mind ” (Beal, <hi rend="italic">Catena,</hi>
                    p. 303). In the “ Lotus of the Good Law ” <hi rend="italic">(S.B.E.</hi> xxi.)
                    the Buddha is the “ Father of the World,” “ Self-born ” or Uncreate (like the
                    eternal Brahmä of the Hindu theology), the protector of all creatures, the
                    Healer (Saviour) of the sickness of their sins. These types have reappeared in
                    Japan. Nichiren taught a philosophical monism in the 13th century which is the
                    basis of a vigorous sect at the present day; and the “ True Sect of the Pure
                    Land;” founded by his older contemporary Shin-ran, and now the most numerous,
                    wealthy and powerful of the Buddhist denominations, has dropped the original
                    Gotama altogether out of sight, and permits worship to Amida alone, the sublime
                    figure of “ Boundless Light,” whose saving power is appropriated by faith. Here
                    is a monotheism of a definite and clear-cut type, arising apparently by
                    spontaneous development apart from any external impulse. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="50"> Cf. Carpenter, “ Japanese Buddhism,”
                        in <hi rend="italic">Hibbert Journal,</hi> April 1906, p. 522. </note> On
                    the other hand, the mono</p>
               <p>theism of Judaism was subject to serious qualifications. An exuberant demonology
                    admitted all kinds of interfering causes in the field of human life. Above man
                    on earth rose rank after rank of angels in the seven heavens. These were of
                    course created, but they were in their turn the agents of the phenomena of
                    nature, “ the angels of the spirit of fire and the angels of the spirit of the
                    winds, and the angels of the spirits of the clouds and of darkness and of snow
                    and of hail and of hoarfrost, and the angels of the voices and of the thunder
                    and of the lightning, and the angels of the spirits of cold and of heat, and of
                    winter and of spring and of autumn and of summer ” <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Jubilees,</hi> tr. R. H. Charles, ii. 2). These powers are of a
                    well-marked animistic type, and correspond to the Chinese Shin, save that they
                    were not incorporated in the cultus. Higher in rank came various mediating
                    forms, like Wisdom, Memra (the Word) or Shekinah (the Presence), more or less
                    definitely personalized. IMahom-medanism still recognizes innumerable <hi
                        rend="italic">jinn</hi> peopling the solitudes of the desert, and over the
                    grave of the deceased saint a little mosque is built, and prayers are offered
                    and miracles performed. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="51"> Cf. Goldziher, <hi rend="italic">Rev. de l’Hist. des Rel.</hi> ii.
                        257 ; Weir, <hi rend="italic">The Shaikhs of Morocco</hi> (1904). </note>
                    Christianity has, in like manner, in the course of its long and eventful
                    history, admitted numerous agencies within the sphere of superhuman causation.
                    The Virgin, the angelic hierarchy, the saints, have received the believer’s
                    homage, and answered his petitions. Theology might draw subtle distinctions
                    between different forms of devotion; but, tried by the comparisons of the
                    anthropologist, the monotheism even of historical Christianity cannot be
                    strictly maintained.</p>
               <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Classification.—</hi> In the panorama of religious
                    development thus briefly sketched, the different stages constantly appear to
                    shade off into one another, and any one of the higher seems to contain elements
                    of all the rest. This is the great difficulty of classification. All religions,
                    even the most conservative and traditional, are in constant flux, they either
                    advance or decay.</p>
               <p>In these processes, which do not take place at equal rates in different cases,
                    all kinds of survivals remain lodged, and embarrass every attempt to fix the
                    place of specific religions in any general course of development. The
                    theologian, the philosopher, the historian, have all tried their hands at
                    distribution. (i.) The 18th-century divine who divided religions into True and
                    False grimly remarked that the second chapter was much the longer of the two.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="52"> Broughton, <hi
                            rend="italic">Diet, of all Religions</hi> (1745), preface. </note> The
                    corresponding distinction into Natural and Revealed breaks down in view of the
                    fact that revelation by dream and oracle, by inspired seer or divine teacher and
                    law-giver, is a practically universal phenomenon in more or less distinctly
                    defined forms, (ii.) Philosophy, in the person of Hegel, classified religion in
                    a threefold form : <hi rend="italic">(a)</hi> the religion of Nature, ( <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> ) the religion of Spiritual Individuality,</p>
               <p>(c) the Absolute Religion (Christianity). <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="53">
                        <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of Religion</hi> (Eng. trans.), i. p. 266.
                    </note> The subdivisions of this scheme have been long since abandoned, as the
                    progress of knowledge rendered them untenable. K. F. A. Wuttke, however, adopted
                    its fundamental idea <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="54">
                        <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Heidenthums</hi> (1852), i. p. 95. </note>
                    and distinguished three periods or phases: (1) the objective, producing the
                    religions of nature;</p>
               <p>(2) the subjective, God as comprehended in the individual mind;</p>
               <p>(3) God as Absolute Spirit. In the same way Dr Edward Caird <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="55">
                        <hi rend="italic">Evolution of Religion</hi> (1893), lect. vii. </note>
                    recognizes three similar stages: (1) objective consciousness, the divine in
                    nature; (2) self-consciousness, the divine in man ' <hi rend="italic">(e.g.</hi>
                    Judaism, Stoicism, and modern philosophy of the type of Kant) ; (3)
                    God-consciousness, where God is above the contrast of subject and object, yet is
                    revealed in both (Christianity), (iii.) On the historical side numerous bases
                    have been suggested. (1) Max Müller proposed to group religions ethnologically
                    by tests of language. This had the obvious advantage of lifting two great
                    families into prominence, the Semitic and the Indo-Germanic. The Semitic peoples
                    were closely bound together by common types of thought and civilization, and
                    produced three of the leading religions of the world, Judaism, Christianity and
                    Isläm. But a glance at the table of Indo-Germanic religions</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0073" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0096.jp2"/>
               <p>drawn up by Tiele <hi rend="italic">(Ency. Bril.,</hi> 9th ed., voI. xx. p. 360)
                    will show what diversified products are blended together. Why should
                    philosophical Brahmanism, or the Buddhism which reacted against it, be
                    associated with so undeveloped a form as the religion of the ancient Latin
                    settlers in mid-Italy? And why, on the other hand, should the religions of the
                    lower culture, which are practically of a common type, be separated
                    genealogically into numerous independent families? (2) Whitney <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="56">
                        <hi rend="italic"/> @@@ <hi rend="italic">Princeton Review,</hi> May 1881,
                        quoted by Tiele, <hi rend="italic">Elements of the Science of Religion</hi>
                        (1897), i. p. 42. </note> found the most important distinction to lie
                    between religions which were the collective product of the wisdom of the
                    community, race-religions as they might be called, and those which proceeded
                    from individual founders. But, as TieIe pointed out, the “ individual ” element
                    cannot be eliminated from the “ race-religion,” where each myth has been first
                    uttered, each rite first performed, by some single person. And the founder who
                    enters history with an impressive personality can only do his work through the
                    response made to him by the insight and feeling of his time. (3) Kuenen
                    disengaged another characteristic, the scope and aim of any given religion; was
                    it limited to a particular people, or could it be thrown open to the world? On
                    this foundation the higher religions were classed as national or universal, the
                    latter group being formerIy supposed to include Buddhism, Christianity and
                    Mahommedanisra. Here, once more, the student is confronted with many
                    qualifications. A missionary religion Uke Mithraism, which established itself
                    all the way from Western Asia to the borders of Scotland, was certainly not “
                    national.” Judaism and Brahmanism both passed beyond the confines of race. The
                    Confucian morality could be adopted without difficulty in Japan. In other words,
                    there was either a definite tendency to expansion, or there was no impediment in
                    the religion itself when circumstances promoted its transplantation. Further,
                    there are elements of Islam, like the usages of the <hi rend="italic">hajj</hi>
                    (or pilgrimage to the sacred places at Mecca), the dryness of its official
                    doctrine and the limitations of its real character as indicated in the Wahhabi
                    revival, which so impair its apparent Universalism that Kuenen found himself
                    obliged to withdraw it from the highest rank of religions. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="57">
                        <hi rend="italic"/> @@@ <hi rend="italic">National Religions and Universal
                            Religions</hi> (Hibbert Lectures, 1882). </note> (4) Professor M.
                    Jastrow, jun., starting from the relation of religion to life, distinguishes
                    four groups, the religions of savages, the religions of primitive culture, the
                    religions of advanced culture and the religions which emphasize as an ideal the
                    coextensiveness of religion with life. It may, however, be doubted whether the
                    fundamental assumption of such a scheme, viz. that in the life of the savage
                    religion plays a comparatively small part, can be satisfactorily established.
                    The evidence rather implies that, so far as the sanctions of relligion affect
                    the savage at all, they affect him with unusual force. In the absence of other
                    competing interests his religious beliefs and duties occupy a much larger share
                    of his attention than the votaries of many higher faiths bestow on theirs; and
                    though his ethical range may be very limited, yet the total influence of his
                    religion in determining for him what he may do and what he may not, brings the
                    greater part of conduct under its control. The savage who finds himself
                    encompassed by taboos which he dare not break, lives up to his religion with a
                    faithfulness which many professing Christians fail to reach. (5) There remains a
                    broad distinction between religions that are in the main founded on the relation
                    of man to the powers of Nature, and those based on ethical ideas, which partly
                    corresponds to the philosophical division already cited. This enabled Professor
                    Tiele to arrange the chief religions in certain groups, starting from the
                    primitive conception of the common life of the objects of the surrounding
                    scene:— <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="58">
                        <hi rend="italic"/> @@@ <hi rend="italic">Ency. Brit.,</hi> 9th ed., art. “
                        Religions ” ; <hi rend="italic">Elements of the Science of Religion,</hi>
                        vol. i. (1897), with some corrections communicated by letter to Professor
                        Chantcpie de la Saussaye, <hi rend="italic">Religionsgesch.</hi> (3rd ed.,
                        1905), vol. i. p. n. </note>
               </p>
               <p>I. <hi rend="italic">Nature Religions—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. Polyzoic Naturalism (hypothetical).</p>
               <p>2. Polydemonistic-magical religions under the control of</p>
               <p>Animism (religions of savages).</p>
               <p>3. Purified or organized magical religions. Therianthropic</p>
               <p>Polytheism.</p>
               <p>(fl) Unorganized (religions of the Japanese, Dravidians, Finns, Esths, the
                    ancient Arabs, the ancient Pelasgi, the Old-Italian peoples, the Etruscans (?),
                    the Old-Slavs).</p>
               <p>(ά) Organized (religions of the half-civilized peoples of America, ancient
                    Chinese state-religion, religion of the Egyptians).</p>
               <p>4. Worship of beings in human form, but of superhuman</p>
               <p>power and half-ethical nature. Anthropomorphic polytheism (religions of the
                    Vedic Indians,the ancient Persians, the later Babylonians and
                    Assyrians,thea.dvanced Semites, the Kelts, Germans, Hellenes, Greeks and
                    Romans).</p>
               <p>II. <hi rend="italic">Ethical Religions</hi> (spiritualistic ethical religions
                    of Revelation)—</p>
               <p>1. National Nomistic (nomothetic) Religious Communions</p>
               <p>(Taoismand Confucianism <hi rend="sub">i</hi> Brahmanism,Jainism, Mazde-ism,
                    Mosaism and Judaism, the two last already passing into 2).’.</p>
               <p>2. Universalistic Religious Communions(Buddhism,Christian</p>
               <p>ity: Islam with its particularistic and nomistic elements only partially belongs
                    to this group). <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="59">
                        For a long series of suggested bases of classification see Raoul de la
                        Grasserie, <hi rend="italic">Des Religions Comparées au Point de Vue
                            Sociologique</hi> (1899), chap, xii.; cf. further E. von Hartmann, <hi
                            rend="italic">Religionsphilosophie</hi> (1888); Siebeck, <hi
                            rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Religionsphilosofhie</hi> (1893); Domer, <hi
                            rend="italic">Grundriss der Religionsphilosophie</hi> (1903). Siebeck
                        proposed to distribute religions in three grades: (1) Nature-Religions, <hi
                            rend="italic">i.e.</hi> those of the lower culture; (2)
                        Morality-Religions in various grades and stages, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>
                        Mexicans and Peruvians, Arcadians, Chinese, Egyptians, Hindus, Persians,
                        Germans, Romans, with the Greek religion in the highest rank; (3) Religions
                        of Redemption (Judaism forming the transition from the second group),
                        Buddhism in the sense of world-negation, and, positively, Christianity.
                        Bousset, <hi rend="italic">Whot is Religion?</hi> (1907) reckons Platonism
                        along with Buddhism. For criticism of Siebeck’s scheme see Tiele, <hi
                            rend="italic">Elements of the Science of Religion,</hi> vol. i. (1897),
                        pp. 62,65. Pfleiderer, <hi rend="italic">Religion and HistoricFaiths</hi>
                        (1907), p. 88, recognizes more clearly the difficulty of carrying almost any
                        division through the whole field, without frequent breach of historical
                        connexions. </note>
               </p>
               <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Revelation.—</hi> The second group in this division
                    practicaIly corresponds to the second stage recognized by Caird; but it rests
                    upon a somewhat different basis, the conception of revelation addressed to the
                    conscience in the form of religious law. Neither Taoism nor Confucianism,
                    indeed, makes this claim. The <hi rend="italic">Tao-teh-king,</hi> or book of
                    aphorisms on “ the Tao and virtue ” ascribed to Lao Tsze, is wholly unlike such
                    a. composition as Deuteronomy; and the disciples of Confucius carefully
                    refrained from attributing to him any kind of supernatural inspiration in his
                    conversations about social and personal morality. The sacred literatures of
                    India and Israel, however, present many analogies, and emerge out of a wide
                    range of phenomena which have their roots in the practices of the lower culture.
                    The belief that the Powers controlling man’s life are w illin g upon occasion to
                    disclose something of their purpose, has led to widespread rites of divination,
                    which Plato described as the “ art of fellowship between gods and men,” and the
                    Stoics defended on grounds of a priori religious expectation as well as of
                    universal experience. Through the dream the living was put into communication
                    with the dead, which sometimes embodied itself in peculiar and pathetic literary
                    forms, such as the Icelandic dream-verses imparted by the spirits of those who
                    had been lost at sea or overwhelmed by the snow; and a whole series of steps
                    leads up from necromancy to prophecy and oracle, as the higher gods become the
                    teachers of men. The gods of revelation are naturally not the highest, since
                    they appear as the interpreters of one superior to themselves. The revealing
                    agency may be only a voice like Aius Locutius, to which the Romans raised a
                    temple; or, like Hermes, he may be the messenger of the gods; or, like Marduk,
                    pre-eminently the god of oracles in Babylonia, he may be the son of Ea, the
                    mighty deep encompassing the earth, source of all wisdom and culture. To Marduk
                    the prophet-god Nabu in his turn became son, and his consort Tasbmit (“ causing
                    to hear ”) was the personification of Revelation. Egyptian thought ascribed this
                    function to Thoth, who played somewhat different parts in different systems, but
                    emerges as the representative of the immanent intelligence</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0074" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0097.jp2"/>
               <p>of the world, brother of Maät and the giver of laws and culture to man. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="60"> Cf. Maspero, <hi
                            rend="italic">Dawn of Civilization,</hi> p. 204; Wiedemann, <hi
                            rend="italic">Religion of the Ancient Egyptians,</hi> p. 227; Budge, <hi
                            rend="italic">Gods of Egypt,</hi> i. p. 415. </note> Thoth “ the
                    thrice-great ” passed into Hermes Trismegistus whom Christian fathers could
                    recognize, <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="61"> Aug.
                            <hi rend="italic">De Civ. Dei,</hi> xviii. 39, attributes the origin of
                        philosophy to his era. </note> when the supremely beautiful figure of Greek
                    theology, Apollo, had lost his dignity and ceased to be desired. Thoth was a
                    voluminous author, and the collection of forty-two books which bore his name was
                    a kind of primitive cyclopaedia of theology, astronomy, geography and
                    physiology. Apollo proclaims at his birth that he will declare the counsel of
                    Father Zeus to men. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="62">
                        <hi rend="italic">Hom. Hymn.</hi> i. </note> But his utterances have been
                    only casually preserved. A special literature of oracles did indeed arise; the
                    divine words were collected and the circumstances which produced them' were
                    recorded; and had Delphi become in fact the centre of Greece, as Plato conceiyed
                    it, here might have been the nucleus of a scripture. Theories of inspiration
                    lurk behind the rich vocabulary of Greek prophecy; the seer is <hi rend="italic"
                        >cvBcos, BcFKrprros, BclnrvcvaTOS, BcOfkbprjTOS,</hi> and Bakis and Musaeus
                    give their names to sacred verses. The story of the Sibylline books in Rome, on
                    the other hand, shows the growth of the idea of authority. They are deposited in
                    a temple, in charge of a small sacred college; new deities and rites are
                    introduced under their sanction; when they are accidentally destroyed, envoys
                    are sent to the East and fresh collections are made; these are in their turn
                    purged, the false are discarded and the true reverently preserved. By what
                    method the books were consulted is not known; but they exhibit the idea of a
                    sacred canon in process of formation. The theologians of India guarded their
                    ancient hymns with the utmost care. A vast literary apparatus was devised for
                    their protection. The famous Purusha-hymn <hi rend="italic">(R. V.</hi> x. 90)
                    already claimed a divine origin for the three Vedas, the Rik, the Saman and the
                    Yajush. The “ triple knowledge ” was sometimes derived from the “ Lord of
                    Creatures ” Prajapati—one of the unifying forms of Brahmanical theology—through
                    Vac or “ speech.” The Veda, that is to say, had existed in the divine mind ere
                    it was made known to men, and as such it belonged to the realm of the deathless
                    and the infinite. The tribal poets were supposed to have “ seen ” the heavenly
                    originals; elaborate arguments were devised to explain how the names of
                    particular objects like rivers and mountains could have existed in the Eternal;
                    while the grounds of belief in the infallibility of the sacred verses were
                    enforced with the double weight of philosophy and tradition. Buddhism repudiated
                    the authority of the Veda, but found it needful to supply its place; and the
                    word of the omniscient Teacher, faithfully reported by his disciples and
                    guaranteed by concurrent traditions, became the rule of belief for the new
                    Order. Nor were the authors of the scriptures whose fragments are preserved in
                    the Zend Avesta less conscious of their divine value. The ancient Gāthās, which
                    were supposed to be the composition of Zarathustra himself, received the homage
                    of later worshippers. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="63">
                        <hi rend="italic">Yasna,</hi> lv. ; <hi rend="italic">S.B.E.</hi> xxxi. p.
                        294. </note> Daena, the ideal personification of law and religion, is the
                    object of praise and sacrifice. She dwells on high in the Heavenly Home, the
                    radiant “Abode of song,” but Zarathustra summons her thence, begs for her
                    fellowship, and prays her for righteousness of thought, speech and deed. <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="64">
                        <hi rend="italic">S.B.E.</hi> xxiii. p. 264. </note> She is produced by Vohu
                    Mano, the “ Good Thought ” of Ahura,· one of the six Holy Immortals; she thus
                    belongs to the ideal creation before the earth and its inhabitants; <note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="65">
                        <hi rend="italic">Bundahis,</hi> i. 25 ; <hi rend="italic">S.B.E.</hi> v. p.
                        9. </note> but how the heavenly Daena was wrought by Zarathustra into
                    written form is nowhere stated. This conception of pre-existent spiritual
                    counterparts was not without influence on the later theology of Israel. The
                    sacred law (Torah) was the earthly reproduction of a heavenly Torah which had no
                    origin in time, and constituted the sum of ideal wisdom into which God looked
                    when he would create the world. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="66">
                        <hi rend="italic">Midrash Bereshith Rabba,</hi> tr. Wunsche, I. i. ver. i.
                    </note>
               </p>
               <p>Even Mahommedanism felt the spell of the same modes of thought. The idea of
                    revelation was expressed by “ sending down ” (from <hi rend="italic"
                        >nazala,</hi> to descend) ; that which passed from heaven to earth was a
                    pre-existent word, eternal as God Himself. Allusions in particular passages of
                    the Koran to the “ mother of the scripture,” the invisible originals of the
                    prophet’s speech, led to the doctrine of its uncreated being. The whole history
                    of religion presents perhaps no more singular spectacle than the mosques of
                    Bagdad in the middle of the 9th century filled with vast crowds of twenty and
                    thirty thousand of the faithful, assembled to discuss the dogmas of the created
                    and the uncreated Koran. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="67"> Von Kremer, <hi rend="italic">Die Herrschenden Ideen des
                            Islams,</hi> p. 233 ff. </note>
               </p>
               <p>8. <hi rend="italic">Ethics and Eschalology.—</hi> The second distinguishing
                    mark in Tiele’s higher group is implied in the term “ Ethical.” By this it is
                    not intended to assert that moral ideas are wanting in the so-called “ naturist
                    ” religions. Anthropologists have, it is true, taken widely different views of
                    the relation of ethics and religion, and the stage at which an effective
                    alliance between them might be recognized. Like all problems of origins, the
                    question is necessarily extremely obscure, and cannot be definitely settled by
                    historical evidence. Broadly speaking, however, it may be said that the attempt
                    to show that certain savages are destitute of moral feeling cannot be sustained;
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="68"> See
                        Westermarck, <hi rend="italic">Origin and Development of Moral Ideas,</hi>
                        vol.i. (1906), η. 125, on Lord Avebury’s conclusions. </note> and evidence
                    has been already cited above (in the section on <hi rend="smallcaps">Primitive
                        Religion)</hi> proving the varied and immediate effects of religion on the
                    life of the lowest tribes. Continuous interaction marks the slow courses of
                    advance. At a very early period in social development the rules of conduct are
                    referred to some higher source. Thus among the tribes of south-eastern Australia
                    described by Mr Howitt, <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="69">
                        <hi rend="italic">Native Tribes of SE. Australia</hi> (1904), pp. 488, 489,
                        495, 543. </note> the native rites and laws handed down from generation to
                    generation were supposed to have been first imparted by some higher being such
                    as Nurrundere, who made all things on the earth; or Nurelli, who created the
                    whole country, with the rivers, trees and animals; or Daramulun, who (like
                    Nurrundere) bestowed weapons on the men, and instituted the rites and ceremonies
                    connected with life and death. As religion advances with improved social
                    organization, a series-of figures, partly human, partly divine, embodies the
                    idea that the command of nature implied in the progress of the arts is due to
                    some kind of instruction from above, and that the obU-gations of law are of more
                    than human origin. The Algonquin Manibozho and Quetzalcoatl of Mexico stand for
                    a whole group of typical personalities in North and-Central America. The
                    mysterious fish-man Oannes,who taught the primitive inhabitants of Babylonia,
                    according to Alexander Polyhistor, has been identified with Ea, god of the deep,
                    the source of wisdom, culture and social order. Zeus gave laws to Minos; Apollo
                    revealed the Spartan constitution to Lycurgus; Zaleucus received the laws for
                    the Locrians from Athena in a dream; Vishnu and Manu condescended to draw up
                    law-books in India. The worship of ancestors has again and again gathered around
                    it powerful and ethical influences, emphasizing the parental and filial
                    relations, and strengthening the mutual obligations of communal life. Hirata
                    answered by anticipation the modern reproach against Shinto, founded on the
                    absence of any definite morality connected with it, by laying down the simple
                    rule, “ Act so that you need not be ashamed before the Kami of the unseen.”
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="70"> Satow, “
                        Revival of Pure Shinto,” <hi rend="italic">Trans.</hi> As. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Soc. Japan,</hi> vol. iii. Appendix, p. 87. </note> The mythological
                    embodiments of the connexion of law in nature with the social and moral order
                    have already been briefly noted: a few words may be said in conclusion on
                    another product of the union of religion and ethics, viz. the doctrine of
                    judgment after death. That this doctrine is not essential to a highly moralized
                    religion is clear from the fact that it formed no part of the earlier Hebrew
                    prophecy. Judgment, indeed, was an inevitable outcome of the sovereignty of
                    Yahweh, but it would be passed upon the nation in the-immediate scene of its
                    misdoings; and even when the scope of the divine doom</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0075" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0098.jp2"/>
               <p>was extended to include the nations of the world, it was still upon the living
                    that it would alight. The seers of Israel were content to dismiss their dead to
                    a land of silence and darkness, the vast hollow gloom of the subterranean Sheol.
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="71"> Cf. Ezek.
                        xxxii. 17-32; Ps. lxxxviii 3-4, io, 11; Job x. 21-22, and many other
                        passages. </note> A far ruder outlook on life, however, which has again and
                    again appealed to some form of the divine cognizance by means of the ordeal and
                    the oath, frequently supplements the moral issues of this world by the judicial
                    award of the next. Assuming the proper fulfilment of the ritual of death, ethics
                    gradually extends its control over the future. At first the social distinctions
                    of this life are simply continued hereafter: the chief remains a chief, the
                    slave a slave; and the Conditionsof the future only prolong those of the
                    present. In so far as tribal eminence depends on superior skill or courage or
                    wisdom, the germs of ethical differentiation may be discovered even here. The
                    process is carried further (i) in individual cases of retribution, when (as
                    among the Kaupuis) crime within the tribe was punished, and a murderer becomes
                    in the next life his victim’s slave; <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="72"> Watt, <hi rend="italic">Journ. Anthrop.
                            Institute,</hi> xvi p. 356. Cf. Codrington, <hi rend="italic">The
                            Melanesians</hi> (1891), p. 274. </note> or (2) when service to the
                    community received special reward, and warriors who had fallen in battle, women
                    who had died in childbirth and merchants who had perished on a journey were sent
                    in Mexico to the house of the sun. <note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial" n="73"> Bancroft, <hi rend="italic">Native Races of the
                            Pacific States of N. America,</hi> iii. P- 532. </note> As the social
                    order acquires more definiteness and stability, the control of life by the gods
                    tends to become more clearly moralized. This brings with it new standards
                    independent of clan-customs or tribe-usage. Only the worst offences, however, at
                    first draw down post-mortem punishment. The Homeric Erinyes chastise outrages on
                    the poor, injuries to guests, failure to show the respect due to parents or to
                    recognize the rights of age, in this life; only on perjury does the divine doom
                    extend to the next. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="74">
                        <hi rend="italic">II.</hi> iii. 278-79; xix. 258-60. </note> On the other
                    hand, the Egyptian version of “ the whole duty of man ” in the famous 125th
                    chapter of the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Dead</hi> embraces a singular
                    complex of ritual, social and personal sins, in which the inward states of
                    lying, anger and ill-will are condemned along with murder, theft and adultery,
                    beside violation of the times of offerings to the gods, or interference with the
                    food of the blessed dead. The great judgment of Osiris formulates with the
                    utmost precision the alliance between morals and religion. The doctrine
                    established itself in Greek theology under the influence of Orphism, and
                    supplied Plato with mythic forms for his “ criticism of life.” In India the
                    union of morality and religion was effected in another manner. True, Yama, first
                    of men to enter the world beyond, became the “ King of Righteousness ” before
                    whose tribunal the dead must appear. But a new agency began to engage the
                    speculations of thinkers, the moral values of action embodied in the Deed. “.The
                    deed does not perish,” ran an early formula. <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="75">
                        <hi rend="italic">S.B.E.</hi> ii. p. 271; xiv. pp. 116, 310. </note> “ A man
                    is born into the world that he has made,” said another: <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="76"> Ibid., xii. p. 181. </note> and what
                    was laid down first as a ritual principle survived as an ethical. Buddhism
                    conceived men as constantly making their own world for good and ill; it took
                    over from Brahmanism a whole series of heavens and hells to provide an exact
                    adjustment in the future for the virtue or vice of the present; and its
                    eschatologie confidence was one of the potent instruments of its success in
                    countries which, like China and Japan, had developed no theories of retribution
                    or reward beyond the grave. Along a different line of thought the Iranian
                    teachers, beholding the world divided between hostile powers, demanded, as the
                    fundamental postulate of religion, the victory of the good. The conflict must
                    end with the triumph of light, truth and right. The details of this remarkable
                    scheme must be studied elsewhere (see Zoroaster). The award of the angel-judges
                    at the Bridge of Assembly, soon after death, despatched the individual to his
                    appropriate lot in the homes of Good or Evil Thought, Word and Deed. But at
                    length the long struggle would draw to an end. The great “ divine event,” the
                        <hi rend="italic">frasho-kereti,</hi> the renovation, would set in. A new
                    heaven and a new earth would be created: a generaI resurrection shouId take
                    place; the powers of evil should be overthrown and extinguished; and hell should
                    be brought back for the enlargement of the world. Eschatology has again and
                    again expressed the alliance between ethics and religion. It remains for the
                    future to show how long that alliance will require its support.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.—(For primitive religion see preceding
                        section.) Only a selection of the copious and ever-increasing literature can
                        here be named. Monographs on the separate religions are named in their
                        respective articles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. After Hume’s <hi rend="italic">Natural Hist, of Religions</hi> (1757) earlier
                    surveys will be found in Meiners, <hi rend="italic">Allgem. Krit. Gesch. der
                        Religionen</hi> (2 vols., 1806-7); Constant, <hi rend="italic">De la
                        religion</hi> (5 vols., 1824-31); Baur <hi rend="italic">Symbolik und
                        Mythologie</hi> (3 vols., 1825); Creuzcr <hi rend="italic">Symbolik und
                        Mythol. der alten Volker <hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi> (18^7); F. D. Maurice, <hi rend="italic">The Religions of the World</hi>
                    (1846); Hardwick, <hi rend="italic">Christ and other Masters</hi> (4 vols.,
                    1855-59); Dollinger, <hi rend="italic">The Gentile and the Jew</hi> (2 vols.,
                    1863). On Mythology and Religion English study was chiefly influenced by F. Max
                    Müller, <hi rend="italic">Essay on Comparative Mythology</hi> (1856); <hi
                        rend="italic">Chips from a German Workshop</hi> (1867 onwards); <hi
                        rend="italic">Lectures on the Science of Language</hi> (2 vols., 1861-64) *»
                        <hi rend="italic">Contributions to the Science of Mythology</hi> (2 vols.,
                    1897); cf. A. Lang, <hi rend="italic">Modern Mythology</hi> (1897). Earlier
                    Anthropology, Bastian, <hi rend="italic">Der Mensch in der Gesch.</hi> (3 vols.,
                    Leipzig, i860); Waitz-perïand, <hi rend="italic">Anthropologie</hi> (6 vols. <hi
                        rend="sub">;</hi> Leipzig, 1877).</p>
               <p>2. Translations from the Scriptures of various religions.— <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sacred Books of the East</hi> (49 vols., 1879 and onwards); <hi
                        rend="italic">Annales du Musée Guimet</hi> (1880 and onwards).</p>
               <p>3. Manuals, treatises and series in single or collective authorship.— C. P.
                    Tiele, <hi rend="italic">Outlines of the History of Religion,</hi> tr. Carpenter
                    (London, 1877); <hi rend="italic">Gesch. der Religion im Altcrthum <hi
                            rend="sub"> i</hi></hi> tr. Gehrich (2 vols., Gotha,895*98) ; <hi rend="italic">Kompendium der
                        Religionsgesch.,</hi> tr. Webef (Breslau, 1903) ; G. Rawlinson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Religions of the Ancient World</hi> (London, 1882); <hi
                        rend="italic">Religious Systems of the. World,</hi> by various authors
                    (London, 1890); Menzies, <hi rend="italic">Hist, of Religion</hi> (1895);
                    Orelli, <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Religionsgesch.</hi> (Bonn, 1899); <hi
                        rend="italic">Great Religions of the World,</hi> by various authors (1901) ;
                    Bousset, <hi rend="italic">Das Wesen der Religion</hi> (Halle, 1903); Eng.
                    trans., <hi rend="italic">What is Religion?</hi> (London, 1907); Chantepie de la
                    Saussaye, <hi rend="italic">ReligionsgeschJ</hi> (2 vols., 1905); Achelis, <hi
                        rend="italic">Abriss der Vergleichenden Religionswissenschaft</hi> (Sammlung
                    Göschen) ; “ Die Orientalischen Religionen ” (in <hi rend="italic">Die Kultur
                        der Gegenwart),</hi> by Variousauthors (1906); Pfleiderer <hi rend="italic"
                        >Religion und Religionen</hi> (Berlin, 1906) ; Eng. trans., <hi
                        rend="italic">Religion and Historic Faiths</hi> (London, 1907); Haarlem
                    Series, <hi rend="italic">Die Voornaamste Godsdiensten <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> beginning, with Islam, by Dozy (1863 onwards); Soc. for Promotion of
                    Christian Knowledge, <hi rend="italic">Non-Christian Religions ;</hi> Hibbert
                    Lectures on <hi rend="italic">The Origin and Growth of Religion</hi> (15 vols.»
                    beginning with F. Max Müller, 1878) ; AsehendorfTs series, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Darstellungen aus dem Gebiete der Nichtchristl. Religionsgesch.</hi> (14
                    vols.. Münster i.w., beginning 1890); <hi rend="italic">Handbooks on the History
                        of Religions,</hi> ed. Jastrow, beginning with Hopkins on India (1895); <hi
                        rend="italic">American Lectures on the History of Religions,</hi> beginning
                    with Rhys Davids on Buddhism (1896); Constables series, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Religions, Ancient and Modern</hi> (London, beginning 1905), brief and
                    popular; J. Freeman Clarke, <hi rend="italic">Ten Great Religions</hi> (Boston,
                    1871); S. Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Oriental Religions,</hi> &amp;c. (3
                    vols.); <hi rend="italic">IndiaJ</hi> (London, 1873); <hi rend="italic"
                        >China</hi> (Boston, 1877); <hi rend="italic">Persia</hi> (1885); Lippert,
                        <hi rend="italic">Die Religionen der Europäischen Cultur-Volker</hi>
                    (Berlin, 1881); A. Réville, <hi rend="italic">Prolêgom. de Fhist. des rel.</hi>
                    (Paris, 1881 ; Engl, trans., 1884); <hi rend="italic">Les Rel. des peuples
                        non-civilisés</hi> (2 vols., Paris, 1883); <hi rend="italic">Rel. du
                        Mexique</hi> (1885) ; <hi rend="italic">Rel. chinoise</hi> (1889);
                    Letourneau, <hi rend="italic">HEvolution religieuse*</hi> (Paris, 1898);
                    Publications of the <hi rend="italic">École des hautes études, section des
                        sciences religieuses','</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Annales du Musée
                        Guimet,</hi> " Bibliothèque de Vulgarisation.”</p>
               <p>4. Works bearing on history.—Fustel de Coulanges, <hi rend="italic">La Cité
                        antique</hi> (Paris, 1864); Lubbock, <hi rend="italic">Origin of
                        Civilization</hi> (1870); Whitney, <hi rend="italic">Oriental and Linguistic
                        Studies</hi> (New York, 1872 and 1874) ; Brinton, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Religious Sentiment</hi> (1876); <hi rend="italic">Myths of the New
                        World</hi> (New York, 1876); <hi rend="italic">Essays of an Americanist</hi>
                    (1890); <hi rend="italic">Religions of Primitive Peoples</hi> (1897); Keary, <hi
                        rend="italic">Outlines of Primitive Belief</hi> (London, 1882) ; Leblois,
                        <hi rend="italic">Les Bibles et les initiateurs de l’humanité</hi> (4 vols,
                    in 7 parts, Paris, 1883); Goblet d’Alviella, <hi rend="italic">Introd. à l'hist.
                        générale des religions</hi> (Brussels, 1887); <hi rend="italic">La Migration
                        des symboles</hi> (Paris, 1891); Hartland, <hi rend="italic">The Legend of
                        Perseus</hi> (3 vols., London, 1894); Ratzel, <hi rend="italic">The History
                        of Mankind,</hi> tr. Butler (3 vols., London, 1896) ; Usener, <hi
                        rend="italic">Götternamen</hi> (Bonn, 1896) ; Grant Allen, <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Evolution of the Idea of God</hi> (London, 1897); Forlong, <hi
                        rend="italic">Short Studies in the Science of Comp. Religions</hi> (London,
                    1897); Lang, <hi rend="italic">The Making of Religion</hi> (1898); Lyall, <hi
                        rend="italic">Asiatic Studies</hi> (2 vols., London, 1899); Baissac, <hi
                        rend="italic">Les Origines de la religion</hi> (Paris, 1899); Marillicr,
                    “Religion,” <hi rend="italic">Grande Encyclop.</hi> xxviii. (Paris, 1900);
                    Maculloch, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Theol.</hi> (1902); Dieterich, <hi
                        rend="italic">Mutter Erde</hi> (Leipzig, 1905);</p>
               <p>S. Reinach, <hi rend="italic">Cultes, mythes et religions</hi> (2 vols., Paris,
                    1905-6); Frazer, <hi rend="italic">Adonis, Attis and Osiris</hi> (1906); Ed.
                    Meyer, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. des Alterthums,</hi> I. i. “ Einleitungz
                    Elemente der Anthropologie ” (1907).</p>
               <p>5. Psychology, Philosophy and History.—Hegel, <hi rend="italic">Philosophy
                        of</hi>
               </p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0076" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0099.jp2"/>
               <p>                    <hi rend="italic">Religion</hi> (Eng. trans., 3 vols., 1895) ; Pflelderer, <hi
                        rend="italic">Die Religion (2</hi> vols., Berlin, 1869); <hi rend="italic"
                        >Philos, of Religion,</hi> vol. iii. (Engl, trans., London, 1888); <hi
                        rend="italic">Religionsphilosophie *</hi> (Berlin, 1896); F. MaxMiiller, <hi
                        rend="italic">Introd. to the Science of Religion</hi> (1873); <hi
                        rend="italic">Hibbert Lectures</hi> (1878); <hi rend="italic">Gifford
                        Lectures</hi> (4 vols., 1889-93) ; Spencer, <hi rend="italic">Principlesof
                        Sociology,</hi> i. (1876) ; Fairbairn, <hi rend="italic">Studies in the
                        Philosophy of Religion and History</hi> (1876); E. von Hartmann, <hi
                        rend="italic">Das Relig. Bewusstsein der Menschheit</hi> (Berlin, 1882) ;
                    Rauwenhoff, <hi rend="italic">Weisbegeerte van den Godsdienst</hi> (Leiden,
                    1887); E. Caird, <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Religion</hi> (2 vols.,
                    1893) ; Siebeck, <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Religionsphilosophie</hi>
                    (Freiburg i. B., 1893); Tiele, <hi rend="italic">Elements of the Science of
                        Religion</hi> (2 vols., 1897); Raoul de la Grasserie, <hi rend="italic">Des
                        religions comparées au point de vue sociologique,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >De la psychologie des religions</hi> (Paris, 1899); Starbuck, <hi
                        rend="italic">Psychology of Religion</hi> (London, 1900); Jastrow, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Study of Religion</hi> (London, 1901); W. James, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Varieties of Religious Experience</hi> (1903); Dorner, <hi
                        rend="italic">Grundriss der Religionsphilosophie</hi> (Leipzig, 1903);
                    Girgensohn, <hi rend="italic">Die Religion, ihre Psychischen Formen und ihre
                        Zentralidee</hi> (Leipzig, 1903); Wundt, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Völkerpsychologie,</hi> Bd. ii. <hi rend="italic">Mythus und Religion</hi>
                    (1905-6); Ladd, <hi rend="italic">The Philosophy of Religion</hi> (2 vols.,
                    London, 1906); Hoffding, <hi rend="italic">The Philosophy of Religion</hi>
                    (Engl, trans., 1906) ; Wester-maarck, <hi rend="italic">The Origin and
                        Development of the Moral Ideas,</hi> i. (London, 1906); Hobhouse, <hi
                        rend="italic">Morals in Evolution</hi> (2 vols., London, 1906).</p>
               <p>6. Periodicals, &amp;c.— <hi rend="italic">Revue de l’hist. des
                        religions</hi> (Paris, 1880 onwards); <hi rend="italic">Folk-Lore</hi>
                    (London, 1890 onwards); <hi rend="italic">Archiv, für Religionswissenschaft</hi>
                    (Freiburg i. B., 1898 onwards); <hi rend="italic">L’Année sociologique</hi>
                    (Paris, 1898 onwards); <hi rend="italic">Actes du premier congrès international
                        d’histoire des religions</hi> (Paris, 1900); <hi rend="italic">Verhandlungen
                        des II. Internationalen Kongresses für Allgemeine Religionsgeschichte in
                        Basel</hi> (1904).</p>
               <p>Much information on the growth and present condition of the study has been
                    collected by Jordan, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Religion, its Genesis and
                        Growth</hi> (Edinburgh, 1905). (J. E. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
