<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0288-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0311.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>RICCI, MATTEO</label> (1552-1610), Italian missionary to China, was born
                    of a noble family at Macerata in the March of Ancona on the 7th of October 1552.
                    After some education at a Jesuit college in his native town he went to study law
                    at Rome, where in 1571, in opposition to his father’s wishes, he joined the
                    Society of Jesus.</p>
               <p>In 1577 Ricci and other students offered themselves for the East Indian
                    missions. Ricci, without visiting his family to take leave, proceeded to
                    Portugal. His comrades were Rudolfo Acquaviva, Nicolas Spinola, Francesco Pasio
                    and Michcle Ruggieri, all afterwards, like Ricci himself, famous in the Jesuit
                    annals. They arrived at Goa in September 1578. After four years spent in India,
                    Ricci was summoned to the task of opening China to evangelization.</p>
               <p>Z Several fruitless attempts had been made by Xavier, and since his death, to
                    introduce the Church into China,—as by Melchior Nunes of the Jesuit Society
                    operating from Sanchian <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="1"> The island (properly Chang-chuen) on which the Portuguese had a
                        temporary settlement before they got Macao, and on which F. Xavier died in
                        1552. </note> in 1555; by Gaspar da Cruz, a Dominican, in that or the
                    follow-ing year; by the Augustinians under Martin Herrada, 1575; and in 1579 by
                    the Franciscans led by Pedro d’Alfaro. In 1571 a house of the Jesuits had been
                    set up at Macao (where the Portuguese were estabHshed in 1557), but their
                    attention was then occupied with Japan, and it was not till the arrival at Macao
                    of Alessandro Valignani on a visitation in 1582 that work in China was really
                    taken up. For this object he had obtained the services first of M. Ruggieri and
                    then of Ricci. After various disappointments they found access to Chow-king-fu
                    on the Si-Kiang or West River of Canton, where the viceroy of the two provinces
                    of Kwang-tung and Kwang-si then had his residence, and by his favour were able
                    to establish themselves there for some years. Their proceedings were very
                    cautious and tentative; they excited the curiosity and interest of even the more
                    intelligent Chinese by their clocks, their globes and maps, their books of
                    European engravings, and by Ricci’s knowledge of mathematics, including dialling
                    and the projection of maps. They conciliated some influential friends, and their
                    reputation spread widely in China. This was facflitated by the Chinese system of
                    transfer of pubHc officers from one province of the empire to another, and in
                    the later movements of the missionaries they frequently met with one and another
                    of their old-acquaintances in office, who were more or less well disposed.
                    Eventually troubles at Chow-king compelled them to seek a new home; and in 1589,
                    with the viceroy’s sanction, they migrated to Chang-chow in the northern part of
                    Kwang-tung, not far from the well-known Meiling Pass;.</p>
               <p>During his stay here Ricci was convinced that a mistake had been made in
                    adopting a dress resembling that of the bonzes, a class who were the objects
                    either of superstition or of contempt. With the sanction of the visitor it was
                    ordered that in future the missionaries should adopt the costumes of Chinese
                    literates, and, in fact, they before long adopted Chinese manners altogether.</p>
               <p>Chang-chow, as a station, did not prove a happy selection, but it was not till
                    1595 that an opportunity occurred of travelling northward. For some time Ricci’s
                    residence was at Nan-chan g-fu, <hi rend="sup">!</hi> the capital of Kiang-si;
                    but in 1598 he was able to proceed under favourable conditions to Nan-king, and
                    thence for the first time to Peking, which had all along been the goal of his
                    missionary ambition. But circumstances were not then propitious, and the party
                    had to return to Nan-king. The fame of the presents which they carried had,
                    however, reached the court, and the Jesuits were summoned north again, and on
                    the 24th of January 1601 they entered the capital. Wan-Η, the emperor of the
                    Ming dynasty, in those days lived in seclusion, and saw no one but his women and
                    the eunuchs. But the missionaries were summoned to the palace; their presents
                    were immensely admired, and the emperor had the curiosity to send for portraits
                    of the fathers themselves.</p>
               <p>They obtained a settlement, with an allowance for subsistence, in Peking, and
                    from this time to the end of his Hfe Ricci’s estimation among the Chinese was
                    constantly increasing, as was at the same time the amount of his labours.
                    Visitors thronged the mission house incessantly; and inquiries came to him from
                    all parts of the empire respecting the doctrines which he taught, or the
                    numerous Chinese publications which he issued. This in itself was a great
                    burden, as Chinese composition, if wrong impressions are to be avoided, demands
                    extreme care and accuracy. As head of the mission, which now had four stations</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0289" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0312.jp2"/>
                <p>in China, he also devoted much time to answering the letters of the priests under
                    him, a matter on which he spared no pains or detail. New converts had to be
                    attended to—always welcomed, and never hustled away. Besides these came the
                    composition of his Chinese books, the teaching of his people and the maintenance
                    of the record of the mission history which had been enjoined upon him by the
                    general of the order, and which he kept well up to date. Thus his labours were
                    wearing and incessant. In May 1610 he broke down, and after an illness of eight
                    days died on the nth of that month. His colleague Pantoja applied to the emperor
                    for a burying-place outside the city. This was granted, with the most honourable
                    official testimonies to the reputation and character of Ricci; and a large
                    building in the neighbourhood of the city was at the same time bestowed upon the
                    mission for their residence.</p>
                <p>Ricci’s work was the foundation of the subsequent success attained by the Roman
                    Catholic Church in China. When the missionaries of other Roman Catholic orders
                    made their way into China, twenty years later, they found great fault with the
                    manner in which certain Chinese practices had been dealt with by the Jesuits, a
                    matter in which Ricci's action and policy had given the tone to the mission in
                    China—though in fact that tone was rather inherent in the Jesuit system than the
                    outcome of individual character, for controversies of an exactly parallel nature
                    arose two generations later in southern India, between the Jesuits and
                    Capuchins, regarding what were called “ Malabar rites.” The controversy thus
                    kindled in China burned for considerably more than a century with great
                    fierceness. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> The
                        list of the literature of this controversy occupies forty-one columns in M.
                        Cordier’s excellent <hi rend="italic">Bibliographie de la Chine.</hi> </note> The chief points were (1) the lawfulness and expediency of certain terms
                    employed by the Jesuits in naming God Almighty, such as <hi rend="italic">Tien,
                        “</hi> Heaven' and <hi rend="italic">Shangai,</hi> “ Supreme Ruler ” or “
                    Emperorinstead of <hi rend="italic">Tien-Chu,</hi> “ Lord of Heaven’ and in
                    particular the erection of inscribed tablets in the churches, on which these
                    terms were made use of; <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                        n="3"> Compare Browning, <hi rend="italic">The Ring ana the Book,</hi> x.,
                        The Pope, 1589-1603. </note> (2) in respect to the ceremonial offerings made
                    in honour of Confucius, and of personal ancestors, which Ricci had recognized as
                    merely “ civil ” observances; (3) the erection of tablets in honour of ancestors
                    in private houses; and (4), more generally sanction and favour accorded to
                    ancient Chinese sacred books and philosophical doctrine, as not really
                    trespassing on Christian faith.</p>
                <p>Probably no European name of past centuries is so well known in China as that of <hi rend="italic">Li-ma-leu,</hi> the form in which the name of Ricci
                    (Rt-cci <hi rend="italic">Mat-leo)</hi> was adapted to Chinese usage, and by
                    which he appears in Chinese records.The works which he composed in Chinese are
                    numerous; a list of them (apparently by no means complete, however) will be
                    found in Kircher <hi rend="sup">i</hi> S <hi rend="italic">China Illustrata,</hi> and also in Abel <hi rend="italic">Remusat''sNouveasuzanges Asiatiques</hi> (ii. 213-15). They are said to display an aptitude for clothing ideas in a
                    Chinese dress very rare and remarkable in a foreigner. One of the first which
                    attracted attention and reputation among Chinese readers was a Treatise upon
                    Friendship, in the form of a dialogue containing short and pithy paragraphs;
                    this is stated in the <hi rend="italic">De Expeditione</hi> to have been
                    suggested during Ricci’s stay at Nan-chang by a conversation with the prince of
                    Kien-ngan, who asked questions regarding the laws of friendship in the West.</p>
                <p>’The name comes forward prominently in the mouth of the emperor Kang-hi, in a
                    dialogue which took place between him ana Monsgr. Maigrot, the leader of the
                    anti-Jesuit movement (mentionea in Browning’s lines referred to above), at the
                    summer residence in Tartary, August 1706—a dialogue which the Jesuits have
                    reported with not a little malice:—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"> <hi rend="sup">ii</hi> Emperor,</hi> ‘ Tell me why do the people call me <hi rend="italic">Van-sui</hi> .(10,000 years)/ <hi rend="italic">The
                        Most Reverend (i.e.</hi> Maigrot), <hi rend="sup">4</hi> To express their
                    desire for your Majesty’s long life.’ <hi rend="italic">Emp.</hi> * Good. You
                    see, then, Chinese words are not always to be taken literally. We pay cult to
                    Confucius and to the dead to express our respect for them. How is that
                    inconsistent with your religion? When did it begin to be so? Is it since
                    Ly-Mattheu’s time? Hast thou ever read Ly-Mattheu ? ’ <hi rend="italic">The
                        Most Reverend,</hi> turning to P. Parenin, whispers, * Who’s he ? ’ and
                    learning that it was P. Matteo Ricci, . . . answered the emperor: ‘1 have not
                    read that book.’. <hi rend="italic">Emp.</hi> <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Ly-Mattheu and his fellows came hither some two
                    centuries ago; and before their time China never heard anything of the
                    Incarnation, anything of <hi rend="italic">Tien-chu,</hi> who had not become
                    incarnate in this part of the world. Why then, if it was lawful to call God <hi
                        rend="italic"> Tien</hi> before Ly-Mattheu’s time, should it be improper
                    now?’ ”— <hi rend="italic">Epistola de Eventu Apostolicae Legationis, scripta a
                        PP. Missionariis . . . ad Praepositum Generalem S. J.,</hi> An. 1706, 1
                    Novembris.</p>
                <p>In the early part of his residence <hi rend="bold">at</hi> Peking, when
                    enjoying constant intercourse with scholars of high position, Ricci brought out
                    the <hi rend="italic">T’ien-chu shih-i,</hi> or “ Veritable Doctrine of the
                    Lord of Heaven,” which deals with the divine character and attributes under
                    eight heads. “ This work,” says A. Wylie, “ contains some acute reasoning in
                    support of the propositions laid down, but the doctrine of faith in Christ is
                    very slightly touched upon. The teachings of Buddhism are vigorously attacked,
                    whilst the author tries to draw a parallel between Christianity and the
                    teachings of the Chinese literati.”</p>
                <p>In 1604 Ricci completed the <hi rend="italic">Erh-shih-wu yen,</hi> a scries of
                    short articles of moral bearing, but exhibiting little of the essential
                    doctrines of Christianity. <hi rend="italic">C hi-j en shih pien</hi> is
                    another of his productions, completed in 1608, and consisting of a record of ten
                    conversations held with Chinese of high position. The subjects are: (1) Years
                    past no [longer ours; (2) Man a sojourner on earth; (3) Advantage of frequent
                    contemplation of eternity; (4) Preparation for judgment by such contemplation;
                    (5) The good man not desirous of talking; (6) Abstinence, and its distinction
                    from the prohibition to take life; (7) Self-examination and self-reproof
                    inconsistent with inaction; (8) Future reward and punishment; (9) Piydng into
                    futurity hastens calamity; (10) Wealth with covetousness more wretched than
                    poverty with contentment. To this work is appended a translation of eight
                    European hymns, with elucidations, written in 1609.</p>
                <p>Some of the characteristics thus indicated may have suggested the bitterness of
                    attacks afterwards made upon Ricci’s theology. An example of these is found in
                    the work called <hi rend="italic">Anecdotes sur Vêlai de religion dans la Chine</hi> (Paris, 1733-35), the author of which (Abbé Villers) speaks of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> T’icn-chu shih-i</hi> in this fashion: “The Jesuit was also
                    so ill versed in the particulars of the faith that, as the holy bishop of Conon,
                    Monsgr. Maigrot, says of him, one need merely read his book on the true religion
                    to convince oneself that he had never imbibed the first elements of theology.” .
                    . .</p>
                <p>Ricci’s pointed attacks on Buddhism, and the wide circulation of his books,
                    called forth the opposition of the Buddhist clergy. One of the ablest who took
                    their part was Chu-hang, a priest of Hang-chow, who had abandoned the literary
                    status for the Buddhist cloister. He wrote three articles against the doctrine
                    of the missionaries. These were brought to Ricci’s notice in an ostensible tone
                    of candour by Yu-chim-he, a high mandarin at the capital. This letter, with
                    Ricci’s reply, the three Buddhist declamations and Ricci’s confutation, were
                    published in a collected form by the Christian Sen-Kwang-K’e.</p>
                <p>Another work of Ricci’s which attracted attention was the <hi rend="italic">Hsi-kuo fa,</hi> or “ Art of Memory as practised in the West.” Ricd was
                    himself a great expert in <hi rend="italic">memoria technica,</hi> and
                    astonished the Chinese by his performances in this line. He also wrote or edited
                    various Chinese works on geography, the celestial and terrestrial spheres,
                    geometry and arithmetic. And the detailed history of the mission was drawn out
                    by him, which after his death was brought home by P. Nicolas Trigault, and
                    published at Augsburg, and later in a complete form at Lyons under the name <hi
                        rend="italic"> De Expeditione Christiana apud Sinas Suscepta, 'ab Soc. Jesu,</hi> Ex P. Mat. Ricci ejusdem Societatis <hi rend="italic">Commentariis,</hi> Trigault himself adding many interesting notes on China and the Chinese.</p>
                <p>Among the scientific works which Ricci took into China was a set of maps, which
                    at first created great interest, but afterwards disgust when the Chinese came to
                    perceive the insignificant place assigned to the “ Middle Kingdom,” thrust, as
                    it seemed, into a corner, instead of being set in the centre of the world like
                    the gem in a ring. Ricci, seeing their dissatisfaction, set about constructing a
                    map of the hemisphere on a great scale, so adjusted that China, with its subject
                    states, filled the central</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r03-0290" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0313.jp2"/>
                <p>area, and, without deviating from truth of projection, occupied a large space in
                    proportion to the other kingdoms gathered round it. All the names entered in
                    Chinese calligraphy. This map obtained immense favour, and was immediately
                    engraved at the expense of the viceroy and widely circulated.</p>
                <p>In the accompanying cut we have endeavoured to portray this map. The projection
                    adopted is a perspective of the hemisphere as viewed from a point at the
                    distance of one diameter from the surface, and situated on the production of the
                    radius which passes through the intersection of 115° E. long. (Greenwich) with
                    30° N. lat. Something' near this must have been Li-ma-teu’s projection. With a
                    vertex much more distant the desired effect would be impaired, and with one
                    nearer neither of the poles would be seen, whilst the exaggeration of China
                    would have been too gross for a professed representation of the hemisphere.</p>
                <p>The chief facts of Ricci’s career are derived from Trigault; some contemporary
                    works on the rites controversy have also been consulted; in the notice of
                    Ricci’s Chinese writings valuable matter has been derived from <hi rend="italic"
                        > Notes on Chinese Literature</hi> by A. Wylie (London and Shanghai, 1867).
                    A number of Ricci’s letters are extant in the possession of the family, and
                    access to them was afforded to Giuseppe La Farina, author of the work caUed <hi
                        rend="italic"> La China, Considerata nella sua Storia,</hi> &amp;c.
                    (Florence, 1843), by the Marchese Amico Ricci of Macerata, living at Bologna. La
                    Farina’s quotations contain nothing of interest. There is a curious Chinese
                    account of Ricci published by Dr Breitschneider in the <hi rend="italic">China
                        Review,</hi> iv. 391 sq. (H. Y.)</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
