<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r02-0245-01" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0268.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>RHINTHON</label>
<hi rend="smallcaps">(c.</hi> 323-285 B.C.), Greek dramatist, son of a potter. He was probably a native of Syracuse and afterwards settled at Tarentum. He invented the <hi rend="italic">Iiilarotragoedia <hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi> a burlesque of tragic subjects. Such travesties were also called <hi rend="italic">Phlyaces</hi> (“ fooleries ”) and their writers <hi rend="italic">phlyacographi.</hi> Hc was the author of thirty-eight plays, of which only a few titles <hi rend="italic">(Amphitryon <hi rend="sub">i</hi> Herocles <hi rend="sub">i</hi> Orestes)</hi> and lines have been preserved, chiefly by the grammarians, as illustrating dialectic Tarentinc forms. The metre is iambic, in which the greatest Hcence is allowed. The <hi rend="italic">Amphitruo</hi> of Plautus, although probably imitated from a different writer (Archippus of the Middle Comedy), may be taken as a specimen of the manner in which such subjects were treated. There is no doubt that the hilaro-tragoedia exercised considerable influence on Latin comedy, the <hi rend="italic">Rhinthonica (i.e.</hi> fabula) being mentioned by various authorities amongst other kinds of drama known to the Romans. Scenes from these travesties are probably represented in certain vase paintings from Lower Italy, for which see H. Heydemann, “ Die Phlyakendarstellungen auf bemalten Vasen,” in <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch des archäologischen Instituts,</hi> i. (1886).</p><p>Fragments in monograph by E. Völker (Leipzig, 1887); see also E. Sommerbrodt, <hi rend="italic">De Phlyacographici Graecorum</hi> (Breslau, 1875); W. Christ, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der griechischen Litteratur</hi> (1898).</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>