<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0332.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0326-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEWER</label>,
<hi rend="italic">in the Houſehold,</hi> an officer who arranges on the table the diſhes of a king or nobleman.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sewer,</hi> is also a pssage or gutter made to carry water into the ſea or a river, whereby to preſerve the land, &amp;e. from inundations and other annoyances.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Court of Commſsioners of</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sewers</hi> <hi rend="italic">in England,</hi> a temporary tribunal, erected by virtue of a commiſſion under the great ſeal ; which formerly uſed to be granted <hi rend="italic">pro re nata</hi> at the pleaſure of the crown, but now at the discretion and nomination of the lord chancellor, lord treaſurer, and chief juſtices, purſuant to the ſtatute 23 Hen. VIII. c. 5. Their juriſdiction is to overlook the repairs of ſea-banks and ſea-walls, and the cleansing of rivers, public ſtreams, ditches, and other conduits, whereby any waters are carried off ; and is confined to ſuch county or particular diſtrict as the commiſſion ſhall expreſsly name. The commiſſioners are a court of record, and may fine and imprison for contempts ; and in the execution of their duty may proceed by jury, or upon their own view, and may take order for the removal of any annoyances, or the ſafeguard and conſervation of the ſewers within their commiſſion, either according to the laws and cuſtoms of Romney-marſh, or otherwiſe at their own diſcretion. They may alſo aſſess ſuch rates or foots upon the owners of lands within their diſtrict as they ſhall judge neceffary : and if any person refuſes to pay them, the commiſſioners may levy<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0333.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0327"/>
the ſame by diſtreſs of his goods and chattels ; or they may, by ſtatute 23 Hen. VIII. c. 5. ſell hrs freehold- lands (and by the 7 Ann. c. 10. his copyhold alſo), in order to pay ſuch ſcots or asseſſments. But their conduct is under the controul of the court of King’s-bench, which will prevent or puniſh any illegal or tyrannical proceedings. And yet in the reign of King James I. (8th Nov. 1616.), the privy-council took upon them to order, that no action or complaint ſhould be proſecuted againſt the commiſſioners unleſs before that board; and committed ſeveral to priſon who had brought ſuch actions at common law, till they ſhould releaſe the ſame: and one of the reaſons for diſcharging Sir Edward Coke from his office of lord chief-juſtice, was for countenancing thoſe legal proceedings. The pretence for theſe arbitrary meaſures was no other than the tyrant’s plea of the <hi rend="italic">necessity</hi> of unlimited powers in works of evident utility to the public, “ the ſupreme reaſon above all reaſons, which is the ſalvation of the king’s lands and people.” But now it is clearly held, that this (as well as all other inferior juriſdictions) is ſubject to the diſcretionary coercion of his majeſty’s court of King’s- bench.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Common</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Sewers,</hi> in Rome, were executed at a great expence. It was propoſed that they ſhould be of ſufficient dimenſions to admit a waggon loaded with hay. When theſe common ſewers came to be obſtructed, or out of repair, under the republic, the cenſors contracted to pay a thouſand talents, or about 193,000 l. for clearing and repairing them. They were again in diſrepair at the acceſſion of Auguſtus Cæsar, and the re- inflating them is mentioned among the great works of Agrippa. He is laid to have turned the courſe of ſeven rivers into theſe ſubterraneous passages, to have made them navigable, and to have actually paſſed in barges under the ſtreets and buildings of Rome. Theſe works are ſtill ſuppoſed to remain ; but as they exceed the power and reſources of the preſent city to keep them in repair, they are quite concealed, except at one or two places. They were in the midſt of the Roman greatneſs, and ſtill are, reckoned among the wonders of the world ; and yet they are ſaid to have been works of the elder Tarquin, a prince whoſe territory did not extend, in any direction, above 16 miles; and, on this ſuppoſition, they muſt have been made to accommodate a city that was calculated chiefly for the reception of cattle, herdſmen, and banditti. Rude nations ſometimes execute works of great magnificence, as fortreſſes and temples, for the purpoſes of war and ſuperſtition ; but ſeldom palaces, and ſtill more ſeldom works of mere convenience and cleanlineſs, in which for the most part they are long defective. It is not unreaſonable, therefore, to queſtion the authority of tradition in respect to this singular monument of antiquity, which ſo greatly exceeds what the beſt accommodated city of modern Europe could undertake for its own conveniency. And as thoſe works are ſtill entire, and may continue ſo for thouſands of years, it may be ſuſpected that they were even prior to the ſettlement of Romulus, and may have been thc remains of a more ancient city, on the ruins of which the followers of Romulus fettled, as the Arabs now hut or encamp on the ruins of Palmyra and Balbeck. Livy owns, that the common ſewers were not accommodated to the plan of Rome, as</p><p>it was laid out in his time ; they were carried in directions acroſs the ſtreets, and paſſed under buildings of the greateſt antiquity. This derangement indeed he imputes to the haſty rebuilding of the city after its destruction by the Gauls ; but haste, it is probable, would have determined the people to build on their old foundations, or at leaſt not to change them ſo much as to croſs the direction of former ſtreets.</p></div></body></text></TEI>