<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0247.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0241-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEDITION</label>,
among civilians, is uſed for a factious commotion of the people, or an aſſembly of a number of citizens without lawful authority, tending to diſturb the peace and order of the ſociety. This offence is of different kinds: ſome ſeditions more immediately threatening the ſupreme power, and the ſubverſion of the preſent conſtitution of the ſtate; others tending only towards the redreſs of private grievances. Among the Romans, therefore, it was variouſly puniſhed, according as its end and tendency threatened greater miſchieſ. See lib. i. <hi rend="italic">Cod. de Seditiosis,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mat. de Crimin. lib.</hi> ii. n. 5. <hi rend="italic">de Loeſa Majestate.</hi> In the puniſhment, the authors and ringleaders were justly diſtinguished from thoſe who, with leſs wicked intention, joined and made part of the multitude.</p><p>The ſame diſtinction holds in the law of England and in that of Scotland. Some kinds of Edition in England amount to high treaſon, and come within the flat. 25 Edw. III. as levying war againſt the king. And ſeveral ſeditions are mentioned in the Scotch acts of parliament as treaſonable. <hi rend="italic">Bayne’s Grim. Law of Scotland,</hi> p. 33, 34. The law of Scotland makes riotous and tumultuous aſſemblies a ſpecies of ſedition. But the law there, as well as in England, is now chiefly<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0248.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0242"/>
regulated by the riot act, made 1 Geo. I. only it is to be obſerved, that the proper officers in Scotland, to make the proclamation thereby enacted, are ſheriffs, ſtewards, and bailies of regalities, or their deputies; magiſtrates of royal boroughs, and all other inferior judges and magiſtrates; high and petty conſtables, or other officers of the peace, in any county, ſtewartry, city, or town. And in that part of the iſland, the puniſhment of the offence is any thing ſhort of death which the judges, in thecir diſcretion, may appoint.</p></div></body></text></TEI>