<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0267.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0261-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEMI</label>,
a word borrowed from the Latin, ſignifying <hi rend="italic">half ;</hi> but only uſed in composition with other words, as in the following articles.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SEMI_Arians,</hi> in eccleſiaſtieal hiſtory, a branch of the ancient Arians, conſiſting, according to Epiphanius, of ſuch as, in appearance, condemned the errors of that hereſiarch, but yet acquieſced in ſome of the principles thereof, only palliating and hiding them under softer and more moderate terms. Though they ſeparated from the Arian faction (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Arians),</hi> they could never be brought to acknowledge that the Son was homoouſios, that is, conſubſtantial, or of the ſame ſubſtance with the Father ; they would only allow him to be homoiouſios, that is, of a like ſubſtance with the Father, or ſimilar to the Father in his eſſence, not by nature, but by a peculiar privilege.</p><p>The ſemi-arianiſm of the moderns conſists in their maintaining that the Son was from all eternity begotten by the <hi rend="italic">will</hi> of the Father, contrary to the doctrine of the orthodox, who ſeem to teach that the eternal generation is <hi rend="italic">neceſſary.</hi> Such at leaſt are the respective opinions of Dr Clarke and Bishop Bull. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semicircle,</hi> in geometry, half a circle, or that figure comprehended between the diameter of the circle and half its circumference.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semicolon,</hi> in grammar, one of the points or ſtons uſed to diſtinguiſh the several members of a ſentence from each other.</p><p>The mark or character of the ſemicolon is (;), and has its name as, being of somewhat leſs effect than a colon ; or as demanding a ſhorter pauſe.</p><p>The proper uſe of the ſemicolon is to diſtinguiſh the conjunct members of a ſentence. Now, by a conjunct member of a ſentence is meant ſuch a one as contains at leaſt two simple members.—Whenever, then, a ſentence can be divided into ſeveral members of the ſame degree, which are again diviſible into other ſimple members, the former are to be ſeparated by a ſemicolon. For inſtancc : “ If fortune bear a great ſway over him, who has nicely ſtated and concerted every circumſtance of an affair ; we muſt not commit every thing, without reſerve, to fortune, left ſhe have too great a hold of us." Again : <hi rend="italic">Si quantum in agro lociſque deſertis audacia poteſt, tantum in foro atque judiciis impudentia valeret ; non minus in causa cederet Aulus Caecinna Sexta Æbutii impu∙</hi><pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0268.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0262"/>
<hi rend="italic">denties, quam tum in vi facienda cessit audaciae.</hi> An inſtance in a more complex ſentence we have in Cicero : <hi rend="italic">Res familiaris primum bene parta sit, nulloque turpi quaestu: tum quam plurimis, modo dignis, ſe utilem praebeat; deinde augeatur ratione, diligentia, parsimonia ; nec libidini potius luxuriaeque, quam liberalitati et beneficentiis pareat·</hi></p><p>But though the proper uſe of the ſemicolon be to diſtinguiſh conjunct members, it is not neceſſary that all the members divided hereby be conjunct. For upon dividing a ſentence into great and equal parts, if one of them be conjunct, all thoſe other parts of the ſame degree are to be diſtmguiſhed by a ſemicolon.—Sometimes alſo it happens, that members that are oppoſite to each other, but relate to the ſame verb, are separated by a ſemicolon. Thus Cicero : <hi rend="italic">Ex hαc parte pudor, illinc petulantia ; hinc fides illinc fraudatio ; hinc pietas, illinc scelus</hi>, &amp;c. To this likewiſe may be referred ſuch ſentences, where the whole going before, the parts follow: as “ The parts of oratory are four ; invention, diſpoſition, elocution, and pronunciation.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semicubium,</hi> in medicine, an half-bath, wherein the patient is only placed up to the navel.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semidiameter,</hi> half the diameter, or a right line drawn from the centre of a circle or ſphere to its circumference ; being the ſame with what is otherwrſe called the <hi rend="italic">radius.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semiflosculus,</hi> in botany, a term uſed to expreſs the flowers of the ſyngeneſia claſs. Theſe ſemifloſculi are petals, hollow in their lower part, but in their upper flat, and continued in the ſhape of a tongue.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Semitone,</hi> in mulic. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Interval.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>