<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0449.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0443-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SHORE</label>,
a place waſhed by the ſea, or by ſome large river.</p><p>Count Marſigli divides the ſea-ſhore into three portions : the firſt of which is that track of land which the ſea juſt reaches in ſtorms and high tides, but which it never covers ; the second part of the ſhore is that which is covered in high tides and ſtorms, but is dry at other times ; and the third is the deſcent from this, which is always covered with water.</p><p>The firſt part is only a continuation of the continent, and ſuffers no alteration from the neighbourhood of the ſea, except that it is rendered fit for the growth of ſome plants, and wholly unfit for that of others, by the ſaline steams and impregnations : and it is ſcarce to be conceived by any, but thoſe who have obſerved it, how far on land the effects of the ſea reach, ſo as to make the earth proper for plants which will not grow without this influence ; there being ſeveral plants frequently found on high hills and dry places, at three, four, and more miles from the ſea, which yet would not grow unleſs in the neighbourhood of it, nor will ever be found elſewhere.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0450.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0444"/>
The ſecond part or portion of the ſhore is much more affected by the ſea than the former, being frequently waſhed and beaten by it. Its productions are rendered ſalt by the water, audit is covered with sand, or with the fragments of ſhells in form of fand, and in ſome places with a tartarous matter depoſited from the water ; the colour of this whole extent of ground is uſually duſky and dull, eſpecially where there are rocks and ftones, and theſe covered with a ſlimy matter.</p><p>The third part of the ſhore is more affected by the ſea than either of the others ; and is covered with an uniform crust of the true nature of the bottom of the ſea, except that plants and animals have their reſidence in it, and the decayed parts of theſe alter it a little.</p></div></body></text></TEI>