<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0254.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0248-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SEISIN</label>,
in law, ſignifies poſſeſſion. In this ſenſe we ſay, <hi rend="italic">premier seisin,</hi> for the firſt poſſeſſion, &amp;c.</p><p>Seiſin is divided into that <hi rend="italic">in deed</hi> or <hi rend="italic">in fact,</hi> and that <hi rend="italic">in law.</hi> A ſeiſin in <hi rend="italic">deed</hi> is where a poſſeſſion is actually taken : but a ſeiſin in <hi rend="italic">law</hi> is, where lands deſcend, and the party has not entered thereon ; or in other words, it is where a perſon has a right to lands, &amp;c. and is by wrong diſſeiſed of them. A ſeiſin in law is held to be ſufficient to avow on ; though to the bringing of an aſſize, actual ſeiſin is required; and where ſeiſin is alleged, the perſon pleading it muſt ſhow of what eſtate he is ſeiſed, &amp;c.</p><p>Seiſin of a ſuperior ſervice is deemed to be a ſeiſin<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0255.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0249"/>
of all superior and casual ſervices that are incident thereto ; and ſeiſin of a leſſee for years, is ſufficient for him in reverſion.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Livery oſ</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Seisin,</hi> in law, an eſſential ceremony in the conveyance of landed property ; being no other than the pure feodal inveſtiture, or delivery of corporal poſſeſſion of the land or tenement. This was held abſolutely neceſſary to complete the donation ; <hi rend="italic">Nam feudam sine inνestiitura nullo modo constitui potuit :</hi> and an eſtate was then only perfect when, as Fleta expreſſee it in our law, fi <hi rend="italic">t juris et seisinae cοnjunctio.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">FeofM</hi> ENT.</p><p>Inveſtitures, in their original rife, were probably intended to demonſtrate in conquered countries the actual poſſeſſion of the lord ; and that he did not grant a bare litigious right, which the ſoldier was ill qualified to proſecute, but a peaceable and firm poſſeſſion. And, at a time when writing was ſeldom practiſed, a mere oral gift, at a diſtance from the ſpot that was given, was not likely to be either long or accurately retained in the memory of byſtanders, who were very little intereſted in the grant. Afterwards they were retained as a public and notorious act, that the country might take notice of and teſtify the transfer of the eſtate; and that ſuch as claimed title by other means might know againſt whom to bring their actions.</p><p>In all well-governed nations, ſome notoriety of this kind has been ever held requiſite, in order to acquire and aſcertain the property of lands. In the Roman law, <hi rend="italic">plenum dominium</hi> was not ſaid to ſubſiſt unleſs where a man had both the <hi rend="italic">right</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">corporal poſſeſſion;</hi> which poſſeſſion could not be acquired without both an actual intention to poſſeſs, and an actual ſeiſin, or entry into the premiſſes, or part of them in the name of the whole. And even in ecclesiaſtical promotions, where the freehold paſſes to the perſon promoted, corporal poſſeſſion is required at this day to veſt the property completely in the new proprietor ; who, according to the diſtinction of the canoniſts, acquires the <hi rend="italic">jus ad rem,</hi> or inchoate and imperfect right, by nomination and institution ; but not the <hi rend="italic">jus in re,</hi> or complete and full right, unleſs by corporal poſſeſſion. Therefore in dignities poſſeſſion is given by inſtalment ; in rectories and vicarages by indiction; without which no temporal rights accrue to the miniſter, though every ecclefiaſtical power is veſted in him by inſtitution. So also even in deſcents of lands, by our law, which are caſt on the heir by act of the law itſelf, the heir has not <hi rend="italic">plenum dominium,</hi> or full and complete ownerſhip, till he has made an actual corporal entry into the lands ; for if he dies before <hi rend="italic">entry</hi> made, <hi rend="italic">his</hi> heir ſhall not be entitled to take the poſſeſſion, but the heir of the perſon who was laſt actually ſeiſed. It is not therefore only a mere right to enter, but the actual entry, that makes a man complete owner ; ſo as to tranſmit the inheritance to his own heirs : <hi rend="italic">non jus, sed seisina, ſacit stipitem.</hi></p><p>Yet the corporal tradition of lands being ſometimes inconvenient, a ſymbolical delivery of poſſeſſion was in many caſes anciently allowed ; by transferring ſomething near at hand, in the preſence of credible witneſſes, which by agreement ſhould ſerve to repreſent the very thing deſigned to be conveyed ; and an occupancy of this sign or ſymbol was permitted as equivalent to occupancy of the land itſelf. Among the Jews we find the evidence of a purchaſe thus defined in the book of Ruth ; “ Now this was the manner in former time in Iſrael, concerning redeeming and concerning changing, for to confirm all things : a man plucked off his ſhoe, and gave it to his neighbour ; and this was a teſtimony in Iſrael.” Among the ancient Goths and Swedes, contracts for the ſale of lands were made in the preſence of witneſſes, who extended the cloak of the buyer, while the ſeller caſt a clod of the land into it, in order to give poſſeſſion ; and a ſtaff or wand was alſo delivered from the vender to the vendee, which paſſed through the hands of the witneſſes. With our Saxon anceſtors the delivery of a turf was a neceſtary ſolemnity to eſtabliſh the conveyance of lands. And, to this day, the conveyance of our copyhold eſtates is uſually made from the ſeller to the lord or his ſteward by delivery of a rod or verge, and then from the lord to the purchaſer by re-delivery of the ſame in the preſence of a jury of tenants.</p><p>Conveyances in writing were the laſt and moſt refined improvement. The mere delivery of poſſeſſion, either actual or ſymbolical, depending on the ocular teſtimony and remembrance of the witneſſes, was liable to be forgotten or miſrepreſented, and became frequently incapable of proof. Beſides, the new occalions and neceſſities introduced by the advancement of commerce, required means to be devised of charging and incumbering eſtates, and of making them liable to a multitude of conditions and minute deſignations, for the purpoſes of raising money, without an abſolute ſale of the land; and ſometimes the like proceedings were found uſeful in order to make a decent and competent proviſion for the numerous branches of a family, and for other domeſtic views. None of which could be effected by a mere, ſimple, corporal ttansſer of the soil from one man to another, which was principally calculated for conveying an abſolute unlimited dominion. Written deeds were therefore introduced, in order to ſpecify and perpetuate the peculiar purpoſes of the party who conveyed : yet ſtill, for a very long series of years, they were never made uſe of, but in company with the more ancient and notorious method of transfer by delivery of corporal poſſeſſion.</p><p>Livery of ſeiſin, by the common law, is neceſſary to be made upon every grant of an eſtate of freehold in hereditaments corporeal, whether of inheritance or for life only. In hereditaments incorporeal it is impoſſible to be made ; for they are not the object of the ſenfes : and in leaſes for years, or other chattel intereſts, it is not neceſſary. In leaſes for years indeed an actual <hi rend="italic">entry</hi> is neceſſary, to veſt the eſtate in the leſſee: for a bare leaſe gives him only a right to enter, which is called his intereſt in the term, or <hi rend="italic">interesse termini :</hi> and when he enters in purſuance of that right, he is then, and not before, in poſſeſſion of his term, and complete tenant for years. This entry by the tenant himſelf ſerves the purpoſe of notoriety, as well as livery of ſeiſin from the granter could have done ; which it would have been improper to have given in this caſe, becauſe that ſolemnity is appropriated to the conveyance of a freehold. And this is one reaſon why freeholds cannot be made to commence <hi rend="italic">in ſuturo,</hi> becauſe they cannot (at the common law) be made but by livery of ſeiſin ; which livery, being an actual manual tradition of the land, must take effect <hi rend="italic">in praeſenti,</hi> or not at all.</p><p>Livery of ſeiſin is either in <hi rend="italic">deed</hi> or in <hi rend="italic">law.</hi><pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0256.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0250"/>
Livery in <hi rend="italic">deed</hi> is thus performed. The feoffor, leſſor, or his attorney, together with the feoffee, leſſee, or his attorney, (for this may as effectually be done by deputy or attorney as by the principals themſelves in person), come to the land or to the houſe ; and there, in the preſence of witneſſes, declare the contents of the feoffment or leaſe on which livery is to be made. And then the feoffor, if it be of land, doth deliver to thc feoffee, all other perſons being out of the ground, a clod or turf, or a twig or bough there growing, with words to this effect : “ I deliver theſe to you in the name of ſeisin of all the lands and tenements contained in this deed.” But, if it be of a houſe, the feoffor must take the ring or latch of the door, the houſe being quite empty, and deliver it to the feoffee in the same form ; and then the feoffee muſt enter alone, and ſhut the door, and then open it, and let in the others. If the conveyance or feoffment be of divers lands, lying ſcattered in one and the same county, then in the feoffor’s poſſession, livery of ſeisin of any parcel, in the name of the rest, ſufficeth for all ; but if they be in ſeveral counties, there muſt be as many liveries as there are counties. For, if the title to theſe lands comes to be diſputed, there muſt be as many trials as there are counties, and the jury of one county are no judges of the notoriety of a fact in another. Beſides, anciently, this ſeisin was obliged to be delivered <hi rend="italic">coram paribus de vicineto,</hi> before the peers or freeholders of the neighbourhood, who atteſted ſuch delivery in the body or on the back of the deed ; according to the rule of the ſeodal law, <hi rend="italic">Pares debent interesse inveſliturae feudi, et non alii :</hi> for which this reason is expressly given ; becauſe the peers or vaſſals of the lord, being bound by their oath of fealty, will take care that no fraud be committed to his prejudice, which strangers might be apt to connive at. And though afterwards the ocular atteſtation of the <hi rend="italic">pares</hi> was held unneccſſary, and livery might be made before any credible witneſſes, yet the trial, in caſe it was diſputed, (like that of all other atteſtations), was ſtill reſerved to the <hi rend="italic">pares</hi> or jury of the county. Alſo, if the lands be out on leaſe, though all lie in the same county, there muſt be as many liveries as there are tenants : becauſe no livery can be made in this caſe, but by the conſent of the particular tenant ; and the conſent of one will not hind the rest. And in all theſe caſes it is prudent, and usual, to endorſe the livery of ſeisin on the back of the deed, ſpecifying the manner, place, and time of making it ; together with the names of the witneſſes. And thus</p><p>much for livery in deed.</p><p>Livery in <hi rend="italic">law</hi> is where the ſame is not made <hi rend="italic">on</hi> the land, but <hi rend="italic">in sight of it</hi> only ; the feoffor ſaying to the feoffee, “ I give you yonder land, enter and take poſſeſſion.” Here, if the feoffee enters during the life of the feoffor, it is a good lively, but not otherwise ; unleſs he dares not enter through fear of his life or bodily harm ; and then his continual claim; made yearly in due form of law, as near as poſſible to the lands, will ſuffice without an entry. This livery in law cannot, however, be given or received by attorney, but only by the parties themſelves.</p></div></body></text></TEI>