<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0318.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s03-0312-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SERRATED</label>,
in general, ſomething indented or notched in the manner of a ſaw ; a term much uſed in the deſcription of the leaves of plants. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany.</hi> SERRATULA, <hi rend="smallcaps">saw-wort,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of ſyngeneſia, and to the order of polygamia æqualis. In the natural ſyſtem it is ranged under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Compositœ.</hi> The calyx is ſubcylindrical, imbricated ; the ſcales of it pointed, but not spinous. There are 15 ſpecies : The tinctoria, alpina, arvenſis, coronata, japonica, ſalicifolia, multiflora, noveboracenſis, præalta, glauca, ſquarroſa, ſcarioſa, ſpicata, amara, and centauroidcs. The three firſt ſpecies</p><p>arc Britiſh. I. The <hi rend="italic">tintoria</hi> is diſtinguiſhed by a stem erect and ſlender, branched at the top, and three feet high. The leaves are ſmooth, pinnatifid, and ſerrated ; The flowers are purple, in umbels, and terminal. The down of the seed is gloſſy, with a brown or gold tinge. It grows in woods and wet paſtures. It dyes cloth of an exceeding fine yellow colour, which ſtands well when, fixed with alum. Goats eat this plant ; horſes are not fond of it ; cattle, ſwine, and ſheep, leave it untouched. 2. The <hi rend="italic">alρina,</hi> or mountain ſaw-wort, The root and stem are woody ; the latter being from one to two feet high. The leaves are numerous, triangular, long, pointed, ſubſtantial, dark green above, white beneath, and ſerrated, with round intervals between the teeth, on footſtalks. The flowers are purple. The ſcales of the calyx are very ſhort and downy. It grows on high mountains, and flowers commonly in July or Auguſt. 3. The <hi rend="italic">arvenſis,</hi> corn ſaw-wort, or way-thiſtle. The stem is generally erect, branched, and two or three feet high. The leaves are ſinuated, ſerrated, and ſpinous ; thoſe above being almoſt entire. The flowers are of a pale purple ; the down is very long·. This plant grows in cultivated grounds and by way- ſides, and flowers in July or Auguſt. When burned it yields good aſhes for making glaſs or fixed alkali.</p></div></body></text></TEI>