<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0607.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0532-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPELLING</label>,
in <hi rend="italic">Grammar,</hi> that part of orthography which teaches the true manner of resolving words into their syllables.</p><p>All words are either simple or compound, as <hi rend="italic">use, disuse; done, undone;</hi> and the rules for dividing each must be such as are derived from the analogy of language in general, or from the established custom of speaking ; which, for the English language, are reduced to the following rules : 1. A consonant between two vowels must be joined with the latter in spelling, as <hi rend="italic">nature, ve-ri-ly, ge-ne-rous ;</hi> except, however, the letter <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> which is joined to the first, as in <hi rend="italic">flax-en, ox-en,</hi> &amp;c <hi rend="italic">.,</hi> and compound words, as in <hi rend="italic">upon, unused,</hi> &amp;c. 2. A double consonant must be divided, as in <hi rend="italic">letteτ, manner,</hi> &amp;c. 3. Those consonants which can begin a word, must not be parted in spelling, as in <hi rend="italic">defraud, re-prove, distinct :</hi> this rule, however, is sometimes found to fail ; for though <hi rend="italic">gn</hi> begins a word, as in <hi rend="italic">gnaw, gnat,</hi> &amp;c., yet it must be divided in spelling, as in <hi rend="italic">cog-ni-zance, ma-lig-ni-ty,</hi> &amp;c. 4. Those consonants which cannot begin a word must be divided, as <hi rend="italic">ld</hi> in <hi rend="italic">seldom, lt</hi> in <hi rend="italic">multitude, mp</hi> in <hi rend="italic">tem-per, rd</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ar-dent ;</hi> but in final syllables there are exceptions, as <hi rend="italic">tl</hi> in <hi rend="italic">title, dl</hi> in <hi rend="italic">handle,</hi> &amp;c. 5. When two vowels come to gether, and are both of them distinctly sounded, they must be separated in spelling, as in <hi rend="italic">co-e-val, mutual,</hi> &amp;c. 6. The grammatical terminations or endings must be separated in spelling, as <hi rend="italic">ed</hi> in <hi rend="italic">wing-ed, edst</hi> in <hi rend="italic">de-li-ver-edst,ing</hi> in <hi rend="italic">hearing, αnce</hi> in <hi rend="italic">deliverance, &amp;c</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> .</hi> 7. Compound words must be resolved into their simple and component words, <hi rend="italic">as up on, into, neverthe∙less, not∙withstand∙ing,</hi> &amp;c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>