<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0651.jpf" type="entry"
                xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0570-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SECTION I</label> —CONSIDERATIONS OP A GENERAL NATURE</p>
                <p>REGARDING THE PROPERTIES, PHENOMENA AND APPLICATIONS OF STEAM.</p>
                <p>1. * <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam</hi> is the name given in our language to the
                    visible, moist vapour which arises from all bodies which contain juices easily
                    expelled from them by heats not sufficient for their combustion. Thus we say,
                    the steam of boiling water, of malt, of a tan-bed. It is distinguished from
                    smoke by its not having been produced by combus tion, by not containing any
                    soot, and by its being condensible by cold into water, oil, inflammabIe spirits, or liquids composed of
                    these.</p>
                <p>2. * We see it rise in great abundance from bodies when they are heated, forming
                    a white cloud, which diffuses itself and disappears at no very great distance
                    from the body from which it was produced. In this case the surrouuding air is
                    found loaded with the water or moisture which seems to have produced it, and the
                    steam seems to be completely soluble in air, composing, while thus united, a
                    transparent elastic fluid.</p>
                <p>3. * But, in order to its appearance in the form of an <hi rend="italic">opaque
                        white</hi> cloud, the mixture with or dissemination in air seems necessary.
                    If a teakettle boils violently, so that the steam is formed at the spout in
                    great abundance, it may be observed, that the visible cloud is not formed at the
                    very mouth of the spout, but at a small distance before it, and that the vapour
                    is perfectly invisible at its first emission. This is rendered still more
                    evident by fitting to the spout of the teakettle a glass pipe of any length, and
                    of as large a diameter as we please. The steam is produced as copiously as
                    without this pipe, but the vapour is transparent and colourless throughout the
                    whole of the pipe. Nay, if this pipe communicate with a glass vessel terminating
                    in another pipe, and if the vessel be kept sufficiently hot, the steam will be
                    as abundantly produced at the mouth of this second pipe as before, and the
                    vessel will remain quite transparent. The visibility, therefore, of the matter
                    which constitutes the steam is an accidental circumstance, and appears to
                    require its dissemination in the air ; and we know that one perfectly
                    transparent body, when minutely divided and diffused among the parts of another
                    transparent body, but not dissolved in it, makes a mass which is visible. Thus
                    oil beaten up with water makes a <hi rend="italic">white opaque</hi> mass.</p>
                <p>4. If the column of steam which ascends from a boiler that is suddenly opened, be
                    observed in a clear dry day, when the sun is shining, the column of vapour,
                    gradually widening as it rises, will be observed to be of a very brilliant
                    silvery white, and will cast a strong dark shadow upon the objects which it
                    intercepts from the direct rays of the sun : but, if the observer be placed in
                    this shadow, the sun will appear to him to be of a strong tawny, or fiery red
                    colour, or, if the column be very dense, the sun will be invisible. These
                    appearances closely resemble some phenomena of the clouds, which we know are
                    corn posed of watery vapour, and which sometimes appear of a fleecy white, again
                    of a fiery red or a burnished gold colour, or again of a dappled grey, down
                    through every degree of darkness, until the vapour become so dense and opaque as
                    altogether to obscure the light of the sun by a thick black cloud. These
                    appearances have been satisfactorily accounted for. Steam, in its attenuated
                    state, is a transparent, invisible, colourless gas. When disseminated through
                    the air, in excessive quantities, small globuIes are formed, of a film of water,
                    enclosing light vapour. These globules, floating thickly in the air, form an
                    aggregation of minute films of fluid, capable of reflecting and transmitting
                    light. When we are so placed that the light may be reflected to us, and when the
                    cloud is so thick as to reflect it completely, we have the same brilliant white
                    which results from the comminution of glass, rosin, ice, and other transparent
                    media ; and, nt the same time, an observer, placed on the opposite side of the
                    cloud, sees it as a dense black opaque mass, because the light being totally<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0652.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0571"/>
                    reflected, none of it can be transmitted to him. The richer colours transmitted
                    by thinner strata of vapour are thus noticed by M Leopold Nobili of Reggio. “
                    The tints exhibited by the clouds in every variety of aspect are al most all
                    comprised in Sir Isaac Newton’s first ring (the white, yellow, orange, red ; or
                    the blood, tawny, copper, ochre, and fire red, and vialaceous red, or No. 1—12
                    of Mr Nobili’s scale). Tints of this kind do not arise from refraction and
                    diffraction, they are produced only <hi rend="italic">by means of thin
                        plates.</hi> Now the measurements of Sir Isaac New ton have shown what are
                    the dimensions of the layers of air, of water, and of glass, which produce the
                    colours of the several rings ; and, as we know that the vesicular vapours are
                    formed of water, and that they do not reflect or transmit any other tint, we may
                    conclude that their external film is in no case thicker than ten millionth parts
                    of an inch. This result appears to me to be so decidedly certain as to be
                    entitled to a place in science.” It was to the effect of thin plates on light
                    that Newton referred the colours of all bodies ; and the accounting for the rich
                    golden hues of the clouds, and the fiery red colour of light passing through
                    dispersed steam, by the effect of the thin plates of water enclosing the vapoury
                    spheroids of pure steam, must be regarded as one of the most satisfactory
                    applications of his theory. (See article <hi rend="smallcaps">Optics</hi>.)</p>
                <p>5. A very singular phenomenon takes place, if the flame of a candle or lamp be
                    held below a jet of steam, as it issues from the mouth of a small pipe ; the
                    steam instantly ceases to be visible. In this case, one of two changes may be
                    conceived to take place, either or both of which account for the permanent
                    invisibility of the vapour : the intense heat of the flame may disperse the
                    particles to such a distance, that there does not remain in a given space a
                    sufficient number to form a vesicle of vapour, and it therefore remains diffused
                    in combination with the air, which always holds a large quantity of invisible
                    vapour, especially at high temperatures ; or the vapour may be decomposed by the
                    flame into the permanent and invisible gnses, of which it consists, which may
                    again become combined, to a certain extent, with the burning substance, and
                    support the flame.</p>
                <p>6. *When steam is produced, the water gradually wastes in the teakettle, and will
                    soon be totally expended if we continue it on the fire. It is reasonable,
                    therefore, to suppose that this steam is nothing but water, changed by heat into
                    an aerial or elastic form. If so, we should expect that the privation of this
                    heat would leave it in the form of water again. Accordingly, this is fully
                    verified by experiment ; for, if the pipe fitted to the teakettle be surrounded
                    with ice, or any cold substance, no steam will issue, but water will continually
                    trickle from it in drops : and if the process be conducted with the proper
                    precautions, the water which we thus obtain from the pipe will be found equal in
                    quantity to that which disappears from the teakettle. Steam is therefore the
                    matter of water, converted by heat into an elastic vapour.</p>
                <p>7. Steam, water, and ice, are three conditions of the same substance, which it
                    assumes under different circum stances of heat and of external pressure. In each
                    condition it obeys different laws ; as a solid, ice obeys the laws of the
                    mechanics of solid bodies : in Russia it is quarried Iike rock, and is used for
                    building houses and paving ways ; it is cast into moulds for domestic purposes,
                    like iron or lead ; it is painted like alabaster, and chiselled like marble : ns
                    a liquid, water is the exemplar of the hydrostatical laws of all fluids : as a
                    vapour, it obeys the laws of aerostatics ; and we now know that steam is, in all
                    respects, similar in its constitution and phenomena to all other elastic fluids
                    or gases. If we apply heat to a bar of extremely cold ice, it expands like other
                    solids with heat, gradually elongating with its increased temperature, its
                    particles receding</p>
                <p>from one another by the repulsive action induced between the particles by the
                    entrance of caloric between them, the cohesion of the particles becoming less
                    and less, until at last, if the heat be continually thrown in, the cohesion of
                    the particles is altogether overcome, they lose their aggregation, they become
                    separable without effort, and, falling to pieces, the bar of ice loses its form
                    and subsides into water. When thus melted, the water being placed in a vessel,
                    and having heat applied to it, will, like other fluids, continue to expand from
                    its point of greatest den sity, and will increase in bulk nearly one-twentieth
                    by about 172°, but at last the entrance of so large a quantity of heat will
                    produce a repulsive force between the particles so strong as to cause them
                    suddenly to spring apart from one another, so as to recede to a distance twelve
                    times as far asunder as in the state of water, and they have now assumed the
                    aerial condition of gas or vapour, and constituting steam, occupy 1728 times
                    their original space. The ice passing into the condition of water, is said to be
                        <hi rend="italic">liquefied,</hi> and the heat necessary to convert ice into
                    water is called the <hi rend="italic">caloric of liquidity of ice,</hi> or the
                        <hi rend="italic">caloric of condition of water ;</hi> when water is con
                    verted into steam, the quantity of caloric necessary for this purpose is called
                    the <hi rend="italic">caloric of vaporization of water,</hi> or the <hi
                        rend="italic">caloric Of elasticity of steam,</hi> and the water is then
                    said to <hi rend="italic">boil</hi> or <hi rend="italic">evaporate.</hi> This
                    process may be reversed. If the steam have been collected in a close receptacle,
                    it may be squeezed by external compression into its original bulk, or by cooling
                    the outside so as to withdraw the caloric of elasticity from between the
                    particles, they may be allowed to come together by the at traction of cohesion,
                    and resuming their original proximity to each other, appear once more in their
                    former condition of water, and in this case the <hi rend="italic">vapour</hi> is
                    said to be <hi rend="italic">condensed ;</hi> and if the process of abstraction
                    of caloric, with sufficient pressure, be continued, the liquid particles
                    approaching each other, will gradually contract the bulk of the mass, and at a
                    certain point will take again the original character of ice, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">liquid</hi> is then said to be <hi rend="italic"
                        >congealed</hi> or <hi rend="italic">frozen.</hi> The same particles of
                    matter do “ thus in turn play many parts.”</p>
                <p>Ice melts and becomes water by increment of heat. Water evaporates into steam by
                    increment of heat. Steam is condensed into water by decrement of heat. Water
                    congeals into ice by decrement of heat.</p>
                <p>(8.) These phenomena are not confined to one sub</p>
                <p>stance : many substances, apparently the most refractory, have been melted and
                    again congealed, while other sub stances which had never been observed in any
                    other form than that of transparent air or invisible gas, have been condensed by
                    the expedients of modern artifice into liquids heavier than water, and have even
                    been congealed into hard and strong solids. To so great an extent has this taken
                    place, that we are now almost warranted in deducing, from a wide induction of
                    facts, the following generalization ; that all bodies assume the solid, liquid,
                    or gaseous condition, according to the accidents of temperature and pressure
                    under which they happen to be placed ; and that it is merely from the
                    circumstance of their being more ordinarily found, at the present temperature of
                    the earth and under the weight of our present atmosphere, in one of these states
                    rather than another, that some substances have been characterised and
                    distinguished, and classed as permanent solids, liquids, or airs. We now speak
                    of ice only as frozen water ; but had we lived under a temperature such as that
                    which the inhabitants of the planet Jupiter, at their distance from the sun, may
                    be conceived to endure, we should have spoken of swallowing <hi rend="italic"
                        >melted ice</hi> as we now speak of molten lead, and a separate name for
                    melted ice would have remained unknown ; or, if we conceive, in like manner, our
                    air to be withdrawn, and the<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0653.jpf"
                        xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0572"/> temperature of the earth raised above 212°, we
                    should then have moved under an atmosphere of steam of the same pressure as at
                    present, transparent and colourless, and might only have heard of water as a
                    curious substance obtained from the compression of the air. The phenomena of
                    steam are much simplified and more perfectly explained when we take this
                    enlarged view of its analogy with other kinds of matter.</p>
                <p>9. We are most familiar with steam when in the act of rising violently from
                    heated water in the process of <hi rend="italic">ebullition.</hi> The history of
                    steam at this crisis is highly instructive, and its phenomena may be studied
                    with advantage by examining it in a glass vessel placed over a strong lamp. When
                    heat is first applied, a rapid circulation of the fluid ensues. The water on the
                    bottom, being first heated and expanded, becoming lighter than the rest, rises
                    to the top, and is replaced by the current of colder water descending to receive
                    in its turn a further accession of heat. By and by, small globules of steam,
                    formed on the bottom and surrounded by a film of water, are observed adhering to
                    the glass ; as the heat increases they enlarge, in a short time several of them
                    unite, form a bubble larger than the others, and, detaching themselves from the
                    glass, rise upwards in the fluid. But they never reach the sur face ; they
                    encounter currents of water still comparatively cold, and descending to receive
                    from the bottom their sup ply of heat ; and encountering them, the bubbles are
                    robbed of their heat, shrivel up into their original bulk, and are lost among
                    the other particles of water. In a short time the mass of the water becomes more
                    uniformly heated, the bubbles, becoming larger and more frequent, are condensed
                    with a loud crackling noise, and at last, when the heat of the whole mass
                    reaches 212°, the bubbles from the bottom rise without condensation through the
                    water, swell and unite with others as they rise, and burst out upon the air in a
                    copious volume of steam, of the same heat as the water from which they are
                    formed, and pushing aside the air, make room for themselves. In this process, by
                    continuing the application of heat, the whole of the water may be “ boiled away”
                    or converted into steam.</p>
                <p>10. The singular sounds produced from a vessel of water exposed to heat,
                    previously to boiling, have attracted attention ; the water is then vulgarly
                    said to be simmering or singing ; and, when this takes place, it is because the
                    vessel is boiling at one place and comparatively cold at another. This noise is
                    most distinctly heard when the fire or flame applied is small, and its heat in
                    teuse, when the vessel is large and the water deep ; for in that case the
                    entrance of the caloric will take place more rapidly than the circulation can
                    convey it to the remote particles of fluid, and so bubbles of steam will form
                    rapidly at one place and be rapidly condensed at another ; the degree of
                    velocity with which such bubbles succeed will determine the pitch of the singing
                    tone. We have observed this phenomenon in greatest perfection when we have
                    attached a slender pipe to a close boiler producing steam, and carried its open
                    mouth, of the diameter of <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                        8</hi> or <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> of
                    an inch, down below the surface of cold water in a glass jar. When the mouth of
                    the steam-pipe is held just below the surface of the water, the steam issues
                    with great rapidity in small bubbles, producing an acute tone ; and, on the
                    other hand, when the pipe is held at a considerable depth, the concussions
                    become more violent and louder, their intervals of succession greater, the tone
                    is lowered, and finally, the shocks become detached, and so violent as to shake
                    the glass and surrounding objects with much force. On this subject Professor
                    Robison observes, *that a violent and remarkable phenomenon ap pears, if we
                    suddenly plunge a lump of red-hot iron into a vessel of cold water, taking care
                    that no red part be near the surface. If the hand be now applied to the</p>
                <p>side of the vessel, a most violent tremor is felt, and sometimes strong thumps ;
                    these arise from the collapsing of very large bubbles. If the upper part of the
                    iron be too hot, it warms the surrounding water so much, that the bubbles from
                    below come up through it uncondensed, and produce ebullition without concussion.
                    The great resemblance of this tremor to the sensation which we experience during
                    the shock of an earthquake, has led many to suppose that the latter is produced
                    in the same way ; and their hypothesis, notwithstanding the objections which we
                    have elsewhere stated to it, is by no means unfeasible. Any obstruction on the
                    bottom of a boiler, on the inside, as a piece of metal or stone introduced among
                    the water, may produce a succession of smart concussions by the sudden
                    condensation of gas collected under it.</p>
                <p>11. The permanence of the boiling point is one of the most remarkable of the
                    phenomena of ebullition. When water has once been brought to boil in an open
                    vessel, it is not possible to make the water sensibly hotter, however strongly
                    the fire may be urged or its intensity increased. This circumstance is very
                    striking, because we know that heat continues to be thrown in exactly as fast as
                    before the boiling point, and that in that case the heat rose rapidly, whereas
                    now it has altogether ceased to increase. If a thermometer of mercury, air, oil,
                    or metal be placed among the water, the temperature will constantly increase,
                    and expand the matter of the thermometer, until the water boils, and then,
                    whether it boil slowly or rapidly, with a strong fire or a gentle one, the
                    thermometer will continue to stand at the same point. This point is so well
                    defined, as to furnish our standard for the comparison of temperatures, and is
                    the same on all thermometers, being called <hi rend="italic">the boiling
                        point,</hi> although it is differently numbered on each, being called 212°
                    on our common thermometer or Fahrenheit’s, 80° on Reaumur’s, and 100° on the
                    centigrade thermometer.</p>
                <p>It is also to be remarked, that the temperature of the steam issuing from boiling
                    water is the same with the temperature of the water itself, and remains equally
                    invariable ; so that all the steam produced from water boiling at 212° is itself
                    at 212°. This remark will assist us in accounting for the disposal of the heat
                    which the fire gives out during the time of ebullition ; for it is manifest that
                    the heat is all the while carried off by the large volumes of steam, nt a
                    temperature of 212°, that are diffused through the air ; and so it happens that
                    an increase of heat in the fire, instead of increasing the heat of the water,
                    only increases the volumes of the steam thrown off, and the quantity of heat
                    carried away. This view of the subject is confirmed by a simple experiment. Take
                    a strong glass flask, place water in it and a thermometer among the water, and
                    let it be held over a lamp until the water boil, and the thermometer will be
                    observed rising till it reach 212°, when the steam will begin to escape rapidly
                    from the neck of the flask. Let it now be corked tightly, and the heat
                    continually applied ; and it will be observed that the thermo meter does not now
                    stand at 212°, but rises rapidly from that point up to 220° and 230°, showing
                    that the free escape of the steam into the open air is necessary to the
                    permanence of the boiling point. If the heat be still applied, the experiment
                    may be rendered still more instructive, by suddenly pulling out the cork of the
                    flask, when the vapour will instantly rush out in a large volume, and the
                    thermometer sink down to 212°, showing that all the excess of heat has been
                    carried off by the steam into the air.</p>
                <p>12. Wo have thus seen that a large quantity of heat may be given out to the
                    particles of a certain quantity of water, converting them into steam, and yet
                    that the thermometer shall afford no indication of this quantity. As soon as
                    water boils, the whole mass is heated up to 212°;<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0654.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0573"/> and
                    although the same heat that produced the ebullition be still continually
                    applied, and although we know that this heat must be continually entering into
                    the water, still it is not detected, or in any way exhibited by the thermo
                    meter. On this account, the heat given to water during ebullition is said to
                    become <hi rend="italic">latent,</hi> or lie hid from the thermometer ; and,
                    indeed, the thermometer merely indicates the intensity of heat, the calorimeter
                    alone can measure its quantity. The quantity of heat given out to water after it
                    has begun to boil, is more than fivefold that which is sufficient to bring it
                    from the freezing up to the boiling point ; for, if we continue the fire with
                    the same intensity that was used in bringing it to boil, it will require more
                    than fivefold that duration and quantity of fuel to boil all the water away, or
                    convert it all into steam of 212° of heat. Thus the sensible heat, added from
                    32°, will be 180°, and that latent in the steam is more than fivefiold ; or, in
                    other words, the <hi rend="italic">insensible caloric</hi> in steam is five fold
                    its <hi rend="italic">sensible</hi> heat ; or the same quantity of matter in the
                    condition of steam at 212°, and of water at 212 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>,
                    will hold different quantities of caloric, in the proportion of about 6 to 1.
                    This is called the greater <hi rend="italic">capacity of steam for caloric</hi>
                    than of water for that substance ; and it is in part accounted for, by the
                    greater distances of the particles of the matter of steam and water from each
                    other in the former than the latter condition ; for when the distances of the
                    particles are increased 12 times, the spheres of caloric around each atom may be
                    much larger, without increased elasticity of the calorific fluid. Dr Black was
                    the discoverer of the admirable doctrine of <hi rend="italic">latent
                    heat.</hi></p>
                <p>13. Dr Dalton has thus illustrated the doctrine of latent heat, and of the
                    increased capacity of a liquid for holding caloric, when it passes into the
                    condition of vapour. The liquid and its vapour may be considered as two
                    reservoirs of caloric, capable of holding different quantities of that fluid.
                    Let figure 1. represent to us such an arrangement ; the internal cylinder of
                    smaller capa city, the external one of enlarged capacity surrounding and ex
                    tending far above it, and a small open tube of glass, communicating freely at
                    the bottom with the inside of the cylinders. Let us now conceive water to be
                    poured into the internal cylinder, the water will manifestly flow into the
                    slender tube till it stand on the same level in the tube as in the cylinder. If
                    any additional quantity be now poured into the internal cylinder, the rise of
                    water in the slender glass tube will serve as an index of the quantity of added
                    fluid ; and when it is filled to the top, the fluid will stand at the height
                    marked 212°, and will still be a correct index of the addition of fluid. But if
                    more water be now added to it, it will not make its appearance in the slender
                    tube, but will simply overflow from the internal cylinder over into that of
                    enlarged capacity, so that, while a large quantity is passing into the vessel
                    and gradually filling it up to 212°, no additional rise takes place until the
                    whole of the outer cylinder become filled to that point, after which any further
                    addition will again become sensible, by a corresponding rise in the tube. This
                    process is in precise analogy to the succession of circumstances in heating a
                    liquid, and converting it into steam. The internal cylinder represents the
                    liquid, the external one the vapour of greater capacity, and the slender glass
                    tube at the side the thermometer placed in communication with</p>
                <p>them. When heat flows into the liquid, it passes equally into the thermometer ;
                    and each increment of the one produces an equal increment in the other, until
                    the liquid reaches the limit of its capacity, when it suddenly begins to enlarge
                    its bulk and take the form of steam ; but the quantity of heat required to fill
                    up this enlarged capacity is so great as to require about 5½ times as much to
                    fill it as was contained in the whole liquid before, so that all this time the
                    thermometer is standing still, and it is not until the whole of the steam is
                    thus supplied with 212° of caloric, that the thermometer will begin to show any
                    further elevation ; after which, any increment of heat thrown into the steam
                    will make its appearance on the thermometer, and proceed as formerly, by
                    simultaneous increments.</p>
                <p>14. It appears, therefore, that the cause why water boiling under the open air
                    does not reach a higher temperature than 212°, is, that the steam which is
                    raised by any additional heat, carries that additional quantity of heat along
                    with it into the air. But here a question occurs at once to the enquirer into
                    these phenomena, viz. Why does water require to be heated up to 212° before it
                    will throw off its increments of heat and vapour into the air ? Why does not
                    steam rise equally strongly from water at 200° or 180° ? The categorical reply
                    is, that the elastic force of the heat is not sufficient to enable the steam to
                    force its way against the pressure of the air until it reaches this point. In
                    order to understand the means by which we arrive at this conclusion, it is
                    necessary to know that, when the pressure of air on the surface of the water is
                    artificially diminished, the steam does actually rise, and the water bubbles and
                    boils with great violence, at temperatures far below 212°. It is only when the
                    surface of the water is exposed to the full <hi rend="italic">pressure Of the
                        air</hi> in a common vessel that it is prevented from rising in vapour, at
                    temperatures Iower than the usual boiling point. If the surface of the hot water
                    be protected from the pressure of the air, by being placed under a glass shade,
                    and the air removed from the inside of it by an air-pump, the water may be made
                    to boil at all temperatures below 212°. The following table contains the results
                    of a series of experiments made, with great care, by Dr Dalton, towards the end
                    of last century, in order to ascertain how much of the whole pressure of the air
                    it was necessary to remove, in order to make water boil at a given temperature.
                    In order to understand the</p>
                <p>way in which this</p>
                <p>table was form</p>
                <p>ed, the reader</p>
                <p>must conceive a</p>
                <p>vessel of water</p>
                <p>first of all boiling</p>
                <p>at 212° in the</p>
                <p>open air, as the</p>
                <p>vessel A in figure</p>
                <p>2, the thermo</p>
                <p>meter I being</p>
                <p>placed in it.</p>
                <p>After allowing</p>
                <p>the water to cool</p>
                <p>to 200°, let the</p>
                <p>vessel of water</p>
                <p>and the im</p>
                <p>merged thermo</p>
                <p>meter be now</p>
                <p>placed on the</p>
                <p>plate stand P of an air-pump, and covered over with a strong glass receiver R ;
                    and let a portion of the enclosed air he now withdrawn by the pump from the
                    inside of the receiver by the pipe F ; and suppose that there are in all 30
                    cubical inches, or other volumes, of air in the receiver at first, then the
                    water being at 200°, when about 7<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0655.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0574"/> out
                    of the 30 parts of the air have been withdrawn, leaving only about 23 parts out
                    of 30 pressing on the water, it will be observed instantly to commence giving
                    off steam in rapid ebullition. If next the process be repeated, only allowing
                    the water to cool to 190°, the ebullition will not commence in this lower
                    temperature till about 12 out of the 30 volumes of air have been with drawn ;
                    and if, in a third experiment, the water be cooled down to 180°, the elastic
                    force communicated by this degree of heat will not be capable of overcoming the
                    resistance arising from the pressure of the air, until one half of the original
                    pressure of 30 has been removed. To this pro cess there is no limit ; for as we
                    go on lowering the temperature, we can always find a point at which the water
                    will boil, provided the counteracting pressure be suffi cient[y diminished. The
                    following is Dr Dalton’s table, containing the results of his experiments, as
                    given in his <hi rend="italic">Meteorology.,</hi> in 1793:</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Heat of the Water when boiling under diminished Pressure.</cell>
                        <cell>Quantity of Pressure of Air remaining on the Fluid.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>212°</cell>
                        <cell>300</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                        <cell>22∙8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>190</cell>
                        <cell>16∙6</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>180</cell>
                        <cell>15∙2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>170</cell>
                        <cell>12∙2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>160</cell>
                        <cell>9∙45</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>150</cell>
                        <cell>7∙48</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>140</cell>
                        <cell>5∙85</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>130</cell>
                        <cell>4∙42</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>120</cell>
                        <cell>3∙27</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>110</cell>
                        <cell>252</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>1∙97</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>90</cell>
                        <cell>1∙47</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>80</cell>
                        <cell>1∙03</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>15. In vacuo, therefore, or under a rarified atmosphere»</p>
                <p>the boiling point of water is lower than 212°. Now, the barometer informs us,
                    that the pressure of our atmosphere is not constantly the same ; it has normal
                    and abnormal variations, it has horary, and menstrual, and annual varia tions.
                    It frequently stands at 30 inches, sometimes at 31 inches ; and on the morning
                    of the 7th of January, 1839, it was observed at Edinburgh, by Sir John Robison,
                    to be as low as 27 inches and six-tenth parts. Now, on that morning, water would
                    have been found to boil in the open air at about 208°, instead of 212 ; and for
                    every depres sion of the barometer, there is a corresponding depression of the
                    boiling point. This variation of the boiling temperature with the variation of
                    the barometer, and of the corresponding density of the air, is important : and
                    the following short table shows the changes which take place within the limits
                    of the usual variations of the weather : When the barometer stands at 31∙8,
                    water boils at 215°</p>
                <p>31∙2, 214</p>
                <p>30∙6, 213</p>
                <p>30* inches, 212</p>
                <p>When the barometer falls to 294, 211</p>
                <p>28∙8 210</p>
                <p>28∙2, 209</p>
                <p>27∙7 208</p>
                <p>And at 27∙2, it would boil at 207</p>
                <p>But these extremes are probably greater than have ever been observed on the
                    ordinary level of this country.</p>
                <p>16. There is yet another variation of circumstance which affects the point of
                    ebullition, and that is, distance from the centre of the earth and height above
                    the level of the sea. It is well known, that, on the summit of <hi rend="italic"
                        >a</hi> mountain, the pressure of the air is less than on a plain, and still
                    less there than at the bottom of a pit or deep valley. It is now equally well
                    known, that the cause of this is the</p>
                <p>very limited height to which air in a dense state covers the earth, the whole
                    atmosphere being equivalent to not more than 5 miles in depth of such air as we
                    breathe ; and it is hence obvious, that after a vertical ascent of a mile to the
                    top of a mountain, there would be only about <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> /
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> of the atmosphere remaining above the person on
                    its summit. One of the highest of the Andes has been ascended to such a height,
                    that there remained only <hi rend="superscript"> 13</hi> / <hi rend="subscript">
                        30</hi> of the whole atmosphere above the observer. Now, in this case, the
                    barometer, instead of being sustained at 30 inches, its usual height, had fallen
                    to 13 inches, because, according to the constitution of the barometer (See Arts.
                    BAROMETER and <hi rend="smallcaps">Pneumatics</hi>), the height of the column of
                    mercury in it is proportional to the quantity of air resting above it. Hence, a
                    barometer being carried up a mountain by an observer, falling as he ascends,
                    enables him to ascertain the height of his ascent. This he does with perfect
                    precision, so as to determine accurately the height of any point of the mountain
                    to which he has ascended, and where he has noticed the fall of the haro meter
                    from the point where it stood when at the bottom, by means of an allowance of
                    nearly 100 feet of height for every tenth part of an inch that the barometer has
                    fallen, as explained more fully under the heads <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Barometer</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Atmosphere</hi>.</p>
                <p>The steam of water may be rendered the means of determining the height of a
                    mountain, on the principle of diminished atmospheric pressure, so as to act as a
                    substitute for the barometer. We have just seen that water gives off steam by
                    ebullition, above or below the temperature 212°, according as the pressure of
                    the atmosphere is greater or less than the standard pressure which sustains the
                    barometer at 30 inches. And we have already given a table (Arts. 14 and 15),
                    showing how much the boiling point was raised or depressed by diminishing the
                    pressure of the atmosphere. On consulting Dr Dalton’s table, we see that, when
                    of the air were removed, water boiled at so low a temperature as 180°. This,
                    therefore, would show that, if water boiled on the top of any mountain at 180°,
                    the barometer would stand there at a height of little more than 15 inches ; and
                    if nt the bottom of the moun tain water boiled at 212°, showing the barometer to
                    be then at 30 inches, a similar allowance of height being made, viz. about 1000
                    feet for each inch, or 15,000 feet, would be <hi rend="italic">a</hi> rude
                    approximation to the true height. The table at the end of the third section, and
                    the rules under the head BAROMETER in this work, will enable any one who studies
                    this subject to form rides for closer approximation ; but the following table
                    will be of use to those who may merely wish to put it in practice.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rule for finding heights by boiling water.</hi> —Boil pure
                    water in an open vessel at the bottom of the elevation, and observe on the
                    thermometer the point at which it boils. Boil it again at the top of the
                    mountain, and observe with the thermometer the height at which it now boils :
                    the difference of temperature, multiplied by 530 feet, will give a close
                    approximation to the height of the upper above the lower station.</p>
                <p>This will give an approximation ; but, if greater ac curacy be required, it will
                    further be necessary to correct for the difference of the temperature of the air
                    at the two stations, in the following manner. Add the temperatures of the air at
                    the stations, and subtract 64 from their sum, multiply the remainder by
                    one-thousandth part of the height found ; and this will be the correction to be
                    added to the height formerly found. The result thus found will still require a
                    slight correction for the figure of the earth and latitude of the place ; but
                    this does not amount to more in our latitude than an addition of about two feet
                    in a thousand, which forms a second correction. This method is, however, to be
                    regarded only as an approximation,<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0656.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0575"/> for
                    which all the corrections given under the head <hi rend="smallcaps">Baro</hi>
                    METER would be necessary, in order to render it equally perfect with
                    observations by that instrument. In short, this method may be considered as a
                    telltale on the baro meter, showing where the barometer would stand if placed in
                    its position. Thus, if water boil at 200° on the top of a mountain, that is
                    merely to be considered as indicating that the barometer, if placed there, would
                    stand at 22.8 ; after which, the process of deducing the height remains the
                    same. To illustrate the mode of deducing heights from the boiling point, as we
                    have given it, we take the following example.</p>
                <p>Water boils on the top of Ben Nevis at 203·8 <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi>,
                    while at the side of the Caledonian Canal it boils at 212°, the temperature
                    being 30° on the summit of the mountain, and 35° below. In order to determine
                    the height,</p>
                <p>From 212°</p>
                <p>Take 203∙8° To 30°</p>
                <p>Add 35°</p>
                <p>There remains 8∙2°</p>
                <p>Multiply by 530 Sum 65°</p>
                <p>Subt. 64°</p>
                <p>246∙0</p>
                <p>410 Remain 1° mult, by 4346</p>
                <p>4346 first approx. Latitude 56° nearly 4 first correct. Mult. 4∙350</p>
                <p>by 2∙</p>
                <p>4350 second approx. —</p>
                <p>9∙7 second correct. 9∙700</p>
                <p>Calc, height, 4359 <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 7 third approximation.</p>
                <p>4358· true measured height—the difference being less than 2 feet.</p>
                <p>This method, however, is seldom susceptible of so high a degree of accuracy, even
                    with the most carefully con ducted experiments.</p>
                <p>17. This method of determining heights by the ebullition of water is not a recent
                    invention. It was suggested originally by Mr Fahrenheit, in the 33d volume of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions,</hi> in a paper entitled <hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> "</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Barοmetri Novi Descriptio."</hi> The subject was further
                    matured by Cavallo, who has written concerning it in the 71st volume of the same
                    Transactions ; and the method has finally received from the Rev F. J. H.
                    Wollaston the highest degree of perfection of which it seems to bo capable. His
                    paper, read before the Royal Society on the 6th of March, 1817, and afterwards
                    published in the Philosophical Transactions of that year, gives an account of
                    the very beautiful and ingenious apparatus which he has contrived for
                    facilitating the procedure of taking the observations with the requisite
                    precision. Fig. 4, is a view of the whole apparatus, consisting principally of a
                    tripod stand, surrounded by a sort of tent cover, which is quite essential for
                    the protection of the lamp from the strong winds generally encountered at
                    considerable altitudes. The lamp acts on a small tin vessel, which is a cylinder
                    5½ inches deep and 1½ in diameter, the sides of which are double, leaving an
                    interstitial space of confined air to prevent cooling. Above this vessel is a
                    circular plate of metal G H K, to which the thermometer is to be fixed ; and the
                    scale and neck of the thermometer are seen projecting above the stand. A (fig.
                    3) represents the thermometer made use of, which it is desirable to have of as
                    strong and as compact a construction as possible, while, at the same time, its
                    degrees should range as extensively as possible. These desiderata are attained
                    in Ills construction. The bulb A, one inch in diameter, is blown thick and
                    strong, on the end of a tube about of an inch in diameter : close above the
                    bulb, is a cavity B, swelled out to such a size as to contain whatever mercury
                    will</p>
                <p>expand out of the bulb, between 32 <hi rend="subscript"> o</hi> and the lowest
                    temperature at which the mercury is likely to boil at such altitudes as it will
                    be used to measure. It is this which renders the instrument compact ; because,
                    if it be not taken out of the British islands, it will never, in all
                    probability, boil at less than 200*; and thus the whole length of the stalk is
                    left for a range of 12° or 15” of the thermometer. In the instrument figured,
                    the scale R is 5 inches long, <hi rend="superscript"> 9</hi> / <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 10</hi> of an inch wide, and a length 4∙15 inches is
                    divided into 100 parts, which, by a vernier reads off to 1000 parts, being 241
                    parts to an inch ; so that 1’ Fahr, corresponds to 233 parts on the scale, or to
                    530 feet. Each part of the scale, as read by the vernier, will there fore
                    correspond to 2∙275 feet, being about half the degree of minuteness of the
                    mountain barometer divided into thousandths, each of which is nearly equivalent
                    to one foot of height. The accuracy, however, of this scale is probably greater
                    than the degree of accuracy of which the method of observation is itself
                    capable.</p>
                <p>Whethcr an observer have or have not the means of obtaining such an instrument as
                    this, it will be, in many cases, useful to travellers to be provided with means,
                    more or less accurate, of making observations of this nature, on the summit of
                    such mountains as they may have the opportunity of visiting. For this purpose,
                    the most convenient is a small cooking apparatus, such as will supply the wants
                    of a traveller ; consisting of a round tin stand, protecting a lamp, in which a
                    small quantity of the traveller’s supply of spirituous liquid may be burnt, so
                    as to boil some of the water of a small bottle, which he has also carried with
                    him, or perhaps a little melted snow. An umbrella or waterproof cloak will
                    screen the whole from the wind ; and a thermometer should have been procured,
                    with a stem as minutely divided as possible, and should be insert ed, by means
                    of a small cork, in an aperture of the lid left on purpose. The quantity of the
                    water may be small, and it will serve a culinary purpose immediately after the
                    operation is completed. The thermometer should be inserted only among the steam.
                    The traveller must take great precautions for striking a light, as he will find
                    this much more troublesome in the cold rarified air of a mountain summit than
                    below.</p>
                <p>18. Distillation is a method of separating a liquid from extraneous matter, by
                    first of all converting it into steam,<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0657.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0576"/> and
                    then condensing that steam so as to form the liquid. Different substances take
                    the liquid form at various temperatures ; and, therefore, the heat may he so
                    regulated that only one substance of a mixture shall take the form of vapour,
                    and being conveyed by a pipe through a vessel of cold water, or otherwise
                    exposed to the cooling process, the vapour being condensed will give the pure
                    liquid. A great improvement upon the process of separating liquids has been
                    successfully introduced by Mr. Howard. It consists of <hi rend="italic"
                        >distillation or evaporation in vacuo,</hi> and has been most usefully
                    employed in the refining process of sugar. When sugar is dissolved in water, it
                    requires a much higher temperature than 212° to boil the mixture, or to convert
                    the water into steam and separate it from the solid ; and as the process goes
                    on, and the solution comes to hold less and less water, the requisite degree of
                    heat is further augmented, until the temperature he comes so high as to injure
                    the colour and otherwise deteriorate the article of merchandise in its
                    crystallized state. Instead of this increased temperature, Mr Howard places the
                    syrup in vacuo, and thus boils it at a low and innoxious heat. This he
                    accomplishes by pumping out the air and vaporized water from the close boiler,
                    by means of a large air-pump driven by machinery. The process has produced a
                    great improvement on this article of commerce, and has remunerated its inventor
                    with an ample fortune.</p>
                <p>Distillation in vacuo is peculiarly adapted to obtaining those delicate extracts
                    and essential oils from vegetable substances, which are apt to suffer
                    deterioration from the usual high temperatures.</p>
                <p>19. * The pulse glass, an invention attributed to Dr Franklin, is an apparatus
                    illustrating beautifully the process of ebullition in vacuo at low temperatures.
                    If two glass balls, A and B (fig. 5), be connected by a slender tube, and one of
                    them, A, be filled with water, a small opening or pipe <hi rend="italic">b</hi>
                    being left at the top of the other, and this be made to boil, the vapour
                    produced by it will drive all the air out of the other, and will at last come
                    out itself, producing steam at the mouth of the pipe. When the ball B is
                    observed to be occupied by transparent vapour, we may conclude that the air is
                    completely expelled. Now, shut the pipe by sticking it into a piece of tallow or
                    wax, the vapour in B will soon condense, and there will be a vacuum. The flame
                    of a lamp and blow-pipe being directed to the little pipe <hi rend="italic"
                        >b,</hi> will immediately cause it to close and seal her metically. We have
                    now a pulse glass. Grasp the ball A in the holIow of the hand ; the heat of the
                    hand will immediately expand the bubble of vapour which may be in it, and this
                    vapour will drive the water into B, and then will blow up through it for a Iong
                    while, keeping it in a state of violent ebullition, as long as there remains a
                    drop or film of water in A. But care must be taken that B is all the while kept
                    cold, that it may condense the vapour as fast as it rises through the water.
                    Touching B with the hand, or breathing warm on it, will immediately stop the
                    ebullition. When the water in A has thus been dissipated, grasp B in the hand ;
                    the water will be driven into A, and the ebullition will take place there as it
                    did in B. Putting one of the balls into the mouth will make the ebullition more
                    violent in the other, and the one in the mouth will feel very cold. This is a
                    pretty iliustration of the rapid absorption of the heat by the particles of
                    water which are thus converted into elastic vapour. We have seen this little toy
                    suspended by the middle of the tube like a balance, and thus placed in the
                    inside of a window, having two holes, <hi rend="italic">a, b,</hi> cut in the
                    pane, in such a situation, that, when A is full of water and prepon</p>
                <p>derates, B is opposite to the hole <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Whenever the room
                    became sufficiently warm, the vapour was formed in A and immediately brought the
                    water into B, which was kept cool by the air coming into the room through the
                    hole <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> By this means B was made to preponderate in its
                    turn, and A was then opposite to the hole <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, and the
                    process was now repeated in the opposite direction. This amusement continued as
                    long as the room was warm enough. Instead of water, alcohol or ether may be
                    substituted, and will act more readily.</p>
                <p>20. The following experiment, where ebullition is produced by the application of
                    cold, is instructive. A Florence flask F, is about <hi rend="superscript">
                        1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> full of water, and is placed over a
                    lamp E until the water boils ; and when the steam has been rising for a short
                    time violently from the neck of the vessel, the cork S is to be applied as a
                    stopper, and must fit with great accuracy. The flask thus closed is to be set
                    aside for a few minutes till it have cooled considerably, and is then to be
                    suddenly placed on a stand in the cold water W, contained in the glass reservoir
                    R. The ebullition in the flask will rccommence with a degree of violence
                    proportioned to the cold ness of the water W.</p>
                <p>The theory of this action is simple. When the flask is plunged in the cold water,
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> of its
                    contents are steam: the chill water condenses it into water, it shrinks up into
                    l1728th part of its bulk, and would leave 1727 parts out of 1728 vacuous; but
                    the warm water being now in vacuo, throws up in rapid ebullition (according to
                    Art. 14) copious volumes of vapour of its own temperature, which is again, by
                    coming into contact with the sides of the vessel, and by directly giving off its
                    heat to the water, chilled into water, and so in succession all the vapour thus
                    sent up is in turn reconverted into water, and the vacuum sustained, until at
                    last, the equilibrium between the temperature of the water, within and around
                    the flask, having been established, the interchange of caloric ceases ; and even
                    now, if the flask were plunged into freezing water, the ebullition would
                    recommence as violently as before.</p>
                <p>21. We have already noticed (Art. 11.) the fact that, when water is confined in a
                    close vessel, and heat is applied to it, the water will not boil even at a
                    temperature of 212°. If heat be continually thrown into the water in this state,
                    the particles will acquire a very high temperature ; and, at the same time, the
                    tendency of the enclosed fluid to burst the vessel will become very great. The
                    following experiment upon this subject is one of the most interesting and the
                    earliest of which we are in possession. It was published in 1663 by the Marquis
                    of Worcester, and we give it in his own words. “ I have taken a piece of a whole
                    cannon, whereof the end was burst, and filled it three quarters full, stopping
                    and screwing up the broken end, as also the touch-hole, and making a constant
                    fire under it ; within twenty-four hours it burst, and made a great crack.”</p>
                <p>It is in virtue of the great elastic force by which water, when heated, tends to
                    expand into 1728 times its bulk, in the form of steam, that this element has
                    become a mechanical mover, subject to the control of man. There are two great
                    principles upon which such machines are con<pb
                        facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0658.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0577"/>
                    structed ; the one commonly called high-pressure steam engines, and the other
                    low-pressure steam-engines.</p>
                <p>In a high-pressure steam-engine, the principal source of motion is the <hi
                        rend="italic">elastic force</hi> of steam, formed by water, raised to a high
                    temperature in confined vessels, and tending to escape from them with such
                    force, as to im part motion and movement to solids or fluids, ingeniously
                    arranged to receive from it velocity or direction required for the
                    accomplishment of some end.</p>
                <p>In a low-pressure steam-engine, the principal source of power is derived from
                    using steam merely for the purpose of forming a vacuum. For this purpose steam
                    is admirably calculated. It is only necessary to allow the steam of a liquid to
                    enter any vessel filled with air ; and if there be left an aperture of escape,
                    the steam, entering in abun dance, will push the air out before it. When the air
                    has wholly escaped, it only remains necessary to close all the openings of the
                    vessel, and allow it gradually to cool down, when the steam will be condensed,
                    will shrivel up in the form of water into the 1728th part of its bulk, leaving
                    the other 1727 parts vacuous. The mechanical force of a vacuum on the earth’s
                    surface is well known : it will raise water to a height of more than 30 feet,
                    and support 1.5 lbs. on every square inch of surface exposed to it. What ever,
                    therefore, the formation of a vacuum on the earth’s surface can effect, of that
                    is the force of steam capable at low pressure, scarcely exceeding the
                    temperature of 212°. Hence the low-pressure engine is sometimes called the
                    condensing engine, because it acts principally by condensation of steam to form
                    a vacuum. The high pressure of</p>
                <p>steam, and its vacuumforming power, are frequently used in combination.</p>
                <p>22. There are other properties of steam, besides its mechanical force, that
                    render its use of great practical value. Its great capacity for heat enables it
                    to take up, at one time, and in one place, a large quantity of heat, which it
                    may be employed as a vehicle to transfer, at a subsequent period and at a
                    distant point, to some other substance. It is thus rendered an economizer and
                    distributer, a reservoir of heat derived from the combustion of fuel. In this
                    view it has great value as an agent in distributing the heat used for warming
                    buildings, heating baths, evaporating solutions, distilling, brewing, drying,
                    dyeing, and even for domestic cookery, and the means of extracting wholesome and
                    nutritious food from most un promising and unpalateable materials.</p>
                <p>In order, however, to its successful application as a mechanical power, and its
                    profitable use in each of the various functions which it is capable of
                    performing, it is necessary to study its various phenomena in greater de tail ;
                    to obtain an intimate acquaintance with its proper ties ; to determine its laws
                    in the various relations of space, time, and quantity ; how much heat it
                    requires, what fuel it consumes, what force it exerts, how fast it will move,
                    how it will condense, expand, and contract, and what relation it bears to the
                    different fluids from which it may be derived. Each of these enquiries, and the
                    manner in which each of these objects may be most satisfactorily attained, is
                    the subject of one or other of the following sections of this article.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
