<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0539.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0472-13" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOLIMAN II</label>
. emperor of the Turks, surnamed the <hi rend="italic">Magnificent,</hi> was the only son of Selim I., whom he succeeded in 1520. He was educated in a manner very differ- ent from the Ottoman princes in general ; for he was in- structed in the maxims of politics and the secrets of go- vernment. He began his reign by restoring those persons their possessions whom his father had unjustly plundered. He re-established the authority of the tribunals, which was almost annihilated, and bestowed the government of pro- vinces upon none but persons of wealth and probity. “ I would have my viceroys,” he used to say, “ resemble those rivers that fertilize the field through which they pass, not those torrents which sweep every thing before them.” After concluding a truce with Ishmael Sophy of Persia, and subduing Gozeli Bey, who had raised a rebellion in Syria, he turned his arms against Europe. Belgrade was taken in 1522, and Rhodes fell into his hands the year following, af- ter an obstinate and enthusiastic defence. In 1526 he defeated and slew the king of Hungary in the famous battle of Mohatz. Three years afterwards he conquered Buda, and immediately laid siege to Vienna ; but after continuing twenty days before that city, and assaulting it twenty times, he was obliged to retreat with the loss of 80,000 men. Some time after he was defeated by the Persians, and disappointed in his hopes of taking Malta. He succeeded, however, in dispossessing the Genoese of Chio, an island which had belonged to that republic for more than two hundred years. He died at the age of seventy-six, while he was besieging Sigeth, a town in Hungary, on the 30th August 1566.</p></div></body></text></TEI>