<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0193.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0187-09" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCYLLA</label>
(anc. geog.), a rock in the Fretum Siculum, near the coaſt of Italy, dangerous to ſhipping, oppoſite to Charybdis, a whirlpool on the coaſt of Sicily; both of them famous in mythology.</p><p>Scylla and Charybdis have been almoſt ſubdued by the repeated convulſions of this part of the earth, and by the violence of the current, which is continually in- creaſing the breadth of the Straits. If proper allowance be made for theſe circumſtances, we ſhall acquit the ancients of any exaggeration, notwithſtanding the very dreadful colours in which they have painted this paffage. It is formed by a low peninſula, called <hi rend="italic">Cape Pelorus,</hi> ſtretching to the eaſtward on the Sicilian ſide,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0194.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0188"/>
immediately within which lies the famous whirlpool of Charybdis, and by the rocks of Scylla, which a few miles below on the Calabrian ſhore project towards the weſt. The current runs with ſurpriſing force from one to the other alternately in the direction of the tide, and the tides themſelves are very irregular. Thus veſſels, by ſhynning the one, were in the utmoſt danger of being ſwallowed up by the other.</p><p>At preſent, in moderate weather, when the tide is either at ebb or flood, boats paſs all over the whirlpool: but, in general, it is like the meeting of two contending currents, with a number of eddies all around; and, even now, there is ſcarcely a winter in which there are not ſome wrecks.</p><p>“At the time when we paſſed the Straits (ſays Captain Sutherland, from whom we have obtained this accurate information) the weather was as favourable as we could wiſh; and yet, in ſpite of a ſtrong breeze and the current, which hurried us on with ſurpriſing velocity, the ſhip’s head was ſuddenly whirled round near three points; but the wind blowing freſh, in a few ſeconds ſhe daſhed through the eddy that had caught her; for, to avoid Scylla, and ſecure Meſſina, we had kept pretty cloſe to Charybdis.”</p></div></body></text></TEI>