<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0109.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0103-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SCRIBE</label>,
in Hebrew <hi rend="italic">ſopher,</hi> is very common in ſcripture, and has ſeveral ſignifications. It ſignifies,</p><p>1. A clerk, writer, or ſecretary. This was a very conſiderable employment in the court of the kings of Judah, in which the ſcripture often mentions the ſecretaries as the firſt officers of the crown. Seraiah was ſcribe or ſecretary to king David (2 Sam. viii. 17). Shevah and Shemaiah exerciſed the ſame office under the fame prince (2 Sam. xx. 25). In Solomon’s time we find Elihoreph and Ahiah ſecretaries to that prince (1 Kings iv. 4). Shebna under Hezekiah (2 Kings xix. 2). And Shaphan under Joſiah (2 Kings xxii. 8). As there were but few in thoſe times that could write well, the employment of a ſcribe or writer was very conſiderable.</p><p>2. A ſcribe is put for a commiſſary or muſter-maſter of an army, who makes the review of the troops, keeps the liſt or roll, and calls them over. Under the reign of Uzziah king of Judah, there is found Jeil the ſcribe who had under his hand the king’s armies (2 Chr. xxvi. II). And at the time of the captivity, it is ſaid the captain of the guard, arhong other conſiderable perlons, took the principal ſcribe of the hoſt, or ſecretary at war, which rnuſtered the people of the land ( 2 Kings XXV. 19).</p><p>3. Scribe is put for an able and ſkilful man, a doctor of the law, a man of learning that underſtands affairs. Jonathan, David’s uncle by the father’s ſide, was a counſellor, a wife man, and a ſcribe (1 Chr. xxvii. 32). Baruch, the diſciple and ſecretary to Jeremiah, is called a <hi rend="italic">ſcribe</hi> (Jer. xxxvi. 26). And Ezra is celebrated as a ſkilful ſcribe in the law of his God (Ezra vii. 6). The ſcribes of the people, who are frequently mentioned in the Goſpel, were public writers and profeſſed doctors of the law, which they read and explained to the people. Some place the original of ſcribes un-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0110.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s02-0104"/>
der Moſes: but their name does not appear till under the judges. It is ſaid, that in the wars of Barak againſt Siſera, "out of Machir came down governors, and out of Zebulun they that handle the pen of the writer.” (Judges V. 14). Others think that David firſt inſtituted them, when he eſtabliſhed the ſeveral claſſes of the prieſts and Levites. The ſcribes were of the tribe of Levi; and at the time that David is ſaid to have made the regulations in that tribe, we read that 6000 men of them were conſtituted officers and judges (1 Chr. xxii. 4.); among whom it is reaſonable to think the ſcribes were included. For in 2 Chr. xxiv. 6. we read of Shemaiah the ſcribe, one of the Levſtes; and in 2. Chr. xxxiv. 13. we find it written, “Of the Levites that were ſcribes and officers.”</p><p>The ſcribes and doctors of the law, in the ſcripture phraſe, mean the fame thing; and he that in Mat. xxii. 35. is called a <hi rend="italic">doctor of the law,</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">lawyer,</hi> in Mark xii. 28. is named a <hi rend="italic">ſcribe,</hi> or one <hi rend="italic">of the ſcribes.</hi> And as the whole religion of the Jews at that time chiefly conſiſted in phariſaical traditions, and in the uſe that was made of them to explain the ſcripture; the greateſt number of the doctors of the law, or of the ſcribes, were phariſees; and we almoſt always find them joined together in ſcripture. Each of them valued themſelves upon their knowledge of the law, upon their ſtudying and teaching it (Mat. xxii. 52.): they had the key of knowledge, and ſat in Moſes’s chair (Mat. xxiii. 2). Epiphanius, and the author of the <hi rend="italic">Recognitions</hi> imputed to St Clement, reckon the ſcribes among the ſects of the Jews; but it is certain they made no ſect by themſelves; they were only diſtinguiſhed by their ſtudy of the law.</p></div></body></text></TEI>