<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0583-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0624.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROMANUS</label> the name of four East Roman emperors.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Romanus I. (Lecapenus), who shared the imperial throne with
                        Constantine VII.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> and exercised all the real power from 919 to 944,
                    was admiral of the Byzantine fleet on the Danube when, hearing of the defeat of
                    the army at Achelous (917), he resolved to sail for Constantinople. After the
                    marriage of his daughter Helena to Constantine he was first proclaimed “
                    basileopater ” in 919 and soon after crowned colleague of his son-in-law. His
                    reign, which was uneventful, except for an attempt to check the accumulation of
                    landed property, was terminated by his own sons, Stephen and Constantine, who in
                    944 carried him off to the island of Prote and compelled him to become a monk.
                    He died in 948.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Romanus II. succeeded his father Constantine VII. in 959 at
                        the age of twenty-one, and died—poisoned, it was believed, by his wife,
                        Theophano—in 963. He was a pleasure-loving sovereign, but showed judgment in
                        the selection of bis ministers. The great event of his reign was tbe
                        conquest of Crete by Nicephorus Phocas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Romanus III. (Argyrus), emperor 1028-1034, was an
                        undistinguished Byzantine patrician, who was compelled by the dying emperor
                        Constantine IX. to marry his daughter Zoe and to become his successor. He
                        showed great eagerness to make his mark as a ruler, but was mostly
                        unfortunate in his enterprises. He spent large sums upon new buildings and
                        in endowing the monks, and in his endeavour to relieve the pressure of
                        taxation disorganized the finances of the state. In 1030 he resolved to
                        retaliate upon the incursions of tbe Moslems on the eastern frontier by
                        leading a large army in person against Aleppo, but by allowing himself to be
                        surprised on the march sustained a serious defeat at Azaz near Antioch.
                        Though this disaster was retrieved by the successful defence of Edessa by
                        George Maniakes and by the defeat of a Saracen fleet in the Adriatic,
                        Romanus never recovered his popularity. His early death was supposed to have
                        been due to poison administered by his wife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sec J. B. Bury in the <hi rend="italic">English Historical Review</hi> (1889),
                    pp. 53-57; G. Schlumberger, <hi rend="italic">L'Épopée byzantine</hi> (Paris,
                    1905), iii. pp. 56-158.</p>
               <p>                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Romanus IV. (Diogenes), emperor 1068-1071, was a member of
                        a distinguished Cappadocian family, and had risen to distinction in the
                        army, when he was convicted of treason against the sons of Constantine X.
                        While waiting execution he was summoned into the presence of the empress
                        regent, Eudocia Macrembolitissa, whom he so fascinated that she granted him
                        a free pardon and shortly afterwards married him. After his coronation he
                        carried on three successful campaigns against the Saracens and Seljuk Turks,
                        whom he drove beyond the Euphrates; in a fourth he was disastrously defeated
                        by Alp Arslan on the banks of the Araxes and taken prisoner. After releasing
                        himself by the promise of a large ransom and the conclusion of a peace, he
                        turned his arms against the</hi>
               </p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0584" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0625.jp2"/>
               <p>pretender Michael VII., but was compelled after a defeat to resign the empire
                    and retire to the island of Prote, where he soon died in great misery. It was
                    during this reign that, by the surrender of Bari (1071), the Byzantine empire
                    lost its last hold upon Italy.</p>
               <p>See J. G. C. Anderson in the <hi rend="italic">Journal of Hellenic Studies</hi>
                    (1897), pp. 36-39. On all the above see also J. B. Bury's edition of Gibbon’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Decline and Fell.</hi> (M. O. B. C.)</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
