<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0379-02" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0397.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>REMONSTRANTS</label>
meant originally those Dutch Protestants who, after the death of <hi rend="smallcaps">Arminius</hi> ( <hi rend="italic">q.v</hi> .), continued to maintain the views associated with his name, and in 1610 presented to the states of Holland and Friesland a “ remonstrance ” in five articles formulating their points of departure from stricter Calvinism. Their adversaries met them with a “ counter remonstrance, ” and so were known as the Counter Remonstrants. The conflict continued to rage till 1618-19, when the synod of Dort (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Dort,</hi> i <hi rend="smallcaps">Synod of)</hi> established the victory of the stricter school, i The judgment of the synod was enforced by the deposition and in some cases the banishment of Remonstrant ministers; but the Government soon became convinced that their party was not dangerous to the state, and in 1630 they were formally allowed liberty to reside in all parts of Holland and build churches and schools. In 1621 they had also received liberty to make a settlement in Schleswig, where they built themselves the town of Friedriclistadt. This colony still exists. The doctrine of the Remonstrants was embodied in 1621 in a <hi rend="italic">confessio</hi> written by <hi rend="smallcaps">Episcopius</hi> <hi rend="italic">{q.v.),</hi> their great theologian, while Wytenbogaert gave them a catechism and regulated their churchly order. The</p><p>Remonstrants adopted a simple synodical constitution ; but their importance was henceforth more theological than ecclesiastical. Their seminary in Amsterdam has boasted of many distinguished names—Curcellæus, Limborch, Wetstein, Le Clerc ; and their liberal school of theology, which naturally grew more liberal and even rationalistic, reacted powerfully on the state church. The Remonstrants are now a small body (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Holland,</hi> vol. xii. p. 66), but respected for their traditions of scholarship and liberal thought.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>