<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0346-02" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0364.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>REGNAULT</label>
<hi rend="smallcaps">Henri</hi> (1843-1871), French painter, born at Paris on the 31st October 1843, was the son of Henri Victor Régnault (noticed below). On leaving school he successively entered the studios of Montfort, Lamothe, and Cabanel, was beaten for the Great Prize (1863) by Layraud and Montchablon, and in 1864 exhibited two portraits in no wise remarkable at the Salon. Nothing, in short, produced by Régnault up to 1866 led men to suspect the brilliancy of his endowments, but in that year he made a mark, carrying off the Great Prize with a work of unusual force and distinction—Thetis bringing the Arms forged by Vulcan to Achilles (School of the Fine Arts). The past and the works of the past in Italy did not touch him, but his illustrations to Wey’s <hi rend="italic">Rome</hi> show how observant he was of actual life and manners ; even his Automedon (School of Fine Arts), executed in obedience to Academical regulations, was but a lively recollection of a carnival horse race. At Rome, moreover, Régnault came into contact with the modern Hispano-Italian school, a school highly materialistic in its aims and tendencies, and inclined to regard even the human subject only as one amongst many sources whence to obtain amusement for the eye. The vital, if narrow, energy of this school told on Régnault with ever-increasing force during the few remaining years of his life. In 1868 he had sent to the Salon a life-size portrait of a lady in which he had made one of the first attempts to render the actual character of fashionable modern life, and, on his return from a visit to the exhibition, he seized the opportunity of making a tour in Spain. There he saw Prim pass at the head of his troops, and received that lively image of a military demagogue which he afterwards put on canvas somewhat to the displeasure of his subject. But this work made an appeal to the imagination of the public, whilst all the later productions of Régnault were addressed exclusively to the eye. After a further flight to Africa, abridged by the necessities of his position as a pensioner of the school of Rome, he painted Judith, then (1870) Salome, and, as</p>
<pb xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0347" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0365.jp2"/>
<p>.a work due from the Roman school, despatched from Tangiers the large canvas, Execution without Hearing under the Moorish Kings, in which the painter had played with the blood of the victim as were he a jeweller toying with rubies. The war arose, and found Régnault foremost in the devoted ranks of Buzenval, where he fell on January 19, 1871.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Correspondance de II. Régnault</hi> ; Duparc, <hi rend="italic">II. Régnault, sa vie et son œuvre</hi> ; Cazalis, <hi rend="italic">H. Régnault, 1843-1871</hi> ; Baillière, <hi rend="italic">Les artistes de mon temps ;</hi> C. Blanc, <hi rend="italic">H. Régnault ;</hi> P. Mantz, <hi rend="italic">Gazette du Beaux Arts,</hi> 1872.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>