<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/>         </publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-20-r01-0304-01" facs="encyclopediabrit20newyrich_raw_0322.jp2" type="entry">

<p><label>READING</label>
a city of the United States, capital of Berks county, Pennsylvania, on the east bank of the Schuylkill river, and on the Schuylkill and Union Canals, 58 miles north-west of Philadelphia at the intersection of some fourteen railway lines, representing eight different companies. It occupies an elevated and healthy position</p><p>on a plain that gradually rises towards an amphitheatre of hills, including Penn’s Mount on the east and Neversink Mountain on the south. The plan is extremely regular and the principal streets cross at Penn Square, the business centre of the city. An abundant supply of excellent water helps to keep the whole place sweet and clean. Conspicuous buildings are—the court-house, the city-hall, Trinity Church (Lutheran), Christ Church (Episcopal), the opera-house, Misliler’s academy of music, and the railway station. Besides a very extensive and varied manufacture of iron and iron wares from steam-boilers down to nails, Reading carries on distilling, tanning, cotton-weaving, cigar-rolling, paper-making, and many other industries, and is the seat of extensive machine-shops of the Philadelphia and Reading Railroad. The population—2385 in 1800, 15,743 in 1850, 33,930 in 1870, and 43,278 in 1880—is largely of German origin; and in 1883 one out of its five daily newspapers and six out of its eleven weeklies were in German.</p><p>Laid out in 1748 by Thomas and Richard Penn, Reading received incorporation as a borough in 1783, and was made a city in 1847.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>