<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:24Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>per vein appears conſpicuouſly it may with ſafety be opened.</p><p>With a view to encourage the diſcharge of blood, it has been a conſtant practice in blood-letting, in theſe veins, to dip the feet into warm water immediately on the orifice being made. But this is a very inaccurate method of proceeding, as the quantity of blood taken in this manner can never be ascertained with preciſion ; for the blood being all mixed with the water, the operator can never be in any degree certain as to this point : and beſides, there does not appear to be any neceſſity for this aſſiſtance ; for when the compreſſion of the ſuperior part of the veins is made effectual, and the orifice is of a proper ſize, there is ſeldom more difficulty in obtaining a full diſcharge of blood from the veins of theſe parts than from any other veins of the body.</p><p>On removing the ligature, the diſcharge is generally stopped at once ; ſo that a piece of adheſive plaſter applied over the orifice anſwers all the purpoſe of a bandage. The arm, neck, and ankles are the parts from whence blood is uſually taken by veneſection ; but on ſome occaſions, where the contiguous parts have been particularly affected, it has been thought adviſable to perform veneſection in other places.</p><p>When veneſection is to be performed in the veins called <hi rend="italic">ranula</hi> under the tongue, the apex of the tongue is to be elevated, and the vein on each side opened, becauſe the opening of one only will hardly ever diſcharge blood enough. After a ſufficient quantity has been diſcharged, ſome cold aſtringent fluid taken into the mouth will generally stop the hemorrhagy.</p><p>The vena dorſalis penis, which runs along the back or upper side of this member, being generally pretty much diſtended, and conſpicuous in an inflammation of this part, may be opened about the middle or back part of the penis ; and a ſufficient quantity of blood be diſcharged proportionable to the urgency of the ſymptoms. This being done, apply a compreſs and bandage proper for the penis. The arteries and nerves which lie on each side of the vein are to be avoided : nor ought the bandage to be too tight, otherwiſe the inflammation and other ſymptoms may turn out worſe than before.</p><p>When it is found neceſſary to diſcharge blood in this manner from the penis, the veins can be eaſily brought into view, by producing an accumulation of their contents in the ſame manner as in other parts of the body, through the intervention of a ligature : but in the tongue, in the haemorrhoidal veins about the anus, and other parts where compreſſion cannot be applied, all that the ſurgeon can do, is to make an orifice of a proper ſize in that part of the vein which ſhows itſelf moſt evidently ; and if a ſufficient diſcharge of blood is not thus produced, as there is no other method of effecting it, immerſing the parts in warm water may in ſuch circumſtances be a very neceſſary meaſure.</p><p>There are ſeveral waysof performing the operation of bloodletting in the eyes. We ſhall here only relate the chief : Firſt, the patient is to be ſeated conveniently on the bed-side or on a chair, with his head held in a proper poſture by an aſſiſtant ; which done, the ſurgeon makes a tranſverſe inciſion with a lancet upon the turgid ſmall veſſels in the corners of the eye, ſo as to open them or cut them quite acroſs. Some uſe a ſmall pair of ſciſſars, inſtead of a lancet, to divide the veſſels ; but in uſing either of them, the eye-lids muſt be separated from each other by the fingers of one hand, while the veſſels are cut by inſtruments held in the other. Some, again, elevate the ſmall turgid veſſels with a crooked needle before they divide them, the eye-lids being in the mean time held aſunder by an aſſiſtant. The ſmall veſſels being thus opened or divided, their diſcharge of blood ſhould be promoted by fomentations of warm water frequently applied to the eye by means of a ſponge or ſoft linen rags.</p><p>Among other methods that have been propoſed ſor ſcarifying the blood-veſſels of the eye, the beards of rough barley were at one period much extolled, and are ſtill employed by ſome individuals. By drawing them over thc ſurface of the eye, in a direction contrary to the ſharp ſpiculæ with which they are furniſhed, a conſiderable diſcharge of blood is thereby produced : But the pain attending this operation is exquiſite ; and as it does not poſſeſs any ſuperior advantage to the method with the lancet, it is now falling into general diſuſe.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> III. <hi rend="italic">Of Arteriotomy.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Whatever</hi> particular advantages may in theory have been expected from arteriotomy, and however ſome of its ſupporters may have recommended it, not only as being in many inſtances preferable to veneſection, but as an operation perfectly ſafe even in veſſels of conſiderable ſize ; yet the moſt ſtrenuous friends to the practice have ſhrunk from any real attempt of this kind on the larger arteries. Inſtances have no doubt occurred of large arteries having been opened without any danger enſuing ; but theſe are ſo exceedingly rare, that no practitioner of experience will, from that conſideration, be induced coolly to proceed to open any artery of importance. The ſmaller branches of arteries may indeed be opened with great ſafety, when they are not deeply covered, and eſpecially when they lie contiguous to bones ; but in any of the larger arteries, the attempt muſt be always attended with ſo much hazard, and the advantages to be expected from it, in preference to veneſection, are appearently ſo trifling, as muſt in all probability prevent it from ever being carried into execution.</p><p>There are very few arteries, therefore, which, with any propriety, can be opened : the different branches of the temporal are the only arteries indeed from whence blood, in ordinary practice, is ever taken ; for although the opening of ſome other branches of arteries has by ſome been proposed, yet they are ſituated in ſuch a manner that they either cannot be readily come at, or being in the neighbourhood of ſo large nerves, the opening of them might be attended with bad conſequences. In performing this operation on any of the temporal branches, if the artery lies ſuperficial, it may be done with one puſh of the lancet, in the ſame manner as was directed for veneſection ; but when the artery lies deeply covered with cellular subſtance, it is always neceſſary to lay it fairly open to view, before making the orifice with the lancet : for in all the smaller arteries, when they are cut entirely acroſs, there is little chance of being able to procure any conſiderable quantity of blood from them ; as, when divided in this manner, they are ſure to retract conſiderably within the ſurrounding parts, which commonly puts a stop to all farther evacuation.</p><p>some degree of nicety is alſo neceſſary in making the opening into the artery of a proper oblique direction, neither quite acroſs nor directly longitudinal ; for a longitudinal opening never bleeds ſo freely, either in an artery or in a vein, as when its direction is somewhat oblique.</p><p>If the opening has been properly made, and if the artery is of any tolerable ſize, it will at once diſcharge very freely without any compreſſion ; but when the evacuation does not go on ſo well as could be wiſhed, the diſcharge may be always aſſiſted by compreſſing the artery immediately above the orifice, between it and the correſponding veins. The quantity of blood being thus diſeharged, it will commonly happen, that a very slight compreſſion on theſe ſmaller arteries will ſuffice for putting a stop to the evacuation : and</p></body></text></TEI>