<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is impoſſible to remove the effuſed matter without injuring the cornea ; but conſiderable ſervice is derived from the uſe ogfsuch remedies as are moſt effectual for promoting abſorption ; and with this view a gentle, long continued courſe of mercury, brisk purgatives occasionally, and issues in the neck, are found to be the moſt effectual remedies.</p><p>In the management of ſpecks- which are prominent upon the cornea, and where inflammation is removed and the opacity is conſiderable, if the cornea beneath be ſound, the removal of the diseased part will leave it tranſparent and fit for viſion. The remedies proper ſor this purpoſe are eſcharotics or the knife. The former are applied in the form of a powder, an ointment, or a waſh ; and theſe ought to be very finely prepared, otherwiſe they will be in danger of irritating and inflaming the eye ; and they ought merely to be of such ſtrength as the eye can eaſily bear.</p><p>The applications ſhould be long perſiſted in and frequently repeated; and to make them ſtill more uſeful, ſome of the powders or ointments may be applied evening and morning, and the ſolution two or three times through the courſe of the day. To the remedies already mentioned cauſtic is ſometimes preferred. With this the centre of the ſpeck is to be frequently touched, till the patient complain of conſiderable pain, when pure water is to be applied by a pencil, or by dipping the eye in water, with the eyelids open, till the pain occaſioned by the application of the cauſtic be removed. The eye is then to be covered with compresses moiſtened in ſome ſolution, and this frequently repeated. The cauſtic to be repeated every second or third day, unleſs prevented by inflammation. When the ſurgeon chooſes to employ the knife, which frequently may be more effectual, the eye is to be fixed by a ſpeculum (fig. 29.), or levator (fig. 30) ; the tumor is then to be cautiously ſeparated by means of a ſmall knife, and every attention paid to pre-inflammation. Theſe are the methods moſt likely to be of ſervice ; and when properly managed, they will frequently remove specks, which otherwiſe would entirely deprive the patient of the uſe of the eye ; though it is to be regretted that caſes frequently occur which baffle art.</p><p>A membranous excreſcence, called pterygium, is frequently ſound upon the white part oſ the eye, which often ſpreads over the cornea ſo as entirely to deſtroy viſion. It is ſometimes owing to external injuries ; at other times it ariſes from a general diſeaſe of the ſyſtem, as lues venerea or ſcrophula ; but inflammation is always the more immediate cauſe.</p><p>By a proper application of the remedies above mentioned affections of this kind may generally be prevented from becoming formidable ; but when the reverſe takes place, and excreſcences begin to ſpread over the cornea, other means muſt be uſed. When the diſeaſed part is only ſlightly attached, it may be freely removed by a cut of the knife ; but when this cannot be done without difficulty, it is better to deſtroy the veſſels by the extenſion of which this ſubſtance is chiefly formed. The manner of performing the operation in general is this : The patient being properly ſeated, the eyelids opened, and the eye ſecured, the operator, with a ſmall knife, makes a ſcariſication through the whole thickness of the excreſcence, entirely round, and at a little diſtance from the circumference, by which the ſource of nouriſhment will be cut off ; and, after the blooding is abated, one or two inciſions more may be made, in a ſimilar manner, within the former. Some practitioners raiſe the excreſcence with a needle and ligature before the inciſion is made; and, in ſome caſes, this may be done with advantage, though not in others.</p><p>After the bleeding is over, the part is to be bathed two or three times a-day with a weak ſaturnine ſolution ; and the operation may be repeated occaſionally till the excreſcence is removed. In this way the operation commonly proves effectual ; but inſtances ſometimes occur where, inſtead of being uſeful, it increaſes the diſeaſe. Whenever this happens, a palliative courſe is the only thing to be tried ; and although it will not remove the diſorder, it may commonly prevent the excreſcence from acquiring any additional ſize. With this intention it ought to be frequently bathed with the ſolution laſt mentioned, and afterwards covered with a cooling ointment. When the diſorder cannot even be palliated, when viſion is deſtroyed, and particularly when the pain attending it is ſevere, there is reaſon to ſuſpect cancer. In this caſe the eye ought to be extirpated, otherwiſe deeper parts may ſuffer, and the life of the patient be endangered. The method of performing this operation will be afterwards pointed out.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> IV. <hi rend="italic">Of Abscesses in the Globe of the Eye.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Though</hi> inflammation of the eye generally terminates by reſolution, inſtances ſometimes occur in which an absceſs ensues. This is owing either to improper treatment, or a bad habit of body which counteracts all remedies. The greateſt danger attending theſe complaints is when they are ſituated on the cornea, as the cicatrix left by them may deſtroy viſion. When deep ſeated, a purulent matter is sometimes apt to be found in ſome of the chambers of the eye, the ball becomes enlarged, the humours are diſturbed, and neither the iris, pupil, nor lens can be diſtinguiſhed. In ſome rare caſes again, after theſe appearances have continued ſome time, the cornea burſts, part or whole of the humours are evacuated, and the iris protrudes in a thickened diſtended ſtate. This has now the appearance of an excreſcence, which is called st<hi rend="italic">aphyloma</hi> from a kind of relemblance to a grape. But under this term ſome authors include all collections like thoſe above deſcribed. In moſt inſtances the cornea protrudes, but in others the tunica ſclerotica or opaque part is affected with partial ſwellings or protruſions.</p><p>While the diſeaſe is forming, beſides the loss of ſight, the patient commonly feels great diſtreſs in the eye and head, accompanied by symptoms of fever. When no other diſtreſs is experienced than the loſs of ſight, the ſwelling is but ſmall, and contains chiefly a watery fluid. In the treatment, as viſion is ſeldom preſerved, the principal thing is to abate the pain and remove deformity. There is another kind of absceſs in the eye, termed <hi rend="italic">hypopyon,</hi> where the matter is lodged in the ſubſtance of the coats. It is ſometimes produced by external injuries, but more frequently from pullules of small-pox. If this termination cannot be prevented by the remedies mentioned in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 175, the matter muſt be evacuated by an inciſion into the eye, not regarding the humours, as viſion previous to this time is entirely deſtroyed. The proper part is the cornea or the moſt prominent part of the tumor.</p><p>A variety of this diſorder ſometimes, though rarely, happens, where the humours are abſorbed ; but ſtill the ſame external appearances are obſerved. In this caſe the tumor is formed by a thickening of the coats, eſpecially the iris. The only means of relief is extirpation of the prominent part by the uſe of the knife. After the contents of the eye have been diſcharged, the parts are to be covered with a compreſs moiſtened with a ſaturnine ſolution, and the antiphlogiſtic courſe followed, till a cure is perfected, or ax leaſt inflammation removed. If the ulcers discharge a thin acrid matter, they may be waſhed two or three times a day with a ſolution of corroſive ſublimate, or of white vitriol, &amp;c. Fungous excreſcences, ſometimes conſidered as a cancer of the eye, are apt to form in both theſe diſeaſes after the matter is evacuated ; but they may be prevented from in-</p></body></text></TEI>