<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>xions of the eyes, he applied aſtringents, cupped the temples, and burnt the veins over the temple and forehead. He couched cataracts by depressing the cryſtalline lens to the bottom of the orbit. Teeth, looſened by any accident, he directs, after the example of Hippocrates, to be faſtened with a gold thread to thoſe adjoining on each side. Previous to drawing a tooth, he ordered the gum to be cut round its neck ; and if the tooth was hollow, it was to be filled with lead before extraction, to prevent its breaking by the forceps. He describcs not only the inflammation, but likewiſe the elongation, of the uvula: he alſo delcribes the polvpus, and ſome other diſeaſes affecting the noſe.</p><p>He deſcribes several ſpecies of herniæ or rupture, and the manual aſſiſtance required in thoſe complaints. After the return of the inteſtines into the abdomen, a firm compress was applied to that part of the groin through which they protruded, and was ſecured by a bandage round the loins. In ſome cases, after the return of inteſtinal ruptures, he diminiſhed the quantity of looſe ſkin, and formed a cicatrix, ſo as to contract over the part, to render it more rigid and capable of reſiſting. He deſcribes various diſeaſes of the genital parts, the hydrocele or dropſy of the ſcrotum, a difficulty of urine, and the manner of drawing off the water by a catheter ; the ſigns of ſtone in the bladder, and the method of sounding or feeling for that ſtone. Lithotomy was at that time performed by introducing two fingers into the anus ; the ſtone was then pressed forward to the perinaeum, and a cut made into the bladder ; and by the finger or by a ſcoop the ſtone was extracted. He describes the manner of performing this operation on both the sexes, of treating the patient, and the ſigns of recovery and of danger.</p><p>Celſus directed various corroſive applications and injections to ſiſtulas ; and, in the laſt extremity, opened them to the bottom with a knife, cutting upon a grooved infiniment or conductor. In old callous ulcers, he made a new wound, by either cutting away the hard edges, or corroding them with verdigriſe, quicklime, alum, nitre, and with ſome vegetable eſcharotics. He mentions the ſymptoms of caries in the bone ; directs the bone to be laid bare, and to be pierced with ſeveral holes, or to be burnt or raſped, in order to promote an exfoliation of the corrupted part ; afterwards to apply nitre and ſeveral other ingredients. One of his applications to a cancer was auripigmentum or arſenic. He directs the manner of tapping the abdomen in aſcites, and of drawing blood by the lancet and cupping-glaſſes. His cupping-glaſſes ſeem not to have been ſo convenient as the modern : they were made either of braſs or horn, and were unprovided with a pump. He cured varicoſe veins by uſtion or by inciſion. He gives directions for extracting the dead fœtus ſrom the womb, in whatever poſition it ſhould preſent ; and, after delivery, to apply to the private parts ſoft cloths wet in an infusion of vinegar and roſes. In Celſus’s works there is a great redundance and ſuperfluity of plaſters, ointments, eſcharotics, collyriums, of ſuppurating and diſcutient cataplaſms, and external applications of every kind, both ſimple and compound : Perhaps, amongſt the multitude, there are a few uſeful remedies now laid aſide and neglected.</p><p>The laſt writer of conſequence who flouriſhed at Rome was Galen, phyſician to the emperor Marcus Aurelius. His works are for the moſt part purely medicinal ; although he wrote alſo on ſurgery, and made Commentaries on the Surgery of Hippocrates. He opened the jugular veins, and performed arteriotomy at the temples ; directed leeches, ſcarification, and cupping-glaſſes, to draw blood. He alſo deſcribed with accuracy the different ſpecies of herniæ or ruptures.</p><p>In the year 500 flouriſhed Aetius, in whoſe works we meet with many obſervations omitted by Celſus and Galen, particularly on the ſurgical operations, the diſeaſes of women, the causes of difficult labours, and modes of delivery, He alſo takes notice of the dracunculus, or Guinea worm. Aeſtius, however, is greatly excelled by Paulus Egineta, who flouriſhed in 640 ; whoſe treatiſe on surgery is ſuperior to that of all the other ancients. He directs how to extract darts ; to perform the operation ſometimes required in dangerous cases of rupture or hernia. He treats alſo of aneurism. Galea, Paulus, and all the ancients, ſpeak only of one ſpecies of aneuriſm, and define it to be “ a tumor arising from arterial blood extravaſated from a ruptured artery.” The aneuriſm from a dilatation of the artery is a diſcovery of the moderns. In violent inflammations of the throat, where immediate danger of ſuffocation was threatened, Paulus performed the operation of bronchotomy. In obſtinate defluxions upon the eyes, he opened the jugular veins. He deſcribes the manner of opening the arteries behind the ears in chronic pains of the head. He wrote alſo upon midwifery. Fabricius ab Aquapendente, a celebrated ſurgeon of the 16th century, has followed Celſus and Paulus as text books.</p><p>From the time of Paulus Egineta to the year 900, no writer of any conſequence, either on medicine or ſurgery, appeared. At this time the Arabian phyſicians Rhazes and Avicenna revived in the eaſt the medical art, which, as well as others, was almoſt entirely extinguiſhed in the west. Avicenna’s <hi rend="italic">Canon Medicinae,</hi> or General Syſtem of Medicine and Surgery, was for many ages celebrated through all the ſchools of phyſic. It was principally compiled ſrom the writings of Galen and Rhazes. The latter had correctly deſcribed the spina ventoſa, accompanied with an enlargement of the bone, caries, and acute pain. In difficult labours, he recommends the fillet to aſſiſt in the extraction of the fœtus ; and for the ſame purpoſe, Avicenna recommends the forceps. He deſcribes the compoſition of ſeveral coſmetics to polish the skin, and make the hair grow, or fall off.</p><p>Notwithſtanding this, however, it was not till the time of Albucaſis that ſurgery came into repute among the Arabians. Rhazes complains of their groſs ignorance, and that the manual operations were performed by the phyſicians servants. Albucaſis enumerates a tremendous liſt of operations, sufficient to fill us with horror. The hot iron and cauteries were favourite remedies of the Arabians; and, in inveterate pains, they repoſed, like the Egyptians and eaſtern Aſiatics, great confidence in burning the part. He deſcribes accurately the manner of tapping in aſcites ; mentions ſeveral kinds of inſtruments for drawing blood ; and has left a more ample and correct delineation of ſurgical inſtruments than any of the ancients. He gives various obſtetrical directions for extracting the fœtus in caſes of difficult labour. He mentions the bronchocele, or prominent tumor on the neck, which, he tells us, was moſt frequent among the female ſex. We arc alſo informed by this writer, that the delicacy of the Arabian women did not permit male ſurgeons to perform lithotomy on females ; but when necessary, it was executed by one of their own ſex.</p><p>From the 1lth century to the middle of the 14th, the hiſtory of ſurgery affords nothing remarkable except the importation of that nauſeous diſease the leproſy into Europe. Towards the end of the 15th century the venereal diſeaſe 19 ſaid to have been imported from America by the firſt diſcoverers of that continent.</p><p>At the beginning of the 16th century, ſurgery was held in contempt in this island, and was practiſed indiſcriminately</p></body></text></TEI>