<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſuppoſe that the diſeaſe depends upon a general affection either of the trunk in which it occurs, or of the whole arterious ſyſtem. In ſuch caſes art can give little asiſtance : whereas if the tumor has ſucceeded an external accident, an operation may be attended with ſucceſs.</p><p>In the varicoſe aneuriſm a more favourable prognoſis may generally be given than in either of the other two ſpecies. It does not proceed ſo rapidly; when it has arrived at a certain length, it does not afterwards acquire much additional ſize ; and it may be ſuſtained without much inconvenience for a great number of years. As long as there is reaſon to expect this, the hazard which almoſt always attends the operation ought to be avoided.</p><p>In the second volume of the London Medical Obſervations, two caſes are related by Dr Hunter of the varicoſe aneuriſm. One of them at that time was of 14 years standing, and the other had ſubsisted for five years, without there being any neceſſity for an operation. And in vol. iii. of the same work a ſimilar caſe of five years duration is related by Dr Cleghorn.</p><p>In a letter afterwards from Dr Hunter to Mr Benjamin Bell, the Doctor ſays, “ The lady in whom I firſt obſerved the varicose aneuriſm is now living at Bath in good health, and the arm is in no ſenſe worſe, although it is now 35 years since she received the injury:” and the Doctor farther obſerves, that he never heard of the operation being performed for the varicoſe aneuriſm which was known to be ſuch.</p><p>Mr Dell says, he was informed by Dr William Cleghorn of Dublin, that the caſe of varicoſe aneuriſm, related in the 3d volume of the London Medical Obſervations, remained nearly in the ſame ſtate as at the time that account of it was made out, which included a period of at leaſt 20 years; Only that the veins were rather more enlarged. The patient recovered, and the limb became nearly as ſtrong and ſerviceable as the other. Mr Pott alſo met with three different inſtances of this ſpecies of aneuriſm ; and obſerves, that the operation never became neceſſary in any of them.</p><p>Among other inſtances of varicoſe aneuriſm which have appeared here, a young man from Paiſley was examined ſeveral years ago by different ſurgeons of this place. The diſeaſe was very clearly marked, and no operation was adviſed. He was afterwards found ſerving in the navy, where he underwent great fatigue without any inconvenience from the aneuriſm, though then of 13 years ſtanding.</p><p>But though this aneuriſm, when it has arrived at a certain ſize, commonly remains ſtationary, and may be borne without mutch inconvenience for a long time, this is not always the case ; for ſome inſtances have occurred, where the diſeaſe was attended with great uneasineſs, and where the operation was performed with much difficulty.</p><p>In judging further of the probable evcnt of aneuriſms in general, the ſituation of the tumor next requires attention. When it is ſo ſituated that no ligature or effectual compreſſion can be applied for stopping the circulation in the part, if the artery be large, there would be the greatest danger in opening it. In this caſe therefore the most fatal conſequences are to be apprehended.</p><p>When aneuriſms are ſituated near the upper parts of the extremities, ſurgeons have been hitherto doubtful whether, after tying up the humeral or femoral arteries, the lower parts of the limb would be ſupplied with blood ; and tho’ ſeveral successful instances of performing that operation have been publiſhed, the ſuccess has been pretty generally aſcribed to unuſual branching of the great arteries of thoſe patients, on whom the operation was performed, above the aneuriſm. Mr John Bell, however, in his late very ingenious and important <hi rend="italic">Diſcourſes on Wounds,</hi> has proved, to our ſatisfaction at leaſt, that the inoſculations which take place between the internal iliac and the arteries of the leg, by means of the glutaeal arteries and the profunda femoris, are in every caſe ſufficient to ſupply nouriſhment to the limb ; that the ſame is the caſe in the arm ; and that therefore in every aneuriſm even of the humeral or femoral artery, we ought to perform the operation. Several inſtances of ſucceſs are there related ; among others, an operation performed by Mr J. Bell himſelf, which, as it is perhaps the greateſt that has hitherto been performed, we ſhall here a- bridge for the gratification of our readers. A leech-catcher fell as he was ſtepping out of a boat ; and a pair of long- pointed ſciſſars pierced his hip exactly over the ſciatic notch, where the great iliac artery comes out from the pelvis. The artery bled furiouſly : the patient fainted. The ſurgeon eaſily ſtopt up the wound, as it was very narrow and deep, and healed it. A great tumor ſoon formed. The man travelled from the north country in six weeks to the Edinburgh infirmary, with a prodigious tumor of the hip, the thigh rigidly contracted, the ham bent, the whole leg ſhrunk and cold and uſeleſs. There was no pulſation nor retrocesſion of blood on preſſure ; but the diſtenſion was attended with great pain, and the man was extremely anxious to have an operation performed. Though there was little doubt oſ its being aneuriſm, it might be a great abſeeſs. It was reſolved therefore to make a ſmall inciſion, and just touch the bag with the point of a lancet, and it it contained blood, a full conſultation was to be called. Mr Bell accordingly made an inciſion two inches and an half in length ; the great faſcia formed the coat of the tumor, and under it were ſeen the fibres of the great glutæus muſcle. As ſoon as it was opened at one point, great clots of blood came out ; and Mr Bell, after being certain that it was an aneuriſm of the great artery of the thigh, cloſed up the wound with a tent-like compreſs, put the patient to bed, and a pupil held his hand on the hip. This was done at one o’clock ; at four the conſultation met, and the operation was performed. On making an inciſion eight inches long, the blood was thrown out with a whishing noiſe, and with ſuch impetuoſity, that the assiſtants were covered with it. In a moment twenty hands were about the tumor, and the bag was filled with ſponges and cloths of all kinds ; the blood, however, ſtill made its way ; and the man who had ſupported himſelf on his elbow, fell down; his arms and head hung down, he uttered two or three heavy groans, and they thought him dead. At that critical moment Mr Bell ran the bistoury upwards and downwards, and at once made the wound two feet long ; thruſt his hand to the bottom of the tumor, felt the warm jet of blood, put his finger on the mouth of the artery, the pulſe of which he felt diſtinctly ; which firſt aſſured him that the man was alive. The artery was then tied ; and when Mr Bell lifted up his finger, it was diſcovered to be the posterior iliac ; that it had been cut fairly acroſs, and had bled with open mouth. The patient was ſo low, that after dreſſing the wound, they were obliged to bring in a bed, and leave him to ſleep in the operation room. He was cured or this great wound in less than ſeven months, and afterwards recovered the uſe of his leg completely.</p><p>In every case of aneuriſm, the uſe of preſſure has been indiscriminately recommended, not only in the incipient period of the diseaſe, but even in its more advanced ſtages.</p><p>In the diffuſed or false aneurilm, as preſſure cannot be applied to the artery alone, without at the fame time affecting the refluent veins ; and as this, by producing an increaſed reſistance to the arterial pulſations, muſt force an additional quantity of blood to the orifice in the artery—no advantage</p></body></text></TEI>