<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>plied to the parts underneath, and retained there by the twiſted future, and likewiſe by a few adheſive ſtraps. A large pledgit of ſimple ointment is now to be laid over the whole ; and this is to be covered with a thick compress of lint, tow, or soft linen ; and the dreſſings to be kept in their place, and moderate preſſure made by the napkin and scapulary bandage.</p><p>By this method the integuments will generally ſoon adhere, and a cure will be performed by the firſt intention. But it does not often happen that the operation is performed while this favourable mode of practiſing it will anſwer.</p><p>In general, before extirpation of a breaſt is recommended by the ſurgeon, or ſubmitted to by the patient, a conſiderable portion of the external integuments are ſo much diſeaſed as to render it neceſſary to ſeparate them along with the glandular part of the mamma. It ſometimes happens likewiſe that the tumor adheres to the pectoral muſcle, and that again to the ribs. In either oſ theſe caſes it becomes neceſſary to remove all the diſeaſed parts. For this purpoſe, two inciſions of an oval form, with ſharp extremities, of a ſufficient ſize to include the whole of the affected parts, become neceſſary. If again it be found, that beſides the diſeaſe of the breaſt, the lymphatic glands in the neighbourhood are indurated, or otherwiſe diſeaſed, the firſt inciſion ought to extend at once over theſe ; and after the other parts have been removed, and the veſſels ſecured, the whole of the diſeaſed glands are to be extirpated ; and in performing this part of the operation, conſiderable aſſiſtance may be given by ſupporting them with a hook, or a ligature passed through them, till they are entirely removed. When they lie deep in the axilla, the points of the fingers, or the end of the handle, will ſometimes be ſafer than the edge of the knife. After having removed all the glands which are in the ſmalleſt degree affected, the cut edges of the ſkin are to be brought as near to each other as the nature of the caſe will allow, ſo as to heal as much as poſſible by the firſt intention. After the wound is nearly, or perhaps entirely healed, an iſſue, inserted into the arm of the oppoſite side, will be the beſt means of preventing a relapſe.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> IV <hi rend="italic">Burns.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi> immediate conſequence of burns is a greater or leſs degree of inflammation; and the danger attending ſuch accidents is in proportion to the extent of the injury. Burns which irritate the ſkin only, without deſtroying the cuticle, act nearly in the way of a common bliſtering plaſter. When the cuticle is deſtroyed, no bliſter takes place ; a mortified slough is obſerved ; and when this ſeparates, an ulcer is left. Where the cuticle is not deſtroyed, relief may be procured by holding the part affected a conſiderable time in very cold water, or ſometimes by plunging it two or three times into water a little below the boiling point. Solutions of ſaccharum ſaturni, and other preparations of lead, have been recommended, as in the caſe of other inflammations. Vinegar is found a very effectual application, whether the ſkin be ſound or bliſtered. The part may be entirely immerſed in it, or linen rags dipt in the vinegar may be applied, and the parts kept conſtantly moiſt, till the pain be removed. The ſame application is uſeful where the ſkin is rubbed off, or otherwiſe deſtroyed. In this caſe, indeed, the vinegar is apt to give additional pain on its firſt application ; but this ſoon ceaſes, and the part becomes much cooler and eaſier. If the patient will not ſuffer the vinegar to be applied immediately to the ſurface of the ſore, a linen rag ſoaked in olive-oil may be previously laid on the part, covering the whole with the cloths dipped in vinegar ; and theſe applications are to be occaſionally repeated till the pain and inflammation be entirely removed ; after which the parts are to be dressed in the ſame manner as in the case of a common bliſter. In extenſive burns, where the irritation is great, along with external applications, opium ſhould be preſcribed, in doſes adequate to the degree of pain. Even that ſtupor with which patients in this ſituation are ſometimes attacked, is found to be more readily removed by opium than by any other remedy. With reſpect to the bliſters which ariſe upon burns, it has been diſputed whether they ought to be opened, or allowed to remain till they dry up of themſelves. But, according to the opinions of the lateſt authors, they ought to be opened as ſoon as any conſiderable quantity of fluid is found in them. After the ſerum is diſcharged, a thin liniment of wax and oil, with a little ſaccharum ſaturni, ſhould be applied to the part.</p><p>In caſes of very ſevere burns, where, notwithſtanding the above treatment, there is danger of a violent inflammation being induced, blood-letting, cooling purgatives, and other remedies adapted to the peculiar ſymptoms, muſt be uſed. When, again, burns are from the firſt attended with loſs of ſubſtance, as commonly happens after the application of hot metallic bodies, we ought to have recourſe to the vinegar, as already mentioned, or to a liniment which is now in very common uſe for ſuch purpoſes, made of equal parts of lint-seed oil and lime-water, which, when ſhaken together, forms a thick white ſubſtance, which often gives ſpeedy relief ; and it may be readily applied by daubing the parts frequently over with a ſoft pencil well ſoaked in it. Though this has been conſidered as one of the beſt applications in burns, yet, in ſome caſes, more immediate relief has been procured from the application of Goulard’s cerate, or the unguentum nutritum ; and a weak ſolution of ſaccharum ſaturni has ſometimes been of ſervice.</p><p>When burns are occaſioned by the exploſion of gunpowder, ſome of the grains of the powder are apt to be forced into the ſkin. At firſt they produce much irritation ; and if they are not removed, they commonly leave marks which remain during life. They ſhould, therefore, be picked out as ſoon as poſſible after the accident ; and to prevent inflammation, as well as to dissolve any power which may remain, the parts afflicted ſhould be covered, for a day or two, with emollient poultices. In other reſpects, injuries of this sort are to be treated like any other kind of burns.—When burnt parts are contiguous to each other, they are apt to adhere. To prevent this, pledgits covered with any proper dreſſing ought to be inſerted between them during the courſe of the cure. Ulcers ariſing from burns are apt to become ſoft and fungous, and to riſe above their natural level. When this is obſerved, the emollient ointments, which may have been previouſly uſed, ſhould be laid aſide, and thoſe of a moderately aſtringent nature applied. Gentle compreſſion with a roller is alſo of particular ſervice. Advantage is likewiſe derived from ſaturnine waffles, &amp;c. One of the beſt oiutments, in ſuch caſes, is the common calamine cerate. Theſe will commonly anſwer the purpoſe ; but when they prove inſufficient, burnt alum, blue vitriol, or even lunar cauſtic, may be neceſſary.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> V. <hi rend="italic">Of Inflammatory Tumors.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Inflammatory Tumors</hi> are ſuch as are quick in their progreſs when compared with thoſe of the indolent kind, and are attended with conſiderable pain and other ſymptoms of inflammation. We have here mentioned ſuch only whoſe treatment more properly belongs to the province of the ſurgeon, and which are placed according to their ſituations in the different parts of the body.</p></body></text></TEI>