<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſed in any liquid, it makes it extremely bitter ; the virtues uſually attributed to this ſtone are cleaning the ſtomach, creating an appetitc, and ſweetening the blood.</p><p>Of birds they have a greater variety than of beaſts. The coo-ow, or Sumatran pheaſant, is a bird of uncommon beauty. They have ſtorks of prodigious ſize, parrots, dung-hill fowls, ducks, the largeſt cocks in the world, wood-pigeons, doves, and a great variety of ſmall birds, different from ours, and diſtinguished by the beauty of their colours. Of their reptiles, they have lizards, flying-lizards, and cameleons. The iſland swarms with insects, and their varieties are no leſs extraordinary than their numbers. Rice is the only grain that grows in the country ; they have sugar-canes, beans, peas, radiſhes, yams, potatoes, pumkins, and ſeveral kinds of pot-herbs unknown to Europe ; and here are to be found moſt of the fruits to be met with in other parts of the Eaſt Indies, in the greateſt perfection. Indigo, Braſil- wood, two ſpecies of the bread-fruit tree, pepper, benjamin, coffee, and cotton, are likewiſe the produce of this island, as well as caſſia and camphire mentioned above. Here alſo is the cabbage-tree and ſilk cotton tree ; and the foreſt contains a great variety of valuable species of wood, as ebony, pine, ſandal, eagle or aloes, teek, manchineel, and ironwood, and alſo the banyan tree. Gold, tin, iron, copper, and lead, are found in the country ; and the former is suppoſed to be as plentiful here as in Peru or Mexico. The fineſt gold and gold-duſt are found in the country of <hi rend="italic">Limong,</hi> immediately contiguous to the preſidency of <hi rend="italic">Fort Marlborough,</hi> to which the merchants repair annually for the purchase of opium, and ſuch other articles as they may be in want off, and give for them gold of ſo pure a nature as to contain little or no alloy.@@ The native indolence of the <hi rend="italic">Malay</hi> diſpoſition prevents them from collecting more than is ſufficient to ſupply the few and simple wants of a race of men as yet unenlightened by civilization and science, and ignorant of the full extent of the advantages of the country inhabited by them. The roads leading to this golden country are almoſt impervious ; affording only a ſcanty path to a tingle traveller, where whole nights muſt be paſſed in the open air, expoſed to the malignant influence of a hoſtile climate, in a country infeſted by the moſt ferocious wild beaſts. Theſe are circumſtances that have hitherto checked curioſity ; but perſeverance and ſtudied precaution will ſurmount the obſtacles they furniſh, and ſuch ciſcoveries might be made as would amply compenſate for the difficulties leading to them. The gold merchants who come from the neighbouring and leſs rich countries, give us ſuch accounts of the facility of procuring gold as border nearly on the marvellous, and would be altogether incredible, if great quantities of that metal produced by them did not in ſome degree evince the certainty of their accounts.</p><p>This great abundance of gold in Sumatra induces Mr Marſden to ſhppoſe that iſland to be the Ophir of Solomon ; a conjecture which, in his opinion, derives no ſmall rorce ſrom the word <hi rend="italic">Ophir's</hi> being really a <hi rend="italic">Malay</hi> ſubſtantive, of a compound ſenſe, ſignifying a mountain containing gold. The natives, he confeſſes, have no oral tradition on the ſubject ; and we have elſewhere made it probable, that Ophir was ſituated in a different quarter of the world (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Ophir). </hi>Beſides the metals and different ſpecies of wood which we have mentioned. Sumatra produces ſulphur, arſenic, ſalt- petre, and bees-wax, with edible birds-neſts, which are there commodities of great importance (ſee <hi rend="italic">BIRDS-Nests).</hi></p><p>The Engliſh and Dutch have factories on this iſland ; the principal one of the former being Fort Marlborough, on the ſouth weſt coaſt. The original natives of Sumatra are Pagans ; but it is to be obſerved, that when the Sumatrans. or any of the natives of the eaſtern iſlands, learn to read the Arabic character, and ſubmit to circumciſion, they are ſaid to become Malays ; the term <hi rend="italic">Malay</hi> being underſtood to mean <hi rend="italic">Musſulman.</hi> See ACHEEN.</p><p>SUMMARY, in matters of literature. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Abridgement.</hi></p><p>SUMMER, the name of one of the ſeaſons of the year, being one of the quarters when the year is divided into four quarters, or one half when the year is divided only into two, ſummer and winter. In the former caſe, ſummer is the quarter during which, in northern climates, the fun is passing through the three ſigns Cancer, Leo, Virgo, or from the time of the greateſt declination, till the ſun come to the equinoctial again, or have no declination ; which is from about the 21st of June till about the 22d of September. In the latter caſe, ſummer contains the six warmer months, while the ſun is on one side of the equinoctial ; and winter the other six months, when the ſun is on the other side of it. It is ſaid that a froſty winter produces a dry ſummer, and a mild winter a wet ſummer.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SUMMER-Islands.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Bermudas.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Summer</hi><hi rend="italic"> Red-Bird.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Muscicapa.</hi></p><p>SUMMIT, the top or vertex of any body or figure, as of a triangle, cone, pyramid, &amp;c.</p><p>SUMMONS, in law, a citing or calling a perſon to any court, to anſwer a complaint or to give his evidence.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Summons,</hi> in war. To summon a place, is to ſend a drum or trumpet to command the governor to surrender, and to declare that if the place be taken by ſtorm, all muſt ſubmit to the mercy of the conqueror. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Capitulation </hi>and <hi rend="smallcaps">Chamade.</hi></p><p>SUMMUM <hi rend="smallcaps">bonum,</hi> in ethics, the chief good.</p><p>SUMP, in metallurgy, a round pit of ſtone, lined with clay within, for the receiving the metal on its ſirſt fuſion from the ore.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sump,</hi> in the Britiſh salt-works, where ſea-water is boiled into salt, is the name of a sort of pond, which is made at ſome diſtance from the ſaltern on the ſea-ſhore, between full ſea and low water mark. From this pond a pipe is laid, through which, when the ſea is in, the water runs into a well adjoining to the ſaltern ; and from this well it is pumped into troughs, through which it is carried to the ciſterns, in order to be ready to ſupply the pans. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Salt.</hi></p><p>SUMPH, in mining, denotes a pit sunk down in the bottom of the mine, to cut or prove the lode ſtill deeper than before ; and in order to ſlope and dig it away if neceſſary, and alſo to drive on the lode in depth. The ſumph principally ſerves as a baſon or reſervoir, to collect the water of a mine together, that it may be cleaned out by an engine or machine.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SUMPTER-horse,</hi> is a horſe that carries provisions and neceſſaries for a
                journey.</p><p>SUMPTUARY <hi rend="smallcaps">laws </hi><hi rend="italic">(Leges Sumptuariae), </hi>are laws made to reſtrain exceſs in apparel, coſtly furniture, eating, &amp;c.</p><p>Moſt ages and nations have had their ſumptuary laws ; and ſome regain them ſtill, as the Venetians, &amp;c. But it is obſerved, that no laws are worſe executed than ſumptuary laws. Political writers have been much divided in opinion with reſpect to the utility of theſe laws to a ſtate. Monteſquieu obſerves, that luxury is neceſſary in monarchies, as in France, but ruinous to democracies, as in Holland. With regard to England, whoſe government is compounded of both ſpecies, it may ſtill be a dubious queſtion, ſays judge Blackſtone, how far private luxury is a public evil ; and as ſuch cognizable by public laws.</p><p>The ſumptuary laws of that ancient Locrian legiſlator Zaleucus are famous : by theſe it was ordained, that no woman ſhould go attended with more than one maid in</p><p>@@@[mu] Asiatic Researches, vol. i.</p></body></text></TEI>