<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>medies employed for inflammation, in general, will be of ſervice. When it ariſes from unknown cauſes, ardent ſpirits and aſtringents have been found uſeful, particularly when topical and general bleedings have been previouſly uſed. When an effuſion of a ſerous matter takes place, it is immediately to be diſcharged, as it is almoſt impoſſible to convert it into proper pus. When this ſerum has continued ſo long as to render the bone carious, a removal of the whole bone, or of the carious portion, becomes neceſſary, in order to effect a complete cure.</p><p>Chilblains are inflammatory’ ſwellings, of a purple colour, chiefly affecting the heels, and ſometimes alſo the fingers, toes, arms, hands, or feet, or even the tips of the noſe and  ears, attended with a ſtinging pain, and a degree of itching. The ſwelling ſometimes cracks, and diſcharges an acrid ſerum : ſometimes a mortification takes place, and an ulcer follows very difficult to heal.</p><p>This diſorder is owing to the weaker action of the ſmall veſſels moſt remote from the heart, occaſioned by cold or dampneſs, and occurs moſt frequently in people of a delicate conſtitution.</p><p>When the patient has been for ſome time expoſed to the cold, and the parts are froſt bitten, they ought to be plunged into the coldeſt water and rubbed with ſalt ; when they are only benumbed, rubbing them with camphorated ſpirit of wine will anſwer equally well : but when cracks take place, and an oozing of acrid matter enſues, poultices may be applied, but not long, as they are apt to give riſe to fungous  excreſcences.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> VI. <hi rend="italic">Of Contuſions and Sprains.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Contusions</hi> of the integuments and muſcles produce pain, ſwelling, and inflammation, and theſe, in ſome caſes, may extend to a conſiderable degree ; but in general they are leſs violent than what take place in caſes of ſprains of ligaments or tendons ; for in theſe there is frequently a total loss of motion for many weeks, and ſometimes for years, if proper attention be not paid. An effuſion of fluids always ſucceeds the injury, which ſeems to be, for the moſt part, of a ſerous nature, as the ſkin uſually retains its natural colour ; ſometimes the tumefied parts are of a deep red, or leaden colour, owing to a rupture of ſome veſſels conveying red blood.</p><p>In the treatment of contuſions and ſprains, two circumstances require attention, 1. To endeavour to prevent the ſwelling as far as is practicable ; 2. To employ thoſe remedies afterwards which are known to be moſt powerful in preventing or removing inflammation. In contuſions of the cellular ſubſtance, and even of the muſcles, the effuſed fluids are commonly ſoon abſorbed ; but in ſprains of the tendons or ligaments, a very troubleſome, painful thickneſs of the injured parts is apt to continue for a great length of time, and in ſome inſtances even for life.</p><p>It is neceſſary, therefore, to obviate theſe ſymptoms as ſoon as poſſible ; and for this purpoſe, cold aſtringent applications, as water, vinegar, &amp;c, are moſt commonly uſed. Others again, with a view to relax the parts fully, make uſe of water as hot as the patient can bear it. By immerſing the injured part in theſe immediately after the injury is received, the effuſion will at leaſt be ſomewhat obviated. When the pain is exceſſive, opiates become neceſſary.</p><p>After blood has been freely diſcharged, a repetition of _ the remedies already mentioned will be found to give great relief ; care ſhould be taken, at the same time, that the injured parts be kept in a relaxed and easy poſture.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chap.</hi> VI. <hi rend="italic">Of Indolent Tumors.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">These</hi> are ſuch as are slow in their progreſs, and may continue ſor a long time without being attended with either pain or inflammation ; though occasionally almoſt all of them may be inflamed, and some of them, in that ſtate, attended with conſiderable pain. They are of different kinds according to the nature of their contents, and appear in various parts of the body. They are ſeated in the adipoſe and cellular membrane ; whence it often happens that they take place in the viſcera themſelves, where they are frequently mortal. Sometimes they are filled with a ſubſtance of the conſiſtence of honey, and are thence called m<hi rend="italic">eliceratous</hi> tumors ; ſometimes they are filled with an harder ſubſtance, and are then called <hi rend="italic">atheromatous</hi> tumors ; at other times they are filled with a ſubſtance of the conſiſtence of fat, and are then called st<hi rend="italic">eatomatous.</hi> Sometimes, however, they are found to be repleniſhed with a fluid lymph coagulable by heat, and are then called <hi rend="italic">hydatids.</hi> One ſet are filled with matter like the ſynovia of the joints, and get the name of <hi rend="italic">ganglions.</hi></p><p>Tumors of this kind are eaſily diſtinguiſhed from all others, as having neither heat, pain, nor pulſation, as is to be obſerved in thoſe which incline to ſuppurate ; and they are diſtinguiſhed from each other, before they are laid open, by fluctuation being readily perceived in the meliceris : the atheroma is ſoft and compreſſible, but has no fluctuation ; while the ſteatoma is commonly firm and rolls under the ſkin. But theſe rules are liable to conſiderable exceptions. The meliceris and atheroma are moſt commonly found upon the head, and the ſteatoma upon the other parts of the body ; while ganglions are ſituated over the tendons of the muſcles. Theſe tumors muſt be either extirpated entirely, or laid open ſo as to diſpoſe the cyſt to ſlough off or granulate. If the matter be fluid, we may evacuate it by an opening made with a lancet, or by means of a ſeton ; but as the matter is apt to collect again, it is better to remove the ſac entirely. If large veſſels or nerves prevent this from being done, then it is to be laid freely open and expoſed to the air, ſo that the bag may granulate, or be thrown off. When the tumor is to be extirpated, a longitudinal inciſion is to be made through the integuments ; after which the tumor may be frequently removed by the point of the finger, or by the end of a ſpatula, replacing the integuments with a view to heal by the firſt intention. In every pendulous tumor of this kind, with a narrow neck, we ought to divide the teguments near the bottom of the tumor, in an oval form, ſo that the wound may be afterwards properly covered with the remaining integuments. After the tumor is removed, the ſkin is to be replaced over the wound, and fixed with adheſive ſtraps, covering it with a pledgit of cerate, a ſmall compreſs of linen, with a bandage above all, to make a gentle preſſure on the parts.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> I. <hi rend="italic">Of Steatomatous and Sarcomatous Tumors.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Steatomatous</hi> tumore have been ranked by authors among thoſe of the encyſted kind ; but they have no other cyſt containing them than the common cellular ſubſtance, ſomewhat condenſed ; and the particles of fat compoſing them are found of the ſame ſize with thoſe in a sound part of the body.</p><p>Authors formerly adviſed the diſcuſſion of ſteatoms, or the prevention of their growth, by the application of preſſure ; but by ſuch means the growth is rather promoted than retarded, nor have internal remedies been of any advantage. They can be removed therefore by an operation which is the ſame with that for the extirpation of encyſted tumors.</p><p>Sarcomatous tumors have nearly the ſame external appearance with thoſe of the ſteatomatous kind. The term has been applied, in a general way, to scirrhi oſ the glands;</p></body></text></TEI>