<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the ſtreet except ſhe were drunk : that ſhe ſhould not go out of the city in the night, unleſs ſhe went to commit fornication : that ſhe ſhould not wear any gold or embroidered apparel, unleſs ſhe propoſed to be a common ſtrumpet ; and that men ſhould not wear rings or tiſſues except when they went a whoring, &amp;c.</p><p>Among the Romans, the ſumptuary laws were very numerous : By the <hi rend="italic">Lex Orcha,</hi> the number of gueſts at feaſts was limited, though without any limitation of the charges : by the Fannian law, made 22 years afterwards, it was enacted, that more than 10 <hi rend="italic">aſſes</hi> ſhould not be ſpent at any ordinary feaſt : for the ſolemn feaſts, as the Saturnalia, &amp;c. an hundred aſſes were allowed ; ten of which, Gellius informs us, was the price of a ſheep, and a hundred of an ox. By the Didian law, which was preferred 18 years after, it was decreed, that the former ſumptuary laws ſhould be in force, not only in Rome, but throughout all Italy ; and that for every tranſgreſſion, not only the matter of the feast, but all the gueſts too, ſhould be liable to the penalty.</p><p>The Engliſh have had their ſhare of ſumptuary laws, chiefly made in the reigns of Edw. III. Edw. IV. and Henry VIII. againſt ſhoes with long points, ſhort doublets, and long coats ; though all repealed by ſtatute 1 Jac. I. c. 25. As to excels in diet, there remains still one law unrepealed. Under King Henry IV. Camden tells us, pride was got ſo much into the foot, that it was proclaimed, that no man ſhould wear ſhoes above six inches broad at the toes. And their other garments were ſo ſhort, that it was enacted, 25 Edw. IV. that no perſon, under the condition of a lord, ſhould, from that time, wear any mantle or gown, unleſs of such length, that, ſtanding upright, it might cover his privy members and buttocks.</p><p>SUN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> ☉, in aſtronomy, the great luminary which enlightens the
                world, and by its preſence constitutes day. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Astronomy-Index.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Mock-SUN.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Parhelion.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SUN-Fiſh of the Iriſh.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Squalus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SUN-Flower,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Helianthus.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SUn-Dew,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Drosera.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SUNDA-islands,</hi> a general name for a cluſter of iſlands in the India Ocean, between 93⁰ and 120⁰ of east longitude, and between 8⁰ north and 8⁰ ſouth latitude. The particular names of the iſlands are <hi rend="italic">Borneo, Sumatra, Java, Bally, Banca,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>SUNDAY, or the <hi rend="smallcaps">Lord's-day,</hi> a ſolemn feſtival obſerved by Chriſtians on the firſt day of every week, in memory of our Saviour’s reſurrection. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sabbath.</hi></p><p>In the breviary and other offices we meet with Sundays of the firſt and ſecond claſs. Thoſe of the firſt claſs are, Palm, Eaſter, Advent, and Whitſunday, thoſe of Quasimodo and Q<hi rend="italic">uadragesima.</hi> Thoſe of the ſecond claſs are the common Sundays. Anciently each Sunday in the year had its particular name, which was taken from the introit of the day ; which cuſtom has only been continued to ſome few in lent ; as <hi rend="italic">Reminiscere, Oculi, Laetare, Judica.</hi></p><p>Some are of opinion that the Lord’s-day, mentioned in the Apocalypſe, is our Sunday ; which they believe was so early inſtituted by the apoſtles. Be this as it will, it is certain a regard was had to this day even in the earlieſt ages of the church ; as appears from the firſt apology of Justin Martyr, where he deſcribes the exerciſe of the day not much unlike to ours.</p><p>But it was Constantine the Great who firſt made a law for the proper observation of Sunday; and who, according to Euſebius, appointed it ſhould be regularly celebrated throughout the Roman empire. Before him, and even in his time, they obſerved the Jewiſh Sabbath as well as Sunday ; both to ſatisfy the law of Moſes and to imitate the apoſtles, who uſed to meet together on the firſt day.</p><p>By Conſtantine’s? laws, made in 321, it was decreed, that for the future the Sunday ſhould be kept a day of reſt in all cities and towns ; but he allowed the country people to follow their work. In 538, the council of Orleans prohibited country labour ; but becauſe there were ſtill many Jews in Gaul, and the people fell into many ſuperſtitious uſages in the cclebratiop of the new Sabbath, like thoſe of the Jews among that of the old, the council declares, that to hold it unlawful to travel with horſes, cattle, and carriages, to prepare food, or to do any thing neceſſary to the cleanlineſs and decency of houſes or perſons, favours more of Judaiſm than of Chriſtianity. See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sabbat</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">h- </hi><hi rend="italic">Breaking.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SUNDAY-Schools.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Sunday-S</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">chools</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi></p><p>SUOVETAURILIA, an ancient Roman ſacrifice, ſo called becauſe it conſiſted of a pig <hi rend="italic">(ſus),</hi> a ſheep or rather ram (ovis), and a bull (<hi rend="italic">taurus).</hi> They were all males, to denote the maſculine courage of the Roman people. It was likewiſe called so<hi rend="italic">litaurilia,</hi> becauſe the animals offered up were always <hi rend="italic">ſolida,</hi> whole or uncut.</p><p>SUPERCARGO, a perſon employed by merchants to go a voyage, and overſee their cargo or lading, and diſpoſe of it to the beſt advantage.</p><p>SUPERCILIUM, in anatomy, the eye-brow. See AΝΑΤΟΜΥ, n⁰ 142.</p><p>SUPEREROGATION, in theology, what a man does beyond his duty, or more than he is commanded to do. The Romanists stand up strenuouſly for works of ſupererogation, and maintain that the obſervance of evangelical councils is ſuch. By means hereof, a stock of merit is laid up, which the church has the diſpoſal of, and which ſhe diſtributes in indulgences to ſuch as need.</p><p>This abſurd doctrine was firſt invented towards the cloſe of the 12th century, and modified and embelliſhed by St Thomas in the 13th: according to which, it was pretended that there actually exiſted an immenſe treaſure of merit, compoſed of the pious deeds and virtuous actions which the saints had performed beyond what was neceſſary for their own ſalvation, and which were therefore applicable to the benefit of others ; that the guardian and diſpenſer of this precious treaſure was the Roman pontiff ; and that of consequence he was empowered to assign to ſuch as he thought proper a portion of this inexhauſtible ſource of merit, ſuitable to their reſpective guilt, and ſufficient to deliver them from the puniſhment due to their crimes.</p><p>The reformed church do not allow of any work of ſupererogation ; but hold with the apoſtles, that when we have done our beſt, we are but unprofitable ſervants.</p><p>SUPERFETATION, in medicine, a ſecond or after-conception, happening when the mother, already pregnant, conceives of a latter coition ; ſo that ſhe bears at once two foetuſes of unequal age and bulk, and is delivered of them at different times. We meet with inſtances of ſuperfetations in Hippocrates, Ariſtotle, Du Laurens, &amp;c. : but they are ſaid to be much more frequent in hares and swine.</p><p>SUPERFICIES, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Surface,</hi> in geometry, the outſide or exterior face of any body. This is conſidered as having the two dimenſions of length and breadth only, but 110 thickness ; and therefore it makes no part of the ſubſtance or ſolid content or matter of the body.</p><p>The terms, or bounds, or extremities, of a ſuperficies, are lines ; and ſuperficies may be conſidered as generated by the motions of lines. Superficies are either rectilinear, curvilinear, plane, concave, or convex. A rectilinear ſuperficies is that which is bounded by right lines. Curvilinear ſuperfi-</p></body></text></TEI>