<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">cer ;</hi> which, as long as the edges continue in that ſtate, muſt neceſſarily be prevented from healing. But we are not immediately to deſtroy the lips of it, in expectation of a ſudden cure ; for while the malignity of the ulcer remains which was the occaſion of the callosity, the new lips will be ſubject to a relapſe of the ſame kind, however often the external ſurface of them be deſtroyed : we are to endeavour to bring the body of the ulcer into a dispoſition to recover by other methods. It ſometimes happens to poor laborious people, who have not been able to afford themſelves reſt, that lying a-bed will in a ſhort time give a diversion to the humours of the part, and the callous edges, ſoftening, will without any great aſſiſtance ſhoot out a cicatrix, when the ulcer is grown clean and filled with good fleſh. The effect of a ſalivation is generally the ſame; and even an iſſue ſometimes diſpoſes a neighbouring ulcer to heal. But though calloſities be frequently ſoftened by theſe means, yet when the ſurface of the ulcer begins to yield thick matter and little granulations of red fleſh ſhoot up, it will be proper to quicken nature by deſtroying the edges of it, if they remain hard. The manner of doing this, is by touching them a few days with the lunar cauſtic, or <hi rend="italic">lapis inſernalis.</hi> Some chose to cut them off with a knife : but this is very painful, and not more efficacious. When the lips do not tuck down cloſe to the ulcer, but hang looſe over it, as in ſome venereal buboes, the eaſieſt method is to cut them off with the ſcissars.</p><p>To digeſt the ulcer, or to procure good matter from it when in a putrid ſtate, there are an infinity of ointments invented ; but the baſilico flavum, alone, or ſoftened down ſometimes with turpentines, and ſometimes mixed up with different proportions of red precipitate, ſeems to ſerve the purpoſe of bringing an ulcer to cicatrization as well as any of the others. When the ulcer is incarned, the cure maybe finiſhed as in other wounds ; or if it do not cicatriſe kindly, ſt may be waſhed with aq. calcis, or aq. phag. or dreſſed with a pledgit dipt in tinct. myrrhæ : and if excoriations are ſpread round the ulcer, they may be anointed with ſperm. cet. ointment, or any other ſoft ointment.</p><p>The red precipitate has of late years acquired the credit it deferves for the cure of ulcers ; but, by falling into general uſe, is very often unſkilfully applied : when mixed with the baſilicon, or, what is nearer, a cerate of wax and oil, it is moſt certainly a digeſtive, fince it hardly ever fails to make the ulcer yield a thick matter in 24 hours, which diſcharged a thin one before the application of it.</p><p>If the ulcer produces a ſpongy fleſh, ſprouting very high above the ſurface, it will be neceſſary to deſtroy it by ſome of the eſcharotics, or the knife. This fungus differs very much ſrom that belonging to healing wounds, being more eminent and lax, and generally in one male ; whereas the other is in little diſtinct protuberances. It approaches often towards a cancerous complexion, and when it riſes upon ſome glands ſometimes actually degenerates into a cancer. When theſe excreſcences have ariſen in venereal ulcers, eſeharotics ſhould be applied. Thoſe in uſe, are the vitriol, the lunar cauſtic, the lapis inſernalis, and more generally the red precipitate powder.</p><p>It is but ſeldom that theſe inveterate funguſes appear on an ulcer ; but it is very usual for thoſe of a milder kind to riſe, which may often be made to ſubſide by preſſure and the uſe of mild eſeharotics : however, if the aſpect of the sore be white and ſmooth, as happens in ulcers accompanied with a dropsy, and often in young women with obſtructions, it will anſwer no purpoſe to waste the excreſcences until the conſtitution is repaired when moſt probably they will sink without any aſſiſtance. In ulcers alſo, where the ſubjacent bone is carious, great quantities of looſe flabby fleſh will grow up above the level of the skin : but as the caries is the cauſe of the diſorder, it will be in vain to expect a cure of the excreſcence until the rotten part of the bone be removed ; and every attempt with eſeharotics will be only a repetition of pain to the patient, without any advantage.</p><p>When the pain and inflammation are exceſſive, bleeding and other evacuations will often be ſerviceable ; and above all things, reſt and a horizontal poſition ; which laſt circumſtance is of ſo great importance to the cure of ulcers of the legs, that unleſs the patient will conform to it ſtrictly, the ſkill of the ſurgeon will often avail nothing : for as the indiſpoſition of theſe sores is in ſome mcaſure owing to the gravitation of the humours downwards, it will be much more beneficial to lie along than sit upright, though the leg be laid on a chair ; since even in this poſture they will descend with more force than if the body was reclined.</p><p>In ulcers of the legs, accompanied with varices or dilatations of the veins, the method of treatment will depend upon the other circumſtances of the sore ; for the varix can only be aſſiſted by the application of bandage, which muſt be continued a conſiderable time after the cure. The neateſt bandage is the laced ſtocking, which is particularly ſerviceable in this caſe ; though alſo, if the legs be œdematous, or if, after the healing of the ulcers, they ſwell when the patient quits his bed, it may be worn with ſafety and advantage. There are inſtances of one vein only being varicous; which, when it happens, may be deſtroyed by tying it above and below the dilatation, as in an aneuriſm ; but this operation ſhould only be practiſed where the varix is large and painful.</p><p>Ulcers of many years ſtanding are very difficult of cure ; and in old people the cure is often dangerous, frequently exciting an aſthma, a diarrhoea, or a fever, which deſtroys the patient, unleſs the ſore break out again : ſo that it is not altogether adviſable to attempt the abſolute cure in ſuch caſes; but only the reduction of them into better order, and leſs compaſs, which, if they be not malignant, is generally done with reſt and proper care. The cure of thoſe in young people may be undertaken with more ſafety ; and in all caſes of ſtubborn ulcers, the bark, very copiously given, will be found of the utmoſt ſervice.</p><p>When an ulcer or abſceſs has any ſinuſes or channels opening and diſcharging themſelves into the ſore, they are called <hi rend="italic">ſinuous ulcers.</hi> Theſe ſinuſes, if they continue to drain a great while, grow hard in the ſurface of their cavity, and then are termed fistulae<hi rend="italic">,</hi> and the ulcer a sistulou<hi rend="italic">s ulcer ;</hi> alſo, if matter be diſcharged from any cavity, as thoſe of the joints, abdomen, &amp;c. the opening is called a si<hi rend="italic">nuοus ulcer</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">fistula.</hi></p><p>The treatment of theſe ulcers depends upon a variety of circumſtances. If the matter of the ſinus be thick, ſtrict bandage and compreſs will sometimes bring the oppoſite ſides of the ſinus to a reunion : if the ſinus grow turgid in any part, and the ſkin thinner, ſhowing a diſpoſition to break, the matter must be made to puſh more againſt that part, by plugging it up with a tent ; and then a counter opening muſt be made, which proves often ſufficient for the whole abſceſs, if it be not afterwards too much tented,  which locks up the matter and prevents the healing ; or too little, which will have the ſame effect : for dreſſing quite superficially does ſometimes prove as miſchievous as tents, and ſor nearly the ſame reaſon ; since ſuffering the external wound to contract into a narrow orifice before the internal one be incarned, does almoſt as effectually lock up the matter as a tent.  To preſerve, then, a medium in theſe caſes, a hollow tent of lead or silver may be kept in the orifice, which, at the same time that it keeps it open, gives vent to the matter. The abſcesses where the counter opening is</p></body></text></TEI>