<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>matron that is here particularly treated of, and in which no ſuch varieties are ever obſerved, it is not neceſſary to carry the inquiry farther.</p><p>The prognoſis in every caſe of gangrene is doubtful at firſt, as, even in the ſlighteſt caſes, the patient may suffer from the ſpreading of the diſeaſe; but slight caſes, from external injuries, are more favourable than thoſe which ariſe from internal cauſes, though no perſon can be considered ſafe till the diſeaſed parts are ſeparated, and even entirely caſt off. When inflammation happens round a mortified part, more eſpecially if pus be formed, we may pretty certainly pronounce that the mortified part will be thrown off.</p><p>When there is reaſon to ſuſpect from the violence of the fever and great heat of the inflamed part, that it will terminate in gangrene, blood-letting, and whatever may have a tendency to moderate the inflammation, may check its progreſs. But as the patient, in ſuch caſes, is ſometimes apt to sink afterwards, nothing more ought to be done than is merely neceſſary to moderate the preſent ſymptoms. If an inflamed ſurface put on a gangrenous appearance when the patient is weak, and the pulſe low, we muſt have recourſe to whatever may invigorate the ſyſtem, viz. a nouriſhing diet, with the free uſe of wine. Peruvian bark likewiſe is to be given in as great quantities as the ſtomach of the patient will permit. When the ſtomach cannot bear enough in ſubſtance, which is the beſt form of exhibiting it, it may be given either in form of tincture or joined with aromatics. External applications, ſuch as are of a ſtimulating nature, may likewiſe be uſeſul.</p><p>In the caſe of gangrene ariſing from cold, the part muſt he immerſed in very cold water, or rubbed with ſnow ; for if any thing warm be applied, or the patient brought near a fire, it certainly mortifies. If the whole body has become torpid with cold, the ſame practice muſt be followed ; the very cold water ſhould be afterwards changed for ſome that is a little warmer, and the patient gradually brought to a proper degree of heat. Rubbing with ſalt is ſometimes found uſeful. If the whole body be benumbed, cordials are not to be adminiſtered too suddenly. A glaſs of cold wine ſhould firſt be given, afterwards warm wine by itself, or with ſpices. If ſtronger cordials be required, ardent ſpirits may be employed. Notwithſtanding the greateſt attention, however, a mortification ſometimes takes place, and in ſome inſtances very suddenly ; as in the cafe of carbuncle, where, after an inflammation has continued for ſcarcely 24 hours, the parts become black, and end in real mortification.</p><p>In the treatment of mortified parts, a variety of external applications have been pointed out, and particularly thoſe of the antiſeptic kind ; ſuch as all the warm gums and balſams, ardent ſpirits, and even alcohol : and to admit of their nearer application to the found parts, with a view to the preservation of theſe from putrefaction, deep scarifications through the diſeaſed, and into the found parts, have been generally recommended. But although ſuch articles may be of uſe in preſerving dead animal-ſubſtances from corruption ; yet that they will always prove ſerviceable in the ſame manner in living bodies, is probably very much to be doubted. And it is even apprehended, by the ſtrong irritation they always occaſion when applied to a living fibre, that, in ſuch caſes as the preſent, they may rather do miſchief ; it being only a very slight degree of inflammation that is required to bring on a ſuppuration. The inciſions, when carried into the sound parts, with a view to facilitate the operation of ſuch remedies, may likewiſe do harm ; not only from the risk of wounding the blood-vessels, nerves, and tendons, that lie in the way, but alſo by allowing a free and farther entrance of the putreſcent fluids into the parts not yet affected - and unleſs they are carried so deep as freely to reach the sound parts, applications of the antiſeptic kind can never have any effect in anſwering the purpoſe for which they were intended.</p><p>All the advantages commonly obſerved from the great variety of applications recommcnded for gangrene, are obtained with more eaſe, and generally with more certainty, from the uſe of any gentle ſtimulating embrocation ; which, by exciting a slight irritation upon the ſurface, and especially when aſſiſted by a free uſe of the bark, at laſt commonly produces ſuch a degree of inflammation as is wiſhed for. With this view, a weak ſolution of ſal ammoniac in vinegar and water has been known to anſwer exceedingly well : a dram of the ſalt to two ounces of vinegar and six of water, forms a mixture of a very proper ſtrength for every purpoſe of this kind; but the degree of ſtimulus can be eaſily either increaſed or diminiſhed, according to circumſtances, by uſing a larger or ſmaller proportion of the ſalt.</p><p>Although, for the reaſons formerly advanced, inciſions may not in general be proper; yet in ſuch caſes where the mortification runs very deep, it is ſometimes of ſervice to make ſcarifications into the diſeaſed parts, ſo as to remove part of them ; which, by taking off a conſiderable load perhaps of putrid fleſh, not only lessens the fetor, which in ſuch caſes is always conſiderable, but often renders it more eaſy for the sound parts to free themſelves from the remainder. When with this view, however, inciſions are had recourſe to, care ſhould always be taken that they be not carried the length of the found parts.</p><p>When by the uſe of external or internal remedies, a ſeparation of the mortified part has been effected, and a diſcharge of pus produced, the remaining fore is then to be conſidered merely as a ſimple purulent ulcer, and may be treated in the ſame manner.</p><p>CHAP. IV. <hi rend="italic">Of Ulcers, White Swellings, Cancers, and Burns.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sect.</hi> I. <hi rend="italic">Of Ulcers.</hi></p><p>A <hi rend="smallcaps">solution</hi> of continuity in any of the softer parts of the body, diſcharging either pus, ſanies, or any other vitiated matter, is termed <hi rend="italic">ulcer ;</hi> and when the ſame circumſtances happen to the bones, the term <hi rend="italic">caries</hi> or <hi rend="italic">carious ulcer </hi>is adopted.</p><p>Ulcers are diſtinguiſhed by their particular diſorders, though it ſeldom happens that the affections are not complicated ; and when we lay down rules ſor the management of one ſpecies of ulcer, it is generally requiſite to apply them to almoſt all others. However, the characters of moſt eminence are, the callous ulcer, the ſinuous ulcer, and the ulcer with caries of the adjacent bone : beſides this there is the putrid, the corroſive, the varicoſe ulcers, &amp;c. ; but as they have acquired their names from ſome particular affection, we ſhall ſpeak of the treatment of them under the general head of ulcers.</p><p>It will be often in vain to purſue the beſt means of cure by topical application, unleſs we are aſſiſted by internal remedies ; for as many ulcers are the effects of a particular indiſpoſition of body, it will be difficult to bring them into order while the cauſe of them remains. Thoſe which are cancerous and ſcrophulous ſeem to gain the leaſt advantage from phyſic ; for if in their beginnings they have ſometimes been very much relieved, or cured, by salivation, or any other evacuation, they are alſo often irritated and made worſe by them.</p><p>When an ulcer becomes foul, and diſcharges a naſty thin ichor, the edges of it, in proceſs of time, tuck in, and, growing skinned and hard, give it the name of a <hi rend="italic">callous ul-</hi></p></body></text></TEI>