<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:03:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>theſe animals proves frequently very troubleſome, and ſometimes interrupts for a time the uſe of other remedies.</p><p>Upon the anterior part of the joint, where the cupping- glaſſes have not been placed, a ſmall bliſter ſhould be directly applied, and the part kept open with issue-ointment, till the wounds from the ſcarificator are ſo far healed that a veſicatory may likewiſe be laid on one side of the joint ; and so ſoon as that is nearly healed, the other side ſhould be alſo bliſtered. By thus alternately applying them, firſt to the one side and then to the other, almoſt a constant ſtimulus is kept up ; which, in deep-ſeated inflammations, ſeems to have fully a greater influence than all the diſcharge occaſioned by bliſters. Gentle cooling laxatives at proper intervals are alſo of uſe ; and the patient ſhould, in every reſpect, be kept upon a ſtrict antiphlogiſtic courſe, both as to diet and every other circumſtance.</p><p>It is in the firſt ſtages only of the diſeaſe that ſuch a courſe can be of much ſervice ; and in ſuch it has frequently been a means of curing diſorders which otherwiſe might have proceeded to the laſt ſtages of white ſwellings.</p><p>The original inflammatory affection being once over, theſe sort of drains ſeem to have little or no influence, and ought not then to be long perſiſted in, as they prevent the uſe of other remedies, which, in an advanced ſtate of the diſeaſe, are commonly more efficacious.</p><p>The inflammation being moſtly gone, and while there are yet no appearances of the formation of matter, mercury has ſometimes been known of uſe ; not given ſo as to ſalivate, but merely to affect the mouth gently, and to keep it somewhat ſore for a few weeks.</p><p>The beſt form of uſing it is by way of unction, as it allows, at the ſame time, the application of friction ; which, in all ſuch ſwellings, may of itſelf be in ſome meaſure conſidered as a remedy. For this purpoſe, an ointment of quickſilver and hog’s lard ſhould be prepared ; but with ſo ſmall a proportion of the former, that the patient may admit of two drams of the ointment being rubbed in three times a-day. In order to rub that quantity of the medicine in with gentle friction, an hour each time is at leaſt neceſſary ; for in the ordinary way of continuing friction for a few minutes only, it can ſeldom have much influence.</p><p>By Le Dran, and other French writers, falls of warm water on ſwellings of this nature are much recommended ; and there is no doubt, that a long continued and reiterated application of that remedy may, in the firſt ſtages of ſuch complaints, be often attended with very good effects. By a proper uſe of theſe different applications, viz. of the ſeveral topical remedies in the firſt or inflammatory ſtate of the diſeaſe, and afterwards (ſtill, however, before the formation of matter) of mercurials, friction, &amp;c. many affections of this nature have been entirely removed.</p><p>It frequently happens, by the bent poſition the limb has been for a long time kept in, that the uſe of the joint comes to be entirely loſt, having often acquired ſuch a degree of ſtiffneſs, that any attempts to move it are commonly attended with very great pain. This has been conſtantly attributed to one or other of two different cauſes, which are both in their nature incurable, viz. either to the ends of ſuch bones as compoſe the joints having run into one another, ſo as to become firmly conjoined in conſequence of the ſurrounding cartilages being abraded ; or to the inſpiſſation, as it is termed, of the ſynovia of the joints, whereby their cavities are entirely filled up, and no ſpace left for the future motion of the bones.</p><p>Both theſe opinions, however, are in general very ill founded : as the ſtiffneſs almoſt always proceeds from a contraction of the muſeles and tendons. It may often be cured by a long continued uſe of emollients.</p><p>The beſt emollient that can be uſed is pure olive oil applied warm ; as much of it as can be eaſily rubbed in by an hour’s gentle friction ſhould be regularly done at leaſt three times a-day ; and inſtead of confining the friction altogether to the rigid tendons, it ſhould be extended over the whole muſeles, even to the inſertions of their other extremities ; but more eſpecially on their fleſhy muſcular parts, where the principal cauſe of the continuance of ſuch complaints is probably ſeated.</p><p>The web or omentum of a new-killed ſheep, or of any other animal, applied over all the diſeaſed parts directly on being cut out of the animal, is ſometimes attended with advantage. The application ſhould be renewed as frequently as poſſible, once a day at leaſt, or oftener when it can be done ; for on being more than four or five hours applied it becomes diſagreeable ; and after that time, indeed, as it commonly turns ſtiff, it cannot then probably be of much ſervice.</p><p>The diſorder has hitherto been ſuppoſed not to be ſo far advanced as to have occaſioned the formation of matter ; for when come that length, no conſiderable advantages can be expected from any of the remedies as yet recommended : but even in that ſtate of the complaint, if the patient’s health does not abſolutely require it, amputation of the member ſhould not be immediately had recourſe to. For by opening the different abſcesses ſoon after their formation, the matter may be prevented from deſtroying the capſular ligaments of the joints, which, if once effected, would no doubt render that operation necessary, Even in point of ſucceſs from the operation, it ought never to be adviſed till the complaint is pretty far advanced. For in this diſorder, eſpecially, a greater proportion of patients have recovered after amputation, who have previouſly been conſiderably reduced by diarrhoeas and other weakening ſymptoms, than of ſuch as have ſtill remained in a full plethoric habit of body.”</p><p>All the different obſervations hitherto made upon the treatment, relate particularly to the rheumatic ſpecies of the diſorder ; and when had recourſe to in time, and duly perſiſted in, they will frequently be found of ſervice : but when the diſeaſe is ſo far advanced as to have deſtroyed the capſular ligaments of the joint, and perhaps even the cartilages and bones themſelves, amputation of the member is then no doubt the only reſource.</p><p>In the ſcrophulous white ſwellings, when the diſeaſed parts of the bone begin to cast off, a cure may in that way, by aſſiſting the efforts of nature, be ſometimes obtained in the ſmall joints ; but in all the large joints, as the knee, ankle, &amp;c. it is not probable that any other reſource than amputation will ever afford much relief. And even the effects of that operation can ſeldom be depended on as laſting ; for when the general ſcrophulous taint ſtill ſubſiſts in the conſtitution, the diſorder will moſt probably appear again in ſome other part ; which, however, in the advanced ſtages of the diſeaſe, it is ſometimes necessary to run the riſk of, the pain being often ſo tormenting as to make it more eligible to ſubmit to any hazard rather than to bear it longer.</p><p>When, however, for ſome reaſon or other, amputation is dctermined againſt, as there being almoſt a certainty of the complaint ſoon returning, from the ſcrophulous diſpoſition appearing very ſtrong in the ſyſtem, it then becomes neceſſary to have recourſe to palliatives, ſo as to render the complaint as tolerable as poſſible : and with this view, opiates in large doſes, by moderating the pain and procuring reſt to the patient, will in general be found the principal remedy. In other reſpects, all ſuch medicines and articles of regimen as are found beneficial in ſcrophula, may be had recourſe to.</p></body></text></TEI>