<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:01:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SUB-DEACON, an inferior miniſter, who anciently attended at the altar, prepared the ſacred vessels, delivered them to the deacons in time of divine ſervice, attended the doors of the church during communion-ſervice, went on the the biſhop’s embaſſies with his letters or messages to foreign churches, and was invested with the firſt of the holy orders. They were ſo ſubordinate to the ſuperior rulers of the church, that, by a canon of the council of Laodicea, they were forbidden to sit in the preſence of a deacon without his leave. According to the canons, a perſon muſt be twenty two years of age to be promoted to the order of ſubdeacon. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Deacon.</hi></p><p>SUBDOMINANT, in muſic, a name given by M. Rameau to the fourth note of the tone, which of conſequence is the ſame interval from the tonic when deſcending as the dominant in rising. This denomination ariſes from the affinity which this author finds by inverſion between the minor mode of the ſubdominant and the major mode of the tonic.</p><p>SUBDUPIÆ <hi rend="smallcaps">ratio,</hi> is when any number or quantity is contained in another twice. Thus 3 is ſaid to be ſubduple of 6, as 6 is duple of 3. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ratio.</hi></p><p>SUBDUPLICATE <hi rend="smallcaps">ratio</hi> of any two quantities, is the ratio of their ſquare roots.</p><p>SUBER, the <hi rend="smallcaps">cork-tree,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Quercus.</hi></p><p>SUBJECT, a perſon under the rule and dominion of a ſovereign prince or ſtate.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Subject</hi> is alſo uſed for the matter of an art or ſcience, or that which it conſiders, or whereon it is employed : thus the human body is the ſubject of medicine.</p><p>SUBINFEUDATION, was where the inferior lords, in imitation of their ſuperiors, began to carve out and grant to others minuter eſtates than their own, to be held of themſelves ; and were ſo proceeding downwards <hi rend="italic">in infinitum,</hi> till the ſuperior lords obſerved, that by this method of ſubinfeudation they loſt all their feodal profits, of wardſhips, marriages, and eſcheats, which fell into the hands of theſe meſne or middle lords, who were the immediate ſuperiors of the terre-tenant, or him who occupied the land.@@ This occaſioned the stat. of Weſtm. 3. or <hi rend="italic">quia emptores,</hi> 18 Edw. I. to be made ; which directs, that, upon all ſales or feoffments of lands, the feoffee ſhall hold the ſame, not of his immediate feoffer, but of the chief lord of the fee of whom ſuch feoffer himſelf held it. And from hence it is held, that all manors exiſting at this day muſt have exiſted by immemorial preſcription ; or at leaſt ever ſince the 18 Edw. I. when the ſtatute oſ <hi rend="italic">quia emptores</hi> was made.</p><p>SUBITO, in the Italian muſic, is uſed to signify that a thing is to be performed quickly and haſtily : thus we meet with <hi rend="italic">volti ſubito, turn</hi> over the leaf quickly.</p><p>SUBJUNCTIVE, in grammar. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Grammar.</hi></p><p>SUBLIMATE, a chemical preparation, conliſting of quickſilver united with the marine acid. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemtstry- I</hi><hi rend="italic">ndex.</hi></p><p>SUBLIMATION, in chemiſtry, the condenſing and collecting, in a ſolid form, by means of vessels aptly conſtructed, the fumes of bodies raised from them by the application of a proper heat. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> n⁰ 5-81.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SUBLIM.E, or Sublimity.</hi> See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Grandeur </hi>and <hi rend="smallcaps">Sublimity</hi></p><p>SUBLINGUAL <hi rend="smallcaps">artery.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sublingual</hi><hi rend="italic"> Glands,</hi> in anatomy, two glands under the tongue, placed one on each ſide thereof</p><p>SUBMULTIPLE, in geometry, &amp;,c. A ſubmultiple number, or quantity, is that which is contained a certain number of times in another, and which, therefore, repeated a certain number of times, becomes exactly equal thereto. Thus 3 is a ſubmultiple of 21. In which ſenſe a ſubmultiple coincides with an aliquot part.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SUBMULTIPLE Ratio,</hi> is that between the quantity contained and the quantity containing. Thus the ratio of 3 to 21 is ſubmultiple. In both caſes ſubmultiple is the reverſe of multiple : 21, <hi rend="italic">e. gr.</hi> being a multiple of 3, and the ratio of 21 to 3 a multiple ratio.</p><p>SUBORDINARIES. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Heraldry,</hi> Chap. III. Sect. II. page 454.</p><p>SUBORDINATION, a relative term, expreſſing an inferiority betwixt one perſon and another.</p><p>SUBORNATION, in law, a ſecret, underhand, preparing, inſtructing, or bringing in a falſe witneſs ; and from hence <hi rend="italic">ſubornation of perjury</hi> is the preparing or corrupt alluring to perjury. The puniſhment for this crime was formerly death, then baniſhment or cutting out the tongue, afterwards forfeiture of goods ; and it is now a fine and impriſonment, and never more to be received as evidence. The ſtatute 2 Geo. II. c. 25. ſuperadded a power for the court to order the offender to be ſent to the houſe of correction for a term not exceeding ſeven years, or be tranſported for the ſame period.</p><p>SUBPŒNA, in law, a writ whereby common perſons are called into chancery, in ſuch caſes where the common law hath provided no ordinary remedy ; and the name of it proceeds from the words therein, which charge the party called to appear at the day and place assigned, sub <hi rend="italic">poena centum librarum,</hi> &amp;c. The ſubpoena is the leading proceſs in the courts of equity ; and by ſtatute, when a bill is filed againſt any perſon, proceſs of ſubpoena ſhall be taken out to oblige the defendant to appear and anſwer the bill, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Subpoena</hi><hi rend="italic"> ad testificandum,</hi> a writ or proceſs to bring in witneſſes to give their teſtimony. If a witneſs on being ſerved with this proceſs does not appear, the court will iſſue an attachment againſt him ; or a party, plaintiff or defendant, injured by his non-attendance, may maintain an action againſt the witneſs. See <hi rend="italic">Blackest. Corn.</hi> Vol. III. p. 369.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Subpoena</hi><hi rend="italic"> in Equity,</hi> a proceſs in equity, calling on a defendant to appear and anſwer to the complainant’s bill. See ſtatute 5th Geo. II. c. 25. which enacts, that where the party cannot be found to be ſerved with a ſubpoena, and abſconds (as believed) to avoid being ſerved, a day ſhall be appointed him to appear to the bill of the plaintiff; which is to be inſerted in the London Gazette, read in the pariſh-church where the defendant laſt lived, and fixed up at the Royal Exchange : and if the defendant doth not appear upon that day, the bill ſhall be taken <hi rend="italic">pro confesso.</hi></p><p>SUBREPTITIOUS, a term applied to a letter, licence, patent, or other act, fraudulently obtained of a ſuperior, by concealing ſome truth which, had it been known, would have prevented the conceſſion or grant,</p><p>SUBROGATION, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Surrogation,</hi> in the Civil- Law, the act of ſubſtituting a perſon in the place, and intitling him to the rights, of another. In its general ſenſe, ſubrogation implies a ſucceſſion of any kind, whether of a perſon to a perſon, or of a perſon to a thing;</p><p>There are two kinds of ſubrogation : the one <hi rend="italic">conventional,</hi> the other <hi rend="italic">legal. Conventional</hi> ſubrogation is a contract whereby a creditor transfers his debt, with all appurtenances, thereof, to the profit of a third perſon. <hi rend="italic">Legal</hi> subrogation is that which the law makes in favour oſ a perſon who diſcharges an antecedent creditor; in which caſe there is a legal tranſlation of all rights of the ancient creditor to the perſon of the new one.</p><p>SUBSCRIPTION, in general, ſignifies the signature put at the bottom of a letter, writing, or inſtrument.</p><p>In commerce, it is uſed for the ſhare or intereſt which particular perſons take in a public ſtock or a trading com-</p><p>@@@[mu] Blackstone's Commentary, vol. ii.</p></body></text></TEI>