<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:01:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pany, by writing their names, and the ſhares they require, in the books or regiſter thereof</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Subscription</hi> to articles of faith is required of the clergy of every eftabliſhed church, and of ſome churches not eftabliſhed. Whether ſuch ſubſcription ſerves any good purpoſe, in a religious or theological view, is a very doubtful queſtion. It may be neceſſary in an eſtabliſhment, as a teſt of loyalty to the prince, and of attachment to the conſtitution, civil and eccleſiaſtical, but it cannot produce uniformity of opinion. As all language is more or leſs ambiguous, it becomes difficult, if not impoſſible, to determine in what ſenſe the words of long eftabliſhed creeds are to be interpreted ; and we believe that the clergy of the churches of England and Scotland ſeldom conſider themſelves as fettered by the Thirty-nine Articles, or the Confeſſion of Faith, when compoſing instructions either for their reſpective pariſhes or for the public at large. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Independents.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Subscription,</hi> in the commerce of books, ſignifies an engagement to take a certain number of copies of a book intended to be printed, and a reciprocal obligation of the bookſeller or publiſher to deliver the laid copies, on certain terms.—Theſe ſubſcriptions, which had their rise in England about the middle of the laſt century, were lately very frequent in France and Holland, and are now very common among ourſelves.</p><p>SUBSEQUENT, ſomething that comes after another, particularly with regard to the order of time.</p><p>SUBSIDY, in law, ſignifies an aid or tax granted to the king by parliament, for the neceſſary occaſions of the kingdom ; and is to be levied on every ſubject of ability, according to the rate or value of his lands or goods : but this word, in ſome of our ſtatutes, is confounded with that of cuſtoms. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Tax.</hi></p><p>SUBSTANCE, the ſubject: to which we ſuppoſe qualities belong. Thus gold is the ſubſtance to which the qualities of ductility, yellowneſs, denſity, &amp;c. belong. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> n⁰ 145.</p><p>SUBSTANTIAL, in the ſchools, ſomething belonging to the nature of ſubſtance.</p><p>SUBSTANTIVE, in grammar. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Grammar.</hi></p><p>SUBSTISTUTE, a perſon who officiates for another in his abſence.</p><p>SUBSTITUTION, in the civil law, a diſpoſition of a teſtament, whereby the teſtator subſtitutes one heir for another, who has only the uſufruit, and not the property, of the thing left him.</p><p>SUBSTRACTION, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Subtraction,</hi> in arithmetic, the ſecond rule, or rather operation, in arithmetic, whereby we deduct a leſs number from a greater, to learn their preciſe difference. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Arithmetic</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Algebra.</hi></p><p>SUBTANGENT <hi rend="smallcaps">of a Curve,</hi> the line that determines the intersection of a tangent with the axis ; or that determines the point wherein the tangent cuts the axis prolonged.</p><p>SUBTENSE, formed from <hi rend="italic">ſub</hi> “ under,” and <hi rend="italic">tendo </hi>“ I stretch,” in geometry, a right line which is oppoſite to an angle, and drawn between the two extremities of the arch which meaſures that angle.</p><p>SUBTERRANEOUS, whatever is under ground: thus naturaliſts ſpeak of ſubterraneous fires, ſubterraneous damps, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Subterraneous</hi><hi rend="italic"> Cavern.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Quarries.</hi></p><p>SUBTILE, in physics, an appellation given to whatever is extremely ſmall, fine, and delicate ; ſuch as the animal-ſpirits, the effluvia of ordorous bodies, &amp;c. are ſuppoſed to be.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SUBULARIA, </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Rough-le</hi><hi rend="italic">AVED </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">AlysSON,</hi><hi rend="italic"> or Awl</hi>wort,<hi rend="italic"> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs oſ </hi>tetr adynamia,<hi rend="italic"> and order of </hi>ſiliculoſa ; <hi rend="italic">and in the natural order ranging under the 39th order, Si</hi>liquoſae.<hi rend="italic"> The filicula is entire and ovate ; the valves are ovate, concave, and contrary to the partitions. The ſtyle is ſhorter than the filicula. There is only one species, the </hi>aquatica, <hi rend="italic">which is a native of Britain. It is about an inch high. The leaves are awl-ſhaped, and grow in cluſters round the root. The ſtalk is naked, and produces four or five ſmall white flowers growing alternately on ſhort footſtalks. It flowers under water, whereas moſt aquatic plants emerge above water at the time of flowering. The Author of Nature has, however, carefully prevented the tender flower from receiving any injury from the water, by making the petals dole, and form themſelves into a kind of arch. This plant grows on the borders of the Highland lakes, in Loch Tay, in Scotland, alſo in Wales and Ireland.</hi></p><p>SUBULATED, something ſhaped like an awl.</p><p>SUCCEDANEUM, in pharmacy, denotes a drug ſubſtituted in the place of another.</p><p>SUCCESSION, in metaphyſics, the idea which we get by reflecting on the ideas that follow one another in our mind ; and from the ſucceſſion of ideas we get the idea of <hi rend="italic">time.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> n⁰ 93. and 209.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Succession,</hi> in law. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Descent.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Succession</hi><hi rend="italic"> to the Crown.</hi> See <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Hereditary</hi><hi rend="italic"> Right.— </hi>From the days of Egbert, the firſt ſole monarch of England, even to the preſent, the four cardinal maxims mentioned in that article have ever been held conſtitutional canons of ſucceſſion. It is true, as Sir William Blackſtone obſerves, this ſucceſſion, through fraud or force, or ſometimes through neceſſity, when in hoſtile times the crown deſcended on a minor or the like, has been very frequently ſuſpended ; but has generally at laſt returned back into the old hereditary channel, though ſometimes a very conſiderable period has intervened. And even in thoſe inſtances where this ſucceſſion has been violated, the crown has ever been looked upon as hereditary in the wearer of it. Of which the usurpers themſelves were ſo ſenſible, that they for the moſt part endeavoured to vamp up ſome feeble ſhow of a title by deſcent, in order to amuſe the people, while they gained the poſſeſſion of the kingdom. And, when poſſeſſion was once gained, they conſidered it as the purchaſe or acquiſition of a new eſtate of inheritance, and tranſmitted, or endeavoured to tranſmit it, to their own poſterity by a kind of hereditary right of uſurpation. (See <hi rend="italic">Black. Com. ν.</hi> i. 197—217.) From the hiſtorical view there given, it appears, that the title to the crown is at preſent hereditary, though not quite ſo abſolutely hereditary as formerly : and the common ſtock, or anceſtor, from whom the deſcent muſt be derived, is alſo different. Formerly, the common ſtock was King Egbert ; then William the Conqueror; afterwards, in James I.’s time, the two common ſtocks united ; and ſo continued till the vacancy of the throne in 1688 : now it is the Princeſs Sophia, in whom the inheritance was veſted by the new king and parliament. Formerly, the deſcent was abſolute, and the crown went to the next heir without any reſtriction : but now, upon the new ſettlement, the inheritance is conditional ; being limited to ſuch heirs only, of the body of the Princeſs Sophia, as are Proteſtant members of the church of England, and are married to none but Proteſtants.</p><p>And in this due medium conſiſts the true conſtitutional notion of the right of ſucceſſion to the imperial crown of theſe kingdoms. The extremes between which it ſteers are each of them equally deſtructive of thoſe ends for which ſocieties were formed and are kept on foot. Where the magistrate, upon every ſucceſſion, is elected by the people, and</p></body></text></TEI>