<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>from the knowledge of the whole neighbourhood. The calculation therefore reſpecting
                Kent we may receive as true, while we must increaſe the average number in London
                very conſiderably. Mr Moore computes the average number of suicides in England every
                year at a thousand ; but the principles on which he founds this opinion are ſo
                imperfect and vague, that we do not think it can be depended on as coming near the
                truth.</p>
            <p>It might lead to ſome intereſting concluſions to compare together, not only the
                number of suicides in different countries, but also the rank and principles, the ſex
                and age, of thoſe unhappy persons by whom it has been committed. Mercier ſays, that
                at Paris it was the lower ranks who were moſt commonly guilty of it ; that it was
                moſtly committed in garrets or hired lodgings ; and that it proceeded from poverty
                and oppreſſion. A great many, he says, wrote letters to the magiſtrates bcfore their
                death. Mr Moore’s correſpondent from Geneva informed him, that from the year 1777 to
                1787 more than 100 suicides were committed in Geneva@@; that two thirds of theſe
                unfortunate persons were men ; that few of the clerical order have been known to
                commit it ; and that it is not ſo much the end of an immoral, irreligious,
                diſſipated life, as the effect of melancholy and poverty. By the information
                obtained from the coroners of Kent, it appears, that of the 32, three-fourths have
                deſtroyed themſelves by hanging ; that the proportion of males to females has been
                about two-thirds of the former ; that no one ſeason of the year is more
                diſtinguished tor this crime than another ; and that suicide is upon the increaſe.
                Our accounts reſpecting the city of London are very imperfect ; but we think
                ourſelves intitled to conclude, that suicide is more common among the great and
                wealthy than among the lower ranks, and that it is uſually the effect of gaming and
                diſſipation.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who have inquired into the cauſes of suicide in Britain have enumerated many
                phyſical as well as moral cauſes. They have aſcribed it to the variableneſs of our
                climate, to the great uſe of animal food, to ſtrong ſpirituous liquors, to tea, and
                to the ſulphureous exhalations of the pit-coal uſed as fuel, which are ſaid to
                produce a depreſſion of ſpirits and nervous affections. Of our climate, we have no
                cauſe to complain, nor have we any reaſon to impute any of our vices to its
                influence. There are many climates much more unfavourable where suicide is ſcarcely
                known. That an exceſſive quantity of groſs animal food, or of ſtrong liquors, or of
                tea, will powerfully affect the human conſtitution, we will not deny : but before we
                conſider theſe as cauſes, it muſt firſt be determined, whether thoſe who are guilty
                of self-murder be much addicted to them ; and if they are, whether there be not
                other cauſes much more violent in their nature which have operated on their mind ;
                for we ought not raſhly to attribute vicious effects to any of thoſe things which
                ſeem to have been created on purpoſe for the comfort or convenience of man. We are
                rather ſurpriſed to find that coal is mentioned even as a diſtant cauſe of ſuicide ;
                for it is one of the bleſſings of our iſland : and a good coal fire we have always
                found rather conducive to good ſpirits than injurious to them.</p>
            <p>Among the moral cauſes which are ſuppoſed to co operate in producing ſuicide in
                Britain, the freedom of our conſtitution and laws is reckoned one. That rational
                liberty ſhould have any tendency to encourage crimes of any kind, a Chriſtian
                philosopher can never allow ; for ſuch an opinion is totally diſcountenanced by
                enlightened views of nature. Mercier has aſeribed the frequency of ſuicide in Paris
                to the oppreſſion of the late government. Now it appears ſomewhat extraordinary,
                that suicide in one country ſhould be occaſioned by liberty, and in another by the
                want oſ it. One of theſe opinions muſt be falſe, and it is ſurely not difficult to
                diſtinguiſh which.</p>
            <p>Humanity would in moſt caſes diſpoſe us to to conclude, that ſuicide is the effect of
                inſanity, were there not ſo many inſtances of cool deliberate ſelf-murder. That
                ſuicide is an unnatural crime, which none but a madman would commit, compaſſion
                indeed may ſuppoſe : but the murder of a wife, a father, or a child, are also
                unnatural ; yet compaſſion does not teach us in all caſes to aſcribe ſuch a crime to
                madneſs. Paſſion may often ariſe to ſuch a height of outrage as to be ſcarcely
                diſtnguiſhable from madneſs in its ſymptoms and its effects; yet we always make a
                diſtinction between that madneſs which ariſes from diseaſe and that which is owing
                to a violent perturbation of mind. If a person be capable of managing his wordly
                affairs, of making a will, and of diſpoſing of his property, immediately before his
                death, or after he formed the resolution of dying by his own hands, ſuch a man is
                not to be conſidered as inſane.</p>
            <p>But though a regard for truth prevents us from aſcribing ſuicide in all caſes to
                inſanity, we muſt aſcribe it either to inſanity or to vicious passion. Theſe two
                diviſions, we imagine, will comprehend every ſpecies of it, whether ariſing from
                melancholy, <hi rend="italic">tædium vitae</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ennui,</hi>
                diſappointment in schemes of ambition or love, pride, gaming, or a deſire to avoid
                the ſhame of a public execution ; paſſions which are often increaſed by falſe views
                of God, of man, and of a future ſtate, arising from deiſm and infidelity. If theſe
                be the cauſes of ſuicide in modern time, what a disgraceful contrail do they form to
                thoſe principles which actuated many of the ancient philoſophers,the Gentoos,the
                Japaneſe, and the worshippers of Odin ? When they committed ſuicide, they committed
                it from principle, from a belief of its lawfulneſs, and the hope of being rewarded
                for what they judged an honourable ſacrifice. But in modern times, we are sorry to
                ſay, when it is not the effect of madneſs, it is the effect of vice : and when it is
                the effect of vice, it proves that the vicious paſſions are then indulged to the
                higheſt degree ; for there is no crime which a man can commit that is ſo ſtrong a
                ſympton of the violence of particular paſſions. It is from not attending to this
                circumſtance, that it has been found ſo difficult to refute the arguments in favour
                of ſuicide. If the criminality of ſuicide be confined merely to the violent action,
                many apologies may be made for it ; but if it be conſidered solely as the effect of
                vice, as the ſtrongeſt ſymptom of ungoverned paſſion, he who undertakes its defence
                muſt undertake the defence of what all men will loudly condemn @@<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p>
            <p>It is unneceſſary then to enter particularly into the argu-</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Moore's Full Inquiry into the Causes of Suicide. </p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> Several of the heathens entertained a very juſt
                ſenſe of the atrocity of ſuicide. Quintus Curtins introduces Darius with the
                following ſpeech, when he had loſt his empire : “ I wait (ſays the unfortunate
                monarch) the iſſue of my fate : you wonder, perhaps, that I do not terminate my own
                life ; but I chooſe rather to die by the crime of another than by my own.</p>
            <p>We cannot refuſe ourſelves the pleaſure oſ preſenting to our readers the following
                beautiful paſſage upon this ſubject from Fitzoſborne’s letters:<note
                anchored="true" type="authorial" place="margin">Letter lv.</note> “ I am
                perſuaded (ſays this elegant writer) this diſguſt of life is frequently indulged out
                of a principle of mere vanity. It is eſteemed as a mark of uncommon refinement, and
                as placing a man above the ordinary <pb n="66"/>level of his ſpecies, to ſeem
                ſuperior to the vulgar feelings of happineſs. True good ſenſe, however, moſt
                certainly consists not in deſpiſing, but in managing our stock of life to the best
                advantage, as a cheerful acquieſcence in the measures of Providence is one of the
                strongeſt ſymptoms of a well constituted mind. Self-wearineſs is a circumſtance that
                ever attends folly ; and to condemn our being is the greateſt, and indeed the
                peculiar infirmity, of human nature. It is a noble ſentiment which Tully puts into
                the mouth of Cato, in his Treatiſe upon old Age ; <hi rend="italic">Non lubet
                    mihi.</hi> (ſays that venerable Roman ) <hi rend="italic">deplorare vitam, quod
                    multi, et ii docti, Sœpe Jecerunt ; neque me vixisse paenitet : quoniam ita
                    vixi, ut non frustra me natum exstimem.</hi></p>
            <p>“ It is in the power, indeed, of but a very ſmall portion of mankind to act the ſame
                glorious part that afforded ſuch high ſatisfaction to this diſtinguiſhed patriot ;
                but the number is yet far more inconſiderable of thoſe who cannot, in any station,
                ſecure themſelves a ſufficient fund of complacency to render life juſtly valuable.
                Who is it that is placed out ot the reach of the highest of all gratifications,
                thoſe of the generous affections, and that cannot provide for his own happineſs, by
                contributing ſomething to the welfare of others? As this diſease of the mind
                generally breaks out with moſt violence in thoſe who are ſuppoſed to be endowed with
                a greater delicacy of taste and reaſon than is the uſual allotment of their
                fellow-creatures, one may ask them, whether there is any ſatiety in the purſuits of
                uſeful knowledge ? or, if one can ever be weary of benefiting mankind ? Will not the
                fine arts ſupply a laſting feaſt to the mind ? or, can there be wanting a
                pleaſurable enjoyment, ſo long as there remains even one advantageous truth to be
                diſcovered or confirmed ? To complain that life has no joys, while there is a single
                creature whom we can relieve by our bounty, aſſist by our counsels, or enliven by
                our preſence is, to lament the lots of that which we poſſeſs, and is just as
                rational as to die for thirſt with the cup in our hands. But the misfortune is, when
                a man is ſettled into a habit of receiving all his pleaſures from the mere selfiſh
                indulgences, he wears out of his mind the reliſh of every nobler enjoyment, at the
                ſame time that his powers of the ſenſual kind are growing more languid by each
                repetition. It is no wonder, therefore, he ſhould fill up the meaſure of his
                gratifications long before he has completed the circle of his duration ; and either
                wretchedly sit down the remainder of his days in diſcontent, or raſhly throw them up
                in deſpair.”</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
