<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cur to a greater or lesser degree ; on ſome occaſions, a locked jaw and other convulſive affections ſupervene ; and all theſe ſymptoms continuing to increaſe, it moſt frequently happens that the torture under which the patient has been groaning is at laſt terminated by death.</p><p>Different opinions have prevailed reſpecting the cauſe of theſe ſymptoms. By ſome they have been imputed to wounds of the tendons. By others the tendons are ſuppoſed to be ſo entirely deſtitute of ſenſibility, as to be quite incapable of producing ſo much diſtreſs ; ſo that wounds of the nerves they conſider, on all ſuch occaſions, as the true cauſe of the various ſymptoms we have mentioned.</p><p>One or other oſ theſe ideas continued to be the only ſource for explaining the various phenomena found to occur in this malady, till a different opinion was ſuggeſted by the late ingenious Mr John Hunter of London. Mr Hunter ſuppoſes, that all the dreadful ſymptoms found now and then to be induced by the operation of blood-letting, may be more readily accounted for from an inflamed ſtate of the internal ſurface of the vein, than from any other cauſe. Such a ſtate of the vein he has often traced in horſes that have died of ſuch ſymptoms from veneſection, and the ſame appearances have ſometimes occurred alſo in the human body. And on other occaſions, inflammation having in this manner been once excited, has been known to terminate in ſuppuration ; and the matter thus produced being in the courſe of circulation carried to the heart, Mr Hunter ſuppoſes that in ſuch caſes death may have been induced by that cauſe alone.</p><p>There can be no reaſon to doubt the fact held forth by Mr Hunter, that in ſuch inſtances the vein in which the orifice has been made has frequently after death been found greatly inflamed : but however ingenious his arguments may be for concluding that the ſtate of the vein is the original cauſe of all the bad ſymptoms enumerated, and although we muſt allow that ſuch an inflammatory affection of a vein muſt have a conſiderable influence in aggravating the various ſymptoms previouſly induced by other cauſes ; yet we may very fairly conclude, that it could not probably in any one inſtance be able to account with ſatisfaction for their firſt production.</p><p>In many inſtances the patient, at the very inſtant of the operation, feels a very unuſual degree of pain. In ſome caſes, the violence of the pain is almoſt unſupportable. Now this we can never ſuppoſe to have been produced by the mere puncture of a vein; for although the coats of veins are not perhaps entirely deſtitute of feeling, yet we know well that they are not endowed with ſuch a degree of ſenſibility as to render it probable ſuch intenſe pain could ever be induced by their being punctured in any way whatever. This inflamed ſtate of the veins therefore, as detected by Mr Hunter after death, muſt be conſidered rather as being produced by, than as being productive of, ſuch affections; and that ſuch ailments ſhould frequently produce an inflammation of the contiguous veins, is a very probable conjecture. In the courſe of 48 hours or ſo from the operation, when the febrile ſymptoms are juſt commencing, ſuch a degree of hardneſs and evident inflammation is induced over all the parts contiguous to the orifice, that it would be ſurpriſing indeed if the vein, which is thus perhaps entirely ſurrounded with parts highly inflamed, ſhould eſcape altogether. We ſhall therefore proceed upon the ſuppoſition of this inflamed ſtate of the veins being a conſequence rather than the cauſe of ſuch ailments ; and of courſe we now revert to one or other of the opinions long ago adopted on this ſubject, that all the train of bad ſymptoms found on ſome occaſions to Succeed veneſection, proceeds either from the wound of a nerve or of a tendon.</p><p>That a partial wound of a nerve will now and then produce very diſtreſſing ſymptoms, no practitioner will deny : but it has been attempted to be ſhown, that tendons are almoſt totally deſtitute of ſenſibility ; and it has therefore been ſuppoſed, that their being wounded can never account for the various ſymptoms known to occur in ſuch caſes. There is great reaſon however to think, that in different inſtances the ſame train of ſymptoms have been induced by different cauſes ; that in one inſtance a wounded nerve, and in others pricks of the tendons, have given riſe to them, as we have already ſuppoſed.</p><p>In order to prevent as much as poſſible the conſequent inflammation and other ſymptoms which usually enſue, a conſiderable quantity of blood ſhould be immediately diſcharged at the orifice juſt made : the limb, for ſeveral days at leaſt, ought to be kept in a ſtate of perfect reſt, care being at the ſame time taken to keep the muſeles of the part in as relaxed a ſtate as poſſible : the patient ſhould be kept cool ; on a low diet ; and, if neceſſary, gentle laxatives ought to be adminiſtered.</p><p>When, notwithſtanding theſe means, the ſymptoms, inſtead of diminiſhing, rather become more violent ; if the lips of the orifice turn hard and more inflamed, if the pain becomes more conſiderable, and eſpecially if the ſwelling begins to ſpread, other remedies come then to be indicated. In this ſtate of the complaint, topical blood-letting, by means of leeches applied as near as poſſible to the lips of the wound, frequently affords much relief ; and when the pulſe is full and quick, it even becomes neceſſary to evacuate large quantities of blood by opening a vein in ſome other part. </p><p>The external applications uſually employed in this ſtate of the complaint are warm emollient fomentations and poultices. In ſimilar affections of other parts no remedies with which we are acquainted would probably be found more ſucceſsful ; but in the complaint now under conſideration, all ſuch applications, inſtead of being productive of any advantage, rather do harm. The heat of the part is here one of the moſt diſtreſſing ſymptoms ; and warm emollient applications rather tend to augment this ſource of uneaſineſs. The lips of the wound alſo are rendered still more hard, ſwelled, and of courſe more painful ; and the ſwelling of the contiguous parts is increaſed. The best external remedies are cooling aſtringents, eſpecially the ſaturnine applications. The parts chiefly affected being alternately covered over with cloths wet with a ſolution of ſaccharum ſaturni, and pledgits ſpread with Goulard’s cerate, are kept more cool and eaſy than by any other remedy hitherto uſed. The febrile ſymptoms which occur muſt at the ſame time be attended to, by keeping the patient cool, on a low diet, preſerving a lax ſtate of the bowels ; and, if neceſſary, farther quantities of blood ought to be evacuated.</p><p>On account of the violence of the pain, which is ſometimes ſo exceſſive as to deſtroy entirely the patient’s reſt, opiates ought to be freely exhibited ; and when twitchings of the tendons and other convulſive ſymptoms ſuperveae, medicines of this kind become ſtill more neceſſary. In order, however, to have a proper influence in this ſtate of the complaint, opiates ought to be given in very full doſes ; otherwiſe, inſtead of answering any good purpoſe, they conſtantly tend to aggravate the different ſymptoms, not only by increaſing the heat and reſtleſſness, but by having an evident influence in rendering the ſyſtem more ſuſceptible than it was before of the pain and other diſtreſſing effects produced upon it by the wound.</p><p>It often happens, however, either from neglecting the wound or from improper treatment, that all theſe remedies are had recourſe to without any advantage whatever : the fever, pain,</p></body></text></TEI>