<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-03-26T20:02:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ments of thoſe caſuiſts who have undertaken the deſpicable office of advocates for
                the crime of ſuicide. Their talents might ſurely have been employed more uſefully to
                the world, and more honourably to themſelves, than in pleading for a crime which, if
                it were committed by every man to whom their principles would make it lawful, would
                totally destroy ſome of the nobleſt virtues, fortitude, patience, and reſignation ;
                nay, would deſtroy ſociety itſelf, and teach us to deſpiſe the opinion that this
                world is a state of preparation for another. “ I came into life without my own
                conſent, and may I not quit it at pleaſure?” (say the advocates for ſuicide). If,
                becauſe we came into life without our own conſent, we might quit it at pleaſure, why
                may we not ſpend our life alſo as we pleaſe ? Why may we not rob and murder, and
                commit every kind of crime, if <hi rend="italic">mere inclination </hi>is to be the
                rule of action ? Thus upon the principles of ſuicide the highwayman and murderer may
                reaſon, and every man may find a ſufficient apology for any crime which he is
                tempted to commit. Or this abſurdity may be otherwiſe anſwered ; As we came into
                life without our own conſent, we must have come with the conſent of ſome other being
                ; and logic ſays, that with the conſent of that Being only can we lawfully quit
                it.</p>
            <p>It is ſufficient shortly to say, that ſuicide is contrary to the strongeſt principle
                of the human conſtitution, ſelf-preſervation ; that it is rebellion againſt God ;
                that it is cruelty to the feelings and reputation, and often takes away the
                ſubſiſtence of a wife, a child, or a father ; that it proves a want of fortitude to
                brave misfortunes ; that it delivers only from imagined to plunge into real evils.
                We may add, that almoſt every inſtance of ſuicide of which we have heard was raſh,
                imprudent, and premature, interrupted a uſeful life, or prevented a more honourable
                death. Had Cato’s pride permitted him to yield himſelf to the generality of Cæsar,
                his character and his influence might have contributed to retard the ſlavery of his
                country, which his death tended to hasten. Had Brutus and Cassius not executed the
                fatal reſolution which they had formed, of dying by their own hands in case of
                misfortune, the battle of Philippi might have had a very different iſſue. Had
                Hannibal ſurrendered himſelf to the Romans, inſtead of ſwallowing person, he would
                have gained more glory in braving their tortures than he won in the battle of Cannæ
                ; for to die innocently and heroically is the greateſt exertion of human
                fortitude.</p>
            <p>As ſuicide was deemed a crime by the moſt illuſtrious and virtuous of the Greek and
                Roman philoſophers, it was conſidered as a crime by the laws, and treated with
                ignominy. By the law of Thebes suicides were to have no honours paid to their memory
                @@*. The Athenian law ordained the hand which committed the deed to be cut off, and
                burned apart from the rest of the body. The body was not buried with the uſual
                solemnites, but was ignominiouſly thrown into ſome pit. In Cea and Maſſilia (the
                ancient <hi rend="italic">Marseilles),</hi> it was conſidered as a crime againſt the
                state ; and it was therefore neceſſary for thoſe who wiſhed to destroy themſelves to
                obtain permiſſion from the magiſtrates. @@* Plutarch acquaints us, that an
                unaccountable paſſion for suicide ſeized the Mileſian virgins ; from indulging which
                they could not be prevented by the tears and entreaties of parents and friends : but
                what perſuaſion and entreaty could not effect was accompliſhed by very different
                means. A decree was issued, “ that the body of every young woman who hanged herſelf
                ſhould be dragged naked through the ſtreets by the same rope with which she had
                committed the deed.” This wise edict put a complete flop to the extraordinary
                frenzy, and ſuicide was no longer committed by the virgins of Miletus.</p>
            <p>In the early part of the Roman hiſtory there ſeems to have been ſeldom occaſion for
                framing any laws againſt ſuicide. The only inſtance recorded occurs in the reign of
                Taiquinius Priſcus. The ſoldiers who were appointed to make drains and common
                ſewers, thinking themſelves diſgraced by ſuch ſervile offices, put themſelves to
                death in great numbers. The king ordered the bodies of all the ſelf-murderers to be
                expoſed on croſſes, and this put an effectual ſtop to the practice. It is doubtful
                whether there was any ſtanding law againſt ſuicide during the exiſtence of the
                republic ; but during the reign of the emperors it was thought proper to lay it
                under certain regulations, though not abſolutely to condemn it as a crime.@@ In
                Juſtinian’s Digeſts there is a law, by which it was enacted, “ that if persons
                accuſed, or who had been found guilty, of any crime ſhould make away with
                themſelves, their effects ſhould be</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Petite Comment. in Leges Atticas, p. 523.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Plutarch on the Virtues of Women. </p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Lib. xlviii. Tit. xxi. par. 3.</p>
          
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
