<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196348_0210.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0204-08"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SWALLOW</label>, in natural hiſtory, is classed under the genus of <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Hirundo,</hi> under which article the different ſpecies
                    have been already deſcribed. Concerning this bird, one curious queſtion,
                    however, ſtill remains to be diſcussed, What becomes of it in the winter ? Upon
                    this ſubject there are three opinions. Some ſay that it migrates to a warmer
                        cli-<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0211.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0205"/> mate
                    ; some, that it retiree to hollow trees and caverns, where it lies in a torpid
                    ſtate ; and others have affirmed, that it lies in the ſame ſtate in the bottom
                    of lakes and under the ice. The firſt opinion is ſupported by Marſigh, Ray,
                    Willoughby, Cateſhy, Reaumur, Adanſon, Buffon, <hi rend="italic">8c.</hi> The
                    firſt and ſecond opinion are both adopted by Pennant and White. The third is
                    ſanctioned by Schaeffer, Hevelius, Derham, Klein, Ellis, Linnæus, Kalm : and the
                    ſecond and third have been ſtrongly defended by the honourable Daines
                    Barrington.</p>
                <p>Though we cannot help giving a preference to that opinion which appears the moſt
                    probable, yet we do not think that any one of them is eſtabliſhed upon ſuch
                    evidence as ſo curious a ſubject requires, and as the advanced ſtate of natural
                    history would lead us to expect. We ſhall therefore ſtate the arguments upon
                    which each opinion is founded as fairly and diſtinctly as we can, and as often
                    as poſſible in the very words of their reſpective advocates. By doing ſo, we
                    ſhall place the whole ſubject before the eyes of our readers, who will thus have
                    an opportunity of examining it attentively, and of making ſuch obſervations and
                    experiments as may lead to the truth.</p>
                <p>Thoſe who assert that the ſwallow migrates to a warmer country in winter, argue
                    in this manner : That many birds migrate, is a fact fully proved by the
                    obſervations of natural hiſtorians (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Migration). Is</hi>
                    it not more probable, therefore, that ſwallows, which diſappear regularly every
                    ſeaſon, retire to ſome other country, than that they lie in a ſtate of torpor in
                    caverns or lakes ? But this opinion does not rest on probability, it is founded
                    on facts.</p>
                <p>We often ſee them collected in great flocks on churches, rocks, and trees, about
                    the time when they annually diſappear. The direction of their flight has been
                    obſerved to be Southward. Mr White, the ingenious hiſtorian of Selborne,
                    travelling near the coaſt of the Britiſh Channel one morning early, ſaw a flock
                    of ſwallows take their departure. At the beginning of his journey he was
                    environed with a thick fog; but on a large wild heath the mill began to break,
                    and diſcovered to him numberleſs ſwallows, cluſtered on the ſtanding buſhes, as
                    if they had rooſted there : as ſoon as the ſun burſt out, they were inſtantly on
                    wing, and with an eaſy and placid flight proceeded towards the ſea. After this
                    he ſaw no more flocks, only now and then a ſtraggler.</p>
                <p>Mr Laſkey of Exeter obſerved attentively the direction which a flock of ſwallows
                    took in the autumn of 1793. On the 22d of Sept. about ſeven o’clock in the
                    morning, the wind being eaſterly, accompanied with a cold drizzling rain, Mr
                    Laſkey’s houſe was entirely covered with houſe-ſwallows. At intervals large
                    flocks arrived and joined the main body, and at their arrival an unuſual
                    chirping commenced. The appearance of the whole company was ſo lethargic, that
                    he found it an eaſy matter to catch a conſiderable number of them, which he kept
                    in a room all that day. By heating the room they all revived : he opened four of
                    them, and found their ſtomachs quite full. The main body occupied the houſe top
                    all day, except for two hours. About half an hour after nine on the morning of
                    the 23d, there was a great commotion, with very loud chirping, and within a few
                    minutes after, the whole multitude took their flight, in a direct ſouth-eaſt
                    direction, having aſcended to a great height in the atmoſphere. He let go the
                    birds which he had caught, at certain intervals till four o’clock, and they all
                    flew toward the ſame quarter.</p>
                <p>Not only has the direction of their flight been obſerved, but they have alſo been
                    found on their passage at a great diſtance from land. Mr Adanſon informs us,
                    that</p>
                <p>about 50 leagues from the coaſt of Senegal four swallows ſettled upon the ſhip on
                    the 6th of October; that theſe birds were taken ; and that he knew them to be
                    European ſwallows, which, he conjectures, were returning to the coaſt of Africa.
                    Sir Charles Wager’s authority may alſo be appealed to : “ Returning home (ſays
                    he) in the ſpring of the year, as I came into foundings in our channel, a great
                    flock of ſwallows came and ſettled on all my rigging ; every rope was covered,
                    they hung on one another like a ſwarm of bees ; the decks and carving were
                    filled with them. They ſeemed almost famiſhed and ſpent, and were only feathers
                    and bones ; but, being recruited with a night’s reſt, took their flight in the
                    morning.” This vaſt fatigue proves that their journey muſt have been very great,
                    conſidering the amazing ſwiftneſs of theſe birds : in all probability they had
                    crossed the Atlantic ocean, and were returning from the ſhores of Senegal, or
                    other parts of Africa; ſo that this account from that moſt able and honeſt
                    seaman, confirms the later information of Mr Adanson.</p>
                <p>Mr Kalm, who is an advocate for the opinion that ſwallows lie immerſed in lakes
                    during the winter, acknowledges, that in croſſing the Atlantic from Europe a
                    ſwallow lighted on the ſhip on the 2d September, when it had passed only
                    two-thirds of the ocean. Since, therefore, ſwallows have been ſeen assembled in
                    great flocks in autumn flying off in company towards southern climes, ſince they
                    have been found both in their paſſage from Europe and returning again, can there
                    be any doubt of their annual migration ? —For Mr Barrington’s objections to this
                    opinion, ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Migration,</hi> p. 5.</p>
                <p>The ſecond notion (ſays Mr Pennant) has great antiquity on its side. Ariſtotle
                    and Pliny give it as their belief, that ſwallows do not remove very far from
                    their summer habitation, but winter in the hollows of rocks, and during that
                    time lose their feathers. The former part of their opinion has been adopted by
                    ſeveral ingenious men ; and of late ſeveral proofs have been brought of ſome
                    ſpecies, at leaſt, having been diſcovered in a torpid ſtate. Mr Collinson
                    favoured us with the evidence of three gentlemen, eye-witnesses to numbers of
                    land martins being drawn out of a cliff on the Rhine, in the month of March
                    1762. And the honourable Daines Barrington communicated to us the following
                    fact, on the authority of the late Lord Belhaven, That numbers of ſwallows have
                    been found in old dry walls and in ſand- hills near his Lordship’s ſeat in Eaſt
                    Lothian ; Trot once only, but from year to year ; and that when they were
                    exposed to the warmth of a fire, they revived. We have alſo heard of the ſame
                    annual diſcoveries near Morpeth in Northumberland, but cannot ſpeak of them with
                    the ſame assurance as the two former : neither in the two laſt inſtances are we
                    certain of the particular ſpecies.</p>
                <p>“Other witnesses crowd on us to prove the reſidence of thoſe birds in a torpid
                    ſtate during the ſevere ſeaſon. Firſt, In the chalky cliffs of Suffex ; as was
                    ſeen on the fall of a great fragment some years ago secondly, In a decayed
                    hollow tree that was cut down, near Dolgelli, in Merionethshire. Thirdly, In a
                    cliff near Whitby, Yorkſhire ; where, on digging out a fox, whole bushels of
                    ſwallows were found in a torpid condition. And, laſtly, The reverend Mr Conway
                    of Sychton, Flintſhire, was ſo obliging as to communicate the following fact : A
                    few years ago, on looking down an old lead-mine in that county, he obſerved
                    numbers of ſwallows clinging to the timbers of the ſhaft, ſeemingly asleep ; and
                    on flinging ſome gravel on them, they just moved, but never attempted to fly or
                    change their place : this was between All Saints and Chriſtmas.<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196348_0212.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0206"/> “ Theſe are
                    doubtleſs the lurking places of the later hatches, or of thoſe young birds which
                    are incapable of diſtant migrations. There they continue inſenſible and rigid;
                    but like flies may ſometimes be reanimated by an unſeaſonable hot day in the
                    midſt of winter : for very near Christmas a ſew appeared on the moulding of a
                    window of Merton college, Oxford, in a remarkably warm nook, which prematurely
                    ſet their blood in motion, having the ſame effect as laying them before a fire
                    at the ſame time of year. Others have been known to make this premature
                    appearance ; but as ſoon as the cold natural to the ſeaſon returns, they
                    withdraw again to their former retreats.</p>
                <p>“ The above are circumſtances we cannot but assent to, though seemingly
                    contradictory to the common courſe of nature in regard to other birds. We muſt,
                    therefore, divide our belief relating to theſe two ſo different opinions ; and
                    conclude, that one part of the ſwallow tribe migrate, and that others have their
                    winter-quartets near home. If it should be demanded, why ſwallows alone are
                    found in a torpid ſtate, and not the other many ſpecies oſ ſoft billed birds,
                    which likewiſe disappear about the ſame time ? reaſons might be aſſigned :”</p>
                <p>The third opinion we ſhall ſtate and ſupport in the words of Mr Kalm. “ Natural
                    hiſtory (ſays he), as all other histories, depends not always upon the intrinsic
                    degree of probability, but upon facts founded on the teſtimony of people of
                    noted veracity.— Swallows are ſeldom ſeen sinking down into the water ; ſwallows
                    have not such organs as frogs or lizards, which are torpid during winter ; <hi
                        rend="italic">ergo,</hi> ſwallows live not, and cannot live, under
                    water.—This way of arguing, I believe, would carry us, in a great many caſes,
                    too far : for though it is not clear to every one, it may however be true ; and
                    lizards and frogs are animals of a claſs widely different from that of birds,
                    and muſt therefore of courſe have a different ſtructute ; hence it is they are
                    classed ſeparately. The bear and the marmot are in winter in a torpid ſtate, and
                    have, however, not ſuch organs as lizards and frogs ; and nobody doubts of their
                    being, during ſome time, in the moſt rigid climates, in a torpid ſtate : for the
                    Alpine nations hunt the marmots frequently by digging their holes up ; and find
                    them ſo torpid, that they cut their throats, without their reviving or giving
                    the least ſign of life during the operation ; but when the torpid marmot is
                    brought into a warm room, and placed before the fire, it revives from its
                    lethargy. The queſtion muſt therefore be decided by facts ; nor are theſe
                    wanting here. Dr Wallerius, the celebrated Swediſh chemiſt, informs us, That he
                    has ſeen, more than once, ſwallows aſſembling on a reed, till they were all
                    immerſed and went to the bottom ; this being preceded by a dirge of a quarter of
                    an hour’s length. He atteſts likewiſe, that he had ſeen a ſwallow caught during
                    winter out of a lake with a net, drawn, as is common in northern countries,
                    under the ice ; this bird was brought into a warm room, revived, fluttered
                    about, and ſoon after died.</p>
                <p>“ Mr Klein applied to many farmers-general of the king of Pruſſia’s domains, who
                    had great lakes in their diſtricts, the fiſhery in them being a part of the
                    revenue. In winter the fiſhery thereon is the moſt conſiderable under the ice,
                    with nets ſpreading more than 200 or 300 fathoms, and they are often wound by
                    ſcrews and engines on account of their weight. All the people that were
                    queſtioned made affidavits upon oath before the magiſtrates. Firſt, The mother
                    of the counteſs Lehndorf laid, that ſhe had ſeen a bundle of ſwallows brought
                    from the Friſhe-Haff (a lake communicating with the Baltic at Pillaw), which,
                    when brought into a moderately warm room, revived and fluttered about. Secondly,
                    Count Schileben gave an inſtrument on ſtamped paper, importing, that by fiſhing
                    on the lake belonging to his eſtate of Gerdauen in winter, he ſaw ſeveral
                    ſwallows caught in the net, one of which he took up in his hand, brought it into
                    a warm room, where it lay about an hour, when it began to ſtir, and half an hour
                    after, it flew about in the room. Thirdly, Farmer general (Amtman) Witkouſki
                    made affidavit, that, in the year 1740, three ſwallows were brought up with the
                    net in the great pond at Didlacken ; in the year 1741 he got two ſwallows from
                    another part of the pond, and took them home (they being all caught in his
                    preſence) ; after an hour’s ſpace they revived all in a warm room, fluttered
                    about, and died in three hours after. Fourthly, Amtman Bonke ſays, that having
                    had the eſtate of Kleſkow in farm, he had ſeen nine ſwallows brought up in the
                    net from under the ice, all which he took into a warm room, where ſhe diſtinctly
                    obſerved how they gradually revived ; but a few horns after they all died.
                    Another time his people got likewiſe ſome ſwallows in a net, but he ordered them
                    to be again thrown into the water. Fifthly, Andrew Rutta, a maſter fiſherman at
                    Oletſko, made affidavit, in 1747, that 22 years ago, two ſwallows were taken up
                    by him in a net, under the ice, and, being brought into a warm room, they flew
                    about. Sixthly, Jacob Kosiulo, a maſter fiſherman at Stradauen, made affidavit,
                    that, in 1736, he brought up in winter, in a net, from under the ice of the lake
                    at Raski, a ſeemingly dead ſwallow, which revived in half an hour’s time in a
                    warm room ; and he ſaw, in a quarter of an hour after, the bird grow weaker, and
                    ſoon after dying. Seventhly, I can reckon myſelf (ſays our author) among the
                    eye-witneſſes of this paradox of natural hiſtory. In the year 1735, being a
                    little boy, I ſaw ſeveral ſwallows brought in winter by the fiſhermen from the
                    river Viſtula to my father’s houſe ; where two of them were brought into a warm
                    room, revived, and flew about. I ſaw them ſeveral times settling on the warm
                    ſtove (which the northern nations have in their rooms) ; and I recollect well,
                    that the lame forenoon they died, and I had them, when dead, in my hand. In the
                    year 1754, after the death of my uncle Godefroy Wolf, captain in the Polish
                    regiment of foot-guards, being myſelf one of his heirs, I adminiſtered for my co
                    heirs ſeveral eſtates called the <hi rend="italic">Starosty of Dischau,</hi> in
                    Poliſh Prussia, which my late uncle farmed under the king. In January, the lake
                    of Lybſhaw, belonging to theſe eſtates, being covered with ice, I ordered the
                    fiſhermen to fiſh therein, and in my preſence ſeveral ſwallows were taken, which
                    the fishermen threw in again ; but one I took up to myſelf, brought it home,
                    which was five miles from thence, and it revived, but died about an hour after
                    its reviving.</p>
                <p>“ Theſe are facts atteſted by people of the higheſt quality, by ſome in public
                    offices, and by others who, though of a low rank, however, made theſe affidavits
                    upon oath. It is impoſſible to ſuppoſe indiſcriminately that they were prompted,
                    by views of intereſt, to aſſert as a fact a thing which had no truth in it. It
                    is therefore highly probable, or rather inconteſtably true, that ſwallows retire
                    in the northern countries, during winter, into the water, and stay there in a
                    torpid ſtate till the return of warmth revives them again in ſpring. The
                    queſtion therefore, I believe, ought for the future to be thus ſtated : The
                    ſwallows in Spain, Italy, France, and perhaps ſome from England, remove to
                    warmer climates ; ſome Engliſh ones, and ſome in Germany and other mild
                    countries, retire into clefts and holes in rocks, and remain there in a torpid
                    ſtate. In the colder northern countries the ſwallows immerſe in the ſea, in
                    lakes, and rivers ; and remain in a torpid ſtate, under ice, during winter.
                    There are ſtill ſome objections to this latter<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196348_0213.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0207"/> assertion,
                    which we muſt remove. It is ſaid, Why do not rapacious fiſh, and aquatic
                    quadrupeds and birds, devour theſe ſwallows ? The anſwer is obvious, ſwallows
                    chooſe only ſuch places in the water for their winter retreat as are near reeds
                    and ruſhes; ſo that sinking down there between them and their roots, they are by
                    them ſecured againſt the rapaciouſneſs of their enemies. But others object, Why
                    are not theſe birds caught in ſuch freſh waters as are continually haraſſed by
                    nets ? I believe the ſame anſwer which has been made to the firſt objection will
                    ſerve for this likewise. Fiſhermen take care to keep off with their nets from
                    places filled with reeds and ruſhes, for fear of entangling and tearing their
                    net ; and thus the ſituation of ſwallows under water, is the reaſon that they
                    are ſeldom diſturbed in their silent winter retreats. What confirms this opinion
                    ſtill more is, that ſwallows were never caught in Pruſſia according to the
                    above-mentioned affidavits, but with thoſe parts of the net which passed near to
                    the reeds and ruſhes ; and ſometimes the ſwallows were yet faſtened with their
                    feet to a reed, when they were drawn up by the net. As to the argument taken
                    from their being to long under water without corruption, I believe there is a
                    real difference between animals ſuffocated in water and animals being torpid
                    therein. We have examples of things being a long time under water ; to which we
                    may add the intenſe cold of these northern regions, which preſerves them. Who
                    would have thought that ſnails and polypes might be dissected, and could
                    reproduce the parts ſevered from their bodies, if it was not a fact ? Natural
                    hiſtory ought to be ſtudied as a collection of facts, not as the hiſtory of our
                    guesses or opinions. Nature varies in an infinite manner ; and Providence has
                    diverſified the inſtinct of animals and their economy, and adapted it to the
                    various ſeaſons and climates.”</p>
                <p>With Mr Kahn’s concluding obſervations we heartily concur. Natural hiſtory ought
                    to be ſtudied as a collection of facts ; and it was from this very notion that
                    we have ſtated the above mentioned opinions ſo fully, and brought together the
                    tacts which the best advocates for each opinion have judged moſt proper for
                    ſupporting them. We are ſenſible of the great improbability of the third
                    opinion, and know that many arguments have been uſed to prove its abſurdity :
                    ſuch as theſe, The ſwallow is lighter than water, and therefore cannot sink ; if
                    it moults at all, it muſt moult under water during its torpid ſtate, which is
                    very improbable ; there is no inſtance of land animals living ſo long under
                    water without reſpiration. Many other arguments of the ſame sort have been
                    advanced, and certainly afford a ſhort way of deciding the queſtion ; but unleſs
                    they were sufficient to prove the immerſion of ſwallows a phyſical
                    impoſſibility, they are of no force when oppoſed to the evidence oſ testimony,
                    it there be no cauſe to ſuspect the witneſſes of inaccuracy or design. The true
                    way to refute ſuch an opinion is by accurate obſervation and experiment. We have
                    not heard of any accurate inquiries being made by philoſophers in thoſe northern
                    countries where ſwallows are laid to pass the winter under water. The count de
                    Buffon, indeed, ſhut up ſome ſwallows in an ice-houſe by way of experiment,
                    which died in a few days ; but as he does not tell us what precautions he took
                    to make the experiment ſucceed, it is not intitled to any attention.</p>
                <p>Mr John Hunter made a very judicious experiment on the banks of the Thames, which
                    is deſcribed by a correſpondent in the Gentleman’s Magazine, who aſſerts that he
                    had it from Mr Hunter himſelf.</p>
                <p>One year in the month of September, he prepared a room, with every accommodation
                    and convenience which he could contrive, to ſerve as a dormitory for ſwallows,
                    if they were diſpoſed to ſleep in winter. He placed in the centre a large tub of
                    water with twigs and reeds, &amp;c. which reached to the bottom. In the corners
                    of the room he contrived artificial caverns and holes, into which they might
                    retire ; and he laid on the floor, or ſuſpended in the air, different lengths of
                    old wooden pipes, which had formerly been employed in conveying water through
                    the ſtreets, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>When the receptacle was rendered as complete as poſſible, he then engaged some
                    watermen to take by night a large quantity of the ſwallows that hang upon the
                    reeds in the Thames about the time of their departure. They brought him, in a
                    hamper, a conſiderable number ; and had ſo nicely hit the time of their capture,
                    that on the very day following there were none to be ſeen.</p>
                <p>He put the ſwallows into the room ſo prepared, where they continued to fly about,
                    and occaſionally perch on the twigs, &amp;c. But not one ever retired into the
                    water, the caverns, holes, or wooden pipes, or ſhewed the leaſt diſposition to
                    grow torpid, &amp;c. In this ſituation he let them remain till they all died but
                    one. This, appearing to retain ſome vigour, was ſet at liberty ; when it mounted
                    out of sight, and flew away. All the birds lay dead ſcattered about the room ;
                    but not one was found aſleep or torpid, or had, if the correſpondent remembers,
                    ſo much as crept into any of the receptacles he had ſo provided.</p>
                <p>This experiment was ingenious, and certainly does render the doctrine of
                    immerſion much more improbable ; but it is not decisive ; for it may ſtill be
                    urged by the advocates for that doctrine, as Mr Kalm has done, that it may only
                    be in the colder countries where ſwallows retire into the water. We formerly
                    ſaid that none of the three opinions are ſupported by ſuch evidence as to
                    ſatisfy the mind completely. Opinions which reſpect events which happen every
                    year ought to be confirmed by a great number of obſervations, and not by a few
                    inſtances diveſted of almoſt all their concomitant circumſtances. Can no better
                    proofs be brought to prove the migration of ſwallows than thoſe of Adanſon and
                    Sir Charles Wager, or the circumſtances mentioned by Mr White and Mr Laſkey
                    reſpecting their diſappearing ? We ought not merely to know that ſome ſwallows
                    have taken a ſoutherly flight in autumn, that ſome have been ſound at a great
                    distance from land in the ſpring, or in harveſt ; but we ought to know to what
                    countries they actually retire. Before, we can reſt ſatisfied, too, that it is a
                    general fact that swallows remain in a torpid ſtate during winter, either in
                    caverns or in the bottom of lakes, &amp;c. we muſt have more proofs ; we muſt
                    know what species of ſwallows they are laid to be, in what countries this event
                    takes place, and ſeveral other circumſtances of the same kind.</p>
                <p>We cannot help being of opinion that much remains to be done in order properly to
                    ascertain what becomes of the ſwallows in Europe during winter. It would be
                    necessary, in the firſt place, to know accurately what are the countries in
                    which ſwallows are found. 2. Do they remain visible the whole year ? or, if they
                    diſappear, at what ſeaſon does this happen, and when do they appear again ? 3.
                    Do they ever appear while a ſtrong north wind blows, or do they only come in
                    great numbers with a ſouth wind ? We will endeavour to anſwer ſome of theſe
                    queſtions in part ; but muſt regret, that all the information on this ſubject
                    which we have been able to cull from the beſt writers in natural hiſtory is very
                    ſcanty ; and we merely give it by way of ſpecimen, hoping that future
                    obſervations will ſoon render it more complete.</p>
                <p>There are five ſpecies which viſit Britain during the ſummer months ; the common
                    or chimney swallow, the martin, sand martin, ſwitt, and goat-sucker. The chimney
                    ſwallow frequents almoſt every part of the old continent ; being known (ſays Dr
                    Latham) from Norway to the Cape<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0214.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0208"/> of Good Hope on the one fide, and from
                    Karrjtſchetka to India and japan on the other. It is alſo found in all parts of
                    North America, and in ſeveralof the Weft Indian Iſlands. In Europe it diſappears
                    during the winter months. It appears generally a little after the vernal equinox
                    ; but rather earlier in the ſouthern, and later in the northern latitudes. It
                    adheres to the uſual ſeaſons with much regularity ; for though the months of
                    February and^iarch ſhould be uncommonly mild, and April and May remarkably cold,
                    it never deviates from its ordinary time. In the cold ſpring of '740 ſome
                    appeared in France before the infects on which they feed had become numerous
                    enough to iupport them, and great numbers died<note anchored="true" n="1"
                        place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Buffon's Natural
                                History of Birds,</hi> vol. vi. p. 527.</p></note>. In the mild and
                    even warm ſpring of 1 7 74 they appeared no earlier than uſual. They remain in
                    ſome warm countries the whole year. Kolben affures us that this is the cafe at
                    the Cape of Good Hope ; but (he lays) they are more numerous in winter. Some
                    birds of this ſpecies live, during winter, even in Europe ; for example, on the
                    coaſt of Genoa, where they ſpend the ni;?ht in the open country on the orange
                    ſhrubs.</p>
                <p>2. The <hi rend="italic">martins</hi> are alſo widely diffuſed through the old
                    continent ; but the countries where they reſide or viſit have not been marked by
                    naturaliſts with much attention. 3. The <hi rend="italic">sand martins</hi> are
                    found in every part of Europe, and frequently ſpend the winter in Malta<note
                        anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                                >Ibid.</hi> 527.</p></note>. Two birds of this ſpecies were ſeen in
                    Perigord in France, on the 27th December 1775, when there was a ſoutherly wind,
                    attended with a little rain<note anchored="true" n="3" place="margin"
                        type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> 484.</p></note>. 4. The <hi
                        rend="italic">ſvaiſt</hi> viſits the whole continent of Europe ; has alſo
                    been obſerved at the Cape of Good Hope, and in Carolina in North America. 5. The
                        <hi rend="italic">goat-ſuckers</hi> are not very common birds, yet are
                    widely ſcattered They are found in every country between Sweden and Africa :
                    they are found alſo in India. In April the ſouth-weſt wind brings them to Malta,
                    and in autumn they repaſs in great numbers.</p>
                <p>Mr Markwick of Catsfield, near Battle in Suffex, has drawn up an accurate table,
                    expreſſing the day of the month on which the birds, commonly called <hi
                        rend="italic">migratory,</hi> appeared in ſpring, and diſappeared in autumn,
                    for 16 years, from 1768 to 1783 incluſive.<note anchored="true" n="4"
                        place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Transactions of the
                                Linnaean Society,</hi> vol. 1.</p></note> The obſervations were made
                    at Catsſield. From this table we ſhall extract the dates for five years, and add
                    the very few obſervations which we have been able to collect reſpecting the time
                    when the ſwallow appears and diſappears in other countries.</p>
                <table cols="6">
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2">1779.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell cols="2">1781.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">First seen.</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Last seen.</hi></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">First seen.</hi></cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">Last seen.</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Chim. SwaL</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 14.</cell>
                        <cell>O&lt;fl. 29.</cell>
                        <cell>Sand Mart.</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 26.</cell>
                        <cell>Sep. I.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Martins</cell>
                        <cell>14.</cell>
                        <cell>1J∙</cell>
                        <cell>Swift</cell>
                        <cell>May 12.</cell>
                        <cell>I.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Sand Mart.</cell>
                        <cell>May 7.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1782.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Swift</cell>
                        <cell>9∙</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Chim. Swal.</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 22.</cell>
                        <cell>Sep. I.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>17 80.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Martins</cell>
                        <cell>26.</cell>
                        <cell>Nov. 2.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>China. Swal</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Nov. 3.</cell>
                        <cell>Sand Mart.</cell>
                        <cell>May 13.</cell>
                        <cell>Aug. 28.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Martins</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 29.</cell>
                        <cell>3∙</cell>
                        <cell>Swift</cell>
                        <cell>iS.</cell>
                        <cell>28.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Sand Mart.</cell>
                        <cell>8.</cell>
                        <cell>Sep. S.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1783.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Swift</cell>
                        <cell>May 6.</cell>
                        <cell>8.</cell>
                        <cell>Chim. Swal.</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 13,</cell>
                        <cell>Nov. 6.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>1781.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Martins</cell>
                        <cell>May I.</cell>
                        <cell>6.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Chim. Swal.</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 8.</cell>
                        <cell>O&lt;S. 15,</cell>
                        <cell>Sand Mart.</cell>
                        <cell>July 25.</cell>
                        <cell>Sep. I.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Mai tins</cell>
                        <cell>May 12.</cell>
                        <cell>Sep. 7.</cell>
                        <cell>Swift</cell>
                        <cell>May 13.</cell>
                        <cell>Nov. 6.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2">China. Swal.</cell>
                        <cell><p>Swifts.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Appear</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell>Martin». <hi rend="italic">about</hi></cell>
                        <cell>S. Mart.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In Burgundy<note anchored="true" n="5" place="margin" type="authorial"
                                        ><p><hi rend="italic">Buffon,</hi> Ibid.</p></note></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Ap. 9.</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 12.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In Selborne, Hampiħire<note anchored="true" n="6" place="margin"
                                type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">White's Natural History of
                                        Selborne.</hi></p></note></cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 4.</cell>
                        <cell>Λp. 24.</cell>
                        <cell>Ap. 30.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In South Zele, Devonflιire f</cell>
                        <cell>*5∙</cell>
                        <cell>May i.</cell>
                        <cell>May 15.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In Blackburn, L,ancaflιire ∣</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> S&gt;∙</cell>
                        <cell>Λp∙ 28.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>In Upſal in Sweden<note anchored="true" n="7" place="margin"
                                type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Buffon,</hi>
                            Ibid.</p></note></cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>May 9.</cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Swifts.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Appear</hi></p>
                <p>Were tables of the ſame kind made in every different country, particularly within
                    the torrid zone, it would be eaſy to determine the queſtion which we have been
                    conſi- dering. To many, perhaps, it may not appear a matter of ſuch importance
                    as to be worth the labour. We acknowledge it to be rather a curious than an
                    important inquiry ; yet it is one which muſt be highly gratifying to every mind
                    that can admire the wiſdom of the Great Architect of nature. The inſtinct of the
                    ſwallow is indeed wonderful : it appears among us juſt at the time wſhen infects
                    become numerous ; and it continues with us during the hot weather, in order to
                    prevent them ſrom multiplying too much. It diſappears when theſe infects are no
                    longer troubleſomc. It is never found in folitude ; it is the friend of man, and
                    always takes up its reſidence with us, that it may protect our houſes and our
                    ſtreets ſrom being annoyed with ſwarms of flies.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Swallow-</hi><hi rend="italic">Wort,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Asclepias.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
