<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0255.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0249-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SYLLA</label>
(Lucius Cornelius), was deſcended from the illuſtrious family of the Scipios. His behaviour in his younger years by no means correſponded with the excellent education which he had received. But debauchery, inſtead of bringing along with it infamy and ruin, its uſual attendants, ſerved only to increaſe the wealth of this fortunate Roman ; for Nocopolis, a rich courtezan, whoſe affections he had gained, left him heir to her great eſtate.—He learned. the art of war under Marius, whom he attended to Numidia in quality of queſtor. Though hitherto unaccuſtomed to arms, he became in a ſhort time the moſt ſkilful ſoldier in the army, while by his polite and obliging behaviour he gained the love and eſteem of every body. His courage and dexterity contributed a great deal towards the ſucceſs of the war ; it was his eloquence in particular that perſuaded Bocchus to deliver up Jugurtha. He ſerved afterwards in the ſocial war, where his actions entirely eclipſed thoſe of every other commander. As a reward for this conduct he was raiſed to the praetorſhip. It is pretended by ſome that Sylla purchaſed this dignity ; and that when he threatened one day to make uſe of the powers of h <hi rend="italic">is</hi> office againſt Strabo the father of Pompey, that Roman replied with a ſmile, “ You are in the right to say ſo ; your office is certainly <hi rend="italic">yours,</hi> ſince you purchaſed it.” Be this as it may, after the concluſion of the ſocial war he was made conſul, and ſoon after declared general of the army which was to be ſent againſt Mithridates king of Pontus. Marius, at that time the moſt renowned of the Roman generals, expected that the management of this war would have been committed to him, and was therefore much exaſperated at the diſappointment. The people were perſuaded by his intrigues to reverſe the former decree, and ſubſtitute him in place of Sylla. Upon this he ſent down officers to take the command of the army ; but Sylla by this time had gained over the ſoldiers ; who, inſtead of obeying the decree of the people, slew Marius’s officers, and intreated Sylla to lead them inſtantly to Rome. Accordingly he entered the city ſword in hand, flew Sulpicius the conſul, obliged Marius to flee, new-modelled the laws, and afterwards marched into the Eaſt, and immediately laid ſiege to Athens ; for that city, together with the rest of Greece, had fallen into the power of Mithridates. He wrote to the Amphyctions, who were aſſembled at Delphi, to lend him all the gold which was depoſited in the temple of Apollo, becauſe he stood in need of money ; promiſing, at the same time, to reſtore it again at the end of the war. When he received this treaſure, he obſerved, with an air of raillery, that he now no longer despaired of victory, ſince the gods themſelves furniſhed him with money to pay his troops. Famine ſoon obliged the Athenians to think of a ſurrender. Their ambassadors waited on Sylla, and began to harangue about Theſeus and Codrus, and Marathon and Salamis, —when he interrupted them, and exclaimed, “ Go, repeat theſe fine orations in your ſchools ; I have come hither, not to learn your history, but to chactiſe rebels.” Athens was at laſt taken by aſſault, and Sylla was upon the point of dest roving it, when he recollected its ancient glory, and ſpared (as he ſaid) the living for the sake of the dead. After burning the Piraeus, he gained two deciſive victories over the generals of Mithridates. In the second battle, which was fought at Orchomeniis, he was almoſt defeated ; his troops began to flee, when, leaping from his horſe, he Hatched up a standard, and advanced againſt the enemy, crying out, “ I will die here gloriouſly; and, ſoldiers, when you are aſked where you abandoned your general, anſwer, At Orchomenus.” This reproach recalled the courage of the Romans ; they followed him to the charge, and gained a complete victory. Mithridates, humbled by theſe diſaſters, ſent ambaſſadors to ſue for peace.</p><p>Mean time Cinna had declared againſt Sylla in Italy; and Marius returning from baniſhment, had taken the moſt ſevere vengeance on all his enemies. Sylla was declared a traitor ; his laws were reverſed, his friends murdered, and the government new-modelled. The news of theſe tranſactions induced Sylla to conclude a treaty with Mithridates, and match directly to Rome. His approach terrified the Romans. Marius and Cinna were both dead ; but the conſuls made vigorous preparations to oppoſe him. A civil war was begun ; but Sylla in the end subdued all his enemies, and entirely ruined the Marian faction. He entered Rome at the head of his victorious army, and publicly affirmed the ſurname of <hi rend="italic">Happy.</hi> Happy, indeed, had he ceaſed to live when he ceaſed to conquer. The remainder of his life contains nothing elſe but a catalogue of the moſt abominable cruelties. He declared that every one who expected pardon for their late offences, muſt gain it by deſtroying the enemies of the ſtate. The ſword of the aſſaſſin was thus unſheathed, and murder encouraged as the path to power and diſtinction. The nobleſt of the Romans were everywhere maſſacred ; ſlaves were rewarded for cutting off their maſters ; children were ſeen dragging their parents to execution ; and brothers claiming a recompenſe for the mur-<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0256.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0250"/>
der of brothers. Sylla ordered 8000 wretches, who had thrown themſelves upon his clemency, to be butchered in the Campus Martius. In the mean time he entered the ſenate-houſe, and began to talk with great coolneſs about his exploits. The ſenate, alarmed at the horrid outcries of the ſufferers, at firſt thought that the city was given up to be plundered; but Sylla informed them, with an unembarraſſed air, that it was only ſome criminals puniſhing by his orders, and that they needed not be apprehenſive about their own fate.</p><p>To carry on theſe cruelties with the appearance of juſtice, he commanded the people to elect him dictator. He kept this office for more than two years ; and then, to the amazement of all, laid it down, and offered to ſtand his trial before the people. Soon afterwards he retired into the country, and plunged headlong into every kind of debauchery. Nor did he relinquiſh his cruelty together with his power : His wife falling ill in the midſt of a sumptuous feaſt, he divorced her immediately ; and ordered her to be carried away, lest her death ſhould interrupt the feſtivity of his houſe.</p><p>He died of the morbus pedicularis, in the doth year of his age. His body, according to his orders, was burnt. A little before his death he wrote his epitaph ; the tenor of which was, that no man had ever exceeded him in doing good to his friends or injury to his enemies.</p><p>His perſon was elegant, his air noble, his manners easy and apparently ſincere. He was fond of pleaſure, but fonder of glory ; indulging without ſcruple in ſensual delights, but never ſuffering them to interrupt his serious buſineſs : He was eloquent, liberal, crafty, insinuating ; a profound maſter of diſſimulation ; he ſpoke of himſelf with modeſty, while he laviſhed praiſes on every other perſon : He ſtooped even to an acquaintance with the meaneſt ſoldier, and conſtantly adapted himſelf to the humours, purſuits, and opinions, of those with whom he converſed. Such was his character during the earlier part of his life ; but when succeſs had raiſed him above the neceſſity of diſſimulation, he diſobyed a hideous train of vices, which his ambition had formerly taught him to conceal.—It was Sylla who recovered the works of Ariſtotle at the taking of Athens.</p></div></body></text></TEI>