<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0197.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0191-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SURINAM</label>,
the capital of the Dutch ſettlements in Guiana, situated on a river of the ſame name, in N Lat. 6. 1 <hi rend="italic">6.</hi> W. Long. 56. 0. It gives name to the country for 100 miles round ; and ſtands on a river of the ſame name, which is navigable for 30 leagues up the country. A ſettlement was formed at Surinam in 1650 by the Dutch, who preſerved poſſeſſion of it ever ſince. The chief trade conſiſts in ſugar, cotton, coffee of an excellent kind, tobacco, flax, skins, and ſome valuable drugs for dyeing. Four hundred and thirty plantations have been already formed on the banks of the Surinam and the adjacent country, which in 1775 yielded 24,120,000 weight of rough ſugar, which were sold in Holland for 347,225 1. Serling ; 15,000,387 lb. weight of coffee, which ſold for 357,538 l. ; 970,000 lb. weight of cotton ; 790,854 lb. weight of cocoa ; 152,844 lb. weight of wood for dyeing. The ſum total of theſe productions amounted to 822,905 Sterling, and was brought into the harbours of the republic in 70 veſſels. The number of ſlaves employed in the ſame year was 60,000, who belonged to 2824 maſters, excluſive of the women and children. The white people were of different countries and different religions.</p><p>Connected with Surinam, we may mention the colonies of Demerary, Iſſequibo, and Berbice, which lie a little to the west. The two firſt ſurrendered to the Britiſh troops in 1781 ; but being left defenceleſs, were retaken by a French frigate. Demerary has lately been taken a second time by the army of Great Britain. It is conſidered as a valuable acquiſition, being a flouriſhing colony. In 1769 there were eſtabliſhed on the banks of the Demerary 130 habitations, in which ſugar, coffee, and cotton were ſucceſsfully cultivated, and ſince that period the number of plantations hath increaſed much.</p><p>Iſſequibo is a very inconſiderable ſettlement. Berbice, which lies between Demerary and Surinam, contains about 104 plantations, most of them ſmall, and ſcattered at great distances from one another upon the banks of the Berbice or of Conje. When Raynal publiſhed the laſt edition of his Hiſtory of Settlements and Trade in the Eaſt and West Indies, the population conſiſted of 7c00 ſlaves of every age and ſex, 250 white men, excluſive of the ſoldiers. The coffee, ſugar, and cotton produced was conveyed to Holland in four or five ſhips, and ſold for about 40 or 50,000 l.</p></div></body></text></TEI>