<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>both these generals were signally defeated. The cause of Don Carlos was now visibly declining: the best and bravest of the chiefs who had served him had successively incurred his displeasure, and were either in disgrace, exile, or confinement ; above all, the country was beginning to be favourably disposed to the queen. Her troops however were very unsuccessful in the field. General Orad was defeated at Morella, and General Alaix also suffered a repulse. But the principal battle fought between the Carlists and Christinos was that of Maella, where General Cabrera completely routed the queen’s troops under Pordinas, but sullied his victory by butchering nearly two hundred prisoners in cold blood. The war throughout had been disgraced by similar atrocities, notwithstanding the efforts of Britain to put a stop to them. Both parties appear to have been equally guilty of this inhuman practice. The operations of Eεpar tero were feeble and uncertain. He did little but march a large army from place to place, without striking a decisive blow. As usual, almost every part of Spain continued to be ravaged by guerilla bands, who swarmed over the pro vinces with no other objects in view but plunder and blood shed. During the year, the Cortes had twice met; their deliberations chiefly referred to the state of the finances and the negociation of a loan, which was not effected. The ministry, always feeble, had now become more feeble than ever, notwithstanding that changes were continually taking place. The queen-regent found it impossible to form a strong government in the present political state of the coun try. Its helplessness was such that the generals commanding in the different provinces found it necessary to act in dependently of its arrangements, and to appropriate the revenues of each province to the payment of the military expenses incurred in it, instead of allowing the monies to pass into the treasury. Thus General Van Halen, who had organized a fine army of 40,000 men, called the army of the centre, after declaring the kingdoms of Aragon, Valencia, and Murcia, in a state of siege for the rest of the war, and that in future the civil were to consider themselves in sub ordination to the military authorities, proclaimed, that the entire revenues of those provinces should be paid into the military chest, and exclusively appropriated to the expenses of the war. This was probably the very wisest measure that could have been adopted for bringing the war to a speedy termination. Want of pay had repeatedly paralyzed the operations of the Christine armies ; it had dispersed the British legion ; and at this very moment it was exciting discontent, if not revolt, in the camp of Don Carlos. To place the pay of the queen’s troops upon a sure footing, was therefore the first step to secure ultimate triumph in the field.</p><p>During 1839, the cause of Don Carlos rapidly declined, notwithstanding the desperate efforts made by Generals Cabrera and Maroto to maintain it. Espartero, the comman der-in-chief of the queen’s troops, after some hard fighting, cut off the Carlists completely from the plains of Alava, while Diego Leon likewise expelled them from the rich country between the mountains and the Ebro. Many towns and fortresses of importance, one after another, submitted to the triumphant Christines, so that almost the only parts of Biscay which now owned the authority of Carlos were rugged mountainous tracts of country, whither no regular army could follow the fugitives. An armistice was at length concluded between Maroto and Espartero, which was followed by twenty-one Carlist battalions laying down their arms. Don Carlos himself, reduced to the last extremity, fled for refuge into France, where he formally renounced his pretensions to the throne of Spain, under certain conditions alike reasonable and necessary. The question relative to the fueros of the Basques and Navarre, which, it will be recollected, had been abolished, caused much uneasiness. It seemed perfectly evident that</p><p>these important provinces would not be satisfied, or completely surrender themselves to the queen’s authority, unless their local privileges were restored. After some debating in the Cortes this measure was agreed to, government stipulating that it would so modify the fueros as to reconcile the interests of these provinces with those of the nation, and with the constitution of the monarchy. The only Carlist chief who gave any uneasiness to the government was Ca brera, who, little affected by the pacification of the northern provinces, still maintained his footing in Valencia, determined to support the cause of Carlos while an army remain ed to back him. Towards the close of the year, however, sickness paralyzed his exertions ; nor is it supposed that he will be able to effect much when the season again arrives for an army taking the field. It is to be hoped that this protracted, bloody, and disgraceful war is now virtually at an end. It has left Spain overwhelmed with a debt which at present she has no prospect of being able to pay for many years to come. National property, chiefly that of the church, was sold to the amount of L. 10,000,000, to meet the exigencies of the time, but even this large sum fell far short of what was required. The resources of the country are no doubt great, but a long period of peace, and a wise administration of public affairs, will be necessary before these are developed to their full extent. Spain has scarcely been free from internal war since this century commenced. The injury thus inflicted on agriculture, commerce, trade, and manufactures, is not to be estimated, while its effect on the morals of the people has been most pernicious, transforming the peaceful husbandman into a robber, and the aspiring student into a leader of banditti. That Spain has struggled through this sanguinary period of her history without being involved in total ruin, proves that the natural resources of the country are immense, and only require proper management to raise her above her former rank in the scale of nations.</p><p>STATISTICS.</p><p>The position and boundaries of Spain have already been described. Its extent north and south is from Tarifa Point, in the Straits, in 36° north latitude, to Cape Ortegal in Galicia, 43° 46', making 7° 46' of latitude, or about 540 English miles. From east to west the extreme points are Cape Creus, in Catalonia, 3° 17' of east longitude, and Cape La Roca, 9° 17' of west longitude, the distance in this direction being 560 miles. The Peninsula thus forms almost a square, allowance being made for the irregularity of its outline ; and the entire extent of Portugal being ex cluded, it is reckoned to contain about 176,000 square miles English.</p><p>Spain may be considered as composed of a series of mountain terraces, which, projecting successively their rυgged edges towards the south, present a flight of gigantic steps from the Pyrenees to the Mediterranean. The chains of mountains which terminate and divide the great plains of the Peninsula are branches of the immense ridge that, from the most elevated part of Tartary, runs across Asia and Europe, penetrates into the south of France by Switzerland, and, entering Spain in the direction of the valleys of Roncal and Bastan, separates Navarre from Guipuscoa, Biscay from Alava, the highlands of Burgos from the plains of Old Castille, and Asturias from the kingdom of Leon ; then crosses Galicia, and dips into the ocean at Capes Ortegal and Finisterre.</p><p>The Pyrenees are lateral ramifications of this great trunk, which run east and west on the eastern side of Spain, and take a southwest and northwest direction on the confines of Aragon and Navarre. The accumulated mass of these mountains presents, towards the Peninsula, the convex side of a spherical segment, which, like a shield with its boss to</p></body></text></TEI>