<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:34:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The rich loamy soil brings to maturity the best elm timber. Goose feathers were formerly produced in great abundance ; but the draining and inclosing many of the richest marshy plains has rendered these capable of yielding more profit by other productions, and of late years the quantity of feathers is much diminished. The landed property of the county is much divided, no one proprietor or great family having such extensive possessions as to give a preponderant political influence. There is a great number of yeomen who share the lands, and many of them maintain the homely independence of the past generations.</p><p>The mineral products of this county are valuable. The hills of Mendip supply with coals their vicinity, the cities of Bath and Wells, and the towns of Frome and Shepton -Mallet. The other parts of the county use the coals of Newport, which are brought by sea to Bridgewater. Lead, of a quality superior to that of Derbyshire, is found in Men dip and on the Cheddar hills. Calamine is extensively pro duced, and supplies the brass manufacturers of Bristol. Copper is found near Stowey. Manganese, bole, and red ochre, are among the other products of Mendip.</p><p>This is a manufacturing district for various productions. The manufacture of fine woollen cloth is extensive, chiefly at Frome, where it employs 730 males upwards of twenty years of age; and at Road are employed 59, at Beckington 32, Charter Henton, 24, Twerton, near Bath, 284, Lyn combe and Wedcombe, 565, and at Freshford, 32 makers of fine cloths. In another part of the county, at Wellington and Milverton, are nearly 300 makers of cloth of an inferior description. About 300 men are employed in making sailcloth, sacking, and girthweb, at Crewkerne and the parishes of East Coker, Merriot, West Hatch, and North Perrot. At Chard 478 men, and at Ilminston 21, are occu pied in making silk and lace, or the machinery for those fabrics ; and the same trades afford considerable occupation at Bruton and Taunton. At Yeovil, and some of the towns and villages near it, the chief trade is glovemaking, which gives employment to more than 600 men, and a great number of females. Edge tools are made at Wells, employing 60 men, and also at Whately, Emborrow, and some other places. At Nailsea, 100 men are employed in the manufacture of glass ; papermaking and tanning occupy 59 men at Cheddar; and at various places in the county are noticed manufactures of iron, calamine, copper, brass, paper, and snuff ; and a variety of small articles is made at Bath.</p><p>The foreign commerce of Somersetshire passes chiefly through Bristol, which is the mart for such goods as are required in distant countries. Some of the woollen goods which are manufactured at Taunton and Wellington are shipped from Exeter. The far greater portion of the pro ductions of the county are, however, destined to supply the demand for internal consumption. The cattle, butter, and checse, are chiefly sent to London, and in time of war, to Portsmouth and Plymouth. The linen and woollen goods are distributed through the western and Welsh counties, and, in general, are destined more for the home than for foreign markets.</p><p>The titles derived from this county are those of the dukes of Somerset and Wellington ; the marquises of Lans downe, Bath, and Bristol ; the earls of Bridgewater, Poulet, and Ilchester ; and the barons Mendip and Glastonbury. By the reform bill the county has been politically formed into two divisions, the eastern and the western, and each division elects two members to the house of commons. The election for the first is held at Wells; and the other polling places are Bath, SheptonMallet, Bedminster, Axbridge, and Wincanton. The election for the second is held at Taunton ; and the other polling places are Bridgewater, IIchester, Wiiliton, and Langport.</p><p>The seats of the nobility and gentry, especially of the latter, near Bath and Bristol, are numerous; and our limits</p><p>allow only of noticing the most distinguished of them, viz. Longleet, the seat of the Marquis of Bath ; Hinton, the seat of Earl Poulet ; and the houses of the Earl of Carnarvon, Lord Hood, Mr. Miles, and Colonel Gore Langton.</p><p>Two members are chosen for each of the cities of Bath and Wells, and two for each of the boroughs, Taunton and Bridgewater. The boroughs of Minehead, Ilchester, and MilburnPort, which chose two members each, have been disfranchised, and the town of Frome has been made a par liamentary borough, returning one member. Ilchester, from the elections being held there, and from its containing the gaol and county court, is usually considered the county town, although the assizes in the spring are held at Taunton, and in the summer at Wells and Bridgewater alternately.</p><p>SOMERTON, a town in the hundred of that name in the county of Somerset, 125 miles from London. It is pleasantly situated in a fertile country. The inhabitants were in 1801, 1145; in 1811, 1478; in 1821, 1643; and in 1831, 1786.</p><p>SOMMEANY, a town of Persia, in the province of Mek ram, and the principal seaport of Lus. It is situated on an elevated bank, at the mouth of the river Pooralee, which forms a bar about a mile from the town, with three fathoms depth at low water, and boats can anchor close to the shore. It is an inconsiderable place, and the inhabitants, with the exception of a few Hindu merchants, subsist by fishing.</p><p>SOMMEE, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Guj rat. It is a large place, but has a wretched appearance, and the wall by which it is surrounded is in many parts falling to pieces. It stands in a swamp, and is surrounded by numerous puddles, and in the rainy season is almost under water. It is situated to the southeast of Rahdunpυpr.</p><p>SOMME, a department of the north of France. It has been formed out of those parts of the ancient Picardy known as Amienois, Ponthieu, Vimieux, and Santerre, and <hi rend="italic">extends over</hi> 1,460,932 acres, or 2284 square miles. It is bounded on the north by the Pas de Calais ; on the east by the departments of the North and of the Aisne ; on the south by the Oise and the Lower Seine ; and on the west by the British channel. It contains five arrondisements, with forty-one cantons, and 835 communes, and its population in 1836 amounted to 552,706. The surface is flat and level, but gradually slopes towards the sea on the western side. There are no mountains, but some hills of inconsiderable height rise on the eastern frontier. The Somme, which has its source in the department of the Aisne, is the chief river. The others are the Avre, the Noye, the Celle, and the Brisle. The soil is chalky, and naturally fruitful. The inhabitants cultivate to a great extent corn and hemp, and considerable quantities of corn are exported. Cattle and sheep are reared in large flocks. The country is almost destitute of wood, but the valleys abound in peat. The wine produced is small in quantity, and inferior in quality. Oleaginous seeds are extensively cultivated for the manufacture of oil. In this district are numerous and extensive establishments for the manufacture of woollen cloths and fine linen goods, such as cambrics, lenos, and lawns, carpets, hats, hosiery, leather, soap, cutlery, and other hardware. It is, on the whole, one of the most prosperous divisions of the kingdom, and contains, besides many towns and villages densely inhabited, the large cities Amiens (population, 46,129) and Abbeville, (population, 18,247), in which most of the commerce of the department is concentrated.</p><p>SOMNAMBULISM, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sleepwalking.</hi> According to a report made to the Physical Society of Lausanne, by a committee appointed to examine a young man who was accustomed to walk in his sleep, the disposition to this singular habit seems to depend on a particular affection of the nerves, which both seizes and quits the patient during</p></body></text></TEI>