<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>submit were reduced by the royal troops, now augmented to a considerable body. An attempt of the French king to seize Navarre was happily frustrated, so that in 1522 the whole country was restored to tranquillity.</p><p>In July of that year, the emperor, whose presence had been often requested by the royalists, arrived in Spain. It was expected that summary justice would be inflicted on those who had taken a prominent part in the recent disturbances ; but on this occasion Charles showed a degree of clemency almost unexampled in history, very few being condemned to suffer. During the remainder of this prince’s reign, the domestic tranquillity of Spain was undisturbed, except by an insurrection of the Moors, which was soon sup pressed. Of two expeditions of the emperor to the African coast, to humble, if not to extirpate, the Mahommedan pirates, one was successful, the other disastrous. He compelled the Grand Turk, who penetrated into the centre of Europe, to retreat ; and took his great rival, Francis I. of France, prisoner at Pavia. Such were some of his achievements in his foreign wars, by which the fame of the Spanish arms was ex tended throughout Europe. The mines of the west also had begun to pour their inexhaustible wealth into the country, so that the military and political power of Spain now attained its zenith, and became a source of uneasiness to other nations. In 1525 Charles married the Princess Isabella, sister of Joam III. king of Portugal. The issue of this union was, besides two daughters, the infant Philip, destined to be no less famous than his father. Charles made an ineffectual effort to procure for him the imperial crown of Germany ; but in 1554 succeeded in obtaining the hand of the princess Mary of England. That the nuptial ceremony might be per formed with greater splendour, he invested his son with the regal title, by abdicating in his favour his Italian possessions, the kingdoms of Naples and Sicily, and the duchy of Milan. This was but a prelude to a still more extraordinary sacrifice. It appears that from the very prime of life the emperor had meditated a retreat from the world ; and that on the death of his mother Juana, in 1555, he was determined on fulfilling his long-cherished project. Many reasons have been assigned for this memorable act, but the principal cause is to be traced to his superstitious temperament ; something is also to be allowed for the bad success of his arms during the latter years of his reign. Having concluded a truce with Henry, the successor of Francis, and re called Philip from England, he assembled at Brussels the states of the Netherlands. There, amidst the most imposing solemnity ever witnessed since the days of the Roman Cæsars, he resigned the sovereignty of the Low Countries into the hands of his son. With the same august ceremony he resigned the crown of Spain, and the dominions thereto belonging ; and from the monastic retreat to which he retired, be sent his resignation of the imperial diadem. The place which he had chosen for his residence was the monastery of St Justus, one of the most secluded and delightful situations in Estremadura. Here, employed in religious observances, passed the latter years of the life of the most powerful sovereign Europe had seen since the days of Charlemagne and the empire of the west. His character has been variously described by natives and foreigners ; the former can see little in it to condemn, the latter nothing to admire. His policy was always close, sometimes crooked, and in not a few instances dishonourable. He was no friend either to civil or religious liberty, and may safely be pronounced a bigot. Under him the condition of Spain was more splendid, perhaps also more prosperous, than in any prior or sub sequent reign. Notwithstanding his many wars, the people do not appear to have been overburdened in supporting them, for the New World poured its treasures at his feet. A new impulse was given to national industry by the markets opened for Spanish productions in the transatlantic colonies. But the brightest landscape has its masses of shade. The</p><p>nobles held a power over the people which was often <hi rend="italic">exercised</hi> with violence. Favouritism to foreigners was practised to an unprincipled extent, and the sale of offices be came a branch of traffic. Another baneful evil was the multiplication of religious orders. Lastly, the exemption from taxation of the nobles and clergy, which threw the whole weight of public contribution on the third estate, in creased the disaffection of that body, and was one of the chief causes of the subsequent decline of the kingdom. For an account of the private life and character of Charles, see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> V.</p><p>The reign of Philip II. commenced in 1556, and extend ed to the year 1598. Much of it was occupied in foreign wars, to which we can only briefly advert. For an account of Philip’s long, bloody, and inglorious struggle with his revolted subjects of the Low Countries, see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Holland.</hi> The circumstances which led to the invasion of Portugal, and the annexation of that kingdom to the Spa nish crown, will be found fully detailed under the head Portugal. An attempt was made by the pope, in conjunction with France, to wrest from Philip his Italian dominions, but without success. The duke of Alva, the viceroy of Naples, put his troops in motion, seized several fortresses of the papal states, and the holy city began to tremble for its security. Philip himself invaded France, and inflicted a severe blow on Henry under the walls of St Quentin. The French army, under the duke of Guise, was recalled from Italy ; and the pope, left at the mercy of the duke of Alva, was compelled to purchase his safety by withdrawing from the French alliance. In 1559 peace was made with France ; and Philip having become a widower, further ratified the treaty by marrying Elizabeth, sister of the French king. But the Turks continued to harass Naples, although they durst not make a stand before the Spanish forces. In 1565, Philip assisted the Maltese with 10,000 Spaniards in the famous siege which they underwent from sultan Solyman. Five years afterwards, the war between the Venetian re public and the Porte again brought the Spaniards into collision with the latter power, and they had no small share in achieving the glorious victory of Lepanto. The Mahom medans, however, still continued to make descents on the Italian coast, and to harass the African possessions of Philip; but, on the whole, the war with the misbelievers was honour able to the Spanish arms.</p><p>We now approach an event of peculiar and lasting inte rest to every Briton, the projected invasion of England by the famous Spanish Armada. Elizabeth had certainly done much to provoke the resentment of Philip. She had succoured the insurgents of the Netherlands, fomented the disturbances in Portugal, assisted France, and her naval captains had ravaged the dominions of Spain in both he mispheres. Philip’s patience being exhausted, he prepared a mighty armament for the invasion of England. A complete account of this famous attempt to plant a foreign standard on our shores, and its disastrous termination, will be found in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">England</hi>. A second expedition for the invasion of Ireland shared the fate of the former ; and this effectually cured Philip of all ambition to attempt the subjugation of the most hated of his enemies.</p><p>The revolt of the Moriscos occupies a remarkable place in the native annals of the sixteenth century. These Christianized Moors still remained Mahommedans at heart, making amends for compulsory apostasy by celebrating in secret the rites of their religion. It was the jealous policy of Spain to destroy, if possible, every vestige of their nationality. To effect this end the government had re course to severe and unjust measures, which produced open revolt and civil war in Granada. Dreadful atrocities were committed by the Moriscos, and fierce was the retaliation of the Christians. The war raged with various suc cess for some time, but how the struggle must terminate</p></body></text></TEI>