<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ocean at Cape St Vincent. The pass named Puerto del Rey, where the road from Madrid to Andalusia crosses these mountains, is 821 yards above the sea. Near Cordo ba, where the bold skirts of the <hi rend="italic">Montes Mariani</hi> are seen, within a short distance to the north, like a skreen raised to protect the rich and extensive plains watered by the Gaudalquivir, the ridge borrows the name of the neigh bouring city. On the southern limits of Estremadura, and to the north of Seville, it is called Sierra de Guadal canal. The chain now bends to the southwest, forms the northern boundary of the Portuguese province of Algarve, and, through the Sierras of Caldeiraon and Monchique, connects itself with Cape St Vincent.</p><p>The brink of the last mountain plain towards the south of Spain is skirted by the ridge of Granada and Ronda, which, striking off at the extremity of the Iberian chain, is successively called Sierra de Gador, Sierra Nevada, Ber meja, and de Ronda, till it ends in various points of the coast, but most conspicuously in the Rock of Gibraltar.</p><p>Part of Sierra Nevada rises above the highest Pyrenees. The Cumbre de Mulhacen is 4254 yards above the sea, the Picacho de Veleta 4153. The line of perpetual con gelation is found in these mountains at the height of 3305 yards.</p><p>The five great streams which water the plains lying be tween the great mountain ridges, are the Miño, the Ebro, the Duero, the Tagus, the Guadiana, and the Guadal quivir.</p><p>The Mino, or Minho <hi rend="italic">(Minins</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Bænis),</hi> rises in Galicia, in the district of Lugo, from a beautiful spring called Fuente Miña. This river is navigable only to Salvatierra, two leagues above Tuy. The Ebro rises, near Reynosa, out of a spring so copious that it turns a corn-mill a few steps from its source. After a course of 110 leagues, it flows into the Mediterranean at Alfaques. From the boundaries of Navarre to the sca, the Ebro makes a progress of 1° 12' 42” towards the south. The chief towns on this stream are Logroño and Calahorra, in the province of Rioja; Tudela, in Navarre; Saragossa, in Aragon; and Tortosa, in Catalonia. It is a misfortune for Spain that this great river presents strong obstacles to navigation, both in its course and where it reaches the sea. Of the plans which have been conceived, and partly executed, to obviate these impediments, we shall presently have occasion to speak. The Duero, or Douro, has its source to the north of the city of Osina, in a deep lake, at the summit of that portion of the neighbouring chain of mountains called Sierras de Urbion. Its course is at first towards the south, passing by Garray and Soria, where it turns to the west, continuing in that direction till it reaches Miranda. From this town to Moncorvo the river falls again into a south direction. It lastly takes a decided course to the ocean, which it reaches near Oporto, having traversed a distance of 150 leagues. This river is navigable up to the tower of Moncorvo, a space of thirty leagues. The navigation, which was formerly obstructed by rapids, has been expedited through the exertions of the Portuguese company of Alto Douro. Some of the smaller streams flowing into the Duero rise at remarkable heights. The Adaja, which descends from the northern slope of the great chain between the Duero and the Tagus, is, at Avila, 1271 yards above the sea ; the Eresma, when it flows by the castle of Segovia, is 1107 yards above the same level. We have mentioned that elevated part of the chain between the Tagus and the Guadiana which takes the name of Albarracin, and the truncated mountain called Muela de San Juan. An in considerable spring, denominated Pie Izquierdo, is the source of the majestic Tagus. In its course through the province of Cuenza it is considerably augmented by the contributions of several streams. Before its waters reach Aran juez, they surmount the rocky edge of its native mountain,</p><p>and, dashing upon the plain beneath, sink into a pool of great depth, called Olla de Borlaque. The Tagus, now running placidly through the plains of Zorita and the royal gardens of Aranjuez, at the elevation of 621 yards above the sea, directs its course to Toledo, passes by Talavera, Alcantara, Abrantes, and Santarem, losing itself finally in the sea near Lisbon. The latitudes of several towns on the banks of the Tagus show the gradual inclination of its stream towards the south. The sources of the Guadiana are found north of Alcaraz, in La Mancha, at the pools of Ruidera. The course of the river is first to the northwest for eight leagues. It is then absorbed by the soil, and dis appears for seven leagues. The first gathering of its waters, after their subterraneous dispersion, takes place near Day miel. The spot is called Ojos (Eyes) de Guadiana. The stream now proceeds to Ciudad Real, the chief town of the province of La Mancha, to Merida, Badajos, Mertola in Portugal, and, reentering the Spanish territory, terminates in the ocean at Ayamonte. In its course to this point, the Guadiana passes over a space of more than 100 leagues, but it is not navigable higher than Mertola in Portugal. The Guadalquivir occupies the centre of the plain which lies be tween the Sierra Morena and the chain of Granada, where it takes its course to the northeast of Jaen. The chief towns on its banks are Andujar, Cordoba, Seville, and San Lucar ( <hi rend="italic">Templum Luciferi).</hi> At the ferry near Mengibar, on the road from Madrid to Granada, the Guadalquivir is 203 yards above the sea. This river is navigable for large vessels up to Seville ; but its bed being constantly raised and obstructed by growing shallows, the navigation is extremely tedious.</p><p>If we except the series of small lakes from which the river Guadiana takes its rise, there are in Spain few lakes that merit particular notice. The most remarkable of these is the lake of Abulfera, in the province of Valencia. This lake begins near the village of Cataroija, about a league north of the city of Valencia, and extends nearly four leagues, as far as Cullera. When it is full, it is about four leagues in length, and two in breadth ; but it is so shallow that small boats can scarcely float in it. To supply the deficiency of water, an engine is employed, by which the neighbouring waters are drawn into the bed of the lake; and any super abundant water occasioned by heavy rains is carried off into these by means of an artificial opening. This lake contains a great many fish, and numerous aquatic birds make it their haunt.</p><p>According to Professor Hausmann, viewing Spain as a whole, a threefold principal difference is to be observed. The northern zone, which extends to the Ebro, differs entirely in its characters from the middle zone ; and this again is completely different from the southern zone, which is bounded on the north by the Sierra Morena and a part of the Ostrandes. The northern zone, which includes Galicia, Asturias, the Basques, Navarre, the northern part of Aragon and Catalonia, is a widely extended, mountainous, and hilly country. The snow-fields and glaciers of the Pyrenees on the one side, and on the other the north and northwest winds, have a marked influence in lowering the temperature of the atmosphere, and in increasing the sup ply of water. The increased humidity is favourable to vegetation, which on the whole very much resembles that of the south of France ; and the variety of rocks containing lime, clay, and sand, and also their frequent alternations, operate beneficially on the soil. Everywhere it invites to cultivation, and the inhabitants of this region are active husbandmen. The middle part of Spain, which comprises Old and New Castille, a part of Aragon, Leon, and Estre madura, is not so favourably circumstanced. Generally speaking, it is deficient in either beauty or variety of aspect. The broad and lofty tablelands present a uniform and monotonous surface, destitute of trees, and scorched by the rays</p></body></text></TEI>