<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:34:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>occasion they alone can establish any fact, though, when concurring with facts, they certainly tend to confirm and explain them. It is only from historical facts that we can know to what the name of Sodor was applied.</p><p>It appears from the history of the Orkneys compiled by an old Islandic writer, translated and enlarged by Torfæus, that the Æbudæ, or Western isles of Scotland, were divid- ed into two clusters, Nordureys and Sudereys. The Nor- dureys, which were separated from the Sudereys by the point of Ardnamurchan, a promontory in Argyleshire, con- sisted of Muck, Egg, Rum, Canna, Skye, Rasay, Barra, South Uist, North Uist, Benbecula, and Lewis, including Harris, with a great number of small isles. The Sudereys were, Man, Arran, Bute, Cumra, Avon, Gid, Isla, Colonsay, Jura, Scarba, Mull, Iona, Tiree, Coll, Ulva, and other small islands. All these, when joined together, and sub- ject to the same prince, made up the kingdom of Man and the Isles. In the Norwegian language, <hi rend="italic">Suder</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Norder </hi>signify southern and northern, and <hi rend="italic">ey</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ay</hi> an island. When the Hebrides were under one monarch, the seat of empire was fixed in the Sudereys, and the Nordureys were governed by deputies : hence the former are much oftener mentioned in history than the latter ; hence, too, the Su- dereys often comprehend the Nordureys, as in our days Scotland is sometimes comprehended under England. Su- dereys, or Suder, when Anglicised, became Sodor ; and all the Western isles of Scotland being included in one diocese under the Norwegian princes, the bishop appointed to superintend them was called the bishop of Man and the Isles, or the bishop of Sodor and Man. Since Man was conquered by Edward III. it has been separated from the other isles, and its bishops have exercised no jurisdiction over them. Should it now be asked, why then is the bishop of Man still called the bishop of Sodor and Man ? we reply, that we have been able to discover no reason ; but suppose the appellation to be continued in the same way, as the title king of France was retained by the kings of Great Britain, for several centuries after the English were entirely expelled from France.</p><p>SOEST, a city of Prussian Westphalia, in the government of Minden, the capital of a circIe of the same name, which extends over 240 square miles, and has a population of 33,400 persons. It is situated on the Tosterbache, and is sur- rounded with old and Iofty walls. In 1834 it had 1200 houses in narrow and crooked streets, and 7854 inhabitants, chiefly occupied in manufactures of various kinds. Lat. 51. 34. 5. Long. 8. 0. 1. E.</p><p>SOFALA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sephala,</hi> a kingdom of Africa, lying on the east coast near Zanguebar. The name Sofala denotes, in the Hebrew and Arabic languages, <hi rend="italic">low country.</hi> It has been celebrated by the Arabian geographers for its golden treasures, but it is from the interior that this precious metal is brought. The soil is fertile, and the climate tolerable. Numberless reefs and banks of sand render the approach dangerous. Long. 35. 40. E. Lat. 20. 20. S.</p><p>SOFFITA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Soffit,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Architecture,</hi> any timber ceiling formed of cross beams of flying comices, the square compartments or pannels of which are enriched with sculp- ture, painting, or gilding ; such are those in the palaces of Italy, and in the apartments of Luxembourg at Paris.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Soffita,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Soffit,</hi> is also used for the underside or face of an architrave ; and more particularly for that of the corona or larmier, which the ancients called <hi rend="italic">lacunar,</hi> the French <hi rend="italic">plafond,</hi> and we usually the <hi rend="italic">drip.</hi> It is enriched with compartments of roses ; and in the Doric order has eighteen drops, disposed in three ranks, six in each, placed to the right of the guttæ, at the bottom of the triglyphs.</p><p>SOFIA, a city of Turkey in Europe, the ancient Sardi- ca. It is situated in Romelia, and is the capital of a province of its own name. It is on an extensive plain, between the two rivers Iscar and Rissava. It is surrounded</p><p>with walls flanked by towers, and defended by a citadel. It is the seat of a Greek and of a Catholic bishop ; has twenty-three mosques, several Greek, Catholic, and Ar- menian churches, some Jewish synagogues, 8000 houses, with about 48,000 inhabitants. It is one of the most flou- rishing cities of the empire, depending chiefly on its manu- factures. They consist of silk, woollen and linen goods, and various smaller articles. The general appearance of the town is somewhat imposing ; but many of the houses are of wood, and look meanly, as there are few glass win- dows, and generally iron grating in their stead. Sofia was built by the emperor Justinian out of the ruins of the an- cient Sardica, and fell under the power of the Turks in 1382.</p><p>SOHAGEPOOR, a town and small district of Hindus- tan, in the province of Gundwana. The province is situ- ated between the 23° and 24° of N. lat. It is a barren, mountainous, and unproductive country, possessed by va- rious savage chiefs. The town is situated eighty miles S. by E. from Rewah. Long. 81. 45. E. Lat. 23. 29- N.</p><p>SOHAM, a town of the hundred of Staplac, in the coun- ty of Cambridge, seventy-one miles from London. It is usually called Monks-Soham, to distinguish it from some villages of the same name near it, and from having been formerly the seat of a large Benedictine monastery. It has a charity school and a market on Saturday. The inhabitants were, in 1801, 2004; in 1811, 2386; in 1821, 2856; and in 1831, 3667.</p><p>SOHAUL, a town of Hindustan, province of Allahabad, thirty-five miles S.E. from Callinger. Long. 80. 52. E. Lat. 24. 40. N.</p><p>SOHNPOOR, a town of the province of Gundwana, in Hindustan, possessed by independent chiefs, situated on the Mahanuddy river, 127 miles S.E. from Ruttunpoor. Long. 83. 45. E. Lat. 20. 47. N.</p><p>SOIGNES, a city of the Netherlands, in the province of Hennegan, and arrondisement of Mons. It stands on the river Senne, which rises at the distance of about six miles. The population amounts to 4800 persons, who are chiefly employed in obtaining stone from some valuable quarries. Lat. 50. 32. Long. 3 59. E.</p><p>SOIL, the mould covering the surface of the earth, in which vegetables grow. It serves as a support for vegeta- bles, and as a reservoir for receiving and communicating nourishment. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Agriculture.</hi></p><p>SOISSONS, an arrondisement of the department of the Aisne in France, which extends over 456 square miles, and is divided into six cantons and 167 communes, containing 68,761 inhabitants. The capital, a city of the same name, is situated in a fine valley on the river Aisne. It has a cathedral with two towers, only one of which has been completed. The town, in 1836, contained 8124 inhabitants, employed chiefly in making linens and leather, and in spinning cotton by machinery.</p><p>SOKOR ZOK, a town of Armenia, situated about mid- way between Bellis and Diarbekir, and governed by a powerful prince, who rules over many different tribes of Kurds and Turcomans. Population, 6000.</p><p>SOLANDER’S <hi rend="smallcaps">Island,</hi> in the South Pacific, near the south coast of New Zealand, discovered by Captain Cook in 1770. It is of a craggy surface, of great height. Long. 192. 49. W. Lat. 46. 31. S.</p><p>SOLDER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sodder</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">Soder,</hi> a metallic or mineral composition used in soldering or joining together other metals. Solders are made of gold, silver, copper, tin, bismuth, and lead. In the composition there must commonly be some of the metal that is to be soldered mixed with some higher and finer metals. Goldsmiths usually make four kinds of solder, viz. solder of eight, where to seven parts of silver there is one of brass or copper ; solder of six, where only a sixth part is copper ; solder of four,</p></body></text></TEI>