<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>could never for a moment be doubtful. The Moriscos fled to the mountains, the ancient asylum of liberty ; and in the deep caverns with which they abound they deemed them selves secure. But thither they were hunted by the Chris tians, and, like wild beasts, smoked to death by fires kindled at the mouths of these subterranean retreats. All who were in arms were cut off' in this manner, or by the sword. The total expulsion of the Moriscos, however, did not take place till a subsequent period. To some affairs of a private or more trivial nature it is unnecessary to advert, although some of them deeply implicate the character of Philip. This prince died in September 1598, in the palace of the Escu rial, of which he was the founder, and which is the noblest monument of his reign. By the last of his four wives, Anne of Austria, Philip left a son, who succeeded by the title of Philip III. ; his other male children preceded him to the tomb. Don Carlos, one of these, is generally believed to have been murdered by the command of his bloody and un relenting father. The character of Philip was gloomy, stem, and cruel ; he was suspicious, dark, and vindictive, the irreconcilable foe of civil and religious liberty, for which there can only be brought forward as a palliation his zeal for what he called religion. But Philip was eminently prudent, attentive to public affairs, and what he conceived to be the best interests of his country. It has been supposed that the sceptre of Philip was swayed over 100,000,000 of human beings, including the population of all the foreign pos sessions of Spain. At this time the state of the inhabitants of the Peninsula was one of comparative comfort. Agri culture, manufactures, and commerce, flourished to an ex tent even greater than in the best period of the emperor’s reign. Yet all his vast resources, especially in the New World, were unhappily wasted by Philip; and his own policy destroyed the very foundations on which they rested, and hastened the decay, or rather ruin, of the kingdom. The measures which exercised so fatal an influence over the destinies of Spain may be briefly enumerated. 1. His persecution of the Flemings and Dutch, which led to a re volt that cost him 150,000,000 of ducats ; 2. his war with England, no less expensive and disastrous ; 3. the treasures sent to support the abominable Catholic league, and wars in other quarters ; 4. the subjugation of the Moriscos, and the proceedings of the inquisition, by which the most productive and useful classes of his subjects were ruined or expatriated. From these and from other minor causes, notwithstanding the enormous revenues and resources of the kingdom, Philip died insolvent.</p><p>The greatness of Spain having passed away with Philip II., from this period it declined with fearful rapidity. For a long period there is little to be recorded beyond the reign of worthless favourites, the profligacy of courts, and the feeble efforts of a government struck with mortal paralysis. Our retrospect of these reigns will therefore be charac terized by a brevity corresponding with their importance. The most signal event of Philip III.’s reign was the total expulsion of the Moriscos from all parts of Spain where they had sought a home during the struggle recorded in the last reign. The loss to agriculture and commerce, for they were by far the most ingenious and industrious portion of the community, and the blow which would be inflicted on the national prosperity by the withdrawal of so much wealth as they possessed, were never taken into ac count by the duke of Lerma, the prime ministers, nor any of his inquisitorial councillors. Orders were issued for their immediate expulsion in September 1609, and no fewer than 600,000 individuals were forcibly dragged from their homes, and landed on the African shore, there to be treated even worse, by the most cruel and perfidious of the human family. The foreign transactions of this reign are unimportant. Philip III. died in March 1621, leaving his kingdom to a son who bore his name, and also inherited his imbecility.</p><p>Philip IV. ascended the Spanish throne in his seventeenth year. Profligate extravagance and dissipation soon began to characterize the proceedings of the court, and murmurs and complaints to agitate the people, who were exhausted of their wealth in supporting pantomime and mummery at home, and iniquitous wars abroad. The reins of government were surrendered into the hands of the Conde de Olivares, a worthless favourite. An attempt to enforce an obnoxious measure drove the Catalans to revolt. They sought and obtained the aid of France, and this occasioned a feeble and unimportant war, which languished till 1660, when peace was concluded, but not till Spain had surrendered part of her territory to France. Contemporary with the origin of the Catalan insurrection was that of Portugal, by which the Portuguese freed themselves from the Spanish yoke. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Portugal.</hi> During his long reign, Philip was frequently at war with England, Holland, and France, and every power committed fearful ravages on his territories. England took Jamaica during this disastrous and disgraceful period of Spanish history. In Naples, a terrible shock was sustained in 1646, by the insurrection of Massaniello. See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Naples.</hi> But the most calamitous of Phi lip’s transactions was the war in the Low Countries, which terminated in his recognising the independence of the seven United Provinces. Philip died in 1665. His character needs no description. Since the days of Roderick the Goth, a more disastrous reign than his had not darkened the annals of Spain.</p><p>Charles II. son of Philip IV. succeeded to the throne when only four years of age. As the affairs of the kingdom were then situated, they were not likely to improve under a child ; and it was a further misfortune, that throughout his long reign the king remained little better than a child. He was feeble in body, and next to imbecile in mind ; in proof of which it may be mentioned, that he believed himself bewitched, and submitted to the exorcisms of his confessor with devout solemnity. Louis of France, who espoused Maria Teresa, sister of Charles II. by a prior marriage, in right of his wife preferred a monstrous claim to the Low Countries, and poured his legions over the frontier to make it good. The union of Sweden, Holland, and England, to oppose the ambition of the Frenchman, saved the whole Netherlands from subjugation ; but by the peace of Aixla Chapelle Louis retained the most valuable of the conquests which he had made. In this reign the complete independence of Portugal was recognised. In 1672, France invad ed Holland, now the ally of Spain, conquered Franche Comté, which belonged to Spain, made some destructive in roads into Catalonia, and reduced some fortresses in the Low Countries. By the alliance against France, in which England, Germany, and Spain joined, Louis’s career of ambition was effectually checked. But subsequently he reduced Valenciennes, Cambray, St Omers, and other places ; Ypres and Ghent were assailed with equal success ; and a place on the Catalan frontier also yielded to his arms. Most of these places, however, were restored at the peace of Nimeguen in 1078, one of the conditions of which was, that Charles should receive the hand of Maria Louise, niece of the French king. On the death of this princess in 1689, the French again poured the storm of war over the frontier of Catalonia. Destitute of money and of troops, Spain trembled to her most distant extremities. But circumstances of a delicate nature, into which we shall not enter, induced Louis to restore all his conquests at the peace of Ryswick in 1697. The health of Charles, always infirm, now rapidly declined, and he expired on the 1st of November 1700. He was the last of the Austrian dynasty ; and glorious as the condition of Spain was under its early sovereigns, those who succeeded them had brought the kingdom to the verge of ruin. From the accession of the third Philip it had declined, from causes already specified.</p></body></text></TEI>