<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:37Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Lemberg, the capital of Red Russia, on the 20th of Octo</p><p>'ber 1677. His father was a Polish nobleman, distinguished by his rank and the important offices which he held, but still more by his firmness and courage. In 1704 Stanislas was sent ambassador, by the Assembly of Warsaw, to Charles XII. of Sweden, who had conquered Poland. He was at that time twenty-seven years old, was general of Great Poland, and had been ambassador extraordinary to the Grand Signior in 1699. Charles was so delighted with the frankness and sincerity of his deportment, and with the firmness and sweetness which appeared in his countenance, that he offered him the crown of Poland, and ordered him to be crowned at Warsaw in 1705. He accompanied Charles into Saxony, where a treaty was concluded with King Augustus in 1705, by which that prince resigned the crown, and acknowledged Stanislas king of Poland. The new monarch remained in Saxony with Charles till 1707, when they returned into Poland and attacked the Russians, who were obliged to evacuate that kingdom in 1708. But Charles being defeated by Peter the Great in 1709, Augustus returned into Poland, and being assisted by a Russian army, obliged Stanislas to retire first into Sweden, and afterwards into Turkey. Soon after, he took up his residence at Weissenburg, a town in Alsace. Augustus dispatched Sum his envoy to France to complain of this; but the duke of Orleans, who was then regent, returned this answer : “ Tell your king, that France has always been the asylum of unhappy princes.” Stanislas lived in obscurity till 1725, when Louis XV. espoused the princess Mary his daughter. Upon the death of King Augustus in 1733, he returned to Poland, in hopes of remounting the throne of that kingdom. A large party declared for him ; but his competitor, the young elector of Saxony, being supported by the emperor Charles VI. and the empress of Russia, was declared king, though the majority was against him. Dantzig, to which Stanislas had retired, was quickly taken, and with great difficulty the unfortunate prince made his escape in disguise, after hearing that the Russians had set a price upon his head. In 1736, when peace was concluded between the emperor and France, it was agreed that Stanislas should abdicate the throne, but that he should be acknowledged king of Poland and grand duke of Lithuania, and continue to bear these titles during life ; that all his effects and those of the queen his spouse should be restored ; that an amnesty should be declared in Poland for all that was past, and that every person should be restored to his possessions, rights, and privileges ; that the elector of Saxony should be acknowledged king of Poland by all the powers who acceded to the treaty ; that Stanislas should be put in peaceable possession of the duchies of Lorraine and Bar, but that im mediately after his death those duchies should be united for ever to the crown of France. In Lorraine Stanislas succeeded a race of princes, who were beloved and regretted ; and his subjects found their ancient sovereigns revived in him. He then tasted the pleasure which he had so long desired, the pleasure of making men happy. He assisted his new subjects ; he embellished Nancy and Luneville ; he formed useful establishments ; he founded colleges, and built hospitals. He was engaged in these noble employ ments, when an accident occasioned his death. His nightgown caught fire, and burnt him so severely before it could be extinguished, that he was seized with a fever, and died the 23d of February 1766. He was a protector of the arts and sciences. He wrote several works of philosophy, politics, and morality, which were collected and published at Paris in 1763, in 4 vols. 8vo., under the title of “ Œuvres du Philosophe bienfaisant.” An octavo volume, ornamented with engravings, was published in 1825, under the title of “ Œuvres choisies de Stanislas, Roi de Pologne, Duc de Lorraine et de Bar;” to which an historical notice was prefixed by Madame de Saint-Ouen.</p><p>STANISLAWOW, a circle of the Austrian principality of Gallicia, extending over 1495 square miles. It comprises five cities, thirteen market towns, and 264 villages, with 186,400 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name, between two branches of the river Wistrica. It is well built, and contains Catholic, Greek, and Armenian churches, with 370 houses, and 6880 inhabitants. The Jews and Armenians are the principal traders. Lat. 43. 56. Long. 24. 38. E.</p><p>STANLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas,</hi> a very learned writer, was the son of Sir Thomas Stanley of Laytonstone in Essex, and Cumberlow in Hertfordshire, by his second wife Mary, the daughter of Sir William Hammond of St. Alban’s-court. He was descended from a natural son of Edward earl of Derby. He was born in the year 1625, and received a domestic education under the tuition of William the son of Edward Fairfax, the well-known translator of Tasso. In 1639, he became a fellow-commoner of Pembroke Hall, Cambridge, where he distinguished himself by his progress in classical learning. After having travelled on the conti nent, he resided for some time in the Middle Temple. Here he lived on terms of particular intimacy with his cou sin Edward, afterwards Sir Edward Sherburne, who cultivated similar studies, and who dedicated a volume of Poems to this learned kinsman. Stanley published Poems and Translations in 1649, 8vo. They were reprinted, with additions, in 1651. But his principal work was his “ History of Philosophy, containing the Lives, Opinions, Actions, and Discourses of the Philosophers of every Sect.” Of the original edition, printed in folio, the first part appeared in 1655, and the third in 1660. The work is dedicated to his uncle-in-law, Sir John Marsham, author of the <hi rend="italic">Canon Chronicus,</hi> who first suggested the undertaking. There are four editions of the History, the last and best being that of 1743, 4to. The author has displayed solid as well as extensive erudition, but his valuable materials are not disposed to the best advantage. The reputation of his work extended to the continent ; and a Latin translation of it by Olearius was published at Leipzig, in quarto, in the year 1711. The part relating to the history of oriental philosophy had been translated into the same language by Le Clerc, and published at Amsterdam in 1690, with a dedication to Bishop Bumet. This version he afterwards inserted in the second volume of his “ Opera Philosophica.” Stanley next prepared his elaborate and valuable edition of Æschylus. Lond. 1663, fol. Some copies of the same impression bear the date of 1664. This edition, which includes the fragments and the Greek scholia, and is accompanied with a commentary and a Latin version, was of great importance when it first appeared ; but since the death of the learned editor, so much has been effected by Schiitz, Wellauer, and other scholars, that it has lost a great portion of its original value. The best of all possible editions of Æschylus has for many years been expected from Hermann ; but those who have sufficient means of ascertaining his present views and occupations, have at length begun to despair of its ever making its appearance. It was thought expedient to reprint Stanley’s edition, with the commentary, corrected and enlarged from his papers preserved in the university library at Cam bridge. The charge of this edition was committed to a very competent scholar, Samuel Butler, afterwards promoted to the bishopric of Lichfield ; who, with the addition of his own annotations, published it at Cambridge in the year1809, in 4 vols. 4to., and in 8 vols. 8vo. Some notes on Demosthenes, ascribed to Stanley, have recently been published in the ninth volume of Dobson’s <hi rend="italic">Oratores Attici.</hi> He died at his lodgings in Suflblkstreet,in the parish of St. Martin’s-in-the Fields, on the 12th of April 1678. He had married Dorothy, the daughter and coheiress of Sir James Enyon of Flower in Northamptonshire, Bart. He had a son, who bore his own name, and, like himself, was educated at Pern</p></body></text></TEI>