<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ware. Sedgley contains 500, and Kingswinford 200 manufacturers of the same kinds of goods. At Tettenhall sixty men, and at Brewood 190 men are employed, with 500 in villages, in the less refined manufacture of stock-locks ; and in most of the places here enumerated, the more domestic manufacture of iron nails, furnishes employment to 2500 men, and to a part of their families.</p><p>“ The other great manufacturing branch of the county, the pottery, is spread over the vicinity of Newcastle ; in which the town of Burslera contains 900 men and their families; Shelton, a larger number ; Longtown and Lane End, nearly 1000; Parkhall, 700; Handley, 360; Fenton Cal vert, 300 ; and Sneyd, 150 ; all within the parish of Stoke upon-Trent. In the town of Stafford 800 men are employed in making shoes, and in the district of the potteries is some cotton trade. The working of the coal mines alone, is a great source of occupation for men and machinery.”</p><p>The cultivated lands of this county are nearly all enclosed by good hedges, chiefly of the white thorn, in fields of from twenty to thirty acres. The general rotation of crops in the clayey soil is, 1st, fallow; 2d, wheat; 3d, oats, after which they are laid down with clover, trefoil, and rye-grass, for two or more years. On breaking up an old sward, the usual course is, 1st, oats; 2d, fallow ; 3d, wheat ; 4th, oats; and then the grasses. On the more friable soils the rotation is, 1st, fallow; 2d, wheat; 3d, beans, or pease; 4th, oats, and then the grasses. On the light soil, the Norfolk system of turnips, barley, clover, and then wheat, is most commonly followed.</p><p>The black cattle are generally of the long-horned breed, and of late years have been much improved by the spirited exertions of some distinguished individuals. The sheep are of different races ; the new Leicesters are said to be the most predominant. About Cannoch and Sutton Coldfield they have a breed much resembling the South Downs. On the moorland there is a breed with white faces, without horns, and long combing wool. The county is well stocked with timber, especially on the estates of some of the great proprietors. The lands in an unimproved state are still estimated to amount to nearly one-tenth part of the whole county.</p><p>The Roman antiquities are the Watling Street and the Ichnield roads, which pass through the county ; and the re mains of ancient stations or encampments. Here the Saxons have left few remains that merit particular attention.</p><p>This county gives titles to the following peers : that of marquis of Stafford, to the eldest son of the duke of Sutherland ; those of earls to Ferrers, Talbot, Harrowby, and Lichfield. For parliamentary purposes, the county has been formed into two divisions, distinguished by their position as North and South ; each of which elects two members to the House of Commons. The election for the northern division is held at Stafford ; and the other polling places are Leek, Newcastle-under-Lync, Cheadle and Abbots Bromley. The election for the southern division is held at Walsall ; and the other polling places are Lichfield, Wolverhampton, Penk ridge, and Kingswinford. By the Reform Bill, the towns of Wolverhampton and Stoke-upon-Trent have been en titled to elect two members each, and Walsall to elect one.</p><p>The most remarkable noblemen and gentlemen’s seats are the following :—Trentham, duke of Sutherland ; Beau desert, marquis of Anglesea ; Ingestrie, earl Talbot ; Sandon, earl of Harrowby ; Sandwell, earl of Dartmouth ; Emville, earl of Stamford ; Shugborough, earl of Lichfield ; Wrothesley, Sir. J. Wrothesley ; Wolsely Hall, Sir Charles Wolsely ; Tixall, Sir T. H. Clifford ; Etruria, Josiah Wedge wood, Esq. ; Weston, earl of Bradford.</p><p>See Plott's History of Staffordshire ; Pitt’s Agricultu</p><p>ral Survey of Staffordshire; Aikin’s History of Manches ter ; Shaw’s History and Antiquities of Staffordshire ; Jack son’s History of Lichfield ; Beauties of England and Wales.</p><p>STAGE, in the modern drama, the place of action and representation, included between the pit and the scenes, and answering to the proscenium or pulpitum of the an cients. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Playhouse</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Τηεατrε.</hi></p><p>STAHL, <hi rend="smallcaps">George Ernest,</hi> an eminent German chemist, was born at Anspach, on the 21st of October 1660, and chosen professor of medicine at Halle, when a university was found ed in that city in 1694. The excellency of his lectures while he filled that chair, the importance of his various publications, and his extensive practice, soon raised his reputation to a very great height. He received an invitation to Berlin in 1716, which having accepted, he was made counsellor of state and physician to the king. He died in 1734, in the seventy-fifth year of his age. Stahl is without doubt one of the greatest men of which the annals of medicine can boast : his name marks the commencement of a new and more illustrious era in chemistry. He was the author of the doctrine of phlogiston, which, though now completely overturned by the discoveries of Lavoisier and others, was not without its use, as it served to combine the scatter ed fragments of former chemists into a system, and as it gave rise to more accurate experiments and a more scientific view of the subject, to which many of the subsequent discoveries were owing. This theory maintained its ground for more than half a century, and was received and support ed by some of the most eminent men which Europe has produced; a sufficient proof of the ingenuity and the abilities of its author. He was the author also of a theory of medi cine, founded upon the notions which he entertained of the absolute dominion of mind over body ; in consequence of which he affirmed, that every muscular action is a voluntary act of the mind, whether attended with consciousness or not. This theory he and his followers carried a great deal too far ; but the advices at least which he gives to attend to the state of the mind of the patient, are worthy of the attention of physicians.</p><p>“ Stahl,” says Dr. Cullen, “ has explicitly founded his system on the supposition, that the power of nature, so much talked of, is entirely in the rational soul. He supposes that, upon many occasions, the soul acts independently of the state of the body ; and that, without any physical necessity arising from that state, the soul, purely in consequence of its intelligence, perceiving the tendency of noxious powers threatening, or of disorders anyways arising in the system, immediately excites such motions in the body as are suited to obviate the hurtful or pernicious consequences which might otherwise take place. Many of my readers may think it was hardly necessary for me to take notice of a syssem founded upon so fanciful a hypothesis ; but there is often so much seeming appearance of intelligence and design in the operations of the animal economy, that many eminent persons, as Perrault in France, Nichols and Mead in Eng land, Porterfield and Simson in Scotland, and Gaubius in Holland, have very much countenanced the same opinion, and it is therefore certainly entitled to some regard.”@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>His principal works are, 1. <hi rend="italic">Experimenta et Observationes Chgmicæ et Physicæ,</hi> Berlin, 1731, 8vo. 2. <hi rend="italic">Dissertationes Medicæ.</hi> Halle, 2 vols. 4to. 3. <hi rend="italic">Theoria Medica vera.</hi> 1737, 4to. 4. <hi rend="italic">Opusculum Chpmicophysicο medicum.</hi> 1740, 4to. 5. A Treatise on Sulphur, both Inflammable and Fixed, written in German. 6. <hi rend="italic">Negotium Otiosum.</hi> Halle, 1720, 4to. It is in this treatise chiefly that he establishes his system concerning the action of the soul upon the body. 7. <hi rend="italic">Fundamenta Chymiæ Dogmaticæ et Experimentalis.</hi></p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Cullen’s First Lines of the Practice of Phytic, vol. i. p. 12.</p></body></text></TEI>