<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Wells is comprehended in it, to which circumstance it owes its increased inhabitants, who were, in 1801, 1618; in 1811, 1901 ; in i821, 2297; and in 1831, 2640.</p><p>SPELLING, in <hi rend="italic">Grammar,</hi> that part of orthography which teaches the true manner of resolving words into their syllables.</p><p>All words are either simple or compound, as <hi rend="italic">use, disuse; done, undone;</hi> and the rules for dividing each must be such as are derived from the analogy of language in general, or from the established custom of speaking ; which, for the English language, are reduced to the following rules : 1. A consonant between two vowels must be joined with the latter in spelling, as <hi rend="italic">nature, ve-ri-ly, ge-ne-rous ;</hi> except, however, the letter <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> which is joined to the first, as in <hi rend="italic">flax-en, ox-en, </hi>&amp;c<hi rend="italic">.,</hi> and compound words, as in <hi rend="italic">upon, unused, </hi>&amp;c. 2. A double consonant must be divided, as in <hi rend="italic">letteτ, manner, </hi>&amp;c. 3. Those consonants which can begin a word, must not be parted in spelling, as in <hi rend="italic">defraud, re-prove, distinct :</hi> this rule, however, is sometimes found to fail ; for though <hi rend="italic">gn</hi> begins a word, as in <hi rend="italic">gnaw, gnat,</hi> &amp;c., yet it must be divided in spelling, as in <hi rend="italic">cog-ni-zance, ma-lig-ni-ty, </hi>&amp;c. 4. Those consonants which cannot begin a word must be divided, as <hi rend="italic">ld</hi> in <hi rend="italic">seldom, lt</hi> in <hi rend="italic">multitude, mp</hi> in <hi rend="italic">tem-per, rd</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ar-dent ;</hi> but in final syllables there are exceptions, as <hi rend="italic">tl</hi> in <hi rend="italic">title, dl</hi> in <hi rend="italic">handle,</hi> &amp;c. 5. When two vowels come to gether, and are both of them distinctly sounded, they must be separated in spelling, as in <hi rend="italic">co-e-val, mutual,</hi> &amp;c. 6. The grammatical terminations or endings must be separated in spelling, as <hi rend="italic">ed</hi> in <hi rend="italic">wing-ed, edst</hi> in <hi rend="italic">de-li-ver-edst,ing </hi>in <hi rend="italic">hearing, αnce</hi> in <hi rend="italic">deliverance, &amp;c</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">.</hi> 7. Compound words must be resolved into their simple and component words, <hi rend="italic">as up on, into, neverthe∙less, not∙withstand∙ing,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>SPELMAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Henry</hi>, an eminent antiquary, was descended from an ancient family, and born at Congham, near Lynn in Norfolk, about the year 1561. He was knighted by King James I. who had a particular esteem for him on account of his known capacity for business; and he employed him several times in Ireland in public affairs. When he was about fifty years of age, he went to reside in London ; where falling into a study to which his own genius had always inclined him, he collected all such books and MSS. as concerned the subject of antiquities, either fo reign or domestic. In 1626, he published the first part of his well-known “ Glossarium Archaiologicum," which he never carried beyond the letter L; because, as some have suggested, he had made remarks under “Magna Charta,” and “Maximum Consilium,” which could not then have appeared without giving offence. Upon his death, all his papers came into the hands of his son Sir John Spelman, a gentleman who had abilities to have completed his father’s design, if death had not prevented him. The second part was after wards published by Sir William Dugdale, but with all the marks of a scanty unfinished performance. The next work which he undertook was an edition of the English Councils; of which he published the first volume in 1639, leaving the second volume, as well of this as of his Glossary, to be published by Dugdale. The second volume appeared in 1664. Spelman wrote several other works relating to ancient laws and customs, and died in 1641. His Treatise concerning Tithes, and his History of Sacrilege, deserve a passing notice. His Posthumous Works were published at Oxford, in folio, in the year 1698, under the inspection of Mr. Gibson, afterwards Bishop of London.</p><p>SPENCE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi>, an eminent writer, was bom in the year 1698, but his family-history remains in obscurity. He was probably educated at Winchester, for he became a fellow of New College, Oxford, where he took the degree of A.M. in 1727. During the same year he published a small volume entitled “ An Essay on Pope’s Odyssey, in which some particular beauties and blemishes of that work are considered.” This essay was greatly admired by his con</p><p>temporaries, and it procured him the friendship of Pope. Spence was elected professor of poetry in 1728, and held that office ten years, which is as long as the statutes will allow. His account of Stephen Duck was first published in 1731 ; but it was afterwards much altered, and prefixed to an edition of Duck’s Poems.</p><p>About this time he travelled into Italy as tutor to the Earl of Lincoln, afterwards Duke of Newcastle. In 1736 he republished Gorboduc, at Mr. Pope’s desire, with a preface giving an account of its author, the Earl of Dorset. He quitted his fellowship in 1742, upon being presented by his college to the rectory of Great Harwood in Buckinghamshire. He never resided on his living ; but paid it an annual visit, distributing large sums of money among the poor, and providing for many of their children. The same year he was appointed professor of modern history at Oxford. In 1747 he published a large folio volume entitled “ Polymetis; or, an Inquiry concerning the Agreement between the Works of the Roman Poets and the Remains of ancient Artists ; being an attempt to illustrate them mutually from each other.” This work was treated by Gray with a con tempt which it did not deserve. He raises objections be cause the author did not illustrate his subject from Greek writers ; that is, because he failed to execute what he never undertook. By the publication of his Polymetis, Spence is said to have cleared L.1500. He was installed prebendary of the seventh stall at Durham on the 24th May 1754. He published the same year, “ An Account of the Life, Character, and Poems, of Mr. Blacklock, Student of Philosophy in the University of Edinburgh ;” which was after wards prefixed to Blacklock’s Poems. The prose pieces which he printed in the Museum he collected and published, together with some others, in a pamphlet called, “ Morali ties, by Sir Harry Beaumont” Under the same name, he published, “ Crito, or a Dialogue on Beauty,” and “ A particular Account of the Emperor of China’s Gardens near Pekin, in a letter from F. Attiret, a French missionary now employed by that emperor to paint the apartments in those gardens, to his friend at Paris.” Both these tracts are printed in Dodsley’s Fugitive Pieces, as is also “ A Letter from a Swiss Officer to his friend at Rome;” which Mr. Spence first published in the Museum. In 1758, he published “ A Parallel, in the Manner of Plutarch, between a most celebrated man of Florence and one scarce ever heard of in England.” The Florentine was Magliabecchi, and the other individual was Robert Hill the Hebrew tailor. This tract is also to be found among the Fugitive Pieces. During the same year he made a journey into Scotland, which he described in an affectionate letter to Mr. Shenstone, published in Hull’s Collection of Letters, 1778. In 1764 he was very well described by James Ridley, in his admirable Tales of the Genii, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Phesoi Ecneps</hi> (his name read backwards), dervise of the groves. A letter from Mr. Spence to that ingenious moralist, under the same signature, is preserved in the third volume of “ Letters of eminent Persons.” In 1768 he published “ Remarks and Dissertations on Virgil, with some other classical observations, by the late Mr. Holdsworth.” On the 20th of August the same year he was unfortunately drowned in a canal in his garden at Byfleet in Surrey. He was found flat upon his face at the edge of the canal, where the water was so shallow as not even to cover his head. The fatal accident, it was supposed, for he was quite alone, was occasioned by a fit.</p><p>More than half a century after his death, appeared his “ Anecdotes, Observations, and Characters of Books and Men, collected from the Conversation of Mr. Pope, and others. With notes and a life of the author by S.W. Singer.” London, 1820, 8vo. Mr. Malone had likewise prepared an edition of this work, and, after his death, it was published during the same year.</p></body></text></TEI>