<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ing to the French. The Spanish declaration of war against Britain is dated at Madrid on the 12th of December 1804; and on the 21st of October 1805, the combined fleets of France and Spain were annihilated by Lord Nelson off Cape Trafalgar. After this terrible blow to the naval power of Spain, nothing of importance took place till 1808, when the liberties of Spain were subverted by the machinations of Napoleon. The designs of the French emperor, long suspected, became sufficiently apparent in 1808. Unfortunately the dissensions of the royal family of Spain were so favourable to his plans, that they may be said to have hurried on their execution. The dark and tortuous policy by which he effected his purpose, and the course which events took in Spain, will be found detailed in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>, so that only a brief notice of the leading facts will be given in this place. At this time (1807) the management of state affairs was in the hands of Don Manuel Godoy, the favourite of Charles IV. and his queen, and better known by the name of the Prince of Peace. He had been raised from the humblest station to be the richest and most powerful subject in the kingdom, and to fill its highest posts. Ferdinand, the prince of Astu rias, had refused to marry the sister-in-law of this fortu nate minion, and to secure himself from his vengeance he wrote to Napoleon asking for protection. At the same time he exposed the administration of Godoy, in a letter to his father, and requested to be allowed some participation in the government. This so enraged the queen that she ordered his immediate arrest ; but, on asking pardon of the king, Ferdinand was restored to liberty, not however before Charles had taken the fatal step of appealing to Napoleon regarding his son’s supposed treasonable conduct. The emperor of France was thus constituted umpire between father and son. French troops poured into Spain, which was thrown into a ferment by the rumour that the royal family were preparing to fly to America. Popular indignation was kindled against the hated favourite, who narrowly escaped with his life. At length Charles abdicated in favour of his son, but two days afterwards privately protested against his own act, and sent a copy of this strange paper to Napoleon, who afterwards made it a pretext for his ulterior designs.</p><p>The prince of Asturias, now elevated to the throne un der the title of Ferdinand VII. made his triumphal entry into Madrid. Shortly afterwards he was induced to under take a journey to Bayonne to meet Napoleon, and consult about the affairs of the kingdom. This memorable inter view took place, and the eyes of Ferdinand were now thoroughly opened to the designs of the French emperor, by finding himself a captive in his hands, and his right to be considered king of Spain rudely denied. The rest of the royal family eagerly rushed into the snare set for them by the master of toils at Bayonne. Here father and son sur rendered the crown of Spain into the hands of Napoleon, by whom it was transferred to the head of his brother Joseph. But such a momentous event as a change of dynasties, effected under circumstances of such atrocious perfidy, could not take place without rousing every loyal and every indignant feeling in the bosoms of the Spanish people. No sooner was the fact of the renunciation known, than the northern provinces burst into open insurrection. Asturias and Galicia set the example ; and it was soon followed by almost every part of Spain not immediately occupied or overawed by the armies of France. One of the first steps taken by the leaders of the insurrection was to assemble the juntas or general assemblies of the provinces. When these were organized, they issued proclamations, calling on the Spaniards to rise in defence of their sovereign, and in the assertion of their own independence. Besides these proclamations from the provincial juntas, addresses were published in almost every province by the leaders of the popular cause ; in particular, the province of Aragon</p><p>was addressed by Palafox, a name celebrated in the annals of the Spanish revolution, in a bold and spirited manifesto. The junta of Seville, which assembled on the 27th of May, formed itself into a supreme junta of government, caused Ferdinand to be proclaimed king of Spain, took possession of the military stores, and issued an order for all males from sixteen to forty-five, who had no children, to enroll themselves in the national armies. On the 4th of July the alliance of Great Britain with the Spanish nation was proclaimed, and a struggle began which terminated in the complete ex pulsion of the French from the Peninsula. The events of this celebrated war will be found recorded in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Britian</hi>.</p><p>The loss of the royal family, by which they were deprived of a directing power, a legitimate head to give the constitutional stamp to their proceedings, plunged the Spaniards in great difficulties. Unity of opinion was wanting to the junta, and vacillation and weakness marked its proceedings. It was unfortunate, that while one spirit animat ed the mass of the people against the French, many of the nobles and other influential individuals had given in their adhesion to the French dynasty. The successes of the lat ter were attributed, probably not without some reason, to treachery ; and more than one Spanish general fell a victim to public indignation, whether justly or unjustly cannot now be known. But whatever victories the French gained, they only remained masters of the places which they occu pied. A vast system of guerilla warfare had been organized and vigorously prosecuted, which served to preserve the energy and confidence of the nation unbroken. The guerillas everywhere surrounded and harassed the French; no line of communication was safe for them. These petty achievements, however, could not compensate for the loss of battles on a large scale, and the capture of fortresses, the strongholds of the kingdom. The supreme junta fell under suspicion, and, unable to sustain the weight of government and the storm of public indignation, it was agreed that the Cortes should be convoked, and a regency appointed. The manner in which this celebrated Cortes was constituted has been a subject of keen disputation ; but the circumstances in which the kingdom was placed at the time, rendered it impossible for the members being chosen according to the ancient forms. It has been alleged that this assembly was of a much more popular and democratic nature than the regular Cortes, which is undoubtedly the fact. It ought to be recollected, however, that the nobles were a suspected body, and therefore the burgesses and others might consider it dangerous to admit their voice in a matter which involved the liberties of the kingdom. But, we repeat, the situation in which Spain stood at this eventful moment made it a matter of necessity for those who directed the affairs of the nation, to act as they did. Had not the progress <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the French armies dispersed the central junta, and concentrated the fugitive patriots at Cadiz, it is more than probable that the Cortes would have been assembled according to the ancient forms, and that the privileged classes, supported by the majority of the nation, would have defeated any attempt to alter the old constitution. But Cadiz offered to that par ty which has been since known by the name of liberal, the most favourable opportunity of striking a deadly blow at the very root of the monarchical power under which they had so long groaned in hopeless yet silent restlessness. Cadiz was not only in itself a place much more democratic than any other in Spain, but during the usurpation of the French it had become the asylum of all who professed liberal prin ciples. As they generally belonged to that numerous class of the Spanish gentry who look up to the patronage of <hi rend="italic">government</hi> for the means of subsistence, the court drew them together from the provinces. On the prospect of the political changes which the captivity of Ferdinand opened to the country, these men attached themselves to the central junta, and finally followed its members in their flight from</p></body></text></TEI>