<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>did return them appear to have observed little proportion in the numbers. Two was the number which ought to have been returned by each, but some towns sent eight, while others of larger size sent only one or two. Indeed it seems highly probable that the privilege of sending deputies was a favour granted by the sovereign to such towns as it was his pleasure to honour. It is preposterous, therefore, to look upon the third estate as consisting of independent repre sentatives of the nation : the members were little better than nominees of royalty, and their numbers could be in creased or diminished just as it suited the purposes of government Much as the popular representation of Castille is extolled by national writers, it seems to have been better adapted for securing and extending the power of the crown, than for protecting the rights of the people. Under Ferdinand and Isabella the last lingering traces of popular liberty were destroyed ; but the power of the other orders of the state suffered at the same time a corresponding diminution, as we have already noticed. Such is a brief outline of the government and laws of Castille and Leon, the most import ant of the peninsular kingdoms, and almost the only ones in which the reader will take much interest, or, indeed, regarding which authentic documents remain. It may be mentioned, however, with regard to the kingdom of Aragon, that, with the exception of the lowest order, the serfs of the soil, the Aragonese possessed a greater share of individual liberty than any other people in the Peninsula. The citi zens and nobles frequently coalesced for the purpose of obtaining fueros or privileges from the crown, and when thus united they were generally too powerful to be resisted. Hence numerous concessions were made by successive sovereigns, and an amount of popular freedom obtained by the people which frequently threatened the existence of the monarchy itself. Catalonia and Valencia were always distinct from Aragon, both in government and laws. Each had its Cortes, consisting of three estates, prelates, nobles, and deputies, all no less tenacious of their privileges than those of Aragon.</p><p>■Several historians of note, whose works have come down to us, flourished in the various Christian kingdoms of Spain during the period of Mahommedan domination. Poetry sprung up about the middle of the twelfth century, and some very interesting specimens of these ancient compositions still remain, particularly the <hi rend="italic">Poema del Cid.</hi> The old Spanish ballads are well known, and celebrated throughout Europe. The scientific state of Spain, as compared with the Mahommedan, exhibits a lamentable contrast ; nor does it appear that in any of the useful arts of life the Spanish Christians were equal to the Moors. The most distinguished place in Spanish science during this period has been as signed to Alfonso X. surnamed el Sabio ; but even he was greatly indebted to the Arabians for the perfection which he attained. The theologians of Spain, during the middle ages, were more numerous than all her other writers put together, and the writings of many of these shining lights of the church are to be met with in the libraries of Spain. With regard to religion it is only necessary to state, that the Catholic faith prevailed in full force, and was characterized by the darkest bigotry and the fiercest intolerance, as the doings of the inquisition amply testify.</p><p>Charles I. (V. of Germany) became king of Spain on the death of Ferdinand, but a regency had been nominated to govern the kingdom until he should attain his twentieth year. If the events and transactions in which this monarch was concerned were to be woven into the history of Spain, it would in fact be the history of almost all Europe during the period of his reign. But our business is with events purely peninsular ; or if others of a more general character are occasionally noticed, it will be because they are too closely connected with the former to be separated without violence. His foreign wars, negociations, and other trans</p><p>actions, arose from his position as emperor of Germany, not from his being king of Spain. ; and an account of them will be found under the heads <hi rend="smallcaps">France</hi>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi>, and <hi rend="smallcaps">England</hi>, to which articles the reader is referred.</p><p>The Cardinal Ximenes Cisneros, to whom the regency had been left by the deceased king, was bitterly opposed in his administration, principally by the nobles of Castille, who, envious of his dignity, displeased with his firmness and vi gour, and hoping for impunity under a young monarch, soon showed a disposition to refuse him obedience. Popular discontent reached a great height ; and as his best measures were misrepresented to the king, Charles perceived the necessity of making his appearance in Spain, where he arrived in 1517. Nobles and prelates hastened to meet their sovereign, and among the rest the calumniated Ximenes. But that sovereign he was not destined to see ; he suddenly sickened and died, not without suspicions of poison. Charles brought with him a multitude of Flemings from the Nether lands, who soon monopolized the principal situations in church and state, and in all their dealings evinced an unquenchable thirst for gold. The favour extended to these foreigners so incensed the people, that Charles found extreme difficulty in obtaining the homage of the Spaniards. Although they swore allegiance to him, it was on certain stipulated conditions, sufficiently advantageous to them selves. In 1519 occurred an event destined to exercise great influence over his future life, over his hereditary states, in fact over all Europe. This was his election to the imperial throne of Germany, left vacant by the death of his paternal grandfather Maximilian. The Spaniards were pleased that this dignity was conferred on their sovereign ; but as the old grievances continued to gall them, they were not so dazzled as to be insensible to their own interests. The leading men of many of the principal cities publicly remonstrated with Charles, and it was only by granting certain concessions that he could keep them from open rebellion. His presence having become absolutely necessary in Germany, he quitted Spain, but proceeded first to England to concert with Henry VIII. the means of humbling the power of the French king, Francis I. This monarch had been a candidate for the imperial diadem ; but, disappointed in his ambition, and in hatred of his successful rival, he leagued himself even with the enemy of the Christian faith. He also laid claim to Italy, the Nether lands, and Navarre ; so that war was unavoidable, and hostilities immediately commenced ; for an account of which see the articles already referred to.</p><p>The turbulence of the times was not likely to be assuaged by the absence of the king from his all but revolt ed territories in the Peninsula. Opposition had now de generated into rebellion ; and what before might have been dignified with the name of patriotism, could only be characterized as crafty schemes of personal ambition. Unfortunately for the interests of order, the regency of Castille, where disaffection had assumed the most serious aspect, was held by a man, estimable and virtuous, indeed, but little fitted for such stormy times. The appointment of this in dividual, Cardinal Adrian, who subsequently wore the triple crown, had at the first given great offence to the nobles and deputies at court ; but the king, though solicited, would not change him for another. The persons upon whom the fury of the mob fell were chiefly the governors and deputies of the cities and provinces. Many were massacred ; open insurrection spread from city to city ; and no species of crime was left uncommitted. In this critical position of the royal cause, it was fortunate that Aragon, Catalonia, and most of Andalusia, stood aloof from the confederation. Had they joined it, the evils might have been long protracted, and the whole Peninsula plunged in misery and ruin. But the revolted cities followed one another in making their submis sion to government ; and those which did not voluntarily</p></body></text></TEI>