<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the Commons in 1832, have both laid open the transactions and policy of the bank ; and a quarterly account is now ordered to be published in the Gazette of its circu 1ation, its deposits, its liabilities, and the average amount of its stock of gold. Such information gives to the political inquiries of modern times an incalculable advantage. The progress of freedom in Europe also conduces to the ex tension of statistical knowledge. Where popular assemblies are established, with the right of free discussion, inquiries into all the branches of the public service will naturally fol low. Papers and accounts will be called for; no longer will the transactions of statesmen be shrouded in darkness; they will be dragged into light; and the people formerly re probated by the tyrant Henry VIII. as brutes, who were no more judges of these high matters than a blind man of colours, will insist, in their boldness and presumption, to know how their money is spent. Thus will be obtained the financial ac counts of the kingdom, and those of commerce, and other public matters will follow in due course. Publicity is the true corrective of corruption ; and in the pure administration of free states, the ruler will rather court than shun inquiry, being conscious of nothing that will not bear the light. Accordingly, in 1832, a statistical office was established in the department of the board of trade, for the purpose of collect ing, arranging, and publishing statements relating to the condition and the various interests of the British empire. The volumes to which this arrangement has given birth, are annually printed and laid before Parliament, and con tain an ample store of the most satisfactory details. Several societies have since been formed for prosecuting statistical inquiries. In 1833, a statistical section was formcd in the British Association for the advancement of Science during the period of its meeting at Cambridge; and, before the close of the year, the Manchester Statistical Society was established. The Statistical Society of London, which had been projected at Cambridge, was established in 1834, and has published a monthly journal, which contains much useful information. Statistical societies have been formed in other populous towns, in Liverpool, in Bristol, and in several towns in Ireland, and promise, by their in dustry, to add largely to the existing stock of useful know ledge. Many important publications have of late years issued from the press, on the condition and resources of the country; on its commerce, its agriculture, its currency, as well as on the state of education, which tend to promote, and greatly to aid statistical inquiries. The most important of these is Macculloch’s Dictionary of Commerce, a work which combines extensive research, and the most copious details, with the spirit of philosophy. Other statistical works are, the Statistical Account of the British Empire, by the same author; Statistical Accounts of part of Ireland, by the Officers of the Irish Ordnance Survey ; Milburn’s Orienal Commerce ; Macgregor’s Statistics of Nations ; Porter’s Progress of the Nation ; Martin’s Colonial Magazine, and his British Colonial Library, an elaborate account of the colo nies. An instructive and useful work has lately been published by Mr. A. Trotter on the Commerce and Banking System of the United States, which is a compendium of important statistical information. With all these aids, political science will undoubtedly advance, and may be expected in time to attain to more certain results in all those important inquiries which relate to the actual condition and moral improvement of mankind.</p><p>STATIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Publius Papinus,</hi> a celebrated Latin poct, who was born at Naples, A.n. 61. His father was of a patrician family, but being poor, he maintained himself by teaching rhetoric, first at Naples, and afterwards at Rome. The emperor Domitian is said to have been one of his pupils. He was a master of the Greek as well as the Latin tongue, and was a poet as well as a rhetorician. If we could rely on the statements of his son, he was little</p><p>inferior to Homer in poetical genius; but as his contemporaries have nowhere noticed him, it may fairly be presumed, that his affection for his father blinded the son’s judgment.</p><p>Statius received his education at Rome, and married at an early age <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.D.</hi> 81) a widow named Claudia, whom he frequently mentions in his verses. He was distinguished by his powers as an improvvisatore, which seem to have been very considerable, and he often appeared before the public in the poetical contests of the age. In these he was not unfrequently victorious; yet though crowds flocked to hear the recitation of his Thebaïs, Juvenal, Sat. vii. 87, remarks, that he would have perished from hunger, if he had not been able to sell to the principal actor of the day his tragedy of Agave, which is now lost. His high reputation however excited against him many enemies, and among others Martial, who, it is observed, never took any notice of Statius. The principal poem of Statius is entitled Thebaïs; it is an epic poem in twelve cantos, and a work of considerable merit. It relates to the Theban war under the sons of Œdipus, and is in reality, like that of Silius Ita licus, an historical poem, the materials for which have been drawn principally from Greek sources, more particularly from the Thebaïs of Antimachus. He has taken for his model Virgil’s Æneid, but has not been very successful in his imitation. Another of his poems is entitled Achilleis, being intended to exhibit a detailed account of the life and deeds of Achilles, from the moment of his birth; but the author did not live to complete his plan, and only two books remain, the last of which is imperfect. This portion contains only a small part of the life of Achilles. We have besides a collection of thirty-two poems, divided into five books, and bearing the title of Silvæ. They are mostly in hexameter, but some few in Alcaic, Sapphic, and Phaleucian verse. Having fallen into a feeble state of health, he retired to Naples in the hope of deriving some benefit from his native air. Here he laboured at his Achilleis ; but death arrested his progress before he had completed the thirty-sixth year of his age.</p><p>The poems of Statins exhibit nearly the same faults as are to be found in the works of Silius Italicus, and Valerius Flaccus. He possesses the rhetorical spirit of his age, which, disregarding the beauties of simplicity, aimed at effect by ingenious turns of expression, and a display of great learn ing. His language is sometimes bombastic. His works were at one period, not of the most refined taste, held in as great estimation as those of Virgil. The first collective edition of his poems appeared at Venice in 1483, folio. They had been separately printed at an earlier period. The subsequent editions are sufficiently numerous. Among the more elaborate of the early editions, we must mention that of Lindenbrog, Paris. 1600, 4to. It includes the scholia of Lactantius, or Lactatius, on the Thebaïs and Achilleis. Nor must we omit the accurate edition of Gro novius, Amst. 1653, 12mo. The same able critic had previously published “ In P. Papinii Statii Silvarum libros v. Diatribe.” Hagæ Com. 1637, 8vo. An edition of Statius was not long afterwards published with the very elaborate and learned commentary of Barthius, Cygnæ, 1664,2 tom. 4to. The commentator was then dead, and the edition was su perintended by Daumius. Considerable additions were here made to the ancient scholia formerly printed. Another critic to whom this poet has many obligations, is Markland, who published, with notes and emendations, a separate edition of the “Silvarum libri quinque.” Lond. 1728, 4to. Among the attempts at English translation, we may mention Lewie’s version of “ The Thebaid of Statius,” Oxford, 1767, 2 vols. 8vo.</p><p>STATUARY, a branch of sculpture, employed in the making of statues. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sculpture</hi>.</p><p>STATUE, is defined to be a piece of sculpture in full relievo, representing a human figure. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scülpture.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>