<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:34:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SPAIN.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Τηε</hi> kingdoms of Spain and Portugal together form what is called the Pyrenean Peninsula, the most southerly, and at the same time the most westerly, portion of Europe. Ex cept on the northeast, where it is connected with the rest of Europe by an isthmus about one hundred miles in breadth, this peninsula is wholly surrounded by the ocean. Spain, which occupies by far the greater part of it, has for its boundaries on the south and southeast the Mediterranean Sea ; on the west, partly the long and narrow territory of Portugal, partly the Atlantic Ocean ; on the north, the Bay of Biscay ; and on the northeast the Pyrenees, a chain holding the second rank among the mountains of Europe, and forming a well-defined line of separation between France and Spain.</p><p>That the Peninsula was peopled at a very early period seems abundantly certain, but by whom it would be vain to inquire. The traditions which ascribe its colonization to Tubal, the grandson of Noah, may be allowed to repose undisturbed in the obscurity of the chronicles in which they are embodied. The earliest inhabitants whom his tory makes known to us were the Iberians, a race probably of Asiatic origin. At some period lost in the depths of antiquity, the Celts, amid their widespread migrations, penetrated into the Peninsula ; but we are still ignorant how they entered the country, and whence they came, al though these subjects have been matter of keen disputation. The two nations appear at first to have contended for the sovereignty of the soil, but finally to have amalgamated, to have shared the country between them, and, as a united people, to have assumed the compound name of Celtiberians. They were split into numerous tribes or clans, each of which occupied its own particular territory.</p><p>The delightful climate which Spain enjoys, the fertility of its soil, and the mines of gold, silver, and iron, by which it is enriched, proved powerful attractions to the Rhodians and Phoenicians, who established colonies in the country at a very early period. But the Carthaginians were the people who obtained the firmest footing in it. Availing themselves of the pretext of commerce, they frequented the coast of Cadiz, where they succeeded in erecting fortresses, dwell inghouses, temples, and buildings where business was transacted ; and pushing their conquests into the interior as well as along the coast, they at length made themselves masters of the whole of Bætica or Andalusia, employing force when artifice failed. The Spaniards were roused to make resist ance, but it was too late. Hamilcar, father of Hannibal, succeeded in overrunning a considerable part of the coun try, and bringing it, at least nominally, under subjection to Carthage, 238 years before the birth of Christ. He extend ed his conquests towards Murcia, Valencia, and Catalonia, in the latter of which provinces he founded the city of Barcelona. This conqueror having perished in a battle fought with some of the native tribes, was succeeded by his son inlaw Asdrubal, who built the port of New Carthage, now called Carthagena. The rapid strides which the Cartha ginians had made towards the total subjugation of the Peninsula, aroused the fears of the Greek colonies situated on the coast of Catalonia and Valencia, and alarmed those tribes in the interior who still stoutly maintained their independence. Too weak to make head against Carthage themselves, they applied to the Romans for assistance. This great nation had long regarded with a jealous eye the growing prosperity of its rival Carthage, and eagerly em braced the cause of the discontented states. In the character of ally and protector, Rome sent a deputation to Car thage, and obtained from its senate two important con</p><p>cessions ; that the Carthaginians should not extend their conquests beyond the Ebro ; and that they should not dis turb the Saguntines and the other Greek colonies. But these conditions, although agreed to, did not correspond with the gigantic designs which Asdrubal had formed. The Romans, fully aware of the vast riches which the Car thaginians drew from Spain, and of the immense value of such a country to themselves in prosecuting their own am bitious schemes of foreign conquest, had entered into close alliance with some of the discontented tribes, no doubt with the ulterior view of subjecting them to their own domination. Saguntum, one of the most flourishing cities of the Peninsula, was one of these allies of Rome ; and Asdrubal, in the prosecution of his design of subduing the whole of Spain before Rome could send succours to the confederates, collected a considerable force and marched against this city. On his way, however, he was assassinated by a slave ; but the chief command passed into still abler hands, those of the renowned Hannibal. This famous Car thaginian was then in his twentyfifth year, and greatly es teemed for his valour and his talents. After having con quered the kingdom of Toledo, he besieged Saguntum with his whole force, which is said to have amounted to 150,000 men. The Romans lost much time in fruitless attempts at negociation, and failed to send prompt succour to its faithful ally. The consequence was, that after a vigorous defence, the Saguntines were so reduced by hunger and fa tigue, that they retired from the walls into the centre of the city, where they amassed all their valuable effects, and every thing combustible, into one vast pile. Placing their wives and children around it, they themselves issued from the gates and plunged sword in hand into the midst of the Carthaginians. The slaughter was prodigious on both sides, but in the end the Saguntines were cut off almost to a man. No sooner was their fate known in the city than their wives set fire to the pile, and precipitated themselves and their children into the devouring element. Thus perished Sa guntum, one of the largest and most flourishing cities of Spain ; and its destruction may be regarded as the opening of the second Punic war. Of the contests carried on be tween the Carthaginians and the Romans, till the final sub jugation of the former, and the consequent incorporation of its territories with the Roman empire, an account will be found under the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Carthage</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Roman History</hi>. We shall only in this place notice such leading events as are necessary to give clearness and connection to our nar rative.</p><p>Two centuries were required by Rome to effect the total subjugation of Spain, that is, from the first invasion of the country by Cneus Cornelius Scipio in the year 218 <hi rend="smallcaps">b. c., </hi>till the last tribes, the Cantabrians and Asturians, laid down their arms to Augustus in the year 19 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c. No other conquest had cost Rome so much. The numbers who perished in the field of battle, and the amount of treasure sacrificed, are not to be calculated. At the same time, scarcely any other acquisition was productive of so much advantage to the state, from the inexhaustible riches of the country. After the destruction of the Carthaginian power in Spain, this country was regarded as a Roman province, received the name of Hispania, and was divided by the senate into Cite rior and Ulterior, or Hither and Farther; the Ebro serv ing as a boundary between the two. Each of these was governed by a prætor, annually appointed by Rome. The extortions of these functionaries very soon became so op pressive to the natives, that they at last resolved on attempting to rid themselves of their unprincipled rulers. Viria</p></body></text></TEI>