<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:35:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>field, but took shelter in their fortified places, the war was protracted for upwards of ten years. The Helotes were at last reduced to their former misery ; and the Messenians were obliged to leave Peloponnesus, on pain of being likewise made slaves. These poor people were then received by the Athenians, who granted them Naupactus for their residence, and afterwards brought them back to a part of their own country, from whence in the course of the Peloponnesian war they had driven the Spartans.</p><p>The Peloponnesian war commenced in the year 431 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c.; but for its details we must refer to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Attica</hi>. This war ended most unfortunately for the Athenians ; for their city was taken and dismantled. Thus were the Spar tains raised to the highest pitch of glory ; and in the reign of Agesilaus, they seemed to be on the point of subverting the Persian empire. But here their good fortune and their views of empire were suddenly checked. Agesilaus had carried on the war in Asia with the greatest success ; and as he would hearken to no terms of accommodation, a Per sian governor named Tithraustes, having first attempted in vain to bribe the king, dispatched Timocrates the Rhodian with fifty talents into Greece, in order to try whether he could there meet with any persons less incorruptible than the Spartan monarch. This agent found many who inclined to accept his offers ; particularly in Thebes, Corinth, and Argos. By distributing the money in a proper manner, he inflamed the inhabitants of these three cities against the Spartans ; and the Thebans listened to his terms with the greatest readiness. They saw that their antagonists would not of their own accord break with any of the states of Greece, and did not choose to begin the war themselves, because the chiefs of the Persian taction were unwilling to be accountable for the event. For this reason they persuaded the Locrians to invade a small district which lay in dispute betwixt the Phocians and themselves. The Phocians accordingly invaded Locris ; the Locrians applied to the Thebans, and the Phocians to the Spartans. The latter were glad of an opportunity of breaking with the Thebans ; but met with a much warmer reception than they expected. Their old general Lysander, who had reduced Athens, was defeated and slain, along with a thousand of his soldiers. On this disaster Agesilaus was recalled, and was obliged to relinquish all hopes of conquering the Persians. His re turn changed the fortune of the war so much, that all the states began to grow weary of a contest from which nobody derived any advantage except the king of Persia. In a short time a treaty was concluded, known in history by the name of the peace of Antalcidas. The terms of this treaty were highly disadvantageous and dishonourable to the Greeks ; for even the Spartans, though successful in Greece, had lost a great battle at sea with the Persian fleet under Conon the Athenian, and this event entirely broke their power in Asia.</p><p>By the peace of Antalcidas, the government of Boeotia was taken from the Thebans, which they had for a long time enjoyed ; and they were so much provoked, that at first they absolutely refused to accede to the treaty ; but as Agesilaus made great preparations to invade them, they at last thought proper to comply. It was not however long be fore a new war commenced, which threatened the total sub version of the Spartan state. As, by the peace of Antalcidas, the king of Persia had in a manner guaranteed the sovereignty of Greece to Sparta, this republic very soon be gan to exercise its power to the utmost extent. The Mantineans were the first who felt the weight of their resent ment, although they had been their allies and confederates. In order to find a pretext for making war against them, they commanded them to quit their city, and to retire into five old villages, which, they said, had served their forefathers, and where they would live in peace themselves, and give no umbrage to their neighbours. As they refused to obey,</p><p>an army was sent against them to besiege their city. The siege was continued through the summer with very little success on the part of the Spartans ; but having during the winter season dammed up the river on which the city stood, the water rose to such a height, as either to overflow or throw down the houses ; and the Mantineans were thus compelled to submit to the terms prescribed to them, and to retire into the villages. The Spartan vengeance next fell on the Phliasians and Olynthians, whom they forced to come into such measures as they thought proper. After this they assailed the Thebans, and, by attempting to seize on the Piræum, drew the Athenians also into the quarrel. But here their career was arrested : the Thebans had been taught the art of war by Chabrias the Athenian ; so that even Agesilaus himself took the command of the Spartan army in vain. At sea they were defeated by Timotheus the son of Conon ; and by land the battle of Leuctra put an end to the superiority which Sparta had retained over Greece for nearly five hundred years.</p><p>After this dreadful defeat, the Spartans had occasion to exert all their courage and resolution. The women and nearest relations of those who were killed in battle, instead of spending their time in lamentations, shook each other by the hand, while the relations of those who had escaped from the battle hid themselves among the women ; or if they were obliged to go abroad, they appeared in tattered clothes, with their arms folded, and their eyes fixed on the ground. It was a law among the Spartans, that such as fled from battle should be degraded from their honours, should be constrained to appear in garments patch ed with divers colours, to wear their beards half-shaved, and without resistance to suffer any to beat them who pleased. At present however this law was suspended ; and Agesilaus, by his prudent conduct, kept up the spirits of the people, at the same time that by his skill in military affairs he check ed the progress of the enemy. Yet, during the lifetime of Epaminondas the Theban general, the progress of the war was greatly to the disadvantage of the Spartans ; but he being killed at the battle of Mantinea, all parties soon became desirous of peace. Agesilaus did not long survive ; and with him, we may affirm, perished the glory of Sparta. Soon after this all the states of Greece fell under the power of Alexander the Great ; and the Spartans, as well as the rest, having become corrupt, and lost their martial spirit, became a prey to domestic tyrants, and to foreign invaders. They however maintained their ground with great resolution against the celebrated Pyrrhus king of Epirus; whom they repulsed for three days successively, though not without assistance from one of the captains of Antigonus. Soon after this, one of the kings of Sparta named Agis, perceiving the universal degeneracy that had taken place, made an attempt to restore the laws and discipline of Lycurgus, by which he supposed the state would be restored to its former glory. But though at first he met with some appearance of success, he was in a short time tried and condemed by the ephori as a traitor to his country. Cleomenes, however, who ascended the throne in 216 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.</hi> c. accomplished the reformation which Agis had in vain attempted. He suppressed the ephori ; cancelled all debts; divided the lands equally, as they had been in the time of Lycurgus ; and put an end to the luxury which prevailed among the citizens. But at last he was overborne by the number of enemies which surround ed him; and being defeated in battle by Antigonus, he fled to Egypt, where he put an end to his own life. With him perished every hope of retrieving the affairs of Sparta : the city for the present fell into the hands of Antigonus; after which a succession of tyrants gained and lost the ascendency, till at last all disturbances were ended by the Romans, who reduced Greece to the condition of a pro vince.</p><p>It only remains to make some observations on the cha</p></body></text></TEI>