<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T17:36:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SRI PERMATURA, a town of the south of India, in the province of the Carnatic, celebrated as the birthplace of Rama Anuja Acharya, the great Brahmin saint and re former, and the founder of a sect. He preached successfully against the doctrines of the Joins and the Boodhists. Long. 80. 2. E. Lat. 12. 59. N.</p><p>STABAT MATER, a musical composition upon the La tin text of a sacred cantata, beginning with these words. Pergolesi, Jomelli, and Haydn, have each set these words to music in an admirable manner.</p><p>STADE, a town of the kingdom of Hanover, in the pro vince of Bremen, of which province it is the capital. It stands on the river Schwinge, which falls into the Elbe about one mile below the town, whence large vessels must load and discharge by the aid of river craft. Stade, which was once fortified, contains the provincial courts of law and boards of administration. It contains 5350 inhabitants, who are occupied as brewers, distillers, manufacturers of coarse woollen and hosiery, and in equipping ships for the whale fishery. Opposite the town a Hanoverian ship of war is stationed, which collects a small toll on each vessel that passes upwards to Hamburg or Altona. Lat. 53. 36. 5. Long. 9. 18. 10. E.</p><p>STADIUM, an ancient Greek measure, containing 125 geometrical paces, or 625 Roman feet, corresponding to our furlong. The Greeks usually measured distances by stadia, which they called <hi rend="italic">σταδιασμος.</hi> Stadium also signified the course on which their races were run.</p><p>STADTHOLDER, formerly the principaI magistrate or governor of the Seven United Provinces. This office is now abolished, and that of king substituted.</p><p>STAFF, an instrument ordinarily used to rest on in walking. The staff is also frequently used as a kind of natural weapon, both of offence and defence, and for several other purposes.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Staff</hi>, a light pole erected in different parts of a ship, for hoisting the colours.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Staff</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> five lines, on which, with the intermediate spaces, the notes of a song or piece of music are marked.</p><p>STAFFA, one of the Hebrides or Western Islands of Scotland, remarkable for its basaltic pillars. It was visited by Sir Joseph Banks, who communicated the following ac count of it to Mr. Pennant: “ The little island of Staffa lies on the west coast of Mull, about three leagues north-east from Iona, or Icolumbkill : its greatest length is about an English mile, and its breadth about half a one. On the east side of the island is a small bay where boats generally land, a little to the southward of which the first appearance of pillars is to be observed ; they are small ; and instead of being placed upright, lie down on their side, each forming a segment of a circle. From thence you pass a small cave, above which the pillars, now grown a little larger, are in dining in all directions: in one place in particular, a small mass of them very much resembles the ribs of a ship. From hence having passed the cave, which, if it is not low water, you must do in a boat, you come to the first ranges of pillars, which are still not above half as large as those a little beyond. Over against this place is a small island, called in Erse <hi rend="italic">Boo-sha-la,</hi> separated from the main by a channel not many fathoms wide. The whole island is composed of pillars without any stratum above them ; they are still small, but by much the neatest formed of any about the place.</p><p>“ The first division of the island, for at high water it is divided into two, makes a kind of a cone, the pillars con verging together towards the centre : on the other they are in general laid down flat : and in the front next to the main, you see how beautifully they are packed together, their ends coming out square with the bank which they form. All these have their transverse sections exact, and their surfaces</p><p>smooth, which is by no means the case with the large ones, which are cracked in all directions. I must question, how ever, if any part of this whole island of Boo-sha-la is two feet in diameter.</p><p>“ The main island opposite to Boo-sha-la, and farther to wards the northwest, is supported by ranges of pillars pretty erect, and though not tall, (as they are not uncover ed to the base), of large diameters ; and at their feet is an irregular pavement, made by the upper sides of such as have been broken off, which extends as far under water as the eye can reach. Here the forms of the pillars are apparent; these are of three, four, five, six, and seven sides ; but the numbers of five and six are by much the most prevalent. The largest I measured was of seven; it was four feet five inches in diameter.</p><p>“ The surfaces of these large pillars, in general, are rough and uneven, full of cracks in all directions ; the transverse figures in the upright ones never fail to run in their true directions. The surfaces upon which we walked were often flat, having neither concavity nor convexity ; the larger number, however, was concave, though some were very evidently convex. In some places, the interstices within the perpendicular figures were filled up with a yellow spar : in one place, a vein passed in among the mass of pillars, carrying here and there small threads of spar. Though they were broken and cracked through in all directions, yet their perpendicular figures might easily be traced: from whence it is easy to infer, that whatever the accident might have been that caused the dislocation, it happened after the formation of the pillars.</p><p>“ From hence proceeding along shore, you arrive at Fingal’s Cave. Its dimensions I have given in the form of a table :</p><table><row><cell>Length of the cave from the rock without,</cell><cell><p>Feet.</p><p>371</p></cell><cell><p>In.</p><p>6</p></cell></row><row><cell>From the pitch of the arch, ,</cell><cell>250</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Breadth of ditto at the moutb,</cell><cell>53</cell><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>At the farther end,</cell><cell>20</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Height of the arch at the moutb,</cell><cell>117</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>At the end,</cell><cell>70</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Height of an outside pillar,</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Of one at the northwest corner,</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Depth of water at the moutb,	.</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>At the bottom,</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table><p>“ The cave runs into the rock in the direction of north east-by-east by the compass.</p><p>“ Proceeding farther to the northwest, you meet with the highest ranges of pillars, the magnificent appearance of which is past all description. Here they are bare to their very bases, and the stratum below them is also visible : in a short time it rises many feet above the water, and gives an opportunity of examining its quality. Its surface is rough, and has often large lumps of stone sticking in it as if half immersed : itself, when broken, is composed of a thousand heterogeneous parts, which together have very much the appearance of a lava; and the more so, as many of the lumps appear to be of the very same stone of which the pillars are formed. This whole stratum lies in an inclined position, dipping gradually towards the southeast. As bere abouts is the situation of the highest pillars, I shall mention my measurements of them, and the different strata in this place, premising, that the measurements were made with a line held in the hand of a person who stood at the top of the cliff, and reaching to the bottom ; to the lower end of which was tied a white mark, which was observed by one who stayed below for the purpose : when this mark was set off from the water, the person below noted it down, and made signal to him above, who made then a mark in his rope: whenever this mark passed a notable place, the same signal was made, and the name of the place noted down as before : the line being all hauled up, and the distances between the marks measured and noted down, gave, when compared</p></body></text></TEI>