<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0144-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0150.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REVENUE</label>
the annual income a perfon receives from the rent of his lands, houſes, intereſt of money in the ſtocks, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Royal Revenue,</hi> that which the Britiſh conſtitution hath veſted in the royal perſon, in order to ſupport his dignity and maintain his power ; being a portion which each ſubject contributes of his property, in order to ſecure the remainder. This revenue is either <hi rend="italic">ordinary</hi> or <hi rend="italic">extraordinary.</hi></p><p>I. The king’s <hi rend="italic">ordinary</hi> revenue is ſuch as has either ſubliſted time out of mind in the crown.; or elfe has been granted by parliament, by way of purchaſe or exchange for ſuch of the king’s inherent hereditary revenues as were found inconvenient to the ſubject.— In faying that it has ſubfiſted time out of mind in the χrown, we do not mean that the king is at pre</p><p>ſent in the actual poſſeſſion of the whole of his revenue. Much (nay the greateſt part) of it is at this day in the hands of ſubjects ; to whom it has been grant-ed out from time to time by the kings of England : which has rendered the crown in ſome meafure dependent on the people for its ordinary ſupport and ſub-fiſtenee. So that we muſt be obliged to recount, as part of the royal revenue, what lords of manors and other ſubjects frequently look upon to be their own abſolute rights ; becaufe they and their anceſtors are and have been veſted in them for ages, though in reality originally derived from the grants of our ancient princes.</p><p>1. The firſt of the king’s ordinary revenues, which may be taken notice of, is of an ecclefiaſtical kind (as are alfo the three ſucceeding ones), viz. the cuſtody of the temporalities of biſhops. See Temporalities.</p><p>2. The king is entitled to a corody, as the law calls it, out of every biſhopric ; that is, to fend one of his chaplains to be maintained by the biſhop, or to have a penfion allowed him till the biſhop promotes him to a benefice. This is alfo in the nature of an acknowledgement to the king, as founder of the ſee, fince he had formerly the ſame corody or penfion from every abbey or priory of royal foundation. It is ſuppofed to be now fallen into total diſuſe } though Sir Matthew Hale fays, that it is due of common right, and that no preſcrip-tion will diſcharge it.</p><p>3. The king alfo is entitled to all the tithes ari-fing in extraparochial places : though perhaps it may be doubted how far this article, as well as the laſt, can be properly reckoned a part of the king’s own royal revenue ; fince a corody ſupports only his chaplains, and thefe extraparochial tithes are held under an im-plied truſt that the king will diſtribute them for the good of the clergy in general.</p><p>4. The next branch confiſts in the firft-fru⅛s and tenths of all ſpiritual preferments in the kingdom. See Tenths.</p><p>5. The next bιanch of the king’s ordinary revenue (which, as well as the ſubſequent branches, is of a lay or temporal nature) conſiſts in the rents and profits of the demeſne lands of the crown. Theſe demefne lands, <hi rend="italic">terra dominicales refits,</hi> being either the ſhare reſerved to the crown at the original diſtribution of landed property, or ſuch as came to it afterwards by forfeitures or other means, were anciently very large and exten-five ; comprifing divers manors, honours, and lord-ſhips ; the tenants of which had very peculiar privi-leges, when we ſpeak of the tenure in ancient demeſne. At prefent they are contracted within a very narrow compaſs, having bcen almoſt entirely granted away to private ſubjects. This has occafioned the parliament frequently to interpole ; and particularly after King william III. had greatly impoveriſhed the crown, an act paſſed, whereby all future grants or leaſes from the crown for any longer term than 31 years or three lives, are declared to be void ;■ except with regard to houſes, which may be granted for 50 years. And no rever-fionary leaſe can be made, ſo as to exceed, together with the eſtate in being, the ſame term of three lives or 31 years ; that is, when there is a ſubfiſting leafe, of which there are 20 years ſtill to come, the king can-not grant a future intereſt, to commence after the ex-piration of the former, for any longer term than 11</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0145" facs="gri_33125011196389_0151.tif"/>
<p>years. The tenant muſt alſo be made liable to be puniſhed for committing waſte ; and the uſual rent muſt be reſerved, or, where there has uſually been no rent, one-third of the clear yearly value. The misfor-'tune is, that this act was made too late, after almoſt every valuable poffeffion of the crown had been granted away for ever, or elfe upon very long leafes ; but may be of benefit to poſterity, when thoſe leaſes come to expire.</p><p>6. Hither might have been referred the advantages which were uſed to ariſe to the king from the profits of his military tenures, to which moſt lands in the kingdom were ſubject, till the ſtatute 12 Car. II. c. 24. which in great meaſure aboliſhed them all. Hither al-ſo might have been referred the profitable prerogative of purveyance and pre-emption : which was a right en-joyed by the crown of buying up proviſions and other fteceſſaries, by the intervention of the king’s purveyors, for the uſe of his royal houſehold, at an appraiſed va-luation, in preference to all others, and even without conſent of the owner : and alſo of forcibly impreſſing the carriages and horſes of the ſubject, to do the king’s buſinefs on the public roads, in the conveyance of tim-ber, baggage, and the like, however inconvenient to the proprietor, upon paying him a fettled price. A prerogative which prevailed pretty generally thrβugh-out Europe during the ſcarcity of gold and filver, and the high valuation of money confequential thereupon. In thoſe early times, the king’s houſehold (as well as thoſe of inferior lords) were ſupported by fpecific ren-ders of corn, and other victuals, from the tenants of the reſpective demeſnes; and there was alſo a continual market kept at the palace-gate to furniſh viands for the royal ufe. And this anſwered allpurpoſes, in thoſe ages of ſimplicity, fo long as the king’s court conti-nued in any certain place. But when it removed from one part of the kingdom to another (as was formerly very frequently done), it was found neceſſary to fend purveyors beforehand, to get together a ſufficient quantity of proviſions and other neceſſaries for the houſehold: and, leſt the unuſual demand ſhould raiſe them to an exorbitant price, the powers beforementioned were veſted in 'theſe purveyors ; who in proceſs of time very greatly abuſed their authority, and became a great oppreſſion to the ſubject, though of little advantage to the crown ; ready money in open market (when the royal reſidence was more permanent, and fpecie began to be plenty) being found upon experience to be the beſt proveditor of any. wherefore, by degrees, the powers of purveyance have declined, in foreign coun-tries as well as our own : and particularly were aboliſh-ed in Sweden by Guſtavus Adolphus, towards the be-ginningof the laſt century. And, with us in England, having fallen into diſuſe during the fuſpenſion of monarchy, King Charles, at his refloration, conſented, by the lame ſtatute, to reſign entirely thoſe branches of his revenue and power: and tb.e parliament, in part of recompenfe, fettled on him, his heirs, and ſucceſſcrs, for ever, the hereditary exciſe of 15d. per barrel on all beer and ale fold in the kingdom, and a proportionable ſum for certain Other liquors. So that this hereditary txcife now forms the ſixth branch of his majeſty’s or-dinary revenue.</p><p>7. A ſeventh branch might alſo be computed to have</p><p>arifen from wine-Iicences ; or the rents payable to the crown by ſuch perfems.as are licenſed to fell wine by retail throughout Britain, except in a few privileged places. Thefe were firſt fettled on the crown by die ſtatute 12 Car. II. c. 25. and, together with the hereditary exciſe, made up the equivalent in value for the loſs ſuſtaſhed by the prerogative in the abolition of the military tenures, and the right of pre-emption and purveyance : but this revenue was aboliſhed by the ſta-tute 30 Geo. II. c. 19∙ and an annual ſum of upwards of L. 7000 <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> iſſuing out of the ncw ſtamo-duties impofed on wine-licences, was fettled on the crown in its ſtead.</p><p>8. An eighth branch of the king’s ordinary revenus is uſually reckoned to conſiſt in the profits ariſing ſrom his foreſts. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Forest.</hi> Theſe conſiſt principally in the amercements or fines levied for offences againſt the foreſhlaws. But as few, if any, courts of this kind for levying amercements have been held fince 1632, 8 Char. I. and as, from the accounts given of the pro-ceedings in that court by our hiſtories and law-books, nobody would wiſh to ſee them again revived, it is need-leſs to purſue this inquiry any farther.</p><p>9. The profits ariſing from the king’s ordinary courts of juſtice make a ninth branch of his revenue. And theſe conſiſt not only in fines impoſed upon offenders, forfeitures of recognizances, and amercements levied upon defaulters ; but alſo in certain fees due to the crown in a variety of legal matters, as, for ſetting the great feal to charters, original writs, and other forenſic proceedings, and for permitting fines to be levied of lands in order to bar entails, or otherwiſe to inſure their title. . As none of thefe can be done without the immediate intervention of the king, by himſelf or his officers, the law allows him certain perquiſites and pro-fits, as a recompenfe for the trouble he undertakes for tlie public. Theſe, in proceſs of time, have been al-moſt all granted out to private perſons, or elſe appropriated to certain particular ufes : ſo that, thouoſh our law proceedings are ſtill loaded with their pΓy-ment, very little of them is now returned into the king s exchequer ; for a part of whofe royal maintenance they were originally intended. All future grants of them, however, by the ſtatute 1 Ann. ft. 2. c. 7. are to endure for no longer time than the prince’s life who grants them.</p><p>10. A tenth branch of the king's ordinary revenue, ſaid to be grounded on the conſideration of his guard, ing and protecting the feas. from pirates and robbers, is the right to <hi rend="italic">royalfifih,</hi> which are whale andſturgeon: and theſe, when either thrown aſhore, or caught near the coaſts, are the property of the king, on account of their fuperior excellence. Indeed, our anceſtors feem to have entertained a very high notion of the im-portance of this right ; it being the prerogative of the kings of Denmark and the dukes of Normandy j and from one of theſe it was probably derived to our princes.</p><p>11. Another maritime revenue, and founded partly upon the ſame reaſon, is that of <hi rend="smallcaps">shipwrecks.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">wreck.</hi></p><p>12. A twelfth branch of the royal revenue, the right to mines, has its original from the king’s prerogative of coinage, in order to ſupply him with materials ; and</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0146" facs="gri_33125011196389_0152.tif"/>
<p>therefore thoſe mines which are properly royal, and to which the king is entitled when found, are ^nly thoſe of ſilver and gold. See Mine.</p><p>13. To the fame original may in part be reſerrcdthe revenue of treaſure-trove. See <hi rend="italic">TKKΛsuRK-Trove.</hi></p><p>14. waifs. See waif.</p><p>15. Eſtrays. See Estray.</p><p>Beſides the particular reafons, given in the different articles, why the king ſhould have the ſeveral revenues of royal fiſh, ſhipwrecks, treaſure-trove, waifs, and eſtrays, there is alfo onc general reaſon which holds for them all ; and that is, becauſe they are <hi rend="italic">bona vacantia,</hi> or goods in which no one elſe can claim a property. And, therefore, by the law of nature, they be-longed to the firſt occupant or finder; and ſo continued under the imperial law. But, in ſettling the modern eonſtſtutions of moſt of the governments in Europe, it was thought proper (to prevent that ſtrife and contention which the mere title of occupancy is apt to create and continue, and to provide for the ſupport of public authority in a manner the leaſt burdenſome to individuals) that theſe rights ſhould be annexed to the ſu-preme power by the pofitive laws of the ſtate. And io it came to paſs, that, as Bracton expreſſes it, " hæc, " quæ nullius in bonis ſunt, et olim fuerunt inventons " de jure naturali, jam efficiuntur principis de jure gen-" tium.”</p><p>16. The next branch of the king’s ordinary revenue conſiſts in forfeitures of lands and goods for offences ; <hi rend="italic">bona confiſcata,</hi> as they are called by the civilians, be-caufe they belonged to the <hi rend="italic">fiβus</hi> or imperial treaſury ; or, as our lawyers term them,ybrh <hi rend="italic">ſacta,</hi> that is, ſuch whereof the property is gone away or departed from the owner. The true reaſon and only ſubſtantial ground oſ any forfeiture for crimes, conſiſt in this ; that all property is derived from ſociety, being one of thofe civil rights which are conferred upon individuals, in ex-change for that degree of natural freedom which every man muſt ſacrifice when he enters into ſocial communities. If, therefore, a member of any national community violates the fundamental contract of his affirmation, by tranfgreſſing the municipal law, he forfeits his right to ſuch privileges as he claims by that con-tract ; and the ſtate may very juſtly reſume that portion of property, or any part of it, which the laws have before affigned him. Henςe, in every offence of an atrocious kind, the laws of England have exacted a total confifcation of the moveables or perſonal eſtate ; and, in many caſes, a perpetual, in others only a temporary, lpfs of the offender’s immoveables or landed property ; and have veiled them both in the king, who is the perſon ſuppoſed to be offended, being the one viſible magiſtrate in whom the majeſty of the public re-ſides. See Forfeiture and Deodand.</p><p>17. Another branch of the king’s ordinary revenue arifes from eſcheats of lands, which happen upon the defect of heirs to ſucceed to the inheritance ; where-upon they in general revert to and veſt in the king, who is eſteemed, in the eye of the law, the original pro-prietor of all lands in the kingdom.</p><p>18. The laſt branch of the king’s ordinary revenue, conſiſts in the cuſtody of idiots, from whence we ſhall be naturally led to cυnlider alſo the cuſtody of lunatics. See Idiot and Lunatic.</p><p>This may ſuffice for a ſhort view of the king’s <hi rend="italic">ordi</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">nary</hi> revenue, or the proper patrimony of the crown j which was very large formerly, and capable of being increaſed to a magnitude truly formidable : for there are very few eſtates in the kingdom that have not, at ſome period or other ſince the Norman conqueſt, been veſted in the hands of the king, by forfeiture, eſcheat, or otherwiſe. But, fortunately for the liberty of the ſubject, this hereditary landed revenue, by a ſeries of improvident management, is funk almoſt to nothing ; and the caſual profits, ariſing from the other branches of the <hi rend="italic">cenfus regalis,</hi> are likewiſe almoſt all of them alienated from the crown. In order to ſupply the deficiencies of which, we are now obliged to have recourfe to new methods of railing money, unknown to our early anceſtors ; which methods conſtitute.</p><p>„ II. The king’s <hi rend="italic">extraordinary</hi> revenue. For, the public patrimony being got into the hands of private ſubjects, it is but reaſonable that private contributions ſhonld ſupply the public ſervice. which, though it may perhaps fall harder upon ſome individuals, whoſe anceſtors have had no ſhare in the general plunder, than upon others, yet, taking the nation .throughout, it amounts to nearly the ſame ; provided the gain by the extraordinary ſhould appear to be no greater than the loſs by the ordinary revenue. And perhaps, if every gentleman in the kingdom was to be ſtripped of ſuch of his lands as were formerly the property of the crown, was to be again ſubject to the inconveniences of purveyance and pre-emption, the oppreſſion of fo∙ reſt-laws, and the ſlavery of <hi rend="sup">,</hi> feodal-tenures ; and was to reſign into the king’s hands all his royal franchiſes of waifs, wrecks, eſtrays, treaſure-trove, mines, deo-dands, forfeitures, and the like ; he would find himſelf a greater loſer than by paying his <hi rend="italic">quota</hi> to ſuch taxes as are neceſſary to the ſupport oſ government. The thing, therefore, to be wiſhed and aimed at in a land of liberty, is by no means the total abolition of taxes, which would draw after it very pernicious con-ſequences, and the very fuppoſition of which is the height of political abfurdity. For as the true idea of government and magiſtracy will be found to conſiſt in this, that ſome few men are deputed by many others to preſide over public affairs, ſo that individuals may the better be enabled to attend their private concerns ∙, it is neceſſary that thoſe individuals ſhould be bound to contribute a portion of their private gains, in order to ſupport that government, and reward that magiſtracy, which protects them in the enjoyment of their reſpective properties. But the things to be aimed at are wiſdom and moderation, not only in granting, but alfo in the method of raiſing, the neceſſary fiιpplies j by contriving to do both in ſuch a manner as may be moſt coducive to the national welfare, and at the ſame time moſt conſiſtent with economy and the liberty of the ſubject ; who, when properly taxed, contributes only, as was before obſerved, ſome part of his property in order to enjoy the reſt.</p><p>Theſe extaordinary grants are ufually called by the ſynonymous names of <hi rend="italic">aids, fubfidies,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ſupplies ;</hi> and are granted by the commons of Great Britain, in par-liament aſſembled. See Parliament and Tax.</p><p>The clear nett produce of the ſeveral branches of the revenue, after all charges of collecting and ma-nagement paid, amounted in the year 1786 to about L. I5&gt;397&gt;∞Q Sterling, whſte the expcnditure was.</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0147" facs="gri_33125011196389_0153.tif"/>
<p>found to be about I.,. 14,477,-000, How theſe immenſe ſums are appropriated, is next to be conſidered. And this is, firſt and principally, to the payment of the intereſt of the national debt. See <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> NÀtionai Debt</hi></hi> and Funds.</p><p>The reſpective produces of the ſeveral taxes were originally ſeparate and diſtinct funds ; being ſecurities for the ſums advanced on each ſeveral tax, and for them only. But at laſt it became neceſſary, in order to avoid confuſion, as they multiplied yearly, to reduce the number of theſe ſeparate funds, by uniting and blending them together ; fuperadding the faith of parliament for the general ſecurity of the whole. So that there are now only three capital funds of any account, the <hi rend="italic">aggregate</hi> fund, and the <hi rend="italic">general</hi> fund, ſo called from ſuch union and. addition ; and the <hi rend="italic">South-Sea</hi> fund, being the produce of the taxes appropriated to pay the intereſt of ſuch part of the national debt as was advanced by that company and its annuitants, whereby the ſeparate funds, which were thus united, are become mutual ſecurities for each other; and the whole produce of them, thus aggregated, liable to pay ſuch intereſt or annuities as were formerly charged upon each diſtinct fund : the faith of the legiſlature being moreover engaged to ſupply any caſual deficiencies.</p><p>The cuſtoms, exciſes, and other taxes, which are to ſupport theſe funds, depending on contingencies, upon exports, imports, and conſumptions, muſt neceſſarily be of a very uncertain amount ; but they have always been conſiderably more than was ſufficient to anſwer the charge upon them. The ſurpluſſes, therefore, of the three great national funds, the aggregate, general, and Boutlι-Sea funds, over and above the intereſt and annuities charged upon them, are directed by ſtatute 3 Geo. I. c. 7- to be carried together, and to attend the difpoſition of parliament ; and are uſually denominated <hi rend="italic">Ùscfinking fund,</hi> becauſe originally deſtined to fink and lower the national debt. To this have been ſince added many other entire duties, granted in fubſequent years ; and the annual intereſt of the ſums borrowed on their refpective credits is charged on, and payable out of, the produce of the ſinking fund. However, the nett ſurpluſſes and ſavings, after all deductions paid, amount annually to a very conſiderable fum. For as the intereſt on the national debt has been at ſeveral times reduced (by the conſent of the proprietors, who had their option either to lower their intereſt or be paid their principal), the ſavings from the appropriated revenues muſt needs be extremely large.</p><p>But, before any part of the aggregate fund (the ſurpluſſes whereof are one of the chief ingredients that form the ſinking fund) can be applied to diminiſh the principal of the public debt, it ſtands mortgaged by parliament to raiſe an annual ſum for the maintenance 'of the king’s houſchold and the civil liſt. For this purpoſe, in the late reigns, the produce of certain branches of the exciſe and cuſtoms, the poſt-office, the duty on wine-licences, the revenues of the remaining crown-lands, the profits ariſing from courts of juſtice, (which articles include all the hereditary revenues of the crown), and alſo a clear annuity of L. 120,000 in money, were fettled on the king for life, for the ſupport of his majeſty’s houſehold, and the honour and dignity of the crown. And, as the amount of theſe ſeveral branches was uncertain, (though in the laſt reign they were computed to have⅛bmetimes raiſed almoſt a million), if they did not ariſe annually to L. 800,000, the parliament engaged to make up the deficiency. But his preſent majeſty having, fυoα after his acceffion, ſpon-taneouſly ſignified his conſent that his own hereditary revenues might be ſo diſpoſed of as might beſt conduce to the utility and fatisfaction of the public, and having graciouſly accepted a limited fum, the ſaid hereditary and other revenues are now carried into, and made a part of, the aggregate fund ; and the aggregate fund is charged with the payment of the whole annuity to the crown. The limited annuity accepted by his pre-ſent majeſty was at firſt L. 800,000, but it has been ſince augmented to L. 900,000. The expences them-felves, being put under the ſame care and management as the other branches of the public patrimony, produce more, and are better collected than heretofore ; and the public is a gainer of upwards of L. 100,000 <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi> by this diſintereſted bounty of his majeſty.</p><p>I he finking fund, though long talked of as the laſt reſource of the nation, proved very inadequate to the purpoſe for which it was eſtabliſhed. Miniſters found pretences for diverting it into other channels ; and the diminution of the national debt proceeded ſlowly during the intervals of peace, whilſt each ſucceeding war increaſed it with great rapidity. To remedy this evil, and reſtore the public credit, to which the late war had given a conſiderable ſhock, Mr Pitt conceived a plan for diminiſhing the debt by a fund, which ſhould be rendered unalienable to any other purpoſe. In the feffion 1786, he moved that the annual ſurplus of the revenue above the expenditure ſhould be raiſed, by additional taxes, ſrom L. 900,000 to one million Sterling, and that cer* tain commiſſioners ſhould be veiled with the full power of difpoſing of this fum in the purchaſe of ſtock (ſee Funds), for the public, in their own names. Theſe commiſſioners ſhould receive the annual million by quarterly payments of L. 250,000, to be iſſued out of the exchequer before any other money, except the intereſt of the national debt itſelf ; by theſe proviſions, the fund would be ſecured, and no deficiencies in the na-tional revenues could affect it, but ſuch muſt be fepa~ rately provided for by parliament.</p><p>The accumulated compound intereſt on a million yearly, together with the annuities that would fall into that fund, would, he ſaid, in 28 years amount to ſuch a ſum as would leave a furplus of four millions annually, to be applied, if neceſſary, to the exigencies of the ſtate. In appointing the commiſſioners, he ſhould, he faid, endeavour to choofe perſons of ſuch weight and ' character as correſponded with the importance of the commiſſion they were to execute. The fpeaker of the houfe of commons, the chancellor of the exchequer, the maſter of the rolls, the governor and deputy governor of the bank of England, and the accountant-general of the high court of chancery, were perſons who, from their feveral ſituations, he ſhould think highly proper to be of the number.</p><p>To the principle of this bill no objection was madej though ſeveral ſpecious but ill-founded ones were urged againſt the ſufficiency of the mode which the chancellor of the exchequer had adopted for the accompliſhment. of fo great and ſo deſirable an end. He had made it a clauſe in his bill, that the accumulating million ſhould never be applied but to the purchaſe of ſtock. To this clauſe Mr Fox objected, and moved that the commit-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0148" facs="gri_33125011196389_0154.tif"/>
<p>fioners therein named ſhould be impowered to accept fo much of any future loan as they ſhould have caſh be-longing to the public to pay for. This, he ſaid, would relieve that diſtreſs the country would otherwiſe be under, when, on account of a war, it might be ncceſſary to raiſe a new Ioan : whenever that ſhoiſid be the caſe, his opinion was, that the miniſter ſhould not only raiſe taxes ſufficiently productive to pay the intereſt of the· loan, but alſo ſufficient to make good to the finking, fund whatſoever had been taken from it.</p><p>If, therefore, for inſtance, at any future period a loan of fix millions was propoſed, and there was at that time one million in the hands of the commiſſioners, in fuch caſe they ſhould take a million of the loan, and the <hi rend="italic">bonus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">douceur</hi> thereupon ſhould be received by them for the public. Thus government would only have five millions to borrow inſtead of fix ; and from ſueh a mode of proceeding, he ſaid, it was evident great benefit would ariſe to the public.</p><p>This claule was received by Mr Pitt with the ſtrcngeſt marks of approbation, as was likewiſe another, moved by Mr Pulteney, enabling the commiſſioners named in the bill to continue purchafing ſtock for the public when· it is above par, unleſs otherwiſe directed by parliament, with theſe additional clauſes the bill was read a third-time on the 15th of May, and carried up to the Lords, where it alfo paſſed without meeting with any material oppoſition, and afterwards received the royal aſſent.</p><p><hi rend="sup">r</hi> Γhe operation of this bill ſurpaſſed perhaps the mi-niſter’s moſt ſanguine expectation. The fund was ably managed, and judiciouſly applied ; and in 1793 the commiſſioners had extinguiſhed ſome millions of■ the public debt. The war, however, into which the nation was that year involved, and of which there is yet no cer-tain proſpect of a near end, has made it neceſlary to bor-row additional ſums, ſo large, that .many years of peace muſt elapſe before the operation of the fund can contribute ſenſibly. to the relief of the people. The clear produce of the taxes raiſed on the people of this.country was, in the year; 1792, very near L.. 17,000,oco ; and it muſt henceforth, from the accumulation of the debt, and the enormous expence of the prefent war, be neceſſarily rendered greater.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Revenue,</hi> in hunting, a fleſhy lump formed chiefly by a cluſter of whitiſh worms on the head of the deer, ſuppoſed to occafion the caſting of their horns by gnaw-ing them at the root.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>