<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0142-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0148.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RETREAT</label>, in a military ſenſe. An army or body of men are ſaid to retreat when they turn their backs upon the enemy, or are retiring from the ground they occupied : hence every march in withdrawing from the enemy is called a <hi rend="italic">retreat.</hi></p><p>That which is done in fight of an aélive enemy, who purſues with a ſuperior force, is the moil important part of the ſubject; and is, with reaſon, looked upon as the Ulory of theproſeſſion. It is a manœuvre the moſt delicate, and the propereſt to diſplay the prudence, genius, courage, and addrefs, of an officer who commands: the hiſto-rians of all ages teſtify it ; and hiſtorians have never been ſo laviſh of eulogiums as on the ſubject of the brilliant retreats of our heroes. If it is important, it is no leſs difficult to regulate, on account of the variety of circumſtances, each of which demands different prin-ciples, and an almoſt endlefs detail. Hence a good retreat is eſteemed, by experienced officers, the maſter-pieee of a general. He ſhould therefore be well ac-quainted with the fituation of the country <hi rend="sub">-</hi> through which he intends to make it, and careful that nothing is omitted to make it ſafe and honourable. See WAR.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Retreat, is alſo a beat of the drum, at the firing of the evening gun ; at which the drum-major, with all the drums of the battalion, except ſuch as are upon duty, beats from the camp-colours on the right to thoſe on the leſt, on the parade of encampment : the drums of all the guards beat alſo ; the trumpets at the ſame time founding at the head of their refpective troops. This is to warn the ſoldiers to forbear firing, and the centinels to challenge, till the break of day that the reveille is beat. The retreat is likewiſe called</hi> <hi rend="italic">ſetting the watch.</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>