<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0787-03" facs="gri_33125011197759_0795.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RALEIGH</label>
(Sir walter), fourth fon of walter Raleigh, Eſq; of Fardel, in the pariſh of Cornwood in Devonſhire, was born in 1552 at Hayes, in the pariſh of Budley, a farm belonging to his father. About the year 1568, he was ſent to Οπεί college in oxford, where he continued but a ſhort time ; for in the following year he embarked for France, being one of the hundred volunteers, commanded by Henry Champer-non, who, with other Engliſh troops, were ſent by queen Eliſabeth to aſſiſt the queen of Navarre in defending the Proteſtants. In this ſervice he continued for five or ſix years ; after which he returned to Lon-don, and probably reſided in the Middle Temple. But his entcrpriſing genius would not ſuffer him to remain long in a ſtate of inactivity In 1577 or 1578, he embarked for the Low Countries with the troops ſent. by the queen to aſſiſt the Dutch againſt the Spaniards, and probably ſhared the glory of the deciſive victory over Don John of Auſtria in 1578. Οη his return to England, a new enterprife engaged his attention. His half-brother, Sir Humphrey Gilbert, having obtained a patent to plant and inhabit ſome parts of North America, Mr Raleigh embarked in this adventure ; but, meeting with a Spaniſh fleet, after a fraart engagement they returned, without ſucceſs, in 1579.</p><p>The following year, the king of Spain, in conjunc-tion with the pope, having projected a total couqneſt of the Engliſh dominions, ſent troops to Ireland to aſſiſt the Deſmonds in the Munſter rebellion. Raleigh obtained a captain’s commiſſion under Lord Grey of wilton, then deputy of Ireland, and embarked ſor that kingdom ; where, by his conduct and refolution, he was principally inſtrumental in putting an end to the rebellious attempt. He returned to England ; and attract-ed the notice of queen Eliſabeth, owing, as we are told in Naunton’s <hi rend="italic">Fragmenta Regalia,</hi> to the following accidental piece of gallantry. The queen, as ſhe was one day taking a walk, being ſtopped by a <hi rend="italic">plajhy</hi> place in the road, our gallant young ſoldier took off his new pluſh mantle, and ſpread it on the ground. Her ma∙ jeſty trod gently over the fair foot-cloth, ſurpriſed and pleaſed with the adventure. He was a handſome man, and remarkable for his gentility of addreſs.</p><p>The queen admitted him to her court, and employed him firſt as an attendant on the French ambaſſador Si-mier on his return home, and afterward to cſcort the duke of Anjou to Antwerp. During this excurſion he became perſonally known to the prince of orange ; from whom, at his return, he brought ſpecial acknowledgments to the queen, who now frequently converſed with him. But the inactive life of a courtier did not fuit the enterpriſing ſpirit of Mr Raleigh In the ycar 1583, he embarked with h.is brother, Sir Humphrey Gilbert, on a ſecond expedition to Newfoundland, in a ſhip called the <hi rend="italic">Rat'eigh,</hi> which he built at his own ex-pence ; but was obliged to return on account of an in-fectiυus diſtemper on board. He was, however, ſo little affected by this diſappointment, that he now laid before the queen and council a propoſal for exploring the continent of North America; and in 1584 obtained a patent empowering him to poſſeſs ſnch countries as hc ſhould diſcover in that part of the globe. Accordingly Mr Raleigh fitted out two ſhips at his own expence, which ſailed ip the month of April, and returned to England about the middle of September, reporting that they had diſcovered and taken poſſeſſion of a fine country called <hi rend="italic">Windangocoa,</hi> to which the queen gave the name of <hi rend="italic">Virginia.</hi> About this time he was elected knight of the ſhire for the county of Devon, and ſoon aſter received the honour of knighthood ; and to enable him to carry on his deſigns abroad, the queen granted him a patent for licenſing the venders of wine throughout the kingdom. In 1 ,85 he ſent a fleet of ſeven ſhips to virginia, commanded by his relation Sir Richard Greenville, who left a colony at Roanah of 107 perſons, under the government of Mr Lane; and by the eſtabliſhment of this colony he firſt imported tobacco into England. See Nicotiana. In the ſame year Sir walter Raleigh obtained a grant of 12,000 acres bf the forfeited lands in the county of Corke in Ireland.— About the ſame time he was made ſeneſchal of the duchy of Cornwall, and warden of the {tanneries ; and grew into fuch favour w.th the queen, that even Lei-ccſter was jealous of his influence.</p><p>In 1587, he ſent another colony of 150 men to vir-ginia, with a governor, Mr John white, and 12 aſſiſtants. About this time we find our knight diſtinguiſh-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0788" facs="gri_33125011197759_0796.tif"/>
<p>ed by the titles of <hi rend="italic">Captain oſ the queen's guards,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lieutenant general oſ Cornwall.</hi> From this period to the year 1594, he was continually engaged in projecting new expeditions, fending ſuccours to colonies abroad, defending the kingdom from the inſults of the Spani-ards, and tranſacting parliamentary buſineſs, with equal ability and refolution. whilſt thus employed, he was publicly charged, in a libel written by the infamous Jeſuit Parlous, with being an Atheiſt ; a groundleſs and ridiculous imputation. In 1594, he obtained from the queen a grant of the manor of Sherborne in Dor-ſetſhire, where he built a magnificent houſe : but Sir waiter fell under the queen’s diſpleaſure on account of an intrigue with the daughter of Sir Nicholas Throg-morton, one of the maids of honour ; however, he married the lady, and lived with her in great conjugal har-mony. During his diſgrace at court, he projected the conqueſt of Guiana in South America, and in 1595 failed ſor that country ; of which having taken poſſeſſion, after defeating the Spaniards who were ſettled there, he returned to England the ſame year, and ſoon after publiſhed an account <hi rend="sub">k</hi> of his expedition. In the following year he was one of the admirals in the ſucceſs-ful expedition againſt Cadiz, under the command of Howard and the earl of Eſſex ; and in 1597 he failed with the ſame commanders againſt the Azores. Soon after theſe expeditions, we find him aſſiduouſly engaged in parliamentary buſineſs, [and a diſtinguiſhed perſonage in jouſts and tournaments. In 1600 he was ſent on a joint embaſſy with Lord Cobham to Flanders, and at his return made governor of Jerſey.</p><p>Queen Eliſabeth died in the beginning of the year 1603 ; and with her Raleigh’s glory and felicity funk, never to riſe again. Upon the acceſſion of James, Sir walter loſt his intereſt at court, was ſtripped of his preferments, and accuſed of a plot againſt the king. He was arraigned at wincheſter, and, on his trial, inſulted by the moſt ſhockmg brutality by the famous Coke, attorney-general, whoſe ſophiſtical vociferation influen-ced the jury to convict him without the leaſt proof of guilt. After a month’s impriſonment, however, in daily expectation of his execution, he was reprieved, and ſent to the Tower ; and his eſtat es were given to Car, earl of Somerſet, the king’s favourite. During this confine-ment, he wrote many of his moſt valuable pieces, parti-cularly his Hiſtory of the world. In March 1615, after 16 years impriionment, he obtained his liberty, and immediately began to prepare·for another voyage to Guiana. In Auguſt 161 6, the king granted him a very ample commiflion for that purpoſe ; and in July the year following, he failed from Plymouth : but, ſtrange as it may appear, it is moſt certain that the whole ſcheme was revealed to the Spaniards by the king himſelf, and thus neceſſarily rendered abortive.</p><p>He returned to England in 1618, where he was foon after ſeized, imprifoned, and beheaded ; not for any pre-tended miſdemeanor on the late expedition, but in conſequence of his former attainder. The truth of the matter is, he was ſacrificed by the ptiſillanimous monarch to appeaſe the Spaniards ; who, whilſt Raleigh lived, thought every part of their dominions in danger. He was executed in old Palace Yard, and buried in St Margaret’s adjoining, in the ∙66th year of his age. His behaviour on the ſcaſſold was manly, unaffected, cheer-ful, and eaſy. Being aſked by the executioner which</p><p>be right, it is no matter which way the head lies.” He was a man of admirable parts, extenfive knowledge, un- ' daunted reſſoIution, and ſtrict honour and honeſty. He was the author oſ a great many works, ſome of which have not been printed.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>