<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0205-06" facs="gri_33125011196389_0211.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RHEA</label>
AMERlCANA. The American oſtrſch of authors has been frequently mentioned, but till oſ late years very imperfectly known ; being blended by ſome with other genera, although forming oſ itſelſ a diſtinct one, differing in many things from all others. The older writers, however, have kept it ſeparate. It does not occur to us whether any author has figured this bird except <hi rend="italic">Nieremberg,</hi> whoſe repreſentation conveys no juſt idea, which is wonderful, as it is to be met with iu ſufficient plenty in various parts oſ South America ; nor has the bird itſelſ made its appearance in the cabi-nets oſ coliectors, until the one now in the Leverian muſeum.</p><p>M. Bajon, in his <hi rend="italic">Mem. fur Cayenne,</hi> gives a ſigure and deſcription oſ the jabirus, and ſeems clear that this bird is no other than the oſtrich oſ Amenca. From this affertion, Mr Latham, in his <hi rend="italic">Synopßs,</hi> leaves the matter undecided ; but this author, in his <hi rend="italic">Index Qmi-thol.</hi> ſrom having met with the ſpecimen above alluded to, and ſupported in an account oſ its manners given by Molina in his <hi rend="italic">Hſſl. Nat. da Chili,</hi> treats this matter on more certain grounds, ſo as to enable us to give the following deſcription.</p><p>In ſize the American oſtrich is very little inferior to the common one : the bill is Hoped not unlike that of a gooſe, being flat on the top and rounded at the end r the eyes are black, and the lids furniſhed with hairs : the head is rounded, and covered with downy feathers : the neck is two feet eight inches long, and feathered alſo : from the tip of one wing to that of the other extended, the length is eight feet ; but from the want of continuity of the webs of the feathers, and their laxity of texture, the bird is unable to raiſe itſelf from the ground \ it is, however, capable of greatly affiſtiug itſelf by their motion in running, which it does very ſwiftly : the legs are ſtout, hare of feathers above the knees, and ſurniſhed with three toes, all placed forwards, each having a ſtraight and ſtout claw as in the caſſowary ; on the heel is a callous knob, ſerving in place of a back, toe : the general colour of plumage is dull grey mixed with white, inclining to the latter on the under parts : the tail is very lhort, and not conſpicuous, being entirely covered with long looſe and floating feathers, having origin from the lower part of the hack and rump, and entirely covering it : the bill and legs are brown.</p><p>Molina obſerves that this bird varies ; the body in ſome being white, in others black. In reſpect to manners, it is ſaid.to be a general feeder, but more ſond of flies, which it catches with great dexterity, and will alſo, like the common oſtrich, ſwallow bits oſ iron and <hi rend="sup">1</hi> any other traſh offered to it. In common with the oſtrich of the old world, it lays a number of eggs, from. ' 40 to 60, in the fand, cacti of them holding a quart ;</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0206" facs="gri_33125011196389_0212.tif"/>
<p>but ſt differs from that bird in many particulars, eſpe-cially in wanting the calloſity on the ſternum, and ſpars on the wing. AVith theſe laſt the-common oſtrich is known to defend itſelf : in defect of them, the one here treated of uſes the feet with ſuch addreſs as to become at once a furious and dangerous· antagoniſt. The fe-male calls its young ones together with a kind of whii-'tling note fomewhat ſimilar to that of a man: when young it is very tame, frequently following the ſirſt creature it meets with. The fleſh of this bird is ſaid to be very unpalatable. It is found in various parts of South America, from Patagonia to Guiana, and is known by the name of <hi rend="italic">Choique.</hi> "AVe are happy to be able to preſent our readers with an accurate drawing of the bird. See Plate CCCCXXXVII.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>