<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0057-10" facs="gri_33125011196389_0063.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RELEASE</label>
in law, is a diſcharge or conveyance oſ a man’s right in lands or tenements, to another that</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0058" facs="gri_33125011196389_0064.tif"/>
<p>hath ſome former eſtate in poffeffion. The words generally uſed therein are " remiſed, releaſed, and for ever quit-claimed.” And theſe releaſes may enure, either, I. By way of <hi rend="italic">enlarging an eflate,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">enlarger l'efiate :</hi> as, if there be tenant for life or years, re-mainder to another in fee, and he in remainder releaſes all his right to the particular tenant and his heirs, this gives him the eſtate in fee. But in this caſe the releſſee mult be in <hi rend="italic">pofieffion</hi> of ſome eſtate, for the releaſe to work upon ; for if there be leſſee for years, and, before he enters and is in poffeffion, the leſſor releaſes to him all his right in the reverſion, ſuch releaſe is void ſor want of poffeffion in the releſſee. 2. By way of <hi rend="italic">pfifing an efiate,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">mitter l <hi rend="sup">,</hi> eβate :</hi> as, when one of two coparceners rcleaſeth all his right to the other, this paſſeth the fee-ſimple of the whole. And, in both theſe caſes, there muſt be a privity of eſtate between the releſſor and releſſee ; that is, one of their eſtates muſt be ſo related to the other, as to make but one and the ſame eſtate in law. 3. By way of <hi rend="italic">pa[fiηg a right,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">mitter le droit :</hi> as if a man be diſſeifed, and releafeth to his diſſeifor all his right ; hereby the diſſeifor acquires a new right, which changes the quality of his eſtate, and renders that lawful which before was tortious. 4. By way of <hi rend="italic">extinguiſhment :</hi> as if my tenant for life makes a leaſe to A for life, re-mainder to B and his heirs, and I releaſe to A ; this extinguiſhes my right to the reverſion, and ſhall enure to the advantage of B’s remainder as well as of A’s particular eſtate. 5. By way of <hi rend="italic">entry and feoffment :</hi> as if there be two joint diſſeifors, and the diſſeiſee releaſes to one of them, he ſhall be fole feiſed, and ſhall keep out his former companion ; which is the ſame in effect as if the diſſeiſee had entered, and thereby put an end to the diſſeiſin, and afterwards had enfeoffed one of the diſſeifors in fee. And hereupon we may obſerve, that when a man has in himſelf the poſſeſſion of lands, he muſt at the common law convey the free-hold by feoffment and livery ; which makes a noto-riεty in the country : but if a man has only a right or a future intereſt, he may convey that right or intereſt by a mere releaſe to him that is in poſſeſſion of the land : for the occupancy of the releſſee is a matter of lufficient notoriety already.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>