<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0001-01"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0007.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RANA</label> the frog, in zoology; a genus belonging to the order of
                    amphibia reptilia. The body is naked, furniſhed with four feet, and without any
                    tail. Therc are 17 ſpecics. The moſt remarkable are,</p>
                <p>i. The temporaria, or common frog. This is an animal ſo well known, that it
                    needs no defcription; but ſome of its properties are veιy ſingular.</p>
                <p>Its fpring, or power of taking large leaps, is re-markably great, and it is the
                    beſt ſwimmer of all four-footed animals. Nature hath finely adapted its parts
                    for thofe ends, the fore members of 'the body being very lightly made, the hind
                    legs and thighs very long, and furniſhed with very ſtrong mufcles.</p>
                <p>while in a tadpole ſtate, it is entirely a water animal ; the work of generation
                    is performed in that ele-χr&gt;ent, as may be ſeen in every pond during
                    ſpring, when the female remains oppreſſed by the male for a number of days.</p>
                <p>The work of propagation is extremely ſingular, it be-ing certain that the frog
                    has not a <hi rend="italic">penis intrans.</hi> There appears a ſtrong analogy
                    in this caſe between a certain claſs of the vegetable kingdom and thoſe animals
                    ; for it is well known, that when the female frog depofits its ſpawn, the male
                    inſtantaneouſly impregnates it with what we may call a <hi rend="italic">ſarina
                        f∑cundcms,</hi> in the ſame manner as the palm-tree conveys fructification
                    to the flowers of the female, which would otherwiſe be barren.</p>
                <p>As ſoon as the frogs are releaſed from their tadpole ſtate, they immediately
                    take to land ; and if the weather has been hot, and there fall any reſreihing
                    ſhowers, you may fee the ground for a confiderable ſpace perfectly blackened by
                    myriads of theſe animalcules, ſeek-ing ſor ſome ſecure lurking places. Some
                    philoſo-phers, not giving themſelves time to examine into this phenomenon,
                    imagined them to have been generated in the clouds, and ſhowered on the earth ;
                    but had they, like our Derham, but traced them to the next pool, they would have
                    found a better folution of the difficulty. See <hi rend="italic">Preternatural
                        RAiNs.</hi></p>
                <p>As frogs adhere cloſely to the backs of their own fpecies, ſo we know they will
                    do the ſame by fiſh.— walton mentions a ſtrange ſtory of their deſtroying pike ;
                    but that they will injure, if not entirely kill carp, is a fact ⅛difputable,
                    ſrom the following rela-tion. Not many years ago, on fiſhing a pond belong-ing
                    to Mr Pitt of Encomb, Dorſetſhire, great numbers of the carp were found each
                    with a frog mounted on it, the hind legs clinging to the back, and the fore legs
                    fixed in the corner of each eye of the fiſh, which were thin and greatly wafted,
                    teized by carrying ſo diſagrce-able a load. 1 heſe frogs Mr Pennant ſuppoſes to
                    lιave been males diſapppointed of a mate.</p>
                <p>The croaking of frogs is well known ; and from that in fenny countries they are
                    diſtinguiſhed by ludicrous titles : thus they are ſtyled <hi rend="italic">Dutch nightingales,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Boſ-ton waites.</hi></p>
                <p>Yet there is a time of the year when they become mute, neither croaking nor
                    opening their mouths for a whole month : this happens in the hot ſeaſon, and
                    that is in many places known to the country people by tbe name of the <hi
                        rend="italic"> paddock moon.</hi> It is ſaid, that during that period their
                    mouths are ſo cloſed, that no force (without killing the animal) will be capable
                    of opening them.</p>
                <p>Thefe, as well as other reptiles, feed but a final! ſpace of the year. The food
                    of this genus is flies, in-ſects, and fnails. Toads are ſaid to feed alſo on
                    bees, and to do great injury to thoſe uſeful infects.</p>
                <p>During winter, frogs and toads remain in a torpid ſtate : the laſt of which will
                    dig into the earth, and cover themſelves with almoſt the ſame agility as the
                    mole. See Physiology, n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 48 and note (b), and ſh 52.</p>
                <p>2. The eſculenta, or edible frog, differs from the former, in having a high
                    protuberance in the middle of the back, forming a very ſharp angle. Its colours
                    are alſo more vivid, and its marks more diſtinct ; the ground colour being a
                    pale or yellowiſh green, marked with rows of black ſpots from the head to the
                    rump.—. This, and (Mr Pennant thinks) the former, are eaten. He has feen in the
                    markets at Paris whole hampers full, which the venders were preparing for the
                    tab!e, by fkinning and cutting off the fore-parts, the loins and legs only being
                    kept ; but his ſtrong diſlike to theſc reptiles prevented a cloſe exanſhiatioa
                    into the ſpecies,</p>
                <p>3. In the country of Pennſylvania, and fome other parts of North America, there
                    is a very large ſpecies of frogs called the <hi rend="italic">bullfrog,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">rana ocellatd.</hi> Their irides arc of a duſky red,
                    ſurrounded with a yellow ring. The auricles are covered with a thin circular
                    ſkin, which forms a ſpot behind each eye. They have four toes on the fore-feet,
                    and five palmated toes behind. Their co-lour is a duſky brown, mixed with
                    yellowiſh green, and fpotted with black. The belly is yellowiſh, and faintly
                    fpotted. Theſe make a monſtrous roaring noiſe like a bull, only ſomewhat ſhore
                    hoarſe. Their fize is ſuperior to that of any other of the genus, and they can
                    ſpring forward three yards at a leap. By this means they will equal in fpecd a
                    very good horſe in its ſwiſteſt couiſſe. Their places of abode are ponds, or
                    bogs with ſtagnant water ; but they never frequent ſtreams. when many</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0002" facs="gri_33125011196389_0008.tif"/>
                <p>of them are together, they make ſuch a horrid noiſe, that two people cannot
                    underſtand each other’s ſpeech. They croak all together, and then ſtop for a
                    little and begin again. It feems as if they had a captain atno∏g them : for when
                    he begins to croak, all the others iol-low ; and when he ſtops, they alſo become
                    filent. when this captain gives the ſignal for ſtopping, you hear a note like <hi rend="italic">poop</hi> coming from him. In the day-time they ſeldom
                    make any great noiſe, unleſs the ſky is covered ; but in the night-time thcy may
                    be heard at the diſtance of a mile and an half, when they croak, they are
                    commonly near the ſurface of the water, under the buſhes, and have their heads
                    out of the water. By going ſlowly, therefore, one may get up almoſt quite cloſe
                    to <hi rend="sup">3</hi> them before they go away. As ſoon as they are quite
                    under water, they think themſelves fate, though it be ever ſo ſhallow. Theſc
                    creatures kill and eat young ducklings and goſlings, and ſometimes carry off
                    chickens that come too near the water ; when beaten, they cry out almoſt like
                    little children. As ſoon as the air begins to grow a little cool in autumn, they
                    hide them-felves under the mud in the bottom of ſtagnant waters, and lie there
                    torpid during the winter. As ſoon as the weather grows mild towards ſummer, they
                    begin to get out of their holes and croak. They are ſuppoſed by the people
                    ofvirginia to be the purifiers of waters, and are reſpected as the genii of the
                    fountains. Some of them were brought to England alive ſcveral years ago.</p>
                <p>4. The bufo, or toad, is the moſt deformed and hι-deous of all animals. The body
                    is broad ; the back flat, and covered with a pimply duſky hide ; the belly
                    large, ſwagging, and ſwelling out ; the legs ſhort, and its pace laboured and
                    crawling ; its retreat gloomy and filthy : in ſhort, its general appearance is
                    ſuch as to ſtrike one with diſguſt and horror. Yet it is ſaid by thofe who have
                    refolution to view it with attention, that its eyes are fine ; to this it ſeems
                    that Shakeſpeare alludes, when he makes his Juliet remark,</p>
                <p>Some fay the lark and loathed toad change eyes;</p>
                <p>As if they would have been better beſtowed on ſo charming a ſongſter than on
                    this raucous reptile.</p>
                <p>Çut the hideous appearance of the toad is fuch as to make this one advantageous
                    feature overlooked, and to have rendered it in all ages an object of horror, and
                    the origin of moſt tremendous inventions. Ælian makes its venom' ſo potent, that
                    baſiliſk-like it conveyed death by its vcry look and breath ; but Juvenal is
                    content with making the Roman ladies who were weary of their huſhands form a
                    potion from its entrails, in order to get rid of the good man. This opinion
                    begat others of a more dreadful nature ; for in after-times ſu-perſtition gave
                    it preternatural powers, and made it a principal ingredient in the incantations
                    of nocturnal hags.</p>
                <p>This animal was believed by ſome old writers to have a ſtone in its head fraught
                    with great virtues medical and magical : it was diſtinguiſhed by the name of the
                    reptile, and called the <hi rend="italic">toadfione, lιfοηites, era· paudine,
                        kr( <hi rend="sub">j</hi> ttenfictn ;</hi> but all its-fancied powers,
                    vaniſh-ed on the diſcovery· of its.being nothing but the foſſil-tooth of the
                        ſea-wolfe<note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial" n="1">See <hi
                            rend="italic">Anerrbicas.</hi></note>, or of ſome other flat-toothed
                    fiſh, not unfrequeΛt in our iſland as well as feveral other countries. . .</p>
                <p>But theſe fables have been long exploded. And as to the notion of its being a
                    poifonous animal, it is pro· bable that its exceffive deformity, joined to the
                    faculty it has of emitting a juice from its pimples, and a duſky liquid from its
                    hind parts, is the foundation of the report.</p>
                <p>That it has any noxious qualities there feem to have been no proofs in the
                    fmalleſt degree fatisfactory, tho’ we have heard many ſtrange relations on that
                    point.—. Οη the contrary, there have been many who have taken them in their
                    naked hands, and held them long without receiving the leaſt injury : it is alfo
                    well known that quacks have eaten them, and have beſides ſqueezed their juices
                    into a glaſs and drank them with impunity, we may ſay alſo, that tlieſe reptiles
                    are a common food to many animals ; to buzzards, owls, Norfolk plovers, ducks,
                    and ſnakes, who would not touch them were they in any degree noxious.</p>
                <p>Go far from having venomous qualitics, they have of late been confidered as if
                    they had beneficent ones ; particularly in the cure of the moſt terrible of
                    diſeaſes, the <hi rend="italic">cancer,</hi> by ſuction : (See <hi
                        rend="italic"> Britiſh Zoology,</hi> vol. iii. Append, p. 389, <hi
                        rend="italic"> etfiq.)</hi> But, from all circumſtances, as Mr Pennant
                    obſerves, they ſeem only to have ren« dered a horrible complaint more loathſome.</p>
                <p>The moſt full information concerning the nature and qualities of this animal is
                    contained in the following letters from Mr Arſcott and Mr Pittfield to Dr
                    Milles. " It would give me great pleaſure (ſays Mr Arſcott) to be able to inform
                    you of any particulars worthy Mr Pennant’s notice, concerning the toad who lived
                    ſo many years with us, and was ſo great a favourite. Tlie greateſt curioſity in
                    it was its becoming ſo remarkably tame. It had frequented ſome ſteps before the
                    hall-door ſome years before my acquaintance commenced with it, and had been
                    admired by my father for its ſize (which was of the largeſt I ever met with),
                    who conſtantly paid it a viſit every evening. I knew it mylelf above 30 years ;
                    and by conſtantly feeding it, brought it to be ſo tame, that it always came to
                    the candle, and looked up as if expecting to be taken up and brought upon the
                    table, where I always fed it with infects of all forts ; it was fondeſt of fleſh
                    maggots, which I kept in bran ; it would follow them, and, when within a proper
                    diſtance, would fix its eye, and remain motionlefs for near a quarter of a
                    minute, as if preparing for the ſtroke, which was an inftantaneous throwing its
                    tongue at a great diſtance upon the inſect, which ſtuck to the tip by a
                    glutinous matter : the motion is quicker than the eye can follow<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2">This rapid capture of
                        its prey might give occaſion to the report of its faſcinating powers,
                        Linnæus ſays, <hi rend="italic">Insecta in fauces fasinο
                        revocat.</hi></note>.</p>
                <p>"I always imagined that the root of its tongue was placed in the forepart of its
                    under jaw, and the tip to-wards its throat, by which the motion muſt be a half
                    circle ; by which, when its tongue recovered its fituation, the inſect at the
                    tip would be brought to the place ot deglutition. I was confirmed in this by
                    never obſerving any internal motion in its mouth, excepting one&gt; ſwallow
                    the inſtant its tongue returned. Poſſibly I might be miſtaken ; for I never
                    diffected one, but con-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0003" facs="gri_33125011196389_0009.tif"/>
                <p>tented myſelf with opening its mouth, and ſlightly in-ſpecting it.</p>
                <p>" You may imagine, that a toad, generally deteſted, (although one of the moſt
                    inoffenſive of all animals), ſo much taken notice of and befriended, excited the
                    curioſity of all comers to the houſe, who all deſired to ſee it fed ; ſo that
                    even ladies ſo far conquered the hor-rors inſtilled into them by nurſes, as to
                    deſire to ſee it. This produced innumerable and improbable reports, making it as
                    large as the crown of a hat, &amp;c. &amp;c.”</p>
                <p>The following are anſwers from the ſame gentleman to fome queries propoſed by Mr
                    Pennant.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Firfi,</hi> I cannot ſay how long my father had been
                    acquainted with the toad before I knew it ; but when I firſt was acquainted with
                    it, he uſcd to mention it as the old toad I’ve known ſo many years ; I can
                    anſwer for 36 years.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Secondly,</hi> No toads that I ever ſaw appeared in the
                    winter ſeaſon. The old toad made its appearance as ſoon as the warm weather
                    came, and I always con-cluded it retired to ſome dry bank to repoſe till the
                    ſpring. AVhen we new-lay <hi rend="sup">,</hi> d the ſteps, I had two holes
                    made in every third ſtep, with a hollow of more than a yard long for it, in
                    which I imagine it ſlept, as it came from thence at its firſt appearance.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Thirdly,</hi> It was ſeldom provoked: neither that toad, nor
                    the multitudes I have ſeen tormented with great cruelty, ever ſhowed the leaſt
                    deſire of revenge, by ſpitting or emitting any juice from their pimples.—
                    Sometimes, upon taking it up, it would let out a great quantity of clear water,
                    which, as I have often feen it do the ſame upon the ſteps when quite quiet, was
                    certainly its urine, and no more than a natural evacuation.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fourthly,</hi> A toad has no particular enmity for the
                    ſpider ; he uſed to eat five or fix with his millepedes (which I take to be its
                    chief food) that I generally provided for it before I found out that fleſh
                    maggots, by their continual motion, was the moſt tempting bait ;</p>
                <p>but, when offered, it eat blowing flies and humble bees that come from the
                    rat-tailed maggot in gutters, or in ſhort any inſect that moved. I imagine, if a
                    bee was to be put before a toad, it would certainly eat it to its coſt ; but as
                    bees are ſeldom ſtirring at the ſame time that toads are, they can ſeldom come
                    in their way, as they ſeldom appear after ſun-riſing or before ſun-ſct. In the
                    heat of the day they will come to the mouth of their hole, I believe, for air. I
                    once from my parlour window obſerved a large toad I had in the bank of a
                    bowling-green, about 12 at noon, a very hot day, very buſy and active upon the
                    grafs ; ſo uncommon an appearance made me go out to ſee what it was, when I
                    found an innumerable fwarm of winged ants had drop-ped round his hole, which
                    temptation was as irreſiſtible as a turtle would be to a luxurious alderman.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Fifthly,</hi> whether our toad ever propagated its
                    fpecies, I knφw not ; rather think not, as it always appeared well, and not
                    leſſened in bulk, which it muſt have done, I ſhould think, if it had diſcharged
                    ſo large a quantity of ſpawn as toads generally do. The females that are to
                    propagate in the ſpring, I imagine, inſtead of retiring to dry holes, go into
                    the bottom of ponds, and lie torpid among the weeds : for to my great furprife,
                    in the middle of the winter, having for amufement put a long pole into my pond,
                    and twiſted it till it had gathered a large volume of weed, on taking it off I
                    found many toads ; and having cut ſome aſunder with my knife, by accident, to
                    get off the weed, found them full of ſpawn not thoroughly formed. I am not
                    pofitive, but think there were a few males in March ; I know there are 30 males
                        <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="3">Mr John Hunter
                        has aſſured me, that during his reſidence at Belleiſle, he diſſected ſome
                        hundreds of toads, yet never met with a ſingle female among them. </note> to
                    one female, 12 or 14 of whom I have ſeen clinging round a female : I have often
                    diſengaged her, and put her to a ſolitary male, to fee with what eagerneſs he
                    would ſeize her. They impregnate the ſpawn as it is drawn <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="4"><p>I was incredulous as to the <hi
                                rend="italic"> obfietrical</hi> offices of the male toad; but fince
                            the end is ſo well accounted for, and the fact eſtabliſhed by ſuch good
                            authority, belief muſt take place.</p>
                        <p>Mr Demours, in the Memoirs of the French Academy, as tranſlated by Dr
                            Templeman, vol. i. p. 371, has been very particular in refpect to the
                            male toad as acting the part of an <hi rend="italic">accoucheur :</hi> His account is curious, and claims a place here.</p>
                        <p>" In the evening of one of the long days in fummer, Mr Demours, being in
                            the king’s garden, perceived two toads <hi rend="italic">coupled
                                together</hi> at the edge of an hole, which was formed in part by a
                            great ſtone at the top.</p>
                        <p>“ Curioſity drew him to ſee what was the occaſion of the motions he
                            obſerved, wheβ <hi rend="sub">1</hi> two facts equally new ſurpriſed
                            him. The <hi rend="italic">firfi</hi> was the extreme difficulty the
                            female had in laying her eggs, inſomuch that ſhe did not ſeem capable of
                            being delivered of them without ſome aſſiſtance. The <hi rend="italic">fecond</hi> was, that the male was mounted on the back of the
                            female, and exerted all his ſtrength with his hinder feet in puffing out
                            the eggs, whilſt his forefeet embraced her breaſt.</p>
                        <p>“ In order to apprehend the manner of his working in the delivery of the
                            female, the reader muſt obſerve, that the paws of theſe animals, as well
                            thoſe of the fore-feet as of the hinder, are divided into ſeveral toes,
                            which can perform the office of fingers.</p>
                        <p>" It muft <hi rend="sup">t</hi> be remarked likewiſe, that the eggs of
                            this ſpecies of toads are included each in a membranous coat that is
                            very firm, in which: is contained the embryo ; and that theſe eggs,
                            which are oblong and about two lines in length, being faſtened one to
                            another by a ſhort but very ſtrong cord, form a kind of chaplet, the
                            beads of which are diſtant from each other about the half of their
                            length, lt is by drawing this cord with his paw that the male pcrforms
                            the function of a midwife, and acquits himſelf in it with a dexterity
                            that one would not expect from fo Jumpiſh an animal.</p>
                        <p>" The preſence of the obſerver did not a little diſcompoſe the male :
                            ſor ſome time he ſtopped ſhort, and threw on the <hi rend="italic">curious impertinent</hi> a fixed look that marked his diſquietneſs
                            and fear ; but he ſoon returned to his work with more precipitation than
                            before, and a moment after he appeared undetermined whether he ſhould.
                            continue it or not. The female likewiſe diſcovered her uneaſineſs at the
                            fight of the ſtranger, by motions that interrupted fometimes the male in
                            his operation. At length, whether the ſilence and ſteady poſture of the
                            fpe-tator had diſſipated their fear, or that the <hi rend="italic">caſe</hi> was urgent, tee male reſumed his work with the ſame vigour, and
                            ſuccefsfully performed his function.” </p></note> out in long ſtrings,
                    like a necklace, many yards long, not in a large quantity of jelly, like frogs
                    fpawn.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0004" facs="gri_33125011196389_0010.tif"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Sixthly,</hi> Infects being thctr food, I never ſaw any
                    toad ſhow any liking or diſlike to any plant <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="5">Thia queſtion aroſe from an aſſertion
                        of Linnaeus, that the toad delighted in filthy herbs. <hi rend="italic">Delectatur co-tula, actna, Jiach∖&lt;ιle fcetide.</hi> The unhappy
                        deformity of the animal ſeems to be the only ground of this as vveli as
                        another miſreprefentation, of its conveying a poiſon with its pimples, its
                        touch, and even its. breath» <hi rend="italic">Vtrru^ t¢ iacteſcentes
                            vcnena!x infufi% tactu <hi rend="sub">i</hi> anhelitν, </hi></note>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">" Seventhly,</hi> 1 hardly remember any perfops taking it up
                    except my father and myielf ; 1 do not know whether it had any particular
                    attachment to us.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Eighthly,</hi> In reſpect to its end, I anſwer this laſt
                    query. Had it not been for a tame raven, I make no doubt but it would have been
                    now living ; who one day feeing it at the month of its hole, pulled it out, and
                    although I reſcued it, pulled out one eye, and hurt it ſo, that notwithſtanding
                    its living a twelvemonth it never enjoyed itſelf, and had a difficulty of taking
                    its food, miffing the mark for want of its eye : before that accèdent it had all
                    the appearance of perfect health.”</p>
                <p>6. The rubeta, or natter-jack, frequents dry and fan-dy places : it is found on
                    Putney common, and alſo near Reveſhy abbey, Lmcolnſhire. It never leaps, neither
                    does it crawl with the flow pace of a toad, but its motion is liker to running.
                    Several are found commonly together, and like others of the genus they appear in
                    the evenings. The upper part of the body is of a dirty yellow, clouded with
                    brown, and covered with porous pimples,of unequal ſizes : on the back is a
                    yellow line. The upper fide of the body is of a paler hue, marked with black
                    ſpots, which are rather rough. Οη the fore-feet are four divided toes ; on the
                    hind five, a little webbed. The length of the body is two inches and a quarter;
                    the breadth, one and a quarter: the length of the fore-legs, one inch one-ſixth
                    ; of the hind legs, two inches, we are indebted to Si rJoſeph Banks, for this
                    account.</p>
                <p>7. The pipal, or Surinam toad, is more ugly than even the common one. The body
                    is flat and broad ; the head ſmall ; the jaws, like thoſe of a mole, are
                    extended, and evidently formed for rooting in the ground : tlιe ſkin of the neck
                    forms a fort of wrinkled collar: the colour of the head is of a dark cheſnut,
                    and the eyes are ſmall : the back, which is vcry broad, is of a hghtiſh grey,
                    and feems covered over with a number of ſmall eyes, which are round, and placed
                    at nearly equal diſtances. Theſe eyes are very different from what they ſeem :
                    they are the animal’s eggs, covered with their ſhells, and placed therc for
                    hatching. Thefe eggs are buried deep in the ſkin, and in the beginning of
                    incubation but juſt appear j and are very viſible when the young animal is about
                    to burſt from its confinement. They are of a reddiſh, ihining yellow colour ;
                    and the ſpaces between them are full oſ ſmall warts, reſembling pearls.</p>
                <p>This is their ſituation previous to their coming forth ; but nothing ſo much
                    demands our admiration as the</p>
                <p>manner of their production. The egga, when formed i∏ tſie ovary, are ſent, by
                    ſome internal canals, which anatomiſts have not hitherto deſcribed, to lie aηd
                    come to maturity under the bony ſubſtance of the back : in this ſtate they are
                    impregnated by the male, whoſe ſeed finds its way by pores very ſingularly
                    contrived, and pierces not only the ſkin but the perioſteum : the ſkin, however,
                    is ſtill apparently entire, and forms a very thick covering ever the whole brood
                    ; but as they advance to maturity, at different intervals, one after another,
                    the egg ſeems to ſtart forward, and burgeons from the back, becomes more yellow,
                    and at laſt breaks j when the young one puts forth its head : it ſtill, however,
                    keeps its ſituation until it has acquired a proper degree of ſtrength, and then
                    it leaves the ſhell, but ſtill continues to keep upon the back of the parent. In
                    this manner the pipal is ſeen travelling with her won-derous family on her back,
                    in all the different ſtages of maturity. Some of the ſtrange progeny, not yet
                    come to ſufficient perfection, appear quite torpid, and as yet without life in
                    the egg : others ſeem juſt beginning tts riſe through the ſkin ; here peeping
                    forth from the ſhell, and there having entirely forſaken their priſon ; ſome are
                    ſpprting at large upon the parent’s back, and others defcending to the ground to
                    try their own fortune below. The male pipal is every way larger than the
                    fe-male, and has the ſkin leſs tightly drawn round the body. The whole body is
                    covered with pullules, reſembling pearls ; and the belly, which is of a bright
                    yel-low, ſeems as if it were ſewed up from the throat to the vent,. a feam being
                    ſeen to run in that direction. This animal, like the reſt of the frog kind, is
                    moſt probably harmleſs.</p>
                <p>8. The water frog of Cateſhy has large black eyes* yellow irides, and long limbs
                    : the upper part of the head and body is of a duſky green, fpotted with black ;
                    and from each eye to the noſe is a white line ; and alfi&gt; a yellow line
                    along the ſides to the rump. They fre-quent rivulets and ditches, which they do
                    not quit for the dry land. It is ſaid they will ſpring five or ſix yards at a
                    leap.</p>
                <p>9. The rana arborea, or green tree frog of Cateſhy, is of a ſlender ſhape and
                    bright green colour, marked or» each ſide with a line of yellow : the eyes are
                    black ; the irides yellow ; they have four toes before and five behind ; at the
                    end of each toe there ia a round membrane, concave beneath, and not unlike the
                    mouth of a leech. They lurk under the lower fides of leaves, even of the talleſt
                    trees, and adhere firmly, by means of the membranes at the ends of their toes,
                    {ticking to the ſmootheſt ſurface t a looking-glaſs was held before one,.</p>
                <p></p>
                <p>(d)</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0005" facs="gri_33125011196389_0011.tif"/>
                <p>at fouy yards diſtance ; it reached it at one ieap, and ſtuck cloſely to it. At
                    night theſe frogs make an in-, qeſſant chirping, and leap from fpray to ſpray in
                    ſearch of infects. This ſpecies is common to America and the warmer parts of
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>i o. The land frog of Catefby has much the appearance of a toad; above it is
                    grey or brown, ſpottecſ with duſky; below white, faintly fpotted; the irides are
                    red; and the legs ſhort. They frequent the high-lands, and are ſeen moſt
                    frequently in wet weather and in the hotteſt time of the day : they leap, feed
                    on infects, parti-cularly the fire-fly and ant. Sometimes the Americans bake and
                    reduce this fpecies to powder, which, mixed with υrrice root, is taken as a cure
                    for a tympany.</p>
                <p>11. The cinereous frog has a gibbous, cinereous, and ſmooth back ; the belly is
                    yellow and granulated : on each ſide, from the noſe to the rump, there is a
                    white line ; and there is the ſame on the ontſide of the thighs and legs ; the
                    toes are bullated at their ends. They inhabit Carolina.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
