<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0008-01" facs="gri_33125011196389_0014.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAPHAEL</label>
(D’Urbino), the greateſt, moſt ſublime, and moſt excellent painter that has appeared, ſince the revival of the fine arts, was the ſon of an indifferent painter named <hi rend="italic">Sαnzio,</hi> and was born at Urbi-no on Good Friday 1482. The popes Julius II. and Leo X. who employed him, loaded him with wealth and honour ; and it is ſaid that cardinal De St Bibiana had ſuch a value for him, that he offered him his niece in marriage. His genius is admired in all his pictures ; his contours are free, his ordonnances magnificent, his deſigns correct, his figures elegant, his expreffiυns lively, his attitudes natural, his heads graceful ; in fine, every thing is beautiful, grand, ſublime, juſt, and adorn-ed with graces. Theſe various perfections he derived, not only from his excellent abilities, but from his ſtudy of antiquity and anatomy ; and from the friendſhip he contracted with Arioſto, who contributed not a little to the improvement of his taſte. His pictures are principally to be found in Italy and Paris. That of the Transfiguration, preſerved at Rome in the church of St Peter Monterio, paſſes for his mailer-piece.' He had a handſome perſon, was well proportioned, and had great ſweetneſs of temper ; was polite, affable, and mo-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0009" facs="gri_33125011196389_0015.tif"/>
<p>deft. He, however, lived in the utmoſt ſplendor'; moſt of the eminent maſters of his time were ambitious of working under him 5 and he never went out without a crowd of artiſts and others, who followed him purely through reſpect. He was not only the beſt painter in the world, but perhaps the beſt architect too ; on which account Leo X. charged him with building St Peter’s church at Rome : but he was too much addicted to pleaſure, which occaſioned his death at 37 years ■of age. He left a great number of difciples ; among •whom were Julio Romano and John Francis Pennιζ who were his heirs. Many able engravers, as Raimondi, George Mantuan, and BIoemart, engι aved after Ra-phael. See Painting, p. 595 and 598.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>