<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0200-03"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0206.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>REYNOLDS</label> (Sir Joſhua), the celebrated painter, was, on July the
                    16th 1723, born at Plympton, a fmall town in Devonſhire. His father was miniſter
                    of the pariſh, and alſo maſter of the grammar ſchool ; and being a man of
                    learning and philanthropy, he was beloved and reſpected by all to whom he was
                    known.— Such a man, it will naturally be ſuppofed, was affiduous in the
                    cultivation of the minds of his children, among whom his ſon Joſhua ſhonc
                    conſpicuous, by displaying at a very early period a ſuperiority of genius, and
                    the rudiments of a correct taſte. Unlike other boys, who generally content
                    themſelves with giving a literal explanation of their author, regardleſs of his
                    beauties or his faults, young Reynolds attended to both theſe, difplaying a
                    happy knowledge of what he read^ and entering with ardour into the ſpirit of his
                    author. He diſcovered likewiſe talents for compoſition, and a natural propenſity
                    to drawing, in which his friends and intimates thought him qualified to excel.
                    Emulation was a diſtinguiſhing feature in his mind, wliich his father perceived
                    with the delight natural to a parent ; and deſigning him for the church, in
                    which he hoped that his talents might raife him to eminence, he ſent him to one
                    of the univerſities.</p>
                <p>Soon after this period he grew paffionately fond of painting ; and, by the
                    peruſal of Richardſon’s theory of that art, was determined to make it his
                    profeffion through life. At his own earneſt requeſt, therefore, he was removed
                    to London ; and about the year 1742 be-came a pupil to Mr Hudſon, who, though
                    not himſelf an eminent painter was preceptor to ſeverals who afterwards excelled
                    in the art. One of the ſirſt advices which he gave to Mr Reynolds was to copy
                    carefully Guercino’s drawings. This was done with ſuch ſkill,</p>
                <p>that many of the copies are ſaid to be now preſerved in the cabinets of the
                    curious as the originals of that very great maſter.</p>
                <p>About the year 174.9, Mr IReynolds went to Italy -under the auſpices, and in the
                    company, of the late JLord (then Commodore) Keppel, who was appointed to the
                    command of the .Britiſh ſquadron in the Medi-terranean. in this garden of the
                    world, this magic feat of the arts, he failed not to viſit the fchools of the
                    great maſters, to ſtudy the productions of different ages, and to contemplate
                    with unwearied attention the various beauties which are characteriſtic <hi
                        rend="italic"> ei</hi> each. His labour here, as has been obſerved of
                    another painter, was " the labour of love, not the taſk of the hireling and how
                    much he profited by it is .known to all Europe.</p>
                <p>Having remained about two years in Italy, and ſta-died the language as well as
                    the arts of the country with great ſucceſs, he returned to England, improved by
                    travel and refined bÿ education. On the road to London from the port where he
                    landed, he accidentally found in the inn where he lodged Johnſon’s life oſ
                    Sa-vage ; and was ſo taken with the charms of compoſi-tion, and the maſterly
                    delineation of character diſplay--ed in that performance, that, having begun tp
                    read it while leaning with his arm on the chimney-piece, he continued in that
                    attitude inſenſible of pain till he was hardly able to raiſe his hand to his
                    head. The admiration of the work naturaliy led him to ſeek the acquaintance of
                    its author·, who continued one of his ſincereſt admirers and warmeſt friends,
                    till 1784, when they were ſeparated by the ſtroke of death.</p>
                <p>The firſt thing that diſtinguiſhed him aſter his return to his native country,
                    was a full length portrait of Commodore Keppel ; which in the polite circles was
                    ſpoken of in terms of the higheſt encomium, and tef-tified to what a degree of
                    eminence he had arrived in his profeffion. This was followed by a portrait of
                    Lord Edgecombe, and a few others, which at once introduced him to the firſt
                    buſineſs in portrait painting » and that branch of the art he cultivated with
                    ſuch ſuccefs as will for ever eſtabliſh his fame with all deſcrip-tions of
                    reſined ſociety. Having painted ſome of the ſirſt-rate beauties of the age, the
                    polite world flocked to ſee the graces and the charms of his pencil ; and he
                    ſoon became the moſt faſhionable painter, not only ſu England, but in all
                    Europe. He has indeed preſerved the refemblance of ſo many illuſtrious
                    characters, that we feel the leſs regret for his having left behind him ſo ſcw
                    hiſtorical paintings ; though what he has done in that way ſhows<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> As the lovers of
                        painting may wiſh to have a catalogue of this great maſter’s hiſtorical
                        pieces, we ſubjoin the following from the European Magazine, which we have
                        good reaſon to believe accurate, as the editors of that mifcellany grudge
                        neither trouble nor expence to procure authentic information. Sir Joſhua’s
                        principal hiſtorical pieces, then, are the following : Hope nttrſing Love ;
                        Venus chaſtiſing Cupid for having learned to caſt accounts; Count Ugolino in
                        the dungeon ; the calling of Samuel; Ariadne; a Captain of banditti; Beggar
                        Boy ; a Lady in the character of St /Agnes; Thais; Dionyſius the Areopagite;
                        an infant Jupiter; Maſter Crewe in the character of Henry VIII ; the death
                        of Dido ; a Child aſleep ; Cupid ſſeeping ; Covent Garden Cupid ; Cupid in
                        the Clouds; Cupids painting ; Boy laughing; Maſter Herbert in the character
                        of Bacchus ; Hebe ; Miſs Meyer in the character of Hebe ; Madona, a head ;
                        the Black-guard Mercury ; a little boy (Sa-spuel) praying;
                            and<corr>an</corr> old Man reading ; Love looſing the zone of Beauty ;
                        the Children in the Wood; Cleo<pb/>patra diffolving the Pearl; Garrick in
                        the character of Kitely ; Garrick between Tragedy and Comedy ; Mrs Abingdon
                        in the character of Comedy,; a Child ſurrounded by Guardian Angels ; Miſs
                        Beauclerc in the character of Spenſer’s Una ; Reſignation ; the Ducheſs of
                        Mancheſter in the character of Diana ; Lady Blake in the charaôler of Juno ;
                        Mrs Sheridan in the character of St Cecilia ; Edwin, horn Beattie’s Minſtrel
                        ; the Nativity, hour Cardinal Virtues, and Faith, Hope, and Charity, for the
                        window of New College Chapel, Ox-ford ; the Studious Boy ; a Bacchante ; a
                        daughter of Lord W. Gordon as an Angel ; the Holy Family ; the Cottagers,
                        ſrom Thomfon ; the Veſtal; the Careful Shepherdefs; a Gypſey telling
                        Fortunes; the infant Hercules ſtrangling the Serpent ; the Moufe-trap girl ;
                        Venus ; Cornelia and her Children ; the Bird ; Melancholy; Mrs Siddons in
                        Tragedy ; Head of Lear ; Mrs Talmaſh in the character oſ Miranda, with
                        Prospero and Caliban ; Robin Goodfellow ; Death of Cardinal Beaufort ;
                        Macbeth, with the Caldron of the Witches.</note> him to have been qualified
                    to excel in both departments. The only landſcape, perhaps, which</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0201" facs="gri_33125011196389_0207.tif"/>
                <p>he ever painted, except thofe beautiful and chaſte ones which compofe the back
                    grounds of many of his portraſts, is “ A View on the Thames from Richmond,”
                    which in 1784 was exhibited by the Society for Pro-moting Painting and Deſign in
                    Liverpool.</p>
                <p>In 1764 Mr Reynolds had the merit of being tbe ſirſt promoter of that club,
                    which, having long exiſted without a name, became at laſt diſtinguiſhed by the
                    ap-pellation of the <hi rend="italic">Literary Club.</hi> Upon tbe foundation
                    of the Royal Academy of Painting, Sculpture, and Architecture, he was appointed
                    preſident·; and his ac-knowledged excellence in his profeffion made the
                    appointment acceptable to all the lovers of art. To add to the dignity of this
                    new inſtitution, his majeſty conferred on the preſident the honour of knighthood
                    ; and Sir Joſhua delivered his ſirſt diſcourſe at the opening of the Academy on
                    Januar)' 2. 1769. The merit of that diſcourſe has been univerfally admitted
                    among painters ; but it contains ſome directions reſpecting the proper mode of
                    proſecuting their ſtudies, to which every ſtu-dent of every art would do well to
                    pay attention. “ I would chiefly recommend (ſays he), that an implicit obedience
                    to the <hi rend="italic">rules of art,</hi> as eſtabliſhed by the prac-tice of
                    the great maſters, ſhould be exacted from the young ſtudents. That thoſe models,
                    which have paſſed through the approbation of ages, ſhould be conſidered by them
                    as perfect and infallible guides; as fubjects for their imitation, not tlieir
                    criticiſm. I am confident, that this is tlie only efficacious method of making a
                    progreſs in tlie arts ; and that lie who ſets out with doubting, will find life
                    finiſhed before he becomes maſſer of the rudiments. For it may be laid down as a
                    maxim, that be who begins by preſuming on his own ſenſe, has ended his ſtudies
                    as ſoon as he has commenced them. Every opportunity, therefore, ſhould be taken
                    to dif-countenance that falſe and vulgar opinion, that rules are the fetters of
                    genius. They are fetters only to men of no genius ; as that armour which, upon
                    the ſtrong, becomes an ornament and a defence, upon the weak and iniſhapen turns
                    into a load, and cripples the body which it was made to protect.”</p>
                <p>Each ſucceeding year, on the diſtribution of the prizes, Sir Joſhua delivered to
                    tlie ſtudents a diſcourſe of equal merit with this : and perhaps we do not
                    hazard too much when we ſay, that, from the whole col-lected, the lover of
                    belles lettres and the fine arts will acquire juſter notions oſ what is meant by
                    taſte in ge-r.eral, and better rules for acquiring a correct taſte, than from
                    multitudes of thoſe volumes which have been profeſſedly written on the ſubject.</p>
                <p>In the autumn of 1785 he went to Bruſſels, where he expended about L. 1000 on
                    the purchaſe of paint-ingg, which, having been taken from the different
                    mo-naſterſes and religious houſes in Flanders and Germany, were then expoſed to
                    ſale by tbe command of the Em-peror Joſeph ! Gainſborough and he had engaged to
                    paint each other’s portrait; and the canvas for both being actually ſtretched,
                    Sir Joſhua gave one fitting to his diſtinguiſhed rival ; but, to the regret of
                    every ad-mirer of the art, the unexpected death of the latter pre-vented all
                    further progreſs.</p>
                <p>In 1790 he was anxiouſſy deſirous to procure the vacant profefforſhip of
                    perſpective in the academy for Mr Bonomi, an Italian architect ; but that artiſt
                    not having been yet elected, an affociate was of courſe no academician, and it
                    became neceſſary to raife him to thoſe ſituations, in order to qualify him for
                    being a profeffor. Mr Gilpin being his competitor for the affociateſhip, the
                    numbers on the ballot proved equal, when the preſident by bis caſting vote
                    decided the election in favour of his friend, who was thereby advanced ſo far
                    towards the profeſſorſhip. Soon after this, an academic ſeat be-ing vacant, Sir
                    Joſhua exerted all his influence to ob-tain it for Mr Bonomi ; but finding
                    himſelf outvoted by a majority of two to one, he quitted the chair with great
                    diſſatisſaction, and next day ſent to the fecretary of th&amp;academy a
                    formal reſignation of the office, which for twenty-one years he had filled with
                    honour to himſelf and his country. His indignation, however, ſub-ſiding, he
                    ſuffered himſelf to be prevailed upon to re-turn to the chair, which within a
                    year and a half he was again deſirous to quit for a better reaſon.</p>
                <p>Finding a diſeaſe of languor, occaſioned by an en-largementof the liver, to
                    wliich he had for ſome time been ſubject, increaſe upon him, and daily expecting
                    the total loſs of ſight, he wrote a letter to the academy, inti-mating his
                    intention to reſign the office of preſident on account of bodily infirmities,
                    which difabled him from executing the duties of it to his own ſatisſaction. The
                    academicians received this intelligence with the reſpect-ful concern due to the
                    talents and virtues of their pre-ſident ; and either then did enter, or deſigned
                    to enter, into a refolution, honourable to all parties, namely, that a
                    deputation from the whole body of the academy ſhould wait upon him, jand inform
                    him of their wiſh, that the authority and privileges of the office of preſident
                    might be his during his life ; declaring their willingneſs to permit the
                    performance of any of its duties which might be irkſome to him by a deputy.</p>
                <p>From this period Sir Joſhua never painted more. The laſt effort of his pencil
                    was the portrait of the Honourable Charles James Fox, which was executed in his</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0202" facs="gri_33125011196389_0208.tif"/>
                <p>beſt ſtyle, and ſhows that his fancy, his imagination, and his other great
                    powers in the art which he profeffed, remained unabated to the end of his life,
                    when the laſt touches wcre given to this picture,</p>
                <p>" The hand of Reynolds fell, to rife no more.”</p>
                <p>On Thurſday February tbe 23d 1792, the world was deprived of this amiable man
                    and excellent artiſt at the age of 68 years ; a man than whom no one, according
                    to Johnſon, had paffed through life with more obſervation of men and manners.
                    The ' following character of him is ſaid to be the production of Mr Burke :</p>
                <p>- “ His illneſs was long, but borne with a mild and cheerful fortitude, without
                    the leaſt mixture of any thing irritable or querulous, agreeably to the placid
                    and even tenor of his whole life. He had from the beginning of his malady a
                    diſtinct view of his diffolution, which he contemplated with that entire
                    compoſure which nothing but the innocence, integrity, and uſefulness of his
                    life, and an unaffected ſubmiffion to the will of Providence, could beſtow. In
                    this ſituation he liad every conſolation from family tenderneſs, which his
                    tenderneſs to his family had always merited.</p>
                <p>" Sir Joſhua Reynolds was, on very many accounts, one of the moſt memorable men
                    of his time : Pie was the ſirſt Engliſhman who added the praiſe of the ele-gant
                    arts to the other glories of his country. In tafte, in grace, in facility, in
                    happy invention, and in the richneſs and harmony of colouring, he was equal to
                    the great matters of the renowned ages. In portrait he went beyond them ; for he
                    communicated to that deſcription of the art in which Engliſh artiſts are the
                    moſt engaged, a variety, a fancy, and a dignity, derived from the higher
                    branches, which even thoſe who profeffed them in a ſuperior manner did not ai
                    ways preſerve when they delineated individual nature. His portraits remind the
                    ſpectator of tlie invention of hiſtory and the amenity of landfcape. In painting
                    portraits, he appears not to be raiſed upon that platform, but to de-ſcend to it
                    from a higher ſphere. His paintings illu-ſtrate his leſſons, and his leffons
                    ſeem to be derived from his paintings.</p>
                <p>“ He poffeffed the theory as perfectly as the practice of his art. To be ſuch a
                    painter, he was a profound and penetrating philoſopher.</p>
                <p>" In full happinefs of foreign and domeſtic ſame, admired by the expert in art,
                    and by the learned in ſcience, courted by the great, careffed by ſovereign
                    powers, and celebrated by diſtinguiſhed poets, bis native humility, modeſty, and
                    candour, never forſook him, even on-ſurpriſe or provocation ; nor was the leaſt
                    degree of arrogance or affumption viſible to the maſt ſcrutinizing eye in any
                    part of his conduct or diſcourfe.</p>
                <p>" His talents of every kind—powerful from nature, and not meanly cultivated in
                    letters—his social virtues in all the relations and all the habitudes of life,
                    rendered him the centre of a very great and unparalleled variety of agreeable
                    ſocieties, which will be dissipated by his death. He had too much merit not to
                    excite ſome jealouſy, too much innocence to provoke any enmity. The loſs of no
                    man of his time can be felt with more ſincere, general, and unmixed ſorrow.”
              </p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
