<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0032-15" facs="gri_33125011196389_0038.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RECURVIROSTRA</label>
in ornithology ; a genus belonging to the order of grallæ of Linnaeus, and that of palmipedes of Pennant and Latham. The bill is long, ſubulated, bent back, ſharp and flexible at the point. The feet are webbed, and furniſhed with three toes forwards, and a ſhort one behind. Mr Latham notes of this genus three fpecies, viz. the Avofetta, or the one commonly known, the Americana, and the Alba. This laſt, it is probable, has ſome affinity to the -Americana. The recurviroſtra avoſetta is about the ſize of a lapwing in body, but has very long legs. The fubſtance of the bill is foft, and almoſt membranous at its tip ; it is thin, weak, ſlender, compreffed horizontally, and incapable of defence or effort. Thefe birds are variegated with black and white, and during the win-ter are frequent on the eaſtern ſhores of Great Britain. They viſit alſo the Severn, and ſometimes the pools of Shropſhire. They feed on worms and infects, which they ſcoop out of the fand with their bills. They lay two eggs, white, with a greeniſh hue, and large ſpots of black ; theſe eggs are about the ſize of a pigeon’s.— They are found alſo in various parts of the continent of Europe, in Ruſſia, Denmark, and Sweden, but they are not numerous. They are alſo found in Siberia, but oftener about the ſalt lakes of the Tartarian deſert, and about <hi rend="sup">r</hi> the Caſpian ſea. They are found likewiſe on the coaſts of Picardy in France in April and November, and at orleans, but rarely. In breeding-time they are very plentiful on the coaſts of Bas Poictou. They do not appear to wander farther ſouth in Europe than</p><p>Italy, whether from timidity or addreſs, the avoſet ſhuns ſnares, and is not eaſily taken. The American avoſet is rather larger and longer than the laſt. The bill is ſimilar, and its colour black : the forehead is duſky white : the head, neck, and upper part of the breaſt, arc of a deep cream-colour : the lower parts of the neck behind white : the back is black, and the uιf-der parts from the breaſt pure white : the wings are partly black, partly white, and partly aſh-coloured. Theſe birds inhabit North America, and were found by Dampier in Shark’s Bay, on the coaſt of New Holland. See Plate CCCCXXXV.</p><p>Tlie recurviroſtra, or ſcolopax alba, is about 14 inches and a quarter long, its colour white, the inferior coverts of its wings duſkiſh, its bill orange, its legs brown. Edwards remarks, that the bill of this bird is bent upwards, as in the avoſet ; its bill black at the tip, and orange the reſt of its length ; all the plumage is white,</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0033" facs="gri_33125011196389_0039.tif"/>
<p>except a tint of yellowiſh on the great quills of the wing and of the tail. Edwards ſuppoſes, that the whiteneſs is produced by the cold climate of Hudſon’s Bay, from which he received it, and that they reſume their brown feathers during the ſummer. It appears that ſeveral ſpecies of this bird have ſpread further into A-merica, and have even reached the fouthern provinces : for Sloane found our third ſpecies in Jamaica ; and Fernandez ſeems to indicate two of them in New Spain, by the names <hi rend="italic">chiquatototl</hi> and <hi rend="italic">elototαtl ;</hi> the former being like our woodcock, and the latter lodging under the ſtalks of maize.</p><p>A bird of this kind, Mr Latham ſays, was ſent ſrom Hudſon’s Bay, and from the figure, has every appear-ance of an avoſet : however, in Edwards’s plate, the toes appear cloven to the bottom ; a circumſtance ſeeming to overturn the fuppoſition, and only to be authen-ticated when other ſpecimens ſhall have come under the eye of the well-informed naturaliſt.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>