<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>number of their ſhips embarraſſing them in a place ſo ſtrait and narrow, their courage ſoon abated; which the Greeks obſerving, uſed such efforts, that in a ſhort time breaking into the Perſian fleet, they entirely diſordered them; ſome flying towards Phalarus, where their army lay encamped; others ſaving themſelves in the harbours of the neighbouring iſlands. The Ionians were the firſt that betook themſelves to flight. But Queen Artemiſia diſtinguiſhed herſelf above all the reſt, her ſhips being the laſt that fled: which Xerxes obſerving, cried out that the men behaved like women, and the women with the courage and intrepidity of men. The Athenians were ſo incenſed againſt her, that they offered a reward of 1o, ooo drachmas to any one that ſhould take her alive: but ſhe, in ſpite of all their efforts, got clear of the ſhips that purſued her, and arrived ſafe on the coaſt of Aſia. In this engagement, which was one of the moſt memorable actions we find recorded in hiſtory, the Grecians loſt 40 ſhips; and the Persians 200, beſides a great many more that were taken, with all the men and ammunition they carried.</p><p>The iſland of Salamis is of a very irregular ſhape; it was reckoned 70 or 80 ſtadia, <hi rend="italic">i. e.</hi> 8 or 10 miles long, reaching weſtward as far as the mountains called <hi rend="italic">Kerata. </hi>or <hi rend="italic">The Horns.</hi> Pauſanias informs us, that on one fide of this iſland flood in his time a temple of Diana, and on the other a trophy for a victory obtained by Themiſtocles, together with the temple of Cyehreus, the ſite of which is now thought to be occupied by the church of St Nicholas.</p><p>The city of Salamis was demoliſhed by the Athenians, becauſe in the war with Caſſander it ſurrendered to the Macedonians, from diſaffection. In the ſecond century, when it was viſited by Pauſanias, ſome ruins of the Agora or market-place remained, with a temple and image of Ajax; and not far from the port was ſhown a ſtone, on which, they related, Telamon ſat to view the Salaminian ſhips on their departure to join the Grecian fleet at Aulis. The walls may ſtill be traced, and  it has been conjectured were about four miles in circumference. The level ſpace within them was now covered with green corn. The port is choked with mud, and was partly dry. Among the ſcattered marbles are ſome with inſcriptions. One is of great antiquity, before the introduction of the Ionic alphabet. On another, near the port, the name of Solon occurs. This renowned lawgiver was a native of Salamis, and a ſtatue of him was erected in the market-place, with one  hand covered by his veſt, the modeſt attitude in which he was accuſtomed to addreſs the people of Athens. An inſcription on black marble was alſo copied in 1676 near the ruin of a temple, probably that of Ajax. The iſland of Salamis is now inhabited by a few Albanians, who till the ground. Their village is called <hi rend="italic">Ampelaki,</hi> the Vineyard, ” and is at a diſtance from the port,  ſtanding more inland. In the church are marble fragments and ſome inſcriptions.</p><p>SALARY, a recompenſe or conſideration made to  a perſon for his pains and induſtry in another man’s  buſineſs. The word is uſed in the ſtatute 23 Edw. III. cap. I. <hi rend="italic">Sαlαrium</hi> at firſt ſigniſied the rents or profits of a ſale, hall, or houſe (and in Gaſcoigne they now call the ſeats of the gentry <hi rend="italic">ſala’s,</hi> as we do <hi rend="italic">halls);</hi> but afterwards it was taken for any wages, ſtipend, or annual allowance.</p><p>SALACIA, in botany; a genus of the trigynia order, belonging to the gynandria claſs of plants. The calyx is quinqueſid; the corolla quinquepetalous; the antherae fitting on the top of the germ.</p><p>SALE, is the exchange of a commodity for money; barter, or permutation, is the exchange of one commodity for another. When the bargain is concluded, an obligation is contracted by the buyer to pay the value, and by the feller to deliver the commodity, at the time and place agreed on, or immediately, if no time be ſpeciſied.</p><p>In this, as well as other mercantile contracts, the ſafety of commerce requires the utmoſt good faith and veracity. Therefore, although, by the laws of England, a fale, above the value of 101. be not binding, unleſs earneſt be paid, or the bargain confirmed by writing, a merchant would loſe all credit who refuſed to perform his agreement, although theſe legal requiſιtes were omitted.</p><p>When a ſpecific thing is fold, the property, even before delivery, is in ſome reſpect veſted in the buyer; and if the thing periſhes, the buyer muſt bear the loſs. For example, if a horſe dies before delivery, he muſt pay the value: but if the bargain only determines the quantity and quality of the goods, without ſpecifying the identical articles, and the ſeller’s warehouſe, with all his goods, be burned, he is intitled to no payment. He muſt alſo bear the loſs if the thing periſh through his fault; or when a particular time and place of delivery is agreed on, if it periſh before it be tendered, in terms of the bargain.</p><p>If a perſon purchaſe goods at a ſhop without agreeing for the price, he is liable for the ordinary market- price at the time of purchaſe.</p><p>If the buyer proves inſolvent before delivery, the feller is not bound to deliver the goods without payment or ſecurity.</p><p>If the importation, or uſe of the commodities fold, be prohibited by law, or if the buyer knows that they were ſmuggled, no action lies for delivery.</p><p>The property of goods is generally preſumed, in favour of commerce, to belong to the poſſeſſor, and cannot be challenged in the hands of an onerous purchaſer. But to this there are ſome exceptions. By the Scots law, ſtolen goods may in all caſes be reclaimed by the proprietor, and alſo by the Engliſh law, unleſs they were bought <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> in open market; that is, in the accuſtomed public places, on ſtated days in the country, or in a ſhop in London; and horſes may be reclaimed, unleſs the ſale be regularly entered by the book-keeper of the market. In all caſes, if the goods be evicted by the lawful proprietor, the ſeller is liable to the purchaſer for the value.</p><p>Actions for payment of ſhop-accounts, as well as other debts not conſtituted by writing, are limited in England to fix years. The teſtimony of one witneſs is admitted; and the ſeller’s books, although the perſian that kept them be dead, are good evidence for one year. In Scotland, merchants books may be proved within three years of the date of the laſt article, by one witneſs, and the creditor’s books and oath in ſupplement. After three years, they can only be proved by the oath or writ of the debtor. A merchant’s books are in all caſes good evidence againſt him.</p><p>SALEP, in the materia medica, the dried root of a ſpecies of orchis. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Orchis.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>