<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SCORIFICATION, in metallurgy, is the art of reducing a body, either entirely or in part, into ſcoria.</p><p>SCORPAENA, in ichthyology, a genus belonging to the order of thoracici. The bead is large and ſharp; the eyes are near each other; there are teeth in the jaws, palate, and fauces; and there are ſeven rays in the membrane of the gill. The ſpecies are three, viz. the <hi rend="italic">porcus, ſcrofa,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">horrida.</hi> According to Mr Willoughby, the ſcorpaena is a fiſh of the anguilliform kind, called by the people of Cornwall f<hi rend="italic">ather-laſher. Scorpaena</hi> is alſo the name of a fiſh caught in many parts of the Mediterranean. It ſeldom grows to more than a pound weight. Its body is long, but not flatted, and is moderately thick. Its head is extremely large, and is armed with prickles, and it grows gradually leſs from thence to the tail. The prickles about the head are accounted venomous, and the fishermen uſually cut them off as ſoon as the fiſh is caught. Its tail is not forked, but rounded at the end. The belly and belly-fins are reddiſh.</p><p>@@SCORPIO, in zoology, a genus of infects belonging to the order of aptera. It has eight feet, beſides two frontal claws; the eyes are eight in number, three on each fide of the thorax, and two on the back. It has two claw-ſhaped palpi, a long jointed tail, with a pointed weapon at the extremity; it has likewiſe two combs ſituated betwixt the breaſt and abdomen. There are ſix ſpecies, all natives of ſouthern climates.</p><p>Of all the claſſes of noxious inſects the ſcorpion is the moſt terrible, whoſe ſhape is hideous, whoſe ſize among the infects is enormous, and whoſe ſting is generally fatal. Happy for Britain, the ſcorpion is entirely a ſtranger among us! In ſeveral parts of the continent of Europe it is but too well known, though it ſeldom grows above four inches long: but in the warm tropical climates, it is ſeen a foot in length, and in every reſpect as large as a lobſter, which it ſomewhat reſembles in ſhape. There have been enumerated nine different kinds of this dangerous infect, including ſpecies and varieties, chiefly diſtinguiſhed by their colour; there being scorpions yellow, brown, and aſh-coloured; others that are the colour of ruſty iron, green, pale yellow, black, claret colour, white, and grey. There are four principal parts diſtinguiſhable in this animal; the head, the breaſt, the belly, and the tail. The ſcorpion’s head ſeems, as it were, jointed to the breaſt; in the middle of which are ſeen two eyes; and a little more forward, two eyes more, placed in the fore part of the head: thoſe eyes are ſo ſmall, that they are ſcarcely perceivable; and it is probable the animal has but little occaſiion for feeing. The mouth is furniſhed with two jaws: the undermoſt is divided into two, and the parts notched into each other, which ſerves the animal as teeth, and with which it breaks its food, and thruſts it into its mouth: theſe the ſcorpion can at pleaſure pull back into its mouth, ſo that no part of them can be ſeen. On each ſide of the head are two arms, each compoſed of four joints; the laſt of which is large, with ſtrong muſcles, and made in the manner of a lobſter’s claw. Below the breaſt are eight articulated legs, each divided into ſix joints; the two hind- moſt of which are each provided with two crooked claws, and here and there covered with hair. The belly is divided into ſeven little rings; from the loweſt</p><p>of which is continued a tail, compoſed of ſix joints, which are briſtly, and formed like little globes, the laſt  being armed with a crooked ſting. This is that fatal inſtrument which renders this infect ſo formidable: it is long, pointed, hard, and hollow; it is pierced near the baſe by two ſmall holes, through which, when the animal ſtings, it ejects a drop of poiſon, which is white, cauſtic, and fatal. The reſervoir in which this poiſon is kept, is in a ſmall bladder near the tail, into which the venom is diſtilled by a peculiar apparatus. If this bladder be greatly preſſed, the venom will be ſeen iſſuing out through the two holes above-mentioned; ſo that it appears, that when the animal ſtings, the bladder is preſſed, and the venom iſſues through the two apertures into the wound.</p><p>We have here given the common account of the ſting of theſe noxious animals; but though we cannot pretend to determine between them, we ſhall lay before our readers the following obſervations from a treatiſe on <hi rend="italic">Tropical Diſeaſes,</hi> &amp;c. by Dr Moſeley of the Chelſea Hoſpital. “Galen juſtly obſerves, that a perſon who had not witneſſed the fact, would not ſuppoſe that ſo ſmall an injury as the ſting of a ſcorpion, or the bite of a poiſonous ſpider, could produce the violent effects which they do in the whole body. He ſays, the aculeus, or ſting, of a ſcorpion ends in the minuteſt point; and has no perforation through which any poiſon can paſs into the wound. Yet, he ſays, we muſt ſuppoſe the venom to be ſome ſpirital ſubſtance, or moiſture, in which a great power is concentrated in a ſmall compaſs. Before I had an opportunity (ſays Dr Moſeley) of examining this ſubject, my reſpect for the opinion of Galen made me doubt the accuracy of Leeuwenhoek, Redi, Mead, and others, who aſſert that there is an aperture near the cuſpis of a ſcorpion’s ſting; and that through this aperture a liquid poiſon is injected when a wound is inflicted. Repeated experiments, with the beſt glaſſes, have never enabled me to diſcover any foramen, or opening, whatever. ”</p><p>The following cure may alſo be worth the reader’s notice. “Mrs Pidgeley, at Kingſton in Jamaica, in January 1781, was ſtung by a ſcorpion in the foot, above the little toe. The part became inſtantly red and painful; and ſoon after livid. The pain increaſed to great ſeverity. Some rum was applied to the wound, on when the pain immediately left the foot, and paſſed up to the groin, with great agony. The pain ſtill paſſed upwards, and diffuſed itſelf about the pit of the ſtomach, neck, and throat, attended with tremors, cold ſweats, and languors. As the pain paſſed the abdomen, it occaſioned a violent purging and fainting, which ceaſed on its advancing higher. I @@* was called to her, and gave her the following medicines, a few doſes of which removed every ſymptom. She had been extremely ill for thirty-ſix hours. R.<hi rend="italic"> Sal. Succin. ℈ij</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Camphor. gr.</hi> xij; <hi rend="italic">Cinnabar. Antimοn. gr.</hi> x; <hi rend="italic">Confect. Card. q. ſ. fiant boli ſex.</hi> One of theſe was taken every hour, with four ſpoonfuls of the following mixture: R, Aq.</p><p>Menthae <hi rend="italic">℥ vij; </hi>Elix. Paregoric.<hi rend="italic"> 3 ij; </hi>Syr. Crοci <hi rend="italic">℥ ſſ; </hi>Miſce."</p><p>There are few animals more formidable, or more truly miſchievous, than the ſcorpion. As it takes refuge in a ſmall place, and is generally found ſheltering in houſes, it muſt frequently ſting thoſe among</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@ [mu] Plate CCCC</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">xlv.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@ [m] * Dr Moseley.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>