<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>William Keith the town. The Scots made an obſtinate defence; yet it was evident that they muſt soon have yielded if they had not been relieved. At length the regent, with a numerous army, appeared in the neighbourhood. He endeavoured to convey ſuccours into the town, or to provoke the enemies to quit the advantage of the ground, and engage in battle. But all his efforts were in vain; the Engliſh obſtructed every paſſage, and flood on the defenſive.</p><p>The regent then entered Northumberland, waſted the country, and even aſſaulted Bamborough castle, where Philippa the young queen of England had her residence. He fondly imagined that Edward III. would have abandoned the ſiege of Berwick, after the example of his father, in circumſtances not diſſimilar. Edward nevertheleſs perſevered in his enterpriſe.</p><p>During a general aſſault, the town was set on fire, and in a great meaſure conſumed. The inhabitants having experienced the evils of a ſiege, and dreading the worſe evils of a ſtorm, implored the earl of March and Sir William Keith to ſeek terms of capitulation. A truce was obtained; and it was agreed, that the town and caſtle ſhould be delivered up on terms fair and honourable, unleſs ſuccours arrived before the hour of veſpers on the 19th July.</p><p>It was ſpecially provided, “that Berwick ſhould be held as relieved, in case 200 men at arms, in a body, ſhould force their paſſage into the town.”</p><p>By the treaty, Sir William Keith was permitted to have an interview with the regent. He found him with his army in Northumberland; urged the neceſſity of his return; and ſhowed him, that Berwick, if not inſtantly relieved, was loſt for ever. Perſuaded by his importunities, the regent reſolved to combat the Engliſh, and either to ſave Berwick or loſe the kingdom.</p><p>On the afternoon of the 19th of July, the regent prepared for battle. He divided his army into four bodies. The first was led by John earl of Moray, the ſon of Randoloh; but as he was young and inexperienced in war, James and Simon Fraſer, ſoldiers of approved reputation, were joined with him in the command. The ſecond body was led by the Reward of Scotland, a youth of 16, under the infpection of his uncle Sir James Stewart of Roſyth. The third body was led by the regent himself, having with him the earl of Carrick and other barons of eminence. The fourth body, or reſerve, appears to have been led by Hugh carl of Ross.</p><p>The numbers of the Scottiſh army on that day are variouſiy reported by hiſtorians. The continuator of Hemingford, an author of that age, and Knyghton, who lived in the ſucceeding age, aſcertain their numbers with more precifion than is generally required in historical facts.</p><p>The continuator of Hemingford minutely records the numbers and arrangement of the Scottiſh army. He ſays, that, beſides earls and other lords or great barons, there were 55 knights, 1100 men at arms, and 13,500 of the commons lightly armed, amounting in all to 14,655.</p><p>With him Knyghton appears to concur, when his narrative is cleared from the errors of ignorant or careleſs transcribers.</p><p>It is probable, however, that the ſervants who tended the horſes of perſons of diſtinction and of the men at arms, and the uſeleſs followers of the camp, were more numerous than the actual combatants.</p><p>The Engliſh were advantageoufly poſted on a rising ground at Halydon, with a marſhy hollow in their  front. Of their particular disρosition we are not informed, further than that Baliol had the command of one of the wings.</p><p>It had been provided by the treaty of capitulation, "That Berwick ſhould he coſidered as relieved, in caſe 200 men at arms forced their paſſage into the town." This the Scottiſh men at arms attempted; bet Edward, aware of their purpoſe, oppoſed them in perſon, and repulſed them with great daughter. The Scottiſh army ruſhed on to a general attack; but they had to deſcend into the marſhy hollow before mounting the eminences of Halydon. After having struggled  with the difficulties of the ground, and after having been inceſſantly galled by the Engliſh archers, they reached the enemy. Although fatigued and diſordered in their ranks, they fought as it became men who had conquered under the banners, of Robert Bruce. The Engliſh, with equal valour, had great advantages of ſituation, and were better diſciplined than, their antagoniſts. The earl of Roſs led the reſerve to attack in flank that wing where Baliol commanded; but he was repulſed and ſlain. There fell with him Kenneth earl of Sutherland, and Murdoch earl of Menteith.</p><p>In the other parts of the field, the events were equally diſaſtrous. The regent received a mortal wound, and the Scots everywhere gave way. In the field, and during a purſuit for many miles, the number of  ſlain and priſoners was ſo great, that few of the Scottiſh army escaped.</p><p>Beſides the earls of Ross, Sutherland, and Menteith, there were among the ſlain Malcolm earl of Lenox, an aged baron; he had been one of the foremost to repair to the ſtandard of Robert Bruce, and his last exertions were for his country: Alexander Bruce earl of Carrick, who atoned for the ſhort defection from the family of his benefactor; John Campbell earl of Athole, nephew of the late king; James Fraſer, and Simon Fraser; John de Graham, Alexander de Lindeſay, Alan Stewart,and many other perſonsof eminent rank.</p><p>The Steward had two uncles, John and James. John was killed, and James mortally wounded and made priſoner @@(I).</p><p>The regent, mortally wounded, and abandoned on the field of battle, only lived to ſee his army difcomfited and himſelf a priſoner.</p><p>This victory was obtained with very inconsiderable</p><p>@@@(I) Fordun, 1. xiii. c. 28. relates, that Sir James Stewart was ſlain; the Engliſh historians, that he was mortally wounded and made priſoner. It may be remarked, that at Halydon two Stewarts fought under the banner of their chiefs; the one Alan of Dreghorn, the paternal anceſtor of Charles I. and the other James of Roſyth, the paternal anceſtor of Oliver Cromwell.</p></body></text></TEI>