<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>his army, invaded Scotland in his turn. The particulars of the war are unknown; but it certainly ended much to the diſadvantage of the Scots, as Malcolm agreed to pay him homage. The Engliſh hiſtorians contend that this homage was for the whole of his dominions; but the Scots with more ſhow of reaſon affirm, that it was only for thoſe he poſſeſſed in England. On the concluſion of the peace, a croſs was erected at Stanmore in Richmondſhire, with the arms of both kings, to ſerve as a boundary between the poſſeſſions of William and the feudal dominions of Malcolm. Part of this monument, called <hi rend="italic">Re-croſs,</hi> or rather <hi rend="italic">Roy-croſs, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">The croſs of the kings,</hi> was entire in the days of Camden.</p><p>This peace between Malcolm Canmore and William produced the greateſt alteration in the manners of the Scots. What contributed chiefly to this was the excellent diſpofition of queen Margaret; who was, for that age, a pattern of piety and politeneſs: and next to this was the number of foreigners who had ſettled in Scotland; among whom were ſome Frenchmen, who laid the foundation of that friendſhip with the Scots which laſted for ages. Malcolm himſelf, alſo, though by his ravages in England he ſeems naturally to have been a barbarian, was far from being averſe to a reformation, and even ſet the example himſelf. During her huſband’s abſence in England queen Margaret had choſen for her confeſſor one Turgot, whom ſhe alſo made her aſſiſtant in her intended reformation. She began with new-modelling her own court; into which ſhe introduced the offices, furniture, and manner of living, common among the more polite nations of Europe. She diſmiſſed from her ſervice all thoſe who were noted for immorality and impiety: and charged Turgot, on pain of her diſpleaſure, to give his real ſentiments on the ſtate of the kingdom, after the beſt inquiry he could make. By him ſhe was informed, that faction reigned among the nobles, rapine among the commons, and incontinence among all degrees of men. Above all, he complained that the kingdom was deſtitute of a learned clergy, capable of reforming the people by their example and doctrine. All this the queen repreſented to her huſband, and prevailed upon him to let about the work of reformation immediately; in which, however, he met with conſiderable oppoſition. The Scots, accuſtomed to oppreſs their inferiors, thought all reſtrictions of their power were as many ſteps towards their ſlavery. The introduction of foreign offices and titles confirmed them in this opinion; and ſuch a dangerous inſurrection happened in Moray and ſome of the northern counties, that Malcolm was obliged to march againſt the rebels in perſon. He found them, indeed, very formidable; but they were ſo much intimidated by his reſolution, that they intreated the clergy who were among them to intercede with the king in their favour. Malcolm received their ſubmiſſion, but refuſed to grant an unconditional pardon.. He gave all the common people indeed leave to return to their habitations, but obliged the better ſort to ſurrender themſelves to his pleaſure. Many of the moſt guilty were put to death, or condemned to perpetual impriſonment; while others had their eſtates confiſcated. This ſeverity checked the rebellious ſpirit of the Scots, upon which Malcolm returned to his plans of reformation. Still, however, he found himſelf oppoſed even in thoſe abuſes,</p><p>which were moſt obvious and glaring. He durſt not entirely aboliſh that infamous practice of the landlord claiming the firſt night with his tenant’s bride; though, by the queen’s influence, the privilege was changed into the payment of a piece of money by the bridegroom, and was afterwards known by the name of <hi rend="italic">mercheta mulierum,</hi> or “the woman’s merk.” In thoſe days the Scots were without the practice of ſaying grace after meals, till it was introduced by Margaret, who gave a glaſs of wine, or other liquor, to thoſe who remained at the royal table and heard the thankſgiving; which expedient gave riſe to the term of the <hi rend="italic">grace-drink.</hi> Beſides this, the terms of the duration of Lent and Eaſter were fixed; the king and queen beſtowed large alms on the poor, and the latter waſhed the feet of ſix of their number; many churches, monaſteries, &amp;c. were erected, and the clerical revenues augmented. However, notwithſtanding theſe reformations, ſome hiſtorians have complained, that, along with the manners of the Engliſh and French, their luxuries were alſo introduced. Till this reign the Scots had been remarkable for their ſobriety and the ſimplicity of their fare; which was now converted into exceſs and riot, and ſometimes ended fatally by quarrels and bloodſhed. We are told, at the ſame time, that even in thoſe days, the nobility eat only two meals a-day, and were ſerved with no more than two diſhes at each meal; but that their deviation from their ancient temperance occaſioned a diminution of the ſtrength and ſize of the people.</p><p>In the year 1077, Malcolm again invaded England; but upon what provocation, or with what ſucceſs, is not well known. But in 1088, after the death of the Conqueror, he again eſpouſed the cauſe of Edgar Atheling, who had been reduced to implore his aſſiſtance a ſecond time, when William Rufus aſcended the throne of England. At the time of Edgar’s arrival, Malcolm was at the head of a brave and well-diſciplined army, with which he penetrated a great way into the country of the enemy; and, as it is ſaid, returned to Scotland with an immenſe booty. Some hiſtorians tell us, that in this expedition Malcolm met with a defeat, which obliged him to return; and indeed this is not a little countenanced by others, who ſay, not indeed that he was defeated, but that it was <hi rend="italic">the will oſ God</hi> he ſhould proceed no farther. But, be this as it will, William reſolved to revenge the injury, and prepared great armaments both by ſea and land for the invaſion of Scotland. His ſucceſs, however, was not anſwerable to the greatneſs of his preparations. His fleet was daſhed to pieces by ſtorms, and almoſt all on board of it periſhed. Malcolm had alſo laid waſte the country through which his antagoniſt was to paſs, in ſuch an effectual manner, that William loſt a great part of his troops by fatigue and famine; and, when he arrived in Scotland, found himſelf in a ſituation very little able to reſiſt Malcolm, who was advancing againſt him with a powerful army. In this diſtreſs, Rufus had recourſe to Robert de Mowbray earl of Northumberland, who diſſuaded him from venturing a battle, but adviſed him by all means to open a negociation by means of Edgar and the other Engliſh noblemen who reſided with Malcolm. Edgar undertook the negociation, on condition of his being reſtored to his eſtates in England; but met with more difficulty than he imagined. Malcolm had never yet recognized the right of William Rufus to the throne</p></body></text></TEI>