<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SARDIS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sardes,</hi> now called <hi rend="italic">Sardo</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sart,</hi> is an ancient town of Natolia in Aſia, about 40 miles eaſt of Smyrna. It was much celebrated in early antiquity, was enriched by the fertility of the ſoil, and had been the capital of the Lydian kings. It was ſeated on the ſide of mount Tmolus; and the citadel, placed on a lofty hill, was remarkable for its great ſtrength. It was the ſeat of King Croeſus, and was in his time taken by Cyrus; after which the Perſian Satrapas or commandant reſided at Sardis as the emperor did at Suſa. The city was alſo taken, burnt, and then evacuated by the Mileſians in the time of Darius, and the city and for- treſs ſurrendered on the approach of Alexander alter the battle of Granicus. Under the Romans Sardis was a very conſiderable place till the time of Tiberius Caeſar, when it buffered prodigiouſly by an earthquake. The munificence of the emperor, however, was nobly exerted to repair the various damages it then ſuſtained. Julian attempted to reſtore the heathen worſhip in the place. He erected temporary altars where none had been left, and repaired the temples if any veſtiges remained. In the year 400 it was plundered by the Goths, and ſt ſuffered conſiderably in the ſubſequent troubles</p><p>of Aſia. On the incurſion of the Tartars in 1304, the Turks were permitted to occupy a portion of the citadel, ſeparated by a ſtrong wall with a gate, and were afterwards murdered in their ſleep. The ſite of this once noble city is now green and flowery, the whole being reduced to a poor village, containing nothing but wretched huts. There are, however, ſome curious remains of antiquity about it, and ſome ruins which diſplay its ancient grandeur. See <hi rend="italic">Chandler's Travels in A</hi>ſ<hi rend="italic">ia Minor,</hi> p. 251, &amp;c<hi rend="italic">.</hi></p><p>There is in the place a large caravanſary, where travellers may commodiouſly lodge. The inhabitants are generally ſhepherds, who lead their ſheep into the fine paſtures of the neighbouring plain. The Turks have a moſque here, which was a Chriſtian church, at the gate of which there are ſeveral columns of poliſhed marble. There are a few Chriſtians, who are employed in gardening. E. Long. 28. 5. N. Lat. 37. 51.</p><p>SARDONIUS <hi rend="smallcaps">risus, </hi><hi rend="italic">Sardonian Laughter.</hi> A convulſive involuntary laughter; thus named from the herba ſardonia, which is a ſpecies of ranunculus, and is ſaid to produce ſuch convulſive motions in the cheeks as referable thoſe motions which are obſerved in the face during a fit of laughter. This complaint is ſometimes ſpeedily fatal. If the ranunculus happens to be the cauſe, the cure mull be attempted by means of a vomit, and frequent draughts of hydromel with milk.</p><p>SARDONYX, a precious ſtone conſiſting of a mixture of the chalcedony and carnelian, ſometimes in ſtrata, but at other times blended together. It is found, I. Striped with white and red ſtrata, which may be cut in <hi rend="italic">cameo</hi> as well as the onyx. 2. White with red dentritioal figures, greatly reſembling the mocha-ſtone; but with this difference, that the figures in the ſardonyx are of a red colour, in the other black. There is no real difference, excepting in the circumſtance of hardneſs, between the onyx, carnelian, chalcedony, ſardonyx, and agate, notwithſtanding the different names beſtowed upon them. Mongez informs us, that the yellow, or orange-coloured agates, with a wavy or undulating ſurface, are now commonly called ſardonyx. See <hi rend="smallcaps">CARNELLIAN</hi> and ONYX.</p><p>SARGUS, in ichthyology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sparus. </hi>SARIMPATAM, a country of Indoſtan, lying at the back of the dominions of the Samorin of Malabar, and which, as far as we know, was never ſubdued by any foreign power. Mr Groſe relates, that “it has been conſtantly a maxim with the inhabitants of this country never to make any but a defenſive war; and even then, not to kill any of their adverſaries in battle, but to cut off their noſes. To this ſervice the military were peculiarly trained up, and the dread of the deformity proved ſufficiently ſtrong to keep their neighbours, not much more martial than themſelves, from effectually attacking them. ”</p><p>SARMENTOSAE (from <hi rend="italic">ſarmentum,</hi> a long ſhoot like that of a vine); the name of the 11th claſs in Linnaeus’s Fragments of a Natural Method, conſiſting of plants which have climbing ſtems and branches, that, like the vine, attach themſelves to the bodies in their neighbourhood for the purpoſe of ſupport. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany,</hi> p. 459,</p><p>SAROTHRA, in botany: A genus of the trigynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 20th order, <hi rend="italic">Rotαceα.</hi> The corolla is pentapetalous; the capſule unilocular, trivalved, and coloured.</p><p>SARPLAR ofWOOL, a quantity of wool, otherwiſe called a <hi rend="italic">pocket</hi> or <hi rend="italic">half-</hi>ſ<hi rend="italic">ack;</hi> a ſack containing 80 tod; a tod two ſtone; and a ſtone 14 pounds. — In Scotland it is called <hi rend="italic">ſarpliath,</hi> and contains 80 ſtone.</p><p>SARRACONIA, in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the polyandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 54th order, <hi rend="italic">Miſcellaneae.</hi> The corolla is pentapetalous; the calyx is double, and triphyllous below; pentaphyllous above; the capſule quinquelocular; the ſtyle has a ſtigma of the form of a ſhield.</p><p>SARSAPARILLA, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Smilax.</hi></p><p>SARTORIUS, in <hi rend="smallcaps">Anatomy.</hi> See there, <hi rend="italic">Table of the Muſcles.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Old</hi> SARUM, in Wilts, about one mile north of New Sarum or Saliſhury, has the ruins of a fort which belonged to the ancient Britons; and is ſaid alſo to have been one of the Roman ſtations. It has a double intrenchment, with a deep ditch. It is of an orbicular form, and has a very auguſt look, being erected on one of the moſt elegant plans for a fortreſs that can be imagined. In the north-weſt angle ſtood the palace of the biſhop, whoſe fee was removed hither from Wilton and Sherborn; but the biſhop quarrelling with King Stephen, he ſeized the caſtle and put a garriſon into it, which was the principal cauſe of its deſtruction, as the fee was ſoon after removed from hence to Saliſhury in 1219. The area of this ancient city is ſituated on an artificial hill, whoſe walls were three yards thick, the ruins of which in many places in the circumference are ſtill to be ſeen, and the tracks of the ſtreets and cathedral church may be traced out by the different colour of the corn growing whcre once the city ſtood. Here ſynods and parliaments have formerly been held, and hither were the ſtates of the kingdom ſummoned to ſwear fidelity to William the Conqueror. Here alſo was a palace of the Britiſh and Saxon kings, and of the Roman emperors; which was deſerted in the reign of Henry III. for want of water, ſo that one farm-houſe is all that is left of this ancient city; yet it is called the <hi rend="italic">Bo-</hi></p></body></text></TEI>