<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:32Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>and faces are broad, with flat broad noſes, great blubber hanging lips, and ſtaring
                eyes; their complexion is dark, their hair long and as black as pitch, and they have
                very little beards; and it is ſaid that all the Samoied women have black nipples. If
                they have any religion at all, it is idolatry, though there has been ſome attempts
                of late to convert them. Their huts are made of birch bark ſewed together, which is
                laid upon ſtakes ſet in the ground, and at the top is a hole to let out the ſmoke;
                the fire is made in the middle, and both men and women lie naked round them all
                night. — They have little regard to the nearneſs of kin, and take as many wives as
                they can keep: their only employment is hunting and fiſhing.</p>
            <p>SAMOLUS, in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the pentandria claſs
                of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 21ſt order, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Preciae.</hi> The corolla is ſalver-ſhaped, the ſtamina ſurrounded by ſmall
                ſcales at its throat. The capſule is unilocular inferior.</p>
            <p>SAMOS (anc. geog.), an iſland at no great diſtance from the promontory Mycale, on the
                continent of the Hither Aſia, and oppoſite to Epheſus; the diſtance only ſeven
                ſtadia (Strabo); a free iſland, in compaſs 87 miles (Pliny); or 100 (Iſidorus): with
                a cognominal town (Ptolemy, Horace); famous for the worſhip and a temple of Juno,
                with a noted aſylum (Virgil, Strabo, Tacitus); and hence their coin exhibited a
                peacock (Athenæus): The country of Pythagoras, who, to avoid the oppreſſion of
                tyrants, retired to Italy, the land of freedom. Samos, though not ſo happy in
                producing wine, which Strabo wonders at, all the adjoining iſlands yielding a
                generous fort, yet abounds in all the neceſſaries of life. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vaſa Sarnia,</hi> among earthen ware, were held in high repute. <hi
                    rend="italic">Samii,</hi> the people (Ovid). —The iſland is now in the hands of
                the Turks. It is about 32 miles in length, and 22 in breadth, and extremely fertile.
                The inhabitants live at their eaſe, their taxation by the Turks being moderate. The
                women are very naſty and ugly, and they never ſhift above once a month. They are
                clothed in the Turkiſh manner, except a red coif, and their hair hanging down their
                backs, with plates of ſilver or block-tin faſtened to the ends. — They have
                abundance of melons, lentils, kidney-beans, and excellent muſkadine grapes. They
                have white figs four times as big as the common fort, but not ſo well taſted. Their
                ſilk is very fine, and their honey and wax admirable; beſides which, their poultry
                are excellent: they have iron mines, and moſt of the foil is of a ruſty colour: they
                have alſo emery ſtone, and all the mountains are of white marble. The inhabitants
                are about 12, 000, who are almoſt all Greeks; and the monks and prieſts occupy moſt
                part of the iſland. They have a biſhop who reſides at Cora. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Polycrates.</hi></p>
            <p>SAMPAN, is a Chineſe boat without a keel, looking almoſt like a trough; they are made
                of different dimenſions, but are moſtly covered.@@ Theſe boats are as long as ſloops,
                but broader, almoſt like a baking trough; and have at the end one or more decks of
                bamboo ſticks: the cover or roof is made of bamboo ſticks, arched over in the ſhape
                of a grater; and may be railed or lowered at pleaſure: the ſides are made of boards,
                with little holes, with ſhutters inſtead of win</p>
            <p>dows: the boards are faſtened on both ſides to polls, which have notches like ſteps
                on the inſides, that the roof may be let down, and reft on them: on both ends of the
                deck are commonly two little doors, at leaſt there is one at the hindmoſt end. A
                fine white ſmooth carpet ſpread up as far as the boards make3 the floor, which in
                the middle conſiſts of looſe boards; but this carpet is only made uſe of to ſleep
                on. As theſe boats greatly differ from ours in ſhape, they are likewiſe rowed in a
                different manner: for two rowers, polling themſelves at the back end of the ſampan,
                work it forwards very readily by the motion of two oars; and can almoſt turn the
                veſſel juſt as they pleaſe: the ores, which are covered with a little hollow
                quadrangular iron, are laid on iron ſwivels, which are faſtened in the ſides of the
                ſampan: at the iron the oars are pieced, which makes them look a little bent: in
                common, a rower fits before with a ſhort oar; but this he is forced to lay aſide
                when he comes near the city, on account of the great throng of ſampans; and this
                inconvenience has confirmed the Chineſe in their old way of rowing, Inſtead of
                pitch, they make uſe of a cement like our putty, which we call <hi rend="italic"
                    >chinam,</hi> but the Chineſe call it <hi rend="italic">kiang.</hi> Some authors
                ſay that this cement is made of lime and a reſin exuding from the tree <hi
                    rend="italic">tong yea,</hi> and bamboo ockam.</p>
            <p>Beſides a couple of chairs, they have the following furniture: two oblong tables or
                boards on which ſome Chinefe characters are drawn; a lanthorn for the night-time,
                and a pot to boil rice in. They have alfo a little cover for their houſehold god,
                decorated with gilt paper and other ornaments: before him ſtands a pot filled with
                aſhes, into which the tapers are put before the idol. The candles are nothing elſe
                than bamboo chips, to the upper end of which ſaw-duſt of ſandalwood is ſtuck on with
                gum. Theſe tapers are everywhere lighted before the idols in the pagodas, and before
                the doors in the ſtreets; and, in large cities, occaſion a ſmoke very pernicious to
                the eyes. Before this idol ſtands ſome <hi rend="italic">ſamſo,</hi> or Chineſe
                brandy, water, &amp;c. We ought to try whether the Chineſe would not like to uſe
                juniper-wood inſtead of fandal-wood; which latter comes from Suratte, and has almoſt
                the ſame ſmell with juniper.</p>
            <p>SAMSON, one of the judges of Iſrael, memorable for his ſupernatural ſtrength, his
                victories over the Philiſtines, and his tragical end, as related in the book of <hi
                    rend="italic">Judges.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SAMSON's Poſt,</hi> a fort of pillar erected in a ſhip’s hold,
                between the lower deck and the kelſon, under the edge of a hatchway, and furniſhed
                with several. notches that ſerve as ſteps to mount or deſcend, as occaſion requires.
                This poſt being firmly driven into its place, not only ſerves to ſupport the beam
                and fortify the veſſel in that place, but alſo to prevent the cargo or materials
                contained in the hold, from ſhifting to the oppoſite fide, by the rolling of the
                ſhip in a turbulent and heavy ſea.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Books </hi><hi rend="italic">of </hi>SAMUEL, two canonical books
                of the Old Teſtament, as being uſually aſcribed to the prophet Samuel.</p>
            <p>The books of Samuel and the books of Kings are a continued hiſtory of the reigns of
                the kings of Iſrael and Judah; for which reaſon the books of Samuel are likewiſe
                ſtyled <hi rend="italic">the first and ſecond books of Kings.</hi> Since</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Oshec's Voyage to China and the East Indies</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
