<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Sweyn their king reſolved to direct his whole force againſt him by an invaſion of Scotland. His firſt attempt, however, proved very unſucceſsſul; all his ſoldiers being cut in pieces, except ſome few who eſcaped to their ſhips, while the loſs of the Scots amounted to no more than 30 men. But in the mean time, Duncan, prince of Cumberland, having neglected to pay his homage to the king of England, the latter invaded that country in conjunction with the Danes. Malcolm took the field againſt them, and defeated both; but while he was thus employed in the ſouth, a new army of Danes landed in the north at the mouth of the river Spey. Malcolm advanced againſt them with an army  much inferior in number; and his men, neglecting every thing but the blind impulſes of fury, were almoſt all cut to pieces; Malcolm himſelf being deſperately wounded.</p><p>By this victory the Danes were ſo much elated, that they ſent for their wives and children, intending to ſettle in this country. The caſtle of Nairn, at that time thought almoſt impregnable, fell into their hands; and the towns of Elgin and Forres were abandoned both by their garriſons and inhabitants. The Scots were everywhere treated as a conquered people, and employed in the moſt ſervile offices by the haughty conquerors; who, to render the caſtle of Nairn, as they thought, abſolutely impregnable, cut through the ſmall iſthmus which joined it to the land. All this time, however, Malcolm was raiſing forces in the ſouthern counties; and having at laſt got an army together, he came up with the Danes at Murdoch, near Balveny, which appears at this day to have been a ſtrong Daniſh fortification. Here he attacked the enemy; but having the misfortune to loſe three of his general officers, he was again obliged to retreat. However, the Daniſh general happening to be killed in the purſuit, the Scots were encouraged to renew the fight with ſuch vigour, that they obtained at laſt a complete victory; but ſuffered ſo much, that they were unable to derive from it all the advantages which might otherwiſe have accrued.</p><p>On the news of this ill ſucceſs, Sweyn ordered two fleets, one from England and another from Norway, to make a deſcent upon Scotland, under the command of Camus, one of his moſt renowned generals. The Danes attempted to land at the mouth of the Forth; but finding every place there well fortified, they were obliged to move farther northward, and effected then purpoſe at Redhead in the county of Angus. The caſtle of Brechin was firſt beſieged; but meeting with a ſtout reſiſtance there, they laid the town and church in aſhes. From thence they advanced to the village of Panbride, and encamped at a place called <hi rend="italic">Karboddo.</hi></p><p>Malcolm in the mean time was at hand with his army, and encamped at a place called <hi rend="italic">Barr,</hi> in the neighbourhood of which both parties prepared to decide the fate of Scotland; for as Moray and the northern provinces were already in the poſſeſſion of the Danes, it was evident that a victory at this time mult put them in poſſeſſion of the whole. The engagement was deſperate, and ſo bloody, that the rivulet which proceeds from Loch Tay is ſaid to have had its water dyed with the blood of the ſlain; but at laſt the Danes gave way and fled. There was at that time in the army of Malcolm, a young prince of the name of <hi rend="italic">Keith @@</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> He purſued Camus; and having overtaken him, engaged and killed him; but another Scots officer coming up at the ſame time, diſputed with Keith the glory of the action. While the diſpute laſted, Malcolm came up; who ſuffered them to decide it by Angle combat. In this ſecond combat Keith proved alſo victorious, and killed his antagoniſt. The dying perſon confeſſed the juſtice of Keith’s claim; and Malcolm dipping his finger in his blood marked the ſhield of Keith with three ſtrokes, pronouncing the words <hi rend="italic">Veritas vincit,</hi> “Truth overcomes,” which has ever ſince been the armorial bearing and motto of the family of Keith @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(b).</hi></p><p>The ſhattered remains of the Daniſh forces reached their ſhips; but being driven back by contrary winds, and proviſions becoming ſcarce, they put aſhore 500 men on the coaſt of Buchan, to procure them ſome food: but their communication with the ſhips being ſoon cut off, they fortified themſelves as well as they could, and made a deſperate reſiſtance; but at laſt were all put to the ſword. The place where this maſſacre happened is ſtill called <hi rend="italic">Crudane;</hi> being probably an abbreviation of <hi rend="italic">Cruor Danorum, </hi>the blood of the Danes, a name impoſed on it by the eccleliaſtics of thoſe days.</p><p>Sweyn, not yet diſcouraged, ſent his ſon Canute, afterwards king of England, and one of the greateſt warrious of that age, into Scotland, with an army more powerful than any that had yet appeared. Canute landed in Buchan; and, as the Scots were much weakened by ſuch a long continued war, Malcolm thought proper to act on the defenſive. But the Scots, who now thought themſelves invincible, demanded to be led on to a general engagement. Malcolm complied with their deſire, and a battle enſued; in which though neither party had much reaſon to boaſt of victory, the Danes were ſo much reduced, that they willingly concluded a peace on the following terms, viz. That the Danes ſhould immediately depart Scotland; that as long as Malcolm and Sweyn lived, neither of them ſhould wage war with the other, or help each other’s enemies;</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> This prince is ſaid to have commanded a colony of the Catti, a German nation who fettled in the north- moſt part of Scotland, and from whom the county of Caithneſs takes its name.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(b)</hi> Mr Gordon, in his <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium Septentrionale,</hi> obſerves, that in all probability the Scots gained two victories over the Danes on the preſent occaſion; one near the place called <hi rend="italic">Karboddο, </hi>already mentioned; and the other at Aberlemno, four miles from Brechin. At both places there are monuments with rude ſculptures, erected moſt probably in memory of a victory. That at Karboddo is called <hi rend="italic">Camus's crοss;</hi> near which, ſomewhat more than a century ago, a large ſepulchre, ſuppoſed to be that of Camus, was diſcovered. It conſiſted of four great ſtones; and had in it a huge ſkeleton, ſuppofed to be that of the Daniſh prince. The fatal ſtroke ſeemed to have been given him on the back part of the head; a conſiderable portion of the ſkull being cut away, probably by the ſtroke of the ſword.</p></body></text></TEI>