<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ſupported by very high marble columns; the height of the arches is a ſtone-throw, and
                above them there was an aqueduct, which reached from Salona to Spalatro. There are
                to be ſeen many ruins and veſtiges of large palaces, and many ancient epitaphs may
                be read on fine marble ſtones; but the earth, which is increaſed, has buried the
                moſt ancient ſtones, and the moſt valuable things. ” E. Long. 17. 29. N. Lat. 44.
                10.</p>
            <p>SALONICHI, formerly called <hi rend="italic">Theſſalonica,</hi> a ſeaport town of
                Turkey in Europe, and capital of Macedonia, with an archbiſhop’s ſee. It is ancient,
                large, populous, and rich, being about 10 miles in circumference. It is a place of
                great trade, carried on principally by the Greek Chriſtians and Jews, the former of
                which have 30 churches, and the latter as many ſynagogues; the Turks alſo have a few
                moſques. It is ſurrounded with walls, flanked with towers, and defended on the
                land-ſide by a citadel, and near the harbour with three forts. It was taken from the
                Venetians by the Turks in 1431. The principal merchandize is ſilk. It is ſeated at
                the bottom of a gulph of the fame name, partly on the top, and partly on the ſide of
                a hill, near the river Vardar. E. Long. 23. 13. N. Lat. 40. 41.</p>
            <p>SALSES, a very ſtrong caſtle of France, in Rouſſillon, on the confines of Languedoc.
                It was taken from the Spaniards by the French in 1642; and is ſeated on a lake of
                the ſame name, among mountains, 10 miles north of Perignan. E. Long. 3. 0. N. Lat.
                43. 35.</p>
            <p>SALSETTE, an iſland of the Eaſt Indies, adjacent to Bombay, from which it is in one
                place divided only by a narrow paſs fordable at low water. It is about 26 miles
                long, and eight or nine broad. The ſoil is rich, and by proper cultivation capable
                of producing any thing that will grow in tropical climates. It is everywhere well
                watered, and when in the poſſeſſion of the Portugueſe furniſhed ſuch quantities of
                rice, that it was called the <hi rend="italic">Granary of Gοa.</hi> It abounds alſo
                in all kinds of proviſions, and has great plenty of game, both of the four-footed
                and feathered kind. It has pretty high mountains; and there is a tradition that the
                whole was thrown up from the bottom of the ſea: in confirmation of which it is ſaid,
                that on the top of the higheſt hill there was found, ſome years ago, a ſtone anchor,
                ſuch as was anciently uſed by the inhabitants of that country. Here we meet with the
                ruins of a place called <hi rend="italic">Canara,</hi> where there are excavations
                of rocks, ſuppoſed to be contemporary with thoſe of <hi rend="smallcaps">Elephanγa.
                </hi>They are much more numerous, but not comparable to the former either in bigneſs
                or workmanſhip.</p>
            <p>The iſland of Salſette lately formed part of the Portugueſe dominions in India. It
                ought to have been ceded to the Engliſh along with Bombay, as part of the dower of
                Catharine of Liſhon, eſpouſed to Charles II. The fulfilment of this article,
                however, being evaded, the iſland remained in poſſeſſion of the Portugueſe; and
                notwithſtanding the little care they took of it, the revenue of it was valued at
                60,0001. Such was the negligence of the Portugueſe government, that they took no
                care to fortify it againſt the attacks of the Marattas, from whoſe dominions
                Salſette was only feparated by a very narrow paſs fordable at low water. Here they
                had only a miſerable redoubt of no conſequence, till, on the appearance of an
                approaching war with the Marattas, they began to build another, which indeed would
                have anſwered the purpoſe of protecting the iſland, provided the Marattas had
                allowed them to finiſh it. This, however, was not their intention. They allowed them
                indeed to go quietly on with their works, till they ſaw them almoſt completed, when
                they came and took poſſeſſion of them. The Marattas thus became dangerous neighbours
                to the Engliſh at Bombay, until it was ceded to the latter by the treaty concluded
                with theſe people in 1780. E. Long. 72. 15. N. Lat. 19. 0.</p>
            <p>SALSOLA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Glass-wort</hi>: A genus of the digynia order,
                belonging to the pentandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under
                the 12th order, <hi rend="italic">Holoraceae.</hi> The calyx is pentaphyllous; there
                is no corolla; the capſule is monoſpermous, with a ſcrewed ſeed.</p>
            <p>The ſpecies are, 1. The kali, which grows naturally in the ſalt marſhes in divers
                parts of England. It is an annual plant, which riſes above five or fix inches high,
                fending out many ſide branches, which ſpread on every fide, garniſhed with ſhort
                awl-ſhaped leaves; which are fleſhy, and terminate in acute ſpines. The flowers are
                produced from the fide of the branches, to which they ſit cloſe, and are encompaſſed
                by ſhort prickly leaves; they are ſmall, and of an herbaceous colour. The feeds are
                wrapped up in the empalement of the flower, and ripen in autumn; ſoon after which
                the plant decays. 2. The tragus grows naturally on the ſandy ſhores of the ſouth of
                France, Spain, and Italy. This is alſo an annual plant, which ſends out many
                diſſuſed ſtalks, garniſhed with linear leaves an inch long, ending with ſharp
                ſpines. The flowers come out from the ſide of the ſtalks in the ſame manner as thoſe
                of the former; their empalements are blunt, and not ſo cloſely encompaſſed with
                leaves as thoſe of the other.</p>
            <p> 3. The ſoda, riſes with herbaceous ſtalks near three feet high, ſpreading wide. The
                leaves on the principal ſtalk, and thoſe on the lower part of the branches, are
                long, ſlender, and have no ſpines; thoſe on the upper part of the ſtalk and branches
                are ſlender, ſhort, and crooked. At the baſe of the leaves are produced the flowers,
                which are ſmall, and hardly perceptible; the empalement of the flower afterwards
                encom- paſſes the capſule, which contains one cochleated feed.</p>
            <p> 4. The vermiculata grows naturally in Spain. This hath ſhrubby perennial ſtalks,
                which riſe three or four feet high, fending out many ſide-branches, garniſhed with
                fleſhy, oval, acute-pointed leaves, coming out in cluſters from the ſide of the
                branches; they are hoary, and have ſtiff prickles. The flowers are produced from
                between the leaves toward the ends of the branches; they are ſo ſmall as ſcarce to
                be diſcerned, unleſs they are cloſely viewed. The ſeeds are like thoſe of the other
                kinds. 5. The roſacea grows naturally in Tartary. This is an annual plant, whoſe
                ſtalks are herbaceous, and ſeldom riſe more than five or fix inches high. The leaves
                are awl-ſhaped, ending in acute points; the empalements of the flowers ſpread open:
                the flowers are ſmall, and of a roſe colour, but ſoon fade: the ſeeds are like thoſe
                of the other forts.</p>
            <p>All the forts of glaſs-wort are ſometimes promiſcuouſly uſed for making the ſal kali,
                but it is the third fort which is eſteemed beſt for this purpoſe. The manner of
                making it is as follows: Having dug a trench</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
