<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>houſes, built pretty cloſely together, without any order, and having a winding path between them. They are generally flanked, towards the ſea, with detached walls, which are meant both for ſhelter and defence. Theſe walls conſiſt of looſe ſtones, and the inhabitants are very dexterous in ſhifting them ſuddenly to ſuch places as the direction of the attack may require. In the ſides of the hills, or ſurrounding eminences, they have alſo little holes, or caves, the entrance to which is alſo ſecured by a fence of the ſame kind. They ſerve for places of retreat in caſes of extremity, and may be defended by a ſingle perſon againſt ſeveral aſſailants. Their houſes are of different ſizes, ſome of them being large and commodious, from forty to fifty feet long, and from twenty to thirty broad; while others are mere hovels. The food of the lower claſs conſiſts principally of fiſh and vegetables, to which the people of higher rank add the fleſh of dogs and hogs. The manner of ſpending their time admits of little variety. They riſe with the ſun, and, after enjoying the cool of the evening, retire to reſt, a few hours after ſun-ſet. The making of canoes, mats, &amp;c. forms the occupations of the men; the women are employed in manufacturing cloth, and the ſervants are principally engaged in the plantations and ſiſhing. Their idle hours are filled up with various amuſements, ſuch as dancing, boxing, wreſtling, &amp;c. Their agriculture and navigation bear a great reſemblance to thoſe of the South-ſea iſlands. Their plantations, which are ſpread over the whole ſea coaſt, conſiſt of the taro, or eddy-root, and ſweet potatoes, with plants of the cloth-trees ſet in rows. The bottoms of their canoes are of a ſingle piece of wood, hollowed out to the thickneſs of an inch, and brought to a point at each end. The ſides conſiſt of three boards, each about an inch thick, neatly fitted and laſhed to the bottom part. Some of their double canoes meaſure 70 feet in length, three and a half in depth, and twelve in breadth. Their cordage, fiſh-hooks, and ſiſhing-tackle, differ but little from thoſe of the other iſlands. Among their arts muſt not be forgotten that of making ſalt, which they have in great abundance, and of a good quality. Their inſtruments of war are ſpears, daggers, clubs, and ſlings; and for defenſive armour they wear ſtrong mats, which are not eaſily penetrated by ſuch weapons as theirs. As the iſlands are not united under one ſovereign, wars are frequent among them, which, no doubt, contribute greatly to reduce the number of inhabitants, which, according to the proportion aſſigned to each iſland, does not exceed 400, 000. The ſame ſyſtem of ſubordination prevails here as at the other iſlands, the ſame abſolute authority on the part of the chiefs, and the ſame unreſiſting ſubmiſſion on the part of the people. The government is likewiſe monarchical and hereditary. At Owhyhee there is a regular ſociety of prieſts living by themſelves, and diſtinct in all reſpects from the reſt of the people. Human ſacriſices are here frequent; not only at the commencement of a war, or any ſignal enterpriſe, but the death of every conſiderable chief calls for a repetition of theſe horrid rites. Notwithſtanding the irreparable loſs in the death of captain Cook, who was here murdered through ſudden reſentment and violence, they are acknowledged to be of the moſt mild and affectionate diſpoſition. They live in the utmoſt harmony and friendſhip with each other; and in hoſpitality to ſtrangers they are not exceeded</p><p>even by the inhabitants of the Friendly Iſlands. Their natural capacity ſeems, in no reſpect, below the common ſtandard of mankind; and their improvements in agriculture, and the perfection of their manufactures, are certainly adequate to the circumſtances of their ſituation, and the natural advantages which they enjoy.</p><p>SANDYS (Sir Edwin), ſecond ſon of Dr Edwin Sandys archbiſhop of York, was born about 1561, and educated at Oxford under Mr Richard Hooker, author of the Eccleſiaſtical Polity. In 1581 he was collated to a prebend in the cathedral of York. He travelled into foreign countries; and, upon his return, grew famous for learning, prudence, and virtue. While he was at Paris, he drew up a tract, publiſhed under the title of <hi rend="italic">Europae Speculum.</hi> In 1602, he reſigned his prebend; and, the year following, was knighted by king James I. who employed him in ſeveral important affairs. He was dexterous in any great employment, and a good patriot. However, oppoſing the court with vigour in the parliament held in 1621, he, with Mr Selden, was committed to cuſtody for a month. He died in 1629, having bequeathed 15001. to the univerſity of Oxford, for the endowment of a metaphyſical lecture.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sandys</hi> (George), brother of the foregoing Sir Edwin, and youngeſt ſon of archbiſhop Sandys, was bora in 1577. He was a moſt accompliſhed gentleman; travelled over ſeveral parts of Europe and the Eaſt; and publiſhed a relation of his journey in folio, in 1615. He made an elegant tranſlation of Ovid’s Metamorphoſes; and compoſed ſome poetical pieces of his own, that were greatly admired in the times of their being written. He alſo paraphraſed the Pſalms; and has left behind him a Tranſlation, with Notes, of one Sacred Drama written originally by Grotius, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Christus Patiens;</hi> on which, and A<hi rend="italic">damus Exul,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Masenιus,</hi> is founded Lauder’s impudent charge of plagiariſm againſt our immortal Milton. Our author became one of the privy chamber to Charles I. and died in 1643.</p><p>SAN <hi rend="smallcaps">Fernando,</hi> near the entrance of the Golfo Dolce, in 15 degrees 8 minutes north latitude, has lately been fortified by the Spaniards, with an intent to curb the Muſquito-men, logwood-cutters, and bay-men. It is a very good harbour, with ſafe anchorage from the north and eaſt winds, in eight fathoms water.</p><p>SANGUIFICATION, in the animal œconomy, the converſion of the chyle into true blood. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Blood.</hi></p><p>SANGUINARIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">blood-wort,</hi> in botany: A genus of the monogynia order, belonging to the polyandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 27th order, <hi rend="italic">Rhoeaedae.</hi> The corolla is octopetalous: the calyx diphyllous; the ſiliqua ovate and unilocular. There is only one ſpecies, viz. the canadenſis, a native of the northern parts of America, where it grows plentifully in the woods; and in the ſpring, before the leaves of the trees come out, the ſurface of the ground is in many places covered with the flowers, which have ſome reſemblance to our wood anemone; but they have ſhort naked pedicles, each ſupporting one flower at top. Some of theſe flowers will have 10 or I2 petals, ſo that they appear to have a double range of leaves, which has occaſioned their being termed <hi rend="italic">double flowers;</hi> but this is only accidental, the ſame</p></body></text></TEI>