<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of England, and took part with the empreſs Maud in the civil war ſhe carried on with Stephen. In 1136, David met his antagoniſt at Durham; but as neither party cared to venture an engagement, a negociation took place, and a treaty was concluded. This, however, was obſerved but for a ſhort time; for, in the following year, David again invaded England, on ſome frivolous pretences. He defeated Stephen at Roxburgh; and forced him to retreat precipitately, after loſing one half of his army. Next year he renewed his invaſion; and, though he himſelf was a man of great mildneſs and humanity, he ſuffered his troops to commit ſuch outrages, as firmly united the Engliſh in oppoſition to him. His grand-nephew William cut in pieces the vanguard of the Enghſh army at Clithero; after which he ravaged the country with ſuch cruelty, that the inhabitants became exaſperated beyond meaſure againſt him. New aſſociations were entered into againſt the Scots; and the Engliſh army receiving great reinforcements from the ſouthward, advanced to Northallerton, where the famous ſtandard was produced. The body of this ſtandard was a kind of box which moved upon wheels, from which aroſe the maſt of a ſhip ſurmounted by a ſilver croſs, and round it were hung the banners of St Peter, St John de Beverly, and St Wilfred. Standards of this kind were common at that time on the continent of Europe; and ſo great confidence had the Engliſh in this ſtandard, that they now thought themſelves invincible. They had, however, a much more ſolid ground of confidence, as being much better armed than their antagoniſts. The armies met at a place called <hi rend="italic">Culton Moor.</hi> The firſt line of the Scots army was compoſed of the inhabitants of Galloway, Carric, Kyle, Cunningham, and Renfrew. Theſe by ſome hiſtorians are called <hi rend="italic">Pifts,</hi> and are ſaid to have had a prince of their own, who was a feudatory to David. The ſecond line conſiſted of the Lothian men, by which we are to underſtand the king’s ſubjects in England as well as the ſouth of Scotland, together with the Engliſh and Normans of Maud’s party. The third line was formed of the clans under their different chieftains; but who were ſubject to no regular command, and were always impatient to return to their own country when they had acquired any booty. The Engliſh ſoldiers having ranged themſelves round their ſtandard, diſmounted from their horſes, in order to avoid the long lances which the firſt line of the Scots army carried. Their front-line was intermixed with archers; and a body of cavalry, ready for purſuit, hovered at ſome diſtance. The Picts, beſides their lances, made uſe of targets; but, when the Engliſh cloſed with them, they were ſoon diſordered and driven back upon the centre, where David commanded in perſon. His ſon made a gallant reſiſtance, but was at laſt forced to yield: the laſt line ſeems never to have been engaged. David, ſeeing the victory decided againſt him, ordered ſome of his men to ſave themſelves by throwing away their badges, which it ſeems Maud’s party had worn, and mingling with the Engliſh; after which he himſelf, with his ſhattered forces, retreated towards Carliſle. The Engliſh hiſtorians ſay, that in this battle the Scots were totally defeated, with the loss of 10,000 men; but this ſeems not to be the caſe, as the Engliſh did not purſue, and the Scots were in a condition for carrying on the war next year. However, there were now no great exploits performed on either ſide; and a peace was concluded, by which Henry prince of Scotland was put in poſleſſion of Huntingdon and Northumberland, and took an oath of fealty to Stephen. David continued faithful to his niece the empreſs as long as he lived; and died at Carliſle in the year 1153, after a glorious reign of ſomewhat more than 29 years.</p><p>David was ſucceeded by his grandſon Malcolm IV. ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Maiden,</hi> on account of his continence. He appears to have been a weak and ſuperſtitious prince, and died of a depreſſion of ſpirits in the year 1165. He was ſucceeded by his brother William I. who immediately entered into a war with Henry II. of England, on account of the earldom of Northumber land, which had been given up by Malcolm; but Henry, finding his affairs in a very embarraſſed ſituation, conſented to yield up this county, on William’s paying him homage, rather than continue the miſeries of war. In 1172, he attempted to avail himſelf of the unnatural war which Henry’s ſons carried on againſt their father, and invaded England. He divided his army into three columns: the firſt of which laid ſiege to Carliſle; the ſecond he himſelf led into Northumberland; and the king’s brother, David, advanced with the third into Leiceſterſhire. William reduced the caſtles of Burgh, Appleby, Warkworth, and Garby; and then joined that diviſion of his army which was beſieging Carliſle. The place was already reduced to ſuch ſtraits, that the governor had agreed to ſurrender it by a certain day, provided it was not relieved before that time: on which the king, leaving ſome troops to continue the ſiege, inveſted a caſtle with ſome of the forces he had under his command, at the ſame time ſending a ſtrong reinforcement to his brother David; by which means he himſelf was left with a very ſmall army, when he received intelligence that a ſtrong body of Engliſh under Robert de Stuteville and his ſon were advancing to ſurpriſe him. — WiUiam, ſenſible of his inability to reſiſt them, retired to Alnwick, to which he inſtantly laid ſiege; but in the mean time acted in ſuch a careleſs and unthinking manner, that his enemies actually effected their deſigns. Having dreſſed a party of their ſoldiers in Scots habits, they took the king himſelf priſoner, and carried him, with his feet tied under the belly of a horſe, to Richmond Caſtle. He was then carried in chains before Henry to Northampton, and ordered to be tranſported to the caſtle of Falaiſe in Normandy, where he was ſhut up with other ſtate priſoners. Soon after this an accommodation took place between Henry and his ſons, and the priſoners on both ſides were ſet at liberty, William only excepted, who bore his confinement with great impatience. Of this Henry took the advantage, tp make him pay homage for the whole kingdom of Scotland, and acknowledge that he held it only as a feu of the crown of England; and, as a ſecurity, he was obliged to deliver into the hands of Henry all the principal forts in Scotland, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the caſtles of Roxburgh, Berwick, Jedburgh, Edinburgh, and Stirling; William at the ſame time agreeing to pay the Engliſh garriſons which were put into theſe caſtles. David, the king’s brother, with 20 barons, who were preſent at the ſigning of this ſhameful convention, were put into the hands of Henry as hoſtages for William’s good faith; after which the king was ſet at liberty, and returned to Scotland.</p></body></text></TEI>