<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>its operation is uncertain, a full doſe proving ſometimes ineffectual, whilſt at others a much ſmaller one occaſions dangerous hypercatharſes. This difference, however, is owing entirely to the different circumſtances of the patient, and not to any ill quality or irregularity of operation of the medicine: where the inteſtines are lined with an exceſſive load of mucus, the ſcammony paffes through without exerting itſelf upon them; where the natural mucus is deficient, a ſmall doſe of this or any other reſinous cathartic irritates and inflames. Many have endeavoured to abate the force of this drug, and correct its imaginary virulence, by ex- poſing it to the fume of ſulphur, diſſolving it in acid juices, and the like; but this could do no more than deſtroy as it were a part of the medicine, without making any alteration in the reft. Scammony in ſubſtance, judiciouſly managed, ſtands not in need of any corrector: if triturated with ſugar or with almonds, it becomes ſufficiently ſafe and mild in operation. It may likewiſe be conveniently diſſolved by trituration in a ſtrong decoction of liquorice, and then poured off from the faeces; the college of Wertemberg aſſures us, that by this treatment it becomes mildly purgative, without being attended with gripes, or other inconveniences; and that it likewiſe proves inoffenſive to the palate. The common doſe of ſcammony is from three to twelve grains. </p><p>SCANDALUM <hi rend="smallcaps">Magnatum,</hi> in law, is a defamatory ſpeech or writing to the injury of a perſon of dignity; for which a writ that bears the ſame name is granted for the recovery of damages.</p><p>SCANDERBEG, the ſurname of George Caſtriot king of Albinia, a province of Turkey in Europe, dependent on the Ottoman empire. He was delivered up with his three elder brothers as hoſtages, by their father, to Amurath II. ſultan of the Turks, who poiſoned his brothers, but ſpared him on account of his youth, being likewiſe pleaſed with his juvenile wit and amiable perſon. In a ſhort time he became one of the moſt renowned generals of the age; and revolting from Amurath, he joined Hunniade Corvin, a moſt formidable enemy to the Ottoman power. He defeated the ſultan’s army, took Amurath’s ſecretary priſoner, obliged him to ſign and leal an order to the governor of Croia, the capital of Albania, to deliver up the citadel and city to the bearer of that order, in the name of the ſultan. With this forged order he repaired to Croia; and thus recovered the throne of his anceſtors, and maintained the independency of his country againſt the numerous armies ot Amurath and his ſucceiſor Mahommed II. who was obliged to make peace with this hero <hi rend="italic">in 14</hi>6<hi rend="italic">1.</hi> He then went to the aſſiſtance of Ferdinand of Arragon, at the requeſt of Pope Pius II. and by his aſſiſtance Ferdinand gained a complete victory over his enemy the count of Anjou. Scanderbeg died in 1467.</p><p>SCANDEROON. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexandretta.</hi></p><p>SCANDINAVIA, a general name for the countries of Norway, Sweden, and Denmark, anciently under the dominion of one prince. The inhabitants of theſe countries, in former times, were exceſſively addicted to war. From their earlieſt years they applied themſelves to the military art, and accuſtomed themſelves to cold, fatigue, and hunger. Even the very ſports of youth and childhood were dangerous.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Vol.</hi> XVI. Part II.</p><p>They conſiſted in taking frightful leaps, climbing up the ſteepeſt rocks, fighting naked with offenſive weapons, wreſtling with the utmoſt fury; ſo that it was uſual to fee them grown up to be robuſt men, and terrible in the combat, at the age of 15. At this early age the young men became their own maſters; which they did by receiving a ſword, a buckler, and a lance. This ceremony was performed at ſome public meeting. One of the principal men of the aſſembly named the youth in public; after which he was obliged to provide for his own ſubſiſtence, and was either now to live by hunting, or by joining in ſome incurſion againſt the enemy. Great care was taken to prevent the young men from too early connections with the female ſex; and indeed they could have no hope to gain the affection of the fair, but in proportion to the courage and addreſs they had ſhown in their military exerciſes. Accordingly, in an ancient ſong, we find Bartholin, king of Norway, extremely ſurpriſed that his miſtreſs ſhould prove unkind, as he could perform eight different exerciſes. The children were generally born in camps; and being inured from their infancy to behold nothing but arms, effuſion of blood, and ſlaughter, they imbibed the cruel diſpoſition of their fathers, and when they broke forth upon other nations, behaved rather like furies than like human creatures.</p><p>The laws of this people, in ſome meaſure, reſembled thoſe of the ancient Lacedemonians. They knew no virtue but bravery, and no vice but cowardice. The greateſt penalties were inflicted on ſuch as fled from battle. The laws of the ancient Danes declared ſuch perlons infamous, and excluded them from ſociety. Among the Germans, cowards were ſometimes ſuffocated in mud; after which they were covered over with hurdles, to ſhow, ſays Tacitus, that though the puniſhment of crimes ſhould be public, there are certain degrees of cowardice and infamy which ought to be buried in oblivion. Frotho king of Denmark enacted, by law, that whoever ſolicited an eminent poſt ought upon all occaſions to attack one enemy, to face two, to retire only one ſtep back from three, and never to make an actual retreat till affaulted by four. The rules of juſtice themſelves were adapted and warped to theſe prejudices. War was looked upon as a real act of juſtice, and force was thought to be an inconteſtable title over the weak, and a viſible mark that God had intended them to be ſubject to the ſtrong. They had no doubt but that the intentions of the Deity had been to eſtabliſh the ſame dependence among men that takes place among inferior creatures; and, ſetting out from this principle of the natural <hi rend="italic">inequality</hi> among men, they had from thence inferred that the weak had no right to what they could not defend. This maxim was adopted; with ſuch rigour, that the name of divine judgement was given not only to the judicatory combat, but to conflicts and battles of all ſorts; victory being, in their opinion, the only certain mark by which providence enables us to diſtinguiſh thoſe whom it has appointed to command others. —Laſtly, their religion, by annexing eternal happineſs to the military virtues, gave the utmoſt poſſible degree of vigour to that propenſity which thele people had for war, and to their contempt of death, of which we ſhall now give ſome inſtances. We are informed that Harold, ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Blaatand,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Blue-tooth,</hi> a king of Denmark, who lived in the be-</p></body></text></TEI>