<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>generally but one large black ſpot, though ſometimes a ſingle ſmall one attends it;
                whereas the pectoral fins of the trout are more numerouſly marked. <hi rend="italic"
                    >6thly,</hi> The ſpurious or fat fin on the back is never tipped with red; nor
                is the edge of the anal fin white. <hi rend="italic">6thly,</hi> The ſpots on the
                body are fewer, and not ſo bright: it is alſo marked from the back to the ſides with
                fix or ſeven large bluiſh bars; but this is not a certain character, as the fame is
                ſometimes found in young trouts.<hi rend="italic"> 7thly,</hi> The tail of the
                ſamlet is much more forked than that of the trout. Theſe fi<hi rend="italic"
                    >fkirfιnsts, </hi>h are very frequent in the rivers of Scotland, where they are
                called <hi rend="italic">pars.</hi> They are alſo common in the Wye, where they are
                known by the name of <hi rend="italic">ſkirlings,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >laſprings.</hi></p>
            <p>6. The alpinus, or red charr (umbla minor, or caſe charr of
                Pennant), is an inhabitant of the lakes of the north, and of thoſe of the
                mountainous parts of Europe. It affects clear and pure waters, and is very rarely
                known to wander into running ſtreams, except into ſuch whoſe bottom is ſimilar to
                the neighbouring lake. It is found in vaſt abundance in the cold lakes on the
                ſummits of the Lapland Alps, and is almoſt the only fiſh that is met with in any
                plenty in thoſe regions; where it would be wonderful bow they ſubſiſted, had not
                Providence ſupplied them with innumerable larvæ of the gnat kind: theſe are food to
                the fiſh, who in their turn are a ſupport to the migratory Laplanders, in their
                ſummer voyages to the diſtant lake. In ſuch excurſions thoſe vacant people find a
                luxurious and ready repaſt in theſe fiſh, which they dreſs and eat without the
                addition of ſauces; for exer- ciſe and temperance render uſeleſs the inventions of
                epi- curiſm. There are but few lakes in our iſland that produce this fiſh; and even
                thoſe not in any abundance. It is found in Ullſwater and Windermere in Weſtmoreland;
                in Llyn Quellyn, near the foot of Snowdon; and, before the diſcovery of the copper-
                mines, in thoſe of Llynberris; but the mineral ſtreams have entirely deſtroyed the
                fiſh in the laſt lakes. In Scotland it is found in Loch Inch, and other neighbouring
                lakes, and is ſaid to go into the Spey to ſpawn.</p>
            <p>“The largeſt and moſt beautiful we ever received (ſays Mr Pennant) were taken in
                Windermere, and were communicated by the Rev. Mr Fariſh of Carliſle, with an account
                of their natural hiſtory. He ſent five ſpecimens; two under the name of the <hi
                    rend="italic">caſe charr,</hi> male and female; another he called the <hi
                    rend="italic">geld charr,</hi> i. e. a charr which had not ſpawned the preceding
                ſeaſon, and on that account is reckoned to be in the greateſt perfection. The two
                others were inſcribed, the <hi rend="italic">red charr,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >ſilver</hi> or <hi rend="italic">gild charr,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">carpia
                    lacus benaci,</hi>
                <hi rend="smallcaps">Raii </hi><hi rend="italic">Syn. Piſc.</hi> 66. which laſt are
                in Weſtmoreland diſtinguiſhed by the epithet <hi rend="italic">red,</hi> by reaſon
                of the fleſh aſſuming a higher colour than the other when dreſſed.</p>
            <p>“The umbla minor, or caſe charr, ſpawns about Michaelmas, and chiefly in the river
                Brathy, which uniting with another called the <hi rend="italic">Rowthay,</hi> about
                a quarter of a mile above the lake, they both fall into it together. The Brathy has
                a black rocky bottom; the bottom of the Row thay is a bright ſand, and into this the
                charr are never obſerved to enter. Some of them, however, ſpawn in the lake; but
                always in ſuch parts of it which are ſtony, and reſemble the channel of the Brathy.
                They are ſuppoſed to be in the higheſt perſection about May, and continue ſo alt the ſummer; yet are rarely caught after April.
                When they are ſpawning in the river they will take a bait, but at no other time;
                being commonly taken, as well as the other ſpecies, in what they <hi rend="italic"
                    >breast-nests,</hi> which are in length about 24 fathoms, and about five where
                broadeſt. — The ſeaſon which the other ſpecies ſpawn in is from the beginning of
                January to the end of March. They are never known to aſcend the rivers, but always
                in thoſe parts of the lake which are ſpringy, where the bottom is ſmooth and ſandy,
                and the water warmeſt. The ſiſhermen judge of this warmth, by obſerving that the
                water ſeldom freezes in the places where they ſpawn except in intenſe froſts, and
                then the ice is thinner than in other parts of the lake. They are taken in greateſt
                plenty from the end of September to the end of November; at other times they are
                hardly to be met with. This ſpecies is much more eſteemed for the table than the
                other, and is very delicate when potted. The length of the red charr to the diviſion
                in its tail was 12 inches; its biggeſt circumference almoſt 7. The firſt dorſal fin
                was five inches and three quarters from the tip of its noſe, and conſiſted of 12
                branched rays, the firſt of which was ſhort, the fifth the longeſt; the fat fin was
                very ſmall. Each of the five fiſh had double noſtrils, and ſmall teeth in the jaws,
                roof of the mouth, and on the tongue. —The jaws of the caſe-charr are perfectly
                even; on the contrary, thoſe of the red-charr were unequal, the upper jaw being the
                broadeſt, and the teeth hung over the lower, as might be perceived on paſſing the
                finger over them. —The geld or barren charr was rather more ſlender than the others,
                as being without ſpawn. The back was of a gloſſy duſky blue; the ſides ſilvery,
                mixed with blue, ſpotted with pale red; the ſides of the belly were of a pale red,
                the bottom white. The tails of each bifurcated. ”</p>
            <p>7. The thymallus, or grayling, haunts clear and rapid ſtreams, and particularly thoſe
                that flow through mountainous countries. It is found in the rivers of Derbyſhire; in
                ſome of thoſe of the north; in the Tame near Ludlow; in the Lug, and other ſtreams
                near Leominſter; and in the river near Chriſtchursh, Hampſhire. It is alſo very
                common in Lapland: the inhabitants make life of the guts of this fiſh inſtead of
                rennet, to make the cheeſe which they get from the milk of the rein-deer. It is a
                voracious fiſh, riſes freely to the fly, and will very eagerly take a bait. It is a
                very ſwift ſwimmer, and diſappears like the tranſient paſſage of a ſhadow, from
                whence we believe it derived the name of <hi rend="italic">umbra.</hi></p>
            <p>Effugienſque oculos celeri levis <hi rend="italic">umbra </hi>natatu. <hi
                    rend="italic">Auſon,</hi></p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">umbra</hi> ſwift eſcapes the quickeſt eye.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Thymalus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">thymus</hi> are names beſtowed
                on it on account of the imaginary ſcent, compared by ſome to that of thyme; but we
                never could perceive any particular ſmell. It is a fiſh of an elegant form; leſs
                deep than that of a trout: the largeſt we ever heard of was taken near Ludlow, which
                was about half a yard long, and weighed four pounds fix ounces; but this was a very
                rare inſtance. The irides are ſilvery, tinged with yellow: the teeth very minute,
                ſeated in the jaws and the roof of the mouth, but none on the tongue: the head is
                duſky; the covers of the gills of a gloſſy green: the back and ſides of a fine
                ſilvery grey; but when the fiſh is juft</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
