<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">avalanches)</hi> and fragments of rocks, frequently roll down into them from the impending precipices. The way of travelling is either in ſledges, chairs, or on the- backs of mules: in ſome places the path on the brink of the precipices is ſo narrow, that there is but juſt room for a ſingle perſon to paſs. It begins to ſnow on theſe mountains commonly about the beginning of October In ſummer, in the months of July, Auguſt, and September, many of them yield very fine grass, with a great variety of flowers and herbs; and others box-wood, walnuts, cheſnuts, and pines. The height and different combinations of theſe mountains, their towering ſummits riſing above one another, and covered with ſnow. The many cataracts or falls of water, the noiſe and rapidity of the river Arc, the froth and green tincture of its water, the echoes of its numerous ſtreams tumbling from cliff to cliff, form altogether a very romantic ſcene. Theſe mountainous tracts, notwithſtanding their height, are not altogether free from thunder in ſummer, and are alſo much expoſed to thick clouds, which ſometimes ſettle unexpectedly on them, and continue ſeveral days. There are ſome wolves among the thickets; and they abound with hares, rupicapras or chamois, and marmottes. In the lower parts of Savoy, there are alſo bears, wild boars, deer, and rabbits; and among the deſolate mountains are found great quantities of rock-cryſtal. In the glacieres or ice-valleys, between the high mountains, the air is extremely cold, even in the months of July and Auguſt. The ſurface of theſe ice-valleys looks like a ſea or lake, which, after being agitated by fierce and contrary winds, has been frozen all at once, interſperſed with hideous cracks and chaſms. The noiſe of theſe cracks, when firſt made by the heat of the noon day fun, and reverberated by the ſurrounding rocks and mountains, is aſtoniſhing. The height of the impending mountains is ſuch, that the ſun’s rays ſeldom reach the ice-valleys, except a few hours in the middle of ſummer. The avalanches or ſnow-balls, which the leaſt concuſſion of the air will occaſion, tumble down the mountains with amazing rapidity, continually increaſing, and carrying all before them. People have been taken out alive, after being buried ſeveral days under them. The mountainous nature of this duchy renders the plough a uſeleſs inſtrument of agriculture. The peaſants break up the hungry ſoil with the pickaxe and ſpade, and to improve it carry up mould and dung in baſkets. For the purpoſe of preſerving it from drought in the ſpring and ſummer, they cut ſmall reſervoirs above it, the water of which may be let out at will; and to prevent the earth from giving way, break the declivity of the mountains by building walls on the ſide for its ſupport, which frequently aſſume the appearance of ancient fortification, and are a very pleaſing deception to travellers. The Savoyards carry their better fort of cheeſe into Piedmont, as the flavour is much eſteemed there; but they gain more by their ſkins of bears, chamois, and bouquetins (a ſpecies of the wild goat), or by the ſale of growſe and pheaſants, which they carry in great numbers to Turin.</p><p>The chief rivers are the Rhone, which, on the fide of Geneva, ſeparates Savoy from France; the Arve, which has ſome particles of gold in its ſands; the Iſere, the Seran, the Siers, and the Arc. There are alſo a great many lakes in this country, which yield</p><p>plenty of fiſh, but none of them are very large, together with medicinal and reciprocating ſprings and hot baths.</p><p>The language of the common people is a corrupt French; but the better ſort, and thoſe that live in the great cities, ſpeak as good French as they do in Paris itſelf.</p><p>In their temper, however, and diſpoſition, the Savoyards reſemble the Germans more than the French, retaining ſtill much of the old German honeſty and ſimplicity of manners, which no doubt is partly owing to the poverty and barrenneſs of the country. To this alſo, joined to their longevity and the fruitfulneſs of their women, which are the effects of their cheerful diſpoſition, healthy air, activity, temperance, and ſobriety, it is owing that great numbers of them are obliged to go abroad in queſt of a livelihood, which they earn, thoſe at leaſt who have no trades, by ſhowing marmottes, cleaning ſhoes, ſweeping chimneys, and the like. It is ſaid, that there are generally about 18,000 of them, young and old, about Paris. In ſummer they lie in the ſtreets, and in winter, forty, fifty, <hi rend="italic">or </hi>ſixty of them lodge together in a room: they are ſo honeſt that they may be truſted to any amount The children are often carried abroad in baſkets before they are able to walk. In many villages of Savoy there is hardly a man to be ſeen throughout the year, excepting a month or two. Thoſe that have families generally ſet out and return about the ſame ſeaſon, when their wives commonly lie in, and they never fail to bring home ſome part of their ſmall earnings. Some of them are ſuch conſummate matters of economy, that they ſet up ſhops and make fortunes, and others return home with a competency for the reſt of their days. An old man is often diſpatched with letters, little preſents, and ſome money, from the younger fort, to their parents and relations, and brings back with him freſh colonies, letters, meſſages, and news. The cultivation of their grounds, and the reaping and gathering in of the harveſt and vintage, are generally left to the women and children; but all this is to be underſtood of the mountainous parts of Savoy. Great numbers of the mountaineers of both ſexes are ſaid to be lame and deformed; and they are much ſubject to a kind of wens, which grow about their throats, and very much disfigure them, eſpecially the women; but that is the only inconvenience they feel from them.</p><p>The nobility of Savoy, and the other dominions of the king of Sardinia, labour under great hardſhips and reſtrictions, unheard of in other countries, which we have not room here to particularize. A minute account of them will be found in Mr Keyſler’s Travels. In ſhort, the king has left neither liberty, power, nor much property, to any but himſelf and the clergy, whoſe overgrown wealth he has alſo greatly curtailed.</p><p>No other religion is profeſſed or tolerated in Savoy but that of the church of Rome. The decrees, however, of the council of Trent are not admitted; nor are the churches aſylums for malefactors.</p><p>This duchy is divided into thoſe of Chablais, Genevois, and Savoy Proper, the counties of Tarantaiſe and Maurienne, and the barony of Faucigny.</p><p>SAURIN(James), a celebrated preacher, was born at Niſmes in 1677, and was the ſon of a Proteſtant lawyer of conſiderable eminence. He applied to his ſtudies</p></body></text></TEI>