<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:50Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>1. That they ſhould place the king in his chair of ſtate at the coronation. 2. That they ſhould lead the van of all the royal armies. 3. That they ſhould have a regality within themſelves: and, 4. That if any of Macduff’s family ſhould happen to kill a nobleman un- premeditately, he ſhould pay 24 marks of ſilver, and, if a plebeian, 12. The king’s next care was to reinſtate in their fathers poſſeſſions all the children who had been diſinherited by the late tyrant; which he did in a convention of his nobles held at Forfar. In the time of William the conqueror, we find Malcolm engaged in a dangerous war with England, the occaſion of which was as follows. On the death of Edward the Confeſſor, Harold ſeized the throne of England, to the prejudice of Edgar Atheling the true heir to the crown. However, he created him earl of Oxford, and treated him with great reſpect; but on the defeat and death of Harold, William diſcovered ſome jealouſy of Edgar. Soon alter, William having occaſion to pay a viſit to his dominions in Normandy, he appointed Edgar to attend him, along with ſome other noblemen whom he ſuſpected to be in his intereſt; but on his return to England, he found the people ſo much diſaffected to his government, that he proceeded with great ſeverity, which obliged great numbers of his ſubjects to take refuge in Cumberland and the ſouthern parts of Malcolm’s dominions. Edgar had two ſiſters, Margaret and Chriſtina: theſe, with his two chief friends, Goſpatric and Marteſwin, ſoon made him ſenſible how precarious his life was under ſuch a jealous tyrant, and perſuaded him to make preparations for flying into Hungary or ſome foreign country. Edgar accordingly ſet ſail with his</p><p>mother Agatha, his two ſiſters, and a great train of Anglo-Saxon noblemen; but by ſtreſs of weather was forced into the frith of Forth, where the illuſtrious exiles landed at the place ſince that time called the Queen'<hi rend="italic">s Ferry.</hi> Malcolm no ſooner heard of their landing than he paid them a viſit in perſon; and at this viſit he fell in love with the princeſs Margaret. In conſequence of this, the chief of Edgar’s party repaired, to the court of Scotland. William ſoon made a formal demand of Edgar; and on Malcolm’s refuſal, declared war againſt him.</p><p>William was the moſt formidable enemy the Scots had ever encountered, as having not only the whole force of England, but of Normandy, at his command. However, as he had tyrannized moſt unmercifully over his Engliſh ſubjects, they were much more inclined to aſſiſt his enemies than their own prince; and he even found himſelf obliged to give up the county of Northumberland to Goſpatric, who had followed Edgar, upon condition of his making war on the Scots. This nobleman accordingly invaded Cumberland; in return for which Malcolm ravaged Northumberland in a dreadful manner, carrying off an immenſe booty, and inviting at the ſame time the Iriſh and Danes to join him.</p><p>Even at this time the Danes kept up their claims upon the crown of England, ſb that they could not be ſuppoſed very zealous for the intereſt of Edgar. The Iriſh were alſo intereſted in advancing the cauſe of Harold’s three ſons, who had put themſelves under their protection; and beſides, their chief view ſeems to have been to obtain plunder at the expence of any party. However, as all theſe views tended to the pulling down of William’s power, an union was  formed againſt him;</p><p>but when they came to particular ſtipulations, the parties immediately diſagreed. The three ſons of Harold, with a body of Iriſh, made a deſcent upon Somerſetſhire, and defeated a body of Engliſh; but the Iriſh having thus obtained an opportunity of acquiring ſome booty, immediately retired with it, after having ravaged the country. The Danes landed at the mouth of the Humber from 40 ſmall ſhips, where they were joined by Edgar and his party; and had the allies been unanimous, it is probable that William’s government would have been overthrown.</p><p>By this time William had taken from Goſpatric the earldom of Northumberland, and given it to Robert Cummin one of his Norman barons; but the Northumbrians having joined Goſpatric, and received the Danes as their countrymen, murdered Cummin and all his followers at Durham, where they had been guilty of great cruelties. After this they laid ſiege to the forts built by William in Yorkſhire; but not being able to reduce them, the Engliſh, Scots, and Danes, united their forces, took the city of York itſelf, and put to the ſword three thouland Normans who were there in garriſon; and this ſucceſs was followed by many incurſions and ravages, in which the Danes and Northumbrians acquired great booty. It ſoon appeared, however, that theſe allies had the intereſt of Edgar no more at heart than the Iriſh; and that all the dependence of this forlorn prince was upon Malcolm, and the few Engliſhmen who had followed his fortune: for the booty was no ſooner obtained, than the Danes retired to their ſhips, and the Northumbrians to their habitations, as though they had been in perfect ſafety. But in the mean time William, having raiſed a conſiderable army, advanced northwards. He firſt took a ſevere revenge upon the Northumbrians; then he reduced the city of York, and put to death all the inhabitants; and perceiving that danger was ſtill threatened by the Danes, he bribed them with a ſum of money to depart to their own country.</p><p>Malcolm was now left alone to encounter this formidable adversary; who, finding himſelf unable to oppoſe ſo great a force, withdrew to his own dominions, where he remained for ſome time upon the defenſive, but not without making great preparations for invading England once more. His ſecond invaſion took place in the year 1071, while William was employed in quelling an inſurrection in Wales. He is ſaid at this time to have behaved with the greateſt cruelty. He invaded England by Cumberland; ravaged Teeſdale; and at a place called <hi rend="italic">Hundreds-keld,</hi> he maſſacred ſome Engliſh noblemen, with all their followers. From thence he marched to Cleveland in the north-riding of Yorkſhire; which he alſo ravaged with the utmoſt cruelty, ſending back the booty with part of his army to Scotland: after which, he pillaged the biſhopric of Durham, where he is ſaid not to have, ſpared the moſt. ſacred edifices, but to have burnt them to the ground. In the mean time Goſpatric, to whom William had had again ceded Northumberland, attempted to make diverſion in his favour, by invading Cumberland: but being utterly defeated by Malcolm, he was obliged to ſhut himſelf up in Bamborough caſtle; while Malcolm returned in triumph with his army to Scotland, where he married the princeſs Margaret.</p><p>The next year William, having greatly augmented</p></body></text></TEI>