<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>infantry, and 400 men at arms. Edward would not permit them to enter Scotland by the
                uſual way, as he himſelf did not yet chooſe openly to take part in their quarrel.
                For this reaſon they were obliged to take ſhipping, and landed at a place called <hi
                    rend="italic">Ravenſhare, Ravenspur,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ravensburgh,</hi>
                at the mouth of the Humber @@(<hi rend="smallcaps">h).</hi> Randolph, having
                intelligence of the Engliſh preparations, had marched an army to the frontiers of
                Eaſt Lothian; but, being afterwards informed of the naval armament, he marched
                northwards; but died at Muſſelburgh, ſix miles eaſt of Edinburgh, on the 20th of
                July 1332. With him died the glory of Scotland. The earl of Marr, a man whoſe only
                merit conſiſted in his being related to the royal family, was choſen to ſucceed him
                in the regency.—Edward, in the mean time, fell upon a moſt curious expedient to ſhow
                the juſtice of his cauſe. In March 1332, he had publiſhed a prohibition for any
                perſon to infringe the treaty of Northampton. The diſinherited lords had been
                ſuffered to embark, expreſsly for the purpoſe of invading Scotland, after this
                prohibition was publiſhed. <hi rend="italic">After they were gone,</hi> Henry de
                Percy was empowered to puniſh thoſe who ſhould preſume to array themſelves in
                contempt of his prohibition; and becauſe he underſtood that the Scots were arming in
                order to repel thoſe invaders whom Edward had indirectly ſent againſt them, he
                empowered Henry de Percy to arm againſt them.</p>
            <p>On the 31st of July, Edward Baliol and his aſſociates landed in the neighbourhood of
                Kinghorn, on the Forth; routed the earl of Fife, who oppoſed them; and marched next
                day to Dunfermline. Having then ordered his fleet to wait for him at the mouth of
                the Tay, he proceeded northwards, and encamped on the Miller’s acre at Forteviot,
                with the river Earn in front. Nothing, however, could be more dangerous than his
                ſituation at preſent, and his deſtruction would have been inevitable. The earl of
                Marr was encamped with a numerous army on the oppoſite bank of the river Earn, in
                the neighbourhood of Duplin; and another, nearly as numerous, had advanced from the
                ſouth, through the Lothians and Sfirlingſhire, and fixed its quarters at
                Auchterarder, eight miles to the west of Forteviot. Historians differ as to the
                number of the two armies. Fordun ſays, that the regent had with him 30,000 men, and
                the earl of March as many; and that Baliol had between 500 and 600 men at arms, that
                is, horſemen completely armed. Hemingford reckons each of the Scots armies at
                40,000, and Baliol’s at 500 armed men. Knyghton ſays, that Baliol, when he landed in
                Fife, had 300 armed men, and 3000 more of different forts; but that he had in all
                only 2500 men in his camp at Earn. In this deſperate ſituation, the Engliſh general
                formed a deſign of attacking the Scots in their camp. They were directed to a ford
                by Andrew Murray of Tullibardine. The Scots kept no watch, but abandoned themſelves
                to intemperance and riotous mirth; while their enemies, led by Alexander Moubray,
                croſſed the river at midnight. They aſcended a riſing ground, came unperceived on
                the right flank of the Scottiſh army, and made a dreadful ſlaughter. At the first
                attack, young Randolph halted with 300 men at arms to oppoſe the enemy; and being
                ſeconded by Murdoch earl of Menteith, Alexander Fraſer, and Robert Bruce natural ſon
                to the late king, he gave a check te the Engliſh, and maintained the combat on equal
                terms. But now the regent himſelf, along with the whole multitude, ruſhed forward to
                battle without the leaſt order: ſo that while the hindmoſt preſſed on, the foremoſt
                were thrown down, trodden upon, and ſuffocated. The ſlaughter laſted many hours, and
                the remains of this vaſt army were utterly diſperſed. Many men of eminence were
                killed; among whom were Donald earl of Marr, author of the whole cataſtrophe; Thomas
                earl of Moray, Murdoch earl of Menteith, Robert earl of Carrick,</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(h)</hi> This place does not now exiſt; having been
                overwhelmed by the ſea many centuries ago.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
