<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>devil whom God compelled to praiſe faints. He was among the number of poets whoſe genius was as impetuous as his muſe was decent.</p><p>La Bruyere has painted the character of this Angular and truly original poet in the moſt lively colours.</p><p>Image a man of great facility of temper, complaiſant and docile, in an inſtant violent, choleric, paſſionate, and capricious. A man Ample, credulous, playful, volatile, puerile; in a word, a child in gray hairs: but let him collect himſelf, or rather call forth his interior genius, I venture to ſay, without his knowledge or privacy, what ſallies! what elevation! what images! what latinity! Do you ſpeak of one and the ſame perſon, you will aſk? Yes, of the ſame; of Theodas, and of him alone. He ſhrieks, he jumps, he rolls upon the ground, he roars, he ſtorms; and in the midſt of this tempeſt, a flame iſſues that ſhines, that rejoices. Without a figure, he rattles like a fool, and thinks like a wiſe man. He utters truths in a ridiculous way; and, in an idiotic manner, rational and ſenſible things. It is aſtoniſhing to find good ſenſe diſcloſe itſelf from the boſom of buffoonery, accompanied with grimaces and contortions. What ſhall I ſay more? He does and he ſays better than he knows. Theſe are like two fouls that are unacquainted with each other, which have each their turn and ſeparate functions. A feature would be wanting in this extraordinary portrait, if I omitted ſaying, that he has at once an inſatiable thirſt for praiſe, ready to throw himſelf at the mercy of the critics, and at the bottom ſo docile as to profit by their cenſure. I begin to perſuade myſelf that I have been drawing the portraits of two different perſons: it would not be impoſſible to find a third in Theodas; for he is a good man, a pleaſant man, an excellent man. ”</p><p>This poet ought not to be confounded with <hi rend="italic">Claude de Santeuil,</hi> his brother, a learned eccleſiaſtic, who alſo wrote ſeveral hymns in the Paris Breviary under the name of <hi rend="italic">Santolius Maglioranus,</hi> a name given him from his having lived a long time in the ſeminary of St Magliore at Paris, in quality of ſecular eccleſiaſtic. He was eſteemed not only for his poetical abilities, but alſo for his profound erudition and his exemplary piety. He died at Paris in 1684, aged 57. He wrote ſeveral other pieces of poetry, beſides his hymns, which are printed with his brother’s works.</p><p>SANTILLANE, a ſea-port town of Spain, in the province of Aſturias, of which it is the capital. It is ſeated on the ſea-coaſt, 55 miles eaſt of Oviedo, and 200 north-weſt of Madrid. W. Long. 4. 33. N. Lat. 43∙ 30.</p><p>SANTOLINA, <hi rend="smallcaps">lavender-cotton,</hi> in botany: A genus of the order of polygamia aequalis, belonging to the ſyngeneſia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Compoſite.</hi> The receptacle is paleaceous; there is no pappus; the calyx imbricated and hemiſpherical.</p><p>The moſt remarkable ſpecies are, 1. The chamaecy-pariſus, or common lavender-cotton, which has been long known in the Engliſh gardens; it was formerly titled <hi rend="italic">abrotanum ſaemina, </hi>or<hi rend="italic"> ſemale ſouthernwood, </hi>and by the corruption of words was called <hi rend="italic">brοtany</hi> by the market- people: it grows naturally in Spain, Italy, and the warm parts of Europe. This hath a ligneous ſtalk, dividing into many branches, garniſhed with ſlender hoa</p><p>ry leaves, that are four ways indented, and have a rank, ſtrong, odour when handled. The branches are terminated by a ſingle flower, compoſed of many hermaphrodite florets, which are ſiſtular, cut into five parts at the top, of a ſulphur colour, and are included in one common ſcaly empalement, having no borders or rays. Theſe are ſucceeded by ſmall, oblong, ſtriated ſeeds, which are ſeparated by ſcaly chaff, and ripen in the empalement; the plants love a dry ſoil and a ſheltered ſituation. 2. The villoſa, with woolly leaves, has a ſhrubby ſtalk, which branches out like the former, but the plants ſeldom grow ſo tall. The branches are garniſhed very cloſely below with leaves ſhaped like thoſe of the other fort, but ſhorter, thicker, and whiter; the flowers are much larger, and the brims of the florets are more reflexed; they are of a deeper ſulphur colour than the other. It grows naturally in Spain. 3. The decumbens, with linear leaves, is of lower ſtature than either of the former, ſeldom riſing more than 15 or 16 inches high. The branches ſpread horizontally near the ground, and are garniſhed with ſhorter leaves than either of the former, which are hoary and finely indented; the ſtalks are terminated by ſingle flowers, of a bright yellow colour, which are larger than thoſe of the firſt fort. 4. The virens, with very long linear leaves, riſes higher than either of the former. The branches are more diffuſed; they are ſlender, ſrnooth, and garniſhed with very narrow long leaves, which are of a deep green colour, but two ways indented; the ſtalks are ſlender, naked towards the top, and terminated by ſingle flowers of a gold colour. 5. The roſmarinifolia, with linear entire leaves, hath ſhrubby ſtalks, which riſe about three feet high, ſending out long ſlender branches, garniſhed with ſingle linear leaves of a pale-green colour. The ſtalks are terminated by large, ſingle, globular flowers, of a pale ſulphur colour. 6. The minor, with linear obtuſe leaves, is ſomewhat like the fifth; but the branches are ſhorter, thicker, and cloſer garniſhed with leaves, which come out in cluſters. The flower- ſtalks are ſparſedly diſpoſed, and have leaves to their top; the flowers are ſmall, and of a yellow colour. 7. The chamsemelifolia, with obtuſe woolly leaves,  hath ſhrubby ſtalks, which riſe three feet high, garniſhed with broader leaves than either of the former, whoſe indentures are looſer, but double; they are hoary, and when bruiſed have an odour like chamomile. The leaves are placed pretty far aſunder, and the ſtalks are garniſhed with them to the top. The ſtalks are divided likewiſe at the top into two or three foot-ſtalks, each ſuſtaining one pretty large ſulphur-coloured flower.</p><p>All theſe plants may be cultivated ſo as to become ornaments to a garden, particularly in ſmall boſquets of ever-green ſhrubs, where, if they are artfully intermixed with other plants of the ſame growth, and placed in the front line, they will make an agreeable variety; eſpecially if care be taken to trim them twice in a ſummer, to keep them within bounds, otherwiſe their branches are apt to ſtraggle, and in wet weather to be borne down and diſplaced, which renders them unſightly; but when they are kept in order, their hoary and different-coloured leaves will have a pretty effect in ſuch plantations. —They may be propagated by planting ſlips or cuttings during the ſpring, in a</p></body></text></TEI>