<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:41Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>white, to a browniſh, yellowiſh, greeniſh, &amp;c. white. 2 The red and reddiſh
                ſands, both pure and impure. <hi rend="italic">3.</hi> The yellow ſands, whether
                pure or mixed, are alſo very numerous. 4. The brown ſands, diſtinguiſhed in the ſame
                manner. 5. The black ſands, whereof there are only two ſpecies, viz. a fine ſhining
                greyiſh-black fand, and another of a fine ſhining reddiſh-black colour. 6. The green
                kind; of which there is only one known ſpecies, viz. a coarſe variegated duſky green
                fand, common in Virginia.</p>
            <p>Sand is of great uſe in the glaſs-manufacture; a white kind of fand being employed
                for making of the white glaſs, and a coarſe greeniſh-looking fand for the green
                glaſs.</p>
            <p>In agriculture, it ſeems to be the office of ſand to make unctuous earths fertile,
                and fit to ſupport vegetables, &amp;c. For earth alone, we find, is liable to co-
                aleſce, and gather into a hard coherent maſs, as appears in clay; and being thus
                embodied, and as it were glued together, is no way diſpoſed to nouriſh vegetables.
                But if ſuch earth be mixed with fand, its pores are thereby kept open, and the earth
                itſelf looſe, ſo as thus to give room for the juices to aſcend, and for plants to be
                nouriſhed thereby. A vegetable planted only in fand, or in a fat glebe, or in earth,
                receives little growth or increaſe; but a mixture of both renders the maſs fertile.
                In effect, earth is in ſome meaſure made organical by means of fand; pores and
                ſpaces, ſomething analogous to veſſels, being thereby maintained, by which the
                juices may be conveyed, prepared, digeſted, circulated, and at length diſcharged.
                Common fand is, therefore, a very good addition, by way of manure, to all forts of
                clay-lands; it warms them, and makes them more open and looſe.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SAND-Bags,</hi> in the art of war. See <hi rend="italic">SAcκs oſ
                    Earth.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SAND-Eel,</hi> in ichthyology See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Ammodytes.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SAND-Flοods,</hi> a name given to the flowing of ſand ſo common in
                the deſerts of Arabia. Mr Bruce gives the following accurate deſcription of ſome
                that he ſaw in travelling thro’ that long and dreary deſert. “At one o’clock (ſays
                he) we alighted among ſome acacia-trees at Waadi el Halboub, having gone twenty-one
                miles. We were here at once ſurpriſed and terrified by a ſight furely one of the
                moſt magnificent in the world. In that vaſt expanſe of deſert from weft and to
                north-weſt of us, we ſaw a number of prodigious pillars of fand at different
                diſtances, at times moving with great celerity, at others ſtalking on with a
                majeſtic ſlowneſs: at intervals we thought they were coming in a few minutes to
                overwhelm us; and ſmall quantities of ſand did actually more than once reach us.
                Again they would retreat ſo as to be almoſt out of ſight, their tops reaching to the
                very clouds. There the tops often ſeparated from the bodies; and theſe, once
                disjoined, diſperſed in the air, and did not appear more. Sometimes they were broken
                near the middle, as if ſtruck with a large cannon ſhot. About noon they began to
                advance with conſiderable ſwiftneſs upon us, the wind being very ſtrong at north.
                Eleven of them ranged alongſide of us about the diſtance of three miles. The
                greateſt diameter of the largeſt appeared to me at that diſtance as if it would
                meaſure ten feet. They retired from us with a wind at ſouth-eaſt, leaving an
                impreſſion upon my mind to which I can give no name, though ſurely one ingredient in
                it was fear, with a conſiderable deal</p>
            <p>of wonder and aſtoniſhment. It was in vain to think of flying, the ſwifteſt horſe or
                faſteſt ſailing ſhip could be of no uſe to carry us out of this danger; and the full
                perſuaſion of this rivetted me as if to the ſpot where I flood, and let the camels
                gain on me ſo much in my ſtate of lameneſs, that it was with ſome difficulty I could
                overtake them.</p>
            <p>“The ſame appearance of moving pillars of ſand preſented themſelves to us this day in
                form and diſpoſition like thoſe we had ſeen at Waadi Halboub, only they ſeemed to be
                more in number and leſs in ſize. They came ſeveral times in a direction cloſe upon
                us, that is, I believe, within leſs than two miles. They began immediately after
                ſun-riſe, like a thick wood, and almoſt darkened the ſun: his rays ſhining through
                them for near an hour, gave them an appearance of pillars of fire, Our people now
                became deſperate: the Greek ſhrieked out, and ſaid it was the day of judgment.
                Iſmael pronounced it to be hell, and the Tucorories, that the world was on fire. I
                aſked Idris if ever he had before ſeen ſuch a ſight? He ſaid he had often ſeen them
                as terrible, though never worſe; but what he feared moſt was that extreme redneſs in
                the air, which was a ſure preſage of the coming of the ſimoom.” See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Simoom.</hi></p>
            <p>The flowing of ſand, though far from being ſo tremendous and hurtful as in Arabia, is
                of very bad conſequences in this country, as many valuable pieces of land have thus
                been entirely loſt; of which we give the following inſtances from Mr Pennant,
                together with a probable means of preventing them in future. “I have more; than once
                (ſays he), on the eaſtern coaſts of Scotland, obſerved the calamitous ſtate of
                ſeveral extenſive tracts, formerly in a moſt flouriſhing condition, at preſent
                covered with ſands, unſtable as thoſe of the deſerts of Arabia. The pariſh of
                Furvie, in the county of Aberdeen, is now reduced to two farms, and above L. 500
                a-year loſt to the Errol family, as appears by the oath of the factor in 1600, made
                before the court of ſeſſion, to aſcertain the miniſter’s ſalary. Not a veſtige is to
                be ſeen of any buildings, unleſs a fragment of the church.</p>
            <p>"The eſtate of Coubin, near Forres, is another melancholy inſtance. This tract was
                once worth L. 300 a-year, at this time overwhelmed with ſand. This ſtrange
                inundation was ſtill in motion in 1769, chiefly when a ſtrong wind prevailed. Its
                motion is ſo rapid, that I have been aſſured, that an apple-tree has been ſo covered
                with it in one ſeaſon, that only the very ſummit appeared. This diſtreſs was brought
                on about ninety years ago, and was occaſioned by the cutting down ſome trees, and
                pulling up the bent or ſtar which grew on the ſand-hills; which at laſt gave riſe to
                the act of 15 George II. c. 33. to prohibit the deſtruction of this uſeful
                plant.</p>
            <p>“I beg leave to ſuggeſt to the public a poſſible means of putting a ſtop to theſe
                deſtructive ravages. Providence hath kindly formed this plant to grow only in pure
                fand. Mankind was left to make, in after-times, an application of it ſuitable to
                their wants. The ſand- hills, on a portion of the Flintſhire ſhores, in the pariſh
                of Llanaſa, are covered with it naturally, and kept firm in their place. The Dutch
                perhaps owe the exiſtence of part at leaſt of their country to the ſowing of it on
                the <hi rend="italic">mobile ſolum,</hi> their ſand-banks.</p>
            <p>"My humane and amiable friend, the late Benjamin</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
