<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ry to give some public teſtimony of their diſapproving the late king’s connection with England. It was therefore enacted, “That as the king was now of an age to marry a noble princeſs, <hi rend="italic">born and defended of a noble and worshiρful houſe;</hi> an honourable embaſſy ſhould be ſent to the realms of France, Brittany, Spain, and other places, in order to conclude the matter.” This embaſſy was to be very ſplendid. It was to conſiſt of a biſhop, an earl, or lord of parliament, a ſecretary, who was generally a clergyman, and a knight. They were to be attended by 50 horſemen; 5000 l. was to be allowed them for the diſcharge of their embaſſy, and they were empowered to renew the ancient league between France and Scotland; and, in the mean time, a herald, or, as he was called, a <hi rend="italic">trusty squire,</hi> was ſent abroad to viſit the ſeveral courts of Europe, in order to find out a proper match for the king. One conſiderable obſtacle, however, lay in the way of this embaſſy. The pope had laid under an interdict all thoſe who had appeared in arms againſt the late king; and the party who now governed Scotland were looked upon by all the powers of Europe as rebels and murderers. The embaſſy was therefore ſuſpended for a conliderable time; for it was not till the year 1491 that the pope could be prevailed upon to take off the interdict, upon the moſt humble ſubmiſſions and profeſſions of repentance made by the guilty parties.</p><p>In the mean time, the many good qualities which diſcovered themſelves in the young king began to conciliate the affections of his people to him. Being conſidered, however, as little better than a priſoner in the hands of his father’s murderers, ſeveral of the nobility made uſe of that as a pretence for taking arms. The moſt forward of theſe was the earl of Lenox, who with 2000 men attempted to ſurpriſe the town of Stirling; but, being betrayed by one of his own men, he was defeated, taken unawares, and the caſtle of Dumbarton, of which he was the keeper, taken by the oppoſite party. In the north, the earls of Huntley and Marſhal, with the Lord Forbes, complained that they had been deceived, and declared their reſolution to revenge the late king’s death. Lord Forbes having procured the bloody ſhirt of the murdered prince, diſplayed it on the point of a lance, as a banner under which all loyal ſubjects ſhould lift themſelves. However, after the defeat of Lenox, the northern chieftains found themſelves incapable of marching ſouthwards, and were therefore obliged to abandon their enterpriſe. The cauſe of the murdered king was next undertaken by Henry VII. of England, who made an offer to Sir Andrew Wood of five ſhips to revenge it. The admiral accepted the propoſal; but the Engliſh behaving as pirates, and plundering indiſcriminately all who came in their way, he thought proper to ſeparate himſelf from them, yet without offering to attack or oppoſe them. Upon this, James was adviſed to ſend for the admiral, to offer him a pardon, and a commiſſion to act againſt the Engliſh freebooters. Wood accepted of the king’s offer; and being well provided with ammunition and artillery, he, with two ſhips only, attacked the five Engliſh veſſels, all of which he took, and brought their crews priſoners to Leith, for which he was nobly rewarded by his majeſty.</p><p>This conduct of Wood was highly reſented by the king of England, who immediately vowed revenge. The Scottiſh admiral’s ſhips had been fitted out for commerce as well as war, and Henry commanded his beſt ſea-officer, Sir Stephen Bull, to intercept him on his return from. Flanders, whither he had gone upon a commercial voyage. Wood had no more than two ſhips with him: the Engliſh admiral had three; and thoſe much larger, and carrying a greater weight of metal, than the Scottiſh veſſels. The Engliſh took their ſtation at the iſland of May, in the mouth of the Frith of Forth, and, having come unawares upon their enemies, fired two guns as a ſignal for their ſurrendering themſelves. The Scottiſh commander encouraged his men as well as he could; and finding them determined to ſtand by him to the laſt, began the engagement in fight of numberleſs ſpectators who appeared on both ſides of the frith. The fight continued all that day, and was renewed with redoubled fury in the morning; but, in the mean time, the ebb-tide and a ſouth wind had carried both ſquadrons to the mouth of the Tay. Here the Engliſh fought under great diſadvantages, by reaſon of the ſand-banks; and before they could get clear oſ them, all the three were obliged to ſubmit to the Scots, who carried them to Dundee. Wood treated his priſoners with great humanity; and having afterwards preſented them to King James, the latter diſmiſſed them not only without ranſom, but with preſents to the officers and crews, and a letter to King Henry. To this Henry returned a polite anſwer, a truce was concluded, and all differences for the preſent were accommodated.</p><p>James all this time had continued to diſplay ſuch moderation in his government, and appeared to have the advantage of his ſubjects ſo much at heart, that they became gradually well affected to his government, and in 1490 all parties were fully reconciled. We may from thence date the commencement of the reign of James IV.; and the next year the happineſs of his kingdom was completed, by taking off the pope’s interdict, and giving the king abſolution for the hand he had in his father’s death.</p><p>Tranquillity being thus reſtored, the negociations concerning the king’s marriage began to take place, but met with ſeveral interruptions. In 1493, Henry VII. propoſed a match between the king of Scotland and his couſin the princeſs Catharine. James was too much attached to France to be fond of Engliſh connections, and probably thought this match below his dignity; in conſequence of which the propoſal was treated with contempt. However, notwithſtanding this ill ſucceſs, Henry made another offer of alliance with James; and, in 1495, propoſed a marriage betwixt him and his eldeſt daughter Margaret. This propoſal was accepted: but the match ſeems not to have been at all agreeable to James; for, at the very time in which he was negociating the marriage, he not only protected Perkin Warbeck, the avowed enemy and pretender to the crown of Henry, but invaded England on his account. This conduct was highly reſented by the Engliſh parliament; but Henry himſelf forgave even this groſs insult, and the marriage negociations were once more reſumed. The bride was no more than ten years and  ſix months old; and being only the fourth degree of blood from James, it was neceſſary to procure a diſpenſation from the pope. This being obtained, a treaty of perpetual peace was concluded between the two</p></body></text></TEI>