<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:30Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>43d order, <hi rend="italic">Dumofae.</hi> The calyx is quinquepartite; the corolla quinqueſid; the berry triſpermous.</p><p>The moſt remarkable ſpecies are, I. The nigra, or common black elder-tree, riſes with a tree-ſtem, branching numerouſly into a large ſpreading head, twenty or thirty feet high; pinnated leaves, of two or three pair of oval lobes and an odd one; and large five parted umbels of white flowers towards the ends of the branches, ſucceeded by bunches of black and other different coloured berries, in the varieties; which are. —Common black-berried elder-tree—White-berried elder—Green- berried elder—Laciniated, or parſley-leaved elder, having the folioles much laciniated, ſo as to reſemble parſley leaves—Gold-ſtriped-leaved elder—Silver-ſtriped elder—Silver-duſted elder. 2. The racemoſa, race-moſe red-berried elder, riſes with a tree-like ſtem, branching ten or twelve feet high, having reddiſh-brown branches and buds; pinnated leaves of ſix or ſeven oval deeply-ſawed lobes; and compound, oval, racemous, cluſters of wſhitiſh-green flowers, ſucceeded by oval cluſters of red berries. This is a reſident of the mountainous parts of the ſouth of Europe, and is retained in our gardens as a flowering ſhrub, having a peculiar Angularity in its oval-cluſtered flowers and berries. 3. The Canadenſis, or Canada ſhrubby elder, riſes with a ſhrub- by ſtem, branching eight or ten feet high, having reddiſh ſhoots; ſomewhat bipinnated leaves, often ternate below, the other compoſed of five, ſeven, or nine oval lobes; and towards the ends of the branches, cymoſe. quinquepartite umbels of flowers, ſucceeded by blackiſh red berries. All the forts of elder are of the deciduous tribe, very hardy, and grow freely anywhere; are generally free ſhooters, but particularly the common elder and varieties, which make remarkably ſtrong, jointed ſhoots, of ſeveral feet in length, in one ſeaſon; and they flower moſtly in ſummer, except the racemoſe elder,  which generally begins flowering in April; and the branches being large, ſpreading, and very abundant, are exceedingly conſpicuous; but they emit a moſt diſagreeable odour. The flowers are ſucceeded in the moſt of the forts by large bunches of ripe berries in autumn, which, although very unpalateable to eat, are in high eſtimation for making that well known cordial liquor called <hi rend="italic">elder wine,</hi> particularly the common black- berried elder. The merit of the elder in gardening may be both for uſe and ornament, eſpecially in large grounds.</p><p>SAMIAN <hi rend="smallcaps">earth,</hi> in the materia medica, the name of two ſpecies of marl uſed in medicine, viz. 1. The white kind, called by the ancients <hi rend="italic">collyrium ſamium,</hi> being aſtringent, and therefore good in diarrhoeas, dyſenteries, and hæmorrhagies; they alſo uſed it externally in inflammations of all kinds. 2. The browniſh-white kind, called <hi rend="italic">after ſamius</hi> by Dioſcorides; this alſo ſtands recommended as an aſtringent.</p><p>SAMIELS, the Arabian name of a hot wind peculiar to the deſert of Arabia. @@ It blows over the deſert in the months of July and Auguſt from the north-weſt quarter, and ſometimes it continues with all its violence to the very gates of <hi rend="italic">Bagdad,</hi> but never affects any body within the walls. Some years it does not blow at all, and in others it appears ſix, eight, or ten times, but ſeldom continues more than a few minutes at a time. It often paſſes with the apparent quickneſs of lightning. The Arabians and Perſians, who are acquainted with the appearance of the ſky at or near the time this wind ariſeth, have warning of its approach by a thick haze, which appears like a cloud of dull ariſing out of the horizon; and they immediately upon this appearance throw themſelves with their faces to the ground, and continue in that poſition till the wind is paſſed, which frequently happens almoſt inſtantaneouſly; but if, on the contrary, they are not careful or briſk enough to take this precaution, which is ſometimes the caſe, and they get the full force of the wind, it is inſtant death.</p><p>The above method is the only one which they take to avoid the effects of this fatal blaſt; and when it is over, they get up and look round them for their companions; and if they ſee any one lying motionleſs, they take hold of an arm or leg, and pull and jerk it with ſome force; and if the limb thus agitated ſeparates from the body, it is a certain ſign that the wind has had its full effect; but if, on the contrary, the arm or leg does not come away, it is a ſure ſign there is life remaining, although to every outward appearance the perſon is dead; and in that caſe they immediately cover him or them with clothes, and adminiſter ſome warm diluting liquor to cauſe a perſpiration, which is certainly but ſlowly brought about.</p><p>The Arabs themſelves can fay little or nothing about the nature of this wind, only that it always leaves behind it a very ſtrong ſulphureous ſmell, and that the air at theſe times is quite clear, except about the horizon, in the north-weſt quarter, before obſerved, which gives warning of its approach. We have not been able to learn whether the dead bodies are ſcorched, or diſſolved into a kind of gelatinous ſubſtance; but from the ſtories current about them, there has been frequent reaſon to believe the latter; and in that caſe ſuch fatal effects may be attributed rather to a noxious vapour than to an abſolute and exceſſive heat. The ſtory of its going to the gates of Bagdad and no farther may be reaſonably enough accounted for, if the effects are attributed to a poiſonous vapour, and not an exceſſive heat. The above mentioned wind, Samiel, is ſo well known in the neighbourhood of Bagdad and Baſſora, that the very children ſpeak of it with dread.</p><p>SAMOGITIA, a province of Poland, bounded on the north by Courland, on the eaſt by Lithuania, on the weſt by the Baltic Sea, and on the ſouth by Regal Pruſſia, being about 175 miles in length and 125 in breadth. It is full of foreſts and very high mountains, which feed a great number of cattle, and produce a large quantity of honey. There are alſo very active horſes, in high eſteem. The inhabitants are clowniſh, but honeſt; and they will not allow a young woman to go out in the night without a candle in her hand and two bells at her girdle. Roſſenna and Wormia are the principal places.</p><p>SAMOIEDA, a country of the Ruffian empire, between Aſiatic Tartary and Archangel, lying along the ſea-coaſt as far as Siberia. The inhabitants are ſo rude a people that they can hardly pretend to humanity, except in their face and figure: they have little underſtanding, and in many things reſemble brutes, for they will eat carrion of every kind. They travel on the ſnow on ſledges, drawn with an animal like a reindeer, but with the horns of a ſtag. Thoſe who have ſeen them affirm, that no people on the earth make ſuch ſhocking figures; their ſtature is ſhort; their ſhoulders</p><p>@@@ [mu'] <hi rend="italic">Ives's Voyage from England to India in 1754.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>