<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Levi, Ben Gerſon, and Abarbanel. The greater part of theſe writers maintain, that
                ſacrifices were at firſt a human inſtitution; and that God, in order to prevent
                their being offered to idols, introduced them into his ſervice, though he did not
                approve of them as good in themſelves, or as proper rites of worſhip. That the
                infinitely wise and good God ſhould introduce into his ſervice improper rites of
                worſhip, appears to us ſo extremely improbable, that we cannot but wonder how ſuch
                an opinion ſhould ever have found its way into the minds of ſuch men as thoſe who
                held it. Warburton’s theory of ſacriſice is much more plauſible, and being more
                lately publiſhed, is worthy of particular examination.</p>
            <p>According to this ingenious prelate, ſacriſices had their origin in the ſentiments of
                the human heart, and in the ancient mode of converſmg by action in aid of words.
                Gratitude to God for benefits received is natural to the mind of man, as well as his
                bounden duty. “This duty (ſays the biſhop @@*) was in the moſt early times
                diſcharged in expreſſive actions, the leaſt equivocal of which was the offerer’s
                bringing the firſt fruits of paſturage or agriculture to that ſequeſtered place
                where the Deity uſed to be more ſolemnly invoked, at the ſtated times of public
                worſhip; and there preſenting them in homage, with a demand which ſpoke to this
                purpoſe. — ‘I do hereby acknowledge thee, O my God! to be the author and giver of
                all good: and do now, with humble gratitude, return my warmeſt thanks for theſe thy
                bleſſings particularly beſtowed upon me. ”—Things thus devoted became thenceforth
                ſacred: and to prevent their <hi rend="italic">deſecration,</hi> the readieſt way
                was to send them to the table of the prieſt, or to conſume them in the fire of the
                altar. Such, in the opinion of our author, was the origin of euchariſtical
                ſacriſices. <hi rend="italic">Impetratory </hi>or <hi rend="italic">precative</hi>
                ſacriſices had, he thinks, the fame origin, and were contrived to expreſs by action
                an invocation for the continuance of God’s favour. “Expiatory ſacrifices (ſays the
                learned prelate) were in their own nature as intelligible, and in practice as
                rational, as either of the other two. Here, inſtead of preſenting the firſt fruits
                of agriculture and paſturage, in corn, wine, oil, and wool, as in the euchariſtical,
                or a portion of what was to be ſown or otherwiſe propagated, as in the <hi
                    rend="italic">impetratory; </hi>ſome choſen animal precious to the repenting
                criminal, who deprecates or ſuppoſed to be obnoxious to the Deity who is to be
                appealed, was offered up and ſlain at the altar, in an action which, in all
                languages, when tranſlated into words, ſpeaks to this purpoſe: — ‘I confeſs my
                tranſgreſſions at thy footſtool, O my God! and with the deepeſt contrition implore
                thy pardon; confessing that I deſerve death for thoſe my offences. ’— The latter
                part of the confeſſion was more forcibly ex- preſſed by the <hi rend="italic"
                    >actiοn</hi> of ſtriking the devoted animal, and depriving it of life; which,
                when put into words, concluded in this manner, —‘ And I own that I myſelf deferve
                the death which I now inflict on this animal. ’</p>
            <p>This ſyſtem of ſacriſice, which his lordſhip thinks ſo well ſupported by the moſt
                early movements of ſimple nature, we admit to be ingenious, but by no means
                ſatisfactory. That mankind in the earlier ages of the world were accuſtomed to
                ſupply the deficiencies of their language by expreſſive geſticulations we are not
                inclined to controvert: the cuſtom prevails among ſavage nations, or nations half
                civilized, at the preſent day. His</p>
            <p>lordſhip, however, is of opinion, and we heartily agree with him, that our firſt
                parents were inſtructed by God to make articulate sounds ſignificant of ideas,
                notions, and things (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Language,</hi> n<hi rend="superscript"
                    >o</hi> 6. ), and not left to fabricate a language for themſelves. That this
                heaven- taught language could be at firſt copious, no man will ſuppoſe who thinks of
                the paucity of ideas which thoſe who ſpoke it had to expreſs; but when we confider
                its origin, we cannot entertain a doubt but that it was preciſe and perſpicuous, and
                admirably adapted to all the real purpoſes of life. Among theſe purpoſes muſt ſurely
                be included the worſhip of God as the moſt important of all. Every ſentiment
                therefore which enters into worſhip, gratitude, invocation, confeſſion, and
                deprecation, the progenitors of mankind were undoubtedly taught to clothe in words
                the moſt ſignificant and unequivocal; but we know from Moſes, whole divine legation
                the hilltop ſurely admitted, that Lain and Abel, the eldeſt children of our firſt
                parents, worſhipped God by the rites of ſacrifice: and can we ſuppoſe that this
                practice occurred to <hi rend="italic">them</hi> from their having ſo far forgotten
                the language taught them by their father, as to be under the neceſſity of denoting
                by action what they could not expreſs by words? If this ſupposition be admitted, it
                will force another upon us ſtill more extravagant. Even Adam himſelf muſt, in that
                cafe, have become dumb in conſequence of his fall; for it is not conceivable, that
                as long as he was able to utter articulate sounds, and affix a meaning to them, he
                would ceaſe, in the preſence of his family, to confeſs his sins, implore
                forgiveneſs, and expreſs his gratitude to God for all his mercies.</p>
            <p>The right reverend writer, as if aware of ſome ſuch objection as this to his theory,
                contends, that if ſacrifices had ariſen from any other ſource than the light of
                reason, the Scripture would not have been silent concerning that source; “eſpecially
                ſince we find Moſes carefully recording what <hi rend="italic">God</hi> immediately,
                and not <hi rend="italic">nature,</hi> taught to Adam and his family. Had the
                original of ſacrifice, ſays he, been preſcribed, and directly commanded by the
                Deity, the ſacred hiſtorian could never have omitted the expreſs mention of that
                circumſtance. The two capital obſervances in the Jewiſh ritual were the <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Sabbath</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Sacrifices. To</hi>
                impreſs the higheſt reverence and veneration on the <hi rend="italic">Sabbath,</hi>
                he is careful to record its divine original: and can we ſuppoſe that, had ſacriſices
                had the fame original, he would have neglected to eſtabliſh this truth at the time
                that he recorded the other, ſince it is of equal uſe and of equal importance? I
                ſhould have ſaid, indeed, of much greater; for the multifarious <hi rend="italic"
                    >ſacrifices</hi> of the <hi rend="smallcaps">law </hi>had not only a reference
                to the <hi rend="italic">forfeiture</hi> of Adam, but likewiſe prefigured our
                redemption by Jeſus Chriſt. ”</p>
            <p>But all this reaſoning was foreſeen, and completely anſwered before his lordſhip gave
                it to the public. It is probable, that though the diſtinction of weeks was well
                known over all the eaſtern world, the Hebrews, during their reſidence in Egypt, were
                very negligent in their obſervance of the Sabbath. To enforce a religious obſervance
                of that ſacred day, it became neceſſary to inform them of the time and occaſion of
                its firſt inſtitution, that they might keep it holy in memory of the creation; but,
                in a country like Egypt, the people were in danger of holding ſacrifices rather in
                too high than too low veneration, ſo that there was not the ſame ne-</p>
            <p>@@@* Divine Leg. <hi rend="italic">b. ix. c. 2.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
