<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>within, and ſpotted in many places with ſmall yellowiſh or whitiſh ſpecks. Its ſmell is ſtrong and diſagreeable; its taſte acrid and unpleaſant.</p><p>It is brought to us from Perſia and the Eaſt Indies. The plant which produces it has never been deſcribed; but is ſuppoſed to be, as Dioſcorides ſays, of the ferula kind, from the ſeeds and fragments of the ſtalks ſometimes met with in the body of it.</p><p>Sagapenum is a very great attenuant, aperient, and diſcutient. It is good in all diſorders of the breaſt that owe their origin to a tough phlegm. It has alſo been found to diſcuſs tumors in the nervous parts in a remarkable manner; and to give relief in habitual headache, where almoſt all things elſe have failed. Its doſe is from ten grains to two ſcruples; but it is now ſeldom given alone. It has been found, however, to do great things in aſthmas; in obſtructions of the viſcera, particularly the ſpleen; in nervous complaints; and even in epilepſies. It alſo promotes the menſes, and expels the ſecundines; and is an ingredient in the theriaca, mithridate, and many other of the ſhop compoſitions.</p><p>SAGE, in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Salvia.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sage</hi> (Alain Rene), an ingenious French romance- writer, was born at Ruys in Brittany in the year 1667. He had a fine flow of imagination, was a complete maſter of the French and Spaniſh languages, and wrote ſeveral admired romances in imitation of the Spaniſh authors. Theſe were, The Bachelor of Salamanca, 2 vols 12mo; New Adventures of Don Quixote, 2 vols I2mo; The Devil on Two Sticks, 2 vols 12mo; and Gil Blas, 4 vols 12 mo. He produced alſo ſome comedies, and other pieces of pleaſantry; and died in 1747, in a little houſe near Paris, where he ſupported himſelf by writing.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sage</hi> (the reverend John), ſo juſtly admired by all who knew him for his claſſical learning and reaſoning powers, was born, in 1652, in the pariſh of Creich and county of Fife, North Britain, where his anceſtors had lived for ſeven generations with great reſpect though with little property. His father was a captain in Lord Duffus’s regiment, and fought for his king and country when Monk ſtormed Dundee on the 30th of Auguſt 1651.</p><p>The iſſue of the civil wars, and the loyalty of captain Sage, left him nothing to beſtow upon his ſon but a liberal education and his own principles of piety and virtue. In thoſe days the Latin language was taught in the parochial ſchools of Scotland with great ability and at a trifling expence; and after young Sage had acquired a competent knowledge of that language at one of thoſe uſeful ſeminaries, his father, without receiving from an ungrateful court any recompenſe for what he had loft in the cauſe of royalty, was ſtill able to ſend him to the univerſity of St Andrew’s, where having remained in college the uſual number of terms or ſeſſions, and performed the exerciſes required by the ſtatutes, he was admitted to the degree of maſter of arts, the higheſt honour which it appears he ever received from any univerſity.</p><p>During his reſidence in St Andrew’s he ſtudied the Greek and Roman authors with great diligence, and was likewiſe inſtructed in logic, metaphyſics, and ſuch other branches of philoſophy as then obtained in the ſchools, which, though we affect to ſmile at them in this enlightened age, he always ſpoke of as highly uſeful to him who would underſtand the poets, hiſtorians, and orators of ancient Greece, and even the fathers of the Chriſtian church. In this opinion every man will agree with him who is at all acquainted with the ancient metaphyſics, and has read the writings of Clemens Alexandrinus, Origen, Tertullian, Chryſoſtome, and other fathers of great name; for each of thoſe writers adopted the principles of ſome one or other of the philoſophical ſects, reaſoned from their notions, and often made uſe of their terms and phraſes.</p><p>When Mr Sage had taken his maſter’s degree, the narrowneſs of his fortune compelled him to accept of the ſirſt literary employment which was offered to him; and that happened to be nothing better than the office of ſchoolmaſter in the pariſh of Bingry in Fifeſhire, whence he was ſoon removed to Tippermuir in the county of Perth. In theſe humble ſtations, though he wanted many of the neceſſaries and almoſt all the comforts of life, he proſecuted his ſtudies with great ſucceſs; but in doing ſo, he unhappily imbibed the ſeeds of ſeveral diſeaſes which afflicted him through life, and notwithſtanding the native vigour of his conſtitution impaired his health and ſhortened his days. From the miſerable drudgery of a pariſh-ſchoolmaſter, he was relieved by Mr Drummond of Cultmalundie, who invited him to ſuperintend the education of his ſons, whom he accompanied firſt to the public ſchool at Perth, and afterwards to the univerſity of St Andrew’s. This was ſtill an employment by no means adequate to his merit, but it was not wholly without advantages. At Perth he gained the friendſhip and eſteem of Dr Roſe, afterwards lord biſhop of Edinburgh, and at St Andrew’s of every man capable of properly eſtimating genius and learning.</p><p>The education of his pupils was completed in 1684, when he was left with no determinate object of purſuit. In this moment of indeciſion, his friend Dr Roſe, who had been promoted from the parſonage of Perth to the profefforſhip of divinity in the univerſity which he was leaving, recommended him ſo effectually to his uncle then archbiſhop of Glaſgow, that he was by that prelate admitted into orders and preſented to one of the churches in the city. He was then about 34 years of age, had ſtudied the Scriptures with great aſſiduity, was no ſtranger to eccleſiaſtical hiſtory, or the apologies and other writings of the ancient fathers, was thorough maſter of ſchool-divinity, had examined with great accuracy the modern controverſies, eſpecially thoſe between the Romiſh and reformed churches, and between the Calvſhiſts and Remonſtrants; and it was perhaps to his honour that he did not fully approve of all the articles of faith ſubſcribed by any one of theſe contending ſects of Chriſtians.</p><p>A man ſo far advanced in life, and ſo thoroughly accompliſhed as a ſcholar, would naturally be looked up to by the greater part of the clergy as ſoon as he became one of their body. This was in fact the caſe: Mr Sage was, immediately on his admiſſion into orders, appointed clerk to the ſynod or preſbytery of Glaſgow; an office of great truſt and reſpectability, to which we know nothing ſιmilar in the church of England.</p><p>During the eſtabliſhment of epiſcopacy in Scotland, from the reſtoration of Charles II. till the year 1690, the authority of the biſhops, though they poſſeffed the</p></body></text></TEI>