<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:24Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>membrane which borders their ſides to the very end. — Theſe birds appear on the
                Engliſh coaſts and wet grounds in the winter-time in but ſmall numbers.</p>
            <p> 6. The <hi rend="italic">calidris,</hi> or red-ſhank, is found on moſt of our
                ſhores; in the winter time it conceals itſelf in the gutters, and is generally found
                ſingle or at moſt in pairs. It breeds in the fens and marſhes; and flies round its
                neſt when diſturbed, making a noiſe like a lapwing. It lays four eggs, whitiſh
                tinged with olive, marked with irregular ſpots of black chiefly on the thicker end.
                It weighs five ounces and a half: the length is 12 inches, the breadth 21; the bill
                near two inches long, red at the baſe, black towards the point. The head, hind part
                of the neck, and ſcapulars, are of a duſky aſh-colour, obſcurely ſpotted with black;
                the back is white, ſprinkled with black ſpots; the tail elegantly barred with black
                and white; the cheeks, under ſide of the neck, and upper part of the breaſt, are
                white, ſtreaked downward with duſky lines; the belly white; the exterior webs of the
                quill-feathers are duſky; the legs long, and of a fine bright orange colour; the
                utmoſt toe connected to the middle toe by a ſmall membrane; the inmoſt by another
                ſtill ſmaller.</p>
            <p> 7. The <hi rend="italic">gallinago,</hi> or common ſnipe, weighs four ounces; the
                length, to the end of the tail, is near 12 inches; the breadth about 14; the bill is
                three inches long, of a duſky colour, flat at the end, and often rough like ſhagrin
                above and below. The head is divided lengthwiſe with two black lines, and three of
                red, one of the laſt paſſing over the middle of the head, and one above each eye:
                between the bill and the eyes is a duſky line; the chin is white; the neck is varied
                with brown and red. The ſcapulars are beautifully ſtriped lengthwiſe with black and
                yellow; the quill-feathers are duſky; but the edge of the firſt is white, as are the
                tips of the ſecondary feathers: the quill-feathers next the back are barred with
                black and pale red; the breaſt and belly are white; the coverts of the tail are
                long, and almost cover it; they are of a reddiſh brown colour. The tail conſiſts of
                14 feathers, black on their lower part, then croſſed with a broad bar of deep
                orange, another trarrow one of black; and the ends white, or pale orange. The vent
                feathers are of a dull yellow; the legs pale green; the toes divided to their
                origin. In the winter-time ſnipes are very frequent in all our marſhy and wet
                grounds, where they lie concealed in the ruſhes, &amp;c. In ſummer they diſperſe to
                different parts, and are found in the midſt of our higheſt mountains as well as of
                our low moors; their neſt is made of dried graſs; they lay four eggs of a dirty
                olive colour, marked with duſky ſpots; their young are ſo often found in England,
                that we doubt whether they ever entirely leave this iſland. When they are diſturbed
                much, particularly in the breeding ſeaſon, they ſoar to a vaſt height, making a
                ſingular bleating noiſe; and when they deſcend, dart down with vaſt rapidity: it is
                alſo amuſing to obſerve the cock, while his mate fits on her eggs, poiſe himſelf on
                her wings, making ſometimes a whittling and ſometimes a drumming noiſe. Their food
                is the ſame with that of the woodcock; their flight very irregular apd ſwift, and
                attended with a ſhrill ſcream. They are moſt univerſal birds, found in every quarter
                of the globe, and in all climates.</p>
            <p>SCOLOPENDRA, in zoology, a genus of infects belonging to the order of aptera. The
                feet are very numerous, being as many on each ſide as there arc joints in the body;
                the antennæ are ſetaceous: there are two jointed pappi, and the body is depreſſed.
                —Theſe infects are very formidable and noxious in the warm countries, where they
                grow to the length of a quarter of a yard or more, though in this climate they
                ſeldom grow above an inch long. The ſcolopendra is alſo called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >centipes</hi> from its number of feet. In the Eaſt Indies it grows to ſix
                inches in length, and as thick as a man’s finger: it conſiſts of many joints; and
                from each joint proceeds a leg on each ſide: they are covered with hair, and ſeem to
                have no eyes; but there are two feelers on the head, with which they find out the
                way they are to paſs: the head is very round, with two ſmall ſharp teeth, with which
                they inflict wounds that are very painful and dangerous. A ſailor that was bit by
                one on board a ſhip felt exceſſive pain, and his life was ſuppoſed to be in danger;
                but by the application of roaſted onions to the part he recovered. The bite of the
                ſcolopendra <hi rend="italic">morsitans @@§</hi> in Jamaica is ſaid to be as
                poiſonous as the ſting of a ſcorpion. — Some of the ſpecies live in holes in the
                earth: others under ſtones, and among rotten wood; ſo that the removing of theſe is
                exceedingly dangerous in the countries where the ſcolopendrae breed. —Theſe infects,
                like the ſcorpion, are ſuppoſed to be produced perfect from the parent or the egg,
                and to undergo no changes after their firſt excluſion. They are found of all ſizes;
                which is a ſufficient reaſon for believing that they preſerve their firſt appearance
                through the whole of their exiſtence. It is probable, however, that, like moſt of
                this claſs, they often change their ſkins; but of this we have no certain
                information. The ſcolopendra for- ſicata is the largeſt in this country, of a dun
                colour, ſmooth, and compoſed of nine ſcaly ſegments, without reckoning the head. The
                feet are 15 in number on each fide, and the laſt longer than the reſt, and turned
                backwards, form a kind of forky tail. The antennæ are twice the length of the head,
                and conſiſt of 42 ſhort ſegments. The inſect’s progreſſive motion is very quick, and
                ſometimes ſerpentine. It is found under ſtones on the ground, under flower-pots and
                garden boxes.</p>
            <p>SCOLYMUS, in botany: A genus of the polygamia aequalis order, belonging to the
                ſyngeneſia claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 49th order,
                    <hi rend="italic">Compositae.</hi> The receptacle is paleaceous; the calyx
                imbricated and prickly, without any pappus.</p>
            <p>SCOMBER, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Mackerel,</hi> in ichthyology, a genus belonging to
                the order of thoracici. The head is ſmooth and compreſſed, and there are ſeven rays
                in the gill membrane. There are ten ſpecies; — of which the moſt remarkable are the
                following.</p>
            <p>1. The ſcomber, or common mackerel, a ſummer-fiſh of paſſage that viſits our ſhores
                in vaſt ſhoals. It is leſs uſeful than other ſpecies of gregarious fiſh, being very
                tender, and unfit for carriage; not but that it may be preierved by pickling and
                ſalting, a method, we believe, practiſed only in Cornwall, where it proves a great
                relief to the poor during winter. It was a ſiſh greatly eſteemed by the Romans,
                becauſe it furniſhed the precious garum, a ſort of pickle that gave a high reliſh to
                their fauces; and was beſides uſed medicinally. It was drawn from different kinds of
                fiſh, but that made from the mackerel had the preference: the beſt was made at</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@ § See Plate CCCCXLV.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
