<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of England, and therefore refuſed to treat with him as a ſovereign prince; but offered to enter into a negociation with his brother Robert, ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Curt-hoſe, </hi>from the ſhortneſs of his legs. The two princes accordingly met; and Malcolm, having ſhown Robert the diſpoſition of his army, offered to cut off his brother William, and to pay to him the homage he had been accuſtomed to pay to the Conqueror for his Engliſh dominions. But Robert generouſly anſwered, that he had reſigned to Rufus his right of primogeniture in England; and that he had even become one of William’s ſubjects, thereby accepting of an Engliſh eſtate. An interview with William then followed; in which it was agreed that the king of England ſhould reſtore to Malcolm all his ſouthern poſſeſſions, for which he ſhould pay the ſame homage he had been accuſtomed to do to the Conqueror; that he ſhould reſtore to Malcolm 12 diſputed manors, and give him likewiſe 12 merks of gold yearly, beſides reſtoring Edgar to all his Engliſh eſtates.</p><p>This treaty was concluded in Lothian, according to the Engliſh hiſtorians; but at Leeds in Yorkſhire, according to the Scots. However, the Engliſh monarch looked upon the terms to be ſo very diſhonourable, that he reſolved not to fulfil them. Soon after his departure Edgar and Robert began to preſs him to fulfil his engagements; but receiving only evaſive anſwers, they paſſed over into Normandy. After their departure, William applied himſelf to the fortification of his northern boundaries, eſpecially Carliſle, which had been deſtroyed by the Danes 200 years before. — As this place lay within the feodal dominions of Malcolm, he complained of William’s proceeding, as a breach of the late treaty; and ſoon after repaired to the Engliſh court at Glouceſter, that he might have a perſonal interview with the king of England, and obtain redreſs. On his arrival, William refuſed him admittance to his preſence, without paying him homage. Malcom offered this in the ſame manner as had been done by his predeceſſors, that is, on the confines of the two kingdoms; but this being rejected by William, Malcolm returned to Scotland in a rage, and prepared again for war.</p><p>The firſt of Malcolm’s military operations now proved fatal to him; but the circumſtances of his death are variouſly related. According to the Scots hiſtorians, Malcolm having laid ſiege to Alnwick, and reduced the place to ſuch ſtraits, that a knight came out of the caſtle, having the keys on the point of a ſpear, and pretending that he deſigned to lay them at Malcolm’s feet; but inſtead of this, he ran him through the eye with the ſpear, as ſoon as he came within reach. They add, that prince Edward, the king’s eldeſt ſon, was mortally wounded in attempting to revenge his father’s death. The Engliſh hiſtorians, on the other hand, contend, that the Scots were ſurpriſed in their camp, their army entirely defeated, and their king killed. On this occaſion the Scots hiſtorians alſo inform us, that the family of Piercy received its name; the knight who killed the Scots king having been ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Pierce-eye, </hi>from the manner in which he gave that monarch the fatal ſtroke. Queen Margaret, who was at that time lying ill in the caſtle of Edinburgh, died four days after her huſband.</p><p> After the death of Malcolm Canmore, which happened in the year 1093 the throne was uſurped by his brother Donald Bane; who, notwithstanding the great virtues and glorious achievements of the late king, had been at the head of a ſtrong party during the whole of his brother’s reign. The uſurper, giving way to the barbarous prejudices of himſelf and his countrymen, expelled out of the kingdom all the foreigners whom Malcolm had introduced, and obliged them to take refuge in England. Edgar himſelf had long reſided at the Engliſh court, where he was in high reputation; and, by his intereſt there, found means to reſcue his nephew young Edgar, the king of Scotland’s eldeſt ſon, out of the hands of the uſurper Donald Bane. The favour he ſhowed to him, however, produced an accuſation againſt himſelf, as if he deſigned to adopt young Edgar as his ſon, and ſet him up as a pretender to the Engliſh throne. This accuſation was preferred by an Engliſhman whoſe name was <hi rend="italic">Organ;</hi> but, as no legal proofs of the guilt could be obtained, the cuſtom of the times rendered a ſingle combat between the parties unavoidable. Orgar was one of the ſtrongeſt and moſt active men in the kingdom; but the age and infirmities of Edgar allowed him to be defended by another. For a long time none could be found who would enter the liſts with this champion; but at laſt one Godwin of Wincheſter, whoſe family had been under obligations to Edgar or his anceſtors, offered to defend his cauſe. Orgar was overcome and killed: and, when dying, confeſſed the falſehood of his accuſation. The conqueror obtained all the lands of his adverſary, and William lived ever afterwards on terms of the ſtricteſt friendſhip with Edgar.</p><p>This combat, trifling as it may ſeem to us, produced very conſiderable effects. The party of Edgar and his brother’s (who had likewiſe taken refuge at the Engliſh court) revived in Scotland, to ſuch a degree, that Donald was obliged to call in the Danes and Norwegians to his aſſiſtance. In order to engage them more effectually to his intereſt, the uſurper yielded up to them the Orkney and Shetland iſlands; but when his new allies came to his aſſiſtance, they behaved in ſuch a manner as to become more intolerable to the Scots than ever the Engliſh had been. This diſcontent was greatly increaſed when it was found that William deſigned to place on the throne of Scotland a natural ſon of the late Malcolm, named <hi rend="italic">Duncan,</hi> who had ſerved in the Engliſh armies with great reputation. Donald attempted to maintain himſelf on the throne by the aſſiſtance of his Norwegian allies; but, being abandoned by the Scots, he was obliged to fly to the iſles, in order to raiſe more forces; and in the mean time Duncan was crowned at Scone with the uſual ſolemnity.</p><p>The Scots were now greatly diſtreſſed by two uſurpers who contended for the kingdom, each of them ſupported by a foreign army. One of them, however, was ſoon diſpatched. Malpedir, thane of Mearns, ſurpriſed Duncan in the caſtle of Mentieth, and killed him; alter which he replaced Donald on the throne. The affection of the Scots, however, was by this time entirely alienated from Donald, and a manifeſt intention of calling in young Edgar was ſhown. To prevent this, Donald offered the young prince all that part of Scotland which lay to the ſouthward of the Forth; but the terms, were rejected, and the meſſengers who</p></body></text></TEI>