<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>their purpoſe: they will aſcend rivers hundreds of miles, force themſelves againſt
                the moſt rapid ſtreams, and ſpring with amazing agility over cataracts of ſeveral
                feet in height. Salmon are frequently taken in the Rhine as high up as Baſil; they
                gain the ſources of the Lapland rivers in ſpite of their torrent-like currents, and
                ſurpaſs the perpendicular falls of Leixſlip, Kennerth, and Pont Aberglaſtyn. It may
                here be proper to contradict the vulgar error, of their taking their tail in their
                mouth when they attempt to leap; ſuch as Mr Pennant ſaw, ſprung up quite ſtraight,
                and with a ſtrong tremulous motion.</p>
            <p>The ſalmon is a fiſh ſo generally known, that a very brief deſcription will ſerve.
                The largeſt we ever heard of weighed 74 pounds. The colour of the back and ſides are
                grey, ſometimes ſpotted with black, ſometimes plain: the covers of the gills are
                ſubject to the ſame variety; the belly ſilvery; the noſe ſharp-pointed; the end of
                the under jaw in the males often turns up in the form of a hook; ſometimes this
                curvature is very conſiderable: it is ſaid that they loſe this hook when they return
                to the ſea. The teeth are lodged in the jaws and on the tongue, and are ſlender, but
                very ſharp; the tail is a little forked.</p>
            <p>2. The trutta, or ſea-trout, migrates like the true ſalmon up ſeveral of our rivers;
                ſpawns, and returns to the ſea. That deſcribed by Mr Pennant was taken in the Tweed
                below Berwick, June 1769. The ſhape was more thick than the common trout; the weight
                three pounds two ounces. The irides ſilver; the head thick, ſmooth, and duſky, with
                a gloſs of blue and green; the back of the ſame colour, which grows fainter towards
                the ſide-line. The back is plain, but the ſides, as far as the lateral line, are
                marked with large diſtinct irregularly-ſhaped ſpots of black: the lateral line
                ſtraight; the ſides beneath the line, and the belly, are white. Tail broad, and even
                at the end. The dorſal fin had 12 rays; the pectoral 14; the ventral 9; the anal 10.
                The fleſh when boiled is of a pale red, but well-flavoured.</p>
            <p>3. The fario, or trout; the colours of which vary greatly in different waters, and in
                different, ſeaſons. Trouts differ alſo in fize. One taken in Llynallet,
                Denbighſhire, which is famous for an excellent kind, meaſured t 7 inches, its depth
                three and three quarters, its weight one pound ten ounces; the head thick; the noſe
                rather ſharp; the upper jaw a little longer than the lower; both jaws, as well as
                the head, were of a pale brown, blotched with black; the teeth ſharp and ſtrong,
                diſpoſed in the jaws, roof of the mouth, and tongue. The back wag duſky; the ſides
                tinged with a purpliſh bloom, marked with deep purple ſpots, mixed with black above
                and below the ſide-line, which was ſtraight; the belly white. The ſirſt dorſal ſin
                was ſpotted; the ſpurious ſin brown, tipped with, red; the pectoral, ventral, and
                anal ſins, of a pale brown; the edges of the anal ſin white; the tail very little
                forked when extended. —The ſtomachs of the common trouts are uncommonly thick and
                muſcular. They feed on the ſhell-fish of lakes and rivers, as well as on small fiſh.
                They likewiſe take into their ſtomachs gravel or ſmall ſtones, to aſſiſt in
                comminuting, the teſtaceous parts of their food. The trouts of certain lakes in
                Ireland; ſuch as thoſe of the province of Galway and ſome others, are remarkable for
                the great thickneſs of their ſtomachs, which, from ſome flight reſemblance to the
                organs of digeſtion in birds, have been called <hi rend="italic">gizzards;</hi> the
                Iriſh name the ſpecies that has them <hi rend="italic">gillαroo trouts.</hi> Theſe
                ſtomachs are ſometimes ſerved up to table under the former appellation. Trouts are
                moſt voracious ſiſh, and afford excellent diverſion to the angler. The paſſion for
                the ſport of angling is ſo great in the neighbourhood of London, that the liberty of
                ſiſhing in ſome of the ſtreams in the adjacent counties is purchaſed at the rate of
                101. <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi> Theſe fiſh ſhiſt their quarters to ſpawn;
                and, like ſalmon, make up toward» the heads of rivers to depoſit their roes. The
                under jaw of the trout is ſubject, at certain times, to the ſame curvature as that
                of the ſalmon.</p>
            <p>“It is caught (fay the editors of the Hiſtory of Cumberland) in very great plenty at
                all ſeaſons of the year; one weighing a pound and a half is an uſual ſize, though
                ſome are caught of 4 lb. weight. Five or ſix ounces is a common weight; the largeſt
                are commonly the bell for the table, when they cut of a deep ſalmon colour. In the
                winter months great quantities are potted along with the charre, and ſent to London,
                &amp;c. — The angler, on a favourable day, here enjoys his diverſion in higher
                perfection than in moſt places. A trout occaſionally ſtrays out of the Eamont into
                the lake, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa,</hi> out of the lake into the river.
                They are eaſily diſtinguiſhed by their ſpots; and it is obſerved, that a fish taken
                from its uſual place is not in ſo good a condition as one of equal length taken on
                its own ground; hence it is probable, that they do not, emigrate, except when
                diſeaſed or ſpawning. Geld fiſh (thoſe without ſpawn) are the firmeſt and beſt. They
                have been taken out of a ſolid piece of ice, in which they were frozen, as it were
                in a cafe, perfectly uninjured, after an impriſonment of ſeveral hours. ”</p>
            <p>4. The ſpecies, called, from its colour the <hi rend="italic">white, </hi>migrates
                out of the ſea into the river Elk in Cumberland, from July to September. When
                dreſſed, their fleſh is red, and moſt delicious eating. They have, on their ſirſt
                appearance from the ſalt water, the <hi rend="italic">lernaea ſalmonea,</hi> or
                ſalmon louſe, adhering to them. They have both milt and ſpawn; but no fry has as yet
                been obſerved. This is the fiſh called by the Scots <hi rend="italic">phinocs.
                </hi>They never exceed a foot in length. The upper jaw is a little longer than the
                lower; in the firſt are two rows of teeth, in the laſt one: on the tongue are fix,
                teeth. The back is ſtraight: the whole body of an elegant form: the lateral line is
                ſtraight; colour, between that and the top of the back, duſky and ſilvery
                intermixed; beneath the line, of an exquiſite whiteneſs; firſt dorſal fin ſpotted
                with black: tail black, and much forked.</p>
            <p> 5. The ſamlet is the leaſt of the trout kind; is frequent in the Wye, in the upper
                part of the Severn, and the rivers that run into it, in the north of England, and in
                Wales. It is by ſeveral imagined to be the fry of the ſahnon; but Mr Pennant
                diſſents from that opinion. See his <hi rend="italic">Brit. Zool.</hi> III.
                303.</p>
            <p>This ſpecies has a general reſemblance to the trout, therefore muſt be deſcribed
                comparatively. <hi rend="italic">1st,</hi> The head is proportionably narrower, and
                the mouth leſs than that of the trout. <hi rend="italic">2dly,</hi> Their body is
                deeper. <hi rend="italic">3dly,</hi> They ſeldom exceed fix or ſeyen inches in
                length; at. moſt, eight and a half, <hi rend="italic">4thly</hi> The pectoral fins
                have</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
