<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>grant is ſaid to have been made with the conſent and approbation of the Scottiſh nobility, 29th March 1298. From this period, however, we may date the very great jealouſy which took place between Wallace and the nobles who pretended to be of his party. His elevation wounded their pride; his great ſervices reproached their inactivity in the public cauſe; and thus the counſels of Scotland were perplexed with diſtruſt and envy, when almoſt its very exiſtence depended on unanimity.</p><p>In June 1298, Edward, who had all this time been in Flanders, returned to England, and ſummoned the Scottiſh barons, under pain of rebellion, to attend him in parliament; and, on their diſobeying his ſummons, he advanced with his army towards Scotland. His main force, commanded by himſelf, aſſembled at Berwick; but a body of troops, under the earl of Pembroke, having landed in the north of Fife, were defeated with great loſs by Wallace, on the 12th of June.  The same month Edward invaded Scotland by the way of the eaſtern borders. No place reſiſted him except the caſtle of Dirleton. After a reſolute defence, it ſurrendered to Anthony Beck, biſhop of Durham.</p><p>Meanwhile the Scots were aſſembling all their ſtrength in the interior part of the country. Few barons of eminence repaired to the national ſtandard. They whoſe names are recorded, were John Cornyn of Badenoch, the younger; Sir John Stewart of Bonkill, brother to <hi rend="italic">The Steward;</hi> Sir John Graham of Abercorn; and Macduff, the grand-uncle of the young earl of Fife. — Robert Bruce again acceded to the Scottiſh party; and with his followers guarded the important caſtle of Air, which kept the communication open with Galloway, Argyleſhire, and the iſles.</p><p>The aim of Edward was to penetrate into the weſt, and there to terminate the war. He appointed a fleet, with proviſions, to proceed to the frith of Clyde, and await his arrival in thole parts. This precaution was abſolutely neceſſary for the ſubliſtence of his numerous army in a country impoveriſhed and waſte.</p><p>Waiting for accounts of the arrival of his fleet, he eſtabliſhed his head-quarters at Templeliſton, between Edinburgh and Linlithgow.</p><p>A dangerous inſurrection aroſe in his camp. He had beſtowed a donative of wine among his ſoldiers; they became intoxicated; a national quarrel enſued. — In this tumult the Welſh ſlew 18 Engliſh eccleſiaſtics. The Englilh horſemen rode in among the Welſh, and revenged this outrage with great ſlaughter. The Welſh in diſguſt ſeparated themſelves from the army. It was reported to Edward, that they had mutinied, and gone over to the Scots: “I care not,” ſaid Edward, diſſembling the danger; “let my enemies go and join my enemies; I truſt that in one day I ſhall chaſtiſe them all.”</p><p>Edward was now placed in moſt critical circumſtances. As the fleet with proviſions had been detained by contrary winds, he could not venture to advance, neither could he ſubſiſt any longer in his preſent quarters. To retreat would have ſullied the glory of his arms, and expoſed him to the obloquy and murmurs of a discontented people. Yet he ſubmitted to this hard neceſſity. Abandoning every proſpect of ambition and revenge, he commanded his army to return to the eaſtern borders. At that moment intelligence arrived that the Scots were advanced to Falkirk.</p><p>Edward inſtantly marched againſt them. His army lay that night in the fields. While Edward ſlept on the ground, his war-horſe ſtruck him and broke two of his ribs. The alarm aroſe, that the king was wounded. They who knew not the cauſe, repeated the cry, “The king is wounded; there is treaſon in the camp; the enemy is upon us.” Edward mounted on horſeback, and by his preſence diſpelled the panic. With a fortitude of ſpirit ſuperior to pain, he led on his troops. At break of day, the Scottiſh army was deſcried, forming on a ſtony field at the fide of a ſmall eminence in the neighbourhood of Falkirk.</p><p>Wallace ranged his infantry in four bodies of a circular form. The archers, commanded by Sir John Stewart, were placed in the intervals. The horſe, amounting to no more than a thouſand, were at ſome diſtance in the rear. On the front of the Scots lay a moraſs. Having drawn up his troops in this order, Wallace pleaſantly ſaid, “Now I have brought you to the ring, dance according to your ſkill.”</p><p>Edward placed his chief confidence in the numerous and formidable body of horſemen whom he had ſelected for the Scottiſh expedition. Theſe he ranged in three lines. The firſt was led by Bigot Earl Marſhal, and the Earls of Hereford and Lincoln; the ſecond by the biſhop of Durham, having under him Sir Ralph Baſſet of Drayton; the third, intended for a reſerve, was led by the king himſelf. No mention is made of the diſpoſition of his infantry: it is probable that they were drawn up behind, to ſupport the cavalry, and to annoy the Scots with their arrows and other miſſile weapons.</p><p>Bigot, at the head of the firſt line, ruſhed on to the charge. He was checked by the moraſs, which in his impetuoſity he had overlooked. This obliged him to incline to the ſolid ground on his left, towards the right flank of the Scottiſh army. The biſhop of Durham, who led the ſecond line, inclined to the right, turned the moraſs, and advanced towards the left flank of the Scottiſh army. He propoſed to halt till the reſerve ſhould advance. “To maſs, biſhop,” cried Baffet, and inſtantly charged. The ſhock of the Engliſh cavalry on each ſide was violent, and gallantly withſtood by the Scottiſh infantry; but the Scottiſh cavalry, diſmayed at the number and force of the Engliſh men-at-arms, immediately quitted the field. Stewart, while giving orders to his archers, was thrown from his horſe and flain. His archers crowded round his body and periſhed with him. Often did the Engliſh ſtrive to force the Scottiſh circle. “They could not penetrate into that wood of ſpears,” as one of their hiſtorians ſpeaks. By repeated charges, the outermolt ranks were brought to the ground. The Engliſh infantry inceſſantly galled the Scots with ſhowers of ſtones and arrows. Macduff and Sir John Graham fell. At length the Scots were broken by the numbers and weight of the Engliſh cavalry, and the rout became univerſal.</p><p>The number of the Scots ſlain in this battle muſt have been very great. As is commonly the cafe, it is exaggerated by the hiſtorians of the victors, and reduced too  low by the hiſtorians of the vanquiſhed.</p><p>On the ſide of the Engliſh the loſs was inconsiderable. The only persons of note who fell were Brian le Jay, maſter of the Engliſh Templars, and the prior of Tor-</p></body></text></TEI>