<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that time held by William Douglas knight of Liddeſdale. The king’s liberality proved fatal to Ramſay: for from that time Douglas became his implacable and inveterate enemy; and having, after a pretended reconciliation, unexpectedly ſurptiſed him with three of his friends, he put theta inſtantly to death, carrying off Ramſay himſelf to his caſtle of the Hermitage, where he cauſed him to be ſtarved to death in a moſt barbarous manner. The unhappy man was confined in a room, over which was an heap of wheat; a few grains of which were let fall every day through a hole, not as many as would ſupport life, but as would protract it for a time, and make him longer ſenſible of the agonies of hunger; and in this miſerable ſituation he ſurvived 17 days. About the ſame time Sir William Bullock was put to death by Douglas in a ſimilar manner; nor was King David at that time in a capacity to punish ſuch atrocious cruelties committed by ſo powerful a ſubject.</p><p>In the mean time, David having raiſed a powerful army, prepared to take a ſevere revenge of the Engliſh, from whom he had ſuffered ſo much. Edward was at that time in France, but commanded Baliol to raiſe all the militia beyond the Trent: which order, however, produced but little effect; ſo much was this mean- ſpirited prince deſpiſed by the Engliſh. David invaded Northumberland without opposition, and ravaged the country; but was obliged to raiſe the ſiege of Newcaſtle, which was commanded by Sir John Nevil, an excellent officer. David, exaſperated at this repulſe, entered the biſhopric of Durham, which he ravaged in the moſt cruel manner. However, on the approach of Edward with a powerful army, the Scots thought proper to retire; and a two years truce was agreed upon.</p><p>This pacification was but ſhort lived. In 1345 the Scots again prepared to invade England, while Edward took all neceſſary meaſures for oppoſing them: however, this year the Scots were ſucceſsful, ravaging Weſtmoreland, and burning ſeveral towns. The year ended with a new truce between the two nations; and hoſtilities were not renewed till 1346, when David entered England with an army of 50,000 men. His firſt exploit was the taking of the ſortreſs of Liddel, and maſſacring all whom he found in it. The commander, Sir Waiter Selby, capitulated with a Scots knight for his life; but the bargain being diſapproved of by David, he ordered two of Selby’s ſons to be ſtrangled in his preſence, and then the father’s head to be cut oft. From thence the Scots marched to Bancroft, which they plundered; then paſſing into Northumberland, they pillaged the priory of Hexham, but ſpared the town, that it might ſerve as a magazine. Three other towns, Corbridge, Durham, and Darlington, were ſpared for the fame reaſon. In his march to Durham, it is ſaid that he would have made the county a deſert, had not ſome of the monks paid him a contribution of a thouſand pounds to ſpare their eſtates: however, according to Knyghton, every Engliſhman who fell into David’s hands was put to death, unleſs he could redeem his life by paying threepence.</p><p>To put a ſtop to the cruelties of this barbarous invader, the queen of England, in her huſband’s abſence, aſſembled a powerful army, which was divided into four bodies; the firſt commanded by Lord Henry Percy; the second by the archbiſhop of York; the</p><p>third by the biſhop of Lincoln, the lord Moubray, and Sir Thomas Rokeby; and the fourth and principal division was headed by Edward Baliol.—The king of Scotland headed a choſen battalion, compoſed of the flower of his nobility, and the auxiliaries with which he had been ſupplied by France. The high ſteward of Scotland headed the ſecond line, and the third was commanded by the earls of Moray and Douglas. While the Engliſh were approaching, Lord Douglas and Sir David Graham ſkirmiſhed with them, but were defeated with the loſs of 500 of their men; which ſeemed an omen of the diſaſter that was about to enſue. The general engagement began between the archers on both ſides; but the Engliſh being much ſuperior in the uſe of the bow, the ſteward of Scotland advanced to the relief of his countrymen. The Engliſh archers, unable to bear his attack, fell back upon Lord Henry Percy’s diviſion, which was thus put in confuſion, and would have been totally defeated, had not Baliol advanced to their relief with a body of 4000 horſe. The ſteward was then obliged to retire; by which means the flank of that divifion commanded by David, and which was then engaged with another line of the Engliſh, was left expoſed to an attack. Baliol perceived the advantage; and, without purſuing the ſteward, attacked the king’s diviſion, which was immediately cut in pieces or diſperſed. David was left with about 80 noblemen and gentlemen, but ſtill maintained the fight with obſtinacy; nor would he yield even when wounded in the head with an arrow, expecting every moment to be relieved by the ſteward and that line of his army which was ſtill entire under the Lords Moray and Douglas. At laſt finding himſelf totally overpowered, he attempted to retreat, but was overtaken by a party under one John Copeland. This captain, endeavouring to ſeize the king, had two of his teeth ſtruck out by a blow of his gauntlet; but at laſt, finding it in vain to reſiſt, the king was obliged to give up his ſword and ſurrender himſelf a priſoner. —After he was taken, Baliol attacked and totally routed that diviſion of the Scottiſh army which had hitherto remained entire under the Lords Moray and Douglas. In this battle the Scots loſt a great number of their nobility, and 15,000 common ſoldiers. Many perſons of the firſt diſtinction were alſo taken along with the king; and had it not been that the eſcape of the Scots was favoured by the avarice of the Engliſh ſoldiers, who neglected the purſuit in order to plunder, ſcarce a single Scotſman would have returned.</p><p>King David, after this unfortunate battle, was carried to the caſtle of Bamborough, where he was kept with ſo much privacy, that for ſome time it was not known where he was, or that he had been taken prisoner. As soon as the truth was known, the queen of England demanded the royal priſoner from Copeland; but the latter poiſitively refused to part with him even to the queen, unleſs ſhe could produce an order to that purpoſe under Edward’s hand and ſeal. This reſolute behaviour was reſented by the queen, and a complaint made to the king; in conſequence of which Copeland was ſurhmoned to appear before Edward, after having reſigned David to the cuſtody of Lord Nevil. The Engliſh monarch, at that time in France, approved of all that he had done, rewarded him with 500 l. a year, and ſent him back to England with the honour of</p></body></text></TEI>