<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>flecting upon the unnatural part he had acted, was inexpreſſible; and the noblemen who had been engaged in the rebellion became apprehenſive for their own ſafety. The cataſtrophe of the unfortunate James III. however, was not yet become public; and it was thought by many that he had gone aboard ſome of the ſhips belonging to the Scottiſh admiral Sir Andrew Wood. James, willing to indulge hope as long as it was poſſible, deſired an interview with the admiral; but the latter refuſed to come on ſhore, unleſs he had ſufficient hoſtages for his ſafety. Theſe being delivered, Sir Andrew waited upon the king at Leith. He had again and again, by meſſages, aſſured him that he knew nothing of the late king; and he had even offered to allow his ſhips to be ſearched: yet ſuch was the anxiety of the new king, that he could not be ſatisfied till he had examined him in perſon. Young James had been long a ſtranger to his father, ſo that he could not have diſtinguiſhed him ealily from others. When Wood, therefore, entered the room, being ſtruck with his noble appearance, he aſked him, “Are you my father?” “I am not,” replied Wood, burſting into tears ; “but I was your father’s true ſervant, and while I live I ſhall be the determined enemy of his murderers.” This did not ſatisfy the lords, who demanded whether he knew where the king was. The admiral replied, that he knew not; and upon their queſtioning him concerning his manœuvres on the day of battle, when his boats were ſeen plying backwards and forwards, he told them, that he and his brother had determined to aſſiſt the king in perſon; but all they could do was to ſave ſome of the royaliſts in their ſhips. “I would to God, (ſays he), my king was there ſafely, for I would defend and keep him ſkaithleſs from all the traitors who have cruelly murdered him: for I think to ſee the day to behold them hanged and drawn for their demerits.” This ſpirited declaration, and the freedom with which it was delivered, ſtruck the guilty part of the council with diſmay; but the fear of ſacriſicing the hoſtages procured Wood his freedom, and he was ſuffered to depart to his ſhips. When he came on board, he found his brother preparing to hang the two lords who had been left as hoſtages; which would certainly have been their fate, had the admiral been longer detained.</p><p>Wood had ſcarcely reached his ſhips, when the lords, calling the inhabitants of Leith together, offered them a large premium if they would fit out a ſufficient force to deſtroy that bold pirate and his crew, as they called Wood; but the townſmen, who, it ſeems, did not much care for the ſervice, replied, that Wood’s ſhips were a match for any ten ſhips that could be fitted out in Scotland. The council then removed to Edinburgh, where James IV. was crowned on the 24th of June 1487.</p><p>In the month of October this year, the nobility and others who had been preſent at the king’s coronation, converted themſelves into a parliament, and paſſed an act by which they were indemnified for their rebellion againſt their late ſovereign; after which, they ordered the act to be exemplified under the great ſeal of Scotland, that it might be producible in their juſtification if called for by any foreign prince. They next proceeded to the arduous taſk of vindicating their rebellion in the eyes of the public; and ſo far did they gain upon the king by the force of flattery, that he contented to ſummon the lords who had taken part with his father, before the parliament, to anſwer for their conduct. In conſequence of this, no fewer than 28 lords were cited to appear at Edinburgh in the ſpace of 40 days. The firſt upon the liſt was the lord David Lindſay, whoſe form of arraignment was as follows. “Lord David Lindſay of the Byres, anſwer for the cruel coming againſt the king at Bannockburn with his father, giving him counſel to have devoured the king’s grace here preſent; and, to that effect, gave him a ſword and a good horſe, to fortify him againſt his ſon. Your anſwer hereto.” Lord Lindſay was remarkable for the bluntneſs of his converſation and the freedom of his ſentiments; and being irritated by this charge, he delivered himſelf in ſuch a manner concerning the treaſon of the rebellious lords, as abaſhed the boldeſt of his accuſers. As they were unable to anſwer him, all they could do was to preſs him to throw himſelf upon the king’s clemency; which he refuſed, as being guilty of no crime. His brother, Patrick Lindſay, undertook to be his advocate, and apologized upon his knees for the roughneſs of his behaviour, and at laſt obſerved an informality in the proceedings of the court; in conſequence of which Lindſay was released, upon entering into recognizance to appear again at an appointed day: however, he was afterwards ſent priſoner by the king’s order, for a whole twelvemonth, to the caſtle of Rotheſay in the Iſle of Bute.	∣</p><p>The regicides now endeavoured to gain the public favour by affecting a ſtrict adminiſtration of juſtice. The king was adviſed to make a progreſs round the kingdom, attended by his council and judges; while, in the mean time, certain noblemen and gentlemen were appointed to exercite juſtice, and to ſuppreſs all kinds of diſorders in their own lands and in thoſe adjoining to them, till the king came to the age of 21. The memory of the late king was branded in the moſt opprobrious manner. All juſtices, ſheriffs, and ſtewards, who were poſſeſſed of heritable offices, but who had taken up arms for the late king, were either deprived of them for three years, or rendered incapable of enjoying them for ever after. All the young nobility who had been diſinherited by their fathers for taking arms againſt the late king, were, by act of parliament, reſtored to their ſeveral ſucceſſions in the moſt ample manner. At laſt, in order to give a kind of proof to the world that they intended only to reſettle the ſtate of the nation, without prejudice to the lower ranks of ſubjects, who did no more than follow the examples of their ſuperiors, it was enacted, “That all goods and effects taken from burgeſſes, merchants, and thoſe who had only perſonal eſtates, or, as they are called, <hi rend="italic">un landed men,</hi> ſince the battle of Stirling, were not only to be reſtored, but the owners were to be indemnified for their losses; and their perſons, if in cuſtody, were to be ſet at liberty. Churchmen, who were taken in arms, were to be delivered over to their ordinances, to be dealt with by them according to the law.” The caſtle of Dunbar was ordered to be demolished; and ſome ſtatutes were enacted in favour of commerce, and for the</p><p>exclusion of foreigners.</p><p>Theſe laſt acts were paſſed with a view to recompence the boroughs, who had been very active in their oppoſition to the late king. However, the lords, before they diſſolved their parliament, thought it neceſſa-</p></body></text></TEI>