<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:45Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>dition of his holding it as fief of the crown of England, and aſſiſting in defence of the northern border. Soon after the concluſion of this treaty Malcolm died, and was ſucceeded by his ſon Indulfus. In his reign the Danes became extremely formidable by their invaſions, which they now renewed with greater fury than ever, being exaſperated by the friendſhip ſubſiſting between the Scots and Engliſh monarchs. Their firſt deſcent was upon Eaſt Lothian, where they were ſoon expelled, but croſſed over to Fife. Here they were a ſecond time defeated, and driven out; and ſo well had Indulfus taken care to guard the coaſts, that they could not find an opportunity of landing; till having ſeemed to ſteer towards their own country, the Scots were thrown off their guard, and the Danes on a ſudden made good their landing at Cullen, in Banffshire. Here Indulfus ſoon came up with them, attacked their camp, and drove them towards their ſhips. but was killed in an ambuſcade, into which he fell during the pursuit. He was ſucceeded by Duffus, to whom hiſtorians give an excellent character; but, after a reign of five years, he was murdered, in the year 965. He was ſucceeded by Culen the ſon of Indulfus, who had been nominated prince of Cumberland in his father’s lifetime, as heir-apparent to the throne. He is represented as a very degenerate prince; and is ſaid to have given himſelf up to ſenſuality in a manner almoſt incredible, being guilty of incontinence not only with women of all ranks, but even with his own ſiſters and daughters. The people in the mean time were fleeced, in order to ſupport the extravagance and luxury of their prince. In conſequence of this, an aſſembly of the ſtates was convened at Scone for the reſettling of the government; but on his way thither Culen was aſſaſſinated, near the village of Methven, by Rohard, thane or ſheriff of Fife, whoſe daughter the king had debauched.</p><p>The provocations which Culen had given to his nobility ſeem to have rendered them totally untractable and licentious; which gave an occaſion to a remarkable revolution in the reign of Kenneth III. who ſucceeded Culen. This prince, being a man of great reſolution, began with relieving the common people from the oppreſſions of the nobility, which were now intolerable; and this plan he purſued with ſo much ſucceſs, that, having nothing to fear from the great barons, he ordered them to appear before him at Lanerk; but the greateſt part, conſcious of their demerits, did not attend. The king ſo well diſſembled his diſpleaſure, that thoſe who came were quite charmed with his affability, and the noble entertainment he gave them; in conſequence of which, when an aſſembly was called next year, the guilty were encouraged to appear as well as the innocent. No ſooner had this affembly met, however, than the place of meeting was beſet with armed men. The king then informed them that none had any thing to apprehend excepting ſuch as had been notorious offenders; and theſe he ordered to be immediately taken into cuſtody, telling them, that their ſubmitting to public juſtice muſt be the price of their liberty. They were obliged to accept the king’s offer, and the criminals were accordingly puniſhed according to their deſerts.</p><p>About this time Edgar, king of England, finding himſelf hard preſſed by the Danes, found means to unite the king of Scotland and the prince of Cumberland along with himſelf in a treaty againſt the Danes; which gave occaſion to a report that Kenneth had become tributary to the king of England. This, however, is utterly denied by all the Scots hiſtorians; who affirm that Kenneth cultivated a good correſpondence with Edgar, as well becauſe he expected aſſiſtance in defending his coaſts, as becauſe he intended entirely to alter the mode of ſucceſſion to the throne. About this time the Danes made a dreadful invaſion. Their original intention ſeems to have been to land on ſome part of the Engliſh coaſts; but finding them probably too well guarded, they landed at Montroſe in Scotland, committing every where the moſt dreadful ravages. Kenneth at that time was at Stirling, and quite unprepared; however, having collected an handful of troops, he cut off many of the enemy as they were ſtraggling up and down, but could not prevent them from beſieging Perth. Nevertheleſs, as the king’s army conſtantly increaſed, he reſolved to give the enemy battle. The ſcene of this action was at Loncarty, near Perth. The king is ſaid to have offered ten pounds in ſilver, or the value of it in land, for the head of every Dane which ſhould be brought him; and an immunity from all taxes to the ſoldiers who ſerved in his army, provided they ſhould be victorious: but, notwithſtanding the utmoſt efforts of the Scots, their enemies fought ſo deſperately, that Kenneth’s army muſt have been totally defeated, had not the fugitives been flopped by a yeoman and his two ſons of the name of <hi rend="italic">Hay,</hi> who were coming up to the battle, armed with ſuch ruſtic weapons as their condition in life afforded. Buchanan and Boece inform us, that theſe countrymen were ploughing in a field hard by the ſcene of action, and perceiving that their countrymen fled, they looſed their oxen, and made uſe of the yokes as weapons, with which they firſt obliged their countrymen to ſtand, and then annoyed their enemies. The fight was now renewed with ſuch fury on the part of the Scots, that the Danes were utterly defeated; and, after the battle, the king rewarded Hay with the barony of Errol in the Carſe of Gowrie, ennobled his family, and gave them an armorial bearing alluding to the ruſtic weapons with which they had atchieved this glorious exploit.</p><p>In the year 994, Kenneth was murdered at the inſtigation of a lady named <hi rend="italic">Fenella,</hi> whoſe ſon he had cauſed to be put to death. The murder was perpetrated in Fenella’s caſtle, where ſhe had perſuaded the king to pay her a viſit. His attendants waited long near the place; but being at length tired out, they broke open the doors, and found their king murdered: upon which they laid the caſtle in aſhes; but Fenella eſcaped by a poſtern. The throne was then ſeized by an uſurper named <hi rend="italic">Constantine;</hi> who, being killed in battle after a reign of a year and an half, was ſucceeded by Grime, the grandſon of king Duffus; and he again was defeated and killed by Malcolm the ſon of Kenneth, the lawful heir of the Scottiſh throne. After this victory, however, Malcolm did not immediately aſſume the ſovereignty; but aſked the crown from the nobles, in conſequence of a law paſſed in the reign of Kenneth, by which the ſucceſſion to the throne of Scotland became hereditary. This they immediately granted, and Malcolm was accordingly crowned king. He joined himſelf in ſtrict alliance with the king of England; and proved ſo ſucceſsful againſt the Danes in England, that</p></body></text></TEI>