<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſhop, on his return to Scotland, acted as a ſpy for Edward, and carried on with him a ſecret correſpondence, informing him of all public tranſactions. It appears from this correſpondence, that the Scots were far from being unanimous as to the marriage. Bruce earl of Annandale ſuſpected, for ſome reaſon or other, that the young queen was dead; and, ſoon after Michaelmas 1290, aſſembled a body of forces, and was joined by the earl of Mar and Athol. Intelligence of theſe commotions was carried to Edward by Baliol; and the biſhop of St Andrew’s adviſed Edward, in caſe the report of the queen’s death ſhould prove true, to march a body of troops towards Scotland, in order to ſecure ſuch a ſucceſſor as he thought proper.</p><p>Edward, in the mean time, conſented to allow ambaſſadors to be ſent from Scotland to bring over the young queen; previous to which, he appointed the biſhop of Durham to be lieutenant in Scotland for the queen and her future huſband; and all the officers there, both civil and military, obliged themſelves to ſurrender their employments and fortreſſes to the king and queen (that is, to Edward) immediately on their arrival in Scotland. But while the moſt magnificent preparations were making for the reception of the young queen, certain intelligence of her death was received; but it is not certainly known whether this event happened before the arrival of the ambaſſadors in Norway or after her departure from that country.</p><p>The Scots were thrown into the utmoſt conſternation by the news of their queen’s death; while, on the other hand, Edward was as well prepared as it he had known what was to happen. The ſtate of Scotland at this time indeed was to the laſt degree deplorable. The act of ſucceſſion eſtabliſhed by the late king had no farther operation, being determined by the death of the queen; and ſince the crown was rendered hereditary, there was no precedent by which it could be ſettled. The Scots, in general, however, turned their eyes upon the poſterity of David earl of Huntingdon, brother to the two kings Malcolm the Maiden and his ſucceſſor William, both of whom died without lawful iſſue. The earl had three daughter s. Margaret, the eldeſt, was married to Allan lord of Galloway; the only iſſue of which marriage was Derverguill wife to John Baliol, who had a ſon of the ſame name, a competitor </p><p>for the crown. The ſecond daughter, Iſabella, was married to Robert Bruce; and their ſon Robert was a candidate likewiſe. The third daughter, Ada, had been married to Henry Haſtings, an Engliſh nobleman, and predeceſſor to the preſent earl of Huntingdon. John Haſtings, the ſon of this marriage, was a third competitor; but as his claim was confeſſedly the worſt of the three, he only put in for a third of the kingdom, on the principle that his mother was joint- heir with her two filters @@(C). Several other claimants now ſtarted up. Florence earl of Holland pretended to the crown of Scotland in right of his great grandmother Ada, the eldeſt lawful ſiſter of William, ſometime king; as did Robert de Pynkeny, in the right alſo of his great-grandmother Marjory, ſecond ſiſter of the ſame king William. Patrick Gallightly was the ſon of Henry Gallightly, a baſtard of William; William de Roſs was deſcended of Iſabel; Patrick earl of March, of Ilda or Ada; and, William de Veſci, of Marjory; who were three natural daughters of king William. Roger de Mandeville, deſcended from Aufrie, another natural daughter of William, alſo put in his claim; but the right of Nicolas de Soulis, if baſtardy could give a right, was better than the former. His grandmother Marjory, the wife of Allan le Huiſſier, was a natural daughter of Alexander II. and confequently ſiſter to. Alexander III. John Cummin lord of Badenoch derived his claim from a more remote ſource, viz. Donald Bane, who uſurped the crown about 200 years before this time; but he was willing to reſign his pretenſions in favour of John Baliol. The latter indeed had ſurely the beſt right; and, had the ſucceſſion been regulated as it is in all hereditary kingdoms at this day, he would undoubtedly have carried it. Bruce and Haſtings, however, pleaded that they were preferable, not only to John Baliol the grandchild of Margaret, but alſo to Derverguill her daughter and his mother, for the following reaſon. Derverguill and they were equally related to their grandfather earl David: ſhe was indeed the daughter of his eldeſt daughter; but ſhe was a woman, they were men; and, ſaid they, the male in the ſame degree ought to ſucceed to ſovereignties, in their own nature impartible, preferable to the female.</p><p>Notwithſtanding this number of candidates, how-</p><p>@@@(C) The pedigree of the three principal competitors will be fully understood from the following scheme. </p></body></text></TEI>