<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:58Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>vernor in order to relieve her huſband from chains; but private orders had already been gives to put him to death. His unhappy widow, overwhelmed with grief, complained to Charles duke of Burgundy. He ordered Rhinſauld to marry her, after having made over to her all his poſſeſſions. As ſoon as the deed was ſigned, and the marriage over, Charles commanded him to be put to death. Thus the children of a wife whom he had ſeduced, and of a huſband whom he had murdered, became lawful heirs to all his wealth.</p><p>SAPPHIRE, a genus of precious ſtones, of a blue colour, and the hardeſt of all except the ruby and diamond. They are found in the ſame countries with the ruby; alſo in Bohemia, Alſace, Siberia, and Auvergne. M. Rome de l’Iſle mentions one found at Auvergne, which appeared quite green or blue according to the poſition in which it was viewed. Cronſtedt, however, informs us, that the blue fluor ſpars are frequently met with in collections under the name of <hi rend="italic">ſapphires;</hi> and it is certain from Pliny, B. 37. chap. 9. that the ſapphire of the ancients was our lapis lazuli. They are ſeldom found of a deep blue colour throughout, or free from parallel veins; and when they are but ſlightly tinged, they are named <hi rend="italic">white ſapphires.</hi> The late unfortunate king of France had one with a ſtripe of fine yellow topaz in the middle. Some are found half green and half red, and are foliated like the ruby. The fine hard ſapphires, called by the jewellers <hi rend="italic">oriental,</hi> are of the ſame nature with the ruby and topaz, excepting the mere circumſtance of colour. They are commonly in two oblong hexagon pyramids, joined at their baſe, and pointed at top; ſometimes alſo in hexagonal columns.</p><p>The fineſt ſapphires, like moſt of the gems, come from the Eaſt Indies. Ruſſia does not produce the ſapphire. In Scotland they are found of a hardneſs and luſtre equal to the oriental, both light and deep coloured, at Benachie, and Invercauld, Aberdeenſhire; Portſoy in Banffſhire, and many other places. Mr Deuchar, ſeal-engraver in Edinburgh, has in his poſſeſſion a beautiful ſapphire, which was found in a double cryſtal. On one of theſe is cut a head, which was effected with the greateſt difficulty, on account of its hardneſs; the other is cut into facets, and has a fine water, and great brilliancy.</p><p>The ſpecific gravity of theſe precious ſtones, according to Bergman, is from 3, 650 to 3, 940. According to others the ſpecific gravity of the oriental ſapphires is 3, 994; that of the Braſilian 3, 1307; and of thoſe from Puy in Auvergne, 4, 0769. When powdered, they are fuſible with borax, or microcoſmic ſalt, into a tranſparent glaſs; and the ſame thing happens on treating them with magneſia alba. They are ſaid to loſe their colour by fire, and to become ſo hard and tranſparent as ſometimes to paſs for diamonds; but Mr Achard found this to be a miſtake, and that the true ſapphires are not in the leaſt altered either in colour, hardneſs, or weight, by the moſt intenſe fire. Thoſe of Puy in Auvergne, however, though by their colour and hardneſs they ſeem to approach the oriental ſapphires, loſe both their colour and tranſparency in the fire, becoming black, and even vitrifying, which plainly ſhows them to be of a different kind. Engeſtroom informs us, that the ſapphires, in their rough or native ſtate, generally cryſtallize in two oblong hexagonal pyramids pointed at top,</p><p>and joined at their baſes, but are ſometimes found of an hexagonal or columnar form. —A good ſapphire of ten carats is valued at 50 guineas; if it weighs 20 carats, it is valued at 200 guineas; and, if under ten carats, its value may be found by multiplying the carat at 10s. 6d. by the ſquare of its weight. —Sapphires are preferable to common rubies for jewelling watches, on account of the homogeneous hardneſs of their ſubſtance; ſome red ſtones reſembling rubies being met with, which are not uniformly hard.</p><p>SAPPHO, a famous poeteſs of antiquity, who for her excellence in her art has been called the <hi rend="italic">Tenth Muſe,</hi> was born at Mitylene in the iſle of Leſhos, about 610 years before Chriſt. She was contemporary with Steſichorus and Alcaeus; which laſt was her countryman, and as ſome think her ſuitor. A verſe of this poet, in which he inſinuates to her his paſſion, is preſerved in Ariſtotle, <hi rend="italic">Rhet. lib.</hi> i. <hi rend="italic">cap.</hi> 9. together with the fair damſel’s anſwer.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Alc.</hi> I fain to Sappho would a wiſh impart,</p><p>But fear locks up the ſecret in my heart.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sap.</hi> Thy downcaſt looks, reſpect, and timid air. Too plain the nature of thy wiſh declare.</p><p>If lawlefs, wild, inordinate deſire,</p><p>Did not with thoughts impure thy boſom fire. Thy tongue and eyes, by innocence made bold, Ere now the ſecret of thy ſoul had told.</p><p>M. la Fevre obſerves, that Sappho was not in her uſual good-humour when ſhe gave ſo cold an anſwer to a requeſt, for which, at another time, perhaps ſhe would not have waited. — It has been thought, too, that Anacreon was one of her lovers, and his editor Barnes has taken ſome pains to prove it: but chronology will not admit this; ſince, upon inquiry, it will be found that Sappho was probably dead before Anacreon was born. Of the numerous poems this lady wrote, there is nothing remaining but ſome ſmall fragments, which the ancient ſcholiaſts have cited; a hymn to Venus, preſerved by Dionyſius of Halicarnaſſus; and an ode to one of her miſtreſſes @@<hi rend="italic">†</hi>: which laſt piece confirms a tradition delivered down from antiquity, that her amorous paſſion extended even to perſons of her own ſex, and that ſhe was willing to have her miſtreſſes as well as her gallants.</p><p>Ovid introduces her making a ſacrifice to Phaon, one of her male paramours; from which we learn, that Sappho’s love for her own ſex did not keep her from loving ours. She fell deſperately in love with Phaon, and did all ſhe could to win him; but in vain: upon which ſhe threw herſelf headlong from a rock, and died. It is ſaid that Sappho could not forbear following Phaon into Sicily, whither he retired that he might not ſee her; and that during her ſtay in that iſland ſhe probably compoſed the hymn to Venus, ſtill extant, in which ſhe begs ſo ardently the aſſiſtance of that goddeſs. Her prayers, however, proved ineffectual: Phaon was cruel to the laſt degree. Tire unfortunate Sappho was forced to take the dreadful leap; ſhe went to the promontory Leucas, and threw herſelf into the ſea. The cruelty of Phaon will not ſurpriſe us ſo much, if we reflect, that ſhe was a widow (for ſhe had been married to a rich man in the iſle of Andros, by whom ſhe had. a daughter, named <hi rend="italic">Cleis</hi>); that ſhe had never been hand-</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@ [m] † See </hi>Poetry, <hi rend="italic">n8. 122.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>