<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:29Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>whom it reſides. In ſome of the towns of Italy, and in France, in the province of Languedoc, it is one of the greateſt peſts that torments mankind: but its malignity in Europe is trifling, when compared to what the natives of Africa and the eaſt are known to experience. In Batavia, where they grow twelve inches long, there is no removing any piece of furniture, without the utmoſt danger of being ſ<hi rend="italic">t</hi>ung by them. Boſman aſſures us, that along the Gold Coaſt they are often found larger than a lobſter; and that their ſting is inevitably fatal. In Europe, however, they are by no means ſo large, ſo venomous, or ſo numerous. The general ſize of this animal does not exceed two or three inches; and its ſting is very ſeldom found to be fatal. Maupertius, who made ſeveral experiments on the ſcorpion of Languedoc, found it by no means ſo invariably dangerous as had till then been repreſented. He provoked one of them to ſting a dog, in three places of the belly where the animal was without hair. In about an hour after, the poor animal ſeemed greatly swollen, and became very sick: he then call up whatever he had in his bowels; and for about three hours continued vomiting a whitiſh liquid. The belly was always greatly ſwollen when the animal began to vomit; but this operation always ſeemed to abate the ſwelling; which alternately ſwelled, and was thus emptied, for three hours ſucceſſively. The poor animal after this fell into convulſions, bit the ground, dragged himſelf along upon his fore-feet, and at laſt died, five hours after being bitten. He was not partially ſwollen round the place which was bitten, as is uſual after the ſting of a waſp or a bee; but his whole body was inflated, and there only appeared a red ſpot on the places where he had been ſtung.</p><p>Some days after, however, the ſame experiment was tried upon another dog, and even with more aggravated cruelty: yet the dog ſeemed no way affected by the wounds: but, howling a little when he received them, continued alert and well after them; and ſoon after was ſet at liberty, without ſhowing the ſmalleſt ſymptoms of pain. So far was this poor creature from being terrified at the experiment, that he left his own maſter’s houſe, to come to that of the philoſopher, where he had received more plentiful entertainment. The ſame experiment was tried by freſh ſcorpions upon ſeven other dogs, and upon three hens; but not the ſmalleſt deadly ſymptom was ſeen to enſue. From hence it appears, that many circumſtances, which are utterly unknown, muſt contribute to give efficacy to the ſcorpion’s venom. Whether its food, long faſting, the ſeaſon, the nature of the veſſels it wounds, or its ſtate of maturity, contribute to or retard its malignity, is yet to be aſcertained by ſucceeding experiment. In the trials made by our philoſopher, he employed ſcorpions of both ſexes, newly caught, and ſeemingly vigorous and active. The ſucceſs of this experiment may ſerve to ſhew, that many of thoſe boaſted antidotes which are given for the cure of the ſcorpion’s ſting, owe their ſucceſs rather to accident than their own efficacy. They only happened to cure when their ſting was no way dangerous; but in caſes of actual malignity, they might probably be utterly unſerviceable</p><p>The ſcorpion of the tropical climates being much larger than the former is probably much more venomous. Helbigius, however, who reſided for many years</p><p>in the eaſt, aſſures us, that he was often ſtung by the ſcorpion, and never received any material injury from the wound: a painful tumor generally enſued; but he always cured it by rubbing the part with a piece of iron or ſtone, as he had ſeen the Indians practiſe before him, until the fleſh became inſenſible. Seba, Moore, and Boſman, however, give a very different account of the ſcorpion’s malignity: and aſſert, that, unleſs ſpeedily relieved, the wound becomes fatal.</p><p>It is certain, that no animal in the creation ſeems endued with ſuch an iraſcible nature. They have often been ſeen, when taken and put into a place of ſecurity, to exert all their rage againſt the ſides of the glaſs-veſſel that contained them. They will attempt to ſting a ſtick when put near them; and attack a mouſe or a frog, while thoſe animals are far from offering any injury. Maupertius put three ſcorpions and a mouſe into the ſame veſſel together, and they ſoon ſtung the little animal in different places. The mouſe, thus aſſaulted, ſtood for ſome time upon the defenſive, and at laſt killed them all, one after another. He tried this experiment, in order to ſee whether the mouſe, after it had killed, would eat the ſcorpions; but the little quadruped ſeemed ſatisfied with the victory, and even ſurvived the ſeverity of the wounds it had received. Wolkamer tried the courage of the ſcorpion againſt the large ſpider, and incloſed ſeveral of both kinds in glaſs veſſels for that purpoſe. The ſucceſs of this combat was very remarkable. The ſpider at firſt uſed all its efforts to intangle the ſcorpion in its web, which it immediately began ſpinning; but the ſcorpion reſcued itſelf from the danger, by ſtinging its adverſary to death: it ſoon after cut off, with its claws, all the legs of the ſpider, and then ſucked all the internal parts at its leiſure. — If the ſcorpion’s ſkin had not been ſo hard, Wolkamer is of opinion that the ſpider would have obtained the victory; for he had often ſeen one of theſe ſpiders deſtroy a toad.</p><p>The fierce ſpirit of this animal is equally dangerous to its own ſpecies; for ſcorpions are the cruelleſt enemies to each other. Maupertius put about 100 of them together in the ſame glaſs; and they ſcarce came into contact when they began to exert all their rage in mutual deſtruction: there was nothing to be ſeen but one univerſal carnage, without any diſtinction of age or ſex; ſo that in a few days there remained only 14, which had killed and devoured all the reft.</p><p>But their unnatural malignity is ſtill more apparent in their cruelty to their offspring. He incloſed a female ſcorpion, big with young, in a glaſs veſſel, and ſhe was ſeen to devour them as faſt as they were excluded: there was but one only of the number that eſcaped the general deſtruction, by taking refuge on the back of its parent; and this ſoon after revenged the cauſe of its brethren, by killing the old one in its turn.</p><p>Such is the terrible and unrelenting nature of this inſect, which neither the bonds of ſociety nor of nature can reclaim: it is even aſſerted, that, when driven to an extremity, the ſcorpion will often deſtroy itſelf. The following experiment was ineffectually tried by Maupertius: "But, " ſays Mr Goldſmith, “I am ſo well aſſured of it by many eye-witneſſes, who have ſeen it both in Italy and America, that I have no doubt remaining of its veracity. A ſcorpion, newly caught,</p></body></text></TEI>