<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Stillingfleet, Eſq; recommended the ſowing of this plant on the ſandy wilds of
                Norfolk, that its matted roots might prevent the deluges of fand which that country
                experiences. It has been already remarked, that whereſoever this plant grows the
                ſalutary effects are ſoon obſerved to follow. A ſingle plant will fix the fand, and
                gather it into a hillock; theſe hillocks, by the increaſe of vegetation, are formed
                into larger, till by degrees a barrier is made often againſt the encroachments of
                the ſea; and might as often prove preventative of the calamity in queſtion. I
                cannot, therefore, but recommend the trial to the inhabitants of many parts of North
                Britain. The plant grows in moſt places near the ſea, and is known to the
                Highlanders by the name of <hi rend="italic">murah;</hi> to the Engliſh by that of
                    <hi rend="italic">bent- ſtar, mat-gra</hi>ſ<hi rend="italic">s,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">marram.</hi> Linnaeus calls it <hi rend="italic">arundo
                    arenaria.</hi> The Dutch call it <hi rend="italic">helm.</hi> This plant hath
                ſtiff and ſharp-pointed leaves, growing like a ruſh, a foot and a half long: the
                roots both creep and penetrate deeply into their ſandy beds: the ſtalk bears an ear
                five or six inches long, not unlike rye; the ſeeds are ſmall, brown, and roundiſh.
                By good fortune, as old Gerard obſerves, no cattle will eat or touch this vegetable,
                allotted for other purpoſes, ſubſervient to the uſe of mankind.”</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SAND-Piper,</hi> in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Tringa.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SAND-Stοne, </hi>a genus of ſtones belonging to the order of ſaxa;
                and including all thoſe which conſiſt of ſuch minute particles that they cannot
                eaſily be diſcerned by the eye. The ſpecies enumerated by Cronſtedt are,</p>
                <p> 1. Thoſe cemented by a clay, of which there are two varieties; one with
                    porcelain clay, the other with common clay. The former is met with in Sweden
                    under the ſtratum of coal in a coal-mine in the province of Shone, and is very
                    hard and refractory in the fire; the other is found in the iſland of
                    Gothland.</p>
                <p> 2. With lime, reſembling mortar made with coarſe ſand. There are two varieties,
                    one conſiſting of tranſparent grey-coloured grains of quartz and white lime-
                    ſtone, the other of a looſe texture, hardening in the air; but having the
                    particles too fine to be viſible. The former of theſe is found in Sweden, the
                    latter in France and Livonia.</p>
                <p> 3. Sand-ſtone having its particles bound together by an unknown cement. Of this
                    there are four varieties; 1. Looſe; 2. Somewhat hard; 3. Compact; 4. Very hard;
                    all of them found in different parts of Sweden.</p>
                <p> 4. Cemented by ruſt of iron, found in the form of looſe ſtones in ſeveral
                    places.</p>
            <p>Cronſtedt informs us that the greateſt part of ſand- ſtones conſiſt of quartz and
                mica, being thoſe ſubſtances which moſt readily admit of granulation without being
                reduced to powder. Some years ago the Baron de Dietrich ſhowed a ſingular variety of
                ſand-ſtone at Paris. It conſiſts of ſmall grains of hard quartz which ſtrike fire
                with ſteel united with ſome micaceous particles. It is flexible and elaſtic, the
                flexibility depending on the micaceous part and ſoftneſs of the gluten with which
                the particles are cemented. This elaſtic ſtone is ſaid to have been found at Brazil,
                and brought to Germany by his excellency the marquis de Lavradio. There are alſo two
                tables of white marble, kept in the palace of Borgheſe at Rome, which have the ſame
                property But the ſparry particles of their ſubſtance, though tranſparent, are rather
                ſoft, and may be eaſily ſeparated by the nail. They efferveſce with aquafortis, and
                there is alſo a ſmall mixture of minute particles of talk or mica.</p>
            <p>Sand-ſtones are of great uſe in buildings which are required to reſiſt air, water,
                and fire Some of them are ſoft in the quarry, but become hard when expoſed to the
                air. The looſe ones are moſt uſeful, but the ſolid and hard ones crack in the fire,
                and take a poliſh when uſed as grindſtones. Stones of this kind ought therefore to
                be nicely examined before they are employed for the uſual purpoſes. Our author
                obſerves that the working maſons, or ſtone-cutters, ought to wear a piece of frize
                or baize before their mouths, to preſerve themſelves from a conſumption which their
                buſineſs is otherwiſe apt to bring on. Limeſtone, however, is not obſerved to have
                this effect.</p>
            <p>To the lift of ſand-ſtones Fabroni adds gritſtone, of greater or leſs hardneſs;
                moſtly of a grey, and ſometimes of a yellowiſh colour, compoſed of a ſiliceous and
                micaceous fand, but rarely of a ſparry kind, with greater or leſſer particles
                cloſely connected with an argillaceous cement. It ſtrikes fire with ſteel, vitrifies
                in a ſtrong fire, and is generally indiſſoluble in acids. It is uſed for
                mill-ſtones, whet-ſtones, and ſometimes for filtering ſtones, as well as for
                building.</p>
            <p>SANDAL, in antiquity, a rich kind of flipper worn on the feet by the Greek and Roman
                ladies, made of gold, ſilk, or other precious ſtuff; conſiſting of a fole, with an
                hollow at one extreme to embrace the ancle, but leaving the upper part of the foot
                bare.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sandal,</hi> is alſo uſed for a ſhoe or flipper worn by the pope
                and other Romiſh prelates when they officiate. It is alſo the name of a fort of
                flipper worn by ſeveral congregations of reformed monks. This laſt conſiſts of no
                more than a mere leathern ſole, faſtened with latches or buckles, all the reſt of
                the foot being left bare. The capuchins wear ſandals; the recollects, clogs; the
                former are of leather, and the latter of wood.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SANDAL-Wοοd.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Saunders.</hi></p>
            <p>SANDARACH, in natural hiſtory, a very beautiful native foſſil, though too often
                confounded with the common factitious red arſenic, and with the red matter formed by
                melting the common yellow orpiment.</p>
            <p>It is a pure ſubſtance, of a very even and regular ſtructure, is throughout of that
                colour which our dyers term an <hi rend="italic">orange ſcarlet, </hi>and is
                conſiderably transparent even in the thickeſt pieces. But though, with reſpect to
                colour, it has the advantage of cinnabar while in the maſs, it is vaſtly inferior to
                it when both are reduced to powder. It is moderately hard, and remarkably heavy;
                and, when expoſed to a moderate heat, melts and flows like oil: if ſet on fire, it
                burns very briſkly.</p>
            <p>It is found in Saxony and Bohemia, in the copper and ſilver mines; and is ſold to the
                painters, who find it a very fine and valuable red: but its virtues or qualities in
                medicine are no more aſcertained at this time than thoſe of the yellow orpiment.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Gum-SANDARACH</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">y</hi> is a dry and
                hard reſin, uſually met with in looſe granules, of the bigneſs of a pea, a
                horſe-bean, or larger; of a pale whitiſh yellow colour, tranſparent, and of a
                reſinous ſmell, brittle, very inflammable, of an acrid and aromatic taſte, and
                diffuſing a very pleaſant ſmell when burning. It is produced from</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
