<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>earl of Northumberland, reſolved to take ſignal vengeance. He ravaged the Scots borders, particularly the earl of March’s eſtate, for three days, at the head of 10,000 men. Some time after this, the Scots inſurgents became powerful enough to ſurpriſe Berwick; which, however, was quickly retaken by the Engliſh, who ſoon after invaded Scotland. In this expedition, however, they ſucceeded ſo ill, that Percy thought proper to deſiſt from his expedition. The Scots in the mean time began hoſtilities by ſea, under one Mercer, an experienced ſailor; but he had the misfortune to be taken priſoner by the Engliſh, with all his fleet. In 1379, England was afflicted with a dreadful plague, of which the Scots took advantage to invade the country. The Engliſh hiſtorians tell us that they behaved with the utmoſt barbarity, killing and plundering the defenceleſs inhabitants without mercy.</p><p>This predatory war continued, generally to the diſadvantage of the Engliſh, till the beginning of November 1380, when a truce was concluded, to continue for a year; which, however, related only to the borders. This truce, like the others, was but very indifferently obſerved; ſo that, in 1383, new negociations were ſet on foot: but, in 1384, the war was renewed with greater fury than ever. In the ſpring, the earls of March and Douglas took the castle of Lochmaben, and intercepted a rich convoy which the Engliſh were sending to Roxburgh; burnt to the ground the caſtle of Wark, and committed ſuch devaſtations in the north of England, that ſeveral gentlemen offered to reſign their eſtates to King Richard, becauſe they were not able to defend them againſt the Scots. The Duke of Lancaſter entered Scotland at the head of an army; but the inhabitants had removed every thing valuable, ſo that he marched on to Edinburgh without accompliſhing any thing of conſequence. On his return, he was haraſſed by flying parties of Scots, who deſtroyed a conſiderable number of his men. This year alſo the French ſent a body of auxiliaries into Scotland. The earls of Northumberland and Nottingham entered Scotland with an army of 10,000 horſe and 6000 archers; but retired, after having committed ſome devaſtations in the ſouthern counties. The Scots revenged themſelves by laying waſte all the northern part of England to the gates of Newcaſtle. Berwick was taken by the Scots, and ſoon after ſurrendered for the ſum of 2000 marks. A truce was then, as uſual, concluded; but in the mean time king Robert was meditating a moſt ſevere blow againſt the Engliſh.</p><p>The Duke of Burgundy having come to the poſſeſſion of the eſtate of his father-in-law the earl of Flanders, claimed the ſovereignty of the town of Client; but they refuſed to ſubmit to him, and in this refuſal were protected by king Richard II. of England. On this the duke of Burgundy propoſed to the French court to invade England in concert with the Scots.— This being agreed to, a fleet was fitted out at Sluys; on board of which John de Vienne, the French admiral, embarked, carrying along with him 50,000 pounds in gold, which the duke of Burgundy advanced in order to be diſtributed in Scotland, where the admiral arrived ſafe with a conſiderable reinforcement, together with Supplies of all kinds of military ſtores. Two thouſand auxiliaries, of whom 500 were men-at-arms, arrived with this fleet; and 400 ſuits of complete armour were Brought along with them, in order to be diſtributed among the braveſt of the Scots.</p><p>The Scots were for a ſhort time elated with the great attention which had been paid them by the French king; but, in the mean time, the Flemings having revolted, the French abandoned the Scots to ſuſtain the whole weight of the Engliſh reſentment, that they themſelves might employ their arms in Flanders. King Richard took the field with a more numerous army than had ever been muſtered in England before. Hoſtilſties were begun by the Scots, who, according to cuſtom, invaded the northern parts of England, and carried off a conſiderable booty: however, in their retreat, they were in the utmoſt danger of being cut off by the duke of Lancaſter, who had been ſent with an army to intercept them. The Engliſh army proceeded northwards: but could accompliſh nothing, on account of the country being deſolated, till they came to Edinburgh, which they laid in aſhes. Being, however, inceſſantly haraſsed by parties of the enemy, they were obliged to retreat.</p><p>Nothing remarkable happened till the year 1378, when, after a ſhort truce, the war was renewed with freſh fury. Northumberland and Weſtmoreland were ravaged by the earls of Fife and Douglas, and Lord Nithſdale defeated a body of 3000 Engliſh; after which he formed the plan of invading Ireland, the inhabitants of which had of late been very active againſt the Scots. In 1388, Douglas obtained permiſſion to raiſe a body of forces for this invaſion; and having landed in ſafety, defeated the Iriſh, plundered the town of Carlingford, and loaded fifteen ſhips with the booty. From thence the Scots ſailed to the iſle of Man, which in like manner was plundered and laid waſte; after which they returned with their booty to Loch Rian in Scotland.</p><p>Encouraged by this succeſs, Robert determined to proceed on a more enlarged plan. Having aſſembled a parliament at Aberdeen, a double invaſion of England  was reſolved upon. Two armies were raiſed; the one, conſiſting of 25,000 men, commanded by the earls of Mentieth and Fife, Douglas lord of Galloway, and Alexander Lindſay; the other army, conſiſting of the like number, was commanded by the earls of Douglas, March, Crawford, Moray, the lord high Conſtable of Scotland, and other perſons of diſtinction. The former entered Cumberland, and the latter Northumberland, both which countries they laid waſte, and both armies were to meet within ten miles of Newcaſtle. The Engliſh were thrown into the greateſt conſternation. Newcaſtle was defended by the earl of Northumberland, whoſe age and infirmities rendered him incapable of taking the field; but his place was abundantly ſupplied by his two ſons Henry and Ralph, the former of whom is known in Engliſh hiſtory by the name of <hi rend="italic">Hotſpur. </hi>The town was garriſoned by the flower of the Engliſh nobility and gentry, as well as the inhabitants of the adjacent countries, who had fled thither for refuge. Douglas ſelected 2000 foot and 300 horſemen out of the two armies, and encamped on the north ſide of the town, with a view, according to the Scots hiſtorians, of ſtorming it next day. In the mean time, he was challenged by Hotſpur to fight him hand to hand, with ſharp ground ſpears, in ſight of both armies. Douglas accepted the challenge, and Percy was unhorſed the firſt encounter, and obliged to take refuge within the</p></body></text></TEI>