<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>phichen in Scotland, a knight of another order of religious ſoldiery@@(E).</p><p>The Scots in their retreat burnt the town and caſtle of Stirling. Edward repaired the caſtle, and made it a place of arms. He then marched to the weſt. At his approach, Bruce burnt the caſtle of Ayr, and retired. Edward would have purſued him into Carrick; but the want of proviſions flopped his further progreſs. He turned into Annandale, took Bruce’s caſtle of Lochmaben, and then departed out of Scotland by the weſtern borders.</p><p>Here may be remarked the fatal precipitancy of the Scots. If they had ſtudied to protract the campaign, inſtead of hazarding a general action at Falkirk, they would have foiled the whole power of Edward, and reduced him to the neceſſity of an inglorious retreat,</p><p>In 1299 Edward thought proper to releaſe John Baliol the unfortunate king of Scotland, whom he had kept cloſe priſoner ever ſince the year 1296. Before this time Baliol had uſed the moſt diſgraceful methods to recover his liberty. He had ſolemnly declared, that “he would never have any intercourſe with the Scots; that he had found them a falſe and treacherous people; and that he had reaſon to ſuſpect them of an intention to poiſon him.” However, notwithſtanding all his proteſtations, Edward ſtill detained him in captivity; but at laſt releaſed him at the mediation of the pope, though after a ſingular form: He ordered the governor of Dover to convey him to the French coaſt, and there to deliver him to the papal nuncio, “with full power to the pope to diſpoſe of Baliol and his Engliſh eſtate.” In conſequence of which he was conveyed to Witſand, delivered to the nuncio in preſence of a notary and witneſſes, and a receipt taken for his perſon. Notwithstanding this abject ſtate, however, the Scots continued to own him for their king, and to aſſert their national independency. Tho’ the misfortune at Falkirk had deprived them of a very conſiderable extent of territory, they were ſtill in poſſeſſion of the whole country beyond the Forth, as well as the county of Galloway. By general conſent William Lamberton biſhop of St Andrew’s, Robert Bruce earl of Carrick, and John Cummin the younger, were choſen guardians of Scotland in name of Baliol. Wallace at this time was reduced to the condition of a private man; nor had he any longer the command of the Scots armies, nor any ſhare in their councils. —The new guardians undertook to reduce the caſtle of Stirling, and Edward prepared to defend it. The Scots poſted themſelves at the Torwood, and choſe their ground judiciouſly, ſo that Edward could ſcarce have raiſed the ſiege without diſlodging them; which finding it impoſſible for him to do, he returned home in diſguſt. Next year he invaded Scotland on the weſt fide, wafted Annandale, and reduced Galloway; but the Scots being now taught by experience to avoid a general action, choſe their poſts with ſuch ſkill, that Ed-</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@ (e)</hi> “This account of the action at Falkirk, extracted from Lord Hailes’s <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi>, is drawn, his Lordſhip informs us, from the teſtimony of the Engliſh hiſtorians. “They have done juſtice (he obſerves) to the courage and ſteadineſs of their enemies; while our hiſtorians repreſented their own countrymen as occupied in frivolous unmeaning conteſts, and, from treachery or reſentment, abandoning the public cauſe in the day of trial.</p><p>“It would be tedious and unprofitable to recite all that has been ſaid on this ſubject by our own writers from Fordun to Abercrombie. How Wallace, Stewart, and Cornyn, quarrelled on the punctilio of leading the van of an army which ſtood on the defenſive: How Stewart compared Wallace to ‘an owl with borrowed feathers,’: How the Scottiſh commanders, buſied in this frivolous altercation, had no leiſure to form their army: How Cornyn traiterouſly withdrew with 10,000 men: How Wallace, from reſentment, followed his example: How by ſuch diſaſtrous incidents, the Scottiſh army was enfeebled, and Stewart and his party abandoned to deſtruction. Our hiſtories abound in traſh of this kind: There is ſcarcely one of our writers who has not produced an invective againſt Cornyn, or an apology for Wallace, or a lamentation over the deſerted Stewart. What diſſenſions may have prevailed among the Scottiſh commanders, it is impoſſible to know. It appears not to me that their diſſenſions had any influence on their conduct in the day of battle. The truth ſeems to be this: The Engliſh cavalry greatly exceeded the Scottiſh in numbers, were infinitely better equipped and more adroit: the Scottiſh cavalry were intimidated, and fled. Had they remained on the field, they might have preſerved their honour; but they never could have turned the chance of that day. It was natural, however, for ſuch of the infantry as ſurvived the engagement, to impute their diſaſter to the defection of the cavalry. National pride would aſcribe their flight to treachery rather than to puſillanimity. It is not improbable that Cornyn commanded the cavalry: hence a report may have been ſpread, that Cornyn betrayed his country; this report has been embelliſhed by each ſucceſſive relator. When men are ſeized with a panic, their commander <hi rend="italic">must</hi> from neceſſity, or <hi rend="italic">will</hi> from prudence, accompany them in their flight. Earl Warrenne fled with his army from Stirling to Berwick; yet Edward I. did not puniſh him as a traitor or a coward.</p><p>“The tale of Cornyn’s treachery, and Wallace’s ill-timed reſentment, may have gained credit, becauſe it is a pretty tale, and not improbable in itſelf: but it amazes me that the ſtory of the <hi rend="italic">congreſs</hi> of Bruce and Wallace after the battle of Falkirk ſhould have gained credit. I lay aſide the full evidence which we now poſſeſs, 'that Bruce was not, at that time, of the Engliſh party, nor preſent at the battle.’ For it muſt be admitted, that our hiſtorians knew nothing of thoſe circumſtances which demonſtrate the impoſſibility of the co<hi rend="italic">ngreſs.</hi> But the wonder is, that men of ſound judgment ſhould not have ſeen the abſurdity of a long converſation between the commander of a flying army, and one of the leaders of a victorious army. When Fordun told the ſtory, he placed a 'narrow but inacceſſible glen’ between the ſpeakers. Later hiſtorians have ſubſtituted the river Carron in the place of the inacceſſible glen, and they make Bruce and Wallace talk acroſs the river like two young declaimers from the pulpits in a ſchool of rhetoric. ”</p></body></text></TEI>