<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ſay, who ſeems to have had very minute information as to this event, Cochran rudely
                knocked at the door of the church, juſt after the aſſembly had finiſhed their
                conſultation; and upon Sir Robert Douglas of Lochleven (who was appointed to watch
                the door) informing them that the earl of Mar demanded admittance, the earl of Angus
                ordered the door to be thrown open; and ruſhing upon Cochran, he pulled a maſſy gold
                chain from his neck, ſaying, that a rope would become him better; while Sir Robert
                Douglas ſtripped him of a coſtly blowing horn he wore by his ſide, as was the manner
                of the times, telling him he had been too long the hunter of miſchief. Cochran, with
                aſtoniſhment, aſked them whether they were in jeſt or earneſt; but they ſoon
                convinced him they were in earneſt, by pinioning down his arms with a common halter
                till he ſhould be carried to execution.</p>
            <p>The earl of Angus, with ſome of the chief lords, attended by a detachment of troops,
                then repaired to the king’s tent, where they ſeized his other favourites, Thomas
                Preſton, Sir William Rogers, James Hommil, William Torfiſan, and Leonard: and
                upbraided James himſelf, in very rude terms, with his miſconduct in government, and
                even in private life, in not only being counſelled by the above minions, but for
                keeping company with a lady who was called the <hi rend="italic">Daiſy.</hi> We know
                of no reſiſtance made by James. He only interceded for the ſafety of a young
                gentleman, one John Ramſay of Balmain. Cochran, with his other worthleſs favourites,
                were hanged over Lawderbridge before his eyes; and he himſelf was conducted, under
                an eaſy reſtraint, to the caſtle of Edinburgh.</p>
            <p>James, though confined, behaved with great ſpirit; and even refuſed to pardon thoſe
                who had confined him, or who had any hand in the execution at Lawder. At laſt,
                however, he was relieved by the duke of Albany, who, at the queen’s deſire,
                undertook to deliver her huſband from confinement. This he accompliſhed, as ſome
                ſay, by ſurpriſing the caſtle of Edinburgh; though, according to others, the gates
                were opened, upon a formal requiſition made ſo that purpoſe by two heralds at arms.
                After he had obtained his liberty, the king repaired to the abbey of Holyroodhouſe
                with his brother, who now acted as his firſt miniſter. All the lords who were near
                the capital came to pay him their compliments; but James was ſo much exaſperated at
                what had happened, that he committed 16 of them priſoners to the caſtle of
                Edinburgh. After his releaſe, James granted a patent to the citizens of Edinburgh,
                and enlarged their privileges.</p>
            <p>In 1487, James finiſhed ſome ſecret negociations in which he had engaged with Henry
                king of England ſome time. The principal articles agreed on between the two monarchs
                were, That king James’s ſecond ſon</p>
            <p>ſhould marry Catherine the third daughter of Edward IV. and ſiſter to the princeſs
                Elizabeth, now queen of England; and that James himſelf, who was now a widower,
                ſhould marry queen Elizabeth. A third marriage was alſo to be concluded between the
                duke of Rotheſay and another daughter of Edward IV. That in order to theſe treaties,
                and for ending all controverſies concerning the town of Berwick, which the king of
                Scotland deſired ſo much to poſſeſs, a congreſs ſhould be held the enſuing year.</p>
            <p>But in the mean time moſt powerful confederacy was formed againſt the king; the
                origin of which was as follows. James was a threat patron of architecture; and being
                pleaſed with the ſituation of Stirling caſtle, he reſolved to give it all the
                embelliſhments which that art could beſtow; and about this time he made it the chief
                place of his reſidence. He raiſed within it a hall, which at that time was deemed a
                noble ſtructure; and a college, which he called the chapel-royal. This college was
                endowed with an archdean who was a biſhop, a ſubdean, a treaſurer, a chanter and
                ſubchanter, with a double ſet of other officers uſually belonging to ſuch
                inſtitutions. The expences necessary for maintaining theſe were conſiderable, and
                the king had reſolved to aſſign the revenues of the rich priory of Coldingham for
                that purpoſe. This priory had been generally held by one of the name of Hume; and
                that family, through length of time, conſidered it as their property: they therefore
                ſtrongly oppoſed the king’s intention. The diſpute ſeems to have laſted ſome years:
                for the former parliament had paſſed a vote, annexing the priory to the king’s
                chapel-royal; and the parliament of this year had paſſed a ſtatute, ſtrictly
                prohibiting all perſons, ſpiritual and temporal, to attempt any thing, directly or
                indirectly, contrary or prejudicial to the ſaid union and annexation. The Humes
                reſented their being ſtripped of ſo gainful a revenue, the loſs of which affected
                moſt of the gentlemen of that name; and they united themſelves with the Hepburns,
                another powerful clan in that neighbourhood, under the lord Hales. An aſſociation
                was ſoon formed; by which both families engaged to ſtand by each other, and not to
                ſuffer any prior to be received for Coldingham, if he was not of one of their
                ſurnames. The lords Gray and Drummond ſoon joined the aſſociation; as did many other
                noblemen and gentlemen, who had their particular cauſes of diſcontent. Their agents
                gave out, that the king was graſping at arbitrary power; that he had acquired his
                popularity by deep hypocriſy; and that he was reſolved to be ſignally revenged upon
                all who had any hand in the execution at Lawder. The earl of Angus, who was the ſoul
                of the confederacy, adviſed the conſpirators to apply to the old earl of Douglas to
                head them: but that nobleman was now dead to all ambition, and inſtead</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
