<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>charters belonging to the abbey were carried off, and the ſeals torn from others:
                "which,” ſays Lord Hailes, is the only well-vouched example which I have found of
                any outrage on private property committed by Edward’s army. It is mentioned in a
                charter of Robert I. and we may be aſſured that the outrage was not diminiſhed in
                the relation.”</p>
            <p>On the 28th of Auguſt 1296, Edward held a parliament at Berwick, where he received
                the fealty of the clergy and laity of Scotland. It is ſaid, that while the Engliſh
                monarch was employed in the conqueſt of Scotland, he had promiſed the ſovereignty to
                Robert Bruce, lord of Annandale, in order to ſecure his fidelity; but being put in
                mind of his promiſe, he anſwered, “Have I no other buſineſs but to conquer kingdoms
                for you?” Bruce ſilently retired, and paſſed his days in obſcurity. Among thoſe who
                profeſſed their allegiance at this parliament was Robert Bruce the younger, earl of
                Carrick. After this, Edward took the moſt effectual methods of ſecuring his new
                conqueſt. He ordered the eſtates of the clergy to be reſtored; and having received
                the fealty of the widows of many of the Scottiſh barons, he put them in poſſeſſion
                of their jointure-lands, and even made a decent proviſion for the wives of many of
                his priſoners. Yet, though in every thing he behaved with great moderation towards
                the Scots, he committed the government of certain diſtricts, and of the chief
                caſtles in the ſouth of Scotland, to his Engliſh ſubjects, of whoſe fidelity and
                vigilance he thought himſelf assured. In order to conciliate the affections of the
                clergy, he granted to the Scottiſh biſhops, for ever, the privilege of bequeathing
                their effects by will, in the ſame manner as that privilege was enjoyed by the
                archbiſhops and biſhops of England. In honour of the “glorious Confeſſor St
                Cuthbeit,” he gave to the monks of Durham an annual penſion of 40 pounds, payable
                out of the revenues of Scotland, by the tenure of maintaining, before the ſhrine of
                the ſaint, two wax-tapers of 20 pounds weight each, and of diſtributing twice a-year
                one penny each to 3000 indigent perſons. At laſt, having ſettled every thing, as he
                thought, in tranquillity, he departed for England, with all the pride of a
                conqueror.</p>
            <p>The tranquillity eſtabliſhed by Edward, however, was of ſhort duration. The
                government of Scotland at that time required many qualities which Edward’s
                vicegerents had not. Warenne, earl of Surry, who had been appointed governor, took
                up his abode in England, on pretence of recovering his health. Creſſingham, the
                treaſurer, was a voluptuous, proud, and ſelfiſh eccleſiaſtic; while Ormeſhy the
                juſticiary was hated for his ſeverity. Under theſe officers the adminiſtration of
                Edward became more and more feeble; bands of robbers infeſted the highways, and the
                Engliſh government was univerſally deſpiſed. At this critical moment aroſe Sir
                William Wallace, the hero ſo much celebrated in Scottiſh fables, and by which indeed
                his real exploits are ſo much obſcured, that it is difficult to give an authentic
                relation of them. The moſt probable account is, that</p>
            <p>he was the younger ſon of a gentleman (Wallace of Ellerſlie) in the neighbourhood of
                Paiſley. Having been outlawed for ſome offence (generally ſuppoſed to have been the
                killing of an Engliſhman), he aſſociated with a few companions, of fortunes equally
                deſperate with his own. Wallace himſelf was endowed with great ſtrength and courage,
                and an active and ambitious ſpirit; and by his affability, eloquence, and wiſdom, he
                maintained an authority over the rude and undiſciplined multitudes who flocked to
                his ſtandard. In May 1297, he began to infeſt the Engliſh quarters; and being
                ſucceſsful in his predatory incurſions, his party became more numerous, and he was
                joined by Sir William Douglas. With their united forces, theſe two allies attempted
                to ſurpriſe Ormeſhy the juſticiary, while he held his courts at Scone; but he ſaved
                himſelf by a precipitate flight. After this the Scots roved over the whole country,
                aſſaulted caſtles, and maſſacred the Engliſh. Their party was joined by many perſons
                of rank; among whom were Robert Wiſheart biſhop of Glaſgow, the Steward of Scotland
                and his brother Alexander de Lindſay, Sir Richard Lundin, and Sir Andrew Moray of
                Bothwell. Young Bruce would have been a vaſt acceſſion to the party; for he
                poſſeſſed all Carrick and Annandale, ſo that his territories reached from the frith
                of Clyde to Solway. But the wardens of the weſtern marches of England ſuſpected his
                fidelity, and ſummoned him to Carliſle. He obeyed, and made oath on the conſecrated
                hoſt, and on the ſword of Becket, to be faithful and vigilant in the cauſe of
                Edward; and to prove his ſincerity, he invaded with fire and ſword the eſtate of Sir
                William Douglas, and carried off his wife and children. However, he inſtantly
                repented of what he had done: “I truſt (ſaid he), that the pope will abſolve me from
                an extorted oath;” on which he abandoned Edward, and joined the Scottiſh army.</p>
            <p>All this time Edward was in France, not in the leaſt ſuſpecting an inſurrection among
                people whom he imagined he had thoroughly ſubdued. As ſoon as he received the
                intelligence, he ordered the earl of Surry to ſuppreſs the rebels; but he declining
                the command of the army himſelf on account of his health, reſigned it to his nephew,
                Lord Henry Percy. A great army, ſome ſay no fewer than 40,000 men, was now
                aſſembled, with which Percy marched againſt the Scots. He found them encamped at
                Irwin, with a lake in their front, and their flanks ſecured by entrenchments, ſo
                that they could not be attacked without the utmoſt danger. The Scots, however,
                ruined every thing by their diſſenſions. Wallace was envied on account of his
                accompliſhments, which had raiſed his reputation above the other officers, whoſe
                birth and circumſtances were higher than his. His companions accordingly became
                jealous, and began to ſuggeſt, that an oppoſition to the Engliſh could only be
                productive of farther national deſtruction. Sir Richard Lundin, an officer of great
                rank- formed a party againſt Wallace, and went over to Edward with all his
                followers. He attempted to juſtify</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
