<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:23Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pleaſed to bend their bodies with their genius: his preſence muſt lay thoſe who behold him proſtrate on the earth: he deſires no eagerneſs, no attention; he would only inſpire terror.</p><p>The pope makes no reverence to any mortal except the emperor, to whom he ſtoops a very little when he permits him to kiſs his lips.</p><p>SALUTE, in military matters, a diſcharge of artillery, or ſmall arms, or both, in honour of ſome perſon of extraordinary quality. The <hi rend="italic">colours</hi> likewiſe ſalute royal perſons, and generals commanding in chief; which is done by lowering the point to the ground. In the field, when a regiment is to be reviewed by the king or his general, the drums beat a march as he paſſes along the line, and the officers ſalute one after another, bowing their half-pikes or ſwords to the ground; then recover and take off their hats. The enſigns ſalute all together, by lowering their colours.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Salute,</hi> in the navy, a teſtimony of deference or homage rendered by the ſhips of one nation to another, or by ſhips of the ſame nation to a ſuperior or equal.</p><p>This ceremony is variouſly performed, according to the circumſtances, rank, or ſituation, of the parties. It conſits in firing a certain number of cannon, or volleys of ſmall arms; in linking the colours or top-ſails; or in one or more general ſhouts of the whole ſhip’s crew, mounted on the maſts or rigging for that purpoſe.</p><p>The principal regulations with regard to ſalutes in the royal navy are as follow:</p><p>“When a flag-officer ſalutes the admiral and commander in chief of the fleet, he is to give him fifteen guns; but when captains ſalute him, they are to give him seventeen guns. The admiral and commander in chief of the fleet is to return two guns leſs to flag-officers, and four leſs to captains. Flag-officers ſaluting their ſuperior or ſenior officer, are to give him thirteen guns. Flag-officers are to return an equal number of guns to flag-officers bearing their flags on the fame maſt, and two guns leſs to the reft, as alſo to captains.</p><p>“When a captain ſalutes an admiral of the white or blue, he is to give him fifteen guns; but to vice and rear admirals, thirteen guns. When a flag-officer is ſaluted by two or more of his majeſty’s ſhips, he is not to return the ſalute till all have finiſhed, and then to do it with ſuch a reaſonable number of guns as he ſhall judge proper.</p><p>“In caſe of the meeting of two ſquadrons, the two chiefs only are to exchange ſalutes. And if ſingle ſhips meet a ſquadron confiſting of more than one flag, the principal flag only is to be ſaluted. No ſalutes ſhall be repeated by the ſame ſhips, unleſs there has been a ſeparation of fix months at leaſt.</p><p>“None of his majeſty’s ſhips of war, commanded only by captains, ſhall give or receive ſalutes from one another, in whatſoever part of the world they meet.</p><p>“A flag officer commanding in chief ſhall be ſaluted, upon his firſt hoiſting his flag, by all the ſhips preſent, with ſuch a number of guns as is allowed by the firſt, third, or fifth articles.</p><p>“When any of his majeſty’s ſhips ſhall meet with any ſhip or ſhips belonging to any foreign prince or ſtate, within his majeſty’s ſeas (which extend to Cape Firriſterre), it is expected, that the ſaid Foreign ſhips do</p><p>ſtrike their top-ſail, and take in their flag, in acknowledgement of his majeſty’s ſovereignty in thoſe ſeas: and if any ſhall refuſe or offer to refill, it is enjoined to all flag-officers and commanders to uſe their utmoſt endeavours to compel them thereto, and not ſuffer any diſhonour to be done to his majeſty. And if any of his majeſty’s ſubjects ſhall ſo much forget their duty, as to omit ſtriking their top-ſail in paſſing by his majeſty’s ſhips, the name of the ſhip and maſter, and from whence, and whither bound, together with affidavits of the fact, are to be ſent up to the ſecretary of the admiralty, in order to their being proceeded againſt in the admiralty court. And it is to be obſerved, that in his majeſty’s ſeas, his majeſty’s ſhips are in nowiſe to ſtrike to any; and that in other parts, no ſhip of his majeſty’s is to ſtrike her flag or top-ſail to any foreigner, unleſs ſuch foreign ſhip ſhall have firſt ſtruck, or at the ſame time ſtrike, her flag or top-ſail to his majeſty’s ſhip.</p><p>The flag-officers and commanders of his majeſty’s ſhips are to be careful to maintain his majeſty’s honour upon all occaſions, giving protection to his ſubjects, and endeavouring, what in them lies, to ſecure and encourage them in their lawful commerce; and they are not to injure, in any manner, the ſubjects of his majeſty’s friends and allies.</p><p>"If a foreign admiral meets with any of his majeſty’s ſhips, and ſalutes them, he ſhall receive gun for gun. If he be a vice-admiral, the admiral ſhall anſwer with two guns leſs. If a rear-admiral, the admiral and vice-admiral ſhall return two leſs. But if the ſhip be commanded by a captain only, the flag-officer ſhall give two guns leſs, and captains an equal number.</p><p>“When any of his majeſty’s ſhips come to an anchor in a foreign port or road, within cannon-ſhot of its forts, the captain may ſalute the place with ſuch a number of guns as have been cuſtomary, upon good aſſurance of having the like number returned, but not otherwiſe. But if the ſhip bears a flag, the flag- officer ſhall firſt carefully inform himſelf how flags of like rank, belonging to other crowned heads, have given or returned ſalutes, and to infill upon the ſame terms of reſpect.</p><p>It is allowed to the commanders of his majeſty’s ſhips in foreign parts, to ſalute the perſons of any admirals, commanders in chief, or captains of ſhips of war of foreign nations, and foreign noblemen, or ſtrangers of quality, as alſo the factories of the king's ſubjects, coming on board to viſit the ſhip; and the number of guns is left to the commander, as ſhall be ſuitable to the occaſion and the quality of the perſons viſiting; but he is nevertheleſs to remain accountable for any exceſſes in the abuſe of this liberty. If the ſhip viſited be in company with other ſhips of war, the captain is not to make uſe of the civilities allowed in the preceding articles but with leave and confient of the  commander in chief or the ſenior captain.</p><p>Merchant-ſhips, whether foreigners or belonging to his majeſty’s ſubjects, ſaluting the admiral of the fleet, ſhall be anſwered by ſix guns leſs; when they ſalute any other flag-ſhips, they ſhall be anſwered by four guns leſs; and if they ſalute men of war commanded by captains, they ſhall be anſwered by two guns leſs. If ever 1 merchant-ſhips ſalute in company, no return is to be made till all have finiſhed, and then by</p></body></text></TEI>