<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and ſecondly, by the preſent Infant of Spain, whoſe verſion of this elegant hiſtorian, lately printed in folio, is one of the moſt beautiful books that any country has produced ſince the invention of printing. No man has inveighed more ſharply againſt the vices of his age than this hiſtorian; yet no man had leſs pretenſions to virtue than he. His youth was ſpent in a moſt lewd and profligate manner; and his patrimony almoſt ſquandered away when he had ſcarcely taken poſſeſſion of it. Marcus Varro, a writer of undoubted credit, relates, in a fragment preſerved by Aulus Gellius, that Salluſt was actually caught in bed with Fauſta the daughter of Sylla, by Milo her huſhand; who ſcourged him very ſeverely, and did not ſuffer him to depart till he had redeemed his liberty with a conliderable ſum. A. U. C. 694, he was made queſtor, and in 702 tribune of the people; in neither of which places is he allowed to have acquitted himſelf at all to his honour. By virtue of his queſtorſhip, he obtained an admiſſion into the ſenate; but was expelled thence by the cenſors in 704, on account of his immoral and debauched way of life. In the year 705 Caeſar reſtored him to the dignity of a ſenator; and to introduce him into the houſe with a better grace, made him queſtor a ſecond time. In the adminiſtration of this office he behaved himſelf very ſcandalouſly; expoſed every thing to ſale that he could find a purchaſer for; and if we may believe the author of the invective, thought nothing wrong which he had a mind to do: <hi rend="italic">Nihil non venale habuerit, cujus aliquis emptor ſuit, nihil non aquum et verum duxit, quοd ipſi facere collibuiſſet. </hi>In the year 707, when the African war was at an end, he was made praetor for his ſervices to Caeſar, and ſent to Numidia. Here he acted the ſame part as Verres had done in Sicily; out- rageouſly plundered the province; and returned with ſuch immenſe riches to Rome, that he purchaſed a moſt magnificent building upon mount Quirinal, with thoſe gardens which to this day retain the name of <hi rend="italic">Salluſtian gardens,</hi> beſides his country houſe at Tivoli. How he ſpent the remaining part of his life, we have no account ſrom ancient writers. Euſebius tells us, that he married Terentia, the divorced wife of Cicero; and that he died at the age of 50, in the year 710, which was about four years before the battle of Actium. Of the many things which he wrote, beſide his Hiſtories of the Catilinarian and Jugurthine wars, we have fume orations or ſpeeches, printed with his fragments.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SALLY-ports,</hi> in fortification, or <hi rend="italic">Poſtern-Gates, as</hi> they are ſometimes called, are thoſe under-ground paſſages which lead from the inner works to the outward ones; ſuch as from the higher flank to the lower, or to the tenailles, or the communication from the middle of the curtain to the ravelin. When they are made for men to go through only, they are made with ſteps at the entrance and going out. They are about 6 feet wide and 8 <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> feet high. There is alſo a gutter or ſhore made under the ſally-ports, which are in the middle of the curtains, for the water which runs down the ſtreets to paſs into the ditch; but this can only be done when they are wet ditches. When ſally-ports ſerve to carry guns through them for the out-works, inſtead of making them with ſteps, they muſt have a gradual ſlope, and be 8 feet wide.</p><p>SALMASIUS (Claudius), a French writer of uncommon abilities and immenſe erudition, descended from an ancient and noble family, and born at or near Semur in 1596. His mother, who was a Proteſtant, infused her notions of religion into him, and he at length converted his father: he ſettled at Leyden; and in 1650 paid a viſit to Chriſtina queen of Sweden, who is reported to have ſhown him extraordinary marks of regard. Upon the violent death of Charles I. of England, he was prevailed on by the royal family, then in exile, to write a defence of that king; which was anſwered by our famous Milton in 1651, in a work intitled <hi rend="italic">Deſenfio pro Populo Anglicano contra Claudii Salmafii Defenſionem Regiam.</hi> This book was read over all Europe; and conveyed ſuch a proof of the writer’s abilities, that he was reſpected even by thoſe who hated his principles. Salmaſius died in 1653; and ſome did not ſcruple to ſay, that Milton killed him by the acuteneſs of his reply. His works are numerous, and of various kinds; but the greateſt monuments of his learning are, his <hi rend="italic">Notre in Hiſtoriae Auguſtae Scriptores,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Exercitationes Plinianae in Solinum.</hi></p><p>SALMO, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Salmon</hi>; a genus of the order of abdominales. The head is ſmooth, and furniſhed with teeth and a tongue; the rays of the gills are from four to ten; the back-fin is fat behind; and the belly-fins have many rays. There are 29 ſpecies; of which the moſt remarkable are,</p><p>I. The ſalar, or common ſalmon, is a northern fiſh, being unknown in the Mediterranean ſea and other warm climates: it is found in France in ſome of the rivers that empty themſelves into the ocean, and north as far as Greenland; they are alſo very common in Newfoundland, and the northern parts of North America. Salmons are taken in the rivers of Kamtſchatka; but whether they are of the ſame ſpecies with the European kind, is not very certain. They are in ſeveral countries a great article oſ commerce, being cured different ways, by ſalting, pickling, and drying: there are ſtationary ſiſheries in Iceland, Norway, and the Baltic; but we believe nowhere greater than thoſe at Colraine in Ireland; and in Great Britain at Berwick, and in ſome of the rivers of Scotland. In the Hiſtory of  Cumberland, we are told that “they depoſit their ſpawn even on the upper fide of Pooley-bridge, but always in the ſtream of Eamont. At thoſe times it is not an eaſy matter to drive them away by throwing ſtones at them. They will take a bait of roe, or ſmalt fiſh, while upon the rudd, or laying their ſpawn. We have never heard of a ſalmon or ſalmon ſmelt being ſeen in the lake. They go up the river Derwent in September, through the lake of Baſſenthwaite, up the river which runs through Keſwick into the vale of St John, where they depoſit their ſpawn in the ſmall ſtreams and feeders of the lake. The young ſalmon are called <hi rend="italic">ſalmon ſmeits,</hi> and go down to the ſea with the firſt floods in May. ”</p><p>The ſalmon was known to the Romans, but not to the Greeks. Pliny fpeaks of it as a fiſh found in the rivers of Aquitaine: Auſonius enumerates it among thoſe of the Moſel. The ſalmon is a fiſh that lives both in the ſalt and freſh waters; quitting the ſea at certain ſeaſons for the ſake of depoſiting its ſpawn, in ſecurity, in the gravelly beds of rivers remote from their mouths. There are ſcarce any difficulties but what they will overcome, in order to arrive at places fit for</p></body></text></TEI>