<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>neſs of his horſe, and a few days after made application to Kenneth for a ceſſation of hoſtilities; but as the Scottiſh monarch demanded a ſurrender of all the Pictiſh dominions, the treaty was inſtantly broken off. Kenneth purſued his good fortune, and conquered the Counties of Merns, Angus, and Fife; but as he marched againſt Stirling, he received intelligence that theſe counties had again revolted, and cut off all the garriſons which he had left, and that Druſken was at the head of a conſiderable army in theſe parts. On this Kenneth battened to oppoſe him, and a negociation again took place. The reſult was equally unfavourable with the reſt. Kenneth inſiſted on an abſolute furrender of the counties of Fife, Merns, and Angus; which being refuſed, both parties prepared for a deciſive battle. The engagement was very bloody and deſperate, the Picts fighting like men in deſpair. Druſken renewed the battle ſeven times; but at laſt was entirely defeated and killed, and the counties in diſpute became the immediate property of the conqueror.</p><p>Kenneth did not fail to improve his victory, by reducing the reft of the Pictiſh territories; which he is ſaid to have done with the greateſt cruelty, and even to have totally exterminated the inhabitants. The capital, called <hi rend="italic">Camelon,</hi> (ſuppoſed to have been Abernethy), held out four months; but was at laſt taken by ſurpriſe, and every living creature deſtroyed. This was followed by the reduction of the Maiden Caſtle, now that of Edinburgh; which was abandoned by the garriſon, who fled to Northumberland.</p><p>After the reduction of theſe important places, the reſt of the country made no great reſiſtance, and Kenneth became matter of all the kingdom of Scotland in the preſent extent of the word; ſo that he is juſtly to be eſteemed the true founder of the Scottiſh monarchy. Beſides this war with the Picts, Kenneth is ſaid to have been ſucceſsful againſt the Saxons, though of theſe wars we have very little account. Having reigned 16 years in peace after his ſubjugation of the Picts, and compoſed a code of laws for the good of his people, Kenneth died of a fiſtula, at Fort Teviot, near Duplin in Perthſhire Before his time the feat of the Scots government had been in Argyleſhire; but he removed it to Scone, by transferring thither the famous black ſtone ſuppoſed to be the palladium of Scotland, and which was afterwards carried off by Edward I. of England, and lodged in Weſtminſter abbey.</p><p>Kenneth was ſucceeded by his brother Donald, who is repreſented as a man of the worſt character; ſo that the remaining Picts who had fled out of Scotland were encouraged to apply to the Saxons for aſſiſtance, pro- miſing to make Scotland tributary to the Saxon power after it ſhould be conquered. This propoſal was accepted; and the confederates invaded Scotland with a powerful army, and took the town of Berwick; however, they were ſoon after defeated by Donald, who took alſo their ſhips and proviſions. This capture proved their ruin; for ſome of the ſhips being loaden with wine, the Scots indulged themſelves ſo much with that liquor, that they became incapable of defending themſelves; the conſequence of this was, that the confederates rallying their troops, attacked them in that ſtate of intoxication. The Scots were defeated with exceſſive ſlaughter. Twenty thouſand of the common ſoldiers lay dead on the ſpot; the king and his princi</p><p>pal nobility were taken priſoners; and all the country from the Tweed to the Forth became the property of the conquerors. Still, however, the confederates found themſelves unable to purſue their victory farther; and a peace was concluded, on condition that the Saxons ſhould become maſters of all the conquered country. Thus the Forth and Clyde became the ſouthern boundaries of the Scottiſh dominions. It was agreed that the Forth ſhould from that time forward be called the <hi rend="italic">Scots Sea;</hi> and it was made capital for any Scotſman to ſet his foot on Engliſh ground. They were to erect no forts near the Engliſh confines, to pay an annual tribute of a thouſand pounds, and to give up 60 of the ſons of their chief nobility as hoſtages. A mint was erected by the Saxon prince named <hi rend="italic">Osbreth,</hi> at Stirling; and a croſs raiſed on the bridge at that place, with the following inſcription, implying that this place was the boundary between Scotland and England:</p><p><hi rend="italic">Anglos a Scotis ſeparat crux ista remotis:</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Arma hic stant Bruti, stant Scoti sub hac cruce tuti.</hi></p><p>After the concluſion of this treaty, ſo humiliating to the Scots, the Picts, finding that their intereſt had been entirely neglected, fled to Norway, while thole who remained in England were maſſacred. Donald flιared the common fate of unfortunate princes, being dethroned and ſhut up in priſon, where he at laſt put an end to his own life in the year 858. —In juſtice to this unhappy monarch, however, it muſt be obſerved, that the character of Donald, and indeed the whole account of theſe tranſactions, reſts on the credit of a Angle author, namely Boece; and that other writers repreſent Donald as a hero, and ſucceſsful in his wars: but the obſcurity in which the whole of this period of Scottiſh hiſtory is involved, renders it impoſſible to determine any thing ſatisſactory concerning theſe matters.</p><p>Donald was ſucceeded by his nephew Conſtantine, the ſon of Kenneth Mac Alpin, in whoſe reign Scotland was firſt invaded by the Danes, who proved ſuch formidable enemies to the Engliſh. This invaſion is ſaid to have been occaſioned by ſome exiled Picts who fled to Denmark, where they prevailed upon the king of that country to ſend his two brothers, Hungar and Hubba, to recover the Pictiſh dominions from Conſtantine. Theſe princes landed on the coaſt of Fife, where they committed the moſt horrid barbarities, not ſparing even the eccleſiaſtics who had taken refuge in the iſland of May at the mouth of the Forth. Conſtantine defeated one of the Daniſh armies commanded by Hubba, near the water of Leven; but was himſelf defeated and taken priſoner by Hungar, who cauſed him to be beheaded at a place ſince called the <hi rend="italic">Devil’s Cave,</hi> in the year 874.</p><p>This unfortunate action coſt the Scots 10,000 men; but the Danes ſeem not to have purchaſed their victory very eaſily, as they were obliged immediately afterwards to abandon their conqueſts, and retire to their own country; However, the many Daniſh monuments that are ſtill to be ſeen in Fife, leave no room to doubt that many bloody ſcenes have been acted here between the Scots and Danes beſides that above-mentioned.</p><p>Conſtantine was ſucceeded by his brother Eth, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Svoiſtſooted,</hi> from his agility. Concerning him we find nothing memorable; indeed the accounts are ſo confuſed and contradictory, that it is impoſſible</p></body></text></TEI>