<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Carthagena, vaſt quantities of mackerel being taken near an adjacent iſle, called from that circumſtance <hi rend="italic">Scombraria,</hi> and the garum, prepared by a certain company in that city, bore a high price, and was diſtinguiſhed by the title of <hi rend="italic">garum ſociorum.</hi> This fiſh is eaſily taken by a bait; but the beſt time is during a freſh gale of wind, which is thence called a <hi rend="italic">mackerel gale.</hi> In the ſpring the eyes of mackerel are almoſt covered with a white film; during which period they are half blind. This film grows in winter, and is caſt the beginning of ſummer. It is not often that it exceeds two pounds in weight, yet there have been inſtances of ſome that weighed upwards of five. The noſe is taper and ſharp pointed; the eyes large; the jaws of an equal length; the teeth ſmall, but numerous. The form of this fiſh is very elegant. The body is a little compreſſed on the ſides: towards the tail it grows very ſlender, and a little angular. It is a moſt beautiful fiſh when alive; for nothing can equal the brilliancy of its colour, which death impairs, but does not wholly obliterate.</p><p>2. The thunnus, or tunny, was a fiſh well known to the ancients: it made a conſiderable branch of commerce: the time of its arrival in the Mediterranean from the ocean was obſerved, and ſtations for taking them were eſtabliſhed in places it moſt frequented.</p><p>There are ſtill very conſiderable tunny fiſheries on the coaſt of Sicily, as well as ſeveral other parts of the Mediterranean; where they are cured, and make a great article of proviſion in the adjacent kingdoms. — They are caught in nets, and amazing quantities are taken; for they come in vaſt ſhoals, keeping along the ſhores. See <hi rend="italic">Tunny-FISHERY.</hi></p><p>They frequent our coaſts, but not in ſhoals like the tunnies of the Mediterranean. They are not uncommon in the lochs on the weſtern coaſt of Scotland; where they come in purſuit of herrings; and often during night ſtrike into the nets, and do conſiderable damage. When the fiſhermen draw them up in the morning, the tunny riſes at the ſame time towards the ſurface, ready to catch the fiſh that drop out. On perceiving it, a ſtrong hook baited with a herring, and faſtened to a rope, is inſtantly flung out, which the tunny ſeldom fails to take. As ſoon as hooked, it loſes all ſpirit; and after a very little reſiſtance ſubmits to its fate. It is dragged to the ſhore and cut up, either to be ſold freſh to people who carry it to the country markets, or is preſerved ſalted in large caſks. The pieces, when freſh, look exactly like raw beef; but when boiled turn pale, and have ſomething of the flavour of ſalmon.</p><p>One that was taken when Mr Pennant was at Inverary in 1769, weighed 460 pounds. The fiſh was ſeven feet ten inches long: the greateſt circumference five feet ſeven; the leaſt near the tail one foot fix. The body was round and thick, and grew ſuddenly very  ſlender towards the tail, and near that part was angular. The irides were of a plain green: the teeth very minute. The tail was in form of a creſcent; and two feet ſeven inches between tip and tip. The ſkin on the back was ſmooth, very thick, and black. On the belly the ſcales were viſible. The colour of the ſides and belly was ſilvery, tinged with caerulean and pale purple: near the tail marbled with grey.</p><p>They are known on the coaſt of Scotland by the</p><p>name of <hi rend="italic">mackrelſture: Mackrel,</hi> from being of that genus; and <hi rend="italic">ſture,</hi> from the Daniſh, <hi rend="italic">stor</hi> “great. ”</p><p>SCONE, a town of Scotland, remarkable for being the place where the kings were anciently crowned. W. Long. 3. 10. N. Lat. 56. 28. Here was once an abbey of great antiquity, which was burnt by the reformers at Dundee. Kenneth II. upon his conqueſt of the Picts in the ninth century, having made Scone his principal reſidence, delivered his laws, called the <hi rend="italic">Macalpine laws,</hi> from a <hi rend="italic">tumulus</hi>, named the <hi rend="italic">Mote Hill oſ Scone.</hi> The preſent palace was begun by the earl of Gowrie; but was completed by Sir David Murray of Goſpatrie, the favourite of king James VI. to whom that monarch had granted it; and the new poſſeſſor in gratitude to his benefactor put up the king’s arms in ſeveral parts of the houſe. It is built around two courts. The dining room is large and handſome; and has an ancient and magnificent chimney-piece, and the king’s arms, with this motto:</p><p>Nobis haec invicta miſerunt centum ſex proavi.</p><p>Beneath are the Murray arms. In the drawing room is ſome good old tapeſtry, with an excellent figure of Mercury. In a ſmall bed-chamber is a medley ſcripture-piece in needle-work, with a border of animals, pretty well done, the work of queen Mary during her confinement in Loch Leven Caſtle. The gallery is about 155 feet long, the top arched, divided into compartments filled with paintings in water-colours. The pieces repreſented are various kinds of huntings; that of Nimrod, and king James and his train, appear in every piece. Till the deſtruction of the abbey, the kings of Scotland were crowned here, fitting in the famous wooden chair which Edward I. tranſported to Weſtminſter abbey, to the great mortification of the Scots, who looked upon it as a kind of palladium. Charles II. before the battle of Worceſter, was crowned in the preſent chapel. The old pretender reſided for ſome time at Scone in 1715; and his ſon paid it a viſit in 1745.</p><p>SCOPARIA, in botany: A genus of the nſonogynia order, belonging to the tetrandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 40th order, <hi rend="italic">Personatae.</hi> The calyx is quadripartite; the corolla the ſame, and rotaceous; the capſule unilocular, bivalved, and polyſpermous.</p><p>SCOPER, or <hi rend="smallcaps">scupper Holes,</hi> in a ſhip, are holes made through the ſides, cloſe to the deck, to carry off the water that comes from the pump.</p><p>SCOPOLIA, in botany: A genus of the octandria order, belonging to the gynandria claſs of plants; and in the natural method ranking under the 11th claſs, <hi rend="italic">Sarmentaceoe.</hi> The calyx is diphyllous; the corolla quadrifid; the antherae coaleſce in two columns, one placed above the other. Of this there is only one ſpecies, viz. the <hi rend="italic">Compoſita.</hi></p><p>SCORBUTUS, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Scurvy.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰</p><p>SCQRDIUM, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Water-germander,</hi> in botany, a ſpecies of <hi rend="smallcaps">Teucrium.</hi></p><p>SCORIA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Dross,</hi> among metallurgiſts, is the recrement of metals in fuſion; or, more determinately ſpeaking, is that maſs which is produced by melting metals and ores: when cold, it is brittle, and not diſſoluble in water, being properly a kind of glaſs.</p></body></text></TEI>