<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>former continued in their revolt. Previous to this, he ſent an ambaſſador to offer his mediation between John and his ſubjects. The mediation was accordingly accepted of, and the negociations were opened at Calmar. The deputies of Sweden not attending, John prevailed with thoſe of Denmark and Norway to pronounce ſentence of forfeiture againſt Sture and all his adherents. In the mean time, the ſiege of the caſtle of Stockholm was ſo warmly preſſed. that the garriſon was diminiſhed to a handful, and thoſe deſtitute of all kind of proviſions; ſo that the brave queen was forced to capitulate, and to ſurrender up the fortreſs, on condition that ſhe would be ſuffered to depart for Denmark; but the capitulation was pertidiouſly broken by Sture, and ſhe was confined in a monaſtery.</p><p>It was on this occaſion that James reſolved to employ his maritime power. He wrote a letter, conceived in the ſtrongeſt terms, to the archbiſhop of Upſal, the primate of Sweden, exhorting him to employ all his authority in favour of the king; and another letter to the Lubeckers, threatening to declare war againſt them, as well as the Swedes, if they jointly continued to aſſiſt the rebels. According to Hollinſhed, James, in conſequence of king John’s application, gave the command of an army of 10,000 men to the earl of Arran, who replaced John upon his throne. Though this does not ſtrictly appear to be truth, yet it is certain, that, had it not been for James, John muſt have ſunk under the weight of his enemies. Sture, whoſe arms had made great progreſs, hearing that a conſiderable armament was fitting out in Scotland, and knowing that James had prevailed with the French king to aſſiſt John likewiſe, agreed to releaſe the queen, and to conduct her to the frontiers of Denmark; where he died. By this time, James’s armament, which was commanded by the earl of Arran, had ſet ſail; but perceiving that all matters were adjuſted between John and the Swedes, the ſhips returned ſooner than James expected, “which (ſays he, in a very polite letter he wrote to the queen upon the occaſion) they durſt not have done, had they not brought me an account that her Daniſh majeſty was in perfect health and ſafety.” The severity of John having occaſioned a freſh revolt, James again ſent a ſquadron to his aſſiſtance, which appeared before Stockholm, and obliged the Lubeckers to conclude a new treaty.</p><p>James, having thus honourably diſcharged his engagements with his uncle the king of Denmark, turned his attention towards the Flemings and Hollanders, who had inſulted his flag, on account of the aſſiſtance he had afforded the duke of Gueldres, as well as from motives of rapaciousness, which diſtinguiſhed thoſe traders, who are ſaid not only to have plundered the Scots ſhips, but to have thrown their crews overboard to conceal their villany. James gave the command of a ſquadron to Barton; who put to ſea, and, without any ceremony, treated all the Dutch and Flemiſh traders who fell into his hands as pirates, and ſent their heads in hogſheads to James. Soon after, Barton returned to Scotland, and brought with him a number of rich prizes, which rendered his reputation as a ſeaman famous all over Europe.—James was then ſo much reſpected upon the continent, that we know of no reſentment ſhown</p><p>either by the court of Spain, whoſe ſubjects thole Netherlanders were, or of any other power in Europe, for this vigorous proceeding.</p><p>The peace with England continued all the time of Henry VII. nor did his ſon Henry VIII. though he had not the ſame reaſon as his father to keep well with the Scots, for ſome time ſhew any diſpoſition to break with them. A breach, however, did very ſoon take place, which was never afterwards thoroughly made up.</p><p>About 30 years before, one John Barton (a relation, probably, to the famous Barton) commanded a trading veſſel, which was taken by two Portugueſe ſea- captains in the port of Sluys; and the captain, with ſeveral Scotchmen, were killed in endeavouring to defend their property. The action was eſteemed cowardly as well as piratical, becauſe it was done under the protection of a large Portugueſe ſquadron. The ſhip and the remaining part of the crew, with the cargo, were carried to Portugal, from whence no redreſs could be obtained; and James III. granted letters of marque to John and Robert Bartons, heirs to the Barton who had been murdered. Upon the acceſſion of James IV. to the crown of Scotland, the letters of marque were recalled, and a friendly correſpondence was entered into between James and his Portugueſe majeſty. No redreſs, however, was to be had from the latter; and Robert Barton being made a priſoner, and his ſhip a prize, he was detained in Zealand, till James procured his deliverance, by applying in his favour to the emperor Maximilian. Sir Andrew Barton took part in the quarrel; and having obtained a like letter of marque, he made dreadful depredations on the Portugueſe trade, and, according to Engliſh authors, he plundered many Engliſh ſhips, on pretence of their carrying Portugueſe property, and made the navigation of the narrow ſeas dangerous to Engliſhmem The court of London received daily complaints of Barton’s depredations; but Henry being at this time very averſe to quarrel with James, theſe complaints were heard with great coldneſs at his council-board. The earl of Surry had then two ſons, gallant noblemen; and he declared to Henry’s face, that while he had an eſtate that could furniſh out a ſhip, or a ſon who was capable of commanding one, the narrow ſeas ſhould not be infeſted. Henry could not diſcourage this generous offer; and letters of marque were accordingly granted to the two young noblemen, Sir Thomas and Sir Edward Howard. The prizes that Barton had taken had rendered his ſhips immenſely rich, conſequently they were heavy laden, and unfit for fighting; while we may eaſily ſuppoſe, that the ſhips of the Howards were clean, and of a ſuperior force in every reſpect to thoſe of Barton. After encountering a great deal of foul weather, Sir Thomas Howard came up with the Lyon, which was commanded by. Sir Andrew Barton in perſon; and Sir Edward fell in with the Unicorn, Barton’s other ſhip. The event was ſuch as might be expected from the inequality of the match. Sir Andrew Barton was killed, while he was animating, with his whiſtle, his men to hold out to the laſt; and both the Scotch ſhips being taken, were carried in triumph to London, with their crews priſoners.</p></body></text></TEI>