<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſon as a reſtraint upon his liberty; and obtained his conſent to put himſelf into the chancellor’s hands. The latter, who was a man of activity and courage, knew well how to avail himſelf of this permiſſion; and croſſing the Forth in the dark with a ſtrong body of horſe, they ſurrounded the king as he was hunting next morning by break of day. It was eaſy to perceive from the behaviour of James, that he was no ſtranger to the chancellor’s attempt; but ſome of the king’s guard offering to diſpute the posseſſion of his perſon, Sir William Livingſton, the governor’s eldeſt ſon, reſtrained them, and ſuffered the king to depart quietly. This ſurpriſal happened on a day when the governor was abſent from Stirling; and the chancellor, to make ſure of his royal acquisition, entered Edinburgh at the head of 40000 horſe, where the king and he were received by the citizens with loud acclamations of joy.</p><p>The governor ſhowed no emotion at what had happened; on the contrary, he invited the chancellor to an interview, and ſettled all differences with him in an amicable manner. The young lord Douglas, however, continued to brave both parties. As if he had been a ſovereign prince, he demanded by his ambaſſadors, Malcolm Fleming of Cumbernauld, and Allan Lawder, the inveſtiture of the ſovereignty of Touraine from Charles the ſeventh of France; which being readily granted him, ſerved to increaſe his pride and inſolence. The firſt-fruits of the accommodation between the two great officers of ſtate was the holding of a parliament at Edinburgh, for redreſſing the public diſorders occaſioned by the earl of Douglas; and encouragement was given to all perſons who had been injured to make their complaints. The numbers which on that occaſion reſorted to Edinburgh were incredible; parents, children, and women, demanding vengeance for the murder of their relations, or the plunder of their eſtates; till, by the multiplicity of their complaints, they became without remedy, none being found bold enough to encounter the earl of Douglas, or to endeavour to bring him to a fair trial. The parties therefore were diſmiſſed without relief, and it was reſolved to proceed with the haughty earl in a different manner. Letters were written to him by the governor and chancellor, and in the name of the ſtates, requeſting him to appear with his friends in parliament, and to take that lead in public affairs to which they were intitled by their high rank and great poſſeſſions. The manner in which thoſe letters were penned made the thought- leſs earl conſider them as a tribute due to his greatneſs, and as proceeding from the inability of the government to continue the adminiſtration of public affairs without his countenance and direction. Without dreaming that any man in Scotland would be ſo bold as to attack him, even ſingle or unarmed, he anſwered the letters of the chancellor and governor, by aſſurmg them that he intended to ſet out for Edinburgh: the chancellor, on pretence of doing him honour, but in reality to quiet his ſuſpicions, met him while he was on his journey; and inviting him to his caſtle of Crichton, he there entertained him for ſome days with the greateſt magnificence and appearance of hoſpitality.The earl of  Douglas believed all the chancellor’s profeſſions of friendſhip, and even ſharply checked the wiſeſt of his followers, who counſelled him not to depend too much on appearances, or to truſt his brother and himſelf at the ſame time in any place where the chancellor had power. The latter had not only removed the earl's ſuſpicion, but had made him a kind of convert to patriotism, by painting to him the miſeries of his country, and the glory that muſt redound to him and his friends in removing them. It was in vain for his attendants to remind him of his father’s maxim, never to riſk himſelf and his brother at the ſame time: he without heſitation attended the chancellor to Edinburgh; and being admitted into the caſtle, they dined at the ſame table with the king. Towards the end of the entertainment, a bull’s head, the certain prelude of immediate death, was ſerved up. The earl and his brother ſtarted to their feet, and endeavoured to make their eſcape: but armed men ruſhing in, overpowered them, and tying their hands and thoſe of Sir Malcolm Fleming with cords, they were carried to the hill and beheaded. The young king endeavoured with tears to procure their pardon; for which he was ſeverely checked by his unrelenting chancellor.</p><p>In 1443, the king being arrived at the age of 14, declared himſelf out of the years of minority, and took upon himſelf the adminiſtration of affairs. He appears to have been a prince of great ſpirit and reſolution; and he had occaſion for it. He had appointed one Robert Sempil of Fulwood to be chief governor of the caſtle of Dumbarton; but he was killed by one Galbraeth (a noted partizan of the earl of Douglas), who ſeized upon the government of the caſtle. The popularity of the family of Douglas having ſomewhat subſided, and the young earl finding himſelf not ſupported by the chief branches of his family, he began to think, now that the king was grown up, his ſafeſt courſe would be to return to his duty. He accordingly repaired to the king at Stirling; and voluntarily throwing himſelf at his majeſty’s feet, implored his pardon for all his tranſgreſſions, and ſolemnly promiſed that he would ever after ſet a pattern of duty and loyalty to all the reſt of his ſubjects. The king, finding that he inſiſted on no terms but that of pardon, and that he had unconditionally put himſelf into his power, not only granted his requeſt, but made him the partner of his inmoſt councils.</p><p>James had always disliked the murder of the earl of Douglas and his brother; and the chancellor, perceiving the aſcendency which this earl was daily gaining at court, thought it high time to provide for his own ſafety. He therefore reſigned the great ſeal, and retired to the caſtle of Edinburgh, the cuſtody of which he pretended had been granted to him by the late king during his life, or till the preſent king ſhould arrive at the age of 21; and prepared it for a ſiege. The lord Callendar, who knew himſelf equally obnoxious as Crichton was to the earl of Douglas, and that he could not maintain his footing by himſelf, reſigned likewiſe all his poſts, and retired to one of his own houſes, but kept poſſeſſion of the caſtle of Stirling. As both that and the caſtle of Edinburgh were royal forts, the two lords were ſummoned to ſurrender them; but inſtead of complying, they juſtiſied their conduct by the great power of their enemies, who fought their deſtruction, and who had been ſo lately at the head of robbers and outlaws; but promiſed to ſurrender themſelves to the king as ſoon as he was of lawful age, (meaning, we ſuppoſe, either 18 or 21). This anſwer being deemed</p></body></text></TEI>