<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>portcullis or gate of the town; from whence Douglas brought off his antagoniſt’s lance, with a pennon affixed to it, and ſwore in his hearing that he would carry it into Scotland. Next day Douglas attempted to ſtorm the town; but, being repulſed in the attack, he decamped in the night. Percy, breathing furious revenge, purſued and overtook the Scots at Otterburn. His arrival was quite unexpected, ſo that the principal commanders of the Scottiſh army were ſitting down to ſupper unarmed. The ſoldiers, however, were inſtantly prepared for battle; but in the hurry neceſſarily attending a ſurpriſe of this kind, Douglas forgot to put on his cuiraſs. Both leaders encouraged their men by the moſt animating ſpeeches; and both parties waited for the riſe of the moon, which happened that night to be unuſually bright. The battle being joined on the moon’s firſt appearance, the Scots began to give ground; but, being rallied by Douglas, who fought with a battle-ax, the Engliſh, though greatly ſuperior in number, were totally routed. Twelve hundred were killed on the ſpot; and 100 perſons of diſtinction, among whom were the two Percies, were made priſoners by Keith mariſchal of Scotland. On the ſide of the Scots the greateſt loſs was that of the brave earl Douglas, who was killed in conſequence of going to battle without his armour, as above related. It was this ſingle combat between Douglas and Percy, and the ſubſequent battle, which gave riſe to the celebrated ballad of Chevy Chace.</p><p>In the mean time the biſhop of Durham was marching towards Newcaſtle with an army of 10,000 men; but was informed by the runaways of Percy’s defeat, which happened on the 21ſt of July 1388. In a council of war it was reſolved to purſue the Scots, whom they hoped eaſily to vanquiſh, as being wearied with the battle of the preceding day, and laden with plunder. The earl of Moray, who commanded in chief, having called a conſultation of his officers, reſolved to venture a battle. The priſoners were almoſt as numerous as the whole Scots army; however, the generals required no more of them than their words of honour that they ſhould continue inactive during the battle, and remain priſoners ſtill. This condition being complied with, the Scots drew out their army for battle. — Their rear was ſecured by marſhes, and their flanks by large trees which they had felled. In ſhort, their appearance was ſo formidable, that the Engliſh, dreading to encounter a reſolute enemy ſo ſtrongly ſecured, retired to Newcaſtle, leaving the Scots at liberty to continue their march to their own country.</p><p>Robert being now oppreſſed with age, ſo that he could no longer endure the fatigues of government, the adminiſtration of affairs devolved upon his ſecond ſon the earl of Fife; for his eldeſt ſon was by nature indolent, and beſides lame by an unlucky blow he had received from a horſe. Early in the ſpring of 1389, he invaded England with ſucceſs: but the ſame year a truce was concluded, to laſt from the 19th of June 1389 to the 16th of Auguſt 1392; in which the allies of both crowns were included. This truce was violently oppoſed by the nobility, who ſuſpected their king of being too much under French influence. Upon this the court of France thought proper to ſend over ambaſſadors to perſuade the nobility to comply; informing them, that in caſe of a refuſal, they could expect no</p><p>aſſiſtance either of men or money from the continent. With difficulty they prevailed, and peace between England and Scotland was once more reſtored. Scarce, however, was this truce finiſhed, when the peace of the nation was moſt ſcandalouſly violated by Robert’s third ſon the earl of Buchan. This prince having a quarrel with the biſhop of Murray, burnt down the fine cathedral of Elgin, which has been called by hiſtorians the lanthorn and ornament of the north of Scotland. The king for this crime cauſed his ſon to be impriſoned; and a civil war would have been the conſequence, had it not been for the veneration which the Scots retained for their old king. However, they did not long enjoy their beloved monarch; for he died on the 19th of April 1390, in the 75th year of his age, and the 19th of his reign.</p><p>On the death of Robert II. the crown devolved upon his eldeſt ſon John; but the name being thought unlucky in Scotland, he changed it for that of Robert, though he was ſtill called by the commonalty <hi rend="italic">Robert  John Fernzier.</hi> He had been married to Annabella, the daughter of Sir John Drummond, anceſtor to the noble family of Perth; and was crowned along with his conſort at Scone, on the 13th of Auguſt 1390. He confirmed the truce which had been entered into with England, and renewed the league with France; but the beginning of his reign was diſturbed by the wars of the petty chieftains with each other. Duncan Stewart, ſon to Alexander earl of Buchan, who had died in priſon for burning the cathedral of Elgin, aſſembling his followers under pretence of revenging his father’s death, laid waſte the county of Angus. Walter Ogilvy, the ſheriff of Angus, attempting to repel the invaders, was killed, with his brother and 60 of their followers. The king then gave a commiſſion to the earl of Crawford to ſuppreſs them; which he ſoon did, and moſt of them were either killed or executed. The followers of the earl of Buchan were compoſed of the wildeſt Highlanders, diſtinguiſhed by the title of <hi rend="italic">Catterenes,</hi> which anſwers to that of banditti. That ſuch a race of people exiſted is certain from the records of Scotland; but it is not eaſy to determine how they obtained their ſubſiſtence, being void of the knowledge of agriculture and of every civil art. There is ſome reaſon to believe that many of them came from the Weſtern Iſles; and that they or their anceſtors had emigrated from the eaſtern parts of Ireland. The lands they inhabited were never cultivated till towards the middle of the last century; and, according to the moſt authentic accounts, they lived entirely upon animal food.</p><p>The earl of Crawford’s ſucceſs againſt the followers of Buchan encouraged Robert to intruſt him with a commiſſion for ſubduing other inſurgents by whom the peace of the country was diſturbed. The moſt remark of theſe were the <hi rend="italic">Clan Chattan</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Clan Kay.</hi> As both theſe tribes were numerous and brave, Crawford was not without apprehenſions that they might unite againſt him as a common enemy, and defeat him if he attempted to ſuppreſs them by force. He propoſed, therefore, that the two rival clans ſhould each chooſe 30 men, to determine their differences by the ſword, without being allowed the uſe of any other weapon. The king and his nobility were to be ſpectators of the combat; the conquered clan were to be pardoned for all their former offences, and the conquerors honoured</p></body></text></TEI>