<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:51:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>arrival there, he was informed that the Scots, under the carl of Douglas, had made an irruption into England, where they had burned Newark, but had been forced to return to their own country by a peſtilence, though a new invaſion was daily expected. Inſtead of reſenting this inſult, Henry invited the earl of Douglas to a conference at York; in which the latter agreed to ſerve him during life, by ſea and land, abroad or at home, againſt all living, except his own liege-lord the king of Scotland, with 200 foot and as many horſe, at his own charges; the king of England, in the mean time, allowing an annual revenue of 2001. for paying his expence in going to the army by ſea or land.</p><p>At the ſame time, a new negociation was ſet on foot for the ranſom of king James; but he did not obtain his liberty till the year 1424. Henry V. was then dead; and none of his generals being able to ſupply his place, the Engliſh power in France began to decline. They then became ſenſible how neceſſary it was to be at peace with Scotland, in order to detach ſuch a formidable ally from the French intereſt. James was now highly careſſed, and at his own liberty, within certain bounds. The Engliſh even conſulted him about the manner of conducting the treaty for his ranſom; and one Dougal Drummond, a prieſt, was ſent with a ſafe conduct for the biſhop of Glaſgow, chancellor of Scotland, Dunbar earl of March, John Montgomery of Ardroſſan, Sir Patrick Dunbar of Bele, Sir Robert Lawder of Edrington, Sir William Borthwic of Borthwic, and Sir John Forreſter of Corſtorphin, to have an interview, at Pomfret, with their  maſter the captive king of Scotland, and there to treat cf their common intereſts. Moſt of theſe noblemen and gentlemen had before been nominated to treat with the Engliſh about their king’s return; and Dougal Drummond ſeems to have been a domeſtic favourite with James. Hitherto the Scottiſh king had been allowed an annual revenue of 700 pounds: but while he was making ready for his journey, his equipages and attendants were increaſed to thoſe befitting a ſovereign; and he received a preſent from the Engliſh treaſury of 100 l. for his private expences. That he might appear with a grandeur every way ſuitable to his dignity, at every ſtage were provided relays of horſes, and all manner of fiſh, fleſh, and fowl, with cooks and other ſervants for furniſhing out the moſt ſumptuous royal entertainment. In this meeting at Pomfret, James acted as a kind of a mediator between the Engliſh and his own ſubjects, to whom he fully laid himſelf open; but, in the mean time, the Engliſh regency iſſued a commiſſion for fettling the terms upon which James was to be reſtored, if he and his commiſſioners ſhould lay a proper foundation for ſuch a treaty. The Engliſh commiſſioners, were the biſhops of Durham and Worceſter, the earls of Northumberland and Weſtmoreland, the lords Nevil, Cornwal, and Chaworth, with matter John Wodeham, and Robert Waterton. The inſtructions they received form one of the moſt curious paſſages of this hiſtory; and we ſhall here give them, as they are neceſſary for confirming all we have ſaid concerning the diſpoſitions of the two courts at this juncture.</p><p>Firſt, To make a faint oppoſition to any private conference between the king of Scotland and the Scotch  commiſſioners.</p><p>Secondly, To demand that, before the ſaid king ſhall have his full liberty, the kingdom of Scotland ſhould pay to the Engliſh government at leaſt thirty- ſix thouſand pounds as an equivalent, at two thouſand pounds a-year, for the entertainment of King James, who was maintained by the court of England, and not to abate any thing of that ſum; but if poſſible to get forty thouſand pounds.</p><p>Thirdly, That if the Scots ſhould agree to the payment of the ſaid ſum, the Engliſh commiſſioners ſhould take ſufficient ſecurity and hoſtages for the payment of the ſame; and that if they ſhould not (as there was great reaſon for believing they would) be ſo far mollified, by ſuch eaſy terms, as to offer to enter upon a negociation for a final and perpetual peace between the two people, that then the Engliſh ſhould propoſe the ſame in the moſt handſome manner they could. Farther, that if ſuch difficulties ſhould ariſe as might make it impracticable immediately to conclude ſuch perpetual peace, that the Engliſh ambaſſadors ſhould, under pretence of paving a way for the ſame, propoſe a long truce.</p><p>Fourthly, That in caſe the Engliſh commiſſioners ſhould ſucceed in bringing the Scots to agree to the ſaid truce, they ſhould further urge, that they ſhould not ſend to Charles of France, or to any of the enemies of England, any ſuccours by ſea or land. Farther, that the ſaid Engliſh commiſſioners ſhould employ their utmoſt endeavours to procure the recal of the troops already furniſhed by the Scots to France. The Engliſh are commanded to inſiſt very ſtrenuouſly upon this point, but with diſcretion.</p><p>Fifthly, If the Scots ſhould, as a further bond of amity between the two nations, propoſe a marriage between their king and ſome noblewoman of England, the Engliſh commiſſioners are to make anſwer, That the king of the Scots is well acquainted with many noblewomen, and even thoſe of the blood-royal, in England; and that if the king of the Scots ſhall pleaſe to open his mind more freely on that head, the Engliſh commiſſioners ſhall be very ready to enter upon conferences thereupon.” But (continues the record) in caſe the Scotch commiſſioners ſhould make no mention of any ſuch alliance by marriage, it will not appear decent for the Engliſh to mention the ſame, becauſe the women of England, at leaſt the noblewomen, are not uſed to offer themſelves in marriage to men.</p><p>Sixthly, If there ſhould be any mention made concerning reparation of damages, that the commiſſioners ſhould then proceed upon the ſame as they ſhould think moſt proper; and that they ſhould have power to offer ſafe-conduct to as many of the Scots as ſhould be demanded, for to repair to the court of England. Thoſe inſtructions are dated at Weſtminſter, July 6th  1423.</p><p>Nothing definitive was concluded at this treaty, but that another meeting ſhould be held at York inſtead of Pomfret. This meeting accordingly took place. The Engliſh commiſſioners were, Thomas biſhop of Durham, chancellor of England, Philip biſhop of Wincheſter, Henry Percy earl of Northumberland, and Mr John Wodeham. Thoſe for Scotland were, William biſhop of Glaſgow, George earl of March, James Douglas of Balveny, his brother Patrick abbot of Cambuſkenneth, John abbot of Baimerino, Sir Patrick Dun-</p></body></text></TEI>