<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:46:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">SABLE,</hi> in heraldry, ſignifies "black; ” and is borrowed
                from the French, as are most terms in this ſcience: in engraving it is expreſſed by
                both horizontal and perpendicular lines croſſing each other. Sable of itſelf
                ſigniſies conſtancy, learning, and grief; and ancient heralds will have it, that
                when it is compounded with</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Or.</cell>
                    <cell>it signifies</cell>
                    <cell>Honour.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> Arg. </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Fame.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Gul. </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Reſpect.</cell>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <cell>Azu.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Application.</cell>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <cell>Ver.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Comfort.</cell>
                </row>

                <row>
                    <cell>Pur.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Auſterity.</cell>
                </row>

            </table>
            <p>The occaſion that introduced this colour into heraldry is thus related by Alexander
                Niſhet, p. 8. The duke of Anjou, king of Sicily, after the loſs of that kingdom,
                appeared at a tournament in Germany all in black, with his ſhield of that tincture,
                    <hi rend="italic">ſemé de larmes,</hi></p>
            <p>i. e. beſprinkled with drops of water, to repreſent tears, indicating by that both
                his grief and loſs.</p>
            <p>SABLESTAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sablustan,</hi> a province of Aſia, in Persia, on
                the frontiers of Indoſtan; bounded on the north by Khoraſan; on the eaſt, by the
                mountains of Balk and Candahar; on the ſouth, by Sageſtan or Segeſtan; and on the
                weft, by Heri. It is a mountainous country, very little known to Europeans; nor is
                it certain which is the capital town.</p>
            <p>SABRE, a kind of ſword or ſcimitar, with a very broad and heavy blade, thick at the
                back, and a little falcated or crooked towards the point. It is the ordinary weapon
                worn by the Turks, who are ſaid to be very expert in the uſe of it.</p>
            <p>SABURRA, in medicine, uſually denotes any collection of half putrid indigeſted matter
                in the ſtomach and inteſtines, by which the operation of digeſtion is impeded.</p>
            <p>SABURRÆ, GRITTS, in natural hiſtory; a genus of foſſils, found in minute maſſes,
                forming together a kind of powder, the ſeveral particles of which are of no
                determinate ſhape, nor have any tendency to the figure of cryſtal, but ſeem rudely
                broken fragments of larger maſſes; not to be diſſolved or diſunited by water, but
                retaining their figure in it, and not cohering by means of it into a maſs;
                conſiderably opake, and in many ſpecies fermenting with acids; often fouled with
                heterogene matters, and not unfrequently taken in the coarſer ſtony and mineral or
                metalline particles.</p>
            <p>Gritts are of various colours, as, 1. The ſtony and ſparry gritts, of a bright or
                greyiſh white colour. 2. The red ſtony gritts. 3. The green ſtony gritts, compoſed
                of homogene ſparry particles. 4. The yellow gritt, of which there is only one
                ſpecies. 5. The black and blackiſh gritts, compoſed of ſtony or talky particles.</p>
            <p>SACÆA, a feaſt which the ancient Babylonians and other orientals held annually in
                honour of the deity Anaitis. The Sacæa were in the Eaſt what the Saturnalia were at
                Rome, viz. a feaſt for the ſlaves. One of the ceremonies was to chooſe a priſoner
                condemned to death, and allow him all the pleaſures and gratifications he would
                wiſh, before he were carried to execution.</p>
            <p>SACCADE, in the manege, is a jerk more or leſs violent, given by the horſeman to the
                horſe, in pulling or twitching the reins of the bridle all on a sudden</p>
            <p>and with one pull, and that when a horſe lies heavy upon the hand, or obſtinately
                arms himſelf.</p>
            <p>This is a correction uſed to make a horſe carry well; but it ought to be uſed
                diſcreetly, and but ſeldom.</p>
            <p>SACERDOTAL, ſomething belonging to prieſts. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Priest.</hi></p>
            <p>SACCULUS, in anatomy, a diminutive of ſaccus, ſigniſies a little bag, and is applied
                to many parts of the body.</p>
            <p>SACCHARUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sugar,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Sugar-Cane,</hi>
                in botany: A genus of the digynia order, belonging to the triandria claſs of plants;
                and in the natural method ranking under the 4th order, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Grαmina.</hi> There is no calyx, but a long down; the corolla is bivalved.
                There is but one ſpecies of this genus, viz. the officina. It is a native of Africa,
                the Eaſt Indies, and of Brazil; from whence it was introduced into our Weft India
                iſlands ſoon after they were ſettled. The ſugar-cane is the glory and the pride of
                thoſe iſlands. It amply rewards the induſtrious planter, enriches the Britiſh
                merchant, gives bread to thouſands of manufacturers and ſeamen, and brings an
                immenſe revenue to the crown. For the proceſs of making ſugar, ſee <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Sugar.</hi></p>
            <p>Sugar, formerly a luxury, is now become one of the neceſſaries of life. In crop-time
                every negro on the plantations, and every animal, even the dogs, grow fat. This
                ſufficiently points out the nouriſhing and healthy qualities of ſugar. It has been
                alleged, that the eating of ſugar ſpoils the colour of, and corrupts, the teeth:
                this, however, proves to be a miſtake, for no people on the earth have finer teeth
                than the negroes in Jamaica. Dr Alſton, formerly professor of botany and materia
                medica at Edinburgh, endeavoured to obviate this vulgar opinion: he had a fine ſet
                of teeth, which he aſcribed ſolely to his eating great quantities of ſugar.
                Externally too it is often uſeful: mixed with the pulp of roaſted oranges, and
                applied to putrid or ill-diſpoſed ulcers, it proves a powerful corrector.</p>
            <p>SACCHI (Andrea), a celebrated painter, born at Rome in 1594. He was the diſciple of
                Franciſco Albano, whom he afterwards ſurpaſſed in taſte and cor- rectness. He
                diſtinguiſhed himſelf in a very eminent degree by his paintings in freſco; and a
                ſtrong emulation ſubſiſting between him and Pietro de Cortona, they each arrived at
                a degree of perfection that neither of them might have known without ſuch a
                competition. The works of Sacchi have ſuch intrinfic merit, and are finiſhed with
                ſuch uncommon care and ſkill, as will always ſecure the applauſe of the judicious,
                and preſerve their true value. He died in 1668.</p>
            <p>SACHEVEREL (Dr Henry), a famous clergyman of the Tory faction in the reign of queen
                Anne; who diſtinguiſhed himſelf by indecent and ſcurrilous sermons and writings
                againſt the diſſenters and revolution principles. He owed his conſequence, however,
                to being indiſcreetly proſecuted by the houſe of lords for his aſſize-ſermon at
                Derby, and his 5th of November ſermon at St Paul’s in 1709; in which he aſſerted the
                doctrine of non-reſistance to government in its utmoſt extent; and reflected
                ſeverely on the act of toleration. The high and low church parties were very violent
                at that time; and the trial of Sacheverel inflamed the high-church party to
                dangerous riots and excesses: he was, however, ſuſpended for three years, and his
                sermons burned by the common hangman. The Tories being</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
