<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>extended not only through the lower ranks, but had pervaded the higher claſſes alſo.
                The inhabitants of the borders, indeed, paid very little regard to the orders of
                their reſpective ſovereigns; so that daily hoſtilities were committed by them upon
                each other when there was peace between the ſovereigns. The inhabitants of theſe
                countries had eſtabliſhed with one another certain conventions, which have ſince
                been collected, and go by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Border laws.</hi> The
                families of Douglas and Percy, whoſe eſtates lay contiguous to one another, were at
                perpetual variance. It had been common for the borderers of both kingdoms, during a
                truce, to frequent cach others fairs; and a ſervant of the earl of March had been
                Killed in a fray at that of Roxburgh, which was ſtill in the hands of the Engliſh.
                Juſtice for this murder was demanded from lord Percy; but he flighted the
                cornplaint. On this the earl of March, with his brother the earl of Moray,
                aſſembling their followers, entered the next fair that was held in Roxburgh,
                plundered and burnt the town, and killed all the English who fell into tlheir hands.
                The Engliſh borderers were ordered to lay waste the lands of the earl of March; but,
                in their way thither, deſtroyed the eſtate of Sir John Gordon, a man of great
                property in the ſouth of Scotland. Sir John in his turn invaded England, from whence
                he drove off a large booty in cattle, and a number of priſoners. In his retreat he
                was attacked by a body of freſh troops under Sir John Liſburn, at a place called <hi
                    rend="italic">Carαrn.</hi> An obſtinate encounter followed. The Scots were five
                times repulſed; but at laſt they renewed the charge with such fury, that they made
                Liſburn, his brother, and ſeveral other perſons of diſtinction, priſoners, together
                with all their ſurviving ſoldiers. On this lord Percy with 7000 men encamped at
                Duns, in the ſouth of Scotland; but was obliged to retire, probably for want of
                ſubſiſtence for his army. In the mean time, Muſgrave, the governor of Berwick, who
                had been ordered to join Percy with a detachment from the garriſon, was on his march
                intercepted, defeated, and taken priſoner by Sir John Gordon; after which the border
                war became general on both ſides. The issue of theſe diſturbances is but little
                known; however, in 1377, we find them raging with more violence than ever. The fair
                of Roxburgh was once more the ſcene of action, and the town was again, burnt down by
                the Scots. Lord Percy, who was now</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
