<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:26Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tainous parts of Tweedale, ſurprised and made priſoners Thomas Randolph the king’s nephew, and Alexander Stewart of Bonkhill, who had hitherto continued inimical to the intereſts of Robert. Randolph was conducted to the king, but talked to him in an haughty ſtrain; upon which his uncle put him into cloſe confinement.</p><p>The next exploit of Robert was againſt the lord of Lorn, a diviſion of Argyleſhire. It was this nobleman who had reduced the king to ſuch ſtraits after his defeat at Methven; and he now reſolved to take ample revenge. Having entered the country, the king arrived at a narrow paſs, where the troops of Lorn lay in ambuſh. This paſs had a high mountain on the one  ſide, and a precipice waſhed by the ſea on the other; but Robert having ordered Douglas to make a circuit and gain the ſummit of the mountain with part of the army, he entered himſelf with the reſt. He was immediately attacked; but Douglas with his men ruſhed down the hill, and decided the victory in favour of the king; who ſoon after took the caſtle of Dunſtaffnage, the chief reſidence of this nobleman.</p><p>While Robert and his aſſociates were thus gaining the admiration of their countrymen by the exploits which they daily performed, the Engliſh were ſo unſettled and fluctuating in their counſels, that their party knew not how to act.  Edward ſtill imagined that there was a poſſibility of reconciling the Scots to his government: and for this purpoſe he employed William de Lambyrton, biſhop of St Andrew’s, who, after having been taken priſoner, and carried from one place of confinement to another, had at laſt made ſuch ſubmiſſions, as procured firſt his liberty, and then the confidence of Edward. This eccleſiaſtic having taken a moſt ſolemn oath of fidelity to Edward, now reſolved to ingratiate himſelf, by publiſhing againſt Robert and his adherents a ſentence of excommunication, which had been reſolved on long before. This, however, produced no effect; and the event was, that in 1309, through the mediation of the king of France, Edward conſented to a truce with the Scots. This pacific diſpoſition, however, laſted not long. The truce was ſcarcely concluded, when Edward charged the Scots with violating it, and ſummoned his barons to meet him in arms at Newcaſtle: yet, probably being doubtful of the event of the war, he empowered Robert de Umfraville, and three others, to conclude a new truce; declaring, however, that he did this at the requeſt of Philip king of Fiance, as his deareſt father and friend, but who was in no ſort to be conſidered as the ally of Scotland.</p><p>The new negotiations were ſoon interrupted. They were again renewed; and in the beginning of the year 1310 the truce was concluded, but entirely diſregarded by the Scots. The progreſs of Bruce now became very alarming. The town of Perth, a place at that time of great importance, was threatened; and to relieve it, Edward ordered a fleet to ſail up the river Tay: he alſo commanded the earl of Ulster to aſſemble a body of troops at Dublin, and from thence to invade Scotland; his own barons were ordered to meet him in arms at Berwick. About the end of September, he entered Scotland; paſſed from Roxburgh, through the foreſt of Selkirk, to Biggar; from thence he penetrated into Renfrew; and turning back by the way of Linlithgow, he retreated to Berwick, where he continued inactive for eight months.</p><p>During this invaſion, Robert had carefully avoided a battle with the Engliſh; well knowing, that an invaſion undertaken in autumn would ruin the heavy armed cavalry, on which the Engliſh placed their chief dependence. His cauſe was alſo favoured by a ſcarcſty which prevailed at this time in Scotland; for as magazines and other reſources of modern war were then unknown, the Engliſh army were greatly retarded in their operations, and found it impoſſible to ſubliſt in the country.</p><p>The ſpirit of enterpriſe had now communicated itſelf to all ranks of people in Scotland. In 1311, the caſtle of Linlithgow was ſurpriſed by a poor peaſant, named <hi rend="italic">William Binnock.</hi> The Engliſh garriſon were ſecure, and kept but a ſlight guard; of which Binnock being informed, concealed eight reſolute men in a load of hay, which he had been employed to drive into the caſtle. With theſe, as ſoon as the gate was opened, he fell upon the feeble guard, and became maſter of the place; which was diſmantled by Robert, as well as all the other caſtles taken in the courſe of the war.</p><p>Edward now reſolved to invade Scotland again; and for this purpoſe ordered his army to aſſemble at Roxburgh. But Robert, not contented with defending his own country, reſolved in his turn to invade England. He accordingly entered that country, and cruelly ravaged the biſhopric of Durham. He returned loaded with ſpoil, and laid ſiege to Perth. After remaining ſix weeks before that place, he raiſed the ſiege, but returned in a few days; and having provided ſcaling ladders, approached the works with a choſen body of infantry. In a dark night he made the attack; and having waded through the ditch though the water ſtood to his throat, he was the ſecond man who reached the top of the walls. The town was then ſoon taken; after which it was plundered and burnt, and the fortifications levelled with the ground. This happened on the 8th of January 1312.</p><p>Edward was now become averſe to the war, and renewed his negociations for a truce; but they ſtill came to nothing. Robert again invaded England; burnt great part of the city of Durham; and even threatened to beſiege Berwick, where the king of England had, for the time, fixed his reſidence. He next reduced the caſtles of Butel, Dumfries, and Dalſwinton, with many other fortreſſes. The caſtle of Roxburgh, a place of the utmoſt importance, next fell into his hands. The walls were ſcaled while the garriſon was revelling on the eve of Lent. They retreated into the inner tower; but their governor, a Frenchman, having received a mortal wound, they capitulated.</p><p>Randolph, the king’s nephew, who had been impriſoned, as we have already obſerved, was now received into favour, and began to diſtinguiſh himſelf in the cauſe of his country. He blockaded the caſtle of Edinburgh ſo cloſely, that all communication with the neighbouring country was cut off. The place was commanded by one Leland, a knight of Gaſcony; but the garriſon ſuſpecting his fidelity, impriſoned him in a dungeon, and choſe another commander in his ſtead. One William Frank preſented himſelf to Randolph, and informed him how the walls might be ſcaled. This man in his youth had reſided in the caſtle; and having</p></body></text></TEI>