<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſome; that ſhe had obſerved no meaſure in her paſſion to both ſexes; and that Phaon had long known all her charms. She was, however, a very great wit, and for that alone deferves to be remembered. The Mitylenians held her merit in ſuch high eſteem, that they paid her ſovereign honours after her death, and ſtamped their money with her image. The Romans afterwards erected a noble ſtatue of porphyry to her; and in ſhort, ancients as well as moderns have done honour to her memory. Voſſius ſays, that none of the Greek poets excelled Sappho for ſweetneſs of verſe; and that ſhe made Archilochus the model of her ſtyle, but at the ſame time took care to ſoſten the ſeverity of his expreſſion. It muſt be granted, ſays Rapin, from what is left us of Sappho, that Longinus had great reaſon to extol the admirable genius of this woman; for there is in what remains of her ſomething delicate, harmonious, and impaſſioned to the laſt degree.</p><p>SARABAND, a muſical compoſition in the triple time, the motions of which are flow and ferions.</p><p>Saraband is alſo a dance to the ſame meaſure, which uſually terminates when the hand that beats the time falls; and is otherwiſe much the ſame as the minuet.</p><p>The ſaraband is ſaid to be originally derived from the Saracens, and is uſually danced to the ſound of the guitar or caſtanettes.</p><p>SARACA, in botany; a genus of the hexandria order, belonging to the diadelphia claſs of plants — There is no calyx: the corolla is funnel-ſhaped and quadriſid; the filaments are on each ſide the throat of the corolla; the legumen is pedicellated.</p><p>SARACENS, the inhabitants of Arabia; ſo called from the word <hi rend="italic">ſara,</hi> which ſignifies a deſert, as the greateſt part of Arabia is; and this being the country of Mahomet, his diſciples were called Saracens. </p><p>SARAGOSSA, a city of Spain, in the kingdom  of Arragon, with an archbiſhop’s ſee, an univerſity, and a court of inquiſition It is ſaid to have been built by the Phoenicians; and the Romans ſent a colony here in the reign of the emperor Auguſtus, whence it had the name of <hi rend="italic">Caesar Augustus,</hi> which by corruption has been changed into Saragoſſa. It is a large, handſome, and well-built town. The ſtreets are long, broad, well-paved, and very clean, and the houſes from three to ſix ſtories high. It is adorned with many magnificent buildings; and they reckon 17 large churches, and 14 handſome monaſteries, not to mention others leſs conſiderable. The river Ebro runs croſs the place, dividing it into two; and on its banks is a handſome quay, which ſerves for a public walk. The Holy-ſtreet is the largeſt, and ſo broad that it may be taken for a ſquare; and here they have their bull-fights: in this ſtreet there are ſeveral noblemens families, particularly that of the viceroy. The convents are handſome and richly adorned, as well as the churches. The cathedral church is a ſpacious building, after the Gothic taſte; but the fineſt church is that of Nueſtra Signora del Pilar, ſeated on the ſide of the Ebro, and is a place of the greateſt devotion in Spain. They tell us the Virgin appeared to St James, who was preaching the goſpel, and left him her image, with a handſome pillar of jaſper: it is ſtill in this church which they pretend is the firſt in the world built to her honour. This image ſtands on a marble pillar, with a little Jeſus in her arms; but the place is ſo dark, that it cannot be ſeen without the aſſiſtance of</p><p>lamps, which are 50 in number, and all of ſilver. There are alſo chandeliers and baluſtrades of maſſy ſilver. The ornaments of this image are the richeſt that can be imagined, her crown being full of precious ſtones of an ineſtimable price; in ſhort, there is ſcarce any thing to be ſeen but gold and jewels, and a vaſt number of people come in pilgrimage hither. The town-houſe is a ſumptuous ſtructure, adorned with fine columns: in the hall are the pictures of all the kings of Arragon; and in a corner of it St George on horſeback, with a dragon of white marble under him. It is ſeated in a very large plain, where the Ebro receives two other rivers; and over it are two bridges, one of ſtone and the other of wood, which laſt has been thought the moſt beautiful in Europe. A victory was obtained here over the French and Spaniards in 1710, but it was abandoned by the allies ſoon after. It is 97 miles well by north of Tarragona, 137 weſt of Barcelona, and 150 north-eaſt of Madrid. W. Long. 0. 48. N. Lat. 41. 47.</p><p>SARANNE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Lilium.</hi></p><p>SARCASM, in rhetoric, a keen bitter expreſſion which has the true point of ſatire, by which the orator ſcoffs and inſults his enemy: ſuch as that of the Jews to our Saviour; “ He ſaved others, himſelf he cannot ſave. ”</p><p>SARCOCELE, in ſurgery, a ſpurious rupture or hernia, wherein the teſticle is conſiderably tumefied or indurated, like a ſcirrhous, or much enlarged by a fleſhy excreſcence, which is frequently attended with acute pains, ſo as to degenerate at laſt into a cancerous diſpoſition. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Surgery.</hi></p><p>SARCOCOLLA, a concrete juice brought from Perſia and Arabia, in ſmall whitiſh-yellow grains, with a few of a reddiſh and ſometimes of a deep red colour mixed with them; the wſhiteſt tears are preferred, as being the freſheſt: its taſte is bitter, accompanied with a dull kind of ſweetneſs. This drug diſſolves in watery liquors, and appears chiefly to be of the gummy kind, with a ſmall admixture of reſinous matter. It is principally celebrated for conglutinating wounds and ulcers (whence its name σαρχοχολλα <hi rend="italic">flesh-glue);</hi> a quality which neither this nor any other drug has any juſt title to.</p><p>SARCOLOGY, is that part of anatomy which treats of the ſoft parts, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> the muſcles, inteſtines, arteries, veins, nerves, and fat.</p><p>SARCOMA, in ſurgery, denotes any fleſhy excreſcence.</p><p>SARCOPHAGUS, in antiquity, a fort of ſtone coffin or grave, wherein the ancients laid thoſe they had not a mind to burn.</p><p>The word, as derived from the Greek, literally ſignifies <hi rend="italic">flesh-eater;</hi> becauſe at firſt they uſed a fort of ſtone for the making of tombs, which quickly confirmed the bodies. See the following article.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sarcophagus,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lapis Λſſius,</hi> in the natural hiſtory of the ancients, a ſtone much uſed among the Greeks in their ſepultures, is recorded to have always perfectly confirmed the fleſh of human bodies buried in it in forty days. This property it was much famed for, and all the ancient naturaliſts mention it. There was another very Angular quality alſo in it, but whether in all, or only in ſome peculiar pieces of it, is not known: that is, its turning into ſtone any thing that was put into veſſels made of it. This is recorded</p></body></text></TEI>