<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with the royal favour. This propoſal was readily accepted by both parties, and the north inch of Perth was to be the ſcene of action. But, upon muſtering the combatants, it was found that one of them, belonging to the clan Chattan, had abſented himſelf. It was propoſed to balance this difference by withdrawing one of the combatants from the clan Kay; but not one of them could be prevailed on to reſign his place. At laſt one Henry Wynd, a ſaddler, though no way connected with either party, offered to ſupply the place of him that was abſent, on condition of his receiving a French crown of gold (about 7 s. 6 d. of our money); which was immediately paid him. The combat then began with incredible fury; but at laſt, through the superior valour and ſkill of Henry Wynd, victory declared in favour of the clan Chattan. Only ten of the conquerors, beſides Wynd, were left alive; and all of them deſperately wounded. Of the clan Kay only one remained; and he having received no hurt eſcaped by ſwimming acroſs the Tay.</p><p>While theſe internal broils were going on, the truce which had lately been concluded with England was ſo ill obſerved, that it became neceſſary to enter into freſh negociations. Theſe, like others which had taken place before, had very little effect. The borderers on both ſides had been ſo accuſtomed to ravage and plunder, that they could not live in quiet. King Robert alſo was thought to be too much attached to the king of England. He had introduced the new title of <hi rend="italic">duke, </hi>which he beſtowed firſt on the prince royal; but making an offer of that honour to one of the heads of the Douglas family, it was rejected with diſdain. That powerful family had never loſt fight of an ancient claim they had upon the caſtle of Roxburgh, which was ſtill in the poſſeſſion of the Engliſh; and this year the ſon of the earl of Douglas, Sir William Stewart, and others, broke down the bridge of Roxburgh, plundered the town, and deſtroyed the forage and corn there and in the neighbouring country. The Engliſh applied for ſatisfaction; but obtained none, as the confuſion which involved the kingdom by the depoſition of Richard II. and the acceſſion of Henry IV. prevented them from having recourſe to arms, the only argument to which the Scots patriots in thoſe days would liſten.</p><p>No ſooner was the cataſtrophe of Richard known in Scotland, than they reſolved to avail themſelves of it; and invading the north parts of England, demoliſhed the caſtle of Wark, and laid the neighbouring country under contribution. The ſituation of Henry’s affairs did not admit of his reſenting this inſult. He contented himself with nominating his brother the earl of Weſtmoreland, to treat with the Scots about a truce or peace; or, if that could not be obtained, to make a mutual agreement, that the towns of Dumfries in Scotland, and Penrith in England, ſhould be free from hoſtilities during the ar. To this propoſal the Scots paid no regard; and being encouraged by the court of France, who relented the depoſition of Richard, they renewed their ravages in England. In 1400, the king of England called a parliament, in order to conſult on the moſt proper means of repelling the Scottiſh invaſions; and in this he was greatly aſſiſted by the diviſions of the Scots among themſelves. The duke of Rotheſay, the heir-</p><p>apparent of the crown, was now grown up to man’s eſtate, and it was thought proper to provide a ſuitable conſort for him. The king is ſaid to have ſcandalouſly put up his ſon’s marriage at auction, and offered him to the lady whoſe father could give him the higheſt price. The earl of March was the higheſt bidder; and advanced a considerable ſum in ready money, on condition that his daughter ſhould become the royal bride.— This ſordid match was oppoſed by Douglas, who propoſed his own daughter the lady Margery. So degenerate was the court of Scotland at this time, that neither the king nor the duke of Rotheſay oppoſed this propoſal of a new match, becauſe it was to be purchaſed with a freſh ſum; and they even refuſed to indemnify the earl of March for the money he had already advanced.</p><p>As the duke of Albany ſided with Douglas, a council of the nobility was privately aſſembled, which annulled the contract of the lady Elizabeth Dunbar, the earl of March’s daughter, in favour of the lady Margery, daughter to the earl of Douglas; but without taking any meaſures for repaying the money to the earl of March. The continuator of Fordun informs us, that the earl of Douglas paid a larger ſum for his daughter’s fortune than that which had been advanced by the earl of March, and that the earl of Douglas’s daughter was married to the duke of Rotheſay: that, before the marriage was celebrated, March demanded that the money he had advanced ſhould be reimburſed; but receiving an unſatisfactory anſwer, he declared, that as the king had not fulfilled his bargain, he would bring unexpected calamities upon the country. Accordingly he fled into England, leaving his caſtle of Dunbar to the cuſtody of his nephew Robert Maitland, who ſoon after put it into the hands of the earl of Douglas, called in hiſtory <hi rend="italic">Archibald the Grim,</hi> from the ſternneſs of his viſage.</p><p>As ſoon as Robert heard of the revolt of the earl of March, he ſent ambaſſadors demanding back his ſubject; but the requeſt was diſregarded. On the other hand, the earl of March demanded repoſſeſſion of the caſtle of Dunbar, pleading, that he had committed no act of treaſon, but had come to England under a ſafe conduct from king Henry, on purpoſe to negociate his private affairs: but this requeſt was diſregarded; upon which he ſent for all his family and followers to England, where they joined him in great numbers. This produced a war between the two kingdoms. The earl of March, with Henry Percy ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">Hotspur,</hi> invaded Scotland, penetrating as far as Haddington, and carrying off great numbers of the inhabitants into captivity. From thence they went to Peebles, and then to Linton, ravaging the country all the way as they paſſed along. They next beſieged the caſtle of Hales, and took ſeveral of the neighbouring forts; but Archibald the Grim, or rather his ſon, having raiſed an army againſt them, they were ſtruck with terror, and fled to Berwick, to the gates of which they were purſued by the Scots. At this time the Scottiſh admiral, Sir Robert Logan, was at ſea with a ſquadron; but miſcarried in an attempt he made upon ſome Engliſh ſhips of war that protected their fleet when fiſhing upon the coaſt of Scotland. After this the Engliſh plundered the Orkney islands; which, though belong-</p></body></text></TEI>