<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:49:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The affairs of Scotland were now in the greateſt confuſion. The people of Galloway, at the head of whom were two noblemen or princes called <hi rend="italic">Othred</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gilbert, </hi>had taken the opportunity of aſſerting their independency on the crown of Scotland; and, having expelled all the Scots officers out of the country, they demoliſhed all the forts which William had erected in their country, and put to death all the foreigners. But in the mean time a quarrel enſuing between the two chiefs, Othred was murdered by Gilbert, who immediately applied to. Henry for protection.</p><p>Henry, in order to give all poſſible fonction to the convention betwixt him and William, ſummoned him to meet him and his ſon at York. William obeyed the ſummons, and along with him appeared all the great nobility and landholders; who confirmed the convention of Falaiſe, ſwore fealty to Henry, and put themſelves and their country under his protection. In the mean time, Gilbert, who was at the head of the rebels in Galloway, had offered to put himſelf and his people under the protection of the king of England, and to pay to Henry 2000 merks of ſilver yeatly, with 500 cows and as many hogs, by way of tribute: however, Henry, that he might oblige his new feudatory William, refuſed to have any concern in the affair. On this, William ordered his general Gilchriſt to march againſt him; which he did with ſuch ſucceſs, that Gilbert was entirely defeated, and Galloway again reduced under the dominion of Scotland. Very ſoon after this victory, Gilchriſt fell under the king’s diſpleaſure on the following occaſion. He had married Matilda, ſiſter to William; and on ſuſpicion, or proof, of her incontinence, put her to death at a village called <hi rend="italic">Maynes, </hi>near Dundee. The king being highly diſpleaſed at ſuch a groſs affront to himſelf, ſummoned Gilchriſt to take his trial for the murder: but as the general did not chooſe to make his appearance, his eſtates were confiſcated, his caſtles demoliſhed, and he himſelf baniſhed. He took refuge in England; but as it had been agreed in the convention between William and Henry that the one ſhould not harbour the traiterous ſubjects of the other, Gilchriſt was forced to return to Scotland with his two ſons. There they were expoſed to all the miſeries of indigence, and in perpetual fear of being diſcovered, ſo that they were obliged to ſkulk from place to place. William, on his return from an expedition againſt an uſurper whom he had defeated, happened to obſerve three ſtrangers, who, though diſguiſed like ruſtics, appeared by their noble mien to be above the vulgar rank. William, who firſt diſcovered them, was confirmed in this apprehenſion, by feeing them ſtrike out of the high road, and endeavour to avoid notice. He ordered them to be ſeized and brought before him. The oldeſt, who was Gilchriſt himſelf, fell upon his knees before him, and gave ſuch a detail of his misfortunes as drew tears from the eyes of all preſent; and the king reſtored him to his former honours and eſtates. From the family of this Gilchriſt that of the Ogilvies is ſaid to be deſcended.</p><p>The Scots continued to be in ſubjection to the Engliſh until the acceſſion of Richard I. This monarch being a man of romantic valour, zealouſly undertook an expedition into the Holy Land againſt the Turks, according to the ſuperſtition of the times. That he</p><p>might ſecure the quiet of his dominions in his abſence, he determined to make the king of Scotland his friend; and for this purpoſe, histhought nothing could be more acceptable than releaſing him and his ſubjects from that ſubjection which even the Engliſh themſelves conſidered as forced and unjuſt. However, he determined not to loſe this opportunity of ſupplying himſelf with a ſum of money, which could not but be abſolutely neceſſary in ſuch an expenſive and dangerous undertaking. He therefore made William pay him 10,000 merks for this releaſe: after which he entered into a convention, which is ſtill extant; and in this he acknowledges, that “all the conventions and acts of ſubmiſſion from William to the crown of England had been extorted from him by unprecedented writings and dureſſe” This tranſaction happened in the year 1189.</p><p>The generoſity of Richard met with a grateful return from William; for when Richard was impriſoned by the emperor of Germany in his return from the Holy Land, the king of Scotland ſent an army to aſſiſt his regency aginſt his rebellious brother John, who had wickedly uſurped the throne of England. For this Richard owned his obligation in the higheſt degree; but William afterwards made this an handle for ſuch high demands as could not be complied with. Nevertheleſs, the two monarchs continued in friendſhip as long as Richard lived. Some differences happened with King John about the poſſeſſion of Northumberland and other northern counties: but theſe were all finally adjuſted to the mutual ſatisfaction of both parties; and William continued a faithful ally of the Engliſh monarch till his death, which happened in the year 1214, after a reign of 49 years.</p><p>William was ſucceeded by his ſon Alexander II. a youth of 16. He revived his claim to Northumberland and the other northern counties of England; but John, ſuppoſing that he had now thoroughly ſubdued the Engliſh, not only refuſed to conſider the demands of Alexander, but made preparations for invading Scotland. John had given all the country between Scotland and the river Tees to Hugh de Baliol and another nobleman, upon condition of their defending it againſt the Scots. Alexander fell upon Northumberland, which he eaſily reduced, while John invaded Scotland. Alexander retired to Melros, in order to defend his own country; upon which John burnt the towns of Wark, Alnwick, and Morpeth, and took the ſtrong caſtles of Roxburgh and Berwick. He next plundered the abbey of Coldingham, reduced Dunbar and Haddington, ravaging the country as he paſſed along. His next operation was directed againſt Edinburgh; but being oppoſed by Alexander at the head of an army, he precipitately marched back. Alexander did not fail to purſue; and John, to cover his retreat, burnt the towns of Berwick and Coldingham. In this retreat the king of England himſelf ſet his men an example of barbarity, by ſetting fire every morning to the houſe in which he had lodged the preceding night. In ſhort, ſuch deſolation did John ſpread all around him, that Alexander found it impoſſible to continue his purſuit; for which reaſon he marched weſtward, and invaded England by the way of Carliſle. This place he took and fortified; after which he marched ſouth as far as Richmond, receiving homage from all the great barons as he went</p></body></text></TEI>