<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:48:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>country, beſides the above articles, contains likewiſe valuable mines of ſilver,
                copper, tin, lead, and iron; and abounds in many places with horned cattle, ſheep,
                horſes, and venison. The principal rivers by which it is watered are the Elbe, the
                Schwerze-Elſter, the Mulde, the Saale, the Unſtrut, the Weiſſe-Elſter, and the
                Pleiſſe. Theſe rivers, as well as the lakes and rivulets, abound in fiſh; and in the
                White-Elſter are found beautiful pearls. This electorate is extremely well
                cultivated anti inhabited, and is ſaid to include about 250 great and ſmall towns,
                upwards of 5000 villages, 196 royal manors, and near as many royal caſtles, beſides
                private eſtates, and commanderies. The provincial diets here conſiſt of three
                claſſes. The firſt is compoſed of the prelates, the counts, and lords, and the two
                universities of Leipſic and Wittenberg. To the ſecond belong the nobility in
                general, immediate or mediate, that is, ſuch as ſtand immediately under the
                fief-chancery or the aulic judicatories, and ſuch as are immediately under the
                juriſdiction of the amtman. The third claſs is formed of the towns in general. The
                general provincial diets are ordinarily held every ſix years; but there are others,
                called <hi rend="italic">ſelection diets,</hi> which are convened commonly every two
                years. We would here obſerve, that not only theſe diets, but thoſe in moſt of the
                other ſtates of Germany, are at preſent extremely inſignificant and unimportant,
                retaining little more than the ſhadow of their former power and privileges; for even
                the petty princes, though they depend upon their more potent neighbours, and muſt be
                careful not to give them any umbrage, are almoſt as abſolute in their reſpective
                territories as the grand ſeignior himſelf. As to religion, it was in this country
                that the reformation took its riſe in the 16th century, to which it hath ever ſince
                adhered, according to the doctrines of Luther @@*. The two late electors, when they
                embraced Popery in order to qualify themſelves to be elected kings of Poland, gave
                the moſt ſolemn aſſurances to their people, that they would inviolably maintain the
                eſtabliſhed religion and its profeſſors in the full and free enjoyment of all their
                eccleſiaſtical rights, privileges, and prerogatives whatſoever, in regard to
                churches, worſhip, ceremonies, uſages, univerſities, ſchools, benefices, incomes,
                profits, juriſdictions, and immunities. The electoral families ſtill continue Roman
                Catholics, though they have loſt the crown of Poland, for which they at firſt
                embraced Popery. With reſpect to eccleſiaſtical matters, the country is divided into
                pariſhes, and theſe again into ſpiritual inſpections and conſiſtories, all
                ſubordinate to the eccleſiaſtical council and upper conſiſtory of Dreſden, in which
                city and Leipſic the Calviniſts and Roman Catholics enjoy the free exerciſe of their
                religion. Learning flouriſhes in this electorate; in which, beſides the free-ſchools
                and gymnaſia in moſt of the chief towns, are the two celebrated univerſities of
                Wittenberg and Leipzig, in the laſt of which are alſo ſocieties for the liberal arts
                and the German language, with bookſellers and printers of the greateſt eminence. A
                great variety of manufactures are alſo carried on in this country. The principal are
                thoſe of fine and coarſe linen, thread, fine lace, paper, fine glaſſes and mirrors;
                porcelain, equal it not ſuperior to that of China @@†; iron, braſs, and ſteel wares;
                manufactures of gold and ſilver, cotton, wool, and ſilk; gloves, caps, hats, and
                tapeſtry;. in which, and the natural productions mentioned above, together with
                dye</p>
            <p>ing, an important foreign commerce is carried on. A great addition has been made
                ſince the year 1718 to the electoral territories, by the extinction of the
                collateral branches of Zeitz, Merſeburg, and Weiſſenfels, whoſe dominions devolved
                to the elder electoral branch, deſcended from the margraves of Meiſſen. The firſt of
                theſe, who was elector of Saxony, was Frederick the Warlike, about the beginning of
                the 15th century.</p>
            <p>This elector ſtyles himſelf duke of Saxony, Juliers, Cleve, and Berg, as alſo of
                Engern and Weſtphalia, arch-marſhal and elector of the Holy Roman empire, landgrave
                in Thuringia, margrave of Meiſſen, and of Upper and Lower Luſatia, burgrave of
                Magdeburg, princely count of Henneberg, count of La Mark, Ravenſherg, Barby, and
                Hanau, and lord of Ravenſtein. Among the electors he is reckoned the ſixth, as
                great-marſhal of the empire, of which he is alſo vicar, during an interregnum, in
                all places not ſubject to the vicariate of the count palatine of the Rhine. He is
                moreover ſole director of the circle; and in the vacancy of the ſee of Mentz claims
                the directorium at the diet of the empire. His matricular aſſeſſment, on account of
                the electorate, is 1984 florins, beſides what he pays for other diſtricts and
                territories. To the chamber-courts he contributes, each term, the ſum of 1545 rix
                dollars, together with 83 rix-dollars and 62 kruitzers on account of the county of
                Mansfeld. In this electorate, ſubordinate to the privy council, are various colleges
                for the departments of war, foreign affairs, the finances, fiefs, mines, police, and
                eccleſiaſtical affairs, together with high tribunals and courts of juſtice, to which
                appeals lie from the inferior. The revenues of this elector are as conſiderable as
                thoſe of any prince in the empire, if we except thoſe of the houſe of Auſtria. They
                ariſe from the ordinary and extraordinary ſubſidies of the ſtates; his own demeſnes,
                conſiſting of 72 bailiwics; the impoſt on beer, and the fine porcelain of the
                country; tenths of corn, fruit, wine, &amp;c. his own ſilver mines, and the tenths
                of thoſe that belong to particulars: all which, added together, bring in an yearly
                revenue of betwixt 700,000l. and 800,000l. yet the electorate is at preſent deeply
                in debt. The regular troops commonly amount to 20,000 men, excluſive of the militia
                of the ban, the arriere-ban, and the body of miners and hunters, who are obliged in
                time of war to bear arms. The whole electorate is divided into circles.</p>
            <p>The electoral circle, or the duchy of Saxony, is bounded by the circles of Meiſſen,
                Leipzig, and Thur ringia, the principality of Anhalt, the marche of Brandenburg, and
                Luſatia. The principality of Anhalt lies acroſs it, and divides it into two parts.
                Its greateſt length and breadth is computed at about 40 miles; but though it is
                watered by the Elbe, the Black Elfter, and the Mulde, it is not very fruitful, the
                ſoil for the moſt part conſiſting of fand. It contains 24 towns, three boroughs,
                betwixt 400 and 500 villages,. 164 noblemens eſtates, 11 ſuperintendencies, three
                inspections, under one conſiſtory, and 11 prefecturates or diſtricts. The preſent
                duchy of Saxony is not to be confounded with the old; for the latter was of a much
                greater extent, and contained in it thoſe large tracts: anciently called <hi
                    rend="italic">Eaſtphalia, Engern,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Weſtphalia,</hi> of
                which the electoral circle was no part, but was taken by Albert the Bear, margrave
                of Salzwedel, from the Venedi. His</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@* See </hi>Reformation<hi rend="italic">, n</hi>⁰ 8.</p>
            <p>@@@†See <hi rend="italic">Porcelain,</hi> n⁰ 23, 24.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
