<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:28Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>an intrigue with a woman in the neighbourhood, had been accuſtomed to deſcend the wall, during the night, by means of a ladder of ropes; whence, by a ſteep and difficult path, he arrived at the foot of the rock. Randolph himſelf, with 30 men, undertook to ſcale the caſtle walls at midnight. Frank was their guide, who ſtill retained a perfect memory of the path, and who firſt aſcended the wall. But before the whole party could reach the fummit, an alarm was given, the garriſon ran to arms, and a deſperate combat enſued. The Engliſh fought valiantly till their commander was killed; after which they threw down their arms. Leland, the former governor, was releaſed from his confinement, and entered into the Scottiſh ſervice.</p><p>In 1313, king Robert found the number of his friends increaſing with his ſucceſſes. He was now joined by the earl of Athol, who had lately obtained a grant of lands from Edward. This year, through the mediation of France, the conferences for a truce were renewed. Theſe, however, did not retard the military operations of the Scots. Cumberland was invaded and</p><p>laid waſte: the miſerable inhabitants beſought Edward’s protection; who commended their fidelity, and deſired them to defend themſelves. In the mean time, Robert, leaving Cumberland, paſſed over into the iſle of Man, which he totally reduced. Edward found great difficulties in raiſing the ſupplies neceſſary for carrying on the war; but at laſt overcame all theſe, and, by the beginning of the year 1314, was prepared to invade Scotland with a mighty army. In March he ordered his ſhip's to be aſſembled for the invaſion; invited to his aſſiſtance Eth O‘Connor, chief of the Iriſh of Connaught, and 26 other Iriſh chiefs; ſummoned them and his ſubjects in Ireland to attend his ſtandard, and gave the command of theſe auxiliaries to the earl of Ulſter. His barons were ſummoned to meet him at Berwick on the 11th of June; and 22,000 foot-ſoldiers, from the different counties of England and Wales, were required by proclamation to aſſemble at Wark.</p><p>In the mean time, the ſucceſſes of the Scots continued. Edward Bruce had reduced the cattles of Rutherglen and Dundee, and laid ſiege to the caſtle of Stirling. The governor of the place agreed to ſurrender, if he was not relieved before the 24th of June 1314; and to this Edward agreed, without conſulting his brother. The king was highly diſpleaſed with this raſh treaty, which interrupted his own operations, allowed the Engliſh time to aſſemble their utmoſt force, and at laſt obliged him either to raiſe the ſiege or to put all on the event of a ſingle battle. However, he reſolved to abide by the agreement, and to meet the Engliſh by the appointed day. Having appointed a general rendezvous of his forces between Falkirk and Stirling, he found their number to amount to ſomewhat more than 30,000, beſides upwards of 15,000 of an undiſciplined rabble that followed the camp. He determined to wait the Engliſh in a field which had the brook or <hi rend="italic">burn</hi> of Bannock on the right, and Stirling on the left. His chief dread was the ſtrength and number of the Engliſh cavalry, and theſe he took every method to oppoſe. The banks of the brook were ſteep in many places, and the ground between it and Stirling was partly covered with wood. The king commanded many pits, of about a foot in breadth and two or three feet deep, to be dug in all places where cavalry could have acceſs. From the deſcription given of them by the hiſtorians of thoſe times, there ſeem to have been many rows of them, with narrow intervals. They were carefully covered with bruſhwood and ſod, ſo that they would eaſily be overlooked by a raſh and impetuous enemy. It is ſaid by ſome authors, that he alſo made uſe of caltrops, to annoy the horſes in the moil effectual manner.</p><p>On the 23d of June, the "Scots received intelligence of the approach of Edward, and prepared to decide the fate of their country. The front of their army extended from the brook called <hi rend="italic">Bannockburn</hi> to thc neighbourhood of St Ninians, pretty nearly upon the line of the preſent turnpike-road from Stirling to Kilſyth; and the ſtone in which the king is ſaid to have fixed his ſtandard is ſtill to be ſeen. Robert commanded all his ſoldiers to fight on foot. He gave the command of the centre to Douglas, and Walter the young ſteward of Scotland; his brother Edward had the command of the right wing, and Randolph of the left; the king himſelf taking charge of the reſerve, which conſiſted of the men of Argyle, Carrick, and the iſlanders. In a valley to the rear, ſaid to be to the weſtward of a riſing ground now called <hi rend="italic">Gilles-hill,</hi> he placed the baggage, and all the uſeleſs attendants on his army.</p><p>Randolph was commanded to be vigilant in preventing the Engliſh from throwing ſuccours into the caſtle of Stirling; but 800 horſemen, commanded by Sir Robert Clifford, made a circuit by the low grounds to the eaſt, and approached the caſtle. The king, perceiving their motions, chid Randolph for his inadvertency, on which the latter halted to encounter that body. As he advanced, the Engliſh wheeled to attack him. Randolph drew up his men in a circular form, holding out their ſpears on every fide. At the firſt onſet Sir William Daynecourt, an Engliſh commander of diſtinguiſhed valour, was killed; but Randolph, who had only a ſmall party with him, was ſurrounded on all ſides, and in the utmoſt danger. Douglas perceived his danger, and requeſted the king to let him go to his aſſiſtahce. Robert at firſt refuſed, but afterwards conſented with reluctance. Douglas ſet out without delay; but as he approached he ſaw the Engliſh falling into diſorder; upon which he called to his men to ſtop, and not diminiſh the glory of Randolph and his men by ſharing their victory.</p><p>Robert was in the front of the line when the vanguard of the Engliſh appeared. He was meanly dreſſed, with a crown above his helmet, and a battle ax in his hand. Henry de Bohun, an Engliſh knight, armed cap-a-pee, rode forward to encounter him. Robert did not decline the combat, and ſtruck his antagoniſt ſo violently with his battle-ax, that he is ſaid to have cleft him down to the chin; after which the Engliſh vanguard retreated in confuſion. The Scottiſh generals are ſaid to have blamed their king for his raſhneſs in thus encountering Bohun; and he himſelf, conſcious of the juſtice of their charge, only replied, “I have broke my good battle-ax.”</p><p>On Monday the 24th of June, the whole Engliſh army moved on to the attack. The van, conſiſting of archers and lancemen, was commanded by Gilbert de Clare earl of Glouceſter, nephew to the Engliſh king, and Humphry de Bohun conſtable of England; but the ground was ſo narrow, that the reſt of the army had not</p></body></text></TEI>