<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:50:06Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>compliance with this laſt demand of Edward, the regency of Scotland without
                heſitation yielded to it alſo; for which they gave the following reaſons. “That
                whereas they (the ſtates of Scotland) had, with one aſſent, already granted that
                King Edward, as ſuperior lord of Scotland, ſhould give ſentence as to their ſeveral
                rights and titles to the crown of Scotland, &amp;c. but as the ſaid king of England
                cannot put his judgement in full execution to anſwer effectually without the
                poſſeſſion or ſeiſin of the ſaid country and its caſtles; we will, grant, and
                aſſent, that he, as ſovereign lord thereof, to perform the things aforeſaid, ſhall
                have ſeiſin of all the lands and caſtles in Scotland, until right be done to the
                demandants, and to the guardians and community of the kingdom of Scotland, to
                reſtore both it and its caſtles, with all the royalties, dignities, franchiſes,
                customs, rights, laws, uſages, and poſſeſſions, with their appurtenances, in the
                ſame ſtate and condition they were in when he received them; ſaving to the king of
                England the homage of him that ſhall be king; ſo as they may be reſtored within two
                months after the day the rights ſhall be determined and affirmed; and that the
                profits of the nation which ſhall be received in the mean time ſhall be kept in the
                hands of the chamberlain of Scotland that now is, and one to be joined with him by
                the king of England; ſo as the charge of the government, caſtles, and officers of
                the realm, may be deducted. In witneſs whereof, &amp;c.”</p>
            <p>For theſe reaſons, as it is ſaid, the regency put into the hands of Edward all the
                forts in the country. Gilbert de Umfreville alone, who had the command of the
                caſtles of Dundee and Forfar, refuſed to deliver them up, until he ſhould be
                indemnified by the ſtates, and by Edward himſelf, from all penalties of treaſon of
                which he might afterwards be in danger.</p>
            <p>But though Edward had thus got into his hands the whole power of the nation, he did
                not think proper to determine every thing by his own authority. Inſtead of this, he
                appointed commiſſioners, and promiſed to grant letters-patent declaring that
                ſentence ſhould be paſſed in Scotland. It had been all along foreſeen that the great
                diſpute would be between Bruce and Baliol; and though the plea of Cummin was judged
                frivolous, yet he was a man of too much influence to be neglected, and he agreed
                tacitly to refign it in favour of Baliol. Edward accordingly made him the compliment
                of joining him with Baliol in nominating 40 commiſſioners. Bruce was to name 40
                more; and the names of the 80 were to be given in to Edward in three days; after
                which the king was to add to them 24 of his own chooſing. The place and time of
                meeting were left in their own option. They unanimouſly pitched upon Berwick for the
                place of meeting; but as they could not agree about the time, Edward appointed the
                2d of Auguſt following. Soon after this, the regents reſigned their commiſſions to
                Edward; but he returned them, with powers to act in his name; and he nominated the
                biſhop of Caithneſs to be chancellor of Scotland; joining in the commiſſion with him
                Walter de Hemondeſham an Engliſhman, and one of his own ſecretaries. Still, however,
                he met with great difficulties. Many of his own great men, particularly the earl of
                Glouceſter, were by no means fond of increaſing the power of the Engliſh monarch by
                the acquiſition of Scotland; and therefore threw ſuch obſtacles in his way, that he
                was again obliged to have recourſe to negociation and intrigue, and at laſt to delay
                the meeting until the 2d of June in 1292: but during this interval, that he might
                the better reconcile the Scots to the loſs of their liberty, he propoſed an union of
                the two kingdoms; and for this he iſſued a writ by virtue of his ſuperiority.</p>
            <p>The commiſſioners having met on the ſecond of June 1292, ambaſſadors for Norway
                preſented themſelves in the aſſembly, demanding that their maſter ſhould be admitted
                into the number of the claimants, as father and next heir to the late queen. This
                demand too was admitted by Edward, after the ambaſſadors had acknowledged his
                ſuperiority over Scotland; after which he propoſed that the claims of Bruce and
                Baliol ſhould be previouſly examined, but without prejudice to thoſe of the other
                competitiors. This being agreed to, he ordered the commiſſioners to examine by what
                laws they ought to proceed in forming their report. The diſcuſſion of this queſtion
                was attended with ſuch difficulty, and the opinions on it were ſo various, that
                Edward once more adjourned the aſſembly to the 12th of October following; at which
                time he required the members to give their opinions on the two following points: 1.
                By what laws and cuſtoms they ought to proceed to judgment; and, ſuppoſing there
                could be no law or precedent found in the two kingdoms, in what manner? 2. Whether
                the kingdom of Scotland ought to be taken in the ſame view as all other fiefs, and
                to be awarded in the ſame manner as earldoms and baronies? The commiſſioners
                replied, that Edward ought to give juſtice conformable to the uſage of the two
                kingdoms; but that if no certain laws or precedents could be found, he might, by the
                advice of his great men, enact a new law. In anſwer to the ſecond queſtion they
                ſaid, that the ſuceeſſion to the kingdom might be awarded in the ſame manner as to
                other eſtates and great baronies. Upon this, Edward ordered Bruce and Baliol to be
                called before him; and both of them urged their reſpective pleas, and anſwers, to
                the following purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Bruce pleaded, 1. That Alexander II. deſpairing of heirs of his own body, had
                declared that he held him to be the true heir, and offered to prove by the teſtimony
                of perſons ſtill alive, that he declared this with the advice and in the preſence of
                the good men of his kingdom. Alexander III. alſo had declared to thoſe with whom he
                was intimate, that, failing iſſue of his own body, Bruce was his right heir. The
                people of Scotland alſo had taken an oath for maintaining the ſucceſſion of the
                neareſt in blood to Alexander III. who ought of right to inherit, failing Margaret
                the Maiden of Norway and her iſſue. — Baliol anſwered, that nothing could be
                concluded from the acknowledgment of Alexander II. for that he left heirs of his
                body; but made no anſwer to what was ſaid of the ſentiments of Alexander III. and of
                the oath made by the Scottiſh nation to maintain the ſucceſſion of the next of
                blood.</p>
            <p>2. Bruce pleaded, that the right of reigning ought to be decided according to the
                natural law, by which kings reign; and not according to any law or uſage in force
                between ſubject and ſubject: That by the law of nature, the neareſt collateral in
                blood has a right to the crown; but that the conſtitutions which prevail among
                vaſſals, bind not the lord, much leſs the ſovereign; That although in private
                inheritances, which</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
