<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-14T17:47:38Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Ouranos had much issue, wherefore Ge being grieved at it and jealous, reproached
                Ouranos, ſo as they parted from each other. But Ouranos, though he parted from her,
                yet by force invading her, and lying with her when he liſted, went away again; and
                he alſo attempted to kill the children he had by her. Ge alſo often defended or
                avenged herſelf, gathering auxiliary powers unto her. But when Cronus came to man’s
                age, uſing Hermes' Trismegistus as his counſellor and aſſiſtant (for he was his
                ſecretary), he oppoſed his father Ouranos, avenging his mother. But Cronus had
                children, Perſephone and Athena; the former died a virgin, but by the counſel of the
                latter Athena, and of Hermes, Cronus made of iron a ſcimitar and a ſpear. Then
                Hermes, ſpeaking to the aſſiſtants of Cronus with enchanting words, wrought in them
                a keen deſire to fight againſt Ouranos in the behalf of Ge; and thus Cronus warring
                againſt Ouranos, drove him out of his kingdom, and ſucceeded in the imperial power
                or office. In the ſight was taken a well-beloved concubine of Ouranos big with
                child. Cronus gave her in marriage to Dagon, and ſhe brought forth at his houſe what
                ſhe had in her womb by Ouranos, and called him <hi rend="italic">Demaroon.
                </hi>After theſe things Cronus builds a wall round about his houſe, and founds <hi
                    rend="italic">Byblus</hi> the firſt city in Phenicia. Afterwards Cronus,
                ſuſpecting his own brother Atlus, with the advice of Hermes, throwing him into a
                deep hole of the earth, there buried him, and having a ſon called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sαdid,</hi> he diſpatched him with his own ſword, having a ſuſpicion of him,
                and deprived his own ſon of life with his own hand. He alſo cut off the head of his
                own daughter, ſo that all the gods were amazed at the mind of Cronus. But in proceſs
                of time, Ouranos being in flight, or baniſhment, ſends his daughter Aſtarte, with
                two other ſiſters Rhea and Dione, to cut off Cronus by deceit, whom Cronus taking,
                made wives of theſe ſiſters. Ouranos, underſtanding this, ſent Eimarmene and Hore,
                Fate and Beauty, with other auxiliaries, to war againſt him: but Cronus, having
                gained the affections of theſe alſo, kept them with himſelf. Moreover, the god
                Ouranos deviſed <hi rend="italic">Baetulia,</hi> contriving ſtones that moved as
                having life. But Cronus begat on Aſtarte ſeven daughters called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Titanides</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Artemides; </hi>and he begat on Rhea ſeven
                ſons, the youngeſt of whom, as ſoon as he was born, was conſecrated a god. Alſo by
                Dione he had daughters, and by Aſtarte moreover two fons, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pathos</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Eros,</hi> i. e. Cupid and Love. But Dagon,
                after he had found out bread, corn, and the plough, was called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Zeus Arotrius.</hi> To <hi rend="italic">Sydyc,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">the
                    juſt, </hi>one of the <hi rend="italic">Titanides</hi> bare <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aſclepius.</hi> Cronus had alſo in <hi rend="italic">Peraea</hi> three ſons, I.
                    <hi rend="italic">Cronus</hi> his father’s nameſake. 2. <hi rend="italic">Zeus
                    Belus.</hi> 3. <hi rend="italic">Apollo”</hi></p>
            <p>Is it conceivable, that a writer ſo acute as Porphyry, or indeed that any man of
                common ſenſe either in his age or in that of Philo, would forge a book filled with
                ſuch ſtories as theſe, in order to remove the Chriſtian objections to the immoral
                characters of the Pagan divinities? The very ſuppoſition is impoſſible to be made.
                Nor let any one imagine that Sanchoniatho is here writing allegorically, and by his
                tales of <hi rend="italic">Ouranos,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Ge,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Cronus,</hi> is only perſonifying the <hi rend="italic"
                    >heaven,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">earth,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">time.</hi>
                On the contrary, he aſſures us, that <hi rend="italic">Ouranos,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Epigeus,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Autochthon</hi> (for he gives
                him all theſe names), was the ſon of one<hi rend="italic"> Eliaun</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Hypſiſtos, </hi>who dwelt about Byblus, and that from him the
                ele</p>
            <p>ment which is over us was called <hi rend="italic">heaven,</hi> on account of its
                excellent beauty, as the earth was named <hi rend="italic">Ge </hi>after his fiſter
                and wife. And his tranſlalor is very angry @@* with the Neotoric Greeks, as he calls
                them, becauſe that, "by a great deal of force and ſtraining, they laboured to turn
                all the ſtories of the gods into allegories and phyſical diſcourſes.” This proves
                unanſwerably, that the author of this book, whoever he was, did not mean to veil the
                great truths of religion under the cloak of mythologie allegories; and therefore, if
                it was forged by Porphyry in ſupport of Paganiſm, the forger ſo far miſtook the
                ſtate of the queſtion between him and his adverſaries, that he contrived a book,
                which, if admitted to be ancient, totally overthrew his own cauſe, The next thing to
                be inquired into with repect to Sanchoniatho is his antiquity. Did he really live
                and write at ſo early a period as Porphyry and Philo pretend? We think he did not;
                and what contributes not a little to confirm us in our opinion, is that mark of
                national vanity and partiality, common to after-times, in making the ſacred
                myſteries of his own country original, and conveyed from Phenicia into Egypt. This,
                however, furniſhes an aditional proof that Porphyry was not the forger of the work;
                for he well knew that the myſteries had their origin in Egypt (ſee <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Mysteries), </hi>and would not have fallen into ſuch a blunder.
                He is guilty, indeed, of a very great anachroniſm, when he makes Sanchoniatho
                contemporary with Semiramis, and yet pretends that what he writes of the Jews is
                compiled from the records of Hierombalus the prieſt of the god Jao; for Bochart has
                made it appear in the higheſt degree probable @@†, that <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hierombalus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Jeromb-baal</hi> is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Jerub-baal</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gideon</hi> of ſcripture.</p>
            <p>Between the reign of Semiramis and the Trojan war a period elapſed of near 800 years,
                whereas Gideon flouriſhed not above ſeventy years before the deſtruction of Troy.
                But ſuppoſing Sanchoniatho to have really conſulted the records of Gideon, it by no
                means follows that he flouriſhed at the fame period with that judge of Iſrael. He
                ſpeaks of the building of Tyre as an ancient thing, while our beſt chronologers@@
                place it in the time of Gideon. Indeed, were we certain that any writings had been
                left by that holy man, we ſhould be obliged to conclude, that a large tract of time
                had intervened between the death of their author and their falling into the hands of
                Sanchoniatho; for, ſurely, they could not, in a ſhort period, have been ſo
                completely corrupted as to give any countenance to his impious abſurdities. His
                atheiſtic coſmogony he does not indeed pretend to have got from the annals of the
                prieſt of Jao, but from records which were depoſited in his own town of Berytus by
                Thoth a Phenician philoſopher, who was afterwards made king of Egypt. But ſurely the
                annals of Gideon, if written by himſelf, and preſerved pure to the days of
                Sanchoniatho, muſt have contained ſo many truths of the Moſaic religion, as muſt
                have prevented any man of ſenſe from adopting ſo impoſſible a theory as Thoth’s,
                though ſanctioned by the greateſt name of profane antiquity. Stillingfleet indeed
                thinks it moſt probable that Sancboniatho became acquainted with the moſt remarkable
                paſſages of the life of Jerub-baal from annals written by a Phenician pen. He
                obſerves, that immediately after the death of Gideon, the Iſraelites, with their
                uſual proneneſs to idolatry, worſhiped <hi rend="italic">Baal-berith,</hi> or the
                idol of Berytus</p>
            <p>@@@ <hi rend="italic">[m]</hi>* Apud Euseb. Praep, Evang. <hi rend="italic">lib. I.
                    cap. 6.</hi></p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="italic">[m] </hi>† Geogr. Sair <hi rend="italic">p. 2. book 2, lib. 2.
                    cap. 17.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@[mu] Scaliger.</hi></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
