<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0785-01" facs="gri_33125011197759_0793.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAINBOW</label>
. See optics, Part ∏. Sect. i. § 1.</p><p>In the Philofophical Tranſactions for 1793, we have the following account of two rainbows ſeen by the Rev. Mr St urges.</p><p>" Οη the evening of the 9th of July 1792, between ſeven and eight o’clock, at Alverſtoke, near Goſport, on the ſea-coaſt of Hampſhire, there came up, in the ſonth-eaſt, a cloud with a thunder-ſhower ; while the fun ſhone bright, low in the horizon to the north-weſt.</p><p>“ In this ſhower two primary rainbows appeared, AB and AC, not concentric, but touching each other</p><p>at A, in the ſouth part of the horizon ; with a ſecon-dary bow to each, DE andDF (the laſt very faint, but diſcernible), which touched likewiſe at D. Both the primary were very' vivid for a conſiderable time, and at different times nearly equally ſo ; but the bow AB was "* moſt permanent, was a larger ſegment of a circle, and at laſt, after the other had vaniſhed, became almoſt a ſemi-circle ; the ſun being near ſetting. It was a perfect calm, and the ſea was as ſmooth as glaſs.</p><p>" If I fnight venture to offer a ſolution of this ap-pearance, it would be as follows. I conſider the bow AB as the true one, produced by the ſun itſelf ; and the other, AC, as produced by the reflection of the ſun from the ſea, which, in its perfectly fmooth ſtate, acted as a ſpeculum. The direction of the ſea, between the Iſle of wight and the land, was to the north-weſt in a line with the ſun, as it was then ſituated. The image reflected from the water, having its rays iffuing from a point lower than the real ſun, and in a line coming from beneath the horizon, would conſequently form a bow higher than the true one AB. And the ſhores, by which that narrow part of the ſea is bounded, would before the ſun’s actual ſetting intercept its rays from the ſurſhce of the water, and cauſe the bow AC, which I ſuppoſe to be produced by the reflection, to diſappear before the other.”</p><p>The marine or ſea bow is a phenomenon which maybe frequently obſerved in a much ag⅛ated ſea, and is occaſioned by the wind ſweeping part of the waves, and carrying them aloft ; which when they fall down are refracted by the ſun’s rays, which paint the colours of the bow juſt as in a common ſhower. Thefe bows are often ſeen when a veffel is ſailing with conſiderable force, and daſhing the waves around her, which are raiſed partly by tlre action βf the ſhip and partly by the force of the wind, and, falling down, they form a rainbow ; and they are alſo often occaſioned by the daſhing βf the waves againſt the rocks on ſhore.</p><p>In the Philofophical Tranſactions, it is obſerved by F. Bourzes, that the colours of the marine rain-bow are leſs lively, leſs diſtinct, and of ſhorter con-tinuance, than thoſe of the common bow ; that therc are ſcarce above two colours diſtinguiſhable, a dark yel-low on the ſide next the ſun, and a pale green on the oppoſite ſide. But they are more numerous, there be-ing ſometimes 20 or 30 ſeen together.</p><p>To this claſs of bows may be referred a kind of white or colourlefs rainbows, which Mcntzelius and others affirm to have ſeen at noon-day. M. Marlotte, in his fourth <hi rend="italic">Efifαi de Phyſique,</hi> ſays, theſe bows are formed in miſts, as the others are in ſhowers ; and adds,· that he has ſeen ſeveral both after ſun-riſing and in the night. The want of colours he attributes to the fmallneſs of the va∙ pours which compofe the miſt ; but perhaps it is rather ſhom the exceeding .tenuity of the little veficulæ of the vapour, which being only little watery pellicles bloated with air, the rays of light undergo but little refraction in paſſing out of air into them ; too little to ſeparate the differently coloured rays, &amp;c. Hence the l ays are reflected from them, compounded as they came, that is, white. Rohault mentions * coloured rainbows on the graſs ; formed by the reſractions of the ſun’s rays in the morning dew. Rainbows have been alfo produced by the reflection of the ſun from a river ; and in the Philofophical Tranſactions, V0I. L. p. 2 g 4. we</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0786" facs="gri_33125011197759_0794.tif"/>
<p>have an account of a rainbow, which muſt have been formed by the exhalations from the city of London, when the ſun had been ſet 20 minutes, and conſequently the centre of the bow was above the horizon. The colours were the fame-as in the common rainbow, but fainter.</p><p>It has often been made a fubject of inquiry among the curious how there came to be no rainbow before the flood, which is thought by ſome to have been the caſe from its being made a ſign of the covenant which theDei-fy was pleafed to make with man after that event. Mr whitehurſt, in his <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the Original State and Formation if the Earth,</hi> p∙ 173, &amp;c. endeavours to eſtabliſh it as a matter of great probability at leaſt, that the antediluvian atmoſphere was ſo uniformly temperate as never to be ſubject to ſtorms, tempeſts, or rain, and of courſe it could never exhibit a rainbow. For our own part, we cannot ſee how the earth at that period could do without rain any more than at preſent ; and it appears to us from Scripture equally probable that the rainbow was ſeen before the flood as after it. It was then, how-ever, made a token of a certain covenant ; and it would unqueſtionably do equally well for that purpoſe if it had exiſted before as if it had not.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Lunar Rainbow.</hi> The moon ſometimes alſo exhi-bits the phenomenon of an iris or rainbow by the re-fraction of her rays in drops of rain in the night-time. This phenomenon is very rare. In the Philofophical Tranſactions for 1783, however, we have an account of three feen in one year, and all in the fame place, communicated in two letters by Marmaduke Tunſtall, Efq. The firſt was ſeen 27th February 1782, at Greta Bridge, Yorkſhire, between ſeven and eight at night, and appeared “ in tolerably diſtinct colours, fimilar to a ſolar one, but mare faint : the orange colour ſeemed to predominate. It happened at full moon ; at which time alone they are ſaid to have been always ſeen. Though Ariſtotle is faid to have obſerved two, and ſome others have been ſeen by Suellius, &amp;c. I can only ſind two de-ſcribed with any accuracy ; viz. one by Plot, in his Hiſtory of oxfordſhire, ſeen by him in 1675, though without colours ; the other ſeen by a Derbyſhire gen-tleman at Glapwell, near Cheſterſield, deſcribed by Tho-reſhy, and inferted in N <hi rend="sup">j</hi> 3 31. of the Philofophical Tranſ-actions : this was about Chriſtmas, 1710, and ſaid to have had all the colours of the Iris Solaris. The night was windy ; and though there was then a drizzling rain and dark cloud, in which the rainbow was reflected, it proved afterwards a light froſt.”</p><p>Two others were afterwards ſeen by Mr Tunſtall ; one on July the 30fb, about 11 o’clock, which laſted about a quarter of an hour, without colours. The other, which appeared on Friday october 18. was " perhaps the moſt extraordinary one of the kind ever ſeen. It was firſt viſible about nine o’clock, and continued, tho’ with very different degrees of briſliancy, till paſt two. At firſt, though a ſtrongly marked bow, it was without colours; but afterwards they were very conſpicuous and vivid in the ſame form as in the folar, though faint-cr ; the red, green, and purple, were moſt diſtinguiſhable. About twelve it was the moſt ſplendid in ap-pearance ; its arc was confiderably a ſmaller ſegment of a circle than a folar ; its ſouth-eaſt limb firſt began to fail, and a conſiderable time before its final extinction : the wind was very high, nearly due weſt, moſt part of</p><p>the time, accompanied with a drizzling rain. It is a ſingular circumſtance, that three of theſe phenomena ſhould have been ſeen in ſo ſhort a time in one place, as they have been eſteemed ever ſince the time of Ariſtotle, who is ſaid to have been the firſt obſerver of them, and ſaw only two in 50 years, and ſince by Plot and Thoreſhy, almoſt the only two Engliſh authors who have fpoke of them, to be exceeding rare. They ſeem evidently to be occaſioned by a refraction in a cloud or turbid atmoſphere, and in general are indications of ſtormy and rainy weather : ſo bad a ſeaſon as the late ſummer having, I believe, ſeldom occurred in EngIand. Thoreſhy, indeed, fays, the one he obſerved was ſuc-ceeded by ſeveral days of fine ſerene weather. Ûne particular, rather fingular, in the ſecond, viz. of July the 30th, was its being ſix days after the full of the moon; and the laſt, though of ſo long a duration, was three days before the full : that of the 27th of February was exactly at the full, which ufed to be judged the only time they could be ſeen, though in the Encyclo-pedia there is an account that weidler obſerved one in 1719, in the ſirſt quarter of the moon, with faint co-lours, and in very calm weather. No lunar iris, I ever heard or read of, laſted near ſo long as that on the 18th inſtant, either with or without colours.”</p><p>In the Gentleman’s Magazine for Auguſt 1788 we have an account of a lunar rainbow by a correſpondent who faw it. " Οη Sunday evening the 17th of Auguſt (fays he), after two days, on both of which, par-ticularly the former, there had been a great deal of rain, together with lightning and thunder, juſt as the clocks were ſtriking nine, 23 hours after full moon, looking through my window, I was ſtruck with the appearance of ſomething in the ſky, which ſeemed like a rainbβw. Having never ſeen a rainbow by night, I thought it a very extraordinary phenomenon, and ha-ſtened to a place where there were no buildings to ob-ſtruct my view of the hemifphere : here I found that the phenomenon was no other than a lunar rainbow ; the moon was truly ‘ walking in brightneſs,’ brilliant as ſhe could be ; not a cloud was to be ſeen near her ; and over-againſt her, toward the north-weſt, or perhaps rather more to the north, was a rainbow, a vaſt arch, perfect in all its parts, not interrupted or broken as rainbows frequently are, but unremittedly viſible from one horizon to the other. In order to give ſome idea of its extent, it is neceſſary to ſay, that as I ſtood to-ward the weſtern extremity of the pariſh of Stoke Newington, it ſeemed to take its riſe from the weſt of Hampſtead, and to the end, perhaps, in the river Lea,, the eaſtern boundary of Tottenham ; its colour was white, cloudy, or greyiſh, but a part of its weſtern leg ſeemed to exhibit tints of a faint fickly green. I continued viewing it for ſome time, till it began to rain and at length the rain increafing, and the iky growing more hazy, I returned home about a quarter or 20 minutes paſt nine, and in ten minutes came out again ; but by that time all was over, the moon was darkened by clouds, and the rainbow of courſe vaniſhed.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Marine Rainbow,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sea-bow.</hi> Seethe article <hi rend="smallcaps">Rainbow.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RAiNBοrr-Stοne.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">MοοN-Stοne. ■</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>