<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0033-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0039.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RED</label>
one of the colours called <hi rend="italic">fimple</hi> or <hi rend="italic">primary :</hi> being one of the ſhades into which the light naturally divides itſelfwhen refracted through a priſm. See C <hi rend="smallcaps">h ro-matics∙</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Red,</hi> in dyeing, ſee that article.—Some reckon ſix kinds or caſts of red, viz. fcarlet-rcd, crimſon-red, mad-der-red, half-grain red, lively orange-red, and ſcarlet of cochineal : but it is eaſy to ſee that there can be but one proper ſpecies of red ; namely, the reflection of the light exactly in ſuch a manner as it is refracted by the priſin ; all other ſhades being adulterations of that pure colour, with yellow, brown, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Red,</hi> in heraldry. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gules.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RKn-Bird.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Muscicapa,</hi> n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 7.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rρ∏-Breafi,</hi> in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Motacilla.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RED-Sοok</hi> of the exchequer, an ancient record or manuſcript volume, in the keeping of the king’s re-membrancer, containing divers miſcellany treatiſes re-lating to the times before the conqueſt.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RKû-Lead.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> n <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1213.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RED Precipitate of Mercury.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> n <hi rend="sup">o</hi> 764·</p><p><hi rend="italic">REι&gt;-Ruffa,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Little Rujfia,</hi> a province of Poland, bounded on the weſt by Upper Poland, on the north by Lithuania, on the eaſt by the country of the Little Tartars, and on the ſouth by Moldavia, Tranſylvania, and a part of Hungary. It comprehends Ruſſia pro-perly ſo called, volhinia, and Podolia. lt is about 650 miles in length, and from 150 to 250 in breadth. It conſiſts chiefly of large fields, but little cultivated on account of the frequent inroads of the Tartars, and becauſe there is no water-carriage. It had the name of <hi rend="italic">Red Rujfia,</hi> from the colour of the hair of its inha-bitants. Ruffιa <hi rend="sub">r</hi> properly ſo called, comprehends the three palatinates of Leopol or Lemburg, Belſko, and Chelm.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RED Sea,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Arabic Gulph,</hi> ſo much celebrated in ſa-cred hiſtory, ſeparates Arabia from Upper Ethiopia and part of Egypt. This ſea is 350 leagues in length</p><p>and 40 in breadth. As no river falls into it of ſuffi-cient force to counteract the influence of the tide, it is more affected by the motions of the great ocean than any oſ the inland ſeas nearly in the ſame latitude. It is not much expofed to tempeſts : the winds uſually blow from north to ſouth, and being periodical, like the monſoons of India, invariably determine the feafon of foiling into or out of this ſea. It is divided into two gulphs ; that to the eaſt was called the <hi rend="italic">Ælanitic gulph,</hi> from the city Ælana at the north end of it ; and that to the weſt the <hi rend="italic">Heroopolitic,</hi> from the city of Heroopo-lis ; the former of which belongs to Arabia, and the latter to Egypt.</p><p>Mr Bruce has made many obſervations on this ſea, which are worthy of notice.—with regard to the name, he fays ſt was certainly derived from Edom or Efou the ſon of Jacob ; though in another place he fays, he wonders that writers have not rather fuppoſed it to have got the epithet of <hi rend="italic">Red,</hi> from the colour of the fond on its coaſts, than for other reaſons they have alleged. w ith regard to any redneſs in the water itſelf, or in the bottom, which ſome have aſſerted, our travel-ler aſſures us that there is no ſuch thing. It is more difficult to aſſign a reafon for the Hebrew name of <hi rend="italic">it,</hi> which ſignifies the <hi rend="italic">Sea of Weeds ;</hi> as he never faw a weed throughout the whole extent of it. " Indeed, (ſays he) upon the ſlighteſt conſideration, it will occur to any one, that a narrow gulph, under the immediate influence of the monſoons, blowing from contrary points ſix months each year, would have too much agi-tation to produce ſuch vegetables, ſeldom found but in ſtagnant waters, and ſeldom, if ever, found in folt ones. My opinion then is, that it is from the large trees or plants of white coral, ſpread everywhere over the bottom of the Red Sea, perfectly in imitation of plants on land, that the fea has obtained this name.—I ſaw one of theſe, which, from a root nearly central, threw out ramifications of an almoſt circular form, meaſuring 26 feet every way.”</p><p>our author has alſo made many uſeful obſervations on the navigation of this ſea. " All the weſtern ſhore (he fays) is bold, and has more depth of water than the eaſt; but on this fide there is neither anchoring ground nor ſhoals. It is rocky, with a conſiderable depth of water everywhere ; and there are a number of ſunken rocks, which, though not viſible, are ſufficiently near the ſurface to deſtroy a large ſhip.” The cauſe of this, in Mr Bruce’s opinion, is, that the mountains on the ſide of Abyſſinia and Egypt are all of hard ſtone, porphyry, many different kinds of marble, granite, ala-baſter, and baſaltes. Thefe being all compoſed of ſo-lid materials, therefore, can part with very little duſt or fond, which might otherwiſe be blown from them into the ſea. Οη the oppoſite coaſt, viz. that of He-jaz and Tahamah, on the Arabian ſide, the whole con-ſiſts of moving fonds ; a large quantity of which is blown from the ſouth-eaſt by the dry winter monſoons; which being lodged among the rocks on that ſide, and confined there by the north-eaſt or ſummer monſoon, which is in a contrary direction, hinders them from coming over to the Egyptian fide. Hence the weſtern coaſt is full of funk rocks for want of fond to cover them, with which they would otherwiſe become iſlands. They are naked and bare all round, with ſharp points like ſpears ; while, on the eaſt-ſide, every rock becomes</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0034" facs="gri_33125011196389_0040.tif"/>
<p>an iſland, and every two or three iſlands become an harbour. Οη the ends of the principal of theſe harbours the people have piled up great heaps of ſtones to ſerve as ſignals : " and it is in theſe (ſays Mr Bruce) that the large veffels from Cairo to Jidda, equal in ſize to our large 74 gun-ſhipe (but from the ciſterns of ma-ſon-work built within for holding water, I ſuppoſe double their weight), after navigating their portion of the channel in the day-time, come ſafely and quietly to ut four o’clock in the afternoon ; and in theſe little harbours paſs the night, to ſail into the channel again next morning.”</p><p>The weſtern channel of the Red Sea was choſen, in the days of the Ptolemies, for the track of the Indian and African. Theſe monarchs erected a great number of cities all along the weſtern coaſt ; and notwithſtand-ing the dangers of the navigation, we do not hear that it was ever abandoned on account of them.</p><p>From the obſervations made by our author on the navigation of the Red Sea, he undertakes to point out a ſafe paſſage for large ſhips to the gulph of Suez, ſo that they may be able to judge of the propriety of their own courſe themſelves, without truſting implicitly to the pilots they meet with, who are often very ignorant of their profeſſion. This ſea, according to Mr Bruce, may be divided into four parts, of which the channel occupies two, till near the latitude of 26 <hi rend="sup">j</hi> , or that of Coſſair. Οη the weſt it is deep water, with many recks ; and on the eaſt it is full of iſlands, as has been already mentioned. Between theſe iſlands there are channels and harbours of deep water, where ſhips may be protected in any wind ; but a pilot is neceſſary io failing among theſe ſrom Mocha to Suez, and the voyage beſides can be continued only during part of the day. Ships bound to Suez without the conſent of the ſheriſſe of Mecca, that is, without any intention of felling their cargo at Jidda, or paying cuſtom there, ought to take in their freſh water at Mocha ; or it there be any reaſon againſt this, a few hours will carry them to Azab or Saba on the Abyffinian coaſt, where they may be plentifully ſupplied : but it muſt be remembered,</p><p>“ that the people here are <hi rend="italic">Galla,</hi> the moſt treacherous and villanous wretches on earth.” Here not only •water may be procured, but plenty of ſheep, goats, with ſome myrrh, and incenſe in the proper ſeaſon.·— Great caution, however, muſt be uſed in dealing with the people, as even thoſe of Mocha, who are abſolutely neceſſary to them in their commercial dealings, cannot truſt them without ſurety or hoſtages. Not many years ago, the ſurgeon and mate of the Elgin Eaſt India-man, with ſeveral other ſailors, were murdered by theſe ſavages as they went aſhore to purchaſe myrrh, though they had a letter of ſafe conduit from the ſhekh.</p><p>To ſuch as do not want to be known, our author recommends a low black iſland on the coaſt of Arabia, named <hi rend="italic">Camaran,</hi> in latitude 15 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 30'. It is diſtinguiſhed by a white houſe or fortrefs on the weſt end of it ; where water is to be had in ſtill greater plenty than at Azab ; but no proviſions, or ſuch only as are very bad, can be procured. If it is neceſſary not to be ſeen at</p><p>all on the coaſt, the iſland of Fooſht is recommended by our author as having excellent water, with a ſaint or monk, whofe office is to keep the wells clean. This is one of the chain of iſlands which ſtretches almoſt acroſs the gulph from Loheia to Maſuah, aad from ac</p><p>tual obſervation by Mr'Bruce, is found to be fituated in N. Lat. 15 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 59' 43 '. E. Long. 42 <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 47'. From this to Yambo there is a ſaſe watering-place ; and there is an abſolute neceſſity for having a pilot before you come to Ras Mahomet ; becauſe, over the Ælanitic gulph, the mountains of Aucha, and the Cape itſelf, there is often a thick haze which laſts for many days together, and a number of ſhips are loſt by miſtaking the eaſtern bay or Ælanitic gulph for the entrance of the gulph of Suez ? the former has a ridge of rocks nearly acrofs it. Aſter reaching Sheduan, a large iſlancl, about three leagues farther in a north by weſt direction, there is a bare rock diſtinguiſhed by no particular name ; but ſo ſituated that ſhips ought not to come within three leagues of it. This rock is to be left to the weſtward at the diſtance juſt mentioned ; after paſſing which you meet with ſhoals forming a pretty broad channel, with foundings from 15 to 30 fathoms; and again, on ſtanding directly for Tor, there are two other oval ſands with ſunk rocks in the channel, between which you are to ſteer. Tor may be known at a diſtance by two hills that ſtand near the water ſide ; which, in clear weather, may be ſeen ſix leagues off. Juſt to the ſouth-eaſt of theſe is the town and harbour, where there are ſome palm-trees about the houſes, the more remaιkable, as being the firſt that are ſeen on the coaſt. The foundings in the way to Tor harbour are clean and regular ; " and, by giving the beacon a ſmall birth on the larboard hand, you may haul in a little to the northward, and anchor in five or fix fathom.” In ſpring-tides, it is high water at Tor nearly about 12 o’clock : in the middle of the gulph there is no perceptible tide, but at the ſides it runs at the rate of more than two knots in the hour. Tor itſelf is but a ſmall village, with a convent of monks belonging to thoſe of Mount Sinai. It was taken by Don John de Caſtro, and fortified ſoon after its diſcovery by the Portugneſe ; but has never ſince been a place of any confideration ; ſerving now only for a watering place to the ſhips trading to or from Suez.— From this place there is a diſtinct view of mounts Ho-reb and Sinai, which appear above and behind the others, with their tops frequently covered with ſnow in the winter.</p><p>Mr Bruce next proceeds to confider ſome queſtions which may be reckoned matters of curiofity rather than any thing elſe. Οηε of theſe is concerning the level of the water of this ſea itſelf, which has been ſuppofed ſeveral feet above that of the Mediterranean. " To this (ſays our author) I anſwer, that the fact has been ſup-poſed to be ſo by antiquity, and alleged as a reaſon. why Ptolemy’s canal was made from the bottom of the Heroopolitic gulph rather than brought due north acroſs the iſthmus of Suez ; in which laſt caſe it was feared it would ſubmerge a great part of Afia Minor.. But who has ever attempted to verify this by experiment ? or who is capable of ſettling the difference of levels, amounting, as ſuppofed, to ſome feet and inches, between two points 120 miles diſtant from each other, over a deſert that has no fettled ſurface, but is chan-ging its height every day ? Beſides, ſince all ſeas are in fact but one, what is it that hinders the Indian ocean to flow to its level ? what is it that keeps the Indian ocean up ? Till this laſt branch of the queſtion is reſol-vcd, I ſhall take it for granted that <hi rend="smallcaps">bo</hi> ſuch difference</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0035" facs="gri_33125011196389_0041.tif"/>
<p>rtf level exiſts, whatever Ptolemy’s cngineers might have pretended to him; becauſe, to ſuppoſe it fact, is to ſup-poſe the violation of one very material law of nature.”</p><p>The next thing conſidered by our author is the paſſage of the Iſraelites through the Red Sea. At the place where he ſuppoſes the paffage to have been, the ſea is not quite four leagues broad, ſo that it might ea-fily have been croſſed in one night without any miracle. There is about 14 fathom water in the channel, and 9 at the ſides, with good anchorage everywhere ; the far-theſt ſide is a low fandy coaſt, and a very eaſy landing place. " The draught of the bottom of the gulph (fays he) given by Dr Pococke, is very erroneous in every part of it. It was propoſed to Mr Niebuhr, when in Egypt, to inquire upon the fpot, whether there were not fome ridges of rocks where the water was ſhallow, fo that an army at particular times might paſs over ? Secondly, whether the Eteſian winds, which blow ſtrongly all ſummer from the north-weſt, could not blow ſo violently againſt the fea, as to keep it back on a heap, ſo that the Iſraelites might have paſſed with-⅛&gt;ut a miracle ? And a copy of theſe queries was left for me to join my inquiries likewiſe. But I muſt con-feſs, however learned the gentlemen were who propoſed theſe doubts, I did not think they merited any attention to ſolve them. If the Eteſian winds, blowing from the north-weſt in ſummer, could heap up the fea as a wall on the right or to the ſouth, of 50 feet high, ſtill the difficulty would remain of building the wall on the left hand or to the north. Beſides, water ſtanding in that poſition for a day, muſt have loſt the nature of a fluid, whence came that coheſion of particles that hindered that wall to efcape at the ſides ? This is as great a miracle as that of Moſes. If the Eteſian winds had done this once, they muſt have repeated it many a time before and ſince, from the ſame caufes. Yet Dio-dorus Siculus ſays, the Troglodytes, the indigenous inhabitants of that very ſpot, had a tradition from father to ſon, from their very earlieſt and remoteſt ages, that once this diviſion of the ſea did happen there ; and that, after leaving the bottom ſome time dry, the ſea again came back and covered it with great fury. I he words of this author are of the moſt remarkable kind, we cannot think this heathen is writing in favour of reve-lation. He knew not Mofes, nor ſays a word about Pharaoh and his hoſt ; but records the miracle of the diviſion of the ſea in words nearly as ſtrong as thoſe of Moſes, from the mouths of unbiaſſed undeſigning pagans.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">R ED-Shank,</hi> in ornithology. See Scolopax.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RED-Stari,</hi> a ſpecies of Motacilla.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RKD-Wing.</hi> SeeTuRDus.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>