<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0772-01"
                facs="gri_33125011197759_0780.tif" type="entry">
                <p><label>RABBIT</label> in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Lepus.</hi></p>
                <p>The buck rabbits, like our boar cats, will ki∏ the young ones if they can get at
                    them ; and the does in the warrens prevent this, by covering their ſtocks, or
                    neſts, with gravel or earth, which they cloſe ſo artificially up with the hinder
                    part of their bodies, that it is hard to find them out. They never ſuckle their
                    young ones at any other time than early in the morning and late at night ; and
                    always, for eight or ten days, clofe up the hole at the mouth of the neſt, in
                    this careful manner when they go out. After this they begin to leave a ſmall
                    opening, which they increaſe by degrees ; till at length, when they are about
                    three weeks old, the mouth of the hole is left wholly open that they may go out
                    ; for they are at that time grown big enough to take care of themſelves, and to
                    feed on graſs.</p>
                <p>People who keep rabbits tame for profit, breed them in hutches; but theſe muſt be
                    kept very neat and clean, clſe they will be always ſubject to difeaſes. Care
                    muſt be taken alſo to keep the bucks and does apart till the ∣atter have juſt
                    kindled ; then they are to be turned to the bucks again, and to remain with them
                    till they ſhun and run from them.</p>
                <p>The general direction for the chooſing βf tame rabbits is, to pick the largeſt
                    and faireſt ; but the breeder ihould remember that the ſkins of the
                    ſilver-haired ones ſell better than any other. The food of the tame rabbits may
                    be colewort and cabbage-leaves, carrots, parſ-r&lt;eps, apple-rinds, green corn,
                    and vetches, in the time of the year; alſo vine-leaves, graſs, fruits, oats, and
                    oatmeal, milk-thiſtles, ſow-thiſtles, and the like : but with theſe moiſt foods
                    they muſt always have a pro-portionable quantity of the dry foods, as hay,
                    bread, oats, bran, and the like, otherwiſe they will grow pot-bellied, and die.
                    Bran and grains mixed together have been alſo found to be very good food. In
                    winter they will eat hay, oats, and chaff, and theſe may be given them three
                    times a-day ; but when they eat green things, it muſt be obſerved that they are
                    not to drink at ail, for it would throw them into a dropſy. At all other times a
                    very little drink ſerves their turn, but that muſt always be freſli. when any
                    green herbs or .graſs are cut for their food, care muſt be taken that there be
                    no hemlock among it; for though they will eat this greedily among other things
                    when offered to them, yet it is fudden poiſon to them.</p>
                <p>Rabbits are ſubject to two principal infirmities. Firſt, the rot, which is cauſed
                    by giving them too large a quantity of greens, or from giving them freſli
                    gathered with the dew or rain hanging in drops upon them. It is over-moiſture
                    that always cauſes this diſeaſe. The greens therefore are always to be given
                    dry; and a ſufficient quantity of hay, or other dry food, intermixed with them,
                    to take up the abundant moiſture of their juices. Οη this account the very beſt
                    food that can be given them, is the ſhorteſt and fweeteſt hay that can be got,
                    of which one load will ferve 200 couples a year ; and out of this ſtock of 200,
                    200 may be eat in the family, 200 fold to the markets, and a ſufficient number
                    kept in caſe of accidents.</p>
                <p>The other general diſeaſe of theſe creatures is a fort of madneſs : this may be
                    known by their wallowing and tumbling about with their heels upwards, and
                    hopping Hl an odd manner into their boxes. This diſtem-per is ſuppofod to be
                    owing to the rankneſs of their feeding; and the general cure is the keeping them
                    low, and giving them the prickly herb called <hi rend="italic">tare-th'file</hi>
                    to. eat.</p>
                <p>The general, computation of ma!es and females is, that one buck-rabbit will ſerve
                    for nine does : ſome al-low 10 to one buck £ but thoſe who go beyond this,
                    always ſuffer ſor it in their breed.</p>
                <p>The wild rabbits are either to be taken by ſmall cur-dogs, or by ſpaniels bred up
                    to the ſport ; and the places of hunting thoſe who ſtraggle horn their burrows,
                    is under cloſe hedges or buſhes, or among corn-fields and freſh paſtures. The
                    owners uſe to courſe then» with ſmall greyhounds ; and though they are ſeldctn
                    killed this way, yet they are driven back to their bur-rows, and are prevented
                    from being a prey to others. The common method is by nets called <hi
                        rend="italic">purfi-nets,</hi> and ferrets. The ferret is ſent into the hole
                    to fetch them out; and the purſe-net being ſpread over the hole, takes them as
                    they come out. The ferrets mouths muſt be muffled, and then the rabbit gets no
                    harm. For the more certain taking of them, it may not be improper to pitch up a
                    hay-net or two, at a fmall diſtance from the burrows that are intended to be
                    hunted: thus very few of the number that are attempted will eſcape.</p>
                <p>Some who have not ferrets ſmoke the rabhits out of their holes with burning
                    brimſtone and orpiment. This certainly brings them out into the nets : but. then
                    it is a very troubleſome and offenſive method ; and is very detrimental to the
                    place, as. no rabbit will for a long time, afterwards come near the burrows
                    which have been fumed with thoſe ſtinking ingredients.</p>
                <p>I he teſticle of a rabbit is a very good object for examining the ſtructure of
                    this part of generation in animals. lhe whole ſubſtance ot the teſticle in this
                    ani-. mal is made up of veffels, which lie in round folds in the manner ot the
                    ſmaller inteſtines: but then both ends, of each roll meet at their inſertion,
                    which ſeems to be made into the <hi rend="italic">ductus nervoſus ;</hi> and
                    every one of theſe little rolls is curiouſly embroidered with other veſſels,
                    which, from their red colour, appear to be arteries and veins. The ſeveral
                    little rolls lie in ranges, diſpoſed with an uniformity which is very agreeable
                    to the eye. Every one of theſe rolls is not a ſingle and entire tube, but each
                    conſiſts of ſeveral tubes, beſide the veins and arteries which embroider it.
                    This is beſt diſtinguiſhed by the cutting one of the rolls tranfverſely, and
                    then examining the cut end with a glaſs, which will appear to be made up of the
                    cut and open ends of four, five, or more parallel tubes, which together form the
                    roll, or ſingle tube, as it appears to the eye, being all wrapped, up in one
                    common and very thin membrane. Theſe are fo tender that they cannot be
                    explicated and viewed diſtinct, as De Graaf tells us thoſe of the teſticles of a
                    rat and of fome other animals may. Tlieſe, however, as well as the others, are
                    only made up of a congeries, of veſſels, and the liquors, which are their
                    contents, without any intermediate ſubſtance, or any thing of that parenchyma
                    which many authors have talked of. The teſticles of a bull have the greatest
                    appearance of a fleſhy texture of thoſe of any known animal ; yet even thefσ
                    afford no particle of parenchyma, or fleſh, when examined by glaſſes in any fort
                    of preparation, whether boil-ed, law, foaked in ſpirits} or in whatever other
                    ſtate.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0773" facs="gri_33125011197759_0781.tif"/>
                <p>The t¢ſticles of various anima3s are very variouſly com-poſed, but all in this
                    general manner of veſſels variouſly rolled and folded together: and even the
                    human teſticles are of the ſame fort ; being compoſed ſolely of rolls of
                    veſſels, without any intermediate ſubſtance, be it called by whatever name, but
                    only conſiſting of veſſels and their liquors.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
