<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-15-r01-0798-01" facs="gri_33125011197759_0806.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RAMSEY</label>
a town of Huntingdonſhire, 68 miles north of London, and 12 north-eaſt of Huntingdon. It is ſituated as it were in an iſland, being everywhere .encompaffed with fens, except on the weſt, where it is ſeparated from the <hi rend="italic">terra firma</hi> by a cauſey for two ■miles. The neighbouring meers of Ramſey and whitle-ſey, which are formed by the river Nyne, abound with fowl and fiſh, efpecially eel and large pikes. It was once famous for a very rich abbey, part of the gatehoufe of which is ſtill ſtanding, and a neglected ſtatue of Ail-win ; the epitaph of whoſe tomb, which is reckoned one of the oldeſt pieces of Engliſh ſculpture extant, ftylεs him " kinſman of the famous King Edward, alderman of all England, and the miraculous founder of this abbey.” It was dedicated to St Duriſtan, and its abbots were mitred, and fat in parliament ; and ſo ■many kings of England were benefactors to it, that its yearly rents, ſays Camden, were 70001. The town was then called <hi rend="italic">Ramſey the Rich ;</hi> but by the diſſolution of the abbey it foon became poor, and even loſt its market for many years, till about 185 years ago it recovered it. It is held on Saturday, and is reckoned one of the moſt plentiful and cheapeſt in England. In the year 1721 a great number of Roman coins was found here, ſuppoſed to have been hid by the monks on. ſome incurſion of the Danes. There is a charity ſchool in the town for poor girls. W. Long. o. 19. N. Lat. 52. 26.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsey, an iſland of ſouth wales, on the coaſt of Pembrokeſhire, about two miles in length, and a mile and a half broad. Near it are ſeveral ſmall ones, known by the name of the</hi> <hi rend="italic">biſhop and his clerks.</hi> It is four miles weſt of St David’s, and 17 north-weſt of Mil-ford haven. It belongs to the biſhopric of St Da-vid’s, and was in the laſt age, ſays Camden, famous for the death of one Juſtinian, a moſt holy man, who retiring hither from Britanny, in that age rich in ſaints, and devoting himſelf entirely to God, lived a long while in ſolitude, and being at laſt murdered by his fervant was enrolled among the martyrs. W. Long. 5. 20. N. Lat. 51. 55.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ramsey, in the Iſle of Man, to the north, a moſt</hi> noted and ſpaclous haven, in which the grcat¢ſt fleet may ride at anchor with ſafety enough from all winds but the north eaſt, and in that caſe they need not be embayed. This town ſtanding upon a beach of looſe fand, or ſhingle, is in danger, if not timely prevented, of being waſhed away by the fea.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>