<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0059-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0065.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RELIEF</label> <hi rend="italic">(Relevamen ;</hi> but, in Domefday, <hi rend="italic">Relevαtio, Relevium},</hi> ſignifies a certain ſum of money, which the tenant, holding by knight’s ſervice, grand ſerjeanty, or other tenure, (for which homage or legal ſervice is due), and being at full age at the death of his an-ceſtor, paid unto his lord at his entrance. See Pri-mer.</p><p>Though reliefs had their original while feuds were only life-eſtates, yet they continued after feuds became hereditary; and were therefore looked upon, very juſtly, as one of the greateſt grievances of tenure : eſpecially when, at the firſt, they were merely arbitrary and at the will of the lord ; ſo that, if he pleaſed to demand an exorbitant relief, it was in effect to diſinherit the heir. The Engliih ill brooked this conſequence of their new-adopted policy; and there-fore william the Conqueror by his laws <hi rend="italic">afcertained</hi> the relief, by directing (in imitation of the Daniſh he-riots), that a certain quantity of arms, and habiliments of war, ſhonld be paid by the earls, barons, and vavaſours refpectively ; and, if the latter had no arms, they ſhould pay 100s. william Rufus broke through this compoſition, and again demanded arbitrary un-certain reliefs, as due by the feodal laws ; thereby in effect obliging every heir to new-purchaſe or <hi rend="italic">redeem</hi> his land: but his brother Henry I. by the charter be-fore-mentioned, reſtored his father’s law ; and ordained, that the relief to be paid ſhould be according to the law ſo eſtabliſhed, and not an arbitrary redemption.—■ But afterwards, when, by an ordinance in 27 Hen. II. called the <hi rend="italic">afiſe oſ arms,</hi> it was provided, that every man’s armour ſhould deſcend to his heir, for defence of the realm, and it thereby became impracticable to pay theſe acknowledgments in arms according to the laws of the Conqueror, <hi rend="sup">1</hi> the compoſition was univer-fally accepted of 100 s. for every knight’s fee, as ws find it ever after eſtabliſhed. But it muſt be remem-bered, that this relief was only then payable, if the heir at the death of his anceſtor had attained his full age of 21 years.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To</hi> RELIEVE <hi rend="italic">the Guard,</hi> is to put freſh men upon guard, which is generally every 24 hours.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To Relieve the Trenches,</hi> is to relieve the guard of the trenches, by appointing thoſe for that duty who have been there before.</p><p><hi rend="italic">To Relieve the Sentries,</hi> is to put freſh men upon that duty from the guard, which is generally done every two hours, by a corporal who attends the relief, to ſee that the proper orders are delivered to the ſoldier who relieves.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>