<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0082-06" facs="gri_33125011196389_0088.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REPRIEVE</label>
in criminal law (from <hi rend="italic">reprendre,</hi> "to take back”), is the withdrawing of a ſentence for an interval of time ; whereby the execution is ſuſpended. See Judgment.</p><p>This may be, firſt, <hi rend="italic">ex</hi> <hi rend="italic">ar bitrio judicis,-either</hi> before or after judgment : as, where the judge is not ſatisfied with the verdict, or the evidence is fuſpicious, or the indictment is inſuſſicient, or he is doubtful whether the offence be within clergy ; or ſometimes if it be a ſmall felony, or any favourable circumſtances appear in the criminal’s character, in order to give room to apply to the crown for either an abſolute or conditional pardon. Theſe arbitrary reprieves may be granted or taken off by tlie juſtices of gaol-delivery, although their ſeſſion be finiſhed, and their commiſſion expired : but this ra-ther by common uſage than of ſtrict right.</p><p>Reprieves may alſo be <hi rend="italic">ex neceffitate legis :</hi> as wherc a woman is capitally convicted, and pleads her pregnancy. Though this is no cauſe to ſtay judgment, yet it is to reſpite the execution till ſhe be delivered. This is a mercy dictated by the law of nature, w <hi rend="italic">favorem pro-</hi> <hi rend="italic">lis ;</hi> and therefore no paît of the bloody proceedings in the reign of Queen Mary hath been more juſtly deteſted, than the cruelty that was exerciſed in the--iſland of</p><p>Guernſey, of burning a woman big with child j ' and,' when through the violence of the flames the infant ſprang forth at the ſtake, and was preſerved by the by-ſtanders, after ſome deliberations of the prieſts who aſſiſted at the facrifice, they caſt it into the fire as a young heretic. A barbarity which they newer learned from the laws of ancient Rome; which direct, with the ſame humanity as our own, <hi rend="italic">quod prœgnantis maliens damnatœ pcena cUJfèratur, quoad pariat :</hi> which doctrine, has alſo prevailed in England, as early as the firſt memorials of our law will reach. In caſe this plea be made in ſtay of execution, the judge muſt direct a jury of twelve matrons or dſſcreet women to inquire into the fact : and if they bring in their verdict <hi rend="italic">quick with child</hi> (ſor barely <hi rend="italic">with child,</hi> unleſs it bc alive in the womb, is not ſufficient), execution ſhall be ſtaid generally till the next ſeſſion ; and fo from ſeſſion to ſeſſion, till either ſhe is delivered, or proves by the courſe of nature not to have been with child at all. But if ſhe once hath had the benefit of this reprieve, and been delivered, and afterwards becomes pregnant again, ſhe ſhall not be intitled to the benefit of a farther refpite for that cauſe. For; ſhe may now be executed; before the child is quick in the womb ; and ſhall not, by her own incontinence, evade the ſentence of juſtice.</p><p>Another cauſe.of regular reprieve is, if the offender become <hi rend="italic">non compos</hi> between the judgment and the award of execution : for regularly, though a man be <hi rend="italic">compos</hi> when he commits a capital crime, yet if he becomes <hi rend="italic">non compos</hi> after, be ſhall not be indicted if after indictment, he ſhall not be convicted; if after conviction,, lie ſhall not receive judgment; if after judgment, he ſhall not be ordered for execution : for <hi rend="italic">furioβιs folo furore punit ur ;</hi> and the law knows not but he might have offered fome reaſon, if in his ſenſes, to have ftayed thefe. reſpectivc proceedings. It is therefore an invariable, rule, when any time intervenes between the attainder and the award of execution, to demand of the priſoner what he hath to allege why execution flιould not be awarded againſt him ; and, if he appears to be infane,, the judge in his diſcretion may and ought to reprieve, him. Ογ, the party may plead in bar of execution ; which plea may be either pregnancy, the king’s pardon, an act of grace, or diverfity of perfou, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> that he is not the ſame that was attainted, and the like. In this laſt caſe a jury ſhall be impanelled to try this collateral iſſue, namely, the identity of his perſon ; and nob whether guilty or innocent, ſor that has been decided before. And in theſe collateral iſſues the trial ſliall be <hi rend="italic">inftanter ;</hi> and no time allowed the priſoner to make his. defence or produce his witneffes, unleſs he will make oath that he is not the perfon attainted : neither ſhall-any peremptory challenges of the jury be allowed the priſoner, though formerly ſuch challenges were held to, be allowable whenever a man’s life was in queſtion. If neither pregnancy, inſanity, non-identity, nor other plea,, will avail to avoid the judgment, and ſtay the execution, conſequent thereupon, the laſt and ſureſt reſort. is in the king’s moſt gracious pardon ; the granting of which is-the moſt amiable prerogative of the crown. Sec the article Pardon.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>