<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>venteen volumes folio. Three volumes more were added by Sanderson after Rymer’s death. The whole were reprinted at the Hague in ten vols., 1739. They were abridged by Rapin in French, and inserted in Le Clerc’s <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque,</hi>  a translation of which was made by Stephen Whatley, and printed in four vols. 8vo, 1731. Rymer died on the Hth of December 1713, and was buried in the parish church of St Clement Danes. Some specimens of his poetry are preserved in the first volume of Mr Nichol's Select Collection Of Miscellaneous Poems, 1780.</p><p>RYNABAD, a small village of Hindustan, in the province of Bengal, and district of Jessore. For a long time rumours were circulated that extensive ruins existed in the Sunderbunds, and particularly in the vicinity of Rynabad. But though repeated investigations have been made, none have been discovered.</p><p>RYOTS, in the policy of Hindustan, the name by which the renters of land are distinguished. They hold their possessions by a lease, which may be considered as perpe-tual, and at a rate fixed by ancient surveys and valuations. This arrangement has been so long established, and accords so well with the ideas of the natives concerning the distinction of castes, and the functions allotted to each, that it has been invariably maintained in all the provinces subject either to Mahommedans or Europeans ; and to both it serves as the basis on which their whole system of finance is founded. Respecting the precise mode, however, in which the ryots held their possessions, there are many different opinions, for which we refer to Robertson’s Historical Disquisition concerning India.</p><p>RYSWICK, a village of the province of Holland, in tile circle of the Hague, and near that city, which is pleasantly situated, and contains some good country-houses and pleasure-gardens, and 1820 inhabitants. Near to it is the palace of Niewmburg, where was signed the general treaty of peace in 1697, which bears this name.</p><p>RZESZOW, a city of the Austrian province of Gallicia, and the capital of a circle which extends over 1782 square miles. It comprehends four cities, thirteen market-towns, and three hundred and thirty-three villages, with 251,500 inhabitants. The city stands on the river Wisloch, and contains 388 houses, with 4850 inhabitants. It has some trade in making linen and woollen goods, and some goldsmiths’ work.</p><p>Sor s, the eighteenth letter and fourteenth consonant</p><p>? of our alphabet. The sound of it is formed by driving the breath through a narrow passage between the palate and the tongue elevated near it, together with a motion of the lower jaw and teeth towards the upper, the lips being a little way open, with such a configuration of every part of the mouth and larynx as renders the voice somewhat sibilous and hissing. Its sound, however, varies ; being strong in some words, as <hi rend="italic">this, thus,</hi>  and soft in words which have a final <hi rend="italic">e,</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">muse, wise.</hi>  It is generally doubled at the end of words, by which they become hard and harsh, as in <hi rend="italic">hiss, loss.</hi>  In some words it is silent, as <hi rend="italic">isle, island, viscount.</hi></p><p>In abbreviation, S. stands for <hi rend="italic">societas</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">socius ;</hi>  as R. S. S. for <hi rend="italic">regiœ societatis socius,</hi>  fellow of the royal society. In medicinal prescriptions, S. A. signifies <hi rend="italic">secundum artem,</hi>  according to the rules of art. And in the notes of the ancients, S. stands for <hi rend="italic">Sextus ;</hi>  S. P. for <hi rend="italic">Spurius ;</hi>  S. C. for <hi rend="italic">senαtus consultum ;</hi>  S. P. Q. R. for <hi rend="italic">senatus populusque Romonus ; </hi>S. S. S. for <hi rend="italic">stratum superstratum,</hi>  one layer above another alternately ; S. V. B. E. E. Q. V. for <hi rend="italic">si vales bene est, ego quoque valeo,</hi>  a form used in Cicero’s time in the beginning of letters. Used as a numeral, S. anciently denoted seven ; in the Italian music, S. signifies <hi rend="italic">solo ;</hi>  and in books of navigation, S. stands for south, S. E. for south-east, S. W. for south-west, S. S. E. for south-south-east, S. S. W. for south-south-west, &amp;c.</p><p>SAADE, a town of the mountainous district of Yemen, in Arabia, and the most important in the district. It is the residence of an imam or chief, whose power is limited, and his territories small ; and he is often so hard pressed by his highland neighbours that he finds it difficult to maintain his ground. He imposes a duty on all goods passing from Yemen into the interior of Arabia, and from this source his revenue chiefly arises. It is 368 miles north-north-east of Mocha.</p><p>SAARBRUCK, a city of the Prussian government of</p><p>Treves, the capital of a circle of the same name, and 215 square miles in extent. It stands on the river Saar, over which is a bridge connecting it with the large suburb of St John’s. It is old and strongly built, and the suburb contains 1070 houses, with 6740 inhabitants, who .carry on some iron-works, and have barges navigating the river, which is navigable up to the bridge.</p><p>SAAR-LOUIS, a city of the Prussian government of Treves, and the capital of a circle of the same name, of 189 square miles in extent. It is situated on the river Saar, and celebrated for the strength of its fortifications, which were constructed by Vauban, under Louis XIV. It is well and regularly built, and contains three churches, 550 houses, and 5800 inhabitants, who are employed in iron-works, chiefly in making weapons. Long. 6.43. E. Lat. 49.14. N.</p><p>SAASA<hi rend="sub">1</hi> a village of Palestine, in the district which is said, on the authority of tradition, to have been the burial-place of Nimrod. It is forty miles north-west of Sarchad.</p><p>SAATZ, a city of the Austrian kingdom of Bohemia, the capital of a circle of the same name, which extends over 921 square miles, and contains 126,500 inhabitants. The river Eger rims by the town. It has a collegiate church, a gymnasium, and 640 houses, with 4180 inhabitants. Long. 14.10. E. Lat. 50. 18. 35. N.</p><p>SAAVEDRA, Michael de Cervantes, a celebrated Spanish writer, and the inimitable author of Don Quixote, was born at Madrid in the year 1541. From his infancy he was very fond of books ; but he applied himself wholly to books of entertainment, such as novels and poetry of all kinds, especially Spanish and Italian authors. From Spain he went to Italy, either to serve Cardinal Aquaviva, to whom he was chamberlain at Rome, or else to follow the profession of a soldier, as he did for some years under the victorious banners of Marco Antonio Colonna. He was present at the battle of Lepanto, in the year 1571 ; in which he cither lost his left hand by the shot of an harquebus, or had it so maimed that he lost the use of it. After this he</p></body></text></TEI>