<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Schools under the first head. Ditto under the second do... Ditto under the third do......</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Pupils.</p><p>.. 8,733... .. 2,224... .169,024...</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Annual Budget. Roubles.</p><p>......6,255,000</p><p>...... 632,194</p><p>......1,800,000</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total.........</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.179,981</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8,687,194</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Of these, 179,500 are supporte</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>:d by gover</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>∙nment.</p></cell></row></table><lb/><p>III. <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Schools.</hi>  There are numerous establishments of this nature in Russia, which, as relates to their management, are divided into two heads. The first comprehends the schools of the Greek Church, under the control of the holy synod, and directed by a special commission ; the second, the ecclesiastical schools belonging to other forms of worship, which schools are under the superintendence of the minister of the interior. All these schools are divided into three circuits or departments, viz. those of St Petersburg, Moscow, and Kief. Each district has a superior school, called the ecclesiastical academy ; with a certain number of intermediary schools or seminaries, for the most part established in the chief provincial towns, and of inferior schools, divided into district and parochial ones. These establishments are exclusively reserved for the children of the clergy, an arrangement exactly of a piece with the system practised in the common schools. In 1835 the ecclesiastical institutions stood thus :—</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Greek Church......................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Schools. .....384.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Pupils.</p><p>. ...58,586</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>United or pure Greek Church..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>..... 23.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.... 1,274</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Roman Catholic Church..........</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.....275.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.... 7,073</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Catholic Armenian Church......</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>..... 5.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>....    137</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Gregorian Armenian Church....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>..... 14.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>....    319</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total............</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.....701</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>67,389</p></cell></row></table><lb/><p>Of this number of pupils, 41,586 pay their own expenses, 10,517 receive pecuniary aid from government, and 15,408 are educated wholly at the expense of the state.</p><p>IV. <hi rend="italic">Various</hi><hi rend="italic">Schools.</hi>  The numerous establishments which are comprehended under this head are classified according to the different ministers, or members of the imperial family, who especially superintend them. 1. Under the minister of finance. These consist of mining schools, distributed into inferior, middle, and superior seminaries, where the art of mining is taught. They are situated at St Petersburg, and in the principal manufacturing and mining districts. They are organized on the same vicious principle as the others, being confined to the children of miners, as if talents for particular arts were hereditary in families. The total number of pupils in the mining schools is 4613, who are allowed for their support by government 647,911 roubles annually. Private individuals support similar establishments, at which there may be a thousand pupils more. There are ten other various kinds of schools under the minister of finance. The Practical Institution of Technology was founded in 1828, and intended to form master manufacturers. Two mercantile-marine schools, for forming pilots, were both established in 1829 at St Petersburg and Kherson. There are, besides, the Forest Institute, the Academy of Commerce at Moscow, the Agricultural School at Gorygoretsk, schools of land-surveying and design at Tchemigov, and two schools for forest sciences, all as yet in their infancy. They are attended by 608 pupils, which,</p><lb/><p>added to those attending the mine-schools, makes the num- ber of pupils in the schools of this class amount to 6221.<hi rend="sup"/>The annual budget is 1,032,191 roubles. 2. Schools under the minister of the interior. These are schools of medicine, surgery, and pharmacy, all independent of the university faculties ; rural schools for the cultivation of the vine, and for agriculture in general ; schools for the sons of persons employed in subaltern situations in public offices, who are supported by the state on condition of serving it eight years ; and schools for orphans and poor children. The establishments under the minister of the interior contain 13,340 pupils, of whom 10,500 are in the hospitals. 3. Under the minister of the emperor’s household are the Moscow Academy of the Fine Arts, Moscow School of Architecture, the Theatrical School of St Petersburg, and the Court School of Singers. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> These contain in all only about 345 pupils. 4. The minister of appanages has under him some schools of agriculture, and primary schools for the peasants, but containing only 1070 pupils. 5. Under the general direction of roads and communications is a school of civil engineers and conductors, containing 665 pupils. 6. Under the minister of justice are a school of jurisprudence, and another of land-surveying, to train youth for the exclusive service of government. These two establishments contain 350 pupils. 7. Under the foreign office is an oriental institution for qualifying individuals to act as diplomatic interpreters in the Asiatic tongues. 8. Institutions under the reigning empress, comprehending the foundling hospitals of Moscow and St Petersburg, the boarding-schools for young ladies at St Petersburg, Moscow, and Odessa, which contain 52,912 pupils. The empress has further under her control several patriotic establishments, mostly appropriated to the education of children of indigent or invalid officers. In all they contain 1122 pupils. There are also a number of benevolent institutions, such as houses of industry, establishments for the deaf and dumb, the blind, and others. 9. The Archduchess Helena superintends a number of educational institutions, established in different provincial towns, and managed by the local authorities. 10. There remain to be added to the above a number of schools which are supported without any assistance from government. All the foregoing derive considerable pecuniary aid from that source. There are four German schools at St Petersburg, and 750 in the German colonies, having in all 35,746. In the same provinces are 561 Tartar schools, with 14,000 pupils ; and there are two Jewish schools, with 500 pupils. At Omsk, Cossack and Asiatic schools have been instituted. The latter are intended to supply interpreters to all the frontier line of Siberia.</p><p>The following is M. de Krusenstern's estimate of the establishments of education throughout the Russian empire :</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Pupils.</p><p>The ministry of public instruction 85,707..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Money suppiie by Governmen</p><p>Roubles.</p><p>....7,450,000</p><p>.....8,687,194</p><p>.....3,000,000</p><p>.....9,596,947</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Military schools...................</p><p>Ecclesiastical schools............</p><p>Divers schools......................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... .179,981.. ... 67,024.. ....127,864.,</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total...</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...460,576</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>28,734,141</p></cell></row></table><p>This upon a population of 48,000,000, exclusively of the Asiatic population, gives about one pupil for every 104</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Travellers have remarked, that the Russians possess a singular aptitude for music ; and Reicha, a very eminent musician, particularly notices the admirable accuracy with which the vocal music is performed in the churches, without the aid of any instrumental accompaniment. But in Russia the music of the church, the theatre, the concert∙room, and the chamber, has been chiefly indebted for its progress to Italian and German musicians, though the native music and musical instruments of Russia are sufficiently interesting to deserve much more consideration than has hitherto been bestowed upon them. The occurrence of popular airs in Finland in the unusual measure of is vouched by continental writers. In the interior of Russia, there appear to be many native airs of an uncommon character in respect of melody and tonality. The celebrated Russian horn-music, though very remarkable in its kind, must be considered as of foreign introduction, and as the result of great musical aptitude, and of most careful and laborious training. About the middle of the eighteenth century, J. A. Maresch, a Bohemian, and a very skilful horn-player, who was settled at St Petersburg, invented there the famous Russian horn-music. For a brief account of it, see the Appendix to Graham’s Essay on Musical Composition; and for minute details regarding the notation and the mode of performance of this kind of music, consult J. C. Heinrich’s work,<hi rend="italic">Enlttehung, Fortgang nndjetzige Rctchaffenhcit dcr Russischen Jagdmusik,</hi>  published at St Petersburg in 1796.</p></body></text></TEI>