<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by the Russians under Generals Podhorilshany and Potemkin, near Fokshany. The town of Shursha was taken by Lieutenant-General Von Stoffeln, February 4. A Russian fleet appeared in the port of Maina, in the Morea<hi rend="sub">1</hi> on the 17th February. Mistra, the Lacedæmon of the ancients, and several other towns of the Morea, were taken in February. Arcadira in Greece surrendered, and a multitude of Turks were made prisoncrs, in the same month. The Turks and Tartars were driven from their intrenchrnents near the Pruth, by Count Romantzof, Prince Repnin, and General Bauer, 11th—16th June. Prince Prosorofskoi gained several advantages near Otchakof, June 18. The Russian fleet, under Count Alexei Orlof, gained a complete victory over the Turks near Tschesme, 24th June ; the consequence of this victory was the destruction of the whole Turkish fleet, near Tschesme<hi rend="sub">1</hi> where it was burned by Admiral Greigon the 26th of June. A battle was fought on the Kagul, in which Count Romantzof defeated the Turkish army, consisting of a hundred and fifty thousand men, and took their camp, and all the artillery, July 21. The fortress Bender was taken July 22. The town of Ismail was taken by Prince Repnin, July 26 ; Kilia by Prince Repnin, August 21 ; and Akjerman in October. Brailof was taken on the IOth of November 1771 ; the town of Kaffia, June 29 ; and numberless other victories were obtained by sea and land, till peace was concluded on the 13th January 1775. By this the Crimea was declared independent of the Porte, and all the vast tract of country between the Bog and Dnieper was ceded to Russia, besides the Kuban and the isle of Taman, with free navigation in all the Turkish seas, including the passage of the Dardanelles, privileges granted to the most favoured nations, and stipulations in behalf of the inhabitants of Moldavia and Wallachia.</p><p>In 1779, the empress intending to divide the empire in-fto viceroyalties, began in January with the viceroyalty of <hi rend="sup">i</hi> Orlof. March 21st, a new treaty was signed at Constantinople between Russia and the P<hi rend="sup">i</hi>orte. May 13th, the treaty of peace between the belligerent powers in Germany and the French king was signed under the mediation of her majesty. In October, a ship built at Taganrog, named the Prince Constantine, sailed to Smyrna with Russian commodities. December 3d, the viceroyalty of Voronetsk was instituted ; and the 27th, Count Romantzof Zadunaiski</p><p>opened the viceroyalty of Kursk with great solemnity.</p><p>In 1780, February 28th, appeared the memorable declaration of her imperial majesty, relating to the safety of navigation and commerce of the neutral powers. In 1781,</p><p><hi rend="sup">,</hi> March 1 st, the empress became mediatrix between England and Holland ; April 5th, instituted the first public school in St Petersburg.</p><p>In 1782, by a command of her majesty,, dated January the 18th, a Roman Catholic archbishop was installed in the city of Mohilef, with authority over all the Catholic churches and convents in the Russian empire. August 7th, the famous equestrian statue of Peterthe Great, being finished, was uncovered to the public in presence of the empress, on which occasion she published a proclamation containing pardons for several criminals. November 22d, the order of St Vladimir was instituted. The 27th, the empress published a new tariff.</p><p>In 1783, May 7th, the empress instituted a seminary for ■ the education of young persons of quality at Kursk. June 2lst, a treaty of commerce was concluded with the Otto-<hi rend="sup">1</hi>man Porte. July, the institution of the other viceroyalties of the empire followed in succession. On July 2lst, the empress published a manifesto by her commander-in-chief Prince Potemkin, in the Krim, in regard to the taking possession of that peninsula, the Kuban, and the island of Taman. The 24th, a treaty was concluded with Heraclius II. czar of Kartalinia and Kachetti, by which he submitted himself, his heirs and successors for ever, with his territories and dominions, to the sceptre of her majesty, her heirs and successors. On the 29th, accounts were received from the camp of Prince Potemkin, at Karas-Basar, that the clergy, the beys, and other persons of distinction, with the towns of Karas-Basar, Bachtshiserai, Achmetchet, Kaffa, Kosloff, with the districts of Turkanskoikut and Neubasar, and that of Perekop, in the peninsula of the Krim, together with the hordes of Edissank and Dshambolusk, the sultan Alim Giray, and his vassals, with all the Budshaks and Bashkirs there, and all the tribes dwelling beyond the river Kuban, the sultan Boatur Giray and his vassals, took the oath of allegiance to her imperial majesty, and with willing hearts submitted for ever to her glorious sway. On the 30th the hospodar of Wallachia was deposed, and Draco Sutzo set up in his place. September 22d, her majesty raised Gabriel, archbishop of Novgorod and St Petersburg, to the dignity of metropolitan. October 21st, in the great hall of the Academy of Sciences, the new institution of the Imperial Russian Academy was opened, after a most solemn consecration by the metropolitan Gabriel, and others of the clergy, under the presidency of the Princess DashkofE November 7th, the empress became mediatrix for accommodating the differences between the king of Prussia and tile city of Dantzig. The school for surgery was opened at St Petersburg on the 18th. December 13th, a school commission was instituted for superintending all the public schools. On the 28th, an act was concluded with the Ottoman Porte, by which the possession and sovereignty of the Krim, the Kuban, and Taman, were solemnly made over to the empress.</p><p>1784.    January 1st, the senate, in a speech by Field-Marshal Count Razomofskoi, performed the ceremony, repeated annually, of most humbly thanking her majesty for the benefactions which she had graciously bestowed on the whole empire in the preceding year. October 14th, the Lesgiers, having crossed the river Alasan, and invaded the dominions of Georgia, were repulsed with great loss by a detachment of Russian troops. December 29th, Katolikos Maksim, the serdar and court-marshal Prince Zeretelli, and the chief justice Kuinichese, ambassadors from David, czar of Imeretia, were admitted to a public audience of her majesty, at which they submitted, in the name of the czar, him and his subjects to the will and powerful protection of her imperial majesty, as the rightful head of all the sons of the orthodox eastern church, and sovereign ruler and defender of the Georgian nations.</p><p>1785.    The 12th of January, Maurocordato<hi rend="sub">1</hi> hospodar of Wallachia, was deposed, and Alexander Maurocordato, his uncle, restored to that dignity. The 21st, the empress visited the principal national school, and passed a long time in examining the classes, and the proficiency of the youth in that seminary ; on which occasion a marble tablet was fixed in the wall of the fourth class, with this inscription, in gold letters : Thou visitest the vineyard which THlNE <hi rend="smallcaps">own hand hath planted. April 2lst, the privileges of the nobility were confirmed, and on the same day the burghers of towns constituted into bodies corporate, by a particular manifesto. The public school in Voronetsk was opened. July !4th, a manifesto was issued, granting full liberty of religion and commerce to all foreigners settling in the regions of Mount Caucasus, under the Russian government. September l5th, the public school at Nishnei Novgorod was opened. October 12th, the Jesuits in White Russia, in a general assembly, elected a vicar-general of their order. November 1st, a treaty of commerce was concluded with the emperor of Germany. The 24th, the Russian consul in Alexandria made his public entry on horseback, an honour never before granted to any power ; erected the imperial standard on his house, with discharge of cannon, &amp;c. December 28th, a Russian mercantile frigate, fully freighted, arrived at Leghorn from Constantinople.</hi></p></body></text></TEI>