<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Great Britain. The expense of the navy, like that of the</p><p>army, is comparatively small. “ Indeed,” says Mr Bremner,</p><p>“ it is one of the points which should never be forgotten in considering this question” [viz. the maintenance of such a large fleet], “ that Russia can not only build ships cheaper than any other European power, but can also man them for less. The pay both of officers and men is so small, that the annual outlay on twenty Russian line-of-battle ships would not defray the expense of ten of ours.” The Russian sailor is brave, well-trained, somewhat after a military fashion, and submissive ; but he wants the activity and enthusiasm of the English seaman. To remedy a great defect under which the Russian navy has long laboured, a want of good native officers, colleges of naval cadets have been formed, where young Russians are carefully trained for the higher branches of the service.</p><p>- Ten or fifteen years ago the agricultural operations of the</p><p>Russians were conducted in a very clumsy manner. Rotation of crops was little understood or practised, and husbandry in general was carried on in a very ignorant and unprofitable manner. In the Ukraine, so famous for its fertility, the mode of farming is very simple. They take as many crops out of the ground as it will yield, and then let it lie fallow for a year or two. But this branch of productive industry has made considerable progress within these few years ; partly through the exertions of government, and partly through those of the landed proprietors, who find it for their advantage to approximate to those improved methods of cultivating the soil which are practised in most other parts of Europe. Amongst other means employed by government for encouraging agriculture, it has ordered what are called model-gardens to be formed in a number of governments. Native manufactures have likewise been greatly extended and improved.</p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="4" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">State of the Manufactures of Russia in</hi>  1831.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Value of the Produce (estimated in roubles) of</p></cell><cell cols="2" rows="2"><p>Increase since 1821.</p><p>...230 per cent</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Cotton manufacture..........</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>104,170,481..</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Silk ditto.......................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>16,131,373..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 25</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Woollen ditto.................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>50,000,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 30</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Flax and hemp...............</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>22,615,940..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 45</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Leather........................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>97,213,710..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 12</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Paper..........................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6,468,968..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 10</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Hats............................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,801,900..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 63</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Dyes and colours.............</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,000,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 55</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Tobacco and snuff...........</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>19,623,494..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...150</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Refined sugar.................</p><p>Soap............................</p><p>Tallow candles................</p><p>Snuff-boxes, and different </p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>23,007,004.. 6,591,690.. 8,095,584..</p><p>2,000,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>... 34 ...131</p><p>... 62</p><p>... 0</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>kinds of japanned goods </p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>∙∙∙</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Chemical preparations.......</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3,000,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 11</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>China and earthenware.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4,000,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.... 0</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Glass and crystal.............</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9,000,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.... 11</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Potash..........................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6,000,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>... 32</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">Metallic Produce.</hi></p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Gold..........................</p><p>Silver........................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>25,905,680..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5</p><p>3</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Copper.........................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9,620,736..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.... 13</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Wrought iron and steel... Cast iron.....................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>38,828,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>9</p><p>26</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Sundry minerals..............</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>500,000..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.... 94</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>...</p></cell></row></table><p>The whole amount of the above produce is 509,574,379 roubles. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Russia, which formerly imported nothing but manufactured goods, now imports immense quantities of</p><lb/><p>raw material for the use of her manufactures, as will be seen from our table of the imports ; and the amount is yearly on the increase. In 1815 the total number of manufacturing establishments throughout the empire was estimated at 3250, at which 150,000 workmen were employed. In 1836 the number of manufacturing establishments in activity was 6045, which gave employment to 279,673 workmen. The financial agents of Russia residing at Paris, Vienna, and Berlin, as well as the consuls at the chief commercial towns of Europe, have instructions to contribute to the progress and improvement of national industry, by communicating to Russian manufacturers every information respecting new inventions made in foreign countries, forwarding to them patterns of new manufactures, models of machines, and the like, and by engaging expert workmen for them. Government holds out the greatest encouragement to persons engaging in new commercial enterprises. By a ukase dated 1827, such parties are relieved from certain taxes imposed upon them as members of one of the three city guilds, and in 1835 the land-tax and municipal imposts were also remitted in their favour. A further evidence of the advance which Russia has made in commercial enterprise is furnished by the fact, that the number of persons engaged in such pursuits is rapidly increasing, and that every year many acquire the means of passing from the inferior to the upper guilds. The following statement will make this clear.</p><p>   More than</p><p><hi rend="sup">1835</hi>∙    in 1834.</p><p>Merchants of the first guild............. 695...... 50</p><p>Ditto of the second....................... 1,547...... 56</p><p>Ditto of the third.........................30,099......1,147</p><p>Peasantshavingpermissiontotrade... 4,992...... 388</p><p>Clerks....................................... 7,976...... 831</p><p>In 1836 thirty-five applications were made for    patents for</p><p>new inventions connected with manufactures, of which eleven were granted.</p><p>The distillation of brandy is the most extensive and lu- crative branch of the productive industry of Russia. This article is produced to the amount of 270,000,000 roubles annually, for which government receives an excise duty of 90,000,000 roubles. The brandy monopoly of government is productive of great mischief, as by the universal system of bribery the cost to the consumer is greatly increased. The farmer-general bribes the governor of the province, whose duty it is to see that the article is not adulterated ; the farmer-general, and his secretary who grants licenses, are bribed by the retailer, so that by the time the spirit has reached the tables of the peasantry, amongst whom the use of it is universal, one gallon has multiplied itself to three or even four. A kind of beer called <hi rend="italic">braga</hi>  is likewise made to a great extent, and largely consumed.</p><p>The mines, particularly those on the Ural Mountains, were worked at a very ancient period ; but it is only in modern times that the Russians have applied themselves to that branch of industry. Gold, platina, silver, and copper, are most abundant in the Asiatic governments, or along the last declivities of what is called the great central ridge. The quantities of gold and platina produced will be seen from a table at the end of the exports and imports.</p><p>The silver mines yield annually about 43,200 lbs., besides 1,440,000 lbs. of lead. The aggregate produce of copper from the government and private mines is 7,596,000 lbs. English. By a document published in the Russian Mining Journal for 1830, we find that there were in the Ural districts alone fifty-eight smelting works (seven belonging to the crown and fifty-one to individuals), which in 1827 produced 9,731,147 poods of cast iron. The forges, which</p><lb/><p>@@@ The above official returns are taken from a work of M. Prelezynski, on the State of the Manufacturing Powers of Russia, published in Russian at St Petersburg in 1833.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>