<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>met near the small river Kalka, which flows into the Sea of Azof, and a furious engagement took place, ending in the complete overthrow of the Russians and their allies.</p><p>About thirteen years after this defeat, another horde of Tartars, headed by Baaty Khan, the grandson of Tschinghis Khan, penetrated into Russia, after having attacked and defeated their neighbours the Bulgarians. The invaders soon spread far and wide the terror of their name. Wherever they came, the whole face <hi rend="italic">of</hi>  nature was laid waste ; towns and villages were destroyed by fire ; all the men capable of bearing arms were put to the sword, and the children, women, and old men, carried into captivity. If the inhabitants of the towns to which they approached offered a compromise, the faithless barbarians affected to receivc their submission, but immediately broke the agreement, anc treated those who surrendered to their mercy with as much rigour as those who had endeavoured to defend themselves and had been overcome. If the inhabitants of the open towns and villages came out to meet them, and to receive them as conquerors and friends, death, torture, or the most ignominious bondage, was the reward of their spontaneous submission.</p><p>The first state which the Tartars attacked was Riazan, the prince of which applied for assistance to Yury, commonly called by historians George Vsevolodovitch, grand prince of VOadimir. He sent them a few auxiliaries, but these either came too late, or their number was too small. The principality of Riazan fell, and its fall was succeeded by that of PereiaslavI, Rostof, Susdal, and several others. Like a furious torrent rushing down the mountain side, and irresistibly bearing with it all that impedes its progress, these barbarous hordes poured rapidly along, sweeping all before them in one common devastation. They now approached the principality of Vladimir, and no army appeared to resist them upon the frontiers. They advanced unimpeded to the capital, which, left to its fate by the grand prince, had nothing to expect but the same cruel treatment which the neighbouring cities had received. Yury, with unpardonable negligence, was celebrating a marriage feast, when he ought to have been employed in collecting the means of defence against the enemy, of whose approach to his borders he had received timely intimation. The city of Vladimir, which contained the princess and two of her sons, was left to the protection of a chieftain totally unqualified for its defence ; and the inhabitants seemed to share in the pusillanimity of their governor. Instead of annoying the enemy by occasional excursions, and preparing the means of defending the walls against a sudden attack, they gave themselves up to terror and despair ; and as they conceived death to be inevitable, they prepared for it, by taking the habits of monks and nuns, in order to insure to themselves a blissful departure. A prey to fear and despondency, the city soon fell into the hands of the Tartars. They one morning scaled the walls, and meeting with little opposition, quickly made themselves masters of the place, when they cast aside every feeling of humanity, and, like beasts of prey, glutted their appetite for blood amongst the wretched inhabitants. The grand princess, and other ladies of distinction, dreading the brutality of the relentless conquerors, had taken refuge in the choir of a church, an asylum which all the assurances of the Tartars that they should suffer no injury could not prevail on them to abandon. It was therefore set on fire by the barbarians, who feasted their ears with the shrieks and groans of the women as the flames surrounded them.</p><p>V ury, incensed almost to desperation at the fate of his capital, and the horrible death of his wife and children, was determined to take signal vengeance on the assailants. He assembled all the forces which he could draw together; and though his army was greatly inferior in number to the Iartars, he marched against the enemy, and attacked them</p><p>with the most determined valour. The struggle was short but bloody. The Tartars were victorious, and the body of Yury was found amongst the slain.</p><p>This appears to have been the only vigorous stand made by the Russian princes. The Tartars pushed forward with rapidity, and successively overpowered the principalities of Novgorod and Kief. In the latter city they found immense booty ; but this circumstance did not prevent them from repeating here the same bloody scenes which they had acted in the other capitals. The governor was preserved from the cruelties that had been inflicted upon the inhabitants, by the courage he had displayed in defence of the city; and his noble demeanour, when he fell into the hands of the conqueror, acquiring the esteem and affection of that chief, enabled him to obtain a temporary repose to his country.</p><p>The Tartars had now established themselves in the Russian territories, and their khan or chief, though he did not himself assume the nominal sovereignty, reigned as paramount lord, and placed on the throne any of the native &lt; princes whom he found most obsequious to his will, or who had ingratiated themselves by the magnificence of their presents. Till the middle of the fourteenth century, the throne was successively occupied by Yaroslaf II., Alexander Yaroslavitch called Saint Alexander Neffsky, Yaroslaf Yaroslavitch, Vasilii Yaroslavitch<hi rend="sub">1</hi> Dimitri Alexandrovitch<hi rend="sub">1 </hi>Andrei, Daniil, both brothers of Dimitri, Mikaila Yarosla-vitch, Yury Danilovitch, Alexander Mikailovitch, Ivan Danilovitch, Simeon Ivanovitch, and Ivan Ivanovitch.</p><p>During these several reigns, the miseries of a foreign yoke were aggravated by all the calamities of intestine discord and war ; whilst the knights of Livonia, or Brothers of the Short Sword, as they are sometimes called, a kind of military order of religious, on one side, and the Poles on the other, catching at the opportunity, and attacking Russia, took several of its towns, and even some considerable countries. The Tartars and Russians, whose interests were in this case the same, often united to oppose their common enemy ; but they were generally worsted. The Livonians took Pleskow, and the Poles made themselves masters of Black Russia, the Ukraine, Podolia, and the city of Kief. Casimir the Great, one of their kings, carried his conquests still farther. He asserted his pretensions to a part of Russia, in right of his relation to Boleslas, duke of Kalitz, who died without issue, and forcibly possessed himself of the duchies of Perzesmylia, Kalitz, and Luckow, with the districts of Sanock, Lubakzow, and Trebowla ; of all which countries he made a province of Poland.</p><p>The newly-conquered Russians were ill disposed to endure the government of the Poles, whose law's and customs were more contrary to their own than those of the Tartars had been. They joined the latter to rid themselves of the yoke, and assembled an army numerous enough to overwhelm all Poland, but destitute of valour and discipline. Casimir, undaunted by this deluge of barbarians, presented himself at the head of a few troops on the borders of the Vistula, and obliged his enemies to retire.</p><p>About the year 1362 Dimitri Ivanovitch received the sovereignty from the Tartar chief, and established the seat of his government at Moscow. This prince possessed considerable ambition, and contrived to inspire the other Russian princes with so much respect for his person and government, that they consented to hold their principalities as fiefs under Dimitri. This increased the consequence of the Russian prince, and excited the jealousy of Mammai the Tartar khan, who determined to take measures for maintaining his superiority. He began by demanding an increase of tribute ; but when Dimitri demurred to this new encroachment, the khan not only insisted on his demand, but required the grand prince to appear before him in person. This requisition Dimitri thought proper to refuse,</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>