<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>amounted to 105 (only eight of them being crown property), sent into the markets in the same year 5,578,474 poods of wrought iron. We learn, from the same source, that the steel manufactured in all the empire in 1829 amounted only to 80,000 poods.</p><p>Another branch of industry to which the attention of tile Russian government has been for some time directed, has originated in the discovery of precious stones in the Ural Mountains. Stones of great value have from time to time been detected in that range, and scientific individuals have been employed to make researches for the purpose of obtaining extensive and accurate knowledge of these hidden treasures. Diamonds have likewise been found in the auriferous sands of the Ural. But to what amount annually any of these precious stones may be collected is still uncertain.</p><p>The mines of Finland, particularly those of iron, are also an important branch of productive industry. Some of the hills of that country contain veins of an ore fit for the manufacture of wrought iron, while layers of a fusible ore are found buried at a small depth, in marshes and along the borders of lakes. For a long time the mines of the first description were neglected ; but there are thirteen now at work. The richest ore, produced from the mines of the Gamnholm and Oiama, contains from fifty-three to fifty-four per cent, of metal ; the poorest yields about thirty per cent, of cast iron. The smelting of these ores is performed in eight different furnaces, which consume more ore than Finland can at present furnish ; and the deficit is supplied by Sweden. Almost the whole of the cast iron produced by them is distributed among the forges established in different parts of the country. There are sixteen of these forges, which manufacture annually about 121,350 poods of wrought iron. Those immense beds of iron ore which extend throughout the country, along the shores of lakes, and at the bottom of marshes, have been wrought from time immemorial. The number of forges and smelting-houses for working up this product is considerable ; and as experience has proved that the marsh ore is preferable to any other, several other establishments of forges have recently been erected, and more are in the course of being added to the number. Next to iron, copper is the most important mineral which Finland produces. Until very lately, however, only one mine was wrought, that of Ovi-Yervi, discovered in 1758. But a patent was a short time ago obtained for the working of copper and tin mines found near Nitkaranda. Iron of the best quality is likewise found in the district of Toula, the seat of the iron manufactures. Russia possesses another treasure in the numerous salt-lakes and marshes in the Siberian steppes, and in the country to the north of the Caspian Sea. The quantity of this article obtained throughout the empire amounts to 22,000,000 poods annually. Alum is also produced to the yearly extent of 16,000 poods.</p><p>“ A prodigious quantity of fish,” says M. Schnitzler, “ is supplied by the rivers and lakes, constituting almost the sole food of the population of extensive districts, and during the long Lents replacing the use of meat. The fisheries of the Volga and the Oka are particularly productive. Without speaking of the carp, the pike, the trout, the herring, especially that species of herring termed rei-<hi rend="italic">Pouchhf</hi>  and of the pilchard, I shall cite the sturgeon, beluga, and salmon fisheries, and the pickled lampreys and mackerel of the Crimea. The sterlet of the Volga is a variety of the sturgeon. Caviare, the consumption of which is so great in Russia, is made from the eggs of this fish, and from those of the beluga. A single sterlet will give from ten to thirty pounds weight ; and from a single beluga there may at times, it is said, be taken as much as 120 pounds. The best caviare comes from the Cossacks of the Ural. The sturgeon fishery is usually of considerable value ; 1,850,500 fish of this species, caught in the year 1793 in the Volga, near Astracan, yielded 124,970 poods of caviare, 3575 poods of isinglass. The coasts, which are visited by the cachalot, the whale, and other cetaceous fish, and on which are collected a quantity of pearl-oysters and mussels, likewise furnish cod and herrings. The largest fishery of the latter is in the Sea of Kamtschatka. The net annual value of the Russian fisheries amounts to more than 10,000,000 roubles.” The chase in the Russo-North American colonies, and elsewhere, has long been a profitable branch of national enterprise. Greatquantities of furs and skins, of the otter, beaver, and fox, are annually brought to market by the traders.</p><p>The internal traffic carried on in Russia is very considerable, and yearly upon the increase. The exchange of agricultural produce, as well as of manufactures, is immense. Nineteen fairs have been established for the benefit of trade in several principal towns of the empire, and thirteen in lesser ones. A great number of bazaars have likewise been erected for the accommodation of traders. The great centre of the inland commerce of Russia is Niz-nei-Novgorod, the annual fair at which place is entitled, both from the amount and variety of its articles, to be considered as the first in Europe, perhaps in the world. The trade consists chiefly of three branches ; namely, that of goods brought from Asia, Russian manufactures, and merchandise from Europe and America. The Asiatic trade consists principally of tea from China, of which article immense quantities are annually brought to this great emporium. Russian manufactures form the most important branch of the trade of Niznei-Novgorod, and consist chiefly of cotton, silk, and woollen goods brought from the central provinces of the empire. The merchants of Kiakhta carry back large quantities of cotton and skins ; those of Bukharia and of Khiva purchase nankeens, calicoes, cambrics, cloth, and sugar ; the Armenians and the Persians buy cotton and woollen stufis. Russian and Polish cloths are sent to this market in considerable quantities, part of which are sold to the Transcaucasian provinces, and some are even exported to China.</p><p>The produce of the Russian mines and Ifounderies forms also a considerable item of trade, consisting; of iron, copper, and steel articles from Toula, and which are bought for the use of the inhabitants of the interior. Sugsn is sent from St Petersburg and Archangel. Much country produce is sold for the purpose of exportation ; such as wax, wool, cotton, camel-hair, hemp, feathers, and Russian leather. The superb furs of Siberia and the coast of the White Sea form also most important objects of commerce. There is likewise a smaller trade in earthenware, glass, and soap. The third branch of the commerce of Niznei-Novgorod is the produce of Western Europe and its colonies ; but the amount of goods imported from these countries is scarcely one tenth of' the merchandise sold at the fair. It consists of indigo, cochineal, and madder, used for the purpose of dyeing manufactures. Foreign wines form also an important article of trade. Coffee and rum are imported from the West Indies ; coral is also imported and sold, chiefly to Kiakhta merchants for the Chinese markets. Foreign manufactures, consisting of silks, cotton, and woollen stuffs, are likewise sold in very considerable quantities. The value of the goods which change hands at this fair, according to Klaproth, amounts to ninety-four millions of roubles annually. Dr Lyall and Captain Cochrane raise it to double this sum ; but the statement of Lord Londonderry is more to be relied upon. He says that the value of goods actually sold amounted in 1831 to 98,329,525, in 1833 to 117,210,676, and in 1835 to 117,743,300 roubles. A great deal more merchandise than is sold is always brought to market. It is supposed that this fair is visited by about ISO<hi rend="sub">j</hi>OOOstrangers. The confluence of traders from such remote countries as those mentioned is one of the most striking and picturesque spectacles that can be witnessed. The fair lasts during the months of Augustand September. By the official account of the minister of the interior, the value of merchandise sold</p></body></text></TEI>