<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>wards resumed his historical labours, which were occasionally interrupted by his love of poetry. In the year 1783 he published “ The Tragic Muse,” a poem addressed to Mrs Siddons. To address verses to a player has been considered as beneath the dignity of the literary character. It would be a crime, said a periodical writer, to sacrifice genius on such an uninteresting occasion : we have more dignified subjects for the poetic Muse than an individual whose excellence is only a dazzling meteor, and must be forgotten in a few years at most. Players have sometimes been extravagantly extolled, particularly by grateful or aspiring poets who have written for the stage, and it will doubtless be granted that a poet may easily find a more dignified theme: but supreme excellence in any ingenious art seems to be no improper subject of panegyric; and so rare and difficult are the fleeting attainments of a great actor, that it may be considered as a generous exertion of poetic talent to rescue</p><p>them from oblivion.</p><p>The three volumes which completed the History of Modern Europe made their appearance in 1784. From the manuscript notices to which we have already referred, it appears that in the composition of each of these five volumes he spent about twelve months. This work, which is the chief foundation of his reputation, possesses great merit as a popular view of a very extensive period of history. The author displays no inconsiderable judgment in the selection of his leading incidents, and in the general arrangement of his materials; and he seems to have studied the philosophy of history with assiduity and success. His narrative is always free from languor; and his reflections are conveyed in a lively and elegant style. It is however to be regretted that he should have adopted the useless expedient of exhibiting his work as a series of letters from a nobleman to his son: every reader is sufficiently aware that Dr Russell did not belong to the order of nobility; and the frequent recurrence of “ my dear Philip,” is too apt to remind us of Lord Chesterfield. This work has very often been reprinted, and it still continues to maintain its original popularity. Russell closes his history with the peace of Paris in 1763. A continuation, extending to two volumes, was added by the late Dr Coote; and another writer has continued the narrative to the death of William the Fourth.</p><p>In the year 1787 he married Isabella Scott, a lady of Eskdale, to whom he had long been attached, and in whom he found a pleasant and intelligent companion. He now entered upon the occupation of a comfortable farm at Knottyholm, in the parish of Canonby and county of Dumfries. He fixed his residence in an elegant cottage, delightfully placed on the brink of the Esk, and at the distance of about five miles from the town of Langholm. This may well be described as “ a land of brooks of water, of fountains and depths that spring out of valleys and hills.” A more beautiful tract of pastoral country than that which extends for about twelve miles along the banks of the river, it would not perhaps be very easy to mention. Here he spent the remainder of his days. In this neighbourhood there were several intelligent individuals, with whom he lived in habits of intimacy. Of these the most conspicuous was the late Mr Maxwell, who was eminently distinguished for his scientific skill in music. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>He had now acquired the reputation of a very popular historian; and in 1792 the university of St Andrews conferred upon him the degree of LL. D. Academical honours have sometimes been more unworthily bestowed. The very favourable reception of his last publication had induced him to retrace his steps; and during the following year he published at London, in two volumes octavo, “ The History of Ancient Europe; with a View of the Revolutions in Asia and Africa. In a Series of Letters to a young Nobleman.” In the composition of this work, he professes to have been peculiarly studious to found his facts on original authorities, and to clear the narrative of unimportant events. He seems however to have allotted too many of his pages to the poetical details of the Trojan war. This production partakes of the peculiar merits of his modern history; but as the author did not live to complete his design, it never attained to the same popularity. Of these two volumes, the greater proportion relates to the history of Greece ; and the same ground has recently been trodden by Dr Gillies and Mr Mitford. Dr Coote, having afterwards been induced to supply what he had left deficient, published “ The History of Ancient Europe; in a Series of Letters from a Gentleman to his Son: intended as an accompaniment to Dr Russell’s History of Modern Europe.” Lond. 1815, 3 vols. 8vo.</p><p>Dr Russell did not long survive the publication of his last work. A stroke of palsy suddenly terminated his life, on the 25th of December 1793, after he had completed the fifty-second year of his age. His remains were interred in Westerkirk churchyard, where a plain mural stone distinguishes his grave. He left a widow, who died a few years ago, and an only child, a daughter, who still survives, and continues to reside at Knottyholm.</p><p>He had engaged in various projects which he did not live to execute. Besides two complete tragedies, entitled Zenobia and Pyrrhus, he left in manuscript “ An Analysis of Bryant’s Ancient Mythology,” and the following unfinished productions. 1. The Earl of Strafford, a tragedy. 2. Modern Life, a comedy. 3. The Love-Marriage, an opera. 4. Human Happiness, a poem, intended to have been completed in four books. 5. An Historical and Philosophical View of the Progress of Mankind in the Knowledge of the Terraqueous Globe. 6. The History of Modern Europe, part iii. from the peace of Paris in 1763, to the general pacification in 1783, including an Account of the American War, and of the European Transactions in the East Indies. In a Series of Letters from a Nobleman to his Son. 7. The History of England from the beginning of the reign of George III. to the conclusion of the American War. In the composition of the last of these works Dr Russell was engaged at the close of his life. It was to be comprised in three volumes octavo; for the copyright of which Mr Cadell had stipulated to pay him seven hundred and fifty pounds.    (x.)</p><p>@@@1 John Maxwell, Esq. of Broomholm was bom in the year 1726. In July 1754 he succeeded to an estate which has now belonged to the family for more than two centuries. His father was William Maxwell, his mother was a daughter of Scott of Wool in Selkirkshire. By his wife, Wilhelmina Malcolm, he had nine sons, of whom only one now survives. Her father was minister of Ewes, and the grandfather of the late Sir John Malcolm. Mr Maxwell was for many years a justice of the peace and a deputy lieutenant of the county of Dumfries. He was a remarkably handsome man, about six feet high, and possessing a pleasing address. Broomholm, two miles from Langholm, and three from Dr Russell’s place of residence, stands in a delightful valley near the junction of the Esk and Tarras, and is surrounded by extensive and lofty woods. He published, but without his name, “ An Essay upon Tune; being an Attempt to free the Scale of Music, and the Tune of Instruments, from Imperfection.” Edinb. 1781, 8vo. Pp. 290. The ingenious author died in the month of March 1806, at the age of seventy-nine years and ten months. He had a brother named Walter and a sister named Mary. She was the wife of Mr John Little of Langholm, and the mother of the late Colonel Little, so highly distinguished in the wars of India.    </p></body></text></TEI>