<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>is raised. Hemp and flax are very largely cultivated, and yield not only material for the manufactures of the country, but a large surplus for exportation.</p><p>Whilst corn and cattle constitute the riches of the central districts, the southern abound in productions of a more precious or delicate nature. The peninsula of Crimea is adapted, by climate and soil, for all the productions of Italy and Greece, and here, indeed, many of them are indigenous. Government has taken a most lively interest in developing the resources of each district of the empire ; and in consequence of this the cultivation of the vine, an indigenous plant, and the mulberry tree and sugar-cane, has been carried to a considerable extent. In 1835 there were planted in Crimea 1,454,000 feet of vines, the annual produce of which, in a few years, will be at least 75,000 vedros, or 250,000 gallons. The vine cultivation is extending with great success in the south, in the governments of Astra-can, Kherson, Podolia, the country of the Don Cossacks, and especially in the Taurida. In 1837, 1,150,000 vedros of wine were produced, and 1,300,000 to be distilled ; while in 1836 the whole quantity was not more than 800,000 vedros. The mulberry tree has been as carefully attended to as the vine, and the result has been, upon the whole, favourable. Vast plantations of mulberries have been formed near all the principal towns of the southern districts. Every encouragement is held out to planters by the government. In Crimea and the countries of the Caucasus, the rearing of the silk-worm is likewise rapidly advancing. Experiments have also been made to cultivate sugar-cane and indigo ; but it is doubtful if they will succeed. The corktree was transplanted from Portugal to the Crimea in 1817, but we see no notice of it in recent works.</p><p>In Southern Russia, a region whose climate differs little from that of Asia Minor, we find a similar abundance and variety of fruits and vegetables. The flora of Russia is very abundant in the south. As Pallas informs us, the country presents the most enchanting aspect. On the mountain side, in the valley, in the forest, everywhere, the earth is clothed with a profusion of the loveliest flowers, and aromatic herbs, whose delicate odours embalm all the surrounding atmosphere.</p><p>Russia further produces hops (not sufficient for home consumption), and tobacco, the <hi rend="italic">Nicotiana paniculata,</hi>  of which the young leaves are gradually removed, dried in the <hi rend="sub">t</hi>  shade, and buried beneath hay-ricks, where they become of a brownish-yellow colour. Of garden vegetables there are the usual varieties found in Europe. Spanish pepper is raised on the Samara and Lower Volga ; poppy in Char-kov, where it yields a return of a hundred and sixty fold ; rhubarb, which grows wild in Taurida ; rhapontick, which grows wild in the Urals; and<hi rend="italic">polygonum minus,</hi>  which in the Ukraine engenders worms that yield a beautiful crimson dye used as paint by the Cossack women. Genuine turpentine might be collected to a great extent. Many plants useful for dyeing are produced in a wild state ; and for tanning there are several valuable plants. In short, the Crimea presents great facilities for rendering this a lucrative branch of manufacture. It only remains to be stated with regard to the vegetation of Russia, that in the south there is abundance of excellent food for cattle, consisting not only of a great variety of grasses, but also of the best vegetables recommended for artificial meadows.</p><p>The quadrupeds of Russia are numerous. Some appear to be peculiar to the country, but our business is chiefly with the domesticated animals. Cattle of every description are bred in vast numbers in the steppes, and they have increased with the improvement of agriculture. Black cattle and oxen are raised as far north as the sixty-fourth parallel, especially in Podolia and the Ukraine. Some of the calves of the latter territory weigh from 480 to 600 lbs. Sheep are reared to a great extent, there being supposed to be between sixty and seventy millions of these useful animals in different parts of the country. In Taurida a poor Tartar may have in his possession 1000, and a rich Tartar 50,000. The Merino breed of sheep has been naturalized in Little Russia, in the governments comprised under the name of New Russia on the south and east, and in those of the shores of the Baltic Sea. These different regions, so remote from one another, are too dissimilar to enjoy precisely the same advantages ; nevertheless, the perseverance and judicious management of the cultivators have been crowned with success. Even in those districts least favoured by nature rapid improvement has been made. In 1826 the exports of wool from Odessa were only 18,000 poods, valued at ten roubles each ; in 1835 they were 116,000 poods, the price being advanced to thirty roubles per pood. At Taganrog the exports have increased in the same proportion ; and in Little Russia this branch of commerce is acquiring fresh activity. The wool trade is now also cultivated in Siberia, where a wool-company was established in 1832. In fine, Russia, lately so poor in this species of produce that even in 1824 her exports did not exceed annually 35,000 poods, valued at only 600,000 roubles, in 1834 sold 281,450 poods, the value of which amounted to 1,557,066 roubles. This is of course independently of the demands for the cloth manufactories in the interior, which have increased to a very great extent. The report of the minister of the interior for 1837 states the extensive advancement made in agricultural industry, and the improvement of the breeds of cattle and sheep, especially the great increase in the number of Merino sheep in New Russia, as well as in Esthonia, Livonia, and Courland. Amongst the animals are horses of very different races, to improve the breed of which, races have been instituted ; goats, from the silken hair of some of which animals the celebrated Cashmere shawls are woven ; camels in the warm and saline steppes of Taurida and Kherson ; asses, which are especially domesticated in Taurida ; swine ; rein-deer, so valuable in the north ; the buffalo, and others. Amongst useful insects there are bees, which yield an abundance of honey and wax for exportation. There are many wild animεils, the skins or furs of which constitute important items of trade in the northern parts of Russia ; and abundance of others, whose flesh is useful as food. Birds are very numerous, including field and water game of various kinds. Fish abound in the seas, lakes, and rivers ; and the fishcries constitute an important branch of productive industry, as will be afterwards shown.</p><p>European Russia consists of’a variety of countries, viz. that part improperly termed Muscovy, which is Russia strictly so<hi rend="sup">i </hi>called, and forms the nucleus of the empire ; the country of the Cossacks of the Don and of the Black Sea ; the king- ' doms of Kazan and Astracan, wrested from the Tartars ; Biarmia ; the greater part of Lapland ; Ingria, Karelia, Finland, Astrobothnia, Esthonia, Livonia, the archipelagos of Abo and Aland, and the islands of Dago, Oesel, &amp;c., countries formerly appendages of the Swedish crown ; the largest portion of the once independent kingdom of Poland, comprising the governments of Vitebsk, Moghilev, Minsk, Vol-hynia, Grodno, Vilna, Podolia, the province of Bialystok, and the new kingdom of Poland ; the former khanate of the Crimea, with Little Tartary, Bessarabia, and part of Moldavia, territories conquered from the Ottoman empire ; and the region beyond the Caucasus, wrested from the natives, Turks, and Persians. “ The Russian government,” says Balbi, “ does not recognise the distinction made by geographers betwixt Russia in Europe, Russia in Asia, and Russia in America. The first two are blended in several governments. For instance, Perm and Orenburg, being traversed by the Urals, have one part of their territory in Europe and another in Asia. However, having determined the boundaries of Europe by the crest of the Urals and</p></body></text></TEI>