<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="smallcaps">About the fifth century, a horde of those nations that roved at large on the banks of the Dnieper and the Volkhof, established themselves in that part of the region bordering on the Dnieper, where is now situated the government of Kief or Kiow. These people were called Slavi, or Slavonians, and had advanced eastward from the shores of the Danube. They appear to have laid the first foundation of the Russian monarchy, and to have built Kief, where they fixed their capital. It is probable that about the same time another tribe of Slavi had settled still farther to the east, in the province of Novgorod, where they built the city still known by that name, as their metropolis. Of the government and transactions of these people we have no regular accounts till the conclusion of the ninth century. It appears, however, from a work of the Emperor Constantine Porphyrogenneta on the administration of the empire, that in his time the city of Novgorod was a place of great importance, and carried on an extensive commerce, both with Constantinople and the countries bordering on the Baltic. The government of the Novgorodians appears to have been republican, but the people were probably rather merchants than warriors. We find them involved in frequent disputes with the neighbouring nations, from whose ravages they suffered considerable losses.</hi></p><p>If we may credit the Russian historians, the Slavi that had settled about Kief and Novgorod must have extended the boundaries of their territory northwards as far as the shores of the Baltic. We find that they were much harassed by a piratical nation who dwelt on the coasts of that sea, and were denominated Varages or Varagians, and who made frequent descents on the Russian coasts, and ravaged the country. It is not improbable that these Varagians formed a part of the Scandinavian nations who, under the names of Danes and Saxons, successively made themselves masters of England. They were occasionally employed by the weaker neighbouring states as mercenary auxiliaries, and in this capacity they were once called to the assistance of the Novgorodians. The auxiliaries, after having overcome the enemies whom they were invited to combat, began to think of availing themselves of the advantages which their bravery had given them over their employers. From allies and servants they soon became the masters of the Slavi ; and finding the country about Novgorod superior to that which they had left, they resolved to take up their residence in their new quarters.</p><p>Their leader Ruric built, near the Volkhof, a town whose site is now called Old Ladoga. Here he established the seat of his government. The event appears to have taken place about the year 860 ; and from this period we may date the commencement of the Russian monarchy. Ruric was assisted by two other chiefs of the Varages, Sinaus and Truvor, who are supposed to have been his brothers, and with whom he divided the territory of which he had possessed himself. Of these, Sinaus took up his residence at Bielo Osero, or the White Lake; while Truvor kept his court at Isborsk, or, according to some, at Twertzog, in the district of Pleskow. The three chiefs having thus divided among them the territories of the Novgorodians, continued to reign in amity with each other for several years.</p><p>The Slavi, however, did not immediately submit to the dominion of their new masters. They flew to arms, and chose for their leader Vadim, who by his feats in war had acquired the honourable appellation of the <hi rend="italic">valiant.</hi>  A fierce engagement took place between the Novgorodians and the Varages, which ended in favour of the latter, and the brave</p><p>Vadim, with several other chiefs of the Novgorodians, lost their lives in the attempt to free their country from its ambitious guests. This new success emboldened Ruric to extend his territories, and to change the seat of government from the insignificant town of Ladoga, to the spacious and opulent city of Novgorod. Soon after, by the death of his partners in sovereignty, he became sole monarch of the conquered territory, where he reigned without further molestation for seventeen years, and became the primogenitor of a long line of descendants, who held the throne without interruption for several centuries. He appears to have been zealous for the strict administration of justice in his dominions, and issued his command to all the boyars, or nobles, who held territories under him, in order to see it exercised in an exact and uniform manner. Ruric assumed the title of grand prince. His dominions extended over the present governments of Riga, Revel, Polotsk, Pscov, Vyborg, St Petersburg, Novgorod, Smolensk, Olonetz, Archangel, Vladimir, Yaroslavl, Kostroma, and Vologda.</p><p>As Ruric left only one son, Igor, who was still a minor at his father’s death, Oleg, a kinsman of the deceased monarch, took upon him the administration of affairs. Either from the natural restlessness of the Varages, or from the spirit of rebellion manifested by the Novgorodians, which indicated the necessity of employing his people on some active enterprise, the new ruler did not long remain idle. He appears very early to have projected the extension of his territories, by annexing to them the settlement which the Slavi had formed about Kief, against which he soon undertook a formidable expedition. Collecting a numerous army, composed of Slavi, Varages, and Tschudes (a Finnish tribe dwelling in districts embraced in the modern governments of Pscov and Revel), he carried with him the young prince Igor, and opened the campaign with the capture of Lubitch, and of Smolensk the capital of the Krivitsches.</p><p>Having advanced near the walls of Kief, he did not think it advisable to hazard an open attack. He therefore had recourse to artifice, and leaving behind him the greater part of his troops, he concealed the remainder in the barks that had brought them down the Dnieper from Smolensk. He himself, disguising his name and quality, passed for a merchant sent by Oleg and his ward Igor on business of importance to Constantinople ; and he despatched officers to Oskhold and Dir, the two chieftains of the Kievians, requesting permission to pass through their territory into Greece, and inviting them to visit him as friends and fellow-citizens, pretending that indisposition prevented him from paying his respects to them in person. The princes, free from mistrust, accepted Oleg’s invitation, and scarcely thought it necessary to take with them their ordinary attendants. They were soon undeceived ; for when they arrived at the regent’s encampment, they were quickly surrounded by the Varagian soldiers, who sprung from their place of concealment in the barks. Oleg taking Igor in his arms, and casting on the sovereigns of Kief a fierce and threatening look, exclaimed, “ You are neither princes nor of the race of princes ; behold the son of Ruric.” These words, which formed the signal that had been agreed on, were no sooner uttered, than his soldiers rushed on the two princes, and laid them prostrate at the feet of their master. The inhabitants of Kief, thrown into consternation by this bold and treacherous act, made no resistance, but opened the gates of their city to their invader ; and thus the two Slavonian states were united under one head.</p><p>Having thus made himself master of the key to the eastern</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>