<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ROTATION CONTINUED,  Comparing these with the above equations, we have</p>
            <p>M ⅛ =/ΡΛ», M ⅛ <hi rend="italic">zzfGtdm,</hi> M⅛ =∕R√τz<hi rend="sub">i</hi>.</p>
            <p>Now, the first members of these equations denote respectively the
                quantities of motion in the direction of the axes <hi rend="italic">x, y, z,</hi> of
                a material point whose mass = M, and the integrals <hi rend="italic">f</hi>P<hi
                    rend="italic">dm, f</hi>Q<hi rend="italic">dm, f</hi>R<hi rend="italic">dm</hi>
                denote the quantities of motion of the body or rigid system under consideration,
                subjected to the accelerating forces P, Q, R ; it follows, therefore, that during
                the whole continuance of the motion the centre of gravity moves as if the whole of
                the matter of the body were concentrated there, and the forces which act on the body
                were all applied at that point.</p>
            <p>63.    Having thus given the equations which enable us to determine the motion of the
                centre of gravity of a free system under the action of given forces, we now proceed
                to consider the rotatory movement of the system, and to investigate the position of
                any point of it with respect to the centre of gravity at the end of any given
                interval of time. The investigation of this problem is greatly facilitated by means
                of the following elegant theorem respecting the composition of rotatory motion,
                discovered by Frisi.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Proposition. If a solid body revolve round an axis O A (fig. 13)
                    passing through its centre of gravity with an angular velocity </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">— w,</hi> and if a force be impressed upon it which alone would
                cause it to revolve about an axis OB also passing through its centre of gravity with
                an angular velocity = <hi rend="italic">w'</hi>, then the body will not revolve
                about either OA or OB, but about a third axis OC lying in the plane of the other
                two, and inclined to each of the former axes in angles whose sines are inversely as
                the angular velocities round those axes, or so that sin. AOC : sin. BOC :: <hi
                    rend="italic">w' </hi>:<hi rend="italic"> w' ;</hi> and the angular velocity <hi
                    rend="italic">u</hi> round the new axis is to that round one of the primitive
                axes as the sine of inclination of the two primitive axes is to the sine of the
                inclination of the new axis to the other primitive axis, that is, <hi rend="italic"
                    >u : w</hi> : : sin. AOB : sin. COB, or <hi rend="italic">u : id</hi> : : sin.
                AÔB : sin. AOC.</p>
            <p>64.    In order to prove this proposition, it is necessary to show, lst, that any
                point in the line OC is at rest while the two motions are taking place ; 2d, that
                every particle of the body not situated in AC revolves about the axis AC ; and 3d,
                to assign the velocity of rotation.</p>
            <p>(1.) Let the angular motion about the axis OA be supposed to be in the direction by
                which every point in the angle AOB would be raised above the plane of the paper, and
                that about OB to be in the direction by which every point within the same
                angle wouldbe depressed below theplane of the paper, and take any point E in OC, and
                draw EH and EK respectively perpendicular to OA and OB. The absolute velocity with
                which the point E moves in consequence of the rotation about OA is HE· w, and the
                absolute velocity with which it moves about OB is KE ∙ κ∕. But HF=OE sin. AOC, anil
                KE = OE sin. BOC ; and by hypothesis <hi rend="italic">id : w</hi> : : sin. AOC :
                sin. BOC, whence <hi rend="italic">id</hi> sin. BOC = <hi rend="italic">w</hi> sin.
                AOC, therefore the two velocities HE ∙ <hi rend="italic">w</hi> and KE ∙ <hi
                    rend="italic">id</hi> are equal ; and they are in opposite directions,
                consequently the point E remains at rest. In the same manner, it is shown that every
                other point in OC remains at rest.</p>
            <p>(2.) Let P be the place of any particle of the body, and conceive the surface of a
                sphere to pass through P, intersecting the axes in A and B, and join PA and PB by
                arcs of great circles. Draw PM perpendicular to AP, and make PM = <hi rend="italic"
                    >w ∙</hi> sin. AP = absolute velocity of the particle P about the axis OA in 1"
                of time ; also draw PN perpendicular to BP, and make PN = <hi rend="italic">id
                    ∙</hi> sin. BP = absolute velocity of P about OB in 1" (the radius being unity),
                and complete the parallelogram PMRN.</p>
            <p>Since the particle <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi> in virtue of the rotation about OA, has
                a motion which would cause it to describe the line PM in a second, and in virtue of
                the rotation about OB has also a motion which would cause it to describe PN in a
                second, the particle will describe PR the diagonal of the parallelogram PMRN.
                Through P let an arc of a great circle be described perpendicular to PR, and
                produced to meet the plane AOB in the point C, which at present we
                suppose indeterminate, and join OC ; then OC is the straight line in which a plane
                passing through P, perpendicular to PR. intersects the plane AOB.</p>
            <p>Because APM and CPR are equal, being right angles, take from each the common angle
                APR, and there remains RPM = APC; and because BPN and CPR are right angles, add to
                each NPC, and we have RPN = BPC. Now PM = <hi rend="italic">w</hi> sin. AP, and PN =
                RM = <hi rend="italic">id ∙</hi> sin. BP, therefore</p>
            <p>PM : RM : : <hi rend="italic">w</hi> sin. AP : <hi rend="italic">id</hi> sin. BP ;
                but PM : RM : : sin. MRP (= sin. RPN) : sin. RPM, or PM : RM : : sin. BPC : sin. APC
                ; therefore sin. BPC : sin. APC : : <hi rend="italic">to</hi> sin. AP : <hi
                    rend="italic">id</hi> sin. BP, whence <hi rend="italic">id</hi> sin. BP ∙ sin.
                BPC = <hi rend="italic">w</hi> sin. AP ∙ sin. APC. Now in the spherical triangles
                BPC and APC we have sin BP ∙ sin. BPC = sin. CB ∙ sin. PCB, and sin. AP ∙ sin.</p>
            <p>APC = sin. AC ∙ sin. ACP ; therefore</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">id</hi> sin. CB ∙ PCB = <hi rend="italic">w</hi> sin. AC ∙ sin.
                ACP.</p>
            <p>But sin. PCB = sin. ACP (the one angle being the supplement of the other) ; also sin.
                CB — sin. BOC, sin. AC = sin. AOC, therefore <hi rend="italic">id</hi> sin. BOC =
                    <hi rend="italic">w</hi> sin. AOC, and consequently</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">w : id</hi> : : sin. BOC : sin. AOC.</p>
            <p>From this it follows that OC divides the angle AOB into parts having a given ratio,
                and is therefore given in position ; and as it may be shown in like manner that the
                plane passing through every other particle of the body perpendicular to the
                direction of the motion of that point intersects the plane AOB in OC, OC is
                therefore the axis of rotation.</p>
            <p>(3.) To find «, the angular velocity about OC. In the triangle RPM we have RP : PM :
                : sin. RMP : sin. MRP ; but sin. RMP = sin. MPN = sin. APB, and sin. MRP = sin. RPN
                = sin. CPB, therefore RP : PM : : sin. APB : sin. CPD. Now RP = « sin. CP = absolute
                velocity about OC in 1", and PM = <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >id</hi></hi> sin. AP — absolute velocity about OA in 1". Substituting these
                expressions therefore in the last proportion, and multiplying extremes and means, we
                get</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">u</hi> sin. CP ∙ sin. CPB = <hi rend="italic">w</hi> sin. AP ∙ sin.
                APB.</p>
            <p>But the spherical triangles CPB and APB give sin. CP sin. CPB = sin. CB sin. CBP, and
                sin. AP sin. APB = sin. AB sin. ABP. Therefore, substituting, and leaving out the
                common term, we have <hi rend="italic">u</hi> sin. CB = <hi rend="italic">w</hi>
                sin. AB, or « sin. COB = <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">id</hi></hi> sin.
                AOB, that is,</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">u : w</hi> : : sin. AOB : sin. COB.</p>
            <p>In like manner, it may bc shown that</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">u : id</hi> : : sin. AOB : sin. AOC, whence the proposition is
                demonstrated.</p>
            <p>65.    When the two primitive axes OA and OB are at right angles, sin. AOB = 1, sin.
                COB = cos. AOC, and the above two proportions give <hi rend="italic">u : id</hi> : :
                1 : cos. AOC, <hi rend="italic">u : id : : I</hi> : sin. AOC, whence « cos. AOC =
                    <hi rend="italic">u&gt;,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">u</hi> sin. AOC = <hi
                    rend="italic">id,</hi> and consequently <hi rend="italic">u</hi><hi rend="sup"
                    >2</hi> =<hi rend="italic">w<hi rend="sup">i</hi> + id*,</hi> or M = <hi
                    rend="italic">√(w<hi rend="sup">2</hi></hi> + w'<hi rend="sup">2</hi>).</p>
            <p>66.    Suppose a third axis OD at right angles to OA and OB, and that a force is
                impressed on the body, which alone would cause it to revolve about OD with an
                angular velocity = <hi rend="italic">id' ;</hi> then, as the body is revolving about
                OC with the velocity <hi rend="italic">u,</hi> the effect of this new force will be
                to cause it to revolve about an axis in the plane DOC ; and if we make ∙ψ = the
                angle which this new axis makes with the line OC, and W = the velocity about the new
                axis, we</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
