<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rods of the city wall, with all the buildings upon it, were destroyed ; and, according to the historians, upwards of a hundred and twenty thousand citizens were burned or buried in the ruins. The castle, however, which was strongly fortified, could not be taken ; and the Tartars, hearing that a formidable array was coming against them under the command of Magnus duke of Holstein, whom Ivan had made king of Livonia, thought proper to retire. The war, nevertheless, continued with the Polesand Swedes ; and the Czar being defeated by the latter after some trifling success, was reduced to the necessity of suing for peace ; but the negotiations being broken off, the war was renewed with the greatest vigour. The Livonians, the Poles, and the Swedes, having united in a league against the Russians, gained great advantages over them ; and in 1579, Stephen Batory, who was then raised to the throne of Poland, levied an army expressly with a design of invading Russia, and of regaining all that Poland had formerly claimed, which, indeed, was little less than the whole empire. Ivan found his undisciplined multitudes unable to cope with the regular forces of his enemies ; their conquests were so rapid that he was soon obliged to sue for peace, which, however, was not granted ; and it is possible that the number of enemies which now attacked Russia might have overcome the empire entirely, had not the allies grown jealous of each other. The consequence of this was, that in 1582 a peace was concluded with the Poles, in which the Swedes were not comprehended. However, the Swedes, finding themselves unable to effect any thing of moment after the desertion of their allies, were obliged to conclude a truce ; shortly after which, the Czar, having been worsted in an engagement with the Tartars, died in the year 1584.</p><p>The eldest son of the late Czar, Feodor (or, as he is commonly called, Theodore) Ivanovitch, was by no means fitted for the government of an empire so extensive, and a people so rude and turbulent, as had devolved to him by the death of his father. Ivan had seen the incapacity of his son, and had endeavoured to obviate its effect3 by appointing three of his principal nobles as administrators of the empire ; whilst to a fourth he committed the charge of his younger son Dmitri or Demetrius. This expedient, however, failed of success ; and, partly from the mutual jealousy of the administrators, partly from the envy which their exaltation had excited in the other nobles, the affairs of the empire soon fell into confusion. The weak Feodor had married a sister of Boris Gudonof, a man of great ambition, immense riches, and tolerable abilities. He had long directed his wishes towards the imperial dignity, and began to prepare the way for its attainment by removing Dmitri. This young prince suddenly disappeared; and there is every reason to believe that he was assassinated by the order of Boris. Feodor did not long survive his brother, but died in 1598, not without suspicion of having been poisoned by his brother-in-law. We are told that the Czarina, Irene, was so much convinced of this, that, retiring to a convent, she never afterwards held any communication with her brother.</p><p>With Feodor ended the family of Ruric, a dynasty which had enjoyed the supreme power in Russia ever since the establishment of the principality by the Varagian chief, that is, during a period of above seven hundred years. On the death of Feodor, as there was no hereditary successor to the vacant throne, the nobles assembled to elect a new Czar ; and the artful Boris having, through the interest of the patriarch, procured a majority in his favour, wasdeclared the object of then choice. He pretended unwillingness to accept the crown, declaring that he had resolved to live and die in a monastery ; but when the patriarch, at the head of the principal nobles, and attended by a great concourse of people, bearing before them the cross, and the effigies of several saints, repaired to the convent, where the artful usurper</p><p>had taken up his residence, he was at length prevailed on to accompany them to the palace of the Czars, and suffer himself to be crowned.</p><p>Boris is one instance amongst many of a sovereign who became beneficial to his subjects, though he had procured the throne by unjustifiable means. If we give implicit credit to the historians of those times, he was a murderer and a usurper, though he had the voice of the people in his favour ; but by whatever means he had attained the imperial power, he seems to have employed it in advancing the interest of the nation, and in improving the circumstances of his people. He was extremely active in his endeavours to extend the commerce, and improve the arts and manufactures, of the Russian empire ; and for this purpose he invited many foreigners into his dominions. Whilst he exerted himself in securing the tranquillity of the country, and defending its frontiers against the incursions of his neighbours, he made himself respected abroad, and received ambassadors from almost all the powers of Europe.</p><p>Soon after the commencement of his reign, the city of Moscow was desolated by one of the most dreadful famines recorded in history. Thousands of people lay dead in the streets and roads ; and in many houses the fattest of the inmates was killed to serve as food for the remainder. Parents are said to have eaten their children, and children their parents ; and we are told by one writer of the time that he saw a woman bite several pieces out of her child’s arm as she was carrying it along. Another relates, that four women having desired a peasant to come to one of their houses, on pretence of paying him for some wood, killed and devoured both him and his horse. This dreadful calamity lasted three years, notwithstanding all the exertions of Boris to provide for the necessities of the inhabitants.</p><p>Duringthese distresses of the capital, the power of Boris was thrcatened with annihilation by an adventurer who<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>suddenly started up, and pretended to be the young prince Dmitri, whom all believed to have been assassinated, or, as Boris had given out, to have died of a malignant fever. This adventurer was a monk named Otrepief. He retired from Russia into Poland, where he had the dexterity to ingratiate himself with some of the principal nobles, and to persuade them that he was really the lawful heir to the crown of Russia. The better to insure to himself the support of the Poles, he learned their language, and professed a great regard for the Catholic religion. By this last artifice he both gained the attachment of the Catholic Poles, and acquired the friendship of the Roman pontiff, whose blessing and patronage in his great undertaking he further secured, by promising that, as soon as he should have established himself on the throne, he would make every exertion to bring the Russians within the pale of the Catholic church. To the external graces of a fine person, the pretended Dmitri added the charms of irresistible eloquence ; and by these accomplishments the Polish voyvode of Sandomir was so much captivated that he not only espoused his cause, but promised to give him his daughter in marriage as soon as he should be placed on the throne of his fathers. This respectable man exerted himself so warmly in behalf of his intended son-in-law, that he brought over even the king of Poland to his party. The Kozaks of the Don, who were oppressed by Boris, hoping to gain at least a temporary advantage by the disturbance excited in favour of the adventurer, eagerly embraced the opportunity of declaring in his favour. The news soon penetrated into Russia ; and although Boris did all in his power to destroy the illusion, by prohibiting all intercourse between his subjects and the Poles, and by appealing to the evidence of the murdered prince’s mother in proof of his death, the cause of the pretender continued to gain ground. Many circumstances concurred to interest the Russian</p></body></text></TEI>