<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>it in such a manner that he did not think proper to ask it a second time. Having passed some hours in this extraordinary visit, he returned to his army, after having embraced and taken leave of the king he had dethroned,</p><p><hi rend="sup">1</hi> The armies of Sweden, in Saxony, Poland, and Finland,</p><p><hi rend="sup">!</hi> now exceeded seventy thousand men ; while the available force of Russia amounted to about a hundred thousand. Peter, who had his army dispersed in small parties, instantly assembled it on receiving notice of the king of Sweden’s march, was making all possible preparations for a vigorous resistance, and was on the point of attacking Stanislas, when the approach of Charles struck his whole army with terror. In the month of January 1708, Charles passed the Niemen, and entered the south gate of Grodno just as Peter was quitting the place by the north gate. Charles at this time had advanced some distance before the army, at the head of six hundred horse.</p><p>The czar having received intelligence of his situation, sent back a detachment of two thousand men to attack him ; but these were entirely defeated, and thus Charles became possessed of the whole province of Lithuania. The king pursued his flying enemies in the midst of ice and snow, over mountains, rivers, and morasses, and through obstacles which appeared to be insurmountable. These difficulties, however, he had foreseen, and had prepared to meet them. As he knew that the country could not furnish provisions sufficient for the subsistence of his army, he had provided a large quantity of biscuit, and on this his troops chiefly subsisted, till they came to the banks of the Beresina, in view of Borisow.' Here the czar was posted, and Charles intended to give him battle, after which he could the more easily penetrate into Russia. Peter, however, did not think proper to come to an action, but retreated towards the Dnieper, whither he was pursued by Charles, as soon as he had refreshed his army. The Russians had destroyed the roads and desolated the country, yet the Swedish army advanced with great celerity, and in their march defeated twenty thousand Russians, though intrenched to the very teeth. This victory, from the circumstances in which it was gained, was one of the most glorious that ever Charles had achieved. The memory of it was preserved by a medal struck in Sweden with this inscription ; <hi rend="italic">Sylvœ, paludes, aggeres, hostes, victi.</hi></p><p>VVhen the Russians had repassed the Dnieper, the czar, finding himself pursued by an enemy with whom he could not cope, resolved to make proposals for an accommodation. Charles made only this arrogant reply, “ I will treat with the czar at Moscow ;” a taunt which was received by Peter with the coolness of a hero. “ My brother Charles,” said he, “ affects to play the Alexander, but he shall not find in me a Darius.” He still, however, continued his retreat, and Charles pursued so closely that daily skirmishes took place between his advanced guard and the rear of the Russians. In these actions the Swedes had generally the advantage, though their petty victories cost them dear, by contributing to weaken their force in a country where it could not be recruited. The two armies came so close to each other at Smolensk, that an engagement took place between a body of Russians composed of ten thousand cavalry and six thousand Kalmuks, and the Sw edish vanguard, composed of only six regiments, but commanded by the king in person. Here the Russians were again defeated ; but Charles, having been separated from the main body of his detachment, was exposed to great danger. With one regiment only he fought with such fury as to drive the enemy before him, when they thought themselves sure of making him prisoner.</p><p>By the 3d of October 1708, Charles had approached within a hundred leagues of Moscow ; but Peter had rendered the roads completely impassable, and had destroyed the villages on every side, so as to cut off every possibility of subsistence to the enemy, while the season was far advanced, and the severity of winter was approaching. In these circumstances, the king, at length sensible that he had committed a perilous mistake, endeavoured to retrieve it by a step which proved yet more calamitous. He resolved, before attacking the Russian capital, to achieve the conquest of the Ukraine, where Mazeppa, a Polish gentleman, was general and chief of the Kozaks. Mazeppa having been affronted by the czar, readily entered into a treaty with Charles, whom he promised to assist with thirty thousand men, great quantities of provisions and ammunition, and with all his treasures, which were falsely stated to be immense. The Swedish army advanced towards the rivet' Disna, where they had to encounter the greatest difficulties ; a forest above forty leagues in extent, filled with rocks, mountains, and morasses. To complete their misfortunes, they were led thirty leagues out of the right way ; all the artillery was sunk in bogs and marshes ; the provision of the soldiers, which consisted of biscuit, was exhausted ; and the whole army were spent and emaciated when they arrived at the Disna. Here they expected to have met Mazeppa with his reinforcement ; but instead of that, they perceived the opposite banks of the river covered with a hostile army, and the passage itself rendered almost impracticable. Charles, however, was still undaunted ; he let his soldiers by ropes down the steep banks ; they crossed the river either by swimming, or on rafts hastily put together, drove the Russians from their post, and continued their march. Mazeppa soon after appeared, having with him about six thousand men, the broken remains of the army he had promised. The Russians had got intelligence of his designs, defeated and dispersed his adherents, laid his town in ashes, and taken all the stores collected for the Swedish army. However, he still hoped to be useful by his intelligence in an unknown country ; and the Kozaks, out of revenge, crowded daily to the camp with provisions.</p><p>Greater misfortunes still awaited the Swedes. Wlien Charles entered the Ukraine, he had sent orders to General Lewenhaupt to meet him with fifteen thousand men, six thousand of whom were Swedes, and a large convoy of provisions. Against this detachment Peter now bent his whole force, and marched against him with an army of sixty-five thousand men. Lewenhaupt had received intelligence that the Russian army consisted of only tw'enty-four thousand, a force to which he thought six thousand Swedes superior, and therefore disdained to intrench himself. A furious contest ensued, in which the Russians were defeated with the loss of fifteen thousand men. Now, however, affairs began to take another turn. The Swedes, elated with victory, prosecuted their march into the interior ; but, from the ignorance or treachery of their guides, they were led into a marshy country, where the roads were made impassable by felled trees and deep ditches. Here they were attacked by the czar with his whole array. Le-wenlιaupt had sent a detachment to dispute the passage of a body of Russians over a morass ; but finding his detachment likely to be overpolvered, he marched to support them with all his infantry. Another desperate battle ensued. The Russians were once more thrown into disorder, and were just on the point of being totally defeated, when Peter gave orders to the Kozaks and Kalmuks to fire upon all that fled ; “ Even kill me,” said he, “ if I should be so cow<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ardly as to turn my back.” The battle was now renewed with great vigour ; but notwithstanding the czar’s positive orders, and his own example, the day would have been lost, had not General Bauer arrived with a strong reinforcement of fresh Russian troops. The engagement was once more renewed, and continued without intermission till night. The Swedes then took possession of an advantageous post, but were next morning attacked by the</p></body></text></TEI>