<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>gian, who was the son of a Christian, and had been brought up in the new faith. The unhappy father refused the demanded victim. The enraged people, deeming their prince and their religion insulted, assailed the house, and having burst open the doors, butchered both the father and the son, folded in mutual embraces.</p><p>i Yet this furious Pagan and bloody warrior afterwards became a most zealous Christian, and a shining example of charity and benevolence to his subjects. The circumstances that led to these important changes are, as well as the martial achievements of this favourite prince, related with great minuteness by the Russian annalists, and give this part of their chronicles the air rather of a historical romance than a narrative of facts. We are told that the fame of Vladimir’s military exploits had rendered him so formidable to the neighbouring nations, that each courted his alliance, and strove to render this more lasting by engaging him in the ties of the same religion with themselves. In particular, the Grecian emperors sent to him a philosopher, whose exhortations, though they did not at first induce Vladimir to embrace the Greek ritual, at least succeeded in giving him a favourable opinion of it ; so that the philosopher was entertained with respect, and returned home loaded with presents. We are also told, that, determined to act in the most impartial manner with respect to the several religions which he had been invited to embrace, the prince despatched persons remarkable for their wisdom and sagacity to visit the surrounding nations, inspect the religious tenets and ceremonies that distinguished them, and communicate to him the result of their observations. On the return of these deputies, the report of those who had visited the churches of Constantinople, and witnessed the imposing splendour of religious adoration, and the gorgeous decorations of the Greek priests in the superb basilica of St Sophia, proved so satisfactory to Vladimir, that he determined on embracing the Christian religion according to the Observancesmf the Greek church. But though he resolved on baptism, he was too proud to seek from the Greek emperor a priest by whom the solemn ordinance might be performed. He assembled an army selected from all the nations of which his empire was composed, and marching to Taurida, laid siege to Theodosia, which is the modern Kaffa. On sitting down before the walls of this place, he is said to have offered up the following characteristic prayer : “ O God, grant me thy help to take this town, that I may carry from it Christians and priests to instruct me and my people, and convey the true religion into my dominions.” His prayer was at length granted ; for, rather by stratagem than by force, he made himself master of the town, and, through it, of the whole of the Crimea. He might now have received baptism ; but his desire of being initiated in the Christian faith seems to have been excited more by ambition than by true devotion. His ruling passion promised to be amply gratified by an alliance with the Grecian emperors, as he would thus acquire some legal claim on the territories which they possessed. He therefore demanded in marriage Anna, the sister of Basi-lius and Constantine, who jointly held the imperial dignity; threatening, that if they refused his proffered alliance, he would lay siege to Constantinople. After some deliberation, the emperors complied, on condition that Vladimir and his people should become Christians ; and these conditions being accepted, the Russian monarch was baptized, took the name of Basilius, received the Grecian princess, and, as the reward of his victories, carried off several popes and archimandrites, together with sacred vessels and church books, images of saints, and consecrated relics</p><p>1 Whatever might have been the considerations that swayed Vladimir in his conversion to the Christian faith, it is certain that his new religion had the happiest influence on his subsequent life and conduct. He not only abjured idolatry himself, and destroyed the idols which he had caused</p><p>to be raised in his dominions, but he used every exertion to persuade and compel his subjects to follow his example. Before his conversion he is said to have possessed five wives and eight hundred concubines; but after he became a Christian, he maintained an unshaken fidelity towards the imperial princess. As a Pagan he had been lavish of human blood ; but after he had adopted the religion of Jesus, he could scarcely be prevailed on to sentence to death a single highway robber. His former delight had been in storming towns and gaining battles ; but he now found his greatest pleasure in building churches, and endowing seminaries of education. He encouraged the raising of new cities and towns ; peopled the waste districts of his country with the prisoners whom he had taken in war ; and not only conducted himself as a sovereign who consulted the welfare of his dominions, but displayed many benevolent and amiable qualities that highly endeared him to his subjects. By thus showing that Christianity had made him both a milder and a wiser prince, he insured from his people a respect for the new religion, whilst the striking example of the sovereign and his nobles could not fail to influence the minds of the inferior orders. Having one day issued a proclamation, ordering all the inhabitants of Kief to repair next morning to the banks of the river to be baptized, the people cheerfully obeyed the order ; observing, that if it were not good to be baptized, the prince and the boyars would never submit to the ceremony.</p><p>The establishment of Christianity in the Russian dominions forms one of the most prominent features in the reign of Vladimir, and gives him a much juster claim to the title of Great, which has been bestowed on him by historians, than all his numerous victories. We have therefore dwelt on it with the greater minuteness. Indeed the latter transe actions of his reign afford but little interest. His last days were embittered by domestic vexations. His wife and one of his favourite sons died long before him ; while another of his sons, Yaroslaf, on whom he had bestowed the government of Novgorod, refused to acknowledge him as his liege lord, and applied to the Varagians for assistance against his father. The aged Vladimir, compelled to march against a rebellious son, died of grief upon the road, after a long and glorious reign of thirty-five years.</p><p>Notwithstanding the unfavourable circumstances we have noticed, the improvement which Russia owed to this prince was great and permanent. With the Christian religion he imported from Greece the arts which then flourished in that empire ; and almost entirely new-modelled the language of his country, by engrafting on it the more refined dialect of the Greeks, and adopting, in a great measure, the letters of their alphabet.</p><p>The dominions of Russia, which at first consisted of two principalities, that of Novgorod, bordering on the Baltic, and that of Kief, occupying no very large space on the eastern bank of the Dnieper, were, by the victories of Vladimir, extended westward along the shores of the Baltic into Lithuania and Poland ; southward along the shores of the Euxine, so as to include the Crimea and great part of the Bulgarian territories ; whilst to the east it extended to the Oka, the Don, and the Volga. He still maintained the seat of government at Kief, of which he was styled grand prince, whilst the other districts were either tributary to that principality, or held of it as their superior.</p><p>Before his death, Vladimir had divided his extensive territories amongst his twelve sons, reserving to himself and his immediate heir the grand principality of Kief. The consequences of this ill-judged distribution were disunion, con-<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>tention, and almost perpetual warfare amongst the brothers. The most respectable, and in the end the most powerful of these, was Yaroslaf, or, as he is commonly called, Jarislas, prince of Novgorod. This prince, finding that Sviatopolk<hi rend="sub">1 </hi>who had raised himself to the sovereignty of Kief after his</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>