<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>moment. Let the first of those equations be multiplied by C, and subtracted from the second; we shall have, on making L<hi rend="sup">!</hi>— CK = D,</p><p>D = A (A — C) tc<hi rend="sup">2</hi> + B (B — C) w<hi rend="sup">12</hi>.</p><p>Now, if we suppose the axis of instantaneous rotation to</p><p>be situated at the commencement of the motion, very near the axis OZ, the angular velocity about which = «/', then the angle <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  which it makes with that axis being very small,</p><p>and since (66) sin. <hi rend="italic">y — - </hi>. J ,     follows that</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">v</hi> '    ' V</hi>  (w<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  +<hi rend="smallcaps">m/<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  +</hi><hi rend="italic">w <hi rend="sup">n</hi>)</hi></p><p>the angular velocities <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  and «/ will be very small in comparison of «/', and consequently D must be a very small quantity. Now D is constant; and therefore if the two differences A — C and B — C have the same sign, which will be the case when the value of B is intermediate between A and C, the two velocities <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  and m/ must always be very small; and hence (64) the instantaneous axis will never deviate much from OZ when this is the axis of greatest or of least moment. But if A — C and B — C have opposite signs, as will be the case when the value of C lies between the values of A and B, then D may be a very small quantity, and the equation still be satisfied, although the values of <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  and «/ be large; and hence, although the axis of instantaneous rotation may have been very near the axis C at the commencement of the motion, it may deviate to any extent from that axis during the motion. Hence we infer that the rotation about the axes, both of greatest and least moment, is permanent, but that the rotation about the intermediate axis is not permanent.</p><p>77. The same conclusions may also be obtained by the direct integration of the equations (a) of (75), if we neglect, as insensible, the squares and products of the small velocities <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  and io*. Restricting the calculus to this approximation, the third equation (a) becomes rfw" = 0, whence <hi rend="italic">vf = h, k</hi>  being an assured arbitrary constant. Substituting this value of w" in the first two equations <hi rend="italic">(a) we</hi>  get</p><p>0 zz <hi rend="italic">Adxo</hi>  -p (C — B) <hi rend="italic">hxddt,    / jy</hi></p><p>0 = BrfuZ + (A — C) <hi rend="italic">kwdt,    ' &gt;</hi></p><p>In order to integrate these, assume</p><p><hi rend="italic">w = 0</hi>  sin. (7Z + t), <hi rend="italic">xd — y</hi>  cos. <hi rend="italic">(qt -|~ «),    </hi>(f)</p><p>the quantities /3, <hi rend="italic">y, g, i</hi>  being indeterminate constants. We have then</p><p><hi rend="italic">dw</hi>  = 7,3 cos. (7Z + «), <hi rend="italic">dw' — — qy</hi>  sin. (7Z + «).</p><p>On substituting these values of <hi rend="italic">w, rd, dw, dw',</hi>  and rejecting the common factors, the equations <hi rend="italic">(d)</hi>  become</p><p>0 = <hi rend="italic">Aq0 —</hi>  (B — C) <hi rend="italic">ky,</hi></p><p>0 = Byy — (<hi rend="underline">A — C) </hi>k0,<hi rend="italic">     _</hi></p><p>from which we deduce <hi rend="italic">q = kV(A —</hi>  C) (B — C) -r V'AB; and also, on assuming another indeterminate constant <hi rend="italic">a, 0 = a.</hi>  VB (B — C), <hi rend="italic">y =</hi>  « VA (A — C). Put X <hi rend="sub">=</hi>  V(A — C) (B — C) VAB, then 7 = XA; and the substitution of these values of 7, 3,<hi rend="italic">y</hi>  in the equations (e) gives</p><p><hi rend="italic">w — a.</hi>  VB (B — C) sin. (XAz + 1),</p><p><hi rend="italic">«/ = a V</hi>  A (A — C) cos. (XAz -(- <hi rend="italic">x),</hi></p><p>which are the complete integrals of the equations (d).</p><p>If in these expressions the quantity denoted by X is real, which will be the case when C is the least or the greatest of the three moments, the values of <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">w’</hi>  must always continue small, because they are proportional to the sines and cosines of a real angle; but if C be intermediate between A and B, the X will be an impossible quantity, and the sine and cosine of the arc XAZ -)- <hi rend="italic">i</hi>  will be changed into exponentials which increase continually with the time /, whence the velocities <hi rend="italic">xo</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">xd</hi>  will also increase indefinitely ; and consequently, by Frisi’s theorem, the deviation of the instantaneous axis of rotation from the original axis will increase indefinitely.</p><p>If we suppose that at the commencement of the motion</p><p>the axis of instantaneous rotation coincided accurately with 1 the principal axis OZ, we should have <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  = 0, <hi rend="italic">xd —</hi>  0, when <hi rend="sup">s </hi><hi rend="italic">t</hi>  = 0 ; and as in this case we have also <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  = 0, <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">id </hi>will always be zero, or the body will continue for ever to revolve uniformly about OZ. We have therefore, from what precedes, these mechanical properties relative to the rotation of solid bodies : 1. If a body begins to revolve about any one of the three principal axes, and is affected by no external force, it will continue always to revolve about that axis ; 2. If it begins to revolve about an axis which is very near the axis of the greatest or least moment, then, although the motion is disturbed a little by the action of an extraneous force, the instantaneous axis of rotation will continue very near the original axis ; 3. If the rotation commences about the axis of the mean moment of inertia, then, if the smallest disturbance takes place, the effect will increase indefinitely with the time, and the poles of rotation will entirely change their position on the surface of the body. These properties establish an essential difference between the three principal axes.</p><p>78. Our limits will not permit us to enter further into C the discussion of this subject, nor is it within the scope of the present article to apply the formulæ to the rotation of the planets, an example of which application has already been given in the article Precession of the Equinoxes. It has now been shown that every circumstance relative to the motion of a solid body, acted upon by any number of forces, is expressed by means of two systems of equations (each containing three differential equations of the first order), the first system (62) defining the motion in space of the centre of gravity, and the second (73) the rotation about that centre. At the commencement of the motion these two systems are independent of each other ; but it is important to remark, that this independence does not necessarily continue during the motion. If we suppose the moving forces to act upon different points of the body, and to be functions of the co-ordinates of those points, that is, to vary with their distance from the origin, then the coordinates enter at the same time into both systems of equations, which therefore cannot be integrated separately, the two motions affecting each other. The integrals can then only be obtained by approximation. There are, however, two important cases in which the two motions continue to be permanently independent of each other. The first is that of a projectile which, during its motion, is acted upon by no other force than gravity ; for in this case the equations (62) will be those of an isolated material point, and the weight of the body, acting as a single force applied to the centre of gravity, will have no influence on the rotation, which will be the same as if the centre of gravity were fixed. The second is the case of a sphere, either homogeneous or composed of concentric strata of different densities, the density of each stratum being constant ; for in this case the resultant of all the attractive forces, as was shown by Newton, passes through the centre of gravity, which will therefore move as an isolated point, and the motion of rotation will be the same as if the centre of gravity were fixed.</p><p>The theory of the rotation of solid bodies forming an important branch of mechanics, is treated more or less in every systematic work on that science. As the more important works in which it is especially considered, we may refer the reader to Euler’s <hi rend="italic">Theoria Molxis Corporxim Soli-dorum,</hi>  1765; D’Alembert, <hi rend="italic">Opuscula,</hi>tom. v.andvii.; Vince <hi rend="italic">On the Principles of Progressive and Rotatory Motion,</hi>  Phil. Trans. 1780 ; Frisii <hi rend="italic">Opera,</hi>  tom. ii. 1783 ; Atwood’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the Rectilinear Motion and Rotation of Bodies,</hi>  1784 ; Landen’s <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Memoirs,</hi>  vol. ii. 1789; Laplace, <hi rend="italic">Mécanique Céleste,</hi>  tom. i. ; Lagrange, <hi rend="italic">Mécanique Analytique; </hi>Poisson, <hi rend="italic">Traité de Mécanique;</hi>  Venturoli’s <hi rend="italic">Mechanics,</hi>  translated by Cresswell ; &amp;c.    (s.)</p></body></text></TEI>