<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>any other publication on the subject. When urged to give it to the public, he said dryly, “ The age has so little taste, that the sale would not pay the expense.” Of this work he published an abridgment, to which he subjoined an extract of his prosody.</p><p>Ruddiman next engaged in the management of a newspaper, an employment for which his genius and industry seemed to render him well qualified. But those who should expect either much information or amusement from this publication, would perhaps be greatly disappointed. The newspaper which he conducted was the Caledonian Mercury, and was established in 1720, by William Rolland, a lawyer. Ruddiman acted only for five years in the capacity of printer ; but upon the death of Mr Rolland in 1729, the property was transferred to him, or to his brother Walter and him conjunctly. This paper continued in the family of Ruddiman till the year 1772, when it was sold by the trustees of his grandchildren. The Caledonian Mercury was at first printed three times a week, on Monday, Tuesday, and Thursday, in a small quarto of four pages, with two columns in each page, and fifty lines in each column ; so that the whole paper contained only four hundred lines.</p><p>Mr Ruddiman, after the death of Mr Spottiswoode, librarian, remained for some time in his former station ; but he was at length appointed keeper of the library, though without any increase of salary ; and some years afterwards Mr Goodal, the defender of Queen Mary, succeeded him in the office of sub-librarian.</p><p>The assiduous application of Ruddiman, supported by such learning, was entitled to wealth, which now indeed flowed upon him in what was at that period deemed great abundance. On the lst of October 1735, it appeared, from an exact statement of his affairs, that he was worth L.1882. 5s. 2d. sterling ; and on the 20th of May the ensuing year his wealth had increased to L.1985. 6s. 3d. sterling. In 1710 he had valued his effects at L.24. l4s. 9d. sterling.</p><p>In 1737 the schoolmasters and teachers in Edinburgh formed themselves into a society, in order to establish a fund for the support of their widows and children. Of this scheme Ruddiman was an active promoter, and was chosen treasurer. Perhaps it was this association which in 1742 gave to the Scotch clergy the idea of forming their widows’ fund.</p><p>In 1739 he published <hi rend="italic">Selectus Diplomatum et Numismatum Scoticæ Thesaurus.</hi>  This work was projected and begun by Anderson, and hence called Anderson’s <hi rend="italic">Diplomata, </hi>but was finished by Ruddiman. The preface, w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>hich is an excellent commentary on Anderson’s performance, was written by Ruddiman, and displays a greater extent of knowledge than any of his other productions.</p><p>As Ruddiman had imbibed from his father those political principles which attached him to the family of Stuart, he probably did not remain an unconcerned spectator of the civil commotions which, in 1745, agitated Scotland. He did not, however, take any active part in the rebellion. His principles, he has been heard to say, induced him to be a quiet subject and a good citizen. He retired to the country during the summer of 1745; and whilst his fellow-citizens were spilling each other’s blood, he was more happily engaged in writing Critical Observations on Burmann’s Commentaries on Lucan’s <hi rend="italic">Phαrsαlia.</hi>  The Caledonian Mercury was in the mean time marked with a jealous eye. His son, who had for some time been the principal manager of that newspaper, having copied from an English paper a paragraph which was reckoned seditious, was imprisoned. The solicitation of his father procured his release ; but it was too late, for the unhappy young man had contracted a distemper in the tolbooth of Edinburgh which brought him to a premature grave.</p><p>During the last seventeen years of his life, Ruddiman was almost incessantly engaged in controversy. To this he was in some measure compelled by the violent attacks which some critics of the times had successively made upon his works. He was first called upon by Benson, auditor in the exchequer, to determine the comparative merit of Buchanan and Johnson as poets. He gave a decided preference to Buchanan in perspicuity, purity, and variety of style ; but, like a candid critic, allowed Johnson to be superior in the harmony of his numbers. His next antagonist was Logan, one of the ministers of Edinburgh, a weak and illiterate man, but an obstinate polemic. The subject of contest was, whether the crown of Scotland was strictly hereditary, and whether the birth of Robert III. was legitimate. Ruddiman maintained the affirmative in both points, and certainly far surpassed his antagonist in the powers of reasoning. He proved the legitimacy of Robert by the public records of the kingdom, with a force of argument which admits of no reply ; but in discussing the first question, by which he was led to consider the contest between Bruce and Baliol, he was not so successful ; for there are many instances in the history of Scotland in which the brother succeeded to the crown in preference to the son. He showed, however, that the Scottish crown was at no period properly elective ; and that, according to the old licentious constitution of the kingdom, the right of Bruce, who was the nearest in blood to the royal stock, was preferable to the claim of Baliol, though descended from the eldest daughter.</p><p>But the labours of Ruddiman did not end when the pen dropt from the feeble hand of Logan. He was soon called upon to repel the attacks of Love, schoolmaster of Dalkeith, who maintained, in opposition to him, that Buchanan had neither repented of his treatment of Queen Mary, nor had been guilty of ingratitude to that princess. That Buchanan ever repented there is reason to doubt. Whether he was guilty of ingratitude, let the unbiassed determine, when they are assured by authentic records that Mary conferred on him a pension for life of five hundred pounds Scotch.</p><p>When Ruddiman had arrived at his eightieth year, and was almost blind, he was assailed by James Man, master of an hospital at Aberdeen, with a degree of rancour and virulence, united with some learning and ability, which must have touched him in a sensible manner, and alarmed his fears for his reputation after his decease. He was called a finished pedant, a furious calumniator, and a corrupter of Buchanan’s works. The venerable old man again put on his armour, entered the lists, and gained a complete victory. Man, with all his acuteness, could only point out twenty errors in two folio volumes. Some of these were typographical, some trifling, and some doubtful. Ruddiman, with much pleasantry, drew up against Man an account of four hundred and sixty-nine errors, consisting of fourteen articles, of which two or three may be produced as a specimen: 1. Falsehoods and prevarications, twenty; 2. absurdities, sixty-nine ; and, 3. passages from classical authors which were misunderstood by Man, ten. The triumph which he gained over this virulent adversary he did not long enjoy, for he died at Edinburgh on the 19th of January 1757, in the eighty-third year of his age, and was buried in the Greyfriars churchyard, without any monument to distinguish his grave. He was three times married, but left behind him only one daughter, Alison, who was married in 1747 to Mr James Stewart. He is supposed to have died worth L.3000 sterling.</p><p>He was of the middle size, of a thin and straight make, and had eyes remarkably piercing. Of his talents and learning his works afford the most satisfactory proofs. His memory w as tenacious and exact ; and he was so great a master in the Latin language that he has perhaps been equalled by none since the days of Buchanan.</p><p>Ruddiman has left a character unstained by vice and distinguished by many virtues. His piety was exemplary</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>