<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed blocked up by the British, till they were surrendered by the convention of Cintra ; and another fleet of fifteen sail of the line that proceeded up the Mediterranean, and advanced as far as Trieste, shared a similar fate.</p><p>On the 26th of October the emperor of Russia published a declaration, notifying to the powers of Europe that he had broken off all communication between his empire and Great Britain, until the conclusion of a peace between this power and France. In a counter-declaration, published at London on the IOth of December, his Britannic majesty repels the accusations of Russia, while he regrets the interruption of the friendly intercourse between that power and Britain. His majesty justifies his own conduct, and declares, that when tile opportunity for peace between Great Britain and Russia shall arrive, he will embrace it with eagerness ; satisfied if Russia shall manifest a disposition to return to her ancient feeling of friendship towards Great Britain, to a just consideration of her own true interests, and to a sense of her own dignity as an independent nation.</p><p>In October 1808, a meeting took place at Erfurt between the emperors of France and Russia, and a letter was drawn up under their signature, addressed to his Britannic majesty. The object of this letter was, to induce the king of Great Britain to enter into negotiations for a general peace, and with that view it was despatched by Count Ro-manzoff, the Russian minister at Erfurt, to Mr Canning, the British secretary of state for foreign affairs. It was answered by an official note, requiring the emperors, as an indispensable condition of any treaty with Britain, to receive Sweden as a party, to protect the interests of Portugal and of the ex-king of Naples, and to extend the benefits of the projected arrangements to Ferdinand VIL of Spain. These requisitions were evidently quite inconsistent with Napoleon’s views ; the emperors refused to accede to them ; and all hope of accommodation was in the mean time at an end.</p><p>The demand of concurrence in the views of France and Russia made on Sweden was formally repeated in a declaration of the Emperor Alexander, published at St Petersburg on the IOth of February in this year. In this declaration his imperial majesty intimated to the king of Sweden that he was making preparations to invade his territories ; but that he was ready to change the measures he was about to take, to measures of precaution only, if Sweden would, without delay, join Russia and Denmark in shutting the Baltic against Great Britain, until the conclusion of a maritime peace. He professed that nothing could be more painful to him, than to see a rupture take place between Sweden and Russia ; but that his Swedish majesty had it still in his power to avoid this event, by resolving without delay to adopt that course which could alone preserve strict union and perfect harmony between the two states.</p><p>The king of Sweden, however, determined to abide by the measures which he had for some time pursued, and to adhere to the terms of the convention which had just been concluded between him and the king of Great Britain. In consequence of this determination, a Russian army entered Finland in the beginning of March, under the command of General Buxhovden, and advanced against Helsingfors, which was occupied by a single battalion of a Swedish regiment. This small force retired into the fortress of Swea-borg, where they maintained themselves with great bravery till the 17th of April, when they were obliged to capitulate. The loss of this fortress, though inconsiderable in itself, so highly enraged the king of Sweden, that he dismissed the naval and military commanders who had been concerned in the capitulation.</p><p>On the 27th of April, some slight advantage was gained over the Russians near Rivolax, by the Swedish army under General Count Klinspor ; but this was only a partial gleam</p><lb/><p>of success. The Russians soon overran almost all Finland, took possession of Wasa, Old and New Carleby, and reduced ' under subjection the whole province of which Wasa is the capital. The army of Field-Marshal Klinspor, which originally consisted of sixteen thousand regulars, and many boors, was, by the end of the campaign, reduced to little more than nine thousand men.</p><p>The king of Sweden sent some reinforcements to his army in Finland ; but the forces which should have supported Klinspor were foolishly employed in a fruitless attempt to conquer Norway ; and in 1809 the Swedes were compelled to cede Finland to Russia.</p><p>Russia continued to appear in the unworthy character of Napoleon’s ally ; and when Austria made an effort in 1809 to recover her losses, a Russian army advanced to co-operate with the French. The diversion which this produced was one cause of the final success of Napoleon, whose situation after the battle of Aspern was extremely critical. When Austria was at last compelled to accept of peace on humiliating terms, Russia received as the reward of her services the district of Tarnopol in Galicia, with a population of four hundred thousand souls. This district was restored to Austria in 1815.</p><p>In 1811, hostilities commenced between Russia and the Porte. It is of little consequence to inquire into the causes of this rupture ; a powerful and ambitious government in the neighbourhood of a weak one never wants pretexts for war. The result might have been serious, if not fatal to the Porte, had not the prospect of a more arduous struggle induced Russia to suspend her efforts in that quarter, and conclude a peace on condition of receiving a part of Moldavia and Bessarabia.</p><p>The great contest was now approaching which was to try the resources of Russia, and ultimately to raise her to unexampled greatness. The seizure by France of the territories of the Prince of Oldenburg, who was the emperor of Russia’s brother-in-law, on the one hand, and the admission of British produce into the Russian harbours on the other, furnished the ostensible grounds of the quarrel. After some fruitless negotiations, Napoleon dismissed the Russian ambassador, and left Paris to join the army on the 9th of May 1812. The events of this disastrous expedition into Russia have been minutely related in the article France ; and the reader does not require to be reminded of those lamentable sufferings of the French army, which were its principal result. The spirited resistance of Russia now roused Prussia and Austria ; and early in 1813 a league was formed between these powers, to which Bavaria and other small states acceded. The battle of Leipsic, fought on the 18th of October, led to the final overthrow of the French domination. In all the transactions which followed, Russia bore a leading part. At the congress of Vienna in 1814, the duchy of Warsaw, consisting of part of the original conquests of Austria and Prussia in Poland, was assigned to Russia, which thus ultimately obtained about four fifths of the territory and three fourths of the population of that ancient kingdom.</p><p>In passing to the new system of foreign policy which has prevailed in Russia, as well as in the rest of Europe, since the year 1815, we must pause for a moment to remark the accessions of territory which the empire had made during the half century which preceded that epoch. The reign of Catherine II. had, as we have seen, been by far the most fertile in foreign acquisitions. Her conquests included the Crimea, which was an incorporated portion of Russia since 1783 ; Georgia, gained in 1785, though, as we have observed, not formally annexed till 1801 ; Bessarabia, with a part of Moldavia, and other Turkish possessions, finally secured to ,Russia by the treaty of Bukarescht in 1812; Courland, acquired in 1795; and the extensive spoils of Poland in 1793 and 1794. Paul’s reign made no permanent addition of import-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>