<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>It is not known with certainty what share the empress had in this event ; but it is affirmed that on the very day on which it happened, while the empress was beginning her dinner with much gaiety, an officer, supposed to be one of the assassins, precipitately entered the apartment with his hair dishevelled, his face covered with sweat and dust, his clothes torn, and his countenance agitated with horror and dismay. On entering, his eyes, sparkling and confused, met those of the empress. She arose in silence, and went into a closet, whither he followed her. A few moments afterwards she sent for Count Panin, the former governor of Peter, who was already appointed her minister, and, informing him that the emperor was dead, consulted him on the manner of announcing his death to the public. Panin advised her to let one night pass over, and to spread the news next day, as if they had received it during the night. This counsel being approved, the empress returned with the same countenance, and continued her dinner with the same gaiety. On the day following, when it was published that Peter had died of an hæmorrhoidal colic, she appeared bathed in tears, and proclaimed her grief by an edict.</p><p>The corpse was brought to St Petersburg, there to be exposed. The face was black, and the neck excoriated. Notwithstanding these horrible marks, in order to assuage the commotions, which began to excite apprehension, and to prevent impostors from hereafter disturbing the empire, it was left three days exposed to all the people, with only the ornaments of a Holstein officer. The soldiers, disbanded and disarmed, mingled with the crowd, and as they beheld their sovereign, their countenances indicated a mixture of compassion, contempt, and shame. They were soon afterwards embarked for their country ; but, as the sequel of their cruel destiny, almost all of these unfortunate men perished in a storm. Some of them had saved themselves on the rocks adjacent to the coast ; but they again fell a prey to the waves, while the commandant of Cronstadt despatched a messenger to St Petersburg to know whether he might be permitted to assist them. Thus fell the unhappy Peter III. in 1762, in the thirty-fourth year of his age, after having enjoyed the imperial dignity only six months.</p><p>On her accession, Catherine behaved with great magna-<hi rend="sup">3</hi> nimity and forbearance towards those who had opposed her elevation, or were the declared friends of the deceased em-’ peror. She gave to Prince George, in exchange for his title of Duke of Courland, conferred on him by Peter, the government of Holstein. She reinstated Biren in his dukedom of Courland, received into favour Marshal Munnich, who had readily transferred his fidelity from the dead to the living, and even pardoned her rival the Countess Vo-rontzoff, and permitted her to retain the tokens of her lover’s munificence. She permitted Gudovitch, who was high in the confidence of Peter, and had incurred her particular displeasure, to retire to his native country. Perhaps the most unexpected part of her conduct towards the friends of Peter, was her adhering to the treaty of peace which that monarch had concluded with the king of Prussia six months before. The death of his inveterate enemy Elizabeth had relieved Frederick from a load of solicitude, and had extricated him from his dangerous situation. He now, as he thought, saw himself again involved in a war with the same formidable power ; but, to his great joy, he found that Catherine, from motives of policy, declined entering on a war at the commencement of her reign.</p><p>In one particular the empress showed her jealousy and her fears. She increased the vigilance with which the young prince Ivan was confined in the castle of Schlusselburg, from which Peter III. had expressed a resolution to release him. Not long after her accession, this unfortunate prince was assassinated, though whether this event was to be imputed to the empress or her counsellors, cannot be positively determined. But a manifesto published by the court of St Petersburg, and supposed to have been written by the empress herself, admitted that the prince was put to death by the officers of his guard, alleging that this was necessary, in consequence of an attempt to carry him off.</p><p>Were we to offer a detailed account of the principal transactions that took place during the long reign of Catherine, we should far exceed the limits within which this article must be confined, and should at the same time repeat much of what has already been given under other heads. As the events that distinguished the life of Catherine, however, are too important to be wholly omitted, we shall present our readers with the following chronological sketch of them, referring for a more particular account to Tooke’s Life of Catherine II., and to the articles Catherine IL Britain, France, Poland, Prussia, Sweden, and Turkey, in this work.</p><p>The year 1766 presented at St Petersburg the grandest spectacle that perhaps was ever seen in Europe. At an entertainment, which the empress chose to name a carousal, the principal nobility appeared in the most sumptuous dresses, sparkling with diamonds, and mounted on horses richly caparisoned, in a magnificent theatre erected for that purpose. Here all that has been read of the ancient jousts and tournaments was realized and exceeded in the presence of thousands of spectators, who seemed to vie with each other in the brilliancy of their appearance.</p><p>In 1768, the empress composed instructions for a new code of laws for her dominions ; and the same year she submitted to the danger of inoculation, in order that her subjects, to whom the practice was unknown, might be benefited by her example.</p><p>In the same year a war broke out with the Ottoman Porte. The various events of this long and important conflict, which continued for seven years, must here be only briefly enumerated, as they will hereafter be more particularly noticed under the article Turkey. In this war our countryman Greig, then an admiral in the Russian service, highly distinguished himself by his conduct in a naval engagement with the Turks, in the harbour of Tschesme, in the Archipelago, in which the Turkish fleet was entirely defeated, and their magazines destroyed. This took place on the 4th of November 1772.</p><p>In the beginning of the year 1769, the khan of the Crimea made an attack on the territory of Bachmut, on the river Bog, where he was several times bravely repulsed, with his army of Tartars and Turks, by Major-General Ro-manius and Prince Prosorofskoi. At the same time were fought the battles of Zekanofca and Soroca on the Dnieper, when the large magazines of the enemy were burned. In February the Polish Kozaks in the voyvodeship of Brac-lau put themselves under the Russian sceptre. In the same month the Nisovian Saparogian Kozaks gained a battle in the deserts of Krim. In March the Polish rebels were subdued, and their town taken, by Major-General Ismailof. On the 2d of April the fort of Taganrog, on the Sea of Azof, was taken. On the 15th the Russian army, under the general-in-chief Prince Galitzin, crossed the Dniester. On the 19th a victory was gained by Prince Galitzin near Chotzim. On the 2lst the Turks were defeated not far from Chotzim by Lieutenant-General Count Soltikof. The 29th, an action was fought between the Russian Kalmucks and the Kuban Tartars, to the disadvantage of the latter. June the 8th, the Turks were defeated at the mouth of the Dnieper, near Otchakof. An action took place on the Dniester on the 19th, when the troops of Prince Proso-rofskoi forced the Turks to repass the river in great disorder. Chotzim was taken on the 19th of September. Yassy, in Moldavia, was taken on the 27th of September. Bukarescht, in Wallachia, was taken, and the hospodar made prisoner, in November 1770. A victory was gained</p></body></text></TEI>