<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Dublin out of the hands of the English ; he made eight voyages to the West Indies, and ten to Brazil ; he was then promoted to the rank of rear-admiral, and sent to assist the Portuguese against the Spaniards. When the enemy came in sight, he advanced boldly to meet them, and gave such unquestionable proofs of valour as drew from the Portuguese monarch the warmest applause. His gallantry was still more conspicuous before Salee, a town of Barbary. With a single vessel he sailed through the roads of that place, in defiance of five Algerine corsairs who came to attack him.</p><p>In 1653 a squadron of seventy vessels was despatched against the English, under the command of Admiral Van Tromp. Ruyter, who accompanied the admiral in this expedition, seconded him with great skill and bravery in the three battles which the English so gloriously won. He was afterwards stationed in the Mediterranean, where he captured several Turkish vessels. In 1659 he received a commission to join the king of Denmark in his war with the Swedes ; and he not only maintained his former reputation, but even raised it higher. As a reward of his services, the king of Denmark ennobled him and gave him a pension. In 1661 he run ashore a vessel belonging to Tunis, released forty Christian slaves, made a treaty with the Tunisians, and reduced the Algerine corsairs to submission. His country, as a testimony of her gratitude for such illustrious services, raised him to the rank of vice-admiral and commander in chief. To the latter dignity, the highest that could be conferred upon him, he was well entitled by the signal victory which he obtained over the combined fleets of France and Spain. This battle was fought in 1672, about the time of the conquest of Holland. The battle was maintained between the English and Dutch with the obstinate bravery of nations which were accustomed to dispute the empire of the ocean. Ruyter having thus made himself master of the sea, conducted a fleet of Indiamen safely into the Texel ; thus defending and enriching his country, whilst it had become the prey of hostile invaders. The next year he had three engagements with the fleets of France and England, in which, if possible, his bravery was still more distinguished than ever. D’Estrées, the French vice-admiral, wrote to Colbert, “ <hi rend="italic">I</hi>  w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ould purchase with my life the glory of De Ruyter.” But he did not long enjoy the triumphs which he had so honourably won. In an engagement with the French fleet off the coast of Sicily, he was defeated and received a mortal wound, which in a few days put an end to his life. His corpse was carried to Amsterdam, and a magnificent monument to his memory was there erected by the command of the states-general. The Spanish council had bestowed on him the title of duke, and transmitted a patent investing him with that dignity ; but he died before it arrived. When Louis XIV. was congratulated upon De Ruyter’s death, he replied, “ Every one must be sorry at the death of so great a man.”</p><p>RYACOTTA, a town and celebrated fortress of the south of India, added to the Baramuhl district by the Marquis Cornwallis, in virtue of a treaty he concluded with Tip-poo. The fort is very strong by nature, and it has been further fortified by art, as this place is the chief key to Karna-ta. The air is so temperate here, from the elevation of the ground, that even in the hot season the thermometer scarcely ever rises higher than 82° of Fahrenheit. Ryacotta was besieged in 1791 by Major Gowdie ; and though it was of such strength, yet the garrison were intimidated by the spirited attacks of the besiegers, and surrendered, though amply supplied with guns, ammunition, and provision for its defence. It is ninety-eight miles east by north from Seringapatam. Long. 78. 1. E. Lat. 12. 33. N.</p><p>RYAGUDD, a town of Hindustan, possessed by independent zemindars, in the province of Orissa. It is sixty miles north-west from Cicacole. Long. 83. 27. E. Lat. 19. 1. N.</p><p>RYCHOOR, a town of Hindustan, in the nizam’s territories, and the province of Bejapoor. It is the capital of a district of the same name, and is 130 miles south-west from Hyderabad. It is an irregularly-built town, being an old fort with some new works. It is commanded by a hill, and by some rising grounds near it. Long. 77. 17. E. Lat. 15. 59. N. The district extends along the north bank of the Toombuddra river, between the 15th and 16th degrees of north latitude.</p><p>RYDE, a hamlet within the parish of Newchurch, in the Isle of Wight. It has become a place of some importance, from having of late years been the resort of numerous families for the purpose of sea-bathing. It is opposite to Portsmouth, and from its vicinity to Spithead has some trade in supplying fresh stock and vegetables to the ships of war. It is finely situated, and the bathing is good. The population in 1801 amounted to 2039, in 1811 to 2847, in 1821 to 3945, and in 1831 to 4928.</p><p>RYDROOG, a town and district of Hindustan, in the Balaghaut ceded territories. The town is 170 miles north by east from Seringapatam. Long. 77. 2. E. Lat. 14. 49. N. The district is situated principally between the 14th and 15th degrees of north latitude. The Hoggry is the chief river, and the principal towns are Rydroog and Mulkamarroor. This district was ceded to the Company in 1800, and a pension allowed to the polygar’s family, to whom it belonged.</p><p>RYE, a borough and seaport of the county of Sussex, in the hundred of Gostrow and rape of Hastings, 63 miles from London. It is a member of the Cinque Ports, but of a later date than the others. The harbour has been nearly choked up, partly by the recession of the sea, though it has been recently somewhat improved by a new cut. It was once fortified, but is ill built. It has a corporation, and returned two members to the House of Commons till 1832, since which it elects but one ; and its corporation, by the late law, consists of a mayor, four aldermen, and eleven councillors, but no justice of the peace. It has markets, which are held on Wednesday and Friday. The population amounted in 1821 to 3599, and in 1831 to 3715.</p><p>RYEPOOR, a town of Hindustan, in the province of Gundwana, and district of Choteesgur. This town, from its population and commerce, may be ranked amongst the first in the Choteesgur district. It contains 3000 huts, and has a stone fort on the north-east side of the town. It is sixty-nine miles from Ruttunpoor. Long. 82. 26. E. Lat. 21. 17. N.</p><p>RYLST, a city of Russia, in the government of Kursk, and the capital of a circle of the same name. It is built at the junction of the river Ryla with the Gem, and contains four stone and fourteen wooden churches, 840 houses, with 6300 inhabitants, who have considerable trade. It is 847 miles from St Petersburg. Long. 35. 3. E. Lat. 51. 35. N.</p><p>RYMER, Thomas, the author of that w'ell-known and important work the <hi rend="italic">Fadera,</hi>  was born in the north of England, and educated at the grammar-school of Northallerton. He was admitted a scholar at Cambridge, then became a member of Gray’s Inn, and at length was appointed historiographer to King William in place of Mr Shadwell. He wrote a View of the Tragedies of the last Age, and afterwards published a tragedy named Edgar. For a critic he was certainly not well qualified, for he wanted candour ; nor is his judgment much to be relied on, who could condemn Shakspeare with such rigid severity. His tragedy will show that his talents for poetry were by no means equal to those whose poems he has publicly censured. But though he has no title to the appellation of poet or critic, as an antiquarian and historian his memory will long be preserved. His <hi rend="italic">Foedera,</hi>  which is a collection of all public documents of the kings of England with foreign princes, is esteemed one of our most authentic and valuable records, and is oftener referred to by the best English historians than any other book in the language. It was published at London in the beginning of the eighteenth century, in se-</p></body></text></TEI>