<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>positions, nor so light in his touches, as Paul Veronese, in his carnations less true than Titian, and less delicate than</p><p>" Vandyck. Yet he contrived to give his colours the utmost transparency and harmony, notwithstanding their extraordinary deepness; and he possessed a strength and grandeur of style which were entirely his own. See the article Painting.</p><p>RUBIN, or ROBOAN, a small island in the Red Sea, at the Straits of Bahelmandel, separated from the continent by a channel not above a stone-cast in breadth, which may be forded at low water. Here pilots are taken in for the voyage up the Red Sea, and to its different ports.</p><p>RUBRIC, in the canon law, signifies a title or article in certain ancient law-books, and which was so called because written, as the titles of the chapters in our ancient bibles are, in red letters.</p><p>RUBY, a species of precious stone, belonging to the siliceous genus. The ruby is of various colours, as, of a deep red colour inclining a little to purple, or the carbuncle of Pliny ; the spinell, of the colour of a bright corn poppy flower; and the balass or pale red inclining to violet. Tavernier and Dutens inform us that in the East Indies all coloured gems are named rubies, without regard to what their colours may be ; and that the particular colour is added to the name of each in order to distinguish them from one another. The spinell rubies are above half the value of diamonds of the same weight; and the balass is valued at thirty shillings per carat. Tavernier mentions one hundred and eight rubies in the throne of the Great Mogul, from one to two hundred carats, and a round one almost two and a half ounces. There is also mention made by other travellers, of rubies exceeding two hundred carats in weight. According to Dutens, a perfect ruby, if it weigh more than three and a half carats, is of greater value than a diamond of the same weight. If it weigh one carat, it is worth ten guineas ; if two carats, forty guineas; three carats, a hundred and fifty guineas; if six carats, upwards of a thousand guineas.</p><p>RUCTATION, a ventosity arising from indigestion, and discharging itself at the mouth with a very disagreeable noise.</p><p>RUDBECK, Olaus, a learned Swedish physician, w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>as born of an ancient and noble family in 1630. He became professor of medicine at Upsal, where he acquired great applause by his extensive knowledge, and died in 1702. His principal works are twofold, 1.<hi rend="italic">Exercitatio Anatomica, ex-hibens ductus novos hepaticos aquosos, et vasa glandularum serosa,</hi>  in 4to; 2. <hi rend="italic">Atlantica, sive Manheim, vera Jopheti posterorum sedes ac patria,</hi>  four vols. folio. He there endeavours to prove that Sweden was the country whence all the ancient Pagan divinities and our first parents were derived ; and that the Germans, English, French, Danes, Greeks, and Romans, with all other nations, originally came from thence. This work, in a complete state, is of the greatest rarity.</p><p>RUDDER, in <hi rend="italic">Navigation,</hi>  a piece of timber turning on hinges in the Stem of the ship, and which, opposing sometimes one side in the water and sometimes another, turns or directs the vessel this way or that. See the article Shipbuilding.</p><p>RUDGELEY, a market-town in the county of Stafford, of the hundred of Cuttlestone, 131 miles from London, and seven from Lichfield. It is a well-built place, and contains many manufacturers of hats and of other articles ; and being, by meansof canals, favoured with water communication with the whole of the interior of the kingdom, has considerable trade. There is a good market, which is held on Tuesday. The population amounted in 1801 to 2030, in 1811 to 2213, in 1821 to 2677, and in 1831 to 3165.</p><p>RUDOLSTADT, a city, the capital of the principality of Schwarzburg-Rudolstadt, in Germany. It is situated on the river Saale, over which there is a stone bridge. It is surrounded with walls, is well built and paved, and contains 1 the palace of the prince, two churches, a theological semi-' nary, and two hospitals, with 550 houses, and 4160 inhabitants, who subsist by the expenditure of the government and the college, by making woollen goods, and by breweries and distilleries. Long. 11. 15. 15. E. Lat. 50. 43. 51. N.</p><p>RUDDIMAN, Thomas, one of the most eminent grammarians which Scotland has produced, was born in October 1674, at Raggel, in the parish of Boyndie and county of Banff’. His father, James Ruddiman, was a farmer, and strongly attached to the house of Stuart.</p><p>Mr Ruddiman was instructed in the principles of Latin grammar at the parish school of Boyndie, where his application was so vigorous, and his progress so rapid, that he quickly surpassed all his class-fellows. His master, George Morrison, who was a skilful and attentive teacher, being unwilling to check his ardour for learning, permitted him to follow the impulse of his genius, and to advance without waiting the slow progress of the other boys.</p><p>The pleasure which the youthful mind receives from vivid description, though wild and romantic, approaches to ecstasy, and often makes an impression which remains indelible. Whilst at school, the first book which charmed the opening mind of Ruddiman was Ovid’s Metamorphoses; nor did he cease to relish the beauties of this author when his judgment was mature, for during the rest of his life Ovid was his favourite poet.</p><p>At the age of sixteen he became anxious to pursue his studies at the university ; but his father thinking him too young, opposed his inclination. Hearing of the competition trial which was annually held at King’s College, Aberdeen, for a certain number of bursaries on the foundation of that university, Ruddiman’s ambition was kindled. Without the knowledge of his father, and with only a single guinea in his pocket, which his sister had privately given him, he set out for that place. On the road he was met by a company of gipsies, who robbed him of his coat, his shoes, his stockings, and his guinea. But this misfortune did not damp his enterprising spirit. He continued his journey to Aberdeen, presented himself before the professors as a candidate ; and, though he had neither clothes to give him a decent appearance, nor friends to recommend him, he gained the first prize.</p><p>After attending the university for four years, he obtained the degree of master of arts, an honour of which he was always proud. The thesis says, the disputation on this occasion lasted <hi rend="italic">ab aurora usque ad vesperum,</hi>  that is, “ from morning till night.” Though Ruddiman was only twenty years of age when he left the university, it appears from a book entitled <hi rend="italic">Rhetoricorum Libri tres,</hi>  composed before this period, but never published, that he had then read the Roman classics with uncommon attention and advantage.</p><p>He was soon after engaged as a tutor to the son of Mr Robert Young of Auldbar, the great grandson of Sir Peter Young, who under the direction of Buchanan had been preceptor of James VI. His income here must have been very small, or his situation unpleasant; for within a year he accepted the office of schoolmaster in the parish of Laurencekirk. The profession of schoolmaster in a country parish at that period could not open any field for ambition, nor any prospect of great emolument; for by an act of parliament passed in 1633, the salary appropriated to this office could not be increased above 200 merks Scotch, or L.ll. 2s. 2|d. sterling. In discharging the duties of this humble but important station, it is probable that he used Simson’s <hi rend="italic">Rudimenta Grammatica,</hi>  which was then generally taught in the northern schools, and by which he himself had been instructed in the principles of Latin grammar.</p><p>When Ruddiman had spent three years and a half in this employment, the celebrated Dr Pitcairne happening to pass through Laurencekirk, was detained in that village by a</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>