<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>1786.    The 29th of January, the empress confirmed the plan of a navigation school. February 12th, by a decree, the usual slavish subscriptions to petitions were to be discontinued ; and, instead of them, only the words <hi rend="italic">humble</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">faithful sulgect,</hi>  and in certain cases only <hi rend="italic">subject,</hi>  were ordained to be used. March 2d, the empress granted the university of Moscow a hundred and twenty-five thousand roubles, and all the materials of the palace Kremlin, for increasing its buildings. The 25th, a decree was passed for making and repairing the roads throughout the whole empire at the sole expense of the crown, and four millions of roubles were immediately allotted for the road between St Petersburg and Moscow. April 1 Oth, a new war establishment for the army was signed ; 23d, the hospodar of Wal-lachia was deposed, and Mavroyeni set up in his place. June 28th, the empress instituted a loan bank at St Petersburg, to the fund whereof she allotted twenty-two millions to be advanced to the nobility, and eleven millions to the burghers of the town, on very advantageous terms. August 5th, there were published rules to be observed in the public schools. October 4th, a large Russian ship, with Russian productions, from St Petersburg, arrived at Cadiz. November 24th, the empress erected public schools at Tambov. December 14th, Prince Ypsilanti was appointed hospodar of Moldavia, in the room of the deposed Maurocor-dato. December 31st, a treaty of commerce and navigation was concluded between Russia and France.</p><p>1787.    March, public schools were endowed and opened ■at Rostof, Uglitsh, Molaga, and Romanof, in the viceroyalty of Yaroslavl; also at Ustiug and Arasovitz, in the viceroyalty of Vologda. April 2lst, a manifesto was issued for promoting peace and concord among the burghers of the empire. The 25th, took place the concerted interview between the empress and the king of Poland, near the Polish town of Konief. The treaty of commerce with England being expired, the British factory were informed that they must henceforward pay the duties on imports in silver money, like the other nations who had no commercial treaty. May 7th, the empress hearing that the emperor of Germany was at Cherson, proceeded thither, and met him there on the 12th. June 28th, the twenty-fifth anniversary of her reign, she displayed various marks of her bounty. The debtors to the crown were forgiven, prisoners released, imposts taken off, soldiers rewarded, &amp;c. The 12th July, the new-built school at Riga, called a <hi rend="italic">Lyceum,</hi>  was solemnly dedicated. August 5th, Bulgakoff, the Russian ambassador at the Ottoman Porte, was imprisoned in the Seven Towers, contrary to the law of nations, which the empress regarded as a public declaration of war. 21st, The Turkish fleet at Otchakof attacked the Russian frigate Skorui and the sloop Bitingi, but was repulsed and put to flight by the bravery of the latter. Many signal advantages were gained over the Turks ; several public schools founded in various parts of the empire between this and August following, during which time the war broke out with Sweden.</p><p>1788.    August 12th, in the expedition beyond the Kuban, the Russian troops entirely routed a company of four thousand Arutayans and Alcasinians ; eight hundred of the enemy were slain, and five villages destroyed. 15tll, The surrender of the Turkish fortress of Dubitsha took place. 18th, The Turks made a violent sortie from Otchakof, but were repulsed by the Russian yagers, and, after a battle of four hours, were driven back with the loss of five hundred men. 23d, A fierce battle was fought between the Russian troops and Sacubanians<hi rend="sub">1</hi>  in which the latter lost a thousand men. The Russian fleet kept the Swedish blocked up in Sveaborg ever since the battle of July 6th. The Swedish army left the Russian territory in Finland. September 18th, The town and fortress of Chotzim surrendered to the Russians, with the garrison of two thousand men, a hundred and fifty-three cannon fourteen mortars, and much ammunition.</p><p>19th-29th, A small R ussian squadron from the fleet at Sevastopol, cruising along the coast of Anatolia, destroyed many of the enemy’s vessels, prevented the transporting of the Turkish troops, and returned with great booty. 20th, Us-senier Shamanachin, chief of the Bsheduchovians, was, on his petition, admitted a subject of Russia. 26th, A numerous host of Kubanians and Turks were beaten on the river Ubin, with the loss of fifteen hundred men. November 7th, Prince Potemkin, at the head of his Kozaks, took the island Beresan, with many prisoners and much ammunition. December 6th, the town and fortress of Otchakof were taken by Prince Potemkin Tavritsheskoi ; nine thousand five hundred and ten of the enemy were killed, four thousand taken prisoners, a hundred and eighty standards, three hundred and ten cannons and mortars. All the inhabitants were taken prisoners, amounting to twenty-five thousand ; the Russians lost nine hundred and fifty-six killed and eighteen hundred and twenty-four wounded. December 19th, General Kamenskoy gained considerable advantages over the TurJcs near Gangur.</p><p>1789.    April 16th, Colonel Rimskoy Korsakoff was sur-. rounded by the Turks, who were beaten, with great slaughter, by Lieutenant-General Von Derfelden. 17th-28th, ' Some Russian cruisers from Sevastopol effected a landing on ■ Cape Karakarman, burnt six mosques, and carried off great ∣ booty. 20th, General Derfelden drove the Turks from Ga-latch, gained a complete victory, killed two thousand, took fifteen hundred prisoners, with the seraskier Ibrahim Pasha, and the whole camp. Several skirmishes took place between the Russians and Swedes in Finland, always to the advantage of the former. May 31st, another victory was gained over the Swedes. June 5th, Sulkof was taken from the Swedes, and Fort St Michael on the 8th. July lôth, Admiral Tchitcha-goff engaged the Swedish fleet under the command of the Duke of Sudermania ; but no ship was lost on either side. 21st, A battle was fought at Fokshany, to the great loss of the Turks, and Fokshany was taken. August l3th, the Russian galley fleet fought the Swedish under Count Eh-renschwerdt, the former took a frigate and five other ships, and two thousand prisoners. August 21st, another sea-light took place, and Prince Nassau Siegen made good his landing of the Russian troops in sight of the king of Sweden at the head of his army. September 7th, Prince Rep-nin attacked the seraskier Hassan Pasha near the river Selt-ska, and took his whole camp, llth, Count Suwaroff and prince of Saxe-Cobourg engaged near the river Kymnik the grand Turkish army of nearly a hundred thousand men, and gained a complete victory ; from which Count Suwaroff received the surname Kymnikskoi. 14th, The Russian troops under General Ribas took the Turkish citadel Chod-shabey, in the sight of the whole of the enemy’s fleet. 30th, The fortress Palanka being taken, the town of Belgorod or Akjerman surrendered to Prince Potemkin Tavritsheskoi. November 4th, the town and castle of Bender submitted at discretion to the same commander.</p><p>1790.    April 24, General Numsen gained a victory over the Swedes near Memel. May 2, a sea-fight took place off Revel, in which the Russians captured the Prince Charles of sixty-four guns from the Swedes ; and in this engagement those two gallant English officers Captains Treven-nian and Dennison were killed. 23d, The fleet under Vice-Admiral Kruse engaged the Swedish fleet near the island Siskar in the Gulf of Finland, without any advantage being gained on either side, though they fought the whole day. 24th, An action was fought at Savataipala, when the Swedes were forced to fly. June 6th, the Swedes were defeated by Major Buxhovden, on the island Uransari. June 22, the whole Swedish fleet, commanded by the Duke of Suder-mania, was entirely defeated by Admiral Tchitchagoff and the Prince of Nassau Siegen ; on this occasion five thousand prisoners were taken, amongst whom were the centre admiral and two hundred officers. 28th, General Denisofl' defeated</p></body></text></TEI>