<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and the grain bought there is sent to Berwick for exportation to London. Λ considerable proportion is also sent to Dalkeith, and paid for by ready money. The carts that attend the Dalkeith market, on their return bring back coals or lime, which abound in that quarter. Bone manure, which is now getting into general use, is principally procured from Berwick. If either of the railways projected for connecting Newcastle and Edinburgh be carried into effect, it will be of great advantage to the county.</p><p>The towns are Kelso, Jedburgh, Hawick, and Melrose; and of the villages the most considerable are Yetholm and Kirk-Yetholm, near its eastern boundary. For notices of the towns, the reader is referred to them under their alphabetical heads. The two Yetholms are worthy of notice for their fairs, at which a great part of the cattle, sheep, and wool of the county are sold ; and Kirk-Yetholm is remarkable for being the principal colony of gipsies in Scotland. At Jedburgh, Kelso, Melrose, and the village of Gatton-side, there are some valuable orchards, particularly at Jedburgh and Melrose, where some very old trees which belonged to their abbeys are still remarkably prolific.</p><p>This county, placed on the borders of the two kingdoms, which were constantly at war with each other, presents the ruins of a great many castles and towers, and other remains, of an early age. Amongst these may be mentioned the Castles of Hermitage in Liddesdale ; Cessford in Eckford parish ; Ferniehirst near Jedburgh ; Brankholm on the banks of the Teviot, several miles above Hawick; and Harden, situated in Borthwick Vale, a mile from Hawick, formerly the seat of the Scotts of Harden. The site where the important Castleof Jedburgh stood is now occupied by a prison. The celebrated Catrail, erected by the Britons under the Roman yoke, and also the Roman road, both cross this county. Their remains can be distinctly traced. The county was also distinguished for its religious buildings, for which we refer to the articles Jedburgh, Kelso, and Melrose. The ancient burgh and town of Iloxburghe, which at one time was the fourth town in Scotland in importance and population, was situated on the beautiful peninsula formed by the junction of the Tweed and the Teviot rivers. It was regularly fortified by walls and ditches ; and although it cannot be traced to a remoter period than the reign of Alexander I., it is believed to have been a royal burgh before that time,</p><p>and, as such, governed by an alderman and inferior functionaries. It formed one of the court of four boroughs, which by the wisdom of David I. was instituted as a higher court, for hearing and deciding upon the appeals brought before them by the other royal burghs of the kingdom. Money was also coined here, and coins are yet to be seen in the depositories of antiquaries, of the date of William the Lion and James II. Situated as it was at the foot of one of the strongest castles on the border, it underwent many changes. It was several times burned by the English army, particularly in the years 1369 and 1460. This was the more easily accomplished from the buildings being almost entirely of wood ; and its restoration in a short time may be explained from the abundant supply of wood yielded by the forests which then covered the country. Its site has been partly used for centuries, and is still used, for holding the ancient fair of St James. During the summer of 1842, a considerable portion of the ancient foundations was uncovered by the plough. The castle of the same name was built on an eminence at the west end of the town. This eminence rises to the height of nearly forty feet above the level of the Teviot, which here runs at the south base of the castle. The waters of the river were made subservient to fill the deep fosse which surrounded the fortress on the west, north, and east sides, by means of a dam thrown obliquely across the stream. Only a few remains of what appear to be the outward defences are now standing, but by their thickness they attest its prodigious strength. The interior of the building is now so overgrown with tall trees, that it is impossible to give any idea of the formation of its defences within. What remains is most probably the foundations of the fort erected by the Earl of Somerset after his expedition into Scotland in the year 1547. But it is needless to enter into historical (acts connected with this fortress, as these will be given under the history of Scotland.</p><p>There are various fairs held in the county. The most important are, St Boswell’s, held on the l8th of July, for cattle, sheep, horses, linen and woollen cloth ; and St James’s, held on the 5th of August, for nearly the same articles as at St Boswell’s. There are also fairs held at Melrose, Yetholm, Hawick, Jedburgh, &amp;c.</p><p>The following is a tabular view of the population of the county in the years 1811, 1821, and 1831,</p><lb/><lb/><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">occupations.</hi></p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1"><p>PRRSON9.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>YEARS.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"/><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly em-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>All other Families not corn-</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Males.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="2"><p>Females.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inhabited.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Families.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Uninhabited.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>ployed in Agriculture.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Trade, Manufactures, and Handicraft.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>prised in the two preceding classes.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1811</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2173</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2849</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>88</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1268</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>797</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>784</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5,592</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6,786</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>12,378</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1821</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6587</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8639</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>269</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3613</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2822</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2204</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>19,408</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>21,484</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>40,892</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1831</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6732</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>8930</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>286</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3134</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2942</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2854</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>20,761</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>22,902</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>43,663</p></cell></row></table><p>Roxburghshire sends one member to Parliament ; and Jedburgh, its only royal burgh, joins with Lauder, Haddington, Dunbar, and North Berwick, in electing another. This is one of the few Scottish counties in which there are regular assessments for the poor. Amongst the eminent men to whom this district has given birth are, Thomson, Armstrong, Lord Karnes, Elliot the brave defender of Gibraltar, Leyden, Park the African traveller, and William Dawson the father of the improved agriculture of Scotland.</p><p>ROY BAREILLY, a town of Hindustan, in the nabob of Oude’s territories, situated on the Sye river, forty-five miles south-east by south from Lucknow. Long. 81.12. E. Lat. 26. 16. N.</p><p>ROYAL, something belonging to a king. Thus we say royal family, royal assent, royal exchange, and so forth.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RoyalFamily.</hi>  The first and most considerable branch of the king’s royal family, regarded by the laws of England, is the queen.</p><p>1. The Queen of England is either queen regent, queen consort, or queen dowager. The queen regent, regnant, or sovereign, is she who holds the crown in her own right ; as Queen Elizabeth, Queen Anne, and our present sovereign Queen Victoria. The queen consort is the wife of the reigning king; and she by virtue of her marriage is participant of divers prerogatives above other women. The husband of a queen regnant, as Prince George of Denmark</p></body></text></TEI>