<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0232-03" facs="gri_33125011196389_0238.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RICE</label>
. SeeθRYZA. “ Rice <hi rend="italic">bras,</hi> (ſays MrMarf∙ den) whilſt in the hulk, is in India called <hi rend="italic">paddee,</hi> and aſſumes a different name in each of its other various ſtates. We obſerve no diſtinction of this kind in Europe, where our grain retains through all its ſtages, till it becomes flour, its original name of barley, -wheat, or oats. The following, beſide many others, are names applied to rice, in its different ſtages of growth and preparation: <hi rend="italic">paddee,</hi> original name of the ſeed: <hi rend="italic">oojſay,</hi> grain of laſt ſeaſon : <hi rend="italic">buηηee,</hi> the plants before removed to the ſawoors : <hi rend="italic">bras</hi> or <hi rend="italic">bray,</hi> rice, the huſk of the paddee being taken off : <hi rend="italic">charroop,</hi> rice cleaned for boiling ; <hi rend="italic">naſſe,</hi> boiled rice : <hi rend="italic">peeraηg,</hi> yellow rice : <hi rend="italic">jambar,</hi> a ſervice of rice, &amp;c.</p><p>Among people whoſe general objects of contemplation are few, thoſe which do of neceſſity engage their attention, are often more nicely diſcriminated than the fame objects among more enlightened people, whoſe ideas ranging over the extenſive field of art and ſeience, diſdain to fix long on obvious and common matters.* <hi rend="italic">Paddee,</hi> on Sumatra and the Malay iſlands, is diftin-guiſhed into two ſorts ; <hi rend="italic">Laddang</hi> or up-land paddee, and <hi rend="italic">Saιvoor</hi> or low-land, which are always kept ſeparate, and will not grow reciprocally. Of theſe the former bears the higher price, being a whiter, heartier, and better flavoured grain, and having the advantage in point of keeping. The latter is much more prolific from the ſeed, and liable to leſs rifle in the culture, but is of a watery ſubſtance, produces leſs increaſe in boiling, and is ſubject to a ſwiſter decay. It is, however, in more common uſe than the former. Beſide this general diſtinction, the paddee of each fort, particularly the Laddang, preſents a variety of ſpecies, which, as far as my information extends, I ſhall enumerate, and endeavour to deſcribe. The common kind of dry ground paddee : colour, light brown : the ſize rather large, and very little crooked at the extremity. Paddee <hi rend="italic">undallong:</hi> dry ground : ſhort round grain : grows in whorles or bunches round the ſtock. Paddee <hi rend="italic">ebbaſs:</hi> dry ground : large grain : common. Paddee <hi rend="italic">gαlloo</hi> .∙ dry ground : light coloured : ſcarce. Paddee <hi rend="italic">ſennee :</hi> dry ground : deep coloured ; ſmall grain : ſcarce. Paddee <hi rend="italic">ejoo :</hi> dry-ground ; light coloured. Paddee <hi rend="italic">kooning :</hi> dry ground : deep yelfow : fine rice : crooked, and pointed. Paddee <hi rend="italic">coocoor ballum :</hi> dry ground : much eſteemed : light coloured ; ſmall, and very much crooked, reſetnbling a dove’s nail, ſrom whence its name. Paddee <hi rend="italic">peſang :</hi> dιy ground : outer coat light brown ; inner red : longer, ſmaller, and leſs crooked than the <hi rend="italic">coocoor ballum.</hi> Paddee <hi rend="italic">Saηtong :</hi> the fineſt ſort that is planted in wet ground : ſmall, ſtraight, and light coloured. In general it may be obſerved that the larger grained rice is the leaſt eſteemed, and the ſmaller and whiter the moſt prized. In the Lampoon country they make a diſtinction of paddee <hi rend="italic">cranυaηg</hi> and paddee <hi rend="italic">jerroo ;</hi> the former of which is a month earlier in growth than the latter.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">RιcB~Bird.</hi> See Oryzivera.</p><p><hi rend="italic">R ιcE-Bnnting.</hi> See Emberiza.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>