<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0242-06" facs="gri_33125011196389_0248.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RIGHT</label>
in geometry, ſignifies the ſame with ſtraight ; thus, a ſtraight line is called a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> one.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Right is a title conferred, 1. Together with</hi> <hi rend="italic">Reverend,</hi> upon all biſhops. 2. Together with <hi rend="italic">Honourable,</hi> upon earls, viſcounts, and barons. 3. By courtefy&gt; together with <hi rend="italic">Hoηoural(e,</hi> upon the ſons of dukes, mar-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0243" facs="gri_33125011196389_0249.tif"/>
<p>σuiffe3, and the eldeſt ſons of earls. 4. Together with <hi rend="italic">Honourable,</hi> to the ſpeaker of the houſe of commons ; but to no other commoner excepting thoſe who are members of his majeſty’s moſt honourable privy-council ; and the three lord mayors of London, York, and Dublin, and the lord provoſt of Edinburgh, during their office. See Honourable and PR0v0sτ.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Hereditary Right.</hi> See HeREDitλry.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Right is a word which, in the propriety of the Engliſh language, is uſed ſometimes as an adjective and ſometimes as a ſubſtantive. As an adjective it is nearly of the ſame import with</hi> <hi rend="italic">ft, ſuitable, becoming, proper ;</hi> and whilſt it expreſſes a quality, it indicates a relation*. Thus, when we ſay that an action is <hi rend="italic">right,</hi> we muſt not only know the nature of the action, but, if we ſpeak intelligibly, muſt alſo perceive its relation to the end for which it was performed ; for an action may be <hi rend="italic">right</hi> with one end in view which would be <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi> with another. The conduct of that general would be <hi rend="italic">right,</hi> who, to fave an army that could not be otherwiſe ſaved, ſhould place a ſmall detachment in a ſtation where he knew they would all be inevitably cut off ; but his conduct would be very <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi> were he to throw away the life of a ſingle individual for any purpoſe, however important, which he knew how <hi rend="sup">,</hi> to accompliſh without ſuch a ſacrifice.</p><p>Many philoſophers have talked of actions being <hi rend="italic">right</hi> and <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi> in the abſtract without regard to their natural conſequences ; and converting the word into a ſubſtantive, they have fancied an eternal rule of <hi rend="italic">right,</hi> by which the morality of human conduct is in every particular caſe to be tried. But in theſe phraſes we can diſcover no meaning. Whatever is <hi rend="italic">right</hi> muſt be ſo on <hi rend="italic">ſome account or other ;</hi> and whatever is <hi rend="italic">ft,</hi> muſt be fit for ſome <hi rend="italic">purpoſe.</hi> When he who reſts the foundation of virtue on the <hi rend="italic">moralſenſe,</hi> ſpeaks of an action being <hi rend="italic">right,</hi> he muſt mean that it is ſuch as, through the medium of that ſenſe, will excite complacency in the mind of the agent, and gain to him the general approbation of mankind. When he who reſts moral obligation on the will of God, ſpeaks of ſome actions as <hi rend="italic">right</hi> and of others as <hi rend="italic">wrong,</hi> he muſt mean that the former are agreeable to the divine will, however made known to men, and the latter diſagreeable to it ; and the man who deduces the laws of virtue from what he calls the <hi rend="italic">ftneſs of things,</hi> muſt have ſome <hi rend="italic">end in view,</hi> for which things are fit, and denominate actions <hi rend="italic">right</hi> or <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi> as they tend to promote or counteract that end.</p><p>But the word <hi rend="italic">right,</hi> uſed as a fubſtantive, has in common as well as in philoſophical language a ſignification •which at firſt view appears to be very different from this. &lt;It denotes a <hi rend="italic">juſt claim</hi> or an <hi rend="italic">honeſt poſſeſſon,</hi> Thus we ſay, a father has a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to reverence from his children, a •huſhand to the love and fidelity of his wife, and a king to the allegiance of his ſubjects. But if we trace theſe <hi rend="italic">rights</hi> to their ſource, we ſhall find that they are all laws of moral obligation, and that they are called <hi rend="italic">rights</hi> only becauſe it is agreeable to the will of God, to the in-ſtinctive dictates of the moral ſenſe, or to the fitneſs of things, if ſuch a phraſe has any meaning, that children reverence their parents, that wives love their huſhands, and that ſubjects pay allegiance to their ſovereign. This will be apparent to any man who ſhall put to himſelf ſuch queſtions as theſe : “ <hi rend="italic">Why</hi> have parents a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to Teverence from their children, huſhands to the love of</p><p>their wives, and ſovereigns to the allegiance of their ſubjects ?” As theſe queſtions contain in them nothing abſurd, it is obvious that they are each capable of a preciſe anſwer ; but it is impoſſible to give to any of them an anſwer which ſhall have any meaning, and not imply that <hi rend="italic">right</hi> arid <hi rend="italic">obligation</hi> are reciprocal, or, in other words, that wherever there is a <hi rend="italic">right</hi> in <hi rend="italic">one perſon,</hi> there is a correſponding <hi rend="italic">obligation</hi> upon <hi rend="italic">others.</hi> Thus to the queſtion, “ Why have parents a right to reverence from their children ?” it may be anſwered, “ be-caule, under God, they were the authors of their childrens being, and protected them from danger, and fur-niſhed them with neceſſaries,. when they were in a ſtate ſo helpleſs that they could do nothing for themſelves.” This anſwer conveys no other meaning than that there is an obligation upon children, in return for benefits received, to reverence their parents. But what is the ſource of this obligation ? It can only be the will of God, the moral ſenſe, or the fitneſs of things.</p><p>This view of the nature of right will enable us to form a proper judgment of the aiſertionof a late writer, “ that man has no rights.” The arguments by which this apparent paradox is maintained, are not merely ingenious and plauſible ; they are abſolutely concluſive. But then our philofoρher, who never chooſes to travel in the beaten track, takes the word <hi rend="italic">right</hi> in a ſenfe ve-ry different from that in which it has been uſed by all other men, andconſiders it as equivalent to <hi rend="italic">diſcretionary power,</hi> “ By the word <hi rend="italic">right</hi> (lays he) is underſtood a full and complete power of either doing a thing or omitting it, without the perſon’s becoming liable to ani-madverſion or cenſure from another ; that is, in other words, without lus incurring any degree of turpitude or guilt.” In this ſenſe of the word he affirms, and affirms truly, that a man has no rights, no diſcretionary power whatever, except in things of ſuch total indifference as, whether “ he ſhall fit on the right or on the left ſide of his fire, or dine on beef to day or tomorrow.”</p><p>A propoſition ſo evidently true as this ſtood not in need of argument to ſupport it ; but as his arguments are clearly expreſſed, and afford a complete confutation of ſome popular errors ſanctioned by the reſpectable phraſe <hi rend="italic">rights of man,</hi> we ſhall give our readers an opportunity of ſtudying them in his own words.</p><p>“ Political ſociety is founded on the principles of morality and juſtice. It is impoſſible for intellectual beings to be brought into coalition and intercourſe without a certain mode of conduct, adapted to their nature and connection, immediately becoming a duty incumbent on the parties concerned. Men would never have aſſociated il they had not imagined that, in conſequence of that aſlbciation, they would mutually conduce to the advantage and happineſs of each other.</p><p>I his is the real purpoſe, the genuine bafιs, of their intercourſe ; and, as far as this purpoſe is anſwered, ſo far does ſociety anſwer the end of its inſtſtution. There is only one poſtulate more that is neceſſary to bring us to a concluſive mode of reaſoning upon this ſubject. Whatever is meant by the term <hi rend="italic">right,</hi> there can neither be oppoſite rights, nor rights and duties hoſtile to each other. The rights of one man cannot claſh with or be deſtructive of the rights of another : for this, inſtead of rendering the ſubject an important branch of truth and morality as the advocates of the rights of man certain-</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0244" facs="gri_33125011196389_0250.tif"/>
<p>ly underſtaiid it to be, would be to reduce it to a heap of unintelligible jargon and inconliſtency. If one man have a right to be free, another man cannot have a right to make him a ſlave ; if one man have a right to inflict chaſtifement upon me, I cannot have a right to withdraw myſelf ſrom chaſtifement ; if my neighbour have a right to a ſum of money in my poſſeſſion, I cannot</p><p>. have a right to retain it in my pocket. It cannot be leſs incontrovertible, that I have no right to omit what my duty preſcribes. From hence it inevitably follows that men have no rights.</p><p>“ It is commonly ſaid, ‘ that a man has a right to the diſpoſal of his fortune, a right to the employment of his time, a right to the uncontrolled choice of his profeſſion or purfuits. <hi rend="sup">,</hi> But this can never be confidently affirmed till it can be ſhown that he has no duties, preſcribing and limiting his mode of proceeding in all theſe reſpects.</p><p>“ In reality, nothing can appear more wonderful to a careful inquirer, than that two ideas ſo incompatible as <hi rend="italic">man</hi> and <hi rend="italic">rights</hi> ſliould ever have been aſſociated toge-gether. Certain it is, that one of them muſt be utterly excluſive and annihilatory of the other. Before we aſcribe rights to man, we muſt conceive of him as a being endowed with intellect, and capable of diſcerning the differences and tendencies of things. But a being endowed with intellect, and capable of diſcerning the differences and tendencies of things, inſtantly becomes a moral being, and has duties incumbent on him to diſcharge : and duties and rights, as has already been ſhown, are abſolutely excluſive of each other.</p><p>“ It has been affirmed by the zealous advocates of liberty, ‘ that princes and magiſtrates have no rights ;’ and no poſition can be more incontrovertible. There is no ſituation of their lives that has not its correspondent duties. There is no power intruded to them that they are not bound to exerciſe excluſively for the public good. It is ſtrange, that perſons adopting this principle did not go a ſtep farther, and perceive that the ſame reſtrictions were applicable to ſubjects and citizens.”</p><p>This reaſoning is unanſwerable ; but it militates not againft the <hi rend="italic">rights of man</hi> in the uſual acceptation of the words, which are never employed to denote diſcretionary power, but a juſt claim on the one hand, implying a correſponding obligation on the other. Whether the phraſe be abſolutely proper is not worth the debating : it is authoriſed by cuſtom—the <hi rend="italic">jus et norma loquendi—</hi> and is univerſally underſtood except by ſuch as the dæ-mons of faction, in the form of paradoxical writers on political juſtice, have been able to miſlead by ſophiſtical reaſonings.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Rights,</hi> in the common acceptation of the word, are of various kinds : they are <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> or <hi rend="italic">adventitious, alienable</hi> or <hi rend="italic">unalienable, perfect</hi> or <hi rend="italic">imperſect, particular</hi> or <hi rend="italic">general.</hi> See the article LibeRty.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Natural</hi> rights are thoſe which a man has to his life, limbs, and liberty ; to the produce of his perſonal labour; to the uſe, in common with others, of air, light, and water, &amp;c. That every man has a natural right or juſt claim to theſe things, is evident ſrom their being abſolutely neceſſary to enable him to anſwer that purpoſe, whatever it may be, for which he was made a living and a rational being. This ſhows undeniably, that the Author of his nature deſigned that he ſhould have the uſe of them, and that the man who ſhould wantonly deprive him of any one of them, would be guilty of a breach of the divine law, as well as act inconſiſtently with the fitneſs of things in evere ſenſe in which that phraſe can poſſibly be underſtood.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Adventitious</hi> rights are thoſe which a king has over his ſubjects, a general over his ſoldicrs, a huſhand to the perſon and affections of his wife, and which every man has to the greater part of his property. That the rights of the king and the general are adventitious, is univerſally admitted. The rights of property have been conſidered elſewhere (ſee Property); and though the human conſtitution ſhows ſufficiently that men and women have a natural right to the uſe of each other, yet it is evident that the <hi rend="italic">excluſive</hi> right of any one man to any one woman, and <hi rend="italic">vice νerfα,</hi> muſt be an adventitious right : But the important queſtion is, How are adventitious rights acquired ?</p><p>In anſwer to this queſtion, the moraliſt who deduces the laws of virtue from the will of God, obſerves, that as God appears from his works to be a benevolent Being, who wills the happineſs of all his creatures (ſee Metaphysics, n <hi rend="sup">0</hi> 312.), he muſt of courſe will every thing which naturally tjnds to promote that happineſs» But the exiſtence of civil ſociety evidently contributes in a great degree to promote the ſum of human happineſs (ſee Society) ; and therefore whatever is neceſſary for the ſupport of civil ſociety in general, or for the conduct of particular ſocieties already eſtabliſhed, muſt be agreeable to the will of God : But the allegiance of ſubjects to their ſovereign, the obedience of ſoldiers to their leader, the protection of private property, and the fulfilling of contracts, are all abſolutely neceſſary to the ſupport of ſociety: and hence the rights of kings, generals, huſhands, and wives, &amp;c. though adventitious, and immediately derived ſrom human appointment, are not leſs ſacredthan natural rights, ſince tney may all be ultimately traced to the ſame ſource. The ſame concluſion may eaſily be drawn by the philoſopher, who reſts moral obligation on the fitneſs of things or on a moral ſenſe; only it muſt in each of theſe caſes partake of the inſtability of its foundation.</p><p>To the ſacredneſs of the rights of marriage, an author already quoted has lately urged ſome declamatory objections. “ It is abſurd (ſays he) to expect, that the inclinations and wiſhes of two human beings ſhould coincide through any long period of time. To oblige them to act and to live together, is to ſubject them to ſome inevitable portion of thwarting, bickering, and unhappineſs. Ί his cannot be otherwiſe, ſo long as man has failed to reach the ſtandard of abſolute perfection. The ſuppofition that I muſt have a companion for life, is the reſult of a complication of vices. It is the dictate of cowardice, and not of fortitude. It flows from the deine of being loved and eſteemed for ſome-thing that is not deſert.</p><p>“ But the evil of marriage, as it is practiſed in European countries, lies deeper than this. The habit is, for a thoughtleſs and romantic youth of each ſex to come together, to ſee each other for a few times, and under circumſtances full of deluſion, and then to vow to each other eternal attachment. What is the conſequence of this? In almoſt every inſtance they find themſelves deceived. They are reduced to make the bell of an irretrievable miſtake. They are preſented with the ſtrongeſt imaginable temptation to become the dupes</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0245" facs="gri_33125011196389_0251.tif"/>
<p>of falſchood. They are led to conceive it their wtſeſt policy to ſhut their eyes upon realities; happy if by any perverſion of intellect they can perſuade themſelves that they were right in their firſt crude opinion of their companion.</p><p>“ So long as two human beings are forbidden by poſitive inſtitution to follow the dictates of their own mind, prejudice is alive and vigorous. So long as I ſeek to engroſs one woman to myſelf, and to prohibit my neighbour ſrom proving his ſuperior deſert and reaping the fruits of it, I am guilty of the moſt odious of all monopolies. Over this imaginary prize men watch with perpetual jealouſy ; and one man will find his de-ſires and his capacity to circumvent as much excited, as the other is excited to traverſe his projects and fruſtrate his hopes. As long as this ſtate of ſociety continues, philanthropy will be crcſſed and checked in a thouſand ways, and the ſtill augmenting ſtream of abuſe will continue to flow.</p><p>“ The abolition of marriage will be attended with no evils. The intercourſe of the ſexcs will fall under the ſame ſyſtem as any other ſpecies of friendſhip. Excluſively of all groundleſs and obſtinate attachments, it will be impoſſible for me to live in the world without finding one man of a worth ſuperior to that of any other whom I have an opportunity of obſerving. To this man I ſhall feel a kindneſs in exact proportion to my apprehenſion of his worth. The caſe will be pre-ciſely the ſame with reſpect to the ſemale ſex ; I ſhall aſſiduouſly cultivate the intercourse of that woman whoſe accompliſhments ſhall ſtrike me in the moſt poweiſſul manner. ‘ But it may happen that other men will feel for her the ſame preference that I do.’ This will create no difficulty. We may all enjoy her converſa-tion ; and we ſhall all be wile enough to conſider the ſtnſual intercourse as a very trivial object. This, like every other affair in which two perſons are concerned, muſt be regulated in each ſucceſſive inſtance by the unforced coulent of either party. It is a mark of the extreme depravity of our preſent habits, that we are inclined to ſuppoſe the ſenſual intercourſe anywiſe material to the advantages ariſing from the pureſt affec tion. Reaſonable men now eat and drink, not from the love of pleaſure, but becauſe eating and drinking are effential to our healthful exiſtence. Reaſonable men then will propagate their ſpecies, not becauſe a certain ſenſible pleaſure is annexed to this action, but becauſe it is right the ſpecies ſhould be propagated ; and the manner in wdrch they exerciſe this function will be regulated by the dictates of reaſon and duty.”</p><p>It is right then, according to this political innovator, that the ſpecies ſhould be propagated, and reaſonable men in his Utopian commonwealth would be inci∣cd by reaſon and duty to propagate them : but the way to fulbl this duty, experience, which is ſeldom at one with ſpeculative reformation, has already demonſtrated, not to conſiſt in the promiſcuous intercourſe of ſeveral men with one woman, but in the fidelity of individuals of the t∖*.o ſexes to each other. Common prtfſtitutes among us ſeldom prove with child ; and the ſociety of <hi rend="italic">Arreoys</hi> in Otaheitee, who have completely diveſted themſelves of what our author calls <hi rend="italic">prejudice,</hi> and are by no means guilty of his <hi rend="italic">maſt odious cſ all monopolies,</hi> are for the moſt part childleſs (ſee Otaheitee). He ſeems to think that a ſtate of equal property would ne-</p><p>ceſſitrily deſtroy our reliſh for luxury, dtcreaſe our inordinate appetites of every kind, and lead us univerſally to prefer the pleaſures of intellect to the pleaſures of ſenſe. But here again experience is againft him. The <hi rend="italic">Arreοys,</hi> who have a property in their women perfectly equal, are the moſt luxurious and ſenſual wretches on the face of the earth ; ſenſual indeed to a degree of which the moſt libidinous European can hardly form a conception.</p><p>By admitting it to be a duty to propagate the ſpecies, our author muſt neceſſarily grant that every thing is right which is requilite to the fulfilling of that duty, and the contrary wrong. If ſo, promiſcuous concubinage is wrong, ſince we have ſeen, that by a law of nature it is incompatible with the duty ; whence it follows on his own principles, that the ſexual union by pairs ' muſt be right. The only queſtion therefore to be decided between him and his opponents is, “ Whether ſhould that union be temporary or permanent ?” And we think the following obſervations by Mr Paley ſufficient to decide it to the conviction of every perſon not blinded by the rage of innovation.</p><p>“ A lawgiver, whoſe counrſels were directed by views of general utility, and obſtructed by no local impediments, would make the marriage-contract indiſſoluble during the joint lives of the parties, for the fake of the following advantages: Such a union tends to preſerve peace and concord between married perſons, by perpetuating their common intereſt, and by inducing a ne-ceſſity of mutual compliance. An earlier termination of it would produce a ſeparate intereſt. The wife would naturally look forward to the diſſolution of the partnerſhip, and endeavour to draw to herſelf a fund again!! the time when ſhe was no longer to have acceſs to the ſame reſources. This would beget peculation on one ſide, and miſtruſt on the other ; evils which at preſent very little diſturb the confidence of married life. The ſecond effect of making the union determinable only by death, is not leſs beneficial. It neceſſarily happens, that adverſe tempers, habits, and taſtes, oftentimes meet in marriage. In which caſe, each party muſt take pains to give up what offends, and practice what may gratiſy, the other. A man and woman in love with each other do this inſenſibly : but love is neither general nor durable ; and where that is wanting, no leffons of duty, no delicacy of ſentiment, will go half ſo far with the generality of mankind and womankind as this one intelligible reflection, that they muſt each make the beſt of their bargain ; and that ſeeing they muſt either both be miſerable or both ſhare in the ſame happineſs, neither can find their own comfort but in promoting the pleaſure of the other. Theſe compliances, though at firſt extorted by neceſſity, become in time eaſy and mutual; and though leſs endearing than aſſiduities which take their riſe from affection, generally procure to the married pair a repoſe and ſatisfaction ſufficient for their happinels.”</p><p>So differently from our author does this judicious writer reaſon concerning the effects of-a permanent union on the tempers of the married pair. Inſtead of ſubjecting them to ſome inevitable portion of thwarting, bickering, and unhappineſs, it lays them, in his opinion, under the neceſſity of curbing their unruly paſſions, and acquiring habits of gen tleneſs, forbearance, and peace. To this we may add, that both believing</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0246" facs="gri_33125011196389_0252.tif"/>
<p>the children propagated during their marriage to be their own (a belief unattainable by the father in a ſtate of promiſcous concubinage), they come by a natural proceſs of the human paſſions (ſee Passion) to love each other through the medium of their offspring. But if it be the duty of man to acquire a ſpirit firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſy to be intreated, it muſt be agreeable to the will of God, and a branch of the fitneſs of things, that the ſexual union laſt during the joint lives of the parties ; and therefore the excluſive right of marriage, though adventitious, muſt be equally ſacred with thoſe which are natural.</p><p>But to return from this digreiſion, into which the importance -of the ſubject led us, <hi rend="italic">rights,</hi> beſides being natural or adventitious, are likewiſe <hi rend="italic">alienable</hi> or <hi rend="italic">unalienable.</hi> Every man, when he becomes the member of a civil community, alienates a part of his natural rights. In a ſtate of nature, no man has a ſuperior on earth, and each has a right to defend his life, liberty, and property, by ail the means which nature has put in his power. In civil ſociety, however, theſe rights are all transferred to the laws and the magiſtrate, except in caſes of ſuch extreme urgency as leave not time ſor legal interpoſition. This ſingle conſideration is ſufficient to ſhow, that the right to civil- liberty is alienable ; though, in the vehemence of men’s zeal ſor it, and in the language of ſome political remonſtrances, it has often been pronounced to be an unalienable right. “ The truc reaſon (ſays Mr Paley) why mankind hold in deteſtation the memory of thoſe who have fold their liberty to a tyrant is, that, together with their own, they fold commonly or endangered the liberty of others; of which they had certainly no right to-diſpoſe.” The rights of a prince over his people, and of a huſhand over his wife, are generally and naturally unalienable.</p><p>Another diviſion of rights is into thoſe which are perfect and thoſe which are imperfect. Perfect rights are ſuch as may be preciſely aſcertained and aſſerted by force, or in civil ſociety by the courſe of law. To imperfect rights neither .force nor law is applicable. A man’s rights to his life, perſon, and property, are all perfect ; for if any of theſe be attacked, he may repel the attack by inſtant violence, puniſh the aggreſſor by the courſe of law, or compel the author of the injury to make reſtitution or ſatisfaction. A woman’s right to her honour is likewiſe perfect ; for if ſhe can-Hθt otherwiſe eſcape, ſhe may kill the raviſher. Every poor man has undoubted right to relief from the rich : but his right is imperfect, ſor if the relief be not voluntarily given, he cannot compel it either by law or by violence. There is no duty upon which the Chriſtian religion puts a greater value than alms-giving ; and every preacher of the goſpel has an undoubted right to inculcate the practice of it upon his audience : but even this right is imperfect, for he cannot refuſe the communion to a man merely on account of his illiberality to the poor, as he can to another for the neglect of any duty comprehended under the term juſtice. In elections or apppointments to offices, where the qualifications are preſcribed, the beſt qualified candidate has un-queſtionably a right to ſucceſs ; yet if he be rejected, he can neither ſeize the office by force, nor obtain re-dreſs at law. His right, therefore, is imperfect.</p><p>Here a queſtion naturally offers itſelf to our conſideration : “ How comes a perſon to have a right to a thing,</p><p>and yet have no right to uſe the means neceſſary to obtain it ?” The anſwer is, That in ſuch caſes the object or the circumſtances of the right are ſo indeterminate, that the permiſſion of force, even where the right is real and certain, would lead to force in other caſes where there exiſts no right at all. Thus, though the poor man has a right to relief, who ſhall aſcertain the mode, ſeaſon, and quantum of it, or the perſon by whom it ſhall be adminiſtered ? Theſe things muſt be aſcertained before the right to relief can be enforced by law ; but to allow them to be aſcertained by the poor themſelves, would be to expoſe property to endleſs claims. In like manner, the comparative qualifications of the candidate muſt be aſcertained, before he can enforce his right to the office ; but to allow him to aſcertain his qualifications himſelf, would be to make him judge in his own cauſe between himſelf and his neighbour.</p><p>Wherever the right is imperfect on one ſide, the cor-reſponding obligation on the other muſt be imperfect likewiſe. The violation of it, however, is often not leſs criminal in a moral and religious view than of a perfect obligation. It is well obſerved by Mr Paley, that greater guilt is incurred by diſappointing a worthy candidate of a place upon which perhaps his livelihood depends, and in which he could eminently ſerve the public, than by filching a book out of a library, or picking a pocket of a handkerchief. The ſame ſentiment has been expreſſed by Mr Godwin, but in terms by much too ſtrong, and ſuch as ſhow that he was not at the time complete maſter of his ſubject. “ My neighbour (ſays he) has juſt as much right to put an end to my exiſtence with dagger or poiſon, as to deny me that pecuniary aſſiſtance without which I mult ſtarve, or as to deny me that aſſiſtance without which my intellectual attainments, or my moral exertions, will be materially injured. He has juſt as much right to arauſe himſelf with burning my houſe, or torturing my children .upon the rack, as to ſhut himſelf up in a cell, careleſs about his fellow- men, and to hide ‘ his talent in a napkin.”</p><p>It is certainly true, that the man who ſhould ſuffer another to ſtarve for want of that relief which he <hi rend="italic">knew</hi> that he <hi rend="italic">alone</hi> could afford him, would be guilty of murder, and murder of the cruelleſt kind ; but there is an immenſe difference between depriving ſociety of one of its members, and with-holding from that member what might be neceſſary to enable him to make the greateſt poſſible intellectual attainments. Newton might have been uſeful and happy though he had never been acquainted with the elements of mathematics ; and the late celebrated Mr Ferguiſon might have been a valuable member of ſociety, though he had never emerged from lus original condition of a ihepherd. The remainder of the paragraph is too abſurd to require a formal confutation. Had our author, burying his talent in a napkin, ſhut himſelf up ſeven years ago in a cell, careleſs about his fellow men and <hi rend="italic">political jaſtice,</hi> he would have deprived the public of what he doubtleſs believes to be much uſeful inſtruction ; but had he at that period amuſed himſelf with burning his neighbour’s houſe, and torturing on the rack two or three children, he would have cut off, for any thing he could know, two or three future Newtons, and have himſelf been cut off by the inſulted laws of his country. Now, without ſuppoling the value</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0247" facs="gri_33125011196389_0253.tif"/>
<p>of ten Newtons to be equal to that of one Godwin, we are warranted to ſay, that however great his merits may be, they are not infinite, and that the addition of thoſe of one Newton to them would undoubtedly increaſe their ſum.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Righes,</hi> are particular or general. Particular rights are ſuch as belong to certain individuals or orders of men, and not to others. The rights of kings, of mailers, of huſhands, of wives, and, in ſhort, all the rights which originate in fociety, are particular. General rights are thoſe which belong to the ſpecies collectively. Such are our rights to the vegetable produce of the earth, and to the fleſh of animals for food, though about the origin of this latter right there has been much diverfity of opinion, which we have noticed in another place. (See Theology, Parti, ſect. 2d). If the vegetable produce of the earth be included under the general rights of mankind, it is plain that he is guilty of wrong who leaves any conſiderable portion of land waſte merely for his own amuſement : he is leſſening the common llock of proviſion which Providence intended to diſtribute among the ſpecies. On this principle it would not be eaſy to vindicate certain regulations· re -ſpecting game, as well as ſome other monopolies which are protected by the municipal laws of moſt countries. Mr Paley, by juſt reaſoning, has eſtabliſhed this conclu-fion, “ that nothing ought to be ‘made excluſive property which can be conveniently enjoyed in common.” An equal diviſion of land, however, the dream of ſome viſionary reformers, would be injurious to the general rights of mankind, as it may be demonſtrated, that it would leſſen the common ſtock of proviſions, by laying every man under the neceſſity of being his own weaver, tailor, ſhoemaker, ſmith, and carpenter, as well as ploughman, miller, and baker. Among the general rights of mankind is the right of <hi rend="italic">neceſſity ;</hi> by which a man may uſe or deſtroy his neighbour’s property when it is abſolutely neceſſary for his own preſervation. It is on this principle that goods are thrown overboard to ſave the ſhip, and houſes pulled down to ſtop the pro-greſs of a fire. In ſuch caſes, however, at leaſt in the laſt,reſtitution ought to be made when it is in our power; but this reſtitution will not extend to the original value of the property deſtroyed, but only to what it was worth at the time of deſtroying it, which, conſidering its danger, might be very little.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>