<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0310-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0316.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROBINS</label>
(Benjamin), a moſt ingenious mathematician, was born at Bath in 1707. His parents were Quakers, and of low condition, conſequently neither able nor willing to have him much inſtructed in human learning. Nevertheleſs his own propenlity to ſcience procured him a recommendation to Dr Pemberton at London ; by whoſe aſſiſtance, while he attained the ſublimer parts of mathematical knowledge, he commenced teacher of the mathematics. But the buſineſs of teaching, which required confinement, not ſuiting his active diſpoſition, he gradually declined it, and engaged in buſineſs that required more exerciſe. Hence he tried many laborious experiments in gunnery, from the per-ſuaſion that the reſiſtance of the air has a much greater influence on ſwift projectiles than is generally imagined. Hence alſo he was-led to conſider the mechanic arts that depend on mathematical principles ; as the conſtruction of mills, the building of bridges, the draining of fens, the rendering of rivers navigable, and the making of harbours. Among other arts, fortification much engaged his attention ; and he met with opportunities pi perfecting himſelf by viewing the principal ſtrong places of Flanders, in ſome tours he made abroad with perſons of diſtinction.</p><p>Upon his return from one of theſe excurſions, he</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r02-0311" facs="gri_33125011196389_0317.tif"/>
<p>found the learned atnuſed with Dr Berkeley’s work, intitled <hi rend="italic">The Analyfi,</hi> in which an a <hi rend="sup">t</hi> ttempt was made to explode the method of fluxions. Mr Robins was therefore adviſed to clear up this affair by giving a diſtinct account of Sir Iſaac Newton’s doctrines, in ſuch a manner as to obviate all the objections that had been made without naming them. Accordingly he publiſhed, in l 735, A Diſcourſe concerning the Nature and Certainty of Sir Iſaac Newton’s Method of Fluxions : and ſome exceptions being made to his manner of defending Sir Iſaac Newton, he afterwards wrote two or three additional diſcourſes. In 1738 he defended the ſame great philoſopher againſt an objection contained in a note at the end of a Latin piece, called <hi rend="italic">Mαthn, five Coſmothsoria puerilis ;</hi> and the following year printed Remarks on M. Euler’s Treatiſe of Motion, on Dr Smith’s Syſtem of Optics, and on Dr Jurin’s Diſcourſe of diſtinct and indiſtinct λ <hi rend="sup">z</hi> ifion annexed to Dr Smith’s work. In the meanwhile, Mr Robins did not ſolely confine himſelf to mathematical ſubjects: for iιi 1739 he publiſhed three pamphlets on political affairs, without his name ; when two or them, relating to the convention and négociations with Spain, were ſo univer-ſally eſteemed, as to occaſion his being employed in a very honourable poll ; for on a committee being appointed to examine into the paſt conduct of Sir Robert Walpole, he was choſen their ſecretary.</p><p>In 1742, Mr Robins publiſhed a ſmall treatiſe, in-titled <hi rend="italic">New Principles of Gunnery·,</hi> containing the reſult of many experiments ; when a Diſcourſe being publiſhed in the Philoſophical Tranſactions, in order to invalidate ſome of his opinions, he thought proper, in an account he gave of his book in the fame Tranſactions, to take notice of thoſe experiments ; in conſequence of which, ſeveral of his Diſſertations on the Reſiſtance of the Air were read, and the .experiments exhibited before the Royal Society, for which he was preſented by that honourable body with a gold medal.</p><p>In 1748 appeared Lord Anſon’s Voyage round the World, which, though Mr Walter’s name is in the title, has been generally thought to be the work of Mr Robins. Mr Walter, chaplain on board the Centurion, had brought it down to his departure from Macao for England, when he propoſed to print the work by ſubſcription. It was, hpvyever, it is ſaid, thought proper, that an able judge ſhould review and correct it, and Mr Robins was appointed ; when, upon examination, it was reſolved that the whole ſhould be written by Mr Robins, and that what Mr Walter had done ſhould only ſerve as materials. Hence the introduction entire, and many diſſertations in the body of the work, it is ſaid, were compoſed by him, without receiving rhe leaſt aſſiſtance ſrom Mr AValter’s manuſcript,which chiefly 1 elated to the wind and the weather, the currents, courſes, bearings, diſtances, the qualities of the ground on which they anchored, and ſuch particulars as, generally fill up a ſailor’s account. No production of this kind ever met with a more ſavourable reception ; four large impreſſions were ſold within a twelvemonth ; and it has been tranſlated into moſt of the languages of Europe. The fifth edition, printed at London in 1 749, vyas reviſed and corrected by Mr Robins himſelf. It appears, however, from the corrigenda and addenda to the iſt volume of the Biographia Britannica, printed in the beginning of the fourth volume of that work, that</p><p>Mr Robins was only conſulted with reſpect to the diſ-poſition of the drawings, and that he had left England before the book was printed. Whether this be the fact, as it is aſſerted to be by the widow of Mr Walter, it is not for us to determine.</p><p>It is certain, however, that Mr Robins acquired the fame, and he was ſoon after deſired to compoſe an apology for the unfortunate affair at Preſtonpans in Scotland, which was prefixed as a preface to The Report of the Proceedings of the Board of General Officers on their Examination into the Conduct of Lieutenant-General Sir John Cope ; and this preface was eſteemed a maſterpiece in its kind. He afterwards, through the intereſt of Lord Anion, contributed to the improvements made in the Royal Obſervatory at Greenwich. Having thus eſtabliſhed his reputation, he was offered the choice of two conſiderable employments ; either to-go to Paris as one of the commiſſarie? for adjnſting the limits of Arcadia, or to be engineer-general to the Eaſt India company. He choſe the latter, and arrived in the Eaſt Indies in 1750; but the climate not agreeing with his conſtitution, he died there the year following.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>