<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:42:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>city and suburbs of Shanghai amounts to 156,000. When to this number the boat population, amounting to 11,000, and the mixed inhabitants of the foreign settlements, numbering 145,500, are added, a total is reached of 312,500 souls.</p><p>The vastness of English interests in China and the large British population at Shanghai gave rise in 1865 to the establishment of a British supreme court for China and Japan,—Sir Edmund Hornby, who was then the judge of the British court at Constantinople, being the first judge appointed to the new office. The court thus constituted not only exercises jurisdiction over the British subjects at Shanghai but acts as a court of appeal from all British consular courts in China and Japan. All charges against Chinamen within the settlement are tried before a mixed court, which sits daily, presided over by a Chinese official and an officer of the consular service. During the year 1884 2,304 criminal cases were tried before this tribunal, and 99 civil cases,—in 85 of which cases no less a sum than £60,000 was involved.</p><p>A handsome bund runs along the river frontage of the three foreign settlements, and the public buildings, especially in the British settlement, are large and fine. The cathedral, which is built in the Gothic style, is a notable example of Sir Gilbert Scott’s skill as an architect, and the municipal offices, club-house, and hospitals are all admirable in their way. Shanghai is now connected with Peking by a telegraph, which will doubtless before long be supplemented by a railway. Some years ago a short railway was laid down between Shanghai and Woosung by some foreigners who wished to force the pace at which China was progressing. But the time had not come when such a step would be adopted by the Chinese, and after a few weeks’ existence the plant was bought by the native authorities and shipped to Formosa, where it has since been allowed to rust and rot. The climate of Shanghai is essentially unhealthy. It lies low, and, though the early winter is enjoyable, snow and ice being occasionally seen, the summer months are swelteringly hot. Fever, dysentery, and cholera are unfortunately common complaints, and it is only by frequent trips to Japan and Chefoo that the residents are able to preserve health and strength. But, notwithstanding every disadvantage, the position occupied by Shanghai as a centre of trade, situated as it is at the mouth of the Yang-tsze-kiang, in the immediate neighbourhood of the richest silk and tea districts, and in proximity to Japan and the newly-opened ports of Corea, insures for it an increasing volume of commerce and a widening prosperity in the future.	(R. K. D.)</p><p>SHANNON. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ireland,</hi> vol. xiii. p. 216.</p><p>SHANS. This name is applied to a number of for the most part semi-independent communities occupying a region bounded on the W. by Burmah and Assam, N. and N.E. by the Chinese province of Yun-nan, E. by Tong- king, and S. by Siam (see Plate IX.). Ethnologically the race has a much wider extension, including the Siamese (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Siam),</hi> and also, according to Garnier and Colquhoun, the hill tribes around the Tong-king delta and various tribes of Kwang-tung and Kwang-se, and extending across the north of Burmah into Assam. It is also widely diffused through south-western Yun-nan. Terrien de Lacouperie considers it allied to the Mon, the Mung, and the Pa, and places its early home in the mountains north of Sze-chuen, whence, not having amalgamated with the growing Chinese empire, it was gradually forced southwards. Although the level of civilization and the purity of their Buddhism vary considerably among the different branches of the race, there is everywhere a remarkable resemblance in appearance, manners, customs, and polity. The traditions current of their origin, too, though localized by each in its own habitat, are closely similar. This great homogeneity seems the more remarkable in that the race is found not only living under many different political systems,—<hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> either independent, or subject to Burmah, China, or Siam,—but often in communities isolated by mountain ranges, inhabited by tribes of different race and character. All this seems to point to a political unity in earlier times.</p><p>The Shans probably appeared on the upper Irawadi nearly two thousand years ago, but Burmese and Shan traditions agree that they were established some centuries earlier on the upper waters of the Shweli and on the Salwín and adjacent valleys on the south-west frontiers of Yun-nan. Here, at all events, in the 7th and 8th cen</p><p>turies, we hear of the growth of that power which, temporarily broken by Burmah in the 11th century, reached its highest development in the 13th. This Shan empire, known by the classical Indian name of Kausambi, —corrupted after the punning Chinese fashion into Ko- shan-pyi, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> nine Shan states,—was a confederacy of about ten states, known among themselves by the name of the most powerful member, Mau, or Muang Mau. A great leader, Sam Lung Pha, brother of the king of Mau, overran and conquered Upper Assam from the Satiyas in 1229, the dynasty lasting until the British annexation. These Ahorns still inhabit the Assam districts of Sibsagar and south and east Lakhimpur, though pressed on from the south-west by the Bengalis, whom they despise as a black and inferior race, preferring to associate with the Chinese, whom they regard as congeners, and as the greatest race in the world.</p><p>This 13th and the following century also saw Tali to the east and Arakan to the west invaded, Burmah being then weakened by the Mongol invasion ; Chieng Mai and other southern Shan states were also annexed, and “ Ayuthia ” (<hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>., Siam), Cambodia, and Tavoy are claimed by the Shan historians as among their conquests, the Shan influence being felt even in Java. From the 14th to the 16th century wars with both Burmah and China were frequent, and Shan dynasties ruled at times in Burmah ; but in 1556-62 the Burmese conquered Mogaung, the chief province of Mau, when Buddhism is recorded to have been introduced : probably only a reform of religion is meant. In 1604 the districts now known as the Chinese Shan States, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> the heart of the Mau empire, lying chiefly in the Ta-peng basin, east of Bamo,—a town whose population also is mainly Shan,—were finally conquered by China, Mogaung remaining independent on sufferance till absorbed by Burmah in 1796.</p><p>Zimmé or Chieng Mai (including Kiang Hai, Kiang Sen, Lagong, and Lapong), whose capital is now an important and well-built town, and Vien Chang on the east of the Me-kong, were both great Shan centres, warring, with various fortunes, with Burmah and Cambodia and with each other, till subjected by the growing power of Siam late in the last century.</p><p>The Burmese Shan States, especially those more remote from Mandalay, have latterly become practically independent; and, the tyranny which led to extensive southward migration having thus ceased, the stream is partly returning northwards. Descendants, too, of the population deported by Siam from Kiang Sen about a hundred years ago are now by the king’s permission returning to people that fertile territory. The Burmese plan with the Shans was to govern by fostering internal dissensions, and they are bitterly hated, while the Chinese are in an equal degree liked and respected. The great Shan state of Kiang Hung has now accepted the dictation of China, to whom in fact, like some of its lesser neighbours, it has always paid certain taxes, while acknowledging the supremacy of Burmah. Kiang Tung to the south, which has been Burmese for over a century, has lately made overtures to Siam, though not forgetting the injuries inflicted by that power in 1854. The numerous ruins of great cities over the whole region from Chieng Mai to Kiang Tung testify to former wealth and prosperity, though they may not have all existed contemporaneously. In Luang Pra- bang in the north-east, on the other hand, tribes of a partly Chinese race are pressing southwards. It is remarkable how many of the conquering irruptions of south-east Asia were due mainly to the eviction of such conquerors by some stronger power. Incessant wars and vast deportations have tended to assimilate the various populations of all this region.</p></body></text></TEI>