<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:39:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>His son and successor, Kaikávús, made peace with Lascaris and extended his frontiers to the Black Sea by the conquest of Sinope (1214). On this occasion he was fortunate enough to take prisoner the Comnenian prince (Alexis) who ruled the independent empire of Trebizond, and he compelled him to purchase his liberty by acknowledging the supremacy of the Seljuks, by paying tribute, and by serving in the armies of the sultan. Elated by this great success and by his victories over the Armenians, Kaikávús was induced to attempt the capture of the important city of Aleppo, at this time governed by the descendants of Saladin ; but the affair miscarried. Soon afterwards the sultan died (1219) and was succeeded by his brother, Alá ed-dín Kaikobád, the most powerful and illustrious prince of this branch of the Seljúḳs, renowned not only for his successful wars but also for his magnificent structures at Konieh, Alaja, Sivás, and elsewhere, which belong to the best specimens of Saracenic architecture. The town of Alaja was the creation of this sultan, as previously there existed on that site only the fortress of Candelor, at that epoch in the possession of an Armenian chief, who was expelled by Kaikobád, and shared the fate of the Armenian and Frankish knights who possessed the fortresses along the coast of the Mediterranean as far as Selefke (Seleucia). Kaikobád extended his rule as far as this city, and desisted from further conquest only on condition that the Armenian princes would enter into the same kind of relation to the Seljúḳs as had been imposed on the Comnenians of Trebizond. But his greatest military fame was won by a war which, however glorious, was to prove fatal to the Seljúḳ empire in the future : in conjunction with his ally, the Eyyúbid prince Al-Ashraf, he defeated the Khárizm shah Jelál ed-dín near Arzengán (1230). This victory removed the only barrier that checked the progress of the Mongols. During this war Kaikobád put an end to the collateral dynasty of the Seljúḳs of Erzerúm and annexed its possessions. He also gained the city of Khelát with dependencies that in former times had belonged to the Sháh-i- Armen, but shortly before had been taken by Jelál ed-din ; this aggression was the cause of the war just mentioned. The acquisition of Khelát led, however, to a new war, as Kaikobád’s ally, the Eyyúbid prince, envied him this conquest. Sixteen Mohammedan princes, mostly Eyyúbids, of Syria and Mesopotamia, under the leadership of Al- Malik al-Kámil, prince of Egypt, marched with considerable forces into Asia Minor against him. Happily for Kaikobâd, the princes mistrusted the power of the Egyptian, and it proved a difficult task to penetrate through the mountainous well-fortified accesses to the interior of Asia Minor, so that the advantage rested with Kaikobád, who took Kharput, and for some time even held Harrán, Ar- Roha, and Raḳḳa (1232). The latter conquests were, however, soon lost, and Kaikobád himself died in 1234 of poison administered to him by his son and successor, Ghiyáts ed-din Kaikhosrau II. This unworthy son inherited from his father an empire embracing almost the whole of Asia Minor, with the exception of the countries governed by Vatatzes (Vataces) and the Christian princes of Trebizond and Lesser Armenia, who, however, were bound to pay tribute and to serve in the armies,—an empire celebrated by contemporary reports for its wealth.@@<hi rend="superscript">1 </hi>But the Turkish soldiers were of little use in a regular battle, and the sultan relied mainly on his Christian troops, so much so that an insurrection of dervishes which occurred at this period could only be put down by their assistance. It was at this epoch also that there flourished at Konieh the greatest mystical poet of Islam, and the founder of the order of the Mawlawis, Jelál ed-din Rúmí</p><p>(d. 1273; see <hi rend="smallcaps">Rumi),</hi> and that the dervish fraternities spread throughout the whole country and became powerful bodies, often discontented with the liberal principles of the sultans, who granted privileges to the Christian merchants and held frequent intercourse with them. Notwithstanding all this, the strength and reputation of the empire were so great that the Mongols hesitated to invade it, although standing at its frontiers. But, as they crossed the border, Kaikhosrau marched against them, and suffered a formidable defeat at Kuzadág (between Arzengán and Sivás) in 1243, which forced him to purchase peace by the promise of a heavy tribute. The independence of the Seljúḳs was now for ever lost. The Mongols retired for some years; but, Kaikhosrau dying in 1245, the joint government of his three sons gave occasion to fresh inroads, till one of them died and Hulagu divided the empire between the other two, 'Izz ed-din ruling the districts west of the Halys and Rokn ed-din the eastern provinces (1259). But the former, intriguing with the Mameluke sultans of Egypt to expel his brother and gain his independence, was defeated by a Mongol army and obliged to flee to the imperial court. Here he was imprisoned, but afterwards released by the Tatars of the Crimea, who took him with them to Sarai, where he died. Rokn ed-din was only a nominal ruler, the real power being in the hands of his perváneh, Muín ed-din Sulaimán, who in 1267 procured an order of the Mongol Khán Abaka for his execution. The minister raised his infant son, Ghiyáts ed-din Kaikhosrau III., to the throne, and governed the country for ten years longer, till he was entangled in a conspiracy of several emirs, who proposed to expel the Mongols with the aid of the Mameluke sultan of Egypt (Beybars or Bibars). The latter marched into Asia Minor and defeated the Mongols in the bloody battle of Ablastán (1277); but, when he advanced farther to Cæsarea, the perváneh retired, hesitating to join him at the very moment of action. Beybars, therefore, in his turn fell back, leaving the perváneh to the vengeance of the khán, who soon discovered his treason and ordered a barbarous execution. Ghiyáts ed-din continued to reign in name till 1284, though the country was in reality governed by a Mongol viceroy. Mas'ud, the son of 'Izz ed-din, who on the death of his father had fled from the Crimea to the Mongol khán and had received from him the government of Sivás, Arzengán, and Erzerúm during the lifetime of Ghiyáts ed-din, ascended the Seljúḳ throne on the death of Ghiyáts. But his authority was scarcely respected in his own residence, for several Turkish emirs assumed independence and could only be subdued by Mongol aid, when they retired to the mountains, to reappear as soon as the Mongols were gone. Mas'úd fell, probably about 1295, a victim to the vengeance of one of the emirs, whose father he had ordered to be put to death. After him Kaikobád, son of his brother Farámarz, entered Konieh as sultan in 1298, but his reign is so obscure that nothing can be said of it ; some authors assert that he governed only till 1300, others till 1315. With him ended the dynasty of the Seljúḳs ; but the Turkish empire founded by them continued to exist under the rising dynasty of the Ottomans. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Turkey.)</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi>The best, though insufficient, account of the Seljúḳs is still De Guignes, <hi rend="italic">Histoire Générale des Huns,</hi> bks. x.-xii., from whom Gibbon borrowed his dates. Among translations from original sources (of which the most trustworthy are yet unedited), comp. Mirkhond’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Seldschuken</hi> (ed. Vullers), Giessen, 1838; <hi rend="italic">Tarikh-î-Guzideh,</hi> French translation by Defrémery in the <hi rend="italic">Journal Asiatique,</hi> 1848, i. 417 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> ii. 259 <hi rend="italic">sq</hi>., 334 <hi rend="italic">sq. ; Seid Locmani ex Libro Turcico qui Oghuzname inscribitur Excerpta</hi> (ed. J. H. W. Lagus), Helsingfors, 1854 (on the Seljúḳs of Asia Minor exclusively, but of little value). Information respecting certain periods is given incidentally in the well-known works of Von Hammer and D'Ohsson.	(M. T. H.)</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> See the details in Vincent of Beauvais, <hi rend="italic">Speculum Historiale,</hi> bk. XXX. chaps. 143, 144.</p></body></text></TEI>