<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-12T18:44:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>writers) ; Pallegoix, <hi rend="italic">Royaume Thai ou Siam,</hi> Paris, 1S54 ; Crawford, <hi rend="italic">Embassy to Siam</hi> ; Bowring, <hi rend="italic">The Kingdom and People of Siam,</hi> London, 1857 ; Bastian, <hi rend="italic">Die Völker des östlichen Asiens,</hi> vols. i., iii., Leipsic, 1867 ; Gamier, <hi rend="italic">Voyage d'Exploration en Indo-Chine,</hi> Paris, 1873 ; Mouhot, <hi rend="italic">Travels in Indo-China,</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">; Journ. of Ind. Archip.,</hi> vols, i., v. ; Gréhan, <hi rend="italic">Le Royaume de Siam,</hi> Paris, 1870 ; Réclus, <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle Géographie Universelle,</hi> vol. viii. ; Bagge, <hi rend="italic">Report on the Settlement of the Boundary between Siam and British Burmah,</hi> 1868 ; Satow, <hi rend="italic">Notes of the Intercourse between japan and Siam in the 17th Century</hi> ; Aymonnier, in <hi rend="italic">Excursions et Reconnaissances,</hi> Nos. 20-22 (Saigon) ; <hi rend="italic">Consular Reports,</hi> 18S4-85.	(C. T.)</p><p><hi rend="italic">Language and Literature.</hi></p><p>The Siamese language is spoken over the whole of Siam proper. In the Malay peninsula the boundary-line comes down on the west coast nearly as far as Quedah and Perils, and includes also Junk Ceylon, while on the east coast the population is mainly Siamese as far as Ligor inclusive, and also in Singora Siamese appears to be the ruling language. Its boundary towards Burmah, the Shan and Laos states, and Anam and Cambodia cannot be defined so precisely. There are also in the north-east a number of wild tribes who speak languages of their own. The name by which the Siamese themselves call their language is <hi rend="italic">phâsâ thai,</hi> or “language of the freemen ” ; and it probably dates from the period when the Siamese made themselves independent of Cambodian rule in the 12th century. The Shan tribes, whose language (with those of the Ahom, Khamti, and Laos) is closely akin to Siamese, also use the term <hi rend="italic">tai</hi> (only with the unaspirated <hi rend="italic">t)</hi> for their race and language.</p><p>Both in Shan and Siamese the system of tones, which is one of the main features of all the languages of Indo-China, has attained its greatest development. But, while in Shan the tones are not marked in the written language, in Siamese there are distinct signs to denote at least four of the five simple tones (the even tone not being marked) ; and there is further a classification of the consonants into three groups, in each of which certain tones predominate. It is always the initial consonant of a word that indicates, either by its phonetic power or by the tonic accent super- added or by a combination of the two, the tone in which the word is to be uttered, so that, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> a word beginning with a letter of the second class in which the even tone is inherent, and which has the mark of the ascending tone over it, is to be pronounced with the descending tone. @@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The difficulties caused to a European student of the spoken language by the tones are increased by the greatly expanded vowel - system. In addition to the short and long, there are shortest vowels, sets of open and closed vowels, &amp;c., and a large number of vowel combinations. Owing to the introduction of the Indian consonantal system and the incorporation in it of many letters to express certain sounds peculiar to Siamese, the number of consonants has been swelled to forty-three ; but, while many of these are only used in words adopted from the Sanskrit and Pali, Siamese utterance knows no more than twenty ; <hi rend="italic">kh, g, gh</hi> are all pronounced as <hi rend="italic">kh</hi> ; similarly <hi rend="italic">ph, b, bh </hi>as <hi rend="italic">ph,</hi> &amp;c.,—the language having a predilection for hard letters, especially aspirates. The only compound letters at the beginning of words are combinations of hard letters with <hi rend="italic">l</hi>, <hi rend="italic">r, w, y,</hi> while the finals are confined in pronunciation to <hi rend="italic">k, t, p, it</hi> (ng), <hi rend="italic">n, nt.</hi> This causes a considerable discrepancy between the spelling of words (especially loan words) and their pronunciation. Thus <hi rend="italic">sampurn</hi> is pronounced <hi rend="italic">sombun, bhâsâ—phâsâ, nagara—nakhon, saddharma— satham, kusala—kuson, sesha—set, vâra—van, Magadha—Makhot. </hi>The foreign ingredients in Siamese are principally Sanskrit, mostly in a corrupted form. The importation of Pali words dates from about the 12th century, when, the country having shaken off the yoke of Cambodia, a religious intercourse was established between Siam and Ceylon. Besides these, there are some Khmer (Cambodian) and Malay words. @@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> Exclusive of those foreign importations, Siamese is a monosyllabic language in which neither the form nor the accent or tone of a word determines the part of speech to which it belongs. Homonymous words abound and are only distinguished from one another by the tones. Compare <hi rend="italic">lan, </hi>“white”; làn, “to relate”; lạn<hi rend="italic">,</hi> “to Hatter”; <hi rend="italic">lán,</hi> “to smooth”; <hi rend="italic">lãn,</hi> “relation.” Words are unchangeable and incapable of inflexion. The Siamese are fond of joining two words the second of which is cither purely synonymous to or modifies the sense of the first, or is only a jingling addition. There is no article, anti no distinction of gender, number, or case. These, if it is at all necessary to denote them, are expressed by explanatory words after the respective nouns ; only the dative and ablative are denoted by subsidiary words, which precede the nouns, the nominative being marked by its position before, the objective by its position after, the verb, and the genitive (and also the adjective) by its place after the noun it qualifies. Occasionally, however, auxiliary nouns serve that purpose. Words like “mother,” “son,” “water” are often employed in forming compounds to express ideas for which the Siamese have no single words; e.g., <hi rend="italic">lûk cân,</hi> “the son of hire,” a labourer; <hi rend="italic">me mu,</hi> “the mother of the hand,” the thumb. The use of class words with numerals obtains in Siamese as it does in Chinese, Burmese, Anamese,</p><p>Malay, and many other Eastern languages. As in these, so in Siamese the personal pronouns are mostly represented by nouns expressive of the various shades of superior or lower rank according to Eastern etiquette. The verb is, like the noun, perfectly colourless,—person, number, tense, and mood being indicated by auxiliary words only when they cannot be inferred from the context. Such auxiliary words are <hi rend="italic">yû,</hi> “to be,” “to dwell” (present); <hi rend="italic">dai,</hi> “to have,” <hi rend="italic">len,</hi> “end” (past); ca, “also” (future) ; the first and third follow, the second and fourth precede, the verb. <hi rend="italic">Hài,</hi> “to give” (prefixed), often indicates the subjunctive. As there are compound nouns, so there are compound verbs; thus, <hi rend="italic">e.g., pai,</hi> “to go,” is joined to a transitive verb to convert it into an intransitive or neuter ; and <hi rend="italic">thûk,</hi> “to touch,” and <hi rend="italic">tbng,</hi> “to be obliged,” serve to form a sort of passive voice. @@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> The number of adverbs, single and compound, is very large. The prepositions mostly consist of nouns. The order of the words in a single sentence is subject, verb, object. All attributes (adjectives, genitive, adverbs) follow the word to which they are subordinated. The following simple sentence may serve as an example of Siamese construction and diction ; <hi rend="italic">müa </hi>(time) <hi rend="italic">an</hi> (read) <hi rend="italic">nansü</hi> (book) <hi rend="italic">nî</hi> (this) <hi rend="italic">lêo</hi> (end, done) <hi rend="italic">con</hi> (should) <hi rend="italic">fãk-vai</hi> (entrust) <hi rend="italic">kî (to) phüenbàn</hi> (neighbours) <hi rend="italic">hai</hi> (give, cause) <hi rend="italic">khan</hi>  (they) <hi rend="italic">an</hi> (read), <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “when you have read this book, please give it to your neighbours that they may read it.”</p><p>The current Siamese characters are derived from the more monumental Cambodian alphabet, which again owes its origin to the alphabet of the inscriptions, an offshoot of the character found on the stone monuments of southern India in the 6th and 8th centuries. The sacred books of Siam are still written in the Cambodian character, and some have occasionally an interlinear translation in the current Siamese hand.</p><p>The study of the Siamese language was initiated in Europe by La Loubère (1687), from whom Dr J. Leyden (“The Languages and Literature of the Indo- Chinese Nations,” in <hi rend="italic">Asiatic Researches,</hi> vol. x. pp. 158-289, reprinted in <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous Papers on Indo-China,</hi> vol. i., 1886, pp. 84-171) has derived much of his information. Leyden’s <hi rend="italic">Comparative Vocabulary of the Burma, Malayu, and Thai Languages</hi> appeared in 1810. The first grammar of the language we owe to Janies Low, Calcutta, 1828. Very useful <hi rend="italic">Grammatical Notices of the Siamese Language,</hi> by the Rev. J. Taylor Jones, appeared at Bangkok in 1S42. The <hi rend="italic">Grammatica Linguae Thai</hi> of J. B. Pallegoix, Bangkok, 1850, was followed in 1854 by his great <hi rend="italic">Dictionarium</hi> in Siamese, Latin, French, and English. An analytical account of the language was attempted by Ad. Bastian in his <hi rend="italic">Sprachvergleichende Studien,</hi> 1870, pp. 191-226. In 1881 L. Ewald brought out at Leipsic his <hi rend="italic">Grammatik der T'ai- oder Siamesischen Sprache.</hi> Lastly, Prof. Fr. Müller gave a summary of Siamese grammar in his <hi rend="italic">Grundriss der Sprachwissenschaft,</hi> vol. ii. part 2, Vienna, 1882, pp. 367-376. A new grammar, by the Rev. S. George, is in progress. Compare also W. Schott, <hi rend="italic">Ueber die indochinesischen Sprachen, insonderheit das Siamesische,</hi> 1856 ; and E. Kuhn, <hi rend="italic">Ueber Herkunft und Sprache der transgangetischen Völker,</hi> 1883. An English grammar written in Siamese, and designed for use in schools, appeared at Bangkok in 1837.</p><p>There are no records in Siamese referring to the time antecedent to the settlement of the nation in their present locality, or, in the _ words of Mr Ney Elias, “of earlier date than the founding of their first national capital, Ayuthia, at the commencement of the 14th century.” @@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> The inscription at Sukkothai, said to be of the year 671 of the Siamese era, nine years after the invention of the present Siamese characters, @@<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> cannot be put in evidence as an historical record till a facsimile and revised translation shall have been obtained. The few manuscript annals mentioned by Bishop Pallegoix have not yet been critically examined ; but metrical compositions, containing legendary tales and romances, abound and are eagerly studied. The subjects are mostly taken from the Indian epics, as in the case of the <hi rend="italic">Ráma-kiun</hi> or Rámáyana, more rarely from Malay or Javanese legend, such as the drama <hi rend="italic">L-hnao.</hi> There is a great variety of metres, all of which have been described with much minuteness of detail by Colonel Low in his article on Siamese literature, in <hi rend="italic">Asiatic Researches,</hi> vol. xx. pp. 351-373. @@<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> In their romantic poetry the Siamese have a greater tendency to describe than to relate ; their pictures of places and scenery are gland and striking and form the best part of their poetical conceptions. The great blemish of their poetry consists in tedious embellishments and a hankering after indecent and often gross allusions, from which but few works, such as <hi rend="italic">Sang Sin Chai</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Samut Niyai Si Muang,</hi> may be said to be free. The titles of the principal romances are <hi rend="italic">Hoi Sang, Nang Prathom, Sang Sin Chai, Thepha Lin Thong, Suwanna Hong, Thao Sawatthi Racha, Phra Unarut, Bara Suriwong, Khun Phan, Nong Sip Sang,</hi> and the dramas <hi rend="italic">I-hnao</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Phra Simuang.</hi> The plots of some of these have been given by Colonel Low. The most popular of the religious books, all of which are translations or amplifications from Pali originals, is called <hi rend="italic">Somanakhodom</hi> (Çramana Gautama), which is identical with the <hi rend="italic">Wessantara Jâtaka.</hi> In miscellaneous literature may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Suphâsit,</hi> consisting of 222 elegant sayings in the accented metre called Klong, and <hi rend="italic">Wuta Chindamani </hi>(Vritta Chintâmani), a work on prosody like the Pali <hi rend="italic">Vuttodaya, </hi>but treating also of a number of grammatical questions. The fable literature is of course largely represented ; the lists, however, are</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> See A. Bastian, “Ueber die siamesischen Laut- und Ton-Acceute,"in <hi rend="italic">Monats- ber. d. k. Akad. d. Wissensch, zu Berlin,</hi> June 1867.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> See Pallegoix, <hi rend="italic">Gramm.,</hi> pp. 155-156, and Van der Tunk, <hi rend="italic">Bataksch Leesboek,</hi> vol. iv. pp. 127-133, 208-214.</p><p>@@@3 See “The Passive Verb of the Thai Language,” by F. L. W. von Bergen, Krung Theph Maha Nakhon, 1874.</p><p>@@@4 <hi rend="italic">Sketch of the History of the Shans,</hi> Calcutta, 1876, p. 34.	</p><p>@@@5 Bastian, in <hi rend="italic">Jour. As. Soc. Bengal,</hi> vol. xxxiv. p. 27, and <hi rend="italic">Sprachvergleichende</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Studien,</hi> p. 227.</p><p>@@@6 See also Pallegoix, <hi rend="italic">Gramm. Linguae Thai,</hi> pp. 120-129.</p></body></text></TEI>