<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-22-s04-0172-01" facs="encyclopediabrit22newyrich_raw_0188.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SMITH</label>, Alexander (1830-1867), was the most prominent representative of the so-called “spasmodic” school of poetry, whose peculiarities first gained for it a hasty reputation, and then, having suffered under closer critical examination, it almost as speedily dropped out of mind again. Smith has never yet perhaps had his true position assigned to him. His first book, <hi rend="italic">A Life Drama and other Poems</hi> (1853), which made his name, was a work of real promise. Although deficient in dramatic grasp of subject, in restraint of expression, in metrical quality, and although showing too obviously the influence of Keats and Tennyson in certain exaggerations of epithet and phrase, the book yet contains evidence of a poetic faculty which might, under more fortunate conditions, have developed into genuine power. Alexander Smith was one of those writers who require the critical safeguards of the schools to chasten their somewhat importunate energies ; and for want of these academic restrictions he wasted his powers in discursive experiments of not much abiding value. Born at Kilmarnock on the last day of 1830, he received the usual schooling common at that time ; and, his parents being too poor to send him to college, he was placed in a linen factory to follow his father’s trade of a pattern designer. His literary proclivities, however, soon showed themselves, and from time to time his early poems appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Glasgow Citizen,</hi> in whose editor, James Hedderwick, he found a sympathizing and appreciative friend. His poems, having attracted the attention also of the Rev. George Gilfillan, found through him an opening in the London <hi rend="italic">Citizen. A Life Drama and other Poems,</hi> published in 1853, speedily ran through several editions, and gained Smith the appointment of secretary to Edinburgh university in 1854. In the same year Sydney Dobell, whose name is now familiarly associated with Smith’s, came to Edinburgh, and an acquaintanceship at once sprang up between the two, which resulted in their collaboration in a book of <hi rend="italic">War Sonnets,</hi> inspired by the Crimean War, which was published in 1855. The volumes of verse issued independently by Alexander Smith in the ensuing years did not receive much attention; their author then turned himself to prose, after publishing <hi rend="italic">City Poems</hi> in 1857 and <hi rend="italic">Edwin of Deira,</hi> a Northumbrian epic poem, in 1861. His first prose work was <hi rend="italic">Dreamthorpe,</hi> 1863; it was followed in 1865 by <hi rend="italic">A Summer in Skye,</hi> which contains his best prose writing, and is full of a quiet charm and true sympathy with nature. His last work was an experiment in fiction, <hi rend="italic">Alfred Hagart's Household</hi> (1866), which ran first through <hi rend="italic">Good Words. In</hi> this the same faults of construction, conjoined with the same incidental grace of description, that show themselves in his larger poems are repeated. The strain produced by his literary and other work began to tell towards the end of 1866, and his death followed on 5th January 1867.</p><p>A memoir of Smith by P. P. Alexander is prefixed to a volume of remains, entitled <hi rend="italic">Last Leaves,</hi> in which will be found a fairly complete account of his life and writings.</p></div></body></text></TEI>