<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0310-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0333.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SCHAFARIK (Czech, <hi rend="italic">Šafařík</hi>), PAVEL JOSEF</label>
                    (1795-1861), Slavonic philologist, was born of Slovak parents at Kobeljarova, a
                    village of northern Hungary, where his father was a Protestant clergyman. His
                    first production was a volume of poems in Czech entitled <hi rend="italic">The
                        Muse of Tatra with a Slavonic Lyre</hi> (Levocza, 1814). In 1815 he began a
                    course of study at the university of Jena, and while there translated into Czech
                    the <hi rend="italic">Clouds</hi> of Aristo-phanes and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Maria Stuart</hi> of Schiller. In 1817 he removed to Prague and joined the
                    literary circle of which Dobrovsky, Jungmann and Hanka were members. From 1819
                    to 1833 he was head master of the high school at Neusatz in the south of
                    Hungary. There he studied Servian literature and antiquities, acquired many rare
                    books and manuscripts, and published a collection of Slovak folk-songs in
                    collaboration with Kollar and others (1823-1827). In 1826 his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Geschichte der slawischen Sprache und Literatur nach allen Mundarten</hi>
                    appeared at Budapest (2nd ed., 1869). This book was the first attempt to give
                    any-thing like a systematic account of the Slavonic languages as a whole. In
                    1833 he returned to Prague, where he spent the remainder of his h'fe. There he
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Serbische Lesekörner oder historisch-kritische
                        Beleuchtung der Serbischen Mundart,</hi> and in 1837 his great work <hi
                        rend="italic">Slovanské Starožitnosti</hi> (“Slavonic Antiquities ”). The “
                    Antiquities ” have been translated into Polish, Russian and German; a second
                    edition (1863) was edited by J. Jirečeck. In 1840 he published in conjunction
                    with Palacký <hi rend="italic">Die ältesten Denkmäler der böhmischen
                        Sprache.</hi> In 1837 poverty compelled him to accept the uncongenial office
                    of censor of Czech publications, which he abandoned in 1847 on becoming
                    custodian of the Prague public h*brary. In 1842 he published his <hi
                        rend="italic">Slovanský Národopis,</hi> in which he sought to give a
                    complete account of Slavonic ethnology. He was also for some time conductor of
                    the “ Journal ” of the Bohemian Museum, and edited the first volume of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Vybor,</hi> or selections from old Czech writers, which
                    appeared under the auspices of the Prague literary society in 1845. To this he
                    prefixed a grammar of the Old Czech language, <hi rend="italic">Počátková
                        staroéeské mluvnice.</hi> In 1848 he was made professor of Slavonic
                    philology in the university of Prague, but resigned in 1849. He was then made
                    keeper of the university library. In 1857 he published <hi rend="italic"
                        >Glagolitische Fragmente</hi> in collaboration with Höfler; but in the same
                    year, as a result of overwork, ill health and family anxieties, he became
                    insane. He was nevertheless continued in his appointment until his death in
                    1861.</p>
                <p>Schafarik’s collected works, <hi rend="italic">Sebrané Spisy,</hi> were published
                    at Prague. 1862-1865; his <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der südslawischen
                        Literatur</hi> was edited by Jireček in 3 vols. (1864-1865).</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0311" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0334.jp2"/>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
