<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0357-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0380.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SCHÖMANN, GEORG FRIEDRICH</label> (1793-1879), German classical scholar,
                    was born at Stralsund in Pomerania on the 28th of June 1793. In 1827 he was
                    appointed professor of ancient literature and eloquence in the university of
                    Greifswald, where he died on the 25th of March 1879. Schömann’s attention was
                    chiefly devoted to the constitutional and religious antiquities of Greece. His
                    first works on the subject were <hi rend="italic">De comitiis Atheniensium</hi>
                    (1819), the first independent account of the forms of Athenian political life,
                    and a treatise <hi rend="italic">De sortitione judicum apud Athenienses</hi>
                    (1820). In conjunction with M. H. E. Meier, Schömann wrote <hi rend="italic">Der
                        attische Process</hi> (1824, revised ed. by J. H. Lipsius, 1883-1887),
                    which, although in some respects out of date, still has considerable value.</p>
                <p>Among his other works are:—editions of Isaeus (1831) and Plutarch’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Agis</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">and Cleomenes</hi> (1839, important for the Attic law of
                    inheritance and the history of the Spartan constitution); <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anti-</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">quitates juris publici Graecorum</hi> (1838); a critical
                    examination of Grote’s account of the Athenian constitution (1854, Eng. trans.
                    by B. Bosanquet, 1878) from a conservative point of view; and lastly, <hi
                        rend="italic">Griechische Alterthümer</hi> (1855-1859; 4th ed. by T. H.
                    Lipsius, 1897-1902; Eng. trans. of vol. i. by E. G. Hardy and T. S. Mann, 1880),
                    treating of the general historical development of the Greek states, followed by
                    a detailed account of the constitutions of Sparta, Crete and Athens, the cults
                    and international relations of the Greek tribes. The question of the religious
                    institutions of the Greeks, which he considered an essential part of their
                    public life, had early engaged his attention, and he held the opinion that
                    everything really religious was akin to Christianity, and that the greatest
                    intellects of Greece produced intuitively Christian, dogmatic ideas. From this
                    point of view he edited the <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi> of Hesiod (1868),
                    with a commentary, chiefly mythological, and Cicero’s <hi rend="italic">De
                        natura deorum</hi> (1850, 4th ed. 1876); translated with introduction and
                    notes Aeschylus’s <hi rend="italic">Prometheus Bound,</hi> and wrote a <hi
                        rend="italic">Prometheus Unbound</hi> (1844), in which Prometheus is brought
                    to see the greatness of his offence and is pardoned by Zeus. Of his
                    contributions on grammatical subjects special mention may be made of <hi
                        rend="italic">Die Lehre von den Redetheilen nach den Alten dargestellt</hi>
                    (1862), an introduction to the elements of the science of grammar. His
                    many-sidedness is shown in his <hi rend="italic">Opuscula academica</hi> (4
                    vols., 1856-1871).</p>
                <p>See F. S(usemihl) in C. Bursian's <hi rend="italic">Βiog. Jahrbuch für
                        Altertumskunde</hi></p>
                <p>(1879); A. Baumeister in <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine deutsche Biographie,</hi>
                    xxxii.; C. Bursian, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. der class. Philologie in
                        Deutschland</hi> (1883), and J. E. Sandys, <hi rend="italic">Hist. of
                        Classical Scholarship,</hi> iii. (1908), p. 165.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
