<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0389-02" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0412.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCHWARZ, KARL</label>, (1812-1885), German Protestant theologian, was born at Wiek on the Isle of Rügen on the 19th of November 1812. His father, Theodor Schwarz, pastor at Wiek, was well known as a preacher, and as the writer of a number of popular works (parables, romances, &amp;amp;c.) under the pseudonym “ Theodor Melas.” Karl Schwarz' pursued the study of theology and philosophy at Halle, and afterwards at Bonn (1831) and Berlin (1832-1834). At Berlin he came under the influence of Schleiermacher and Hegel, whose influences are seen in his work <hi rend="italic">Das Wesen der Religion</hi> (1847). In 1837 he was imprisoned for six months on account of his advanced political opinions. After his release he helped (from 1838) with the <hi rend="italic">Hallische Jahrbücher.</hi> From 1843-1845 he lectured at Halle, and was then suspended by the government. In 1849, however, he was appointed professor extraordinarius, and later received a number of dis-tinctions (in 1858 chief court preacher, &amp;amp;c.). Schwarz took an important part in the founding and directing of the German Protestantenverein, and became an eminent exponent of liberal theology. His work <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der neuesten Theologie</hi> (1856, 4th ed. 1869) is a valuable source for the history of theology in Germany. His other works include <hi rend="italic">Lessing als Theologe</hi> (1854) and <hi rend="italic">Grundriss der christl. Lehre</hi> (1873, 5th ed. 1876). He died on the 25th of March 1885. In his memory a <hi rend="italic">Karl-Schwarz-stifIung</hi> was founded in connexion with the theological faculty at Jena.</p><p>See G. Rudloff, <hi rend="italic">Karl Schwarz</hi> (1887); F. Hummel, <hi rend="italic">Die Bedeutung</hi> <hi rend="italic">der Schrift υoη Karl Schwarz: Über das Wesen der Religion</hi> (1890); and Herzog-Hauck, <hi rend="italic">Realencyklopädie.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>