<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0309-02" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0332.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCÈVE, MAURICE</label>, (c. 1500-1564), French poet, was born at Lyons, where his father practised law. Besides following his father’s profession he was a painter, architect, musician and poet. He was the centre of the Lyonnese coterie that elaborated the theory of spiritual love, derived partly from Plato and partly from Petrarch, which was enunciated in Antoine Heroet’s <hi rend="italic">Parfaicte Amye.</hi></p><p>Scève’s chief works are <hi rend="italic">Délie, objet de plus haulte vertu</hi> (1544); two eclogues, <hi rend="italic">Arion</hi> (1536) and <hi rend="italic">La Saulsaye</hi> (1547); and <hi rend="italic">Le Microcοsme</hi> (1562), an encyclopaedic poem beginning with the fall of man. <hi rend="italic">Délie</hi> consists of 450 <hi rend="italic">dizaines</hi> and about 50 other poems in praise of his mistress. These poems, now little read, were even in Scève’s own day so obscure that his enthusiastic admirer Étienne Dolet confesses he could not understand them. Scève was a musician as well as a poet, and cared very much for the musical value of the words he used. In this and in his erudition he forma a link between the school of Marot and the Pléiade <hi rend="italic">Déilie</hi> (an anagram for <hi rend="italic">l'idée</hi>)set the fashion of a series of poems addressed to a mistress real or imaginary, followed by Ronsard in <hi rend="italic">Cassandre</hi> and by Du Bellay in <hi rend="italic">Olive.</hi> The Lyonnese school of which Scève was the leader included his friend Claude de Taillemont and many women writers of verse, Jeanne Gaillarde—placed by Marot on an equality with Christine de Pisan—Pernette du Guillet, Clémence de Bourges and the poet’s sisters, Claudine and Sibylle Scève. Scève died in 1564. See also <hi rend="smallcaps">Labe, Louise).</hi></p><p>See E. Bourciez, <hi rend="italic">La Littérature polie et les mœurs de cour sous Henri II</hi> Paris, 1886); Pernetti, <hi rend="italic">Recherches pour servir à l'histoire de Lyon (2</hi> vols., Lyons, 1757), and F. Brunetière, “ Un Précurseur de la Pléiade, Maurice Scève," in his <hi rend="italic">Études critiques,</hi> vol. vi. (1899).</p></div></body></text></TEI>