<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0253-01" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0272.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SAVORY, SIR WILLIAM SCOVELL</label>, <hi rend="smallcaps">Bart. (1826-1895), British surgeon, was born on the 30th of November 1826, in London. He entered St Bartholomew’s Hospital in 1844, becoming M.R.C.S. in 1847, and F.R.C.S. in 1852. From 1849 to 1859 he was demonstrator of anatomy and operative surgery at St Bartholomew’s, and for many years curator of the museum, where he devoted himself to pathological and physiology work. In 1859 he succeeded Sir James Paget as lecturer on general anatomy and physiology. In 1861 he became assistant surgeon, and in 1867 surgeon, holding the latter post till 1891; and from 1869 to 1889 he was lecturer on surgery. In the College of Surgeons he was a man of the greatest influence, and was president for four successive years, 1885-1888. As Hunterian professor of comparative anatomy and physiology (1859-1861), he lectured on “ General Physiology ” and the “ Physiology of Food.” In 1884 he delivered the Bradshaw Lecture on the “ Pathology of Cancer.” In 1887 he delivered the Hunterian Oration. In 1879, at Cork, he had declared against “ Listerism ” at the meeting of the British Medical Association, “ the last public expression,” it has been said, “ by a prominent surgeon against the now accepted method of modern surgery.” In 1887 he became surgeon-extraordinary to Queen Victoria, and in 1890 he was made a baronet. Savory, who was an able operator, but averse from exhibitions of brilliancy, was a powerful and authoritative man in his profession, his lucidity of expression being almost as valuable as his great knowledge of physiology and anatomy. He died in London on the 4th of March 1895.</hi></p><pb xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0254" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0273.jp2"/>

</div></body></text></TEI>