<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0392-01" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0415.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCHWEIGHÄUSER, JOHANN</label>, (1742-1830), German classical scholar, was bom at Strassburg on the 25th of June 1742. From an early age his favourite subjects were philosophy (especially Scottish moral philosophy as represented by Hutchinson and Ferguson) and Oriental languages; Greek and Latin he took up later, and although he owes his reputation to his editions of Greek authors, he was always diffident as to his classical attainments. After visiting Paris, London and the principal cities of Germany, he became assistant professor of philosophy (1770) at Strassburg. When the French Revolution broke out, he was banished; in 1794 he returned, and after the reorganization of the Academy in 1809 was appointed professor of Greek. He resigned his post in 1824, and died on the 19th of January 1830.</p><p>His son, Johann Gottfried (1776-1844), was also a distinguished scholar and archaeologist, joint-author with M. Golbéry of <hi rend="italic">Antiquités de l’Alsace</hi> (1828).</p><p>Schweighäuser’s first important work was his edition of Appian (1785), with Latin translation and commentary, and an account of the MSS. On Brunck's recommendation, he had collated an Augsburg MS. of Appian for Samuel Musgrave, who was preparing an edition of that author, and after Musgrave’s death he felt it a duty to complete it. His Polybius, with translation, notes and special lexicon, appeared in 1789-1795. But his chief work is his edition of Athenaeus (1801-1807), in fourteen volumes, one of the Bipont editions. His Herodotus (1816; lexicon, 1824) is less successful; he depends too much on earlier editions and inferior MSS., and lacks the finer scholarship necessary in dealing with such an author. Mention may also be made of his <hi rend="italic">Encheiridion</hi> of Epictetus and <hi rend="italic">Tabula</hi> of Cebes (1798), which appeared at the time when the doctrines of the Stoics were fashionable; the letters of Seneca to Lucilius (1809); corrections and notes to Suïdas (1789); some moral philosophy essays. His minor works are collected in his <hi rend="italic">Opuscula academica</hi> (1806).</p><p>See monographs by J. G. Dahler, C. L. Cuvier, F. J. Stiévenart (all 1830), L. Spach (1868), Ch. Rabany (1884), the two last containing an account of both father and son.</p></div></body></text></TEI>