<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0312-02" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0335.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCHÄFFLE, ALBERT EBERHARD FRIEDRICH</label>, (1831-1903), German statesman and political economist, was born at Nürtingen in Württemberg on the 24th of February 1831, and in 1848 became a student at the university of Tübingen. From 1850 to 1860 he was attached to the editorial staff of the <hi rend="italic">Schwäbische Merkur</hi> in Stuttgart, and in the latter year accepted a call to the chair of political economy at Tübingen. From 1862 to 1864 Schäffle was a member of the Württemberg diet, and in 1868 he received a mandate to the German <hi rend="italic">Zollparlament.</hi> This year he was appointed professor of political science at the university of Vienna, and in 1871 he entered the cabinet of Karl Siegmund Graf von Hohenwart as minister of commerce for Austria. But the government fell in the same year, and Schäffle withdrew to Stuttgart, where he took up his residence, devoting himself entirely to literary work. He died at Stuttgart on the 25th of December 1903. Among his numerous writings must be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Das Gesellschaftliche System der menschlichen Wirthschaft</hi> (new ed., 1873); <hi rend="italic">Die Natiοnalökonomische Theorie der ausschliessenden Absatzverhältnisse</hi> (1867); <hi rend="italic">Bau und Leben des socialen Körpers</hi> (2nd ed. 1896); <hi rend="italic">Ein Votum gegen den neuesten Zolltarif</hi> (Tübingen, 1901) ; <hi rend="italic">Die agrarische Gefahr</hi> (Berlin, 1902); <hi rend="italic">Gesammelte Aufsätze</hi> (1885-1887). From 1892 to 1901 Schäffle was the sole editor of the <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für die gesamte Staatswissenschaft.</hi></p><p>See Biermann, <hi rend="italic">Schäffle und der Agrarismus</hi> (Bonn, 1902) and his autobiography, <hi rend="italic">Aus</hi> <hi rend="italic">meinem Leben</hi> (Berlin, 1905).</p></div></body></text></TEI>