<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0326-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0349.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SCHOLTBERGER, JOHANN or HANS</label> (1381-1440?), German traveller and
                    writer, was born of a noble family in 1381 (May 9th?), probably at Hollern near
                    Lohof, half way between Munich and Freising, on what was then a property of his
                    family. In 1394 he joined the suite of Lienhart Richartinger, and went off to
                    fight under Sigismund, king of Hungary (afterwards emperor), against the Turks
                    on the Hungarian frontier. At the battle of Nicopolis (Sept. 28th, 1396) he was
                    wounded and taken prisoner: when he had recovered the use of his feet, Sultan
                    Bayezid I. <hi rend="italic">(Ilderim)</hi> took him into his service as a
                    runner (1396-1402). During this time he seems to have accompanied Ottoman troops
                    to certain parts of Asia Minor and to Egypt. On Bayezid’s overthrow at Angora
                    (July 20th, 1402), Schiltberger passed into the service of Bayezid’s conqueror
                    Timur: he now appears to have followed <hi rend="italic">Themurlin</hi> to
                    Samarkand, and perhaps also to Armenia and Georgia. After Timur’s death
                    (February 17th, 1405) his German runner first became a slave of Shah Rukh, the
                    ablest of Timur’s sons; then of Miran Shah, a brother of Shah Rukh; then of Abu
                    Bekr, a son of Miran Sbah, whose camp roamed up and down Armenia. He next
                    accompanied Chekre, a Tatar prince living in Abu Bekr’s horde, on an excursion
                    to Siberia, of which name Schiltberger gives us the first clear mention in west
                    European literature. He also probably followed his new master in his attack on
                    the Old Bulgaria of the middle Volga, answering to the modem Kazan and its
                    neighbourhood. Wan-derings in the steppe lands of south-east Russia; visits to
                    Sarai, the old capital of the Kipchak Khanate on the lower Volga and to Azov or
                    Tana, still a trading centre for Venetian and Genoese merchants; a fresh change
                    of servitude on Chekre’s ruin; travels in the Crimea, Circassia, Abkhasia and
                    Mingrelia; and finally escape (from the neighbourhood of Batum) followed.
                    Arriving at Constantinople, he there lay hid for a time; he then returned to his
                    Bavarian home (1427) by way of Kilia, Akkerman, Lemberg, Cracow, Breslau and
                    Meissen After his return he became a chamberlain of Duke Albert III., probably
                    receiving this appointment in the first instance before the duke’s accession in
                    1438.</p>
                <p>Schiltberger’s <hi rend="italic">Reisebuch</hi> contains not only a record of his
                    own experiences and a sketch of various chapters of contemporary Eastern
                    history, but also an account of countries and their manners and customs,
                    especially of those countries which he had himself visited. First come the lands
                    “ this side ” of Danube, where he had travelled; next follow those between the
                    Danube and the sea, which had now fallen under the Turk; after this, the Ottoman
                    dominions in Asia; last come the more distant regions of Schiltberger’s world,
                    from Trebizond to Russia and from Egypt to India. In this regional geography the
                    descriptions of Brusa; of various west Caucasian and Armenian regions; of the
                    regions around the Caspian, and the habits of their peoples (especially the <hi
                        rend="italic">Red Tatars);</hi> of Siberia; of the Crimea with its great
                    Genoese colony at Kaffa (where he once spent five months); and of Egypt and
                    Arabia, are particularly worth notice. His allusions to the Catholic missions
                    still persisting in Armenia and in other regions beyond the Euxine, and to
                    (non-Roman ?) Christian communities even in the Great Tatary of the steppes are
                    also remarkable. Schiltberger is perhaps the first writer of Western Christendom
                    to</p>
                <p>five the true burial place of Mahomet at Medina: his sketches of slam and of
                    Eastern Christendom, with all their shortcomings, are of remarkable merit for
                    their time: and he may fairly be reckoned among the authors who contributed to
                    fix Prester John, at the close of the middle ages, in Abyssinia. His work,
                    however, contains many inaccuracies; thus in reckoning the years of his service
                    both with Bayezid and with Timur he unaccountably multiplies by two. His account
                    of Timur and his campaigns is misty, often incorrect, and sometimes fabulous:
                    nor can von Hammer’s parallel between Marco Polo and Schiltberger be sustained
                    without large reservations.</p>
                <p>Four MSS. of the <hi rend="italic">Reisebuch</hi> exist: (1) at Donaueschingen in
                    the Fürstenberg Library, No. 481; (2) at Heidelberg, University Library, 216;
                    (3) at Nuremberg, City Library, 34; (4) at St Gall, Monast. Library, 628 (all of
                    15th century, the last fragmentary). The work was first edited at Augsburg,
                    about 1460; four other editions appeared in the 15th century, and six in the
                    16th; in the 19th the best were K. F. Neumann’s (Munich, 1859), P. Bruun’s
                    (Odessa, 1866, with Russian commentary, in the <hi rend="italic">Records of the
                        Imperial University of New Russia,</hi> vol. i.), and V. Langmantel's
                    (Tübingen, 1885); "Hans Schiltbergcrs Reisebuch,” in the 172nd volume of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliothek des literarischen Vereins in Stuttgart.</hi> See
                    also the English (Hakluyt Society) version, <hi rend="italic">The Bondage and
                        Travels of Johann Schiltberger . .</hi>., trans. by Buchan Telfer with notes
                    by P. Bruun (London, 1879); von Hammer, “ Berechtigung d. orientalischen Namen
                    Schiltbergers,” in <hi rend="italic">Denkschriften d. Königl. Akad. d.
                        Wissenschaften</hi> (vol. ix., Munich, 1823-1824); R. Röhricht, <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliotheca geographica Palaestinae</hi> (Berlin, 1890, pp.
                    103-104); C. R. Beazley, <hi rend="italic">Dawn of Modern Geography,</hi> iii.
                    356-378, 550, 555.</p>
                <p>(C. R. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
