<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0376-01" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0399.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCHOPPE, CASPAR</label>, (1576-1649), German controversialist and scholar, was born at Neumarkt in the upper Palatinate on the 27th of May 1576 and studied at several German universities. Having become a convert to Roman Catholicism about 1599, he obtained the favour of Pope Clement VIII., and, even</p><pb xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0377" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0400.jp2"/><p>in an age of violent polemics, distinguished himself by the virulence of his writings against the Protestants. He became involved in a controversy with Joseph Justus Scaliger, formerly his intimate friend, and others, wrote <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiaslicus auctoriiaii Jacobi regis oppositus</hi> (1611), an attack upon James I. of England; and in <hi rend="italic">Classicum belli scari</hi> (1619) urged the Catholic princes to wage war upon the Protestants. About 1607 Schoppe entered the service of Ferdinand, archduke of Styria, afterwards the emperor Ferdinand II., who found him very useful in rebutting the arguments of the Protestants, and who sent him on several diplomatic errands. According to Pierre Bayle, he was almost killed by some Englishmen at Madrid in 1614, and again fearing for his life he left Germany for Italy in 1617, afterwards taking part in an attack upon the Jesuits. Schoppe, as the long list of his writings shows, knew also something of grammar and philosophy, and had an excellent acquaintance with Latin. His chief work is, perhaps, his <hi rend="italic">Grammatica philosophica</hi> (Milan, 1628). Schoppe died at Padua on the 19th of November 1649. In his <hi rend="italic">Life of Sir Henry Wotton</hi> Izaac Walton, calling him Jasper Scioppius, refers to Schoppe as “ a man of a* restless spirit and a malicious pen.”</p><p>Besides the works already noticed, he wrote <hi rend="italic">De arte critica</hi> (1597); <hi rend="italic">De Antichristo</hi> (1605); <hi rend="italic">Pro auctoritate ecclesiae in decidendis fidei controversiis libellus; Scaliger hypolotymaeus</hi> (1607), a virulent attack on Scaliger; and latterly the anti-jesuitical works, <hi rend="italic">Flagellum Jesuiticum</hi> (1632); <hi rend="italic">Mysteria patrum jesuitorum</hi> (1633); and <hi rend="italic">Arcana societatis Jesu</hi> (1635). For a fuller list of his writings see J. P. Nicéron <hi rend="italic">Mémoires,</hi> (1727-1745). See also C. Nisard, <hi rend="italic">Les Gladiateurs de la république des lettres</hi> (Paris, 1860).</p></div></body></text></TEI>