<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0320-02" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0343.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCHERER, EDMOND HENRI ADOLPHE</label>, (1815-1889), French theologian, critic and politician, was born in Paris on the 8th of April 1815. After a course of legal studies he spent several years in theological study at Strassburg, where he graduated doctor in theology in 1843, and was ordained. In 1843 he was appointed to a professorship in the École Évangélique at Geneva, but the development of his opinions in favour of the Liberal movement in Protestant theology led to his resigning the post six years later. He founded the <hi rend="italic">Anti-Jésuite,</hi> afterwards the <hi rend="italic">Réformation au XIX siècle,</hi> in which he advocated the separa-tion of the Church from the State; but he gradually abandoned Protestant doctrine. In thought he became a pronounced Hegelian. Eventually he settled in Paris, where he at once attracted attention by brilliant literary criticisms, at first chiefly on great foreign writers, contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Revue des deux mondes.</hi> He was elected municipal councillor at Versailles in 1870, deputy to the National Assembly for the department of Seine-et-Oise in 1871 and senator in 1875. He supported the Republican party. Towards the end of his life he devoted himself mainly to literary and general criticism, and was for many years one of the ablest contributors to <hi rend="italic">Le Temps.</hi> He was a frequent visitor to England, and took a lively interest in English politics and literature. He died at Versailles on the 16th of March 1889.</p><p>His chief works are: <hi rend="italic">Dogmatique de l'Église réformée</hi> (1843), <hi rend="italic">De l'état actuel de l'Église réformée en France</hi> (1844), <hi rend="italic">Esquisse d'une théorie de l'Église chrétienne</hi> (1845), <hi rend="italic">La Critique et la foi</hi> (1850), <hi rend="italic">Alexandre Vinet</hi> (1853), <hi rend="italic">Lettres à mon curé</hi> (1853), <hi rend="italic">Études critiques sur la littérature contemporaine</hi> (1863-1889), <hi rend="italic">Études critiques de littérature</hi> (1876), <hi rend="italic">Diderot</hi> (1880), <hi rend="italic">La Démocratie et la France</hi> (1883), <hi rend="italic">Études sur la littérature au XVIII siècle</hi> (1891).</p><p>A memoir of him, by V. C. O. Gréard, appeared in 1890. See also an article by Professor E. Dowden in the <hi rend="italic">Fortnightly Review</hi> (April 1889).</p></div></body></text></TEI>