<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0378-05" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0401.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SCHRIJVER, PETER</label>, (1576-1660), Dutch author, better known as Scriverius, was bom at Haarlem on the 12th of January 1576. He was educated at the university of Leiden, where he formed a close intimacy with Daniel Heinsius. He belonged to the party of Oldenbarneveldt and Grotius, and brought down the displeasure of the government by a copy of Latin verses in honour of their friend Hoogerbeets. Most of his life was passed in Leiden, but in 1650 he became blind, and the last years of his life were spent in his son’s house at Oudewater, where he died on the 30th of April 1660.</p><p>He is best known as a scholar by his notes on Martial, Ausonius, the <hi rend="italic">Pervigilium Veneris;</hi> editions of the poems of Scaliger (Leiden, 1615), of the <hi rend="italic">De re militari</hi> of Vegetius Renatus, the tragedies of Seneca (P. <hi rend="italic">Scriυerii collectanea veterum tragicorum,</hi> 1621), &amp;amp;c. His <hi rend="italic">Opera anecdote, philologica, et poëtica</hi> (Utrecht, 1738) were edited by A. H. Westerhovius, and his <hi rend="italic">Nederduitschc Gedichten</hi> (1738) by S. Dockes. He made many valuable contributions to the history of Holland: <hi rend="italic">Batavia Illustrate</hi> (4 parts, Leiden, 1609); <hi rend="italic">Corte historische Beschryvinghe der Nedertandscher Oorlogen</hi> (1612); <hi rend="italic">Inferior is Germaniae . . . historia</hi> (1611, 4 parts); <hi rend="italic">Beschryvinghe van Out</hi> <hi rend="italic">Batavien</hi> (Arnheim, 1612); <hi rend="italic">Het oude gontsche Chronycxken van Hollandt,</hi> edited by him, and printed at Amsterdam in 1663; <hi rend="italic">Principes Hollandiae Zelandiae et Frisiae</hi> (Haarlem, 1650), translated (1678) into Dutch by Pieter Brugman.</p><p>See Peerlkamp, <hi rend="italic">Vitae Βelgarum qui latina carmina scripserunt</hi> (Brussels, 1822), and J. H. Hoeufft, <hi rend="italic">Parnassus latino-belgicus</hi> (Amsterdam, 1819).</p></div></body></text></TEI>