<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0357-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0380.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SCHOMBERG (originally Schonberg), FRIEDRICH HERMANN</label></p>
                <p>(or Frederic Armand), Duke of (<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">c</hi></hi>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">. 1615-1690), marshal of France and English general, was
                        descended from an old family of the Palatinate, and was born in December
                        1615 or January 1616, at Heidelberg, the son of Hans Meinard von Schönberg
                        (1582-1616) and Anne Sutton, daughter of the 9th Lord Dudley. An orphan
                        within a few months of his birth,’ he was educated by various friends, among
                        whom was the “ Winter King,” Frederick V. of the Palatinate, in whose
                        service his father had been. He began his military career under Frederick
                        Henry, prince of Orange, and passed about 1634 into the Swedish service,
                        whence he entered that of France in 1635. His family, and the allied house
                        of the Saxon Schönbergs had already attained eminence in France.<note
                            anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> Of the Misnian
                            Schönbergs in French history may be named Gaspard de Schomberg, count of
                            Nanteuil (d. 1599), French soldier and statesman, his son, Henri, count
                            of Nanteuil and Duretal, marquis d'Espinoy (1575-1632) grandmaster of
                            the artillery, marshal of France, and Henri’s son Charles (d. 1656), who
                            by marriage became duc d’Halluin, and was marshal of France and also,
                            during the war with Spain, viceroy of Catalonia. Of the Palatinate
                            family, Theodoric (d. 1590) was killed at Ivry in the service of Henry
                            IV. </note></hi> After a time he retired to his family estate at
                    Geisenheim on the Rhine, but in 1639 he reentered the Dutch army, in which,
                    apparently, with a few intervals spent at Geisenheim, he remained until about
                    1650. He then rejoined the French army as a general officer <hi rend="italic"
                        >{maréchal de camp),</hi> served under Turenne in the campaigns against
                    Condé, and became a lieutenant-general in 1665, receiving this rapid promotion
                    perhaps partly owing to his relationship with the duc d’Halluin, but mainly
                    because he was looked upon as the eventual successor of the great generals then
                    at the height of their fame.</p>
                <p>After the peace of the Pyrenees (1659) the independence of Portugal being again
                    menaced by Spain, Schomberg was sent as military adviser to Lisbon with the
                    secret approval of Charles II. of England (who knew him personally and about
                    this time created him baron of Tetford) and Louis XIV., who in order not to
                    infringe the treaty just made with Spain, deprived Schomberg of his French
                    offices. After meeting in the three first campaigns many difficulties from the
                    insubordination of many of the Portuguese officers, Schomberg won the victory of
                    Montes Claros on the 17th of June 1665 over the Spaniards under the prince of
                    Parma. After participating with his army in the revolution which deposed the
                    reigning king in favour of his brother dom Pedro, and ending the war with Spain,
                    Schomberg returned to France, became a naturalized Frenchman and bought the
                    lordship of Coubert near Paris. He had been rewarded by the king of Portugal, in
                    1663, with the rank of Grandee, the title of count of Mertola and a pension of
                    £5000 a year. In 1673 he was invited by Charles to England, with the view of
                    taking command of the army, but sentiment was so strong against the appointment,
                    as savouring of French influence, that it was not carried into effect. He
                    therefore again entered the service of France. His first operations in Catalonia
                    were unsuccessful owing to the disobedience of subordinates and the rawness of
                    his troops, but he retrieved the failure of 1674 by retaking Bellegarde in 1675.
                    For this he was made a marshal, being included in the promotion that followed
                    the death of Turenne. The tide had now set against the Huguenots, and
                    Schomberg’s merits had been long ignored on account of his adherence to the
                    Protestant religion. The revocation of the edict of Nantes (1685) compelled him
                    to quit his adopted country. Ultimately he became general-in-chief of the forces
                    of the elector of Brandenburg, and at Berlin he was the acknowledged leader of
                    the thousands of Huguenot refugees there. Soon afterwards, with the elector’s
                    consent, he joined the prince of Orange on his expedition to England in 1688, as
                    second in command to the prince. The following year he was made a knight of the
                    Garter, was created successively baron, marquis and duke, was appointed
                    master-general of the ordnance, and received from the House of Commons a vote of
                    £100,000 to compensate him for the loss of his French estates, of which Louis
                    had deprived him. In August he was appointed commander-in-chief of the
                    expedition to Ireland against James II. After capturing Carrickfergus he marched
                    unopposed through a country desolated before him to Dundalk, but, as the bulk of
                    his forces were raw and undisciplined as well as inferior in numbers to the
                    enemy, he deemed it imprudent to risk a battle, and entrenching himself at
                    Dundalk declined to be drawn beyond the circle of his defences. Shortly
                    afterwards pestilence broke out, and when he retired to winter quarters in
                    Ulster his forces were more shattered than if they had sustained a severe
                    defeat. His conduct was criticized in ill-informed quarters, but the facts
                    justified his inactivity, and he gave a striking example of his generous spirit
                    in placing at William’s disposal for military purposes the £100,000 recently
                    voted him. In the spring he began the campaign with the capture of Charlemont,
                    but no advance southward was made until the arrival of William. At the Boyne
                    (July 1,1690) Schomberg gave his opinion against the determination of William to
                    cross the river in face of the opposing army. In the battle he commanded the
                    centre, and while riding through the river without his cuirass to rally his men,
                    was surrounded by Irish horsemen and instantly killed. He was buried in St
                    Patrick’s cathedral, Dublin, where there is a monument to him, erected in 1731,
                    with a Latin inscription by Dean Swift.</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-24-s03-0358" facs="encyclopaediabri24chisrich_0381.jp2"/>
                <p>His eldest son Charles, the second duke in the English peerage, died in the year
                    1693 of wounds received at the battle of Marsaglia.</p>
                <p>The most important work on Schomberg’s life and career is Kazner’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Leben Friedrichs von Schomberg oder Schönberg</hi> (Mannheim,
                    1789). The military histories and memoirs of the time should also be
                    consulted.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
