<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0323-04" facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0343.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SAUROPSIDA</label>, . This name was introduced by Huxley in his <hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Classification of Animals,</hi> 1869, to designate a province of the <hi rend="italic">Vertebrata</hi> formed by the union of the <hi rend="italic">Aves</hi> with the <hi rend="italic">Reptilia.</hi> In his <hi rend="italic">Elements of Comparative Anatomy,</hi> 1864, he had used the term “Sauroids” for the same province. The five divisions of the <hi rend="italic">Vertebrata—Pisces, Amphibia, Reptilia, Aves,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mammalia</hi> —are all distinctly definable, but their relations to one another differ considerably in degree. The <hi rend="italic">Amphibia</hi> are more similar to the <hi rend="italic">Pisces</hi> than to any of the other divisions, and the <hi rend="italic">Aves</hi> are closely allied to the <hi rend="italic">Reptilia,</hi> and thus three provinces— <hi rend="italic">Ichthyopsida, Sauropsida,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mammalia—</hi> are formed.</p><p>The characters which distinguish the <hi rend="italic">Sauropsida,</hi> that is, which are common to birds and reptiles, and not found combined in the other classes, have been thus summarized by Huxley :—no branchiae at any period of existence ; a well-developed amnion and allantois present in the embryo ; a mandible composed of many bones and articulated to the skull by a quadrate bone ; nucleated blood-corpuscles ; no separate parasphenoid bone in the skull; and a single occipital condyle. In addition to these principal characters, others exist which are found in all birds and reptiles, but are not exclusively confined to them. The oviduct is always a Mullerian duct separate from the ovary and opening from the body cavity. The adult kidney is a metanephros with separate ureter ; the mesonephros and mesonephric duct become in the adult male, the efferent duct of the testis. The intestine and the reproductive and urinary ducts open into a common cloaca. There is usually an exoskeleton in the form of scales ; in the birds the scales take the form of feathers. There are two aortic arches in reptiles, in birds only one,—the right. The heart is usually trilocular, becoming quadrilocular in crocodiles and birds. In all the eggs are meroblastic and large, possessing a large quantity of yolk ; in all the egg is provided in the oviduct with a layer of albumen and outside this with a horny or calcareous shell. In a few cases the egg is hatched in the oviduct, but in these cases there is no intimate connexion between the embryo and the walls of the duct. Fertilization takes place internally, occurring at the upper end of the oviduct previously to the deposition of the albuminous layer and egg shell.</p><p>Comparative anatomy clearly shows that birds are reptiles which have become specialized in adaptation to the function of flight. This conclusion has been confirmed in the most surprisingly complete manner by the discovery of fossil forms intermediate between birds and reptiles. Two points of specialization in addition to the transformation of the fore limbs into wings are conspicuous in birds,—the reduction of the tail and the absence of teeth. <hi rend="italic">Archaeopteryx</hi> is a flying feathered animal with a long reptilian tail. In the Rocky Mountain region numerous toothed birds have been recently discovered, and have been studied and described in a masterly fashion by Prof. O. C. Marsh. These forms belong to the Mesozoic period. For further details see Reptiles and Birds.</p></div></body></text></TEI>