<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb09-21-s01-0300-03"
                facs="encyclopediabrit21newyrich_raw_0320.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SANTILLANA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Iñigo Lopez de Mendoza</hi></label>,
                    Marquis of (1398-1458), Castilian poet, was born at Carrion de los Condes in Old
                    Castile on August 19, 1398. His father, Don Diego Hurtado de Mendoza, grand
                    admiral of Castile, having died while Inigo was still quite young, the boy was
                    brought up by his uncle Don Alfonso Enriquez. From his twentieth year onwards he
                    became an increasingly prominent figure at the court of Juan II. of Castile,
                    distinguishing himself both in civil and military service ; he was created
                    Marques de Santillana and Conde del Real do Manzanares for the part he took in
                    the battle of Olmedo in 1445. In the protracted struggle of the Castilian nobles
                    against the preponderating influence of Alvaro de Luna he showed great
                    moderation, but ultimately in 1452 he joined the combination which effected the
                    fall of the favourite in the following year. From the death of Juan II. in 1454
                    Mendoza took little part in public affairs, devoting himself mainly to the
                    pursuits of literature and to pious meditation. He died at Guadalajara on March
                    26, 1458.</p>
                <p>Mendoza was the first to introduce the Italian sonnet into Castile, but his
                    productions in this class are somewhat conventional in style and have little to
                    recommend them beyond the charm of smooth versification. He was much more
                    successful in the <hi rend="italic">scrranilla</hi> or highland pastoral after
                    the Provençal manner. His long-popular <hi rend="italic">Gcntiloquio</hi>
                    (1494), consisting of one hundred proverbs, each rendered in an eight-line
                    stanza, was prepared at the request of Juan II. for the instruction of Don
                    Enrique, the heir-apparent. To the same didactic category belong the <hi
                        rend="italic">Diálogo de Bias contra Fortuna</hi> (1448) and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Doctrinal dc Prívados</hi> (1453). The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Comedicta dc Ponza</hi> is a Dantesque dream-dialogue, in octave stanzas,
                    founded on the disastrous sea-fight off Ponza in 1435, when the kings of Aragon
                    and Navarre along with the infante of Castile were taken prisoners by the
                    Genoese.</p>
                <p>The works of Santillana have been edited with commentaries by Amador de los Rios
                    (Madrid, 1852).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
