<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of Jesus Christ revealed to the community. That God is love and that the purpose of His love is the moral organization of humanity in the “ Kingdom of God ”—this idea, with its immense range of application—is applied in RitschVs initial datum.</p><p>From this vantage-ground Ritschl criticizes the use of Aristotel-ianism and speculative philosophy in scholastic and Protestant theology. He holds that such philosophy is too shallow for theology. Hegelianism attempts to squeeze all life into the categories of logic: Aristotclianism deals with “ things in general ” and ignores the radical distinction between nature and spirit. Neither Hegelianism nor Aristotelianism is “ vital ” enough to sound the depths of religious life. Neither conceives “ God ” as correlative to human “ trust " (cf. <hi rend="italic">Theologie und Metaphysik,</hi>  esp. p. 8 seq.). But RitschVs recoil carries him so far that he is left alone with merely “ practical ” experience. “ Faith ” knows God in His active relation to the “ kingdom,” but not at all as “ self-existent.”</p><p>His limitation of theological knowledge to the bounds of human need might, if logically pressed, run perilously near phenomenalism ; and his epistemology (“ we only know things <hi rend="italic">in</hi>  their activities ”) does not cover this weakness. In seeking ultimate reality in the circle of “ active conscious sensation,” he rules out all “ metaphysic.” Indeed, much that is part of normal Christian faith— <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  the Eternity of the Son—is passed over as beyond the range of his method. RitschVs theory of ‘‘ value-judgments ” <hi rend="italic">(Werthur-theile)</hi>  illustrates this form of agnosticism. Religious judgments of value determine objects according to their bearing on our moral and spiritual welfare. They imply a lively sense of radical human need. This sort of knowledge stands quite apart from that produced by “ theoretic ” and “ disinterested ” judgments. The former moves in a world of “ values,” and judges things as they are related to our “ fundamental self-feeling. The latter moves in a world of cause and effect. <hi rend="italic">(N.B.</hi>  Ritschl appears to confine Metaphysic to the category of Causality.) The theory as formulated has such grave ambiguities, that his theology, which, as we have seen, is wholly based on uncompromising religious realism, has actually been charged with individualistic subjectivism. If Ritschl had clearly shown that judgments of value enfold and transform other types of knowledge, just as the “ spiritual man ” includes and transfigures but does not annihilate the “ natural man,” then within the compass of this spiritually conditioned knowledge all other knowledge would be seen to have a function and a home. The theory of value-judgments is part too of his ultra-practical tendency: both “ metaphysic ” and “ mysticism ” are ruthlessly condemned. Faith-knowledge appears to be wrenched from its bearings and suspended in mid-ocean. Perhaps if he had lived to see the progress of will-psychology he might have welcomed the hope of a more spiritual philosophy.</p><p>A few instances will illustrate RitschVs positive systematic theology. The conception of God as Father is given to the community in Revelation. He must be regarded in His active relationship to the/'kingdom/’ as spiritual personality revealed in spiritual purposiveness. His “ Love ” is His will as directed towards the realization of His purpose in the kingdom. His “ Righteousness ” is His fidelity to this purpose. With God as “ First Cause ” or “ Moral Legislator/’ theology has no. concern ; nor is it interested in the “ speculative ” problems indicated by the traditional doctrine of the Trinity. “ Natural theology ” has no value save where it leans on faith. Again, Christ has for the religious life of the community the unique value of Founder and Redeemer. . He is the perfect Revelation of God and the Exemplar of true religion. His work in founding the kingdom was a personal vocation, the spirit of which He communicates to believers, “ thus, as exalted king,” sustaining the life of His Kingdom. His Resurrection is. a. necessary part of Christian belief (G. Ecke, pp. 198-99). “Divinity” is a predicate applied by faith to Jesus in His founding and redeeming activity. We note here that, though Ritschl gives Jesus a unique and unapproachable position in His active relation to the kingdom, he declines to rise above this relative teaching. The “ Two Nature ” problem and the eternal relation of the Son to the Father have no bearing on experience, and therefore stand outside the range of theology.</p><p>Once more, in the doctrine of sin and redemption, the governing idea is God’s fatherly purpose for His family. Sin is the contradiction of that purpose, and guilt is alienation from the family. Redemption, justification, regeneration, adoption, forgiveness, reconciliation all mean the same thing—the restoration of the broken family relationship. All depends on the Mediation of Christ, who maintained the filial relationship even to His death, and communicates it to the brotherhood of Delievers. Everything is defined by the idea of the family. The whole apparatus of “ forensic ” ideas (law, punishment, satisfaction, &amp;c.) is summarily rejected as foreign to God’s purpose of love. Ritschl is so faithful to the standpoint of the religious community, that he has nothing definite to say on many inevitable questions, such as the relation of God to pagan races. His school, in which J. G. W. Herrmann, Julius Kaftan and Adolf Harnack are the chief names, diverges from his teaching in many directions; <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  KafUn appreciates the mystical side, of religion, Harnack’s criticism is very different from RitschVs arbitrary exegesis. They are united on the value of faith-knowledge as opposed to “ mctaphysic.”</p><p>Sec A. Ritscnl, <hi rend="italic">Die Christliche Lehre von der Rechtfertigung und Versöhnung</hi>  (3rd ed., 1889); <hi rend="italic">Unterricht in der Christlichen Lehre</hi>  (very many editions); and. <hi rend="italic">Theologie und Metaphysik</hi>  (2nd cd., 1887), give his main position. Many historical and other works besides.—E. Bertrand, <hi rend="italic">Une nouvelle conception de la redemption. La Doctrine de la justification et de la reconciliation dans le système de Ritschl</hi>  (1891); H. Schoen, <hi rend="italic">Les Origines historiques de la théologie de Ritschl</hi>  (1893); θ· Ecke, <hi rend="italic">DieJHeologische Schule, A, RitschVs und die evangelische Kirche der Gegenwart</hi>  (1897); James Orr, <hi rend="italic">The Ritschlian Theology and the Evangelical Faith</hi>  (London,</p><p>1898)    ; and A. E. Garvie, <hi rend="italic">The Ritschlian Theology</hi>  (Edinburgh,</p><p>1899)    , in both of which the bibliography of the movement is given. Cf. Otto Pfieiderer, <hi rend="italic">Development OfTheology in Germany since Kant </hi>(1890). The German literature, on the subject is very large; see article in <hi rend="italic">Herzog-Hauck,</hi>  vol. xvii.</p><p>RITSCHL, FRIEDRICH WILHELM (1806-1876), German scholar, was born in 1806 in Thuringia. His family, in which culture and poverty were hereditary, were Protestants who had migrated several generations earlier from Bohemia. Ritschl was fortunate in his school training, at a time when the great reform in the higher schools of Prussia had not yet been thoroughly carried out. His chief teacher, Spitzner, a pupil of Gottfried Hermann, divined the boy’s genius and allowed it free growth, applying only so much either of stimulus or of restraint as was absolutely needful. After a wasted year at the university of Leipzig, where Hermann stood at the zenith of his fame, Ritschl passed in 1826 to Halle. Here he came under the powerful influence of Reisig, a young “ Her-mannianer ” with exceptional talent, a fascinating personality and a rare gift for instilling into his pupils his own ardour for classical study. The great controversy between the “ Realists ” and the “ Verbalists ” was then at its height, and Ritschl naturally sided with Hermann against Boeckh. The early death of Reisig in 1828 did not sever Ritschl from Halle, where he began his professorial career with a great reputation and brilliant success, but soon hearers fell away, and the pinch of poverty compelled his removal to Breslau, where he reached the rank of “ ordinary ” professor in 1834, and held other offices. The great event of RitschVs life was a sojourn of nearly a year in Italy (1836-37), spent in libraries and museums, and more particularly in the laborious examination of the Ambrosian palimpsest of Plautus at AIilan. The remainder of his life was largely occupied in working out the material then gathered and the ideas then conceived. Bonn, whither he removed on his marriage in 1839, and where he remained for twenty-six years, was the great scene of his activity both as scholar and as teacher. The philological seminary which he controlled, although nominally only joint-director with Weicker, became a veritable <hi rend="italic">officina Iitterarum,</hi>  a kind of Isocratean school of classical study; in it were trained many of the foremost scholars of the last forty years. The names of Georg Curtius, Ihne, Schleicher, Bernays, Ribbeck, Lorenz, Vahlen, Hübner, Bücheler, Helbig, Benndorf, Riese, Windisch, who were his pupils either at Bonn or at Leipzig, attest his fame and power as a teacher. In 1854 Otto Jahn took the place of the venerable Welcker at Bonn, and after a time succeeded in dividing with Ritschl the empire over the philological school there. The two had been friends, but after gradual estrangement a violent dispute arose between them in 1865, which for many months divided into two hostile forces the universities and the press of Germany. Both sides were steeped in fault, but Ritschl undoubtedly received harsh treatment from the Prussian government, and pressed his resignation. He accepted a call to Leipzig, where he died in harness in 1876.</p><p>RitschVs character was strongly marked. The spirited element in him was^powerful, and to some at times he seemed overbearing, but his nature was noble at the core; and, though intolerant of inefficiency and stupidity, he never asserted his personal claims in any mean or petty way. He was warmly attached to family and friends, and yearned continually after sympathy, yet he established real intimacy with only a few. He had a great faculty for organization, as is shown by his</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>