<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>constitute the “ running rigging,” since they are “ in constant use, to trim yards, and make or shorten sail ” (Admiral Smyth, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.).</hi>  The rigging must also provide the crew with the means of going aloft, and with standing ground to do their work when aloft. Therefore the shrouds (see below) are utilized to form ladders of rope, of which the steps arc called ratlines, by which the crew can mount. Near the heads of the lower masts are the tops—platforms on which men can stand—and in the same place on the topmasts are the “ cross-trees,” of which the main function is to extend the topgallant shrouds. The yards are provided with ropes, extending from the middle to the extremities or arms, called horses, or foot-ropes, which hang about 2 or 3 ft. down, and on which men can stand. The material of which the cordage is made has differed, and still differs greatly. Leather has been used.</p><p>During historic times, however, the prevailing materials have been hemp or esparto grass <hi rend="italic">(Machrocloa,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Stipa tenacissima), </hi>and in recent days chain and wire. As the whole of the rigging is divided into standing and running, so a rope forming part of the rigging is divided into the “ standing part ” and the “ fall.” The standing part is that which is made fast to the mast, deck or block. The fall is the loose end or part on which the crew haul. The block is the pulley through which the rope runs. “ Standing ” in sea language means “ fixed ”—thus the standing part of a hook is that which “ is attached to block, chain or anything which is to heave the hook up, with a weight hanging to it; the part opposite the point ” (Smyth, <hi rend="italic">sub voce). </hi>“ Tackle ” is the combination of ropes and blocks; the combination of cables and anchors constitutes the “ ground tackle."</p><p>The function of all cordage may be said to be to pull, for the purpose either of keeping the masts in their places, or of moving spars and sails. The standing rigging which supports the masts</p><p>must be adapted to resist two kinds of pressure, the longitudinal, whether applied by the wind or by the motion of the vessel when pitching (t.e. plunging head and stern alternately into the hollow of the sea), and the lateral, when the wind is blowing on the side and she is rolling. The longitudinal pressure is counteracted by the bobstays, stays and backstays. A reference to fig. 1 will show that the bobstays hold down the bowsprit, which is Iiablc to be lifted by the tug of the jibs, and of the stays connecting it with the’ fore-topmast. If the bowsprit is lifted the fore-topmast loses part of its support. In the case of a small vessel, the lifting of a bowsprit would wreck her whole system of rigging in an instant. If fig. 1 is followed from the bow to the mizzenmast, it will be seen that a succession of stays connect the masts with the hull of the ship or with one another. All pull together to resist pressure from in front. Pressure from behind is met by the backstays, which connect the topmasts and topgallant masts with the sides of the vessel. Lateral pressure is met by the shrouds and breast-backstays. A temporary or “ preventer ” backstay is used when great pressure is to be met. Seamen have at all times had recourse to special devices to meet particular dangers. When Dundonald, then captain of the “ Pallas ” frigate, was chased by a French squadron in stormy weather, he fortified his masts by ordering “ all the hawsers ” (large ropes a little less strong than the cables which hold the anchor) “ in the ship to be got up to the mast heads, and hove taut," <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>  made fast to the side. Thus she was able to carry more sail than would have been possible with her normal rigging. The running rigging by which all spars and sails are hoisted, or lowered and spread or taken in, may be divided into those which lift and lower— the lifts, jeers, halliards (haulyards)—and those which hold down the lower corners of the sails—the tacks and sheets. A</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>