<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and was the mother of Charles James Fox, and of the beautiful Lady Sarah Lennox (1745-1826) with whom George III. fell in love and contemplated marriage, and who afterwards married, first, Sir Thomas Bunbury, from whom she was divorced, and secondly, George Napier, by whom she was the mother of Generals Sir Charles and Sir William Napier. of the </p><p>Charles, 3rd duke of Richmond (1735-1806), was one of the most remarkable men of the 18th century, being chiefly famous for his advanced views on the question of parliamentary reform. Having succeeded to the peerage in 1750, he was appointed British ambassador extraordinary in Paris in 1765, and in the following year he became a secretary of state in the Rockingham administration, resigning office on the accession to power of the earl of Chatham. In the debates on the policy that led to the War of American Independence Richmond was a firm supporter of the colonists; and he initiated the debate in 1778 calling for the removal of the troops from America, during which Chatham was seized by his fatal illness. He also advocated a policy of concession in Ireland, with reference to which he originated the phrase “ a union of hearts ” which long afterwards became famous when his use of it had been forgotten. In 1779 the duke brought forward a motion for retrenchment of the civil list; and in 1780 he embodied in a bill his proposals for parliamentary reform, which included manhood suffrage, annual parliaments and equal electoral areas. Richmond sat in Rockingham’s second cabinet as master-general of ordnance; and in 1784 he joined the ministry of William Pitt. He now developed strongly tory opinions, and his alleged desertion of the cause of reform led to a violent attack on him by Lauderdale in 1792, which nearly led to a duel between the two noblemen. Richmond died in December 1806, and, leaving no legitimate children, he was succeeded in the peerage by his nephew Charles, son of his brother, General Lord George Henry Lennox.</p><p>The 4th duke (1764-1819) and his wife Charlotte, daughter of the 4th duke of Gordon, were the givers of the famous ball at Brussels on the night before the battle of Quatre Bras, immortalized in Byron’s <hi rend="italic">Childe Harold.</hi>  Their son, the 5th duke (1791-1860), while still known by the courtesy title of earl of March, served on Wellington’s staff in the Peninsula, being at the same time member of parliament for Chichester. He was afterwards a vehement opponent in the House of Lords of Roman Catholic emancipation, and at a later date a leader of the opposition to Peel’s free trade policy. In 1836, on inheriting the estates of his maternal uncle, the 5th and last duke of Gordon, he assumed the name of Gordon before that of Lennox. On his death in 1860 he was succeeded in his titles by his son Charles Henry, 6th duke of Richmond (1818-1903), a statesman who held various cabinet offices in the Conservative administrations of Lord Derby, Disraeli and the marquess of Salisbury; and who in 1876 was created earl of Kinrara and duke of Gordon. These honours in addition to the numerous family titles of more ancient creation passed on his death in 1903 to his son Charles Henry Gordon-Lennox (b. 1845), 7th duke of Richmond and Lennox and 2nd duke of Gordon.</p><p>See Sir Robert Douglas, <hi rend="italic">The Peerage of Scotland,</hi>  edited by Sir J.B.</p><p>Paul; G. E. C., <hi rend="italic">Complete Peerage,</hi>  vol. vi. (London, 1895);</p><p>dy Elizabeth Cust, <hi rend="italic">Some Account</hi>  0f <hi rend="italic">the Stuarts of Aubigny in France</hi>  (London, 1891). For the dukes of the creation of 1675 see also, Anthony Hamilton, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Grammont,</hi>  edited by Sir W. Scott, new edition (2 vols., London, 1885); Horace Walpole, <hi rend="italic">Letters, </hi>edited by P. Cunningham (9 vols., London, 1891), and <hi rend="italic">Memoirs ofthe Reign OfGeorge HI.,</hi>  edited by G. F. R. Barker (4 vols.', London, 1894); the earl of Albemarle, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Rockingham and his Contemporaries</hi>  (2 vols., London, 1852); <hi rend="italic">The Grenville Papers, </hi>edited by W. J. Smith (4 vols., London, 1852); Earl Stanhope, <hi rend="italic">Life of William Pitt</hi>  (4 vols., London, i86f) ; Lord Edmond Fitz-mauriee, <hi rend="italic">Life of William Earl of Shelburne</hi>  (3 vols., London, 1875); the duke of Richmond, <hi rend="italic">The Rigft of the People to Universal Suffrage and Annual Parliaments</hi>  (London, 1817), being an edition, of the 3rd duke’s famous " Letter to Lieut.-Colonel Snarman,” originally published in 1783; Lord William Pitt Lennox, <hi rend="italic">Memoir of Charles Gordon-Lennox, 5th Duke of Richmond</hi>  (London, 1862). (R. J. M.)</p><p>RICHMOND, LEGH (1772-1827), English divine, was born on the 29th of January 1772, at Liverpool. He was educated at Trinity College, Cambridge, and in 1798 was appointed to the joint curacies of Brading and Yaverland in the IsIe of Wight. He was powerfully influenced by William Wilberforce’s <hi rend="italic">Practical View of Christianity,</hi>  and took a prominent interest in the British and Foreign Bible Society, the Church Missionary Society and similar institutions. In 1805 he became assistant-chaplain to the Lock Hospital, London, and rector of Turvey, Bedfordshire, where he remained till his death on the 8th of May 1827. The best known of his writings is <hi rend="italic">The Dairyman'S Daughter,</hi>  of which as many as four millions in nineteen languages were circulated before 1849. A collected edition of his stories of village life was first published in 1814 under the title of <hi rend="italic">Annals of the Poor.</hi>  He also edited a series of Reformation biographies called <hi rend="italic">Fathers of the English Church</hi>  (1807-12).</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>  by T. S. Grimshawe (1828); <hi rend="italic">Domestic Portraiture </hi>by T. Fry (1833).</p><p><hi rend="bold">RICHMOND, SIR WILLIAM BLAKE (1842-    </hi>), English</p><p>painter and decorator, was born in London on the 29th of November 1842. His father, George Richmond, R.A. (1809-1896), himself the son of a successful miniature painter, was a distinguished artist, who painted the portraits of the most eminent people of his day, and played an important part in society. At the age of fourteen William Richmond entered the Royal Academy schools, where he worked for about three years. A visit to Italy in 1859 gave him special opportunity for studying the works of the old masters, and had an important effect upon his development. His first Academy picture was a portrait group (1861); and to this succeeded, during the next three years, several other pictures of the same class. In 1865 he returned to Italy, and spent four years there,· living chiefly at Rome. To this period belongs the large canvas. “ A Procession in Honour of Bacchus,” which he exhibited at the Academy in 1869 when he came back to England. His picture, “ An Audience at Athens,” was exhibited at the Grosvenor Gallery in 1885. He became Slade professor at Oxford, succeeding Ruskin, in 1878, but resigned three years later. He was elected an Associate of the Royal Academy in 1888 and Royal Academician in 1895; he received the degree of D.C.L. in 1896, and a knighthood of the Bath in 1897, and became professor of painting to the Royal Academy. Apart from his pictures, he is notable for his work in decorative art, his most conspicuous achievement being the internal decoration and the glass mosaics of St Paul’s Cathedral. Sir William Richmond also took a keen interest in social questions, particularly in smoke-prevention in London. </p><p>RICHMOND,’ a city of Bourke county, Victoria, Australia, 2 m. S.E. of and suburban to Melbourne. It is one of the pleasantest of the metropolitan suburbs, having numerous parks and public gardens. There are a number of prosperous industries in the city. Pop. (1901) 37,722.</p><p>RICHMOND, a city and the county-seat of Wayne county, Indiana, U.S.A., on the E. branch of the Whitewater river, about 68 m. E. of Indianapolis. Pop. (1890) 16,608; (1900) 18,226, of whom 1467 were foreign-born and 1009 negroes; (1910 census) 22,324. It is served by the Chicago, Cincinnati &amp; Louisville, the Grand Rapids &amp; Indiana and the Pittsburg, Cincinnati, Chicago &amp; St Louis railways, and by the Terre Haute, Indianapolis &amp; Eastern and the Ohio electric inter-urban railways. Richmond has broad well-shaded streets, several parks, including Glen Miller (139 acres), and handsome public buildings. Its public institutions include the Morrisson-Reeves (public) Library (1864), one of the largest (39,000 volumes in 1909) and oldest in the state, an art gallery, the Reid Memorial Hospital, a Home for Friendless Women, the Margaret Smith Home for Aged Women (1888), the Wernle Orphans* Home (1879; Evangelical Lutheran), and the Eastern Indiana Hospital for the Insane (1890). Just west of the city limits is Earlham College (co-educational), opened in 1847, chartered in 1859 and controlled by the Society of Orthodox Friends; in 1908-9 it had 30 instructors, 620 students and a library of 18,000 bound volumes. Richmond was for many years the centre, west of Philadelphia, of the activities of the Society of Friends. Itis an important railway and commercial centre,</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>