<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>hood had gone out of use by the end of the 16th century.@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>Bachelors’ hoods were to be lined throughout with fur<hi rend="italic">{Mun. Acad.</hi>  p. 361), which we learn from the statute <hi rend="italic">de admissione ad pelluram</hi>  (1432) to have been budge. Masters and noblemen might use miniver, or silk in summer <hi rend="italic">{Mun. Acad.</hi>  pp. 283, 301). There were evidently hoods of at least two kinds for masters, sometimes called respectively <hi rend="italic">caputium</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">epomis,</hi>  whether corresponding to the distinction between regents and nonregents we do not know. (See <hi rend="italic">Mun. Acad.</hi>  p. 638, will of Thomas Bray, M.A., and Robinson, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>  In the Oxford <hi rend="italic">Corpus Statulorurn</hi>  of 1768 the <hi rend="italic">epomis</hi>  is worn with the ordinary gown, the <hi rend="italic">Capntiiim</hi>  with the scarlet habit.) At a later date, at Cambridge, a distinction was made between the hoods of non-regents, which were lined with silk, and those of regents, which were lined with miniver.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  Later again the regents wore their hoods in such a way as to show the white lining, while the non-regents wore theirs“ squared,” so that the white did not show. Hence the name “ White Hoods ” and “ Black Hoods ” given to the upper and lower houses of the old Senate respectively. It is not settled when the modern colourings of hoods arose; they probably followed those of·the gowns of the faculties, but about these we are equally uncertain. The Oxford Proctor still wears a miniver hood. The modern Cambridge hood has preserved .the original shape more closely than the Oxford one, being a hood and tippet combined, the hood having square corners. The tippet, which appears as part of the early costume of certain doctors, was probably, like the judges’ tippet, originally the shoulder-cape forming part of the same garment as the hood. Clark and others would derive it from the almuce (ç.v.), but do not seem to show any definite grounds for so doing. Its place seems to have been taken by the scarf worn by D.D.’s, &amp;c., probably developed from the hood with long Hripipe as worn turban-wise on the head or as a scarf round the shoulders. It seems rather ar-fetched to derive the scarf from the two pendants of the almuce.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  (See article<hi rend="smallcaps">Vestments</hi>  and cp. the mayor’s scarf mentioned above.)</p><p>There seem to have been at least three varieties of academic head-dress:@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> firstly, the doctor’s skull-cap with “ apex ” as illustrated in the<hi rend="italic">Chandler MS.</hi>  drawings; secondly, the square cap of cloth as prescribed by Laud’s statutes of 1636 for graduates and foundation scholars (similarly for Cambridge by Burleigh’s letter to the vice-chancellor in 1588), with its counterpart of velvet worn by doctors; thirdly, a round cloth cap prescribed by the Laudian statutes and Burleigh’s letter for undergraduates who were not foundation scholars, with the round cap of velvet for doctors which survives as part of their full dress to the present day. The square cap was adopted at the universities, according to Robinson, after 1520, in imitation of the university of Paris. For the development of Jhe modern “ college cap,” see Biretta. In this connexion should be mentioned the term “ tuft-hunting,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>  attempting to thrust oneself into the society of one’s social superiors, derived from the gold tufts or tassel worn by noblemen and fellow-commoners on their college caps.</p><p>As to the dresses of the different degrees, the drawings from the <hi rend="italic">Chandler MS.</hi>  give a good idea of the early costume. It is also</p><lb/><p>well illustrated by brasses.@@5 Doctors of theology seem to have w’orn a tippet but no hood. Masters of Arts seem to have worn a gowm, over which was a garment with bell-shaped sleeves reaching to the elbow, a tippet and a hood (see Druitt, plate facing p. 136, and p. 135). The same dress was sometimes worn by B.A.’s (see brass of John Palmer, B.A., d. 1479, New College, Oxford, in Druitt, p. 141), and bachelors of law and divinity, the latter being generally already M.A.’s (Druitt, p. 139). Haines’s theory is that alter the middle of the 15th century the dress of the M.A.’a was changed, and they wore a sleeveless tabard reaching to midway bctw'een ankle and knee. This costume certainly occurs on brasses, chiefly of the 16th or late 15th centuries, but the change is hard to explain.@@6·</p><p>Academic dress underwent much inquiry and some revision at the time of the Reformation, chiefly in the direction <hi rend="bold">of </hi>sobriety and uniformity, “ excess of apparel ” being repressed as severely as ever, but not with much more effect.@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi>  Burleigh’s letter to the Vice-Chancellor of Cambridge University (1585), and the statutes of Queen Elizabeth, strictly enforce the wearing of cap and gown by all, and hoods and habits by those entitled to wear them, and similar regulations were made for Oxford by Laud’s statutes of 1633, further details being dealt with by a decree of 1770. Academic dress during the 17th century may be further studied in Bedcl Buck’s book (1665, see Appendix B. to Peacock,<hi rend="italic">Observations on the Statutes of the .University of Cambridge},</hi>  and Loggan’s plates of academic costume in <hi rend="italic">Oxonia Illustrata</hi>  (1675) <hi rend="sup">an</hi>^<hi rend="italic">Cantabrigia Illustrata</hi>  (1690, ed. J. W. Clark, 1905).</p><p>There have been few far-reaching changes since Loggan’s day. Cambridge has of late years inquired into and revised her regulations as to dress, and in the <hi rend="italic">Ordinances</hi>  (latest ed. 1908, Statute A, cap. VII. p. 303) clear rules are laid down; the Oxford reguIations (see <hi rend="italic">Statuta et Decreta Univ. Oxon.</hi></p><lb/><p>have been to prevent this improper use as a scarf. But in this case, what is the force of “ <hi rend="italic">et non Contextum ”?</hi></p><p>@@@An interesting survival, which only disappeared about the middle of the 19th century, was the little black hood placed round the neck of candidates going in for<hi rend="italic">viva voce</hi>  in all examinations subsequent to responsions at Oxford. This was a survival of the custom of conferring on <hi rend="italic">sophistae generales, i.e.</hi>  those who had passed the first stage of the exercises for the B.Ä. degree, a hood of plain black cloth. See A. Clark’s <hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Registers of Oxford University,</hi>  vol. ii. pt. i. p. 22 (Oxford Hist. Soc., 1887).</p><p>@@@ See<hi rend="italic">Caius’ Statutes</hi>  (1557), also an account of the entertainments at Cambridge on the visit of Queen Elizabeth, 1564, given in Nichols, <hi rend="italic">Progresses,</hi>  vol. iii., “ Theologjae Baccalaureos ac non-Regentes primum, sericis caputiis induti, turn Regentes Magistri suis pelliceis albescentibus decorati; tandem Juris Artiumque Baccalaureos suis agninis bracceis conspicui.”</p><p>@@@3 See Rev. E. Wickham Legg in <hi rend="italic">Trans, of St Paul’s Eccles. Soc. </hi>vol. iii. Also Lacey and Robinson <hi rend="italic">{loc. cit.}.</hi></p><p>@@@ The subject is discussed in detail by Clark, “ College Caps and Doctors’ Hats,” in<hi rend="italic">Archaeol. Journal,</hi>  vol. lxi.,and N. F. Robinson, “ PiIeus Quadratus,** in <hi rend="italic">Transact, of St Paul’s Ecclesiological Socy., </hi>vol. V. pt. i. (1901). There is also much miscellaneous information in C. Wordsworth, <hi rend="italic">University Life in the 18th Century,</hi>  p. 499 seq.</p><lb/><p>@@@    See for doctors’ costume, J. G. and L. A. B. Waller’s<hi rend="italic">Series of Monumental Brasses</hi>  (London, 1864), plate of ” Four Ecclesiastics/’ from New College, Oxford, who are also illustrated in Druitt, pp. 131, 129, 119; and for M.A.’s and B.A.’s, Druitt, p. 135 seq. and plate facing p. 136. On the brass of John Lowlhe, D.C.L., should be noticed the two curious long streamers or Iiripipes hanging from the back of his tabard or hood, lt is hard to say w’hat they can be; but the closest parallel is in the two streamers on the back of the old Oxford commoners’ gown, which were probably survivals of sleeves. They are said to have given rise to the term “ plucking,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>  failing in examination, the story being that a man’s creditors might assemble at the conferring of degrees, and by ” plucking ” at his gown prevent him from going up for his degree.</p><p>@@@    It is just possible that this sleeved garment may be the<hi rend="italic">capa manicata</hi>  mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Mun. Acad.</hi>  p. 421, “ nullus regens in artibus ... in capa manicata Iectiones Iegat ordinarias, se&lt;T in pallio vel capa clausa.” Clark (pp. 188,189, &amp;c.) identifies the <hi rend="italic">cappa manicata </hi>with the tabard, but if, as suggested above, the <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi>  is the tabard, the <hi rend="italic">cappa manicata</hi>  cannot be the same. Braun, <hi rend="italic">Liturgische Gewandung,</hi>  p. 308, shows that a sleeved cope, called <hi rend="italic">cappa 'manicata,</hi>  did develop from the <hi rend="italic">cappa Clericalis</hi>  or everyday cope of the clergy, at the end of the 12th century, its use being forbidden by various synods. It is possible, then, that the <hi rend="italic">capa manicata</hi>  may have been w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>orn by non-regents, the tabard (which Haines alleges to have been adopted generally by M.A.’s in the late 15th century), or<hi rend="italic">pallium,</hi>  by regents.</p><p>@@@    The essential parts of Laud’s statutes, Burleigh’s letter, &amp;c., with much other matter bearing on academic costume from the 16th century onwards, will be found in C. Wordsworth’s UwtreriJZy <hi rend="italic">Life in the 18th Century</hi>  (London and Cambridge, 1874, p. 485 seq.). To the passages quoted by him may be added the following from <hi rend="italic">Johannis Berebloci Commentarii,</hi>  an eye-wit ness’s account of Queen Elizabeth’s visit to Oxford in 1566 (published in <hi rend="italic">Elizabethan Oxford<hi rend="sub">9 </hi></hi>ed. C. Plummer, Oxford Hist. Soc., 1887) ; at one of the disputations Mr. Campion, M.A., vvas dressed as follows: “ Toga illi turn Dalmatica talaris fuit, manicis remissis ac Iargitate sua dittîuentibust. Huic pallium inductum est undique consutum, praeter quam qua dextro patebant aditus. Postremo erant hu men superius pellibus albis, Candoreque Iucentibus, redimiti. Atque hic tum habitus fuit omnium magistrorum, praeterquam quod nqnnulli, loco palluda-menti illius pellicei, serico utebantur, omni colore vanegato.” This points to the wide-sleeved gow’n, tabard and hood as the dress of masters, but the colour of the hood was evidently not fixed. For Doctor White, D.C.L., “ ei vestis Dalmatica Iuerat talaris, ex electiori et clarissima purpura; lato clavo coccineo superius induebatur, add it urn postremo humeris pal uda ment urn est ejusdem coloris, cum serico subtegminc, similique turn vestiti habitu omncs Doctores sedebant.” Here <hi rend="italic">vestis Dalmatica</hi>  w'ould be the ordinary gown, <hi rend="italic">clavus latus</hi>  the scarlet gown, and <hi rend="italic">paludamentum </hi>the hood, as before. For costume up to the middle of the IOth century see Wall-Gunning, <hi rend="italic">Cere mon ies observed in the Senate House at Cambridge</hi>  (1828).</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>