<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Great part of Richelieu’s correspondence with Pozzo di Borgo, Capo d'Istria and
                others, with his journal of his travels in Germany and the Turkish campaign, and a
                notice by the duchesse de Richelieu, is published by the Imperial Historical Society
                of Russia, vol. 54. There is an exhaustive study of his career by L. de
                    Crousaz-Crétêt, <hi rend="italic">Le Duc de Richelieu en Russie et en
                    France</hi> (1897), with which compare an article-by L. Rioult de Neuville in
                the <hi rend="italic">Revue des questions historiques</hi> (Oct. 1897). See also R.
                de Cisternes, <hi rend="italic">Le Duc de Richelieu, son. action aux conférences
                    d’Aix-la-Chapelle</hi> (1898), containing copies of documents.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">RICHELIEU, ARMAND JEAN DU PLESSIS DE, </hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Cardinal </hi>(1585-1642), French statesman, was born of an ancient family of
                the lesser nobility of Poitou. The original name of the family was Du Plessis, but
                in the 15th century a younger branch obtained by marriage the estate of Richelieu
                with its strong castle surrounded by the waters of the Mable, and took the name of
                Du Plessis de Richelieu. The family produced not a few turbulent warriors during the
                Hundred Years’ War, and the cardinal’s father, François du Plessis, seigneur de
                Richelieu, began his career by killing the murderer of his elder brother and then
                fighting through the wars of religion, first as a favourite of Henry III., and after
                his death under Henry IV. He was a typical fighting gentleman of the period. The
                mother of the cardinal, Susanne de La Porte, belonged to a family of
                the magistrature, her father, François de La Porte, being one of the first advocates
                of the parlement of Paris. Armand was the third son and was born in Paris on the 9th
                of September 1585. When he was five years old his father died while assisting at the
                siege of Paris (on the 10th of July 1590); and his mother was left with five
                children and the estate heavily in debt. By care and economy, however, aided by
                generous royal grants, she was enabled to pay off mortgages and to bring up the
                children in a way befitting their rank. At the age of nine Armand was sent to Paris
                to the College of Navarre, where he passed with credit the regular courses in
                grammar and philosophy, and then entered a “ finishing academy ” which prepared the
                sons of nobles for the life of a courtier or a cavalier. But his training for a
                military career was suddenly cut short by the refusal of his elder brother,
                Alphonse, to accept the office of bishop of Luçon. The right of preferment to that
                see had been given to the Richelieu family by Henry III. as a reward for
                the services of Armand’s father, and the family drained its revenues for private
                use. When the cathedral chapter found courage to oppose this and opened suit to
                recover the ecclesiastical revenues for ecclesiastical purposes, Richelieu’s mother
                proposed to make her second son, Alphonse, bishop. He defeated this scheme, however,
                by becoming a monk of the Grande Chartreuse, and Armand, whose health was rather
                feeble in any case for a military career, was induced to propose himself for the
                priesthood.</p>
            <p>In 1606, at the age of twenty-one, Richèlieu was nominated bishop of Luçon by Henry
                IV. As he was almost five years under the canonical age, he was obliged <hi
                    rend="bold">to </hi>go to Rome to obtain a dispensation and was consecrated
                there in April 1607. In the winter of 1608 Richelieu went out to his
                poverty-stricken little bishopric, and for the next six years devoted
                himself seriously to his episcopal duties. He became favourably known among the
                zealous reformers of the church, and it was during this stage of his career that he
                made a friend of Father Joseph. Meanwhile he was impatiently waiting for an opening
                to a larger career. This came in 1614 when he was elected by the clergy of Poitou to
                the last States-general which met before the Revolution. In this he attracted the
                favourable attention of Marie de’ Medici, the queen-mother, and was chosen at its
                close to present the address of the clergy embodying its petitions and resolutions.
                After the States-general was dissolved he remained in Paris, and the next year he
                became almoner to Anne of Austria, the child-queen of Louis XIII. Then, by adroit
                courtly intrigue and* faithful service to Concini, he was appointed in 1616 a
                secretary of state to the king. But he owed all to Concini, and his taste of power
                ended with the murder of his patron on the 24th of August 1617.</p>
            <p>The reign which Richelieu was to dominate so absolutely began with his exile from the
                court. He had, however, already shown his ability, his firmness, and his diplomatic
                skill, and conducted the negotiations on the part of the queen-mother with
                Luynes, the king’s representative. Then, as he had incurred too much of the odium of
                a creature of Concini to hope for royal favour, he resigned himself to the post of
                chief adviser to Marie de’ Medici in her exile at Blois. Here he sought to
                ingratiate himself with Luynes and the king by reporting minutely the actions of
                AIarie and by protestations of loyalty. As this ungrateful work brought no reward,
                Richelieu, in spite of the earnest entreaties of the queen-mother, retired once more
                to his bishopric. But the king, while approving his conduct, was still suspicious of
                him, and he was exiled to Avignon, along with his brother and brother-in-law, on the
                7th of April 1618. There he lived in discreet, if melancholy retirement, writing “ A
                Defence of the Main Principles of the Catholic Faith,” and had apparently little
                hope of a further political career when the escape of Marie de’ Medici from Blois,
                on the 22nd of February 1619, again opened paths for his ambition. Luynes and the
                king recalled him to the post at Angoulême with the queen-mother, who received him
                ungraciously but who soon yielded to his judgment and allowed him <hi rend="bold">to
                </hi>sign the treaty of Angoulême with the Cardinal de la Rochefoucauld, acting for
                the king. By this treaty Marie was given liberty to live wherever she wished, and
                the government of Anjou and OfNormandywithseveral Castleswasentrusted to her. The
                bishop of Luçon was led to believe that the king would recommend him for a
                cardinalate, but, if we may trust the evidence, Luynes secretly opposed the request,
                and it was not until after his death that Richelieu was made a cardinal by Pope
                Gregory XV., on the 5th of Septfcmber 1622. His rank in the church was due to his
                skill in intrigue with Marie de’ Medici.</p>
            <p>Luynes’s death on the 15th of December 1621 made possible a reconciliation a month
                later between the king and his mother. Although Louis still distrusted her at heart,
                and disliked her dominating minister more, he allowed her to take up her residence
                in the Luxembourg palace in Paris, thus rendering intercourse possible. Richelieu
                seized his opportunity. He furnished Marie de’ Medici with political ideas and
                acute criticisms of the king’s ministry, especially of the Brularts. Marie zealously
                pushed her favourite towards office, and had gone so far as to absent herself from
                court for three months on account of the king’s persistent refusal, when Charles,
                duc de La Vieuville, then head of the council, in need of her aid in
                his negotiations with reference to the marriage of her daughter Henriette Marie,
                finally agreed to force Richelieu’s appointment to office upon the king, Louis XIII.
                La Vieuville thought to compromise by forcing the cardinal into a “ council of
                despatches,” with merely the privilege of advising the king’s council but entrusted
                with no power. Richelieu raised many objections to such a partial realization of his
                ambition, but the king ended them in April 1624 by naming him as a member of his
                council. By August Vieuville’s worst fears were realized; he was arrested on the
                13th of the month for corrupt practices in office, and the intriguing cardinal who
                had caused his overthrow became chief minister of Louis XIII. His advent was
                hailed with joy by both the Catholic party and the patriotic party, eager for the
                overthrow of Habsburg supremacy in Europe.</p>
            <p>For the next eighteen years the biography of Richelieu is the history of France, and
                to a large degree that of Europe. His work was directed toward a twofold aim: to
                make the royal power—his power—absolute and supreme at home, and to crush the rival
                European power of the Habsburgs. At home there were two opponents to be dealt with:
                the Huguenots and the feudal nobility. The former were crushed by the siege of
                La Rochelle and the vigorous campaign against the duc de Rohan. But the religious
                toleration of the edict of Nantes was reaffirmed while its political privileges were
                destroyed, and Huguenot officers fought loyally in the foreign enterprises of the
                cardinal. The suppression of the independence of the feudal aristocracy was
                inaugurated in 1626 by an edict calling for the destruction of all fortified castles
                not needed for defence against invasion.</p>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
