<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0685-03"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0732.jp2" type="entry">

                <p><label>ROMFORD</label> a market town in the Romford parliamentary division of
                    Essex, England; on the small river Rom, which flows into the Thames; 12j m.
                    E.N.E. from London by the Great Eastern railway. Pop. of urban district (1901)
                    13,656. The ancient church of St Edward the Confessor was replaced in 1850 by a
                    structure in Decorated style. There is a large brewery in the town, and
                    extensive market gardens in the neighbourhood. A grant of a market was obtained
                    in 1247, and this is still of importance as regards both cattle and corn.
                    Romford was included in the liberty of Havering-atte-Bower, which until 1892 had
                    a jurisdiction of its own distinct from that of the county, with a high steward,
                    magistrates, clerk of the peace, coroner and quarter sessions. The name of Bower
                    was derived from a queen’s residence attached to the ancient royal hunting-lodge
                    in the vicinity.</p>
               <p>The fact that Romford (<hi rend="italic">Rumford, Rompford</hi>) lies on the
                    high road between Colchester and London has determined its history. Bronze
                    implements have been found here, but no notice of Romford occurs till the 12th
                    century. It was included in the liberty of Havering, and the chief business of
                    the liberty was conducted there. But the corporation which is mentioned in
                    medieval records is not that of the town of Romford, but of the liberty of
                    Havering. Romford has only had a separate constitution since a local board of
                    health was formed in 1894, under the act of 1875, after the abolition of the
                    liberty in 1892. In the middle ages Romford was rather a meeting-place for
                    merchants than an industrial centre. Brewing, however, is mentioned in 1331, and
                    one tanner at least carried on business in Hare Street in 1467.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
