<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-r04-0725-02"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_0778.jp2" type="entry">

               <p>                   ROSCELLINUS
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(Rucelinus,</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps">Rousselin)
                        (c.</hi> 1050-c. 1122), often called the founder of Nominalism (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Scholasticism),</hi> was born at Compiègne (Compendium).
                    Little is known of his life, and our knowledge of his doctrines is mainly
                    derived from Anselm, Abelard and John of Salisbury. He studied at Soissons and
                    Reims, was afterwards attached to the cathedral of Chartres, and became canon of
                    Compiègne. It seems most probable that Roscellinus was not strictly the first to
                    promulgate nominalistic doctrines; but in his exposition they received more
                    definite expression, and, being applied to the dogma of the Trinity, attracted
                    universal attention. Roscellinus maintained that it is merely a habit of speech
                    which prevents our speaking of the three persons as three substances or three
                    Gods. If it were otherwise, and the three persons were really one substance or
                    thing <hi rend="italic">(una res),</hi> we should be forced to admit that the
                    Father and the Holy Spirit became incarnate along with the Son. Roscellinus
                    seems to have put forward this doctrine in perfect good faith, and to have
                    claimed for it at first the authority of Lanfranc and Anselm. In 1092, however,
                    a council convoked by the archbishop of Reims condemned his interpretation, and
                    Roscellinus, who was in danger of being stoned to death by the orthodox
                    populace, recanted his error. He fled to England, but having made himself
                    unpopular by an attack on the doctrines of Anselm, he left the country and
                    repaired to Rome, where he was well received and became reconciled to the
                    Church. He then returned to France, taught at Tours and Loc-menaeh (Loches) in
                    Brittany (where he had Abelard as a pupil), and finally became canon of
                    Besançon. He is heard of as late as 1121, when he came forward to oppose
                    Abelard’s views on the Trinity.</p>               <p>Of the writings of Roscellinus, nothing is preserved except a letter to Abelard,
                    mainly concerned with the doctrine of the Trinity (ed. J. A. Sehmellcr, Munich,
                    1850). See F. Piearet, <hi rend="italic">Rosselin, philosophe et théologien</hi>
                    (1896), and authorities quoted under Scholasticism.</p>            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
