<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>timber in it above ten feet long and four inches square. The Parliament House, and the Tron Church of Edinburgh, and the great hall of Tarnaway Castle, near Forres, are specimens of those roofs. They are very numerous on the Continent- Indeed Britain retains few monuments of private magnificence. Aristocratic state never was so great with us ; and the rancour of our civil wars gave most of the performances of the carpenter to the flames. Westminster Hall exhibits a specimen of the false taste of the Norman roofs. It contains the essential parts, indeed, very properly disposed ; but they are hidden, or intentionally covered, with what is conceived to be ornamental ; and this is an imitation of stone arches crammed in between slender pillars, which hang down from the principal frames, trusses, or rafters. In a pure Norman roof, such as Tarnaway Hall, the essential parts are exhibited as things understood, and therefore relished. They are refined and ornamented ; and it is here that the inferior kind of taste or the want of it may appear. And here we do not mean to defend all the whims of our ancestors ; but we assert that it is no more necessary to consider the members of a roof as things to be concealed, like a garret or privy, than the members of a ceiling, which form the most beautiful part of the Greek architecture. Should it be said that a roof is only a thing to keep off the rain, it may be answered, that a ceiling is only to keep off the dust, or the floor to be trodden under foot, and that we should have neither compartments in the one, nor inlaid work or carpets on the other. The structure of a roof may therefore be exhibited with propriety, and made an ornamental feature. This has been done even in Italy. The church of Santa Maria Maggiore in Rome, and several others, are specimens ; but it must be acknowledged that the forms of the principal frames of these roofs, which resemble those of our modem buildings, are very unfit for agreeable ornament. As we have already observed, our imaginations have not been made sufficiently familiar with the principles, and we are rather alarmed than pleased with the appearance of the immense logs of timber which form the couples of these roofs, and hang over our heads with every appearance of weight and danger. It is quite otherwise with the ingenious roofs of the German and Norman architects. Slender timbers, interlaced with great symmetry, and thrown by necessity into figures which are naturally pretty, form altogether an object which no carpenter can view without pleasure. And why should the gentleman refuse himself the same pleasure of beholding scientific ingenuity?</p><p>The roof is in fact the part of the building which requires the greatest degree of skill, and where science will be of more service than in any other part. The architect seldom knows much of the matter, and leaves the task to the carpenter. The carpenter considers the framing of a great roof as the touchstone of his art ; and nothing indeed tends so much to show his judgment and his fertility of resource.</p><p>It must therefore be very acceptable to the artist to have a clear view of the principles by which this difficult problem may be solved in the best manner, so that the roof may have all the strength and security that can be wished for, without an extravagant expense of timber and iron. We have said that mechanical science can give great assistance in this matter. We may add, that the framing of carpentry, whether for roofs, floors, or any other purpose, affords one of the most elegant and most satisfactory applications which can be made of mechanical science to the arts of common life. Unfortunately the practical artist is seldom possessed even of the small portion of science which would almost insure his practice from all risk of failure ; and even our most experienced carpenters have seldom any more knowledge than what arises from their experience and natural sagacity. The most approved author in our language is Price in his British Carpenter. Mathurin Jousse is in</p><lb/><p>like manner the author most in repute in France ; but the publications of both these authors are void of every appearance of principle. It is not uncommon to see the works of carpenters of the greatest reputation tumble down, in consequence of mistakes from which the most elementary knowledge would have saved them.</p><p>We shall attempt in this article to give an account of the leading principles of this art, in a manner so familiar and palpable, that any person who knows the common properties of the lever, and the composition of motion, shall so far understand them as to be able, on every occasion, so to dispose his materials, with respect to the strains to which they are to be exposed, that he shall always know the effective strain on every piece, and shall, in most cases, be able to make the disposition such as to derive the greatest possible advantage from the materials which he employs.</p><p>It is evident that the whole must depend on the principles which regulate the strength of the materials, relative to the manner in which this strength is exerted, and the manner in which the strain is laid on the piece of matter. With respect to the first, this is not the proper place for considering it, and we must refer the reader to the article Strength op Materials in Mechanics. We shall just borrow from that article two or three propositions suited to our purpose.</p><p>The force with which the materials of our edifices, roofs, floors, machines, and framings of every kind, resist being broken or crushed, or pulled asunder, is immediately or ultimately the cohesion of their particles. When a weight hangs by a rope, it tends either immediately to break all the fibres, overcoming the cohesion amongst the particles of each, or it tends to pull one parcel of them from amongst the rest, with which they are joined. This union of the fibres is brought about by some kind of gluten, or by twisting, which causes them to bind each other so hard that any one will break rather than come out, so much is it withheld by friction. The ultimate resistance is therefore the cohesion of the fibre ; and the force or strength of all fibrous materials, such as timber, is exerted in much the same manner. The fibres are either broken or pulled out from among the rest. Metals, stone, glass, and the like, resist being pulled asunder by the simple cohesion of their parts.</p><p>The force which is necessary for breaking a rope or wire is a proper measure of its strength. In like manner, the force necessary for tearing directly asunder any rod of wood or metal, breaking all its fibres, or tearing them from amongst each other, is a proper measure of the united strength of all these fibres ; and it is the simplest strain to which they can be exposcd, being just equal to the sum of the forces necessary for breaking or disengaging each fibre. And, if the body is not of a fibrous structure, which is the case with metals, stones, glass, and many other substances, this force is still equal to the simple sum of the cohesive forces of each particle which is separated by the fracture. Let us distinguish this mode of exertion of the cohesion of the body by the name of its <hi rend="italic">absolute strength.</hi></p><p>When solid bodies are, on the contrary, exposed to great compression, they can resist only a certain degree. A piece of clay or lead will be squeezed out ; a piece of freestone will be crushed to powder ; a beam of wood will be crippled, swelling out in the middle, and its fibres lose their mutual cohesion, after which it is easily crushed by tile load. A notion may be formed of the manner in which these strains are resisted, by conceiving a cylindrical pipe filled with small shot, well shaken together, so that each sphericle is lying in the closest manner possible, that is, in contact with six others in the same vertical plane, this being the position in which the shot will take the least room. Thus each touches the rest in six points. Now suppose them all united, in these six points only, by some ccment. This assemblage will stick together and form a</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>