<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>We have already, however, in our biographical notice of Fielding, quoted so amply from Sir Walter Scott’s critique upon his genius and works, that instead of pursuing an exhausted theme, we refer our readers to that article.</p><p>The name of Fielding always suggests that of his rival Smollett (1721-1771,) though, as writers of fiction, they rather admit of being contrasted than compared. They have, in fact, very few, if any, points in common ; agreeing only perhaps in a preference for the delineation of the comic, or the common, over the impassioned and poetical. They chose different departments in novel writing, and they cul</p><lb/><p>ables him to disarm his adversary without endangering the life of either ; a principle which makes the morality not less than the prudence of fighting to depend upon a man’s cunning of fence.</p><p>A strong contrast to the subtlety, the fine perception, and the power over the passions evinced by Richardson, is presented by his rival Fielding, (1707-1754,) who, with no command of the pathetic, no great share of wit, and no taste for that minute analysis of sentiment and wire-drawing of description in which our English Marivaux indulges, has yet maintained a more general and permanent popularity, by a combination of qualities well suited forthe purpose. His graspof observation led him to select with unerring sagacity, the leading traits of ordinary character, and to epitomize nature with skill, instead oftranscribingherat full length. His field of delineation admits of such variety and contrast, that in fact it excludes none but the highest and most poetical elements, in which Fielding had neither power of observation or conception. His flow of animal spirits and healthy vivacity of manner, contrast strangely with the Dutch finishing of Richardson’s pencilling, but are as well suited to the active, out-of-door scenes which Fielding loved to draw, in his pictures of imbroglios at ale-houses, and the stirring life of the road, as the pains-taking inventories of Richardson were to his still-life interiors, and the drowsy monotony of the occupations of their inhabitants. To these he added, at least in his great work, <hi rend="italic">Tom Jones,</hi>  the charm of a plot of unrivalled skill, in which the complex threads of interest are all brought to bear upon the catastrophe in a manner equally unexpected and simple, a grave humour, and power of quiet satire unroixed witll caricature, in which he is equally superior to Richardson and to Smollett. And with his other requisites he combined a knowledge of English life, both in its better features and its deformities, by which we mean, of the essential qualities of men, as modified at that time by the</p><p>accidents of situation, education, and pursuits,—the result, perhaps, of a long, and not always reputable experience,— to which Richardson, surrounded by a circle of female gossips, and weaving out his materials in his quiet back shop, purely from the stores of his imagination, can make but slender pretension.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Amelia,</hi>  much as it was admired by Johnson, is greatly inferior to <hi rend="italic">Tom Jones.</hi>  If the tone of the latter be far from high, that of <hi rend="italic">Amelia</hi>  is creeping and vulgar in no ordinary degree. Booth has Jones’ vices with an additional shade of meanness. Half the plot turns on the embarrassments of debt and contrivances to make both ends meet ; and one or other of the characters is generally in a spunging house. Such, too, is the infirmity of human nature, that we really find it difficult to preserve a sufficiently romantic respect for the heroine, pretty and amiable as she is, when the saucepan is seldom out of her hand.</p><p>“ Nec tantum veneris quantum studiosa culiuæ.”</p><p>The finish is put to the whole by the accident which mars even the personal attractions ofthe heroine ; for though the public were willing to regard Clarissa, after the outrage to her honour, with undiminished sympathy, it is certain they have not been equally indulgent to Amelia, after the misfortune of the broken nose.</p><lb/><p>tivated them by different means. As Fielding was the faithful and graphic painter of all the common features of character, so'the extraordinary and the eccentric were the peculiar appanage of Smollett. He either did not feel sufficiently the charm ofthe natural in character, and its power of endless recombination in the hands of a great artist, or he doubted his own powers, at least in comparison with Fielding, of extracting novelty from such simple materials. But the sphere of humorous exaggeration appeared to be open to him, without the awe of a predecessor, or the dread of a rival ; on that, therefore, he concentrated his powers of mind, neglecting in a great measure the other requisites of fiction ; and undoubtedly with a success, which leaves him, within the province which he was the first to occupy, and with the occupation of which he was content, still the undisputed sovereign. No one has ever yet equalled him in the observation, or where that does not serve his purpose, the creation of oddities and exceptional characters which never did or could exist, but still with just enough of humanity about them, to give us an interest in their eccentric movements, or in the invention of combinations of burlesque incidents not always of the best odour, which his fertile fancy showers forth spontaneously as from a cornucopia ; mistakes, rencounters, equivoques, whimsicalities of speech or action, all generally the best calculated to bring out in high raised and l udicrous relief the comic aberrations of the character represented, and to develope its latent madness; and neverfailing, at all events, to produce that result which Smollett seemed far more studious to attain than that of “ purging the passions by pity or terror ;” namely, the excitement of a broad-grin mirth, and “ laughter holding both his sides.” That the characters, where they have any decided features at all, are generally caricatures; for instance, that such commodores and lieutenants as Trunnion and Hatchway, never floated even under the primitive flag of Benbow; that thc absurdities of Pallet are painted an inch thick ; that by no human possibility could such an accumulation of comic disasters have befallen the characters of the tale, may, and indeed must be granted, even by Smollett’s warmest admirers. But if, following Smollett’s own example, we throw nature mainly out of the question, and look to what seems to have been his real aim, the objection of want of verisimilitude, while it may retain its truth, seems to lose half its force, and, we may add, wholly its power of conviction. It is in vain to point out the extravagance of the scene where Jolter, in an agony of terror, on hearing the direction given to put on the dead lights in the storm off Calais, goes through the steps of a mathematical proposition with infinite fervour, instead of a prayer ; or to criticise the manœuvres of Trunnion, tacking his way to church on his wedding day in consequence of ahead wind;— when the reader cannot see the forceof the objection, through tears of laughter. In that consummation which he chiefly aimed at, and in which he rarely fails, Smollett has gained his end ;—<hi rend="italic">solvuntur risu tabula ;</hi>  the sense of the improbability of the conceptions is lost in the irrepressible merriment which they occasion.</p><p>Humour, then, was the quality in which Smollett felt himself strongest; character, incident, the excitement of the feelings, were obviously with him minor considerations. There is no difficulty in discriminating his style of humour from that of Fielding. Fielding’s iscalmεr, chaster, perhaps of a higher kind than Smollett’s, but it certainly has not its breadth, force, and felicity. As Smollett could hardly have created in its main features so gentle a humourist as Parson Adams, so he probably could have scarcely imagined a stroke of humour so delicate and appropriate to the character, as when the Parson offers to w alk ten miles to fetch his sermon against Vanity,in order to convince his auditor of his total freedom from that vice. But neither, on the other hand, could he have imagined the feast after the manner of the ancients, theapparition of Pipes to the Commodore, the terrors of Pallet on learning</p></body></text></TEI>