<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Weadmitthattheauthorof the <hi rend="italic">Castle of Otranto</hi>  did not trust exclusively to such materials of interest. But granting that the general outlines of “ his feudal tyrant, his distressed damsels, his resigned yet dignified churchman,” are suffi</p><lb/><p>that sombre uniformity which, in his larger novels, produces such a depressing effect.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Rasselas</hi>  of Dr. Johnson (1709-1783), though it wears the form of a tale, has but slender pretensions to be included amongst the class of novels, for it has neither progressive incident nor character. It is a series of dialogues and moral reflections, very solemnly and beautifully written, tinged with that tone of mournfulness and despondency so likely to be the prevailing feeling of his mind in the composition of a work intended to defray the expenses of a mother’s funeral. <hi rend="italic">Rasselas</hi>  is, in fact, the <hi rend="italic">Vanity of human wishes</hi>  in prose ; and its incidents, if such they may be called, have even less pretensions to connected interest than those of <hi rend="italic">Candide,</hi>  to which it may be regarded as a moral and philosophical antithesis.</p><p>Judging, indeed, from <hi rend="italic">Rasselas,</hi>  and from the other wτitings of Johnson, it may be safely assumed, that his success as a novelist would not have been much greater than as a dramatic poet. He has nowhere shewn the least power of creation, by stepping out of himself, and putting on by the force of imagination the nature of others. Through the disguise of all the successive characters which he is obliged to assume in the <hi rend="italic">Rambler,</hi>  the sturdy, controversial, and somewhat pompous moralist stands confessed ; and whether he writes as a fine lady, a fop, a blood, or an elderly gentleman, still, like Puck, “ we know the man by the Athenian garments he hath on.” Independently of this, his views of life would certainly have been untrue, inasmuch as they were one-sided. Far from being disposed “to make the happiness he could not find,” the tendency of his mind,—in consequence, perhaps, of a constitutional melancholy,—was rather to unmake and neutralise the elements of comfort by which human life, in the average, is surrounded. Had he devoted himself in earnest to fictitious composition, he would have lent his eloquence and power of forcible statement, to shape the world of romance according to the gloomy fashion which the reality presented to his eye ; and in an inky coat, indeed, or a drab-coloured suit at best, very unlike the peach-blossom of his friend Goldsmith, he would in all probability have arrayed it.</p><p>About 1769, we witness the revival, though in a new shape, of the old taste for Romance. The delineation of life as it actually existed, was found to afford too little scope to minds who aspired after the imaginative and poetical, and who could not see why natural delineation of character and manners might not be combined with striking events, and with the picture of the higher passions ; why, as Walpole expresses it, in his preface to the <hi rend="italic">Castle of Otranto,</hi>  “ the fancy might not be left to expatiate through the boundless realms of invention, and thence to create more interesting situations, while the mortal agents in the drama still conducted themselves according to the rules of probability.”</p><p>In the first shape, however, in which romance reappeared, after this temporary slumber, the delineation of character occupied, it must be owned, but a very subordinate place. A little more attention was given to verisimilitude of manners, and much was done to abbreviate the tedious style of the old prose romance, and to throw life and movement into the narrative by dialogue, and by the omission of unimportant incidents not bearing on the catastrophe ; but the main efforts of our first modern romance writers were directed chiefly to the excitement of that feeling of love of the marvellous which exists more or less in every human breast. They chose for their favourite themes the varieties of the supernatural.</p><p>“ Somnia, terrores magicos, miracula, sagas,</p><p>Nocturnos lemures portentaque."</p><lb/><p>ciently correct, we are at a loss to perceive in any of his characters that individuality which gives to such pictures their chief value. To us they seem light, sketchy, and somewhat vague, although we think it quite possible that the effect produced by greater truth and distinctness of feature in the mortal agents of the piece, might not have harmonised with the extravagant demands upon the imagination which the author makes by his supernatural machinery. We agree with Sir Walter Scott, in thinking Walpole acted with judgment in leaving his machinery without those attempts at explanation introduced by Mrs. Radcliffe, always inadequate, and even throwing an air of ridicule over the mysteries of the piece upon a second perusal. But we cannot concur with him in his toleration of the extent to which Walpole has carried the marvels and improbabilities of his romance.</p><p>The apparition of Alfonso in the moonlight, dilated to a gigantic form, is impressive, and in certain moods of the mind even the skeleton ghost in the hermit’s cowl may have its terrors. But Clara Reeve was certainly right in the protest which she enters in her preface against the introduction of such machinery as that of a sword so large as to require a hundred men to lift it ; a helmet that, by its own weight, forces a passage through a court yard into an arched vault, and crushes a boy to death ; or a picture walking out of its frame. The effect of such violent instruments of terror is suicidal ; they destroy the very feeling they were intended to create, and give to the romance the air of a nursery tale. 1 ndeed, were it not for the singular charm of the style, which, like all Walpole’s compositions, is of the purest and most idiomatic English, and terse and condensed in a very high dcgree, we feel persuaded that the <hi rend="italic">Castle of Otranto, </hi>although the first specimen of the modem romance, would at the present day find few admirers.</p><p>In some respects, then, we think the <hi rend="italic">Old English Baron </hi>of Clara Reeve was an improvement on the <hi rend="italic">Castle of Otranto.</hi></p><p>For there the marvellous was brought within some limit of proportion ; “ the extravagant and erring spirit hied to his confine,” and, consequently, so far as regarded the creation of an impression of superstitious terror, or giving an air of probability and keeping to her narrative, we must admit, that her ghost of Lord Lovel, who is always exhibited under the obscurity of a dim religiouslight, did, in our youthful days, produce upon us a certain species of awe. In other respects, we rather fear the apprehension which is expressed in her preface, namely, that in avoiding the defects of Walpole, the spirit of his wild composition might evaporate, was not altogether without foundation. The style of the narrative in her hands became heavy, often dry and vulgar, like the ancient chronicle she professes to follow ; her dialogue is peculiarly flat and cumbrous, and the plot deformed, and rendered tedious by trifling incidents which now appear to us needlessly homely ; and yet the strong interest with which, as we can state from experience, this romance is perused at an early age, is a proof that in the cardinal point of exciting curiosity, and a feeling of mysterious interest, the ruder narrative of Clara Reeve effects, in a great measure, what all the liveliness of style, the deeper antiquarian reading, and more creative fancy of Walpole, failed to attain.</p><p>But this species of romance w riting was probably carried M to its perfection by Mrs. Radcliffe (1764-1823), who, in her di own walk of fiction, has never been excelled, though opinions may differ as to the comparative rank which she holds among writers of fiction, and also as to the soundness of that principle of composition which led her systematically to unravel her own spells, and to attempt an explanation by natural means, of effects which we had at first been encouraged to refer to the agency of supernatural causes. Indeed, we might rather say, that, in regard to this last point, there</p><p>is no room for doubt, and that this system of explanations is exposed to every possible objection ;—as totally inadequate in general, to account for the effects ascribed to it ; as run-</p></body></text></TEI>