<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rious opinions, of which the most commonly received is tl.at which represents them as sprung from the great family of the Mongolian Tartars, and in some way connected with those tribes called by the Chinese, Hioung-Nou. But there was also among them a manifest mixture of various nomad tribes, of which the predominant were probably the Finnish. It would indeed be absurd to imagine that a mighty migration of nomad tribes, sweeping onwards from the wilds of Mongolia to the Tanais (Don) and the Palus Mæotis (Sea of Azov), could be other than a mingled mass of all the various tribes whom they had conquered and absorbed in their tide-like course. Crossing the Tanais, the Huns drove before them the nations north of the Danube ; and these uprooted nations in their turn threw themselves headlong upon the Roman provinces, both impelled and supported hy the countless hordes that continued to press resistlessly behind. The Goths, unable to repel these terrible barbarians, sought and obtained permission to settle in the waste lands of Thrace, which formed part of the Roman province of Mœsia. Unfortunately for both themselves and the empire, the Goths had been taught Arianism, and as a very violent hatred subsisted between the Arians and the orthodox Christians, the Goths neither were well received by the Romans, nor entertained sentiments of much friendship towards them. And not less unfortunately, the officers whom Valens appointed to superintend the new settlements ofthe Goths were men of the most depraved and abandoned characters, and treated them with the utmost perfidy and cruelty. At length Lupicinus, the chief of these officers, attempted at a feast to murder Fritigern and the other Gothic leaders ; but the plot being prematurely discovered, the Gothic chiefs escaped, and arming their followers, massacred the greater part of the Roman troops in the province. In the mean time, the Huns advancing on their devastating career, drove the Ostrogoths before them into the territories possessed by the Visigoths ; and thus mightily swelled the strength of the infuriated Goths. Uniting themselves under Fritigern, the Goths laid waste Thrace, Macedon, and Thessaly, and approached to the very walls of Constantinople.</p><p>In this state of affairs, Valens, assailed by a strong and vengeful foe, applied to Gratian, the young emperor of the west, for aid. He had been engaged in warring successfully against the Germans, and was at that time in the field ; but seeing the urgent necessity of saving the eastern empire, he immediately marched to the assistance of his uncle. Before his arrival, the Gothic chief, Fritigern, thinking it lawful to use deceit against a deceitful foe, found means to draw Valens into a situation in which he was almost compelled to fight, without waiting for the arrival of succour. A decisive battle was fought near Adrianople ; Valens himself was killed on the field, and nearly two-thirds of the Roman army were cut to pieces. Not even on the dreadful field of Cannae had the Romans sustained a more fatal overthrow ; and the stern unconquerable spirit of the republic being no more, the fate of the eastern empire seemed to be inevitable. But what direct force might not have been able to accomplish, was effected by a rare combination of wisdom, valour, and probity. In consequence of his wars with the invaders of his own dominions, Gratian was unable to undertake the conduct ofthe war against the Goths ; but he called to his aid Theodosius, son of that Theodosius whom he had unjustly put to death, and whose death he had bitterly repented. Him he now raised to the dignity of emperor, and gave him at once the eastern empire, with the addition of the province of Illyricum. Theodosius thus raised to the purple, speedily showed himself worthy of the high trust committed to him, that of restoring the fortunes of a falling empire. The courage of the Romans had been so much shaken by their late defeat, that Theodosius did not think it prudent to hazard a general</p><p>engagement with the Goths ; but, like another Fabius, he saved his own forces, harassed the enemy, taught his men that the Goths were not invincible, and gradually restored to them their courage, perfected by improved discipline and temperate caution. At length Fritigern died ; and the Goths having no longer a leader capable of controlling the haughty chiefs of their ill-compacted confederacy, became disunited, and one by one submitted to the superior skill, policy, and authority of Theodosius. Great numbers of them received the pay, and were incorporated into the armies of that empire which they had so recently been on the brink of destroying, and the remainder voluntarily engaged to defend the Danube against the Huns. Thus, in about four years, the eastern empire was rescued from the most formidable danger by which it had ever been assailed, and seemed once more in a state of security.</p><p>While Theodosius was thus employed, another calamity befel the western empire. The character and conduct of Gratian had defrauded the fair expectations formed of him on his accession, and exposed him to the contempt of the more warlike part of his subjects. Maximus, who held the chief command in Britain, revolted against him, passed into Gaul, and prepared to dethrone the feeble emperor. The army violated its allegiance, and Gratian having fled towards Italy, was overtaken and killed at Lyons. The death of this prince left his young brother Valentinian II. nominal emperor of the west, though the usurper Maximus assumed that title. Theodosius was obliged to conceal his resentment against the murderer ofhis benefactor, not being yet in a condition to quit his own dominions ; and he even entered into a treaty with him, leaving him in the undisturbed possession of Gaul and Britain. But Maximus, encouraged by the success with which his rebellion had been followed, resolved to deprive Valentinian of even the nominal power which he enjoyed in Italy. Unable to defend his territories, he fled to Theodosius, and besought his aid. Theodosius having completed the pacification of his own dominions, immediately marched against the usurper, defeated him in two successive engagements, and his own troops having yielded him up, put him to death. Valentinian II. was thus restored to the throne of the western empire ; a throne which his weak character did not enable him to fill and to defend.</p><p>Theodosius, after his triumph over Maximus, resolved to visit Rome, and aid his imperial pupil in reforming the abuses prevalent in that city. This visit is memorable on account of the decrees published by Theodosius for the complete suppression of idolatrous worship in Rome. All sacrifices were prohibited under heavy penalties, the idols were defaced, and the temples of the gods abandoned to ruin and contempt. These decrees met but a feeble resistance, and from that time may be dated the complete and final overthrow- of pagan idolatry in Rome. It would be an easy though an unpleasant task, to show how the ill-judging teachers of Christianity, in their zeal to make converts, in order to make the transition more easy to the pagan multitude, adopted many of the rites and festivals of the ancient idolatry, assigning merely to some saint what had been ascribed to some subordinate deity, and thus introduced much of the ill-disguised heathenism which forms so large a proportion of papal superstition: but this we leave to the pen of the ecclesiastical historian. Having thus completed the triumph of Christianity over paganism, Theodosius returned to the east, and employed himself in the kindred task of putting an end to the heresies ofthe church, establishing the predominancy of the orthodox over the Arian party.</p><p>Valentinian II. had but a short time recovered possession of the empire of the west, when he was murdered by Ar-bogastes, a Frank of a bold and warlike character, who had obtained a great ascendancy over him. Arbogastes did</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>