<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ents. But had they retained them for ages, the sentient ' inhabitants of the earth, or at least the nobler animals, with man at their head, would not thence have derived much advantage. The general laws of nature produce changes in our atmosphere which must ever render these great elevations unfruitful. That genial warmth, which is equally necessary for the useful plant as for the animal which lives on it, is confined to the lower grounds. The earth, which on the top of Mount Hæmus could only bring forth moss and dittany, when brought into the gardens of Spalatro produced pot-herbs so luxuriant, that Diocletian told his colleague Maximian that he had more pleasure in their cultivation than the Roman empire could confer. Thus nature not only provides us manure, but conveys it to our fields. She even keeps it safe in store for us till it shall be wanted. The tracts of country which are but newly inhabited by man, such as great part of America, and the newly-dis-covered regions of Terra Australis, are still almost occupied by marshes and lakes, or covered with impenetrable forests ; and they would remain long enough in this state, if population, continually increasing, did not increase industry, and multiply the hands of cultivators along with their necessities. The Author of Nature was alone able to form the huge ridges of the mountains, to model the hillocks and the valleys, to mark out the courses of the great rivers, and give the first trace to every rivulet ; but has left to man the task of draining his own habitation and the fields which are to support him, because this is a task not beyond his powers. It was therefore of immense advantage to him that those parts of the globe into which he has not yet penetrated should remain covered with lakes, marshes, and forests, which keep in store the juice of the earth, which the influence of the air and the vivifying warmth of the sun would have expended long ere now in useless vegetation, and which the rains of heaven would have swept into the sea, had they not been thus protected by their situation or their cover. It is therefore the business of man to open up these mines of hoarded wealth, and to thank the Author of all good, w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ho has thus husbanded them for his use, and left them as a rightful heritage for those of after days.</p><p>The earth had not in the remote ages, as in our day, those great canals, those capacious voiders, always ready to drain off the rain-waters (of which only part is absorbed by the thirsty ground) and the pure waters of the springs from the foot of the hills. The rivers did not then exist, or were only torrents, whose waters, confined by the gulleys and glens, are searching for a place to escape. Hence arise those numerous lakes in the interior of great continents, of which there are still remarkable relics in North America, which in process of time will disappear, and become champaign countries. The most remote from the sea, unable to contain its waters, finds an issue through some gorge of the hills, and pours over its superfluous waters into a lower basin, which, in its turn, discharges its contents into another, and the last of the chain delivers its waters by a river into the ocean. The communication was originally begun by a simple overflowing at the lowest part of the margin. This made a torrent, which quickly deepened its bed ; and this circumstance increasing its velocity, as we have seen, would extend this deepening backward to the lake, and draw off more of its waters. The work would go on rapidly at first, while earth and small stones only resisted the labours of nature ; but these being washed away, and the channel hollowed out to the firm rock on all sides, the operation must go on very slowly, till the immense cascade shall undermine what it cannot break off, and then a new discharge will commence, and a quantity of flat ground will emerge all round the lake. The torrent, in the mean timc, makes its way down the country, and digs a canal, which may be called the first sketch of a river, which will deepen and widen its bed continually. The water of several basins</p><lb/><p>united, and running together in a great body, will, according to the principles which we have established, have a much greater velocity, with the same slope, than those of the lakes in the interior parts of the continent ; and the sum of them all united in the basin next the sea, after having broken through its natural mound, will make a prodigious torrent, which will dig for itself a bed so much the deepcr as it has more slope and a greater body of waters.</p><p>The formation of the first valleys, by cutting open many springs which were formerly concealed under ground, will add to the mass of running waters, and contribute to drain off the waters of these basins. In course of time many of them will disappear, and flat valleys among the mountains and hills are the traces of their former existence.</p><p>When nature thus traces out the courses of future rivers, it is to be expected that those streams will most deepen their channels which in their approach to the sea receive into their bed the greatest quantities of rain and spring-waters, and that towards the middle of the continent they will deepen their channels less. In these last situations the natural slope of the fields causes the rain-water, rills, and the little rivulets from the springs, to seek their ways to the rivers. The ground can sink only by the flattening of the hills and high grounds ; and this must proceed with extreme slowness, because it is only the gentle though incessant work of the rains and springs. But the rivers, increasing in bulk and strength, and of necessity flowing over every thing, form to themselves capacious beds in a more yielding soil, and dig them even to the level of the ocean.</p><p>The beds of rivers by no means form themselves in one inclined plane. If we should suppose a canal AB (fig. 14) perfectly straight and horizontal at</p><p>B, where it joins with the sea, this</p><p>canal would really be an inclined</p><p>channel of greater and greater slope</p><p>as it is farther from B. This is evi</p><p>dent ; because gravity is directed to</p><p>wards the centre of the earth, and the</p><p>angle CAB contained between the</p><p>channel and the plumb-line at A is</p><p>smaller than the similar angle CDB ;</p><p>and consequently the inclination to the horizon is greater in A than in D. Such a canal, therefore, would make the bed of a river ; and some have thought that this was the real form of nature’s work ; but the supposition is a whim, and it is false. No river has a slope at all approaching to this. It would be eight inches declivity in the mile next the ocean, twenty-four inches in the second mile, forty inches in the third, and so on in the duplicate ratio (for the whole elevation) of the distances from the sea. Such a river would quickly tear up its bed in the mountains (were there any grounds high enough to receive it), and, except its first cascade, would soon acquire a more gentle slope. But tile fact is, and it is the result of the imprescriptible laws of nature, that the continued track of a river is a succession of inclined channels, whose slope diminishes by steps as the river approaches to the sea. It is not enough to say that this results from the natural slope of the countries through which it flows, which we observe to increase in declivity as we go to the interior parts of the continent. Were it otherwise, the equilibrium at which nature aims in all her operations would still produce the gradual diminution of the slope of rivers. Without it they could not be in a permanent train.</p><p>That we may more easily form a notion of the manner in which the permanent course of a river is established, let us suppose a stream or rivulet s <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  (fig. 15) far up the country, makes its way through a soil perfectly uniform to the sea, taking the course <hi rend="italic">s abed ef</hi>  and receiving the <hi rend="italic">permanent additions</hi>  of the stream <hi rend="italic">g a, h</hi>  ⅛, t <hi rend="italic">c, hd,l e,</hi>  and that its velocity and slope in all its parts are so suited to the tenacity</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>