<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Laws were also passed, rendering every magistracy open to individuals of either order, the patricians to the tribunate as well as the commons to the consulship ; and there seemed to be now a complete union of all parties in the state, with the exception of one point, the law prohibiting intermarriages between the patricians and the commons.</p><p>A re-action, however, took place, and the patricians had sufficient influence to prevent the new constitution from coming into operation. No plebeian consul was elected ; and all the military tribunes, six in number, were chosen from patrician houses. Another struggle took place ; the tribune Canuleius proposed a law to repeal the prohibition of intermarriages between the two orders ; and after a temporary secession to the Janiculum, this law was carried. Still the plebeians were not content without the consulship being rendered accessible to them ; but this they were not yet able to obtain.</p><p>A new patrician magistracy was next appointed, which acquired powers not probably expected, or at first intended. This was the Censorship, the main duty of which had at first been limited to taking the census of the people ; but which, from the office of superintending the public morals with which it was entrusted, derived the power of reducing any dangerous citizen to insignificance, by degrading him from his rank and order. The commons bad now acquired full security for their persons and their property ; and while ambitious individuals would continue to be desirous of additional powers and privileges, the great body of the community felt little interest in their personal intrigues, and the state began to enjoy a period of comparative internal repose. The people had now learned the secret of their own strength, and how to make it available. For not long afterwards we find them aiding the senate when the consuis appeared inclined to disobey its authority, thus asserting their supreme power, and also refusing to permit the enrolment of soldiers for the Veientine war, unless the question of war were first submitted to the comitia centuriata.</p><p>The war with the Æqui and Volsci was again renewed, but was now waged by the united force of the republic, and with corresponding success. Several victories were gained and towns taken. Treaties were formed on favourable terms with the Latins and the Hernici, and Rome again began to extend her boundaries as she had done in the days of her kings. Her attention was now turned to the right bank of the Tiber, the peace with Veii being near its termination.</p><p>Between Rome and Veii a keen rivalship had long existed ; and as the truce approached its close, both nations prepared for a strife which both intended to be final. The taking of Anxur from the Volsci, enabled the Romans to send the greater part of their army against Veii. Several battles were fought, in which the Romans were generally successful, and Veii itself was invested. For some time it was rather a blockade than a siege ; and when the Romans attempted a complete circumvallation, the Veientians, aided by some of the neighbouring states, stormed one of the Roman camps, and broke up the siege. Again was the city invested by the Roman armies, and again were those armies so severely worsted by the assistance of the Faliscans and Capenatians, that it was deemed necessary to appoint thecelebrated Marcus Furius Camillus to the dictatorship.</p><p>Immediately upon his taking the command, the war began to assume a different aspect. A close siege was formed, and pressed with vigour ; all attempts from without to raise it were defeated; all sallies from within repelled with great loss. The poetical legends connected with the fall of Veii, mention several prodigies that portended the approaching doom of the one or the other of the belligerent nations. The supernatural swell of the Alban lake, and the formation of a tunnel, by which its waters were drained off, and directed into the fields of the circumjacent country, was one romantic episode of this poetic lay. The stratagem by which the city was taken, a mine carried underneath the walls, and opening into the precincts of the temple of Juno, by which the Roman soldiers were enabled to burst from the earth in the very heart of the city, rush to the gates, and open them for the admission of their countrymen, while the genera) himself, issuing from the same subterranean passage, finished a sacrifice to Juno, which the priest had declared to be the omen ofvictory, certainly bears more the appearance ofpoetic fiction than of historic reality. Veii, the rival of Rome, was taken, and the greater part of the districts, formerly subject to the Veientians, added to the Roman dominions. Capena and Falerii followed its fate, and the whole valley of the Tiber, on both banks, formed now tlle natural extent of the territories acknowledging the sway of the seven-hilled city.</p><p>More important to the future glory of Rome, than tlle territory gained by the conquest of Veii, was the new principle in the organization of her armies to which the siege of that city gave rise. In order to insure the destruction of Veii, it was determined to surround it completely, and prevent it from receiving any supplies of men or provisions, either by summer or winter. This rendered it necessary that the beseiging army should continue its operations during winter, which was a measure never previously adopted. But as the soldiers were, in general, cultivators of land, and supported themselves by the produce of their own industry, without pay from the state, it was necessary to give them pay if their services were to be required permanently in the field.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> This could be done only by the patrician holders of public land paying fairly their tithe into the public funds, besides bearing their due share of the public taxes. To this they consented, in order to secure tlle overthrow of their rival. Still the heaviest burden, and the greatest share of the danger fell on the commons ; and in order to procure their consent, the election of military tribunes out of their order was at length sanctioned by law. Rome had now nearly acquired that formidable character in which she soon afterwards appeared to terrify and subdue the world ; a military republic, where every citizen was, or might bc, a soldier, and with a standing army inured to war and conquest.</p><p>Camillus, the conqueror of Veii, and the most distinguished man of his time, was accused of having secretly appropriated to his own use a portion of the plunder of that city. Whether he had been really guilty of so mean an action, or whether the accusation was prompted by envy of his glory, dislike of his haughtiness, or dread of his power, cannot be determined ; but seeing the probability that he would not be acquitted, he w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ent into voluntary exile to Ardea ; and as he passed through the gates he is said to have turned, and invoked the gods, that if he were driven unjustly into exile, some grievous calamity might fall upon his ungrateful countrymen, and force them to feel his want, and to be glad to recall him to their rescue. Such a calamity was at hand, and ready to burst on the devoted city.</p><p>The Gauls had some time previously crossed the Alps, gained possession of the plains of the Po, penetrated the passes of the Apennines, and were advancing into central Italy. It is probable that the report of their approach was what prevented a union of the Etruscan cities when Veii was besieged by Rome. The Romans having accomplished their object, became also alarmed at tlle rumour of the advance of this terrible foe, and sent some of their citizens into Etruria to observe their movements, or at least obtain accurate intelligence. They arrived at Clusium just as it was beset by the Gauls. The Roman deputies joined the citizens in a sally, and one of them slew a Gaulish chief, and was recognized as a Roman while he was stripping off the spoil. The Gauls sent to Rome to demand the aggressors</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Livy, iv. 59, CO.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>