<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>on that side where the bank is low and flat, for in no other form would it withstand the action of the stream ; and it has been worn away till its flatness compensates for the greater force of the stream. The stream on the other side must be more gentle, otherwise the bank could not remain abrupt. In short, in a state of permanency, the velocity of the stream and form of the bank are just suited to each other. It is quite otherwise before the river has acquired its proper regimen.</p><p>A careful consideration therefore of the general features of rivers w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>hich have settled their regimen, is of use for informing us concerning their internal motions, and directing us to the most effectual methods of regulating their course.</p><p>We have already said that perpendicular brims are inconsistent with stability. A semicircular section is the form which would produce the quickest train of a river whose expense and slope are given ; but the banks at B and D (fig. 16) would crumble in,</p><p>and lie at the bottom, where their horizontal surface would secure them from farther change. The bed will acquire the form GcF, of equal section, but greater width, and with brims less shelving.</p><p>The proportion of the velocities at A and <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  may be the same with that of the velocities at A and C ; but the velocity at G and F will be less than it was formerly at B, C, or D ; and the velocity in any intermediate point E, being somewhat between those at F and c, must be less than it w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as in any intermediate point of the semicircular bed. The velocities will therefore decrease along the border from c towards G and F, and the steepness of the border will augment at the same time, till, in every point of the new border GcF, these two circumstances will be so adjusted that the necessary equilibrium is established.</p><p>The same thing must happen in our trapezium. The slope of the brims may be exact, and will be retained ; it will, however, be too great anywhere below, where the velocity is greater, and the sides will be worn away till the banks are undermined and crumble down, and the river will maintain its section by increasing its width. In short, no border made up of straight lines is consistent with that gradation of velocity which will take place whenever we depart from a semicircular form. And we accordingly see, that in all natural channels the section has a curvilineal border, with the slope increasing gradually from the bottom to the brim.</p><p>These observations will enable us to understand how nature operates when the inequality of surface or of tenacity obliges the current to change its direction, and the river forms an elbow.</p><p>Supposing always that the discharge continues the same, and that the mean velocity is either preserved or restored, the following conditions are necessary for a permanent regimen.</p><p>1.    The depth of water must be greatcr in the elbow than anywhere else.</p><p>2.    The main stream, after having struck the concave bank, must be reflected in an equal angle, and must then be in the direction of the next reach of the river.</p><p>3.    The angle of incidence must be proportioned to the tenacity of the soil.</p><p>4.    There must be in the elbow an increase of slope, or of head of water, capable of overcoming the resistance occasioned by the elbow.</p><p>The reasonableness, at least, of these conditions will appear from the following considerations.</p><p>1. It is certain that force is expended in producing this change of direction in a channel which by supposition diminishes the current. The diminution arising from any</p><lb/><p>cause which can be compared with friction must be greate when the stream is directed against one of the banks. I may be very difficult to state the proportion, and it woulι occupy too much of our time to attempt it ; but it is suf ficient that we be convinced that the retardation is greate in this case. We see no cause to increase the mean velo city in the elbow, and we must therefore conclude that it i diminished. But we are supposing that the discharge con tinues the same ; the section must therefore augment, or th&lt; channel increase its transverse dimensions. The only ques tion is, In what manner it does this, and what change o form does it affect, and what form is competent to the fina equilibrium and the consequent permanency of the bed i Here there is much room for conjecture. Du Buat reason; as follows : If we suppose that the points B and C (fig 17,</p><lb/><p>continue on a level, and that the points H and I at the beginning of the next reach are also on a level, it is an inevitable consequence that the slope along CMI must be greater than along BEH, because the depression of II below B is equal to that of I below C, and BEH is longer than CMI. Therefore the velocity along the convex bank CMI must be greater than along BEH. There may even be a stagnation and an eddy in the contrary direction along the concave bank. Therefore, if the form of the section were the same as up the stream, the sides could not stand on the convex bank. When therefore the section has attained a permanent form, and the banks are again in equilibrio witll the action of the current, the convex bank must be much flatter than the concave. If the water is really still on the concave bank, that bank will be absolutely perpendicular, nay, may overhang. Accordingly, this state of things is matter of daily observation, and justifies our</p><p>reasoning, and entitles us to say, that this</p><p>is the nature of the internal motion of the</p><p>filaments which we cannot distinctly ob</p><p>serve. The water moves most rapidly along</p><p>the convex bank, and the thread of the</p><p>stream is nearest to this side. Reasoning</p><p>in this way, the section, which we may suppose to have beer originally of the form MA αE (fig 18), assumes the shape MBAE.</p><p>2. Without presuming to know the mechanism of the internal motions of fluids, we know that superficial waves art reflected precisely as if they were elastic bodies, making the angles of incidence and reflection equal. In as far, there fore, as the superficial wave is concerned in the operation, M de Buat’s second position is just. The permanenc5 of th&lt; next reach requires that its axis shall be in the direction o the line EP (fig. 17), which makes the angle GEP = FEN If the next reach has the direction EQ, MR, the wave re flected in the line ES will work on the bank at S, and will b∣</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>