<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>avowed adherent, he expired in the thirtieth year of his reign.</p><p>The three sons of Constantine had been named Cæsars by their father, and on his death they divided the empire among them. Constantine obtained Gaul, Spain, and Britain ; Constantius, the Asiatic provinces, with the capital, Constantinople ; and Constans, Italy and Africa. The late emperor had assigned provinces to his two nephews, Dalmatius and Hannibilianus ; but the three new emperors, on the ground of a false accusation, barbarously murdered their uncles, cousins, and every member of the imperial house, except two cousins, Gallus and Julian, one suffering under a hopeless malady, the other a mere child. This bloody deed did not long secure to the brothers the quiet possession of their dominions. A dangerous war arose in the East, where Constantius was unable to resist the growing power of the Persians, but suffered several heavy defeats, and was in danger of losing the whole of Mesopotamia, when the Persians were obliged to offer a peace, in consequence of their own dominions being assailed by the nomad tribes beyond the Oxus.</p><p>In the mean time, ambition had kindled a war between the other two imperial brothers, Constantine and Constans. Not satisfied with his portion of the empire, Constantine first seized upon Africa, and then attempted to wrest Italy from Constans. He crossed the Alps, and began to ravage the country round Aquileia ; when falling into an ambuscade he was slain, together with the greater part of his troops. Constans immediately took possession of his fallen brother’s dominions, and thus became the sovereign of two-thirds of the empire. Satisfied, apparently, with this great acquisition, he plunged into the most dissolute indulgences, refused to cede any portion to Constantius, and even allowed that prince to wage an unequal war against the Persians, refusing to lend him any assistance. At length his general, Magnentius, raised the standard of revolt. Constans fled towards Spain, but was overtaken and killed near the Pyrenees.</p><p>While Constantius was preparing to avenge the death of hisbrother,anew revolt broke out in ∏lyricum. The army of that province compelled their general, Vetranio, to assume the purple ; and Constantina, sister of the emperor, encouraged him to the deed, and even urged him to form an alliance with the usurper Magnentius, who had so recently slam her brother Constans. Not deeming it prudent to engage in a war of such magnitude without providing for the administration of affairs during his absence, Constantius placed his cousin Gallus in the rank of Cæsar, and advanced to Constantinople, which Vetranio had seized while the emperor was engaged in the Persian war. Pretending to be willing to admit Vetranio to an equal share of power with himself, he obtained permission to enter the imperial city ; and immediately roused the feeling of the army and the people so far, that they declared him sole emperor. Vetranio quietly submitted, his life was spared, and he retired to Prusa, where he spent the remainder of his life in calm seclusion. Maxentius, fully determined to maintain his usurped power, marched at the head of a strong army into Pannonia to meet Constantius. The hostile forces came to an encounter on the plains of Mursa, and a furious combat ensued. It terminated in favour of Constantius, but the victory was purchased by the loss of his bravest troops ; a loss which the exhausted state of the population could not adequately supply. Next summer Constantius gained possession of Italy ; and Maxentius having fled to Gaul, sustained there another defeat, and seeing further resistance in vain, put an end to his own life.</p><p>Constantius was not long permitted to enjoy his triumph in tranquillity. His cousin Gallus, whom he had created Cæsar, instigated by the ambitious Constantina, and being himself of a morose and haughty disposition, caused so much</p><p>dissatisfaction in the provinces of the East, that Constantius was obliged first to recall him, and soon afterwards to put him to death. Of the race of Constantine the Great, there now remained only Julian, the cousin of the present emperor ; and he escaped the fate of his brother Gallus, partly in consequence of the intercession of the empress Eusebia, partly because he had hitherto preferred a scholar’s life to the dangerous eminence of military fame. He was permitted to prosecute his studies among the philosophers of Athens, from whom he imbibed that love of the mythology of ancient Greece, which led to his subsequent apostacy from Christianity.</p><p>Having thus once more arranged the affairs of the empire, Constantine paid a visit to Rome, where he was received with demonstrations of the most flattering character. But he was again called away, in consequence of the Germanic tribes assailing the western, and the Persians the eastern provinces of the empire. He sent Julian to command the armies in Gaul, and to oppose the Germans, while he himself endeavoured to maintain the eastern provinces. In his campaigns he obtained but little success ; and was even compelled to abandon the siege of Bezade, which the Persians had taken. Mean while, Julian was distinguishing himself in a very remarkable manner in Gaul. Instead of a mere scholar, ignorant of every thing but the jargon of the sophists, as Constantius had thought him, he appeared at once, when in command of the army, an intrepid soldier, and a consummate general. The Franks he completely overthrew in several engagements, gained by his personal courage and his skilful conduct, even though the generals had secret orders rather to thwart than second his efforts. Having repelled the Germanic tribes, he crossed the Rhine, plunged through the morasses, penetrated the forests, and traversed the plains of Germany, spreading havoc and dismay among these ancient enemies of the empire. Constantius, envious of his renown, and jealous of his rising power, demanded from him the best legions of his army, on the pretext that their services were required in the Persian war. The legions refused to obey, and proclaimed Julian emperor. Both parties prepared for a war, to decide their pretensions to the imperial diadem ; but while Constantius was exerting himself to the utmost, and while his mind was filled with rage and apprehension, he was seized with a fatal illness, and left the throne to his rival without bloodshed.</p><p>The high reputation of Julian, which had preceded him, procured tor him a triumphant reception at Constantinople. Immediately on his arrival, he began a rigorous reform in the whole administration ; banished the corrupt and servile ministers of his predecessor ; dismissed those whose sole employment had been to gratify the sensual and luxurious habits of the court; appointed men of talent and activity to administer the affairs of the empire ; and revived in Constantinople some of the forms of the ancient Roman constitution, particularly the senate and the consular title. But along with these reforms, he had planned a change of a much more extensive nature, nothing less than the subversion of Christianity, and the establishment of a somewhat reformed paganism in its stead. Trained as he was, in the philosophic lore of Greece, he imagined that he saw the deep mysteries of a true natural religion concealed beneath the fables of the heathen mythology ; and though he did not imagine the popular mind capableof understanding the deeper meaning, he purposed to remove some of the grossest parts of the external mythic rites, give these, so reformed, to the people, and retain the secret mysteries for the learned. All this, he was well aware, could not be accomplished at once. But he adopted the most subtle methods to promote his ulterior designs. He revoked all the edicts against idolatry ; discouraged Christianity, by removing Christians from all places of public honour and influence, and prohibiting them from teaching in the public schools, with the evident design</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>