<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in the droughts of summer, with a slope of one in 4800. This, by the formula of uniform motion, will have a velocity = 23½ inches per second, and its discharge will be 405216 cubic inches, or 234½ feet. It is proposed to give this river a depth of not less than five feet in any place, by means of floodgates of six feet in height and eighteen feet in width.</p><p>We first compute the height at which this body of 234½ cubic feet of water will discharge itself over the floodgates. This we shall find by Prob. II. to be 30¼ inches, to which adding 72, the height of the gate, we have I02¼ for the whole height of the water above the floor of the gate ; the primitive depth of the river being 3 feet, the rise or swell 5 feet 6¼ inches. In the next place, we find the range or sensible extent of this swell by Prob. I. and the observations which accompany it. This will be found to be nearly 9177 fathoms. Now, since the primitive depth of the river is three feet, there is only wanted two feet of addition ; and the question is reduced to the finding what point of the curved surface of the swell is two feet above the tangent plane at the head of the swell, or how far this point is from the gate. The whole extent being 9177 fathoms, and the deviations from the tangent plane being nearly in the duplicate ratio of the distances from the point of contact, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>e may institute this proportion, 66¼ : 24 = 9177<hi rend="sup">2</hi> : 5526<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. The last term is the distance (from the head of the swell) of that part of the surface which is two feet above the primitive surface of the river. Therefore 9177 — 5526, or 3651 fathoms, is the distance of this part from the floodgate ; and this is the distance at which the gates should be placed from each other. No inconvenience would arise from having them nearer, if the banks be high enough to contain the waters ; but if they are farther distant, the required depth of water cannot be had without increasing the height of the gates ; but if reasons of conveniency should induce us to place them nearer, the same depth may be secured by lower gates, and no additional height will be required for the banks. This is generally a matter of moment, because the raising of water brings along with it the chance of flooding the adjoining fields. Knowing the place where the swell ceases to be sensible, we can keep the top of the intermediate floodgate at the precise height of the curved surface of the swell by means of the proportionality of the deviations from the tangent to the distances from the point of contact.</p><p>But this rule will not do for a gate which is at a greater distance from the one above it than the 3651 fathoms already mentioned. We know that a higher gate is required, producing a more extensive swell ; and the one swell does not coincide with the other, although they may both begin from the same point A.</p><p>Nor will the curves even be si</p><p>milar, unless the thickness of</p><p>the sheet of water flowing over</p><p>the gate be increased in the same</p><p>ratio. But this is not the case,</p><p>because the produce of the river,</p><p>and therefore the thickness of the sheet of water, is constant. But we may suppose them similar without erring more than two or three decimals of an inch ; and then we shall have AF : AL = y F : DL ; from which, if we take the thickness of the sheet of water already calculated for the other gates, there will remain the height of the gate DL.</p><p>By following these methods, instead of proceeding by random guesses, we shall procure the greatest depth of water at the smallest expense possible.</p><p>But there is a circumstance which must be attended to, and which, if neglected, may in a short time render all our works useless. These gates must frequently be open in the time of freshes ; and as this channel then has its natural elope increased in every reach by the great contraction of the section in the gates, and also rolls along a greater body of water, the action of the stream on its bed must be increased by the augmentation of velocity which these circumstances will produce ; and although we may say that the general slope is necessarily secured by the cills of the floodgates, which are paved with stone or covered with planks, yet this will not hinder this increased current from digging up the bottom in the intervals, undermining the banks, and lodging the mud and earth thus carried off in places where the current meets with any check. All these consequences will assuredly follow if the increased velocity is greater than what corresponds to the regimen relative to the soil in which the river holds on its course.</p><p>In order therefore to procure durability to works of this kind, which are generally of enormous expense, the local circumstances must be most scrupulously studied. It is not the ordinary hurried survey of an engineer that will free us from the risk of our navigation becoming very troublesome by the rise of the waters being diminished from their former quantity, and banks formed at a small distance below every sluice. We must attentively study the nature of the soil, and discover experimentally the velocity which is not inconsistent with the permanency of the channel. If this be not a great deal less than that of tile river when accelerated by freshes, the regimen may be preserved after the establishment of the gate, and no great changes in the channel will be necessary ; but if, on the other hand, the natural velocity of the river during its freshes greatly exceeds what is consistent with stability, we must enlarge the width of the channel, that we may diminish the hydraulic mean depth, and along with this the velocity. Therefore, knowing the quantity discharged during the freshes, divide it by the velocity of regimen, or rather by a velocity somewhat greater (for a reason which will appear by and by), the quotient will be the area of a new section. Then taking the natural slope of the river for the slope which it will preserve in this enlarged channel, and afteι<hi rend="sup">,</hi> the cills of the floodgates have been fixed, we must calculate the hydraulic mean depth, and then the other dimensions of the channel. And, lastly, from the known dimensions of the channel and the discharge (which we must now compute), we proceed to calculate the height and the distances of the floodgates, adjusted to their widths, which must be regulated by the room which may be thought proper for the free passage of the lighters which are to ply on the river. An example will illustrate the whole of this process.</p><p>Suppose then a small river having a slope of two inches in 100 fathoms, or j⅛<hi rend="sub">ff</hi>, which is a very usual declivity of such small streams, and whose depth in summer is two feet, but subject to floods which raise it to nine feet. Let its breadth at the bottom be eighteen feet, and the base of its slanting sides four thirds of their height. All of these dimensions are very conformable to the ordinary course of things. It is proposed to make this river navigable in all seasons by means of keeps and gates placed at proper distances ; and we want to know the dimensions of a channel which will be permanent in a soil which begins to yield to a velocity of eighty inches per second, but will be safe under a velocity of twenty-four.</p><p>The primitive channel having the properties of a rectangular channel, its breadth during the freshes must be B = 30 feet, or 360 inches, and its depth <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  nine feet or 108 inches ; therefore its hydraulic mean depth <hi rend="italic">d =</hi></p><p>= 61∙88 inches. Its real velocity, therefore, during the freshes, will be 38∙9447 inches, and its discharge 1514169 cubic inches or 876¼ cubic feet per second. We see therefore that the natural channel will not be permanent, and will be very quickly destroyed or changed by this great velocity. We have two methods for procuring stability, vii.</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>