<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>dam or weir, and even when this is immersed in water on both sides, as in a bar or keep, frequently employed for raising the waters of the level streams in Flanders in order to render them navigable. We mentioned an observation@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>of Du Buat to this effect, when he saw a gooseberry rise up from the bottom of the canal along the face of the bar, and then rapidly fly over its top. We have attempted to represent this motion of the filaments in these different situations.</p><p>Fig. 5.</p><p>A shows the motion through a thin plate.</p><p>B shows the motion when a tube of about two diameters long is added, and when the water flows with a full mouth. This does not always happen in so short a pipe (and never in one that is shorter), but the water frequently detaches itself from the sides of the pipe, and flows with a contracted jet</p><p>C shows the motion when the pipe projects into the inside of the vessel. In this case it is difficult to makc it flow full.</p><p>D represents a mouth-piece fitted to the hole, and formed agreeably to that shape which a jet would assume of itself. In this case all contraction is avoided, because the mouth of this pipe may be considered as the real orifice, and nothing now diminishes the discharge but a trifling friction of the sides.</p><p>E shows the motion of water over a dam or weir, where the fall is free or unobstructed ; the surface of the lower stream being lower than the edge or sole of the waste-board.</p><p>F is a similar representation of the motion of water over what we would call a <hi rend="italic">bar</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">keep.</hi></p><p>It was one great aim of the experiments of Michelotti and Bossut to determine the effects of contraction in these cases. Michelotti, after carefully observing the form and dimensions of the natural jet, made various mouth-pieces resembling it, till he obtained one which produced the smallest diminution of the computed discharge, or till the discharge computed for the area of its smaller end approached the nearest to the effective discharge. And he at last obtained one which gave a discharge of 983, when the natural discharge would have been 1000. This piece was formed by the revolution of a trochoid round the axis of the jet, and the dimensions were as follow ;</p><p>Diameter of the outer orifice = 36 Diameter of the inner orifice = 46 Length of the axis    = 96</p><p>The results of the experiments of the Abbé Bossut and of Michelotti scarcely differ, and they are expressed in the following table :</p><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>N or the natural expense...............</p><p>Q for the thin plate, fig. A, almost at the surface........................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>.10000 - 027-78 √Λ</p><p>6526 = 018-13 √∕ι</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Q for ditto at the depth of 8 feet.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>. 6195 — 017-21 √Λ</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Q for ditto at the depth of 16 feet.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>. 6173-017-15 √Λ</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Q for a tube 2 diameters long, fig. B..</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>. 8125 = 022-57 √Λ</p></cell></row></table><table><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p><hi rend="sup">Q for ditto projecting inwards and flowing full</hi> } 6814 = 018-93√Λ</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="2" rows="1"><p>Q for ditto with a contracted jet, fig. ∣     _θ 14-27 √Λ</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Q for the mouth-piece, fig. D.....</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>........9831 -O27∙3I √A</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Q for a weir, fig. E..................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Q for a bar, fig. F...................</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"/></row></table><p>The numbers in the last column of this little table are the cubical inches of water discharged in a second when the height <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  is one inch.</p><p>It must be observed, that the discharges assigned here for the weir and bar relate only to the contractions occasioned by the passage over the edge of the board. The weir may also suffer a diminution by the contractions at its two ends, if it should be narrower than the stream, which is generally the case, because the two ends are commonly of square masonry or wood-work. The contraction there is nearly the same with that at the edge of a thin plate. But this could not be introduced into this table, because its effect on the expense is the same in quantity whatever is the length of the waste-board of the weir.</p><p>In like manner, the diminution of discharge through a sluice could not be expressed here. When a sluice is drawn up, but its lower edge still remains under water, the<hi rend="sup"> </hi>discharge is contracted both above and at the sides, and the diminution of discharge by each is in proportion to its extent. It is not easy to reduce either of these contractions to computation, but they may be very easily observed. We frequently can observe the water, at coming out of a sluice into a mill-course, quit the edge of the aperture, and show a part of the bottom quite dry. This is always the case when the velocity of efflux is considerable. When it is very moderate, this place is occupied by an eddy water almost stagnant. When the head of water is eight or ten inches, and runs off freely, the space left between it and the sides is about one and a half inch. If the sides of the entry have a slope, this void space can never appear ; but there is always this tendency to convergence, which diminishes the quantity of the discharge.</p><p>It will frequently abridge computation very much to consider the water discharged in these different situations as moving with a common velocity, which we conceive as produced not by a fall from the surface of the fluid (which is exact only when the expense is equal to the natural expense), but by a fall <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  accommodated to the discharge : or it is convenient to know the height which would produce that very velocity which the water issues with in these situations.</p><p>And also, when the water is observed to be actually moving with a velocity V, and we know whether it is coming through a thin plate, through a tube, over a dam, &amp;c. it is necessary to know' the pressure or head of water <hi rend="italic">h </hi>which has actually produced this velocity. It is convenient therefore to have the following numbers in readiness.</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">s</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">h</hi>  for the natural expense....................=</p><p>V*</p><p><hi rend="italic">h</hi>  for a thin plate at the depth of 8 feet... =</p><p>V<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">h</hi>  for a tube 2 diam. long.....................= —</p><p><hi rend="italic">h</hi>  for a dam or weir............................=</p><p>702</p><p>V’</p><p><hi rend="italic">h</hi>  for a bar......................................= ——</p><p>«31</p><p>It was necessary to premise these facts in hydraulics,</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  See<hi rend="smallcaps">Resistance of Fluids,</hi>  p. 180.</p></body></text></TEI>