<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>will be no contraction at the sides when the weir is the whole breadth of the river. But, further, the water is not now stagnant, but moving with the velocity -g-, S being the section of the river.</p><p>Therefore let <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  be the height of the weir from the bottom of the river, and <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  the height of the water above the edge of the weir. We have the velocity with which the</p><p>water approaches the weir = .<hi rend="italic">     l</hi>  being the length</p><p><hi rend="italic">I </hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">(l</hi><hi rend="sup">-</hi>t^ Λy</p><p>of the weir or breadth of the river. Therefore the height</p><p>producing the primary mean velocity is (—-=5-.</p><p>V <hi rend="italic">V2g (α + hy</hi></p><p>The equation given a little ago will give A=    ’,</p><p>when the water above the weir is stagnant. Therefore,</p><p>when it is already moving with the velocity <hi rend="sub">r7</hi>-i&gt;<hi rend="sub">i</hi>-=, we shall i(α +<hi rend="italic">h)</hi></p><p>haveΛ = (-——∑=V—(-=—-∖  . It would be</p><p>∖0∙431 ∕√2G∕ V/ <hi rend="italic">V2g (a</hi>  + A)/</p><p>very troublesome to solve this equation regularly, because the unknown quantity A is found in the second term of the answer. But we know that the height producing the velocity above the weir is very small in comparison of A and of α, and, if only estimated roughly, will make a very insensible change in the value of A ,∙ and, by repeating the operation, we can correct this value, and obtain A to any degree of exactness.</p><p>To illustrate this by an example. Suppose a river, the section of whose stream is 150 feet, and that it discharges 174 cubic feet of water in a second ; how much will the waters of this river be raised by a weir of the same width, and 3 feet high.</p><p>Suppose the width to be 50 feet. This will give 3 feet for the depth ; and we see that the water will have a clear fall, because the lower stream will be the same as before.</p><p>The section being 150 feet, and the discharge 174, the mean velocity is ¼¼⅙  = 1∙16 feet = 14 inches nearly, which requires the height of ¼ of an inch very nearly. This may be taken for the second term of the value of A. Therefore</p><p>A = f-D     ∖  ’— ί Now √2G is, in the present case,</p><p>∖,O*431∕√2G7 <hi rend="sup">i</hi>     &gt; t    &gt;</p><p>27∙03, <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  is 600, and D is 174 X 1728 = 300672. Therefore A = 12*28 — 0*25 = 12*03 nearly. Correct this value by substituting a more accurate value of the second</p><p>∕ D ∖<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>term <hi rend="italic">I</hi>  —τ=&gt;-) , or 0∙14. This will give us A =</p><p>V√¾(α + A√    <hi rend="sup">e</hi></p><p>12*28 —0*25 = 12*03 for a more accurate value, differing from the former about ⅛ of an inch. It is needless to carry the approximation farther. Thus we see that a weir which dams up the whole of the former current of three feet deep, will only raise the waters of this river one foot.</p><p>The same rule serves for showing how high we ought to raise this weir in order to produce <hi rend="italic">any given rise</hi>  of the waters, whether for the purposes of navigation, or for taking off a draft to drive mills, or for any other service ; for if the breadth of the river remain the same, the water will still flow over the weir with nearly the same depth. A very small and hardly perceptible difference will indeed arise from the diminution of slope occasioned by this rise, and a consequent diminution of the velocity with which the river approaches the weir. But this difference must always be a small fraction of the second term of our answer ; which</p><lb/><p>term is itself very small ; and even this will be compensat; in some degree, by the freer fall which the water will ha over the weir.</p><p>If the intended weir is not to have the whole breadth the river (which is seldom necessary even for the purpos of navigation), the waters will be raised higher by the saι height of the wasteboard. The calculation is precisely t same for this case. Only in the second term, which giι the head of water corresponding to the velocity of the riv <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  must still be taken for the whole breadth of the riv while in the first term <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  is the length of the wasteboa Also √2G must be a little less, on account of the contn tions at the ends of the weir, unless these be avoided giving the masonry at the ends of the wasteboard a cure shape on the upper side of the wasteboard. This shoι not be done when the sole object of the weir is to ra the surface of the waters. Its effect is but trifling at a rate, when the length of the wasteboard is considerable, proportion to the thickness of the sheet of water flowi over it.</p><p>The following comparisons of this rule with experiment will give our readers some notion of its utility.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><lb/><table><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Discharge of the Weir per second.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Head producing the velocity at the Weir.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Head producing the velocity above it.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Calculated Height of the ltiver above the Wasteboard.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Observe</p><p>Height</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>Inches.</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3888</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>7*302</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0*625</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6*677</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>6*583</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>2462</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5*385</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0*350</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>5*035</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>4*750</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1112</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3*171</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0*116</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3*055</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>3* 166</p></cell></row><row><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>259</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1*201</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>0*0114</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1*189</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1"><p>1*250</p></cell></row></table><lb/><p>It was found extremely difficult to measure tile ext height of the water in the upper stream above the wasι board. The curvature AI extended several feet up t stream. Indeed there must be something arbitrary in tl measurement, because the surface of the stream is not 1 rizontal. The deviation should be taken, not from a ho zontal plane, but from the inclined surface of the river.</p><p>It is plain that a river cannot be fitted for continued ι vigation by weirs. These occasion interruptions ; but few inches may sometimes be added to the waters of a riι by a bar, which may still allow a flat-bottomed lighter oι raft to pass over it. This is a very frequent practice Holland and Flanders ; and a very cheap and certain cc veyance of goods is there obtained by means of strea which we would think no better than boundary ditch and unfit for every purpose of this kind. By means of a I the water is kept up a very few inches, and the stream 1 free course to the sea. The shoot over the bar is preveι ed by means of another bar placed a little way below lying flat in the bottom of the ditch, but which may raised up on hinges. The lighterman makes his boat f' to a stake immediately above the bar, raises the lower b brings over his boat, again makes it fast, and, having h down the other bar again, proceeds on his journey. The contrivance answers the end of a lock at a very trifling e pense ; and though it does not admit of what we are accι tomed to call navigation, it gives a very sure conveyan∣ which would otherwise be impossible. When the watι can be raised by bars, so that they may be drawn off 1 machinery or other purposes, they are preferable to wei because they do not obstruct floating with rafts, and s not destroyed by the ice.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. III. Given the height of a bar, the depth of wal</hi></p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> This table from Du Buat is expressed io French measures.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>