<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>pellation of Augustus, by which name he is henceforward to be known in history ; and by an unanimous vote, they committed to him the entire government of the state. With this vote ended the Roman republic ; and from this period was dated the commencement of the Roman empire, under its first undisputed sovereign, Augustus Imperator.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">section hi.</hi></p><p>Augustus Cæsar now found himself possessed of the undisputed sovereignty of Rome, every competitor having perished, and the servile senate being ready to bestow upon him all titles, honours, and privileges which he could desire. He had before him the contrasted fates of Sylla and of Cæsar ; the former of whom died in peace after relinquishing the perpetual dictatorship, the latter was slain when in its full enjoyment. For a time, it is said, he hesitated whether to retire, like Sylla, into private life, or to retain imperial power; but by the sage advice of the politic Maecenas, his chief favourite, he was persuaded to retain it, and merely to govern under republican forms, though possessing a real and absolute monarchy. In consequence of the same advice, he laid aside the dictatorship, as too manifestly despotic, was annually chosen consul, and finally received tbe consular power in perpetuity ; and by being created perpetual tribune, his person was rendered sacred and inviolable, which gave a conventional security, at least to his life, and led to the enactment of the <hi rend="italic">judicia majestatis,</hi>  or accusations of <hi rend="italic">high treason.</hi>  As imperator he retained the command of all the forces ; and by assuming the censorship and the pontificate, he became possessed ofthe right of raising or depressing in rank, and of regulating every thing that depended upon religious ceremonies.</p><p>This supreme dominion, which his own power would have enabled him to seize and perpetuate, he pretended to be unwilling to retain, and made an offer in the senate of laying it down. This they requested him not to do ; and upon their urgent entreaties, he consented to retain it for a period of ten years ; on the expiration of which, the same form was repeated, and a similar prolongation conferred. This example, followed by succeeding emperors, gave rise to the <hi rend="italic">sacra decennalia,</hi>  festivals celebrated at every renewal of the imperial authority. It is not necessary to imagine that this decree of the senate was entirely the result of slavish submission to absolute power. Many of the senators could still remember the horrors of those contentions for supremacy which had taken place in the times of Marius and Sylla, and of the two triumvirates, and might be really apprehensive of equal convulsions and bloodshed, should he abdicate his power, and thus re-open the sources of contention, anarchy, and bloodshed. The wiser of them might see, that there did not now survive enough of republican virtue to render a republic any longer possible, and as Augustus, after the fall of all his antagonists, had displayed a great degree of mildness and clemency, they might fairly conclude, that his government was the bcst of which Rome was then capable, and might therefore desire its perpetuity, as the best method of securing the welfare of the empire. On his own part, his character had begun to assume an aspect very different from what it bore at the beginning of his ambitious career. At that time, its chief element appeared to be cold, remorseless cruelty ; now it became mild, placable, benignant, alike respectful to the senate, and benevolent to the people. The truest patriot might therefore be most earnest in desiring the continuance of his power, however it might have been acquired.</p><p>But while Augustus received equal manifestations of attachment from the senate and the people, he was sufficiently «ware, that to the army he owed his elevation, and that its favour must be secured. It could neither be disbanded nor retained in one place and body, with due regard to safety. Following the example of Sylla, he dispersed his veterans over Italy, settling them in thirty-two colonies, to make room for which, the former proprietors were in many instances dispossessed of their property. The settlement of one of these colonies near Mantua, was the cause of Virgil’s removal to Rome. Eight entire legions were posted on the Rhine, four on the Danube, three in Spain, and one in Dalmatia. Eight more were stationed in Asia and Africa. The whole standing army of tlle empire amounted to upwards of one hundred and seventy thousand men. There were also quartered in Rome and its vicinity twelve cohorts, amounting to about ten thousand men ; nine of these, called the prætorian bands, were intended as the imperial body-guard, the rest for the garrison of the city. These prætorian cohorts afterwards became not the guards merely, but also the dispensers of imperial power. Two powerful fleets were also maintained, the one in the Adriatic sea, the other for the protection of the western Mediterranean. As Augustus still allowed the senate a nominal share in the government, the appointment of lieutenants for the administration of affairs in some of the provinces was left to them, the others he himself retained; but as the imperial provinces were those on the frontiers of the empire, where tbe troops were stationed, the armies constituting the real power were still under his command. The financial affairs of Rome he also arranged anew, taking care to cause the treasures of the empire to flow chiefly into his own private and military coffers. At this period, the state revenue of Rome is computed to have amounted to upwards of forty millions of our money. These revenues were drawn chiefly from tithes charged on conquered lands, tribute and customs from provinces, crown lands, taxations amounting to a twentieth upon inheritances, and fines of different kinds imposed by different laws. Of these the tributes and customs from the provinces, and the rental of the crown lands, were by far the most productive, directing the main stream of wealth into the imperial treasury.</p><p>The internal administration of affairs being thus arranged, Augustus had leisure to attend to its enlargement, by conquests on the frontier. Nor were these inconsiderable. Western Gaul, and the mountainous districts in the north of Spain, were completely subdued. An expedition into Armenia, if of little consequence in itself, was nevertheless very gratifying to Roman pride, by being the means of recovering from the Parthians the standards that had been lost in the unfortunate campaign of Crassus. In Africa, the boundaries of the empire were extended into very remote regions, productive however of little else but empty fame. But the most important of these conquests was tllat of the regions south of the Danube, Rhætia, the country of the Vindelici, and Noricum, as well as Pannonia, and afterwards Mœsia. The arms of Augustus could not, however, penetrate far into Germany, defended as it was both by the determined valour of its inhabitants, and by its extensive forests and marshes. The chief successes in Germany were ρb-tained by the valour and skill of Tiberius and Drusus Nero, especially the latter, sons of the empress Livia by her former husband. A peace being at length concluded with the Germans, and Augustus not being desirous of extending his dominions beyond the territories over which he had obtained complete possession, and which were comprised within well-defined boundaries, the world obtained repose, and with great rejoicing, the temple of Janus was formally closed, to intimate the existence of universal peace.</p><p>During this period of general tranquillity, when the world was at rest, and a deep calm was brooding over the nations, in this “ fulness ofthe times,” there w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>asbomat Bethlehem in Judæa, of the lineage of David, the<hi rend="italic">Prince of Peace,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Saviour of the World,</hi>  whose coming thus brought with it</p></body></text></TEI>