<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>selves thus distrusted, and incapable of serving their country in council, they resolved to emigrate in a body, and establish themselves on one ofthe outposts of the Roman territory, to be a defence against aggression from that quarter. They settled on the Cremera, in Etruria ; but about two years afterwards the Veientians surprised them, put them all to the sword, and destroyed their settlement. Three hundred of the Fabianhouse are saidto have perishedby this disastrous event.</p><p>In a short time afterwards new contests arose ; the plebeians seized the Capitol ; and the patricians were obliged to yield to the passing of the Publilian law, by which it was enacted, that tlle tribunes should thenceforth be chosen by the votes of the commons in their tribes, and not by those of the whole people in their centuries. They could now elect their tribunes freely ; and they had formerly obtained the right of discussing all national questions in their own assembly. Had it been possible, when this great step was gained, for the two parties to have laid aside their contention, and regarded each other as truly brethren and fellow-citizens, instead of rivals, those rankling animosities might have been altogether allayed, which terminated only in the destruction of the republic, and the establishment of an imperial dominion, which was in fact a military despotism, so frequently the consummation of civil dissensions and revolutionary contests.</p><p>The wars between the Romans and the Æquians and Vol-scians still continued without any marked success on either side, internal feuds preventing Rome from exerting her whole strength ; nay, at times inducing the army to sufferitself to be beaten, out of dislike to its patrician general. During these wars, some eventsof a striking character are said tohave occurred, which seem to have formed the subject of popular poems, and have in that form been admitted into regular history. The story of Caius Marcius Coriolanus is the most brilliant of these warlike legends. He is said to have contributed mainly by his great personal valour to the capture of Corioli, and the defeat of a Volscian army assembled for its aid, on the same day. For this gallant exploit he received the name of Coriolanus. Soon afterwards, during a scarcity at Rome, he opposed the distribution of a supply of provisions sent by the king of Sicily, unless the plebeians would consent to forego the privileges they had so hardly won. For this he was tried in the comitia tributa and banished. He immediately joined the Volscians, and by his military skill and renown, at once defeated and appalled the Romans, till having taken almost all their subject cities, he advanced at the head of the Volscian army against Rome itself. In vain did embassies of his former friends entreat him to spare his country; he remained inexorable. Atlength a band of Roman ladies, headed by the mother and wife of Coriolanus, proceeded to his tent, where the lofty remonstrances of his mother were more powerful than all the arms of Rome. Coriolanus granted her request, at the same time exclaiming, “ O mother, thou hast saved Rome, but lost thy son.” Some accounts state, that he was soon afterwards killed by the Volscians in a tumult ; others, that he lived to an advanced age among that people, often towards the close of his life exclaiming, “ How miserable is the state of an old man in banishment!”</p><p>Another well-known and spirit-stirring legend of the Volscians is that of the dictator Cincinnatus. His son, Cæso Quinctius, had been banished on account of his violent abuse of the tribunes during some of the numerous contests between the patricians and the plebeians ; and he had retired to his own patrimony, aloof from popular tumults. The successes of the Æqui and Volsci atlength rendered the appointment of a dictator necessary, especially for the rescue of the consul and his army, who were surrounded by the enemy and blockaded in tbeir camp. The dictator laid aside his rural habiliments, assumed the ensigns of absolute power, levied a new army, marched all night to bring to the consul</p><lb/><p>Minucius the necessary succour, and before morning had surrounded the enemy’s army, and reduced it to a condition exactly similar to that in which the Romans had been. The baffled Æqui were glad to submit to the victor’s terms ; and returning in triumph to Rome, he laid down his dictatorial power, after having held it only fourteen days.</p><p>About the same time, Rome was engaged in a war which ultimately led to consequences of the utmost importance. This was the war with Veii, at that time the most powerful city of Etruria, and distant only about ten miles from Rome. There had been peace between Rome and Etruria from the days of Porsenna ; and the Etruscans had even supplied Rome with grain in a time of great scarcity, and when no other neighbouring state would grant any relief. A contest at length arose, which led to a war of nine years’ duration, and a peace of forty years. This peace was concluded in the year of Rome 280.</p><p>The intestine feuds between the patricians and the plebeians still continued with unabated animosity. Occasionally one of the consuls favoured the plebeians, and proposed some mitigation of their suffering, or increase of their privileges, but generally with little success. The Agrarian law, proposed by Spurius Cassius, continued to be the main demand of the commons and their supporters ; but its passing was constantly either directly prevented or evaded. But at last the commons became convinced that they need hope for no complete redress of their grievances, until they should have previously secured the establishment of some constitutional principle, from which equal justice would of necessity, and from its very nature, flow. Accordingly Caius Terentilius Harsa, one of the tribunes, proposed a law fora complete reform of the existing state of things. Its purport was, that ten commissioners should be chosen, five by the patricians, and five by the commons, to draw up a constitution, which should define all points of constitutional, civil,and criminal law ; and should thus determine, on just and fixed principles, all the political, social, and civil relations of all orders of the Roman people. The question of passing the Terentilian law, was now the subject of contention in Rome ; and the patricians seem to have endeavoured to prevent it chiefly by interruptions to the proceedings of the popular assemblies, caused by the violence of the young patricians. In consequence of these interruptions, tlle commons carried the Icilian law, by which a tribune was empowered to impeach before the commons in their own assembly (the <hi rend="italic">comitia tributa),</hi>  any patrician who should interrupt him when discussing public measures, and might require him to give security for his appearance, on the penalty of death and confiscation of his goods, if he should refuse to give such security. This law gave to the plebeian assembly jurisdiction over a patrician, and thus placed in their hands, not only the means of defence, but of retribution or revenge. The banishment of Caeso Quinctius, and perhaps also of Coriolanus, were tlle consequences of the Terentilian law ; but no dependence can be placed upon the dates given to these perhaps legendary lays.</p><p>Three commissioners were at length sent to Greece, to collect from the Greek states, such notices of their laws and constitutions as might be serviceable to the Romans. After the absence of a year they returned; andthecommons finding it in vain to insist upon five of their own body forming part of the revisers of the law, yielded the point, and ten of the most distinguished of the patrician and senatorial body were chosen to form an entirely new and complete code of laws, by which the state should be governed. They were named decemviri, and during their office they were to supersede every other magistrate ; and each in his turn was to administer the government for a day, till they should complete their legislative labours.</p><p>After the careful deliberations of a few months, the result was laid before the people, in the form of ten tables, fully</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>