<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>should at once migrate to Veii, and raise it to an equality with Rome in power and privileges. This destructive proposal was at the time successfully resisted by the more clearsighted patricians ; but now, when Rome was in ruins, the people few and dispirited, and Veii in a flourishing condition, its buildings better than even those of Rome had been, the proposal to quit the scene of devastation, and remove to one of comfort, was renewed and listened to with eagerness. It required all the authority of Camillus, enforced by that of the senate, and strengthened by every kind of assistance and encouragement that could be devised, to induce the Romans to remain, and undertake the heavy and almost hopeless task of rebuilding the ruined city of their fathers.</p><p>Livy informs us, that while the senate were sitting in grave and final deliberation respecting the removal to Veii, or the rebuilding of Rome, the people at the same time standing in clusters about the forum eagerly debating the same subject, some cohorts, returning from relieving guards, chanced to pass through the forum, when a centurion in the comitium called aloud, “ standard-bearer, plant your standard ; here we shall best remain.” The well-omened expression was seized upon by the senate, they rushed out, exclaiming with one voice, that “ they accepted the omen ;” the surrounding commons applauded and re-echoed the cry; and all, with one voice and one mind, agreed to abide by the will of the gods thus indicated, to raise from prostrate ruin, and maintain the destinies of their everlasting city. There is little doubt that Camillus planned this fortunate omen, and by his well-directed efforts in this point, not less than in war, gained the glorious designation of a new Romulus, FATHER OF HIS COUNTRY, AND SECOND FOUNDER OF RθME. Hitherto we have been led to trace the growth of Rome</p><p>from the building of the thousand Romulean huts on the Palatine, till under the Etruscan dynasty of its kings it had extended its power in all directions, entered into treaties with transmarine nations, and raised at home structures of great magnitude and imperishable durability. We have seen it sink into comparative feebleness during the intestine wars by which it was tom immediately after the expulsion of its tyrant monarch ; yet even then have we also seen noble proofs of that love of liberty, that strength of stern indomitable will, that irrepressible perseverance, and that lofty confidence in their own destinies, which conspired to render the proud citizens of Rome the conquerors of the world. Of even more importance is it to trace the growth of constitutional law, as it arose out of the struggles of one party which wished to engross and retain all civic rights and privileges, and the growing wealth, intelligence, and power of another, which gradually became more and more sensible of its rights, and more and more determined to obtain them. Even the most careless observerof these contests, and their fluctuations of success and disappointment, must have marked, that whatever either party gained by unconstitutional violence, was never to either a permanent gain ; that any premature advance of popular liberty was almost instantly followed by a recoil, proving, that not the soundness of a principle, nor the truth and accuracy of a theory, but the substantial, the felt, the practical necessity of the measure, is the only sure foundation of any addition to, or change in, the institutions of a country ; and that the natural and spontaneous adjustment of existing rights and institutions, which takes place wherever they are pervaded by the genial influence of a healthful vitality, is productive of a far greater and more lasting amount of true liberty, public and private, and of all that can promote real national welfare, than could ever be obtained or secured by those impetuously philanthropic legislators, who dream of creating a commonwealth in a day, as a magician would produce a palace by the utterance of some all-powerful spell.</p><p>To trace the growth of constitutional law as accurately as possible, we must revert to the earliest period of Rome, and endeavour to extricate from their fabulous en-velopements the historical truths contained in what are now admitted to be poetic legends. By this process we may hope to obtain as rational and intelligible a view of the city, the people, and the constitution of Rome, as the preceding narrative is capable of affording. It has already been stated, that the various inhabitants of that district of Italy, in which Rome was built, were the Oscan, Pelasgian, and Etruscan. The Pelasgi appear to have settled chiefly along the coast of Italy, from which they drove back the original inhabitants, who were probably Oscans. In process of time the Oscans descended again in great force from the mountains, overpowered the Pelasgians, and reduced them to a species of servitude, allowing them however to remain as tillers of the land, and artificers. From this intermixture arose the people subsequently known by the name of Latins ; combining the hardy and warlike habits of the Oscan mountaineers with the superior skill and civilization of the Pelasgi. This view may be regarded as confirmed by the fact, first pointed out by Niebuhr, that the words which relate to agriculture and the comparatively refined arts of life, in the Latin language, are closely allied to the same words in Greek, indicating the Pelasgian origin of both ; while the Latin words pertaining to war and the chase are entirely alien from the Greek, and are in short of Oscan origin.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> From this it may be inferred, that during the formation of the Latin language, the nation was composed of two races, the Oscan and the Pelasgian, of whom the Oscan held the chief sway. The two races being both accustomed to the simple patriarchal, or family form of rule, would have a natural tendency to blend together so as speedily to become one people. This seems to have been tlle condition in which they were, during tlle period when Rome is said to have been built.</p><p>Whether the traditionary founder of Rome was of Oscan or Pelasgian race, cannot be ascertained. The greater part of his followers appear to have been Pelasgian ; and from them the settlement may have obtained its name, which was afterwards given to the legendary hero himself. One of the traditionary accounts of Romulus, represents him as having been sent in his youth to an Etruscan city, for the purpose of receiving instruction superior to what could be obtained in Latium. Were we receiving the narrative as that respecting a real person, we should ascribe to his Etrurian education the attention paid by Romulus to augury, and the other arts of divination, in which the Etruscans are known to have excelled. The tradition may however refer to some influential Etruscan leader, who may have joined the early founders of Rome, and contributed greatly to mould their religious institutions. This view is supported by the statement of some authors, that an Etruscan chief, named Lucumo, was an early ally of Romulus, and aided him in the Sabine war, in which he was killed. The term Lucumo, we know, was not a personal name, but one of rank and office common to the Etruscan chiefs, who were all Lucumones. This Lucumo may have been the Tuscan chief Caeles Vibenna, who is said to have settled on the Caelian hill, to which he gave his name.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> If this be admitted, and we suppose the followers of this Etruscan Lucumo removed to Rome by the Roman founder, after the fall of their own chief, we have a very probable account of the origin of the third tribe of the Roman people, the Luceres, who, though admitted as an original tribe, were in some respects subordinate to the other two, the Ramnenses and Titienses, or Romans and Sabines. The Luceres may have been 01 a more mixed race than the other two tribes, and on that account somewhat less esteemed. It is indeed by no means improbable that the first inhabitants of Rome were compos</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Niebuhr, vol. i. p, 83.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  Ibid. pp. 382, 383.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>