<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>closely invested the town, and began the siege. The Numantines made the most desperate defence ; and after more than six months of almost incessant assault and repulse, the citizens destroyed their wives and children, set lire to the city, and by the flames or mutual slaughter perished to a man, leaving to Scipio to triumph, not over Numantia, but over the smouldering tomb of its unconquered children.</p><p>Amidst these triumphs of her arms, the policy of Rome obtained an acquisition more important in some respects, but also of darker omen. Attalus, king of Pergamus, at his death, bequeathed his dominions to the Roman republic ; and the senate, disregarding the remonstrances of Aristonicus, the natural heir, immediately took possession of this valuable inheritance. By what means Attalus had been induced to make this strange bequest, has never been accurately stated ; but thus, by some deep stroke of policy, Rome acquired possession of the largest and fairest portion of Asia Minor. The extensive provinces now held by Rome caused a very great and fatal alteration in part of her international policy. The inhabitants of these countries were entirely subject to Rome ; and the administration of them was conducted by those who had enjoyed the office of consuls, and by prætors, subordinate to whom were the quæs-tors, or collectors of thc revenue. Till about this time prætors were expressly appointed to each province ; but it now began to grow customary for the prætors who had vacated office to succeed to the provinces, under the name of pro-prætors. The highest military and civil powers were united in these governors ; and being thus prolonged in a species of self-appointed and irresponsible tenure of office, the consequence was equally injurious to the provinces, in the oppression and extortion inflicted on them, and to Rome, in the degeneracy thus fatally introduced. From this time forward Roman virtue was little but a name; while the armies and generals of the haughty and corrupt republic fought not so much for fame and dominion, as for the means of gratifying licentiousness and avarice.</p><p>The destructive consequences of Roman corruption and degeneracy soon became but too manifest in tlle seditions and civil broils which sprung up, and found no end but in the overthrow of the republic itself. It may be expedient to devote a few sentences to an explanation of the causes and the nature of the dissensions by which the very existence of the state was endangered ; especially, as owing to the resemblance which they bear to the ancientcontests between the patricians and the plebeians, they are liable to be misunderstood, as if they were merely a renewal of those ancient broils.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> They were, however, essentially different. The contests between the patrician populus and the plebeian commons of Rome’s earlier days was for the possession of the rights and privileges of citizenship, which was at first enjoyed by the patrician order alone, and for an equal share in which the plebeians strove. These contests had terminated soon after the passing of the Licinian law, and the admission of all orders alike to an equality in rights, privileges, and eligibility to all offices in the state. From that period, though the designations of patricians and plebeians might still be retained, the essential distinctions between them had ceased to exist ; and whatever contests arose, sprung from causes entirely different.</p><p>Although there had long ceased to be any legal distinction between the patricians and the plebeians, so that they could not accurately be regarded as different orders in the state, yet there continued to subsist the great difference between wealth and poverty, aggravated by the fact, that the senate wielded the entire power of the republic, and in general engrossed its emoluments. In consequence of this exclusive possession of power, the senators had gradually acquired the almost equally exclusive possession of that por</p><p>tion of the lands of conquered states which the laws of Rome devoted to the commonwealth. The Licinian law had been passed to prevent this unjust seizure of the public lands by the patricians, but was insufficient for that purpose, even its author being convicted of violating it soon after its enactment. While the attention of the state was almost incessantly occupied with the management of public wars, the senatorial body imperceptibly gained possession of the public lands, by grants, by pretended purchase, or in some instances by fair means, farming them from the state, in others by forcible seizure. In this manner the patricians, though no longer a peculiar order, possessing distinctive privileges in the state, became a wealthy and powerful aristocracy, engrossing nearly all public influence by means of their wealth, as their ancestors had done by means of their exclusive citizenship.</p><p>On the other hand, the great body of the citizens, deprived of their due share of the public lands, and not permitted by law to engage extensively in commerce, which was the privilege of the equestrian order, possessed the rights of freemen, and the privilege of voting, as citizens in all public matters in the comitia, notwithstanding their extreme poverty. Not obtaining their due share of the public lands, and not being permitted by the wealthy patricians to farm them, which they rather entrusted to their slaves, these poorer citizens were reduced to the necessity of resorting to Rome, and attaching themelves to one or other ofthe more powerful and wealthy of the patricians, by whom they were supported in return fbr their votes in the comitia. Thus the wealth of the one partly enabled them to purchase, and the poverty of the other obliged them to sell, those rights of voting on all public matters, which, instead of being the safeguards of freedom, became the very elements of tyranny and licentiousness. This consequence seems to have been foreseen, and partly guarded against, by the institution of the city tribes, for the purpose of preventing the undue influence of what was truly a city rabble, devoid ofthe means of subsistence, although voting in the public assemblies. But this preventive measure was not sufficient. The immense wealth which flowed into the public treasury from the tribute of conquered provinces, and into the coffers of the chief senators, from their public lands, the command of armies and of provinces, together with other public employments, enabled the state, as such, to maintain in idleness, by donations of money and provisions, great numbers of the people, whose votcs they thus secured ; and the wealthy families to maintain great numbers more, who might be either added to the supporters of the senate, or employed as the partizans of ambitious individuals. In this manner did it come to pass, that the main body of the citizens of Rome had sunk to the very lowest depth of poverty and venal degradation, and was ripe for any sedition or the perpetration of any crime. At the same time these idle and dependent citizens must have been often exposed to the real ills and sufferings of poverty ; and must have been often impelled to view with bitter envy the excessive wealth of their more fortunate countrymen, whose equals nevertheless they knew themselves to be in the eye of the law. That feelings fiercely democratical should spring up in the breasts of those who were at one time supported, and at another time trampled on, by a proud and avaricious aristocracy, which tlle senate had become, was both natural and inevitable ; and that some measure should be framed to check the increasing disparity between the wealthy and the poor, and to prevent the enormous accumulation of wealth in the hands of the senate as a body, or of a few families in that body, was absolutely indispensable to the permanent well-being of the republic. But such a measure would have required to be framed with the most consum∙*</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  See Heeren<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s History of the Revolution of the Gracchi.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>