<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dr. Johnson has defined Romance, in its primary sense, to be “ a military fable of the middle ages ; a tale of wild adventures in love and chivalry.” But although this definition expresses correctly the ordinary idea of the word, it is not sufficiently comprehensive to answer our present purpose. A composition may be a legitimate romance, yet neither refer to love nor chivalry—to war nor to the middle ages. The “ wild adventures ” are almost the only absolutely essential ingredient in Johnson’s definition. We would be rather inclined to describe a </hi><hi rend="italic">Romance</hi>  as “ a fictitious narrative in prose or verse ; the interest of which turns upon marvellous and uncommon incidents ;” being thus opposed to the kindred term <hi rend="italic">Novel,</hi>  which Johnson has described as “a smooth tale, generally of love ;” but which we would rather define as “afictitious narrative, differing from the romance, because the events are accommodated to the ordinary train of human events, and the modern state of society.” Assuming these definitions, it is evident, from the nature of the distinction adopted, that there may exist compositions which it is difficult to assign precisely or exclusively to the one class or other ; and which, in fact, partake of the nature of both. But the distinction will, be found broad enough to answer all general and useful purposes.</p><p>The word Romance, in its original meaning, was far from corresponding with the definition now assigned. On the contrary, it signified merely one or other of the popular dialects of Europe, founded, as almost all these dialects were, upon the Roman tongue, that is, upon the Latin. The name of romance was indiscriminately given to the Italian, to the Spanish, even, in one remarkable instance at least,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> to the English language. But it was especially applied to the compound language of France ; in which the Gothic dialect of the Franks, the Celtic of the ancient Gauls, and the classical Latin, formed the ingredients. Thus Robert De Brunne:</p><p>·* All is calde geste Inglis,</p><p>That en this language spoken is—</p><p>Frankis speech is caled <hi rend="italic">Romance.</hi></p><p>So saj∙is clerkis and men of France."</p><p>At a period so early as 1150, it plainly appears that the Romance language was distinguished from the Latin, and that translations were made from the one into the other ; for an ancient romance on the subject of Alexander, quoted by Fauchet, says it was written by a learned clerk,</p><p>“ Qui <hi rend="italic">de Latin</hi>  la trest, et <hi rend="italic">en Roman</hi>  la mit."</p><p>The most noted romances of the middle ages were usually composed in the romance or French language, which was, in a peculiar degree, the speech of love and chivalry; and those which are written in English always affect to refer to some French original, which usually, at least, if not in all instances, must be supposed to have a real existence. Hence, the frequent recurrence of the phrase,</p><p>“ As in romance we read Or,</p><p>“ Right as the romaunt us tells</p><p>and equivalent phrases, well known to all who have at any time perused such compositions. Thus, very naturally, though, undoubtedly by slow degrees, the very name of romaunt, or romance, came to be transferred from the language itself to that peculiar style of composition in which it was so much employed, and which so commonly referred to it. How early a transference so natural took place, we have no exact means of knowing ; but the best authority assures us, that the word was used in its modern sense so early as the reign of Edward III. Chaucer, unable to sleep during the night, informs us, that, in order to pass the time,</p><p>“ Upon my bed I sate upright :</p><p>And bβde one reebin me a hoke,</p><p>A Romaunce, and it me took To read and drive the night away."</p><p>The book described as a romance contained, as we are informed,</p><p>“--Fable»</p><p>That clerkis had, in old time,</p><p>And other poets, put in rhyme."</p><p>And the author tells us a little lower,</p><p><hi rend="sup">,,</hi> This book ne spake but of such things,</p><p>Of Queens' lives and of Kings."</p><p>The volume proves to be no other than Ovid’s <hi rend="italic">Metamor-]&gt;hoses;</hi>  and Chaucer, by applying to it the name of romance, sufficiently establishes that the word was, in his time, correctly employed under the modern acceptation.</p><p>Having thus accounted for the derivation of the word, our investigation divides itself into three principal branches, though of unequal extent. In the first of these we propose to inquire into the general history and origin of this peculiar species of composition, and particularly of romances relating to European chivalry, which necessarily form the most interesting object of our inquiry. In the second, we shall give some brief account of the bistory of the romance of chivalry in the different states of Europe. Thirdly, we propose to notice cursorily the various kinds of romantic composition by which the ancient romances of chivalry were followed and superseded, and with these notices to conclude the article.</p><p>I. In the views taken by Hurd, Percy, and other older authorities, of the origin and history of romantic fiction, their attentions were so exclusively fixed upon the romance of chivalry alone, that they appear to have forgotten that, however interesting and peculiar, it formed only one species of a very numerous and extensive genus. The progress of romance, in fact, keeps pace with that of society, which cannot long exist, even in the simplest state, without exhibiting some specimens of this attractive style of composition. It is not meant by this assertion, that in early ages such narratives were invented, in the character of mere fictions, devised to beguile the leisure of those who had time enough to read and attend to them. On the contrary, romance and real history have the same common origin. It is the aim of tile former to maintain as long as possible the mask of veracity ; and indeed the traditional memorials of all earlier ages partake in such a varied and doubtful degree of the qualities essential to those opposite lines of composition, that they form a mixed class between them ; and may be termed either romantic histories, or historical romances,</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> This curious passage was detected by the industry of Ritson in<hi rend="italic">Girαldus Cambrensis, “ Ab aqua iUa optima, qua Scottice νocatα esr </hi>FROTH; <hi rend="italic">Brittanice, </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Weird; Romane vero </hi><hi rend="italic">Scotte-Wattre." </hi>Here the various names assigned to the Frith of Forth are given in the Gaelic or Enrse, the British or Welsh ; and the phrase <hi rend="italic">Roman</hi>  is applied to the ordinary language of Englnnd. But it would be dilhculr to shew another instance of the English language being termed Homan or Romance.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>