<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Though this was the actual termination of the Roman Empire, yet it ought to be added, that Odoacer never assumed the purple and diadem, or the title of king of Italy, being satisfied with the regal title alone, without any local application ; and that after a comparatively peaceful, prosperous, and prudent reign of fourteen years, his fortunes sunk before the superior genius of Theodoric, the king of the Ostrogoths, a prince alike capable of founding or reconstructing a monarchy, under whose sway all vestiges of the imperial government were swept away, or remodelled, and Italy was formed into a kingdom.</p><p>There is no portion of profane history more pregnant with important instruction, than that which relates to the rise, the growth, the fluctuations, and the fall of Rome. It equally demands the studious attention of the scholar, the statesman, the philosopher, and the Christian. In its literature, the scholar will find treasures second only to those of Greece ; in its political struggles and changes, the statesman will find much to guide him in his endeavours to mould the constitution of his own country ; in its peculiar mental aspect and character, the philosopher will find a full development of one of the most vigorous and striking phases of mind that have ever been displayed in the history of humanity ; and in its resistance to the pure and simple truths of the gospel, the Christian will be led humbly to ponder on the deep depravity of man, and the danger of rejecting that system of religion which can alone elevate the character of individuals, and promote the security and happiness of communities. To point out the ftιll application of these views would require a dissertation far beyond our limits ; and we must therefore leave the intelligent and inquisitive reader to trace them for himself, «ell assured that the labour will amply prove its own reward.</p><p>(B.O.)</p><p>STATISTICS OF ROME.</p><p>Having thus related at length the rise and progress, decline and fall, of the empire of Rome, we now proceed to give a topographical and statistical description of that famous city.</p><p>Rome, by the shortest route, Brighton, Dieppe, Paris, Geneva, Simplon, Milan, Bologna, Florence, and Sienna, s about 1169 English miles distant from London.</p><p>The hills of Rome are chiefly composed of volcanic granular tufa, but the greater part of the Capitoline is lithoid tufa, which resembles the peperine stone of Albano, and the same material is found in some parts of the Cælian and Aventine hills. The valleys among the hills are chiefly of siliceous-calcareous sand, but argillaceous substances are very prevalent in the soil of Rome.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The height, in English feet, of the principal hills above the sea, is as follows : Capitol, at west angle of Tarpeian rock, 151 ; at north end, 160 ; Palatine, 170 ; Aventine, 148 ; Cælian, 146 ; Esquiline, 180 ; Quirinal, at Pope’s palace, 150 ; Pincian, 206.</p><p>Modern Rome occupies a triangular space, each side of which is nearly two miles long. The ground upon which it is built covers about 1000 acres, or one mile and a half square ; its walls form a circuit of fifteen miles, and embrace an area of 3000 acres. The greatest part of the population of Rome is now comprised within the limits of the Campus Martius. Three of the seven hills are covered with buildings, but are only thinly inhabited ; the Transtiberine district, including the Borgo, contains the rest of the inhabitants. The ancient city, however, was more than treble the size of the modern, for it had very extensive suburbs beyond the walls. The greater portion of the city stands extremely low, being only from forty to fifty feet above the sea, though sixteen miles distant from it. The Tiber, where it enters the city, is only about twenty feet above the level of the sea.</p><p>According to the unanimous opinion of all ancient writers, Rome was originally confined to tile Palatine hill,@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and after the union of the Romans with the Sabines, the latter, with their king Tatius, had their abode on the Capitoline. After the death of Romulus, a temple to his honour, under the name of Quirinus, was erected by Numa on the Quirinal hill, to which it gave the name.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p>The Cælian hill tvas added by Tullus Hostilius, who had his own dwelling there, and appropriated part of the mount for the residence of the conquered Albans.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> The Aventine mount was annexed to Rome by Ancus Martius, tile fourth king, who gave it for the accommodation of the Latins after his conquest of their country.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> He also surrounded mount Janiculum with a wall, and erected upon it a fort, lest this advantageous post should fall into the possession of an enemy. He likewise connected it with the city, by throwing across the Tiber the famous bridge called the<hi rend="italic">Pons Sublicius. </hi>When the waters of the river are not above their usual level, the traveller may still see the foundations of this bridge, the scene of the heroic exploit of Horatius Codes.@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi>  The city, which now contained four hills, the Palatine, the Capitol, the Cælian, and the Aventine, was enclosed with a stone wal! by Tarquinius Priscus; and his successor Servius Tullius having added the Quirinal, Viminal, and Esquiline hills, surrounded the whole city with a wall, built of large squares of peperine stone, and fortified it on the eastern side behind the Viminal hill, by his celebrated “Agger,”@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi>  which was finally completed by Tarquin the Proud. All around the wall, on both sides.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Brocchi's Description of the Soil of Rome ; Burgess’s Antiquities of Rome, vol. i.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>    It is impossible to ascertain the precise limits of the city of Romulus, but an outline of it has been traced by Tacitus : “ Igitur a Foro Boario, ubi æreum Tauri simulacrum adspicimus, quia id genus animalium aratro subditur, sulcus designandi oppidi cœptus, ut magnam Herculis aram amplecteretur. Inde certis spatiis interjecti lapides, per ima montis Palatini ad Aram Consi, mox ad Curias veteres, tum ad sacellum Larium : Forumque Romanum et Capitolium non a Romulo, sed a Tito Tatio additum urbi credidere.” Tacit. Ann. lib. xii. cap. 24- Compare also Dionysius, lib. ii. cap. 50; und Sextus Aurelius Victor in Romulo.</p><p>The Palatine was nearly a square, and hence Rome was sometimes called “ Roma Quadrata."</p><p>“ Et quis extiterit Romae regnare qundratæ ?”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ennius,</hi>  quoted by Festus.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> “ Tura ferant, placentque novum pia turba Quirinum.</p><p>Templa Deo fiunt, collis quoque dictus ab illo ;</p><p>Et referunt certi sacra paterna dies.”</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Ovid.</hi>  Fast. lib. ii. 507, &amp;e.</p><p><hi rend="italic">'lfpοu μiv οlu avτω</hi>  eστt <hi rend="italic">κaτeσκevnσμivou fu τω λόψω</hi>  τω <hi rend="italic">Kupιvω πpoσtryopevoμlvω</hi>  δt<hi rend="sup">,</hi><hi rend="italic">èKfiucv.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Plvtλhch.</hi>  “ in Romulo."</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Tit. Liv. lib. i. cap. 30. Eutropius in Tull. Host. &amp;c. “ Cselium montem intra mcenia clausit, numero et potentia crescente Roma ’ Vide Messala Corvino, lib. de August. Progen. p. 696. Aug. Histor. &amp;c.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi>    “ Aventinum novæ multitudini datum, &amp;c.....Janiculum quoque adjectum, non inopia loci, sed ne quando ea arx hostium esset ;</p><p>id non muro solum, sed etiam ob commoditatem itineris, ponte Sublicio tum primum in Tiberi facto, conjungi urbi placuit." Liv. lib. i-cap. 33.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Liv. lib. ii. cap. 13, &amp;c.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> Aggere et fossis et muro circumdat urbem ; ita Pomœrium profert." Tit. Liv. lib. i. cap. 44. See also Plin. Hiat. lib. iii. eaρ∙S∙</p></body></text></TEI>