<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>lution of the frame, in which it is progressively wound up during the process of making, the yarns are cut off ; and three of these strands, from so many stationary strand frames, each of which has performed the operation last described, revolving only round its own separate axis, are concentred together, and pass through the axis of one end of a rotatory frame, which twists them into a rope, and coils it up, progressively as made, upon a barrel within the frame.</p><p>1801.    Mr Cutting of the United States invented a method of making lines and ropes. His machinery was of much the same kind as Sylvester’s, FothergilΓs, and others already described.</p><p>1802.    January, a patent was granted to Mr Chapman for his invention of the application of certain substances to the preservation of cordage. This has already been noticed under the head Rope.</p><p>1802. March 9th, a patent was obtained by Messrs Mitchell and Son for further improvements in rope-making, in addition to their patent of 1799. The specification of this patent will be found in the second series of the Repertory of Arts (vol. viii. p. 241).</p><p>1804. Mr Huddart took out a patent for a machine for manufacturing hemp and flax into yarn. We have seen that in hand-spinning the fibres of hemp are spun into the yam by their bight or double, but by this invention they were to be spun into the yam by their end. The spinner, in this case, instead of walking backwards, remained stationary, with the machine containing the apparatus for twisting at a little distance from him. In front of the spinner a table or other support, containing a number of upright pins like those of the hackle, was fixed. This table was made broad enough to hold on it half the length of the article to be spun, while the other end was held by the spinner. The spinner commenced his work by drawing some fibres of the hemp, and making them fast to the hook of a whirl ; the machine was then set in motion, and the spinner with his spinning cloth took hold of and compressed the yarn as it was formed. By this means, says Mr Huddart, in his description, the longest hemp or flax may be spun without having its fibres reduced in length ; for tile pins before mentioned occasion all the fibres to be drawn out to their full respective length, or nearly so, and also prevent irregular drawing of the fibres.</p><p>It may not be amiss to mention in this place, that in France a method of spinning fibres by the end instead of the bight had long existed. Instead of the spinner fastening his bundle of hemp round his waist, it was fastened to a distaff by being laid along it and tied at the upper end, and the distaff was fastened by its lower end to the waist, and lay on the left shoulder of the spinner ; the lower end of the bundle of hemp thus hung loose, and the fibres were spun into the thread endlong.</p><p>M. Duhamel made certain experiments to ascertain what advantage this method had over the usual way of spinning by the bight, and the result did not warrant him in recommending its adoption where the men had been accustomed to the other mode.</p><p>•1805. October 30th, Mr Huddard took another patent for improvements in the manufacture of large cables and cordage in general. This invention consisted of a machine for twisting into ropes the strands formed by the machinery formerly invented by him, and resembled in some parts the machine of Mr Cartwright, called the cordelier.</p><p>In Mr Huddard’s machine the three strands were wound on their separate reels, which were hung in frames having a motion round their own axes, so as to give hardening to the strands ; and also a motion round a common centre in an opposite direction, in order to combine the strands into a rope. On the end of the axis round which the reels were carried for the last-mentioned purpose, the top was fixed, having in it three holes for the strands, and behind the top the rope was passed round three whirls, in such a manner as to regulate its tension while twisting.</p><p>1805.    November l6th, Mr Curr secured by patent an invention of a method of laying or putting together the strands which form a rope.</p><p>The invention consisted, first, in so proportioning the teeth of the wheel at the upper end of the walk which twists the strands, to the teeth of that of the lower end which closes the rope, that the workmen, by keeping time with each other in their heaving round the winches of their respective wheels, would give the proper amount of hardening twist to the strands and closing twist to the rope ; and, second, in regulating the motion of the laying-top, by having attached to it the end of a line or wire which is wound on a reel fixed to one of the wheels of the sledge, and made to move with a certain velocity according to the size and intended hardness of the rope.</p><p>1806.    August 9th, Mr Ralph Walker of Blackwall took out a patent for a new mode of making ropes and cordage, applicable to the making of ropes and cordage of any size.</p><p>The machinery for effecting these purposes is on the same principles as many of those already described ; but the arrangement of the parts is different, and very ingenious. In place of the reels with their yarns being hung on the face of three revolving discs, as in Mr Chapman’s machine, they are arranged on the surface of three cylindrical flyers, and the yarns are carried over rollers in the inside of the cylinders, and conveyed to their axes at one extremity, where they are compressed by passing through a hole. These cylinders, like the discs, revolve round their axes, and twist the yarns at that point of the axis where they pass through ; and they also revolve round a common axis, which is the main shaft of the machine. When the strands leave the cylinders they are guided by pulleys to a point in the main shaft, where they are formed into a rope. The patentee also describes a manner of tarring the yarns previously to their being wound upon the reels. In this case the tar in the kettle is heated by steam, and the yarns are passed through the kettle under a large roller which keeps them immersed. Engravings of all the machinery may be found in the Repertory of Arts, 2d series, vol. xxvi.</p><p>1806.    In this year Mr Curr took out a patent for proportioning the number of twists in the yarns to the length, moved by the spinners, so that they might elongate equally on being untwisted in forming the strand. To effect this purpose he had a cord wound upon a barrel attached to the spinning-wheel, and receiving a determinate motion from it ; the end of this cord, when the spinners were going to set oft', was attached to any one of them, whose speed could thus be regulated by the unwinding of the cord, and the other spinners had to keep pace with him.</p><p>1807.    October 30th, Messrs Chapman obtained a patent for a method or methods of making a belt or flat band of rope for mining and other purposes. This invention consisted in the combination of two or any greater number of the strands of shroud laid-ropes placed side by side so as to form any determinate breadth of belt or band ; and in a locomotive machine for stitching or riveting them together when stretched at full length.</p><p>1808.    June 25th, Mr S. Gadd took a patent for a method of forming ropes, which consisted in twisting the threads together in pairs, and forming the strands of these doubled threads.</p><p>1808. June 28th, Mr John Hall took a patent for regulating the twist of the thread in spinning, by means of an endless band traversing the walk, and moved with a given speed by pulleys fixed on the head of the spinning-wheel. To certain parts of this band marks are attached. When one of these marks is at the wheel, a spinner sets on, and in spinning keeps pace with the motion of the band, as indicated to him by the mark.</p><p>1828. September 4th, Mr Robertson took a patent for im-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>