<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Kyτle, who died in 1724, having spent his income on works of utility and of beneficence. The market is held on Thursday. The population amounted in 1801 to 2347, in 1811 to 2261, in 1821 to 2962, and in 1831 to 3078.</p><p>Ross, or Ross Carbery, a town in the county of Cork, Munster, Ireland, is situated on an eminence, at the head of a narrow creek in Ross Bay. It is a place of great antiquity. The town is laid out on a regular plan, and consists of a square, from the four corners of which diverge so many streets. It has an ancient cathedral, embosomed in trees, which, with the wooded banks of the bay, forms a remarkably beautiful feature in the appearance of the town. The harbour is spacious, but of little use, in consequence of being blocked up by the sand. The population amounted in 1831 to 1522.</p><p>Ross, <hi rend="italic">New.</hi>  See New Ross.</p><p>ROSSIANO, a city of Italy, in the province of Calabria Citeriore, and the kingdom of Naples. It stands on the sea-shore, between the rivers Lucena and Celano. It is the see of a bishop, and has a cathedral, and twenty-three other churches, of which nine belong to the same number of monasteries or nunneries. The inhabitants amount to 7700.</p><p>ROSS-SHIRE, a county of Scotland, having that of Cromarty so curiously intermixed with it, that the description of both under one head is a matter not only of convenience, but of necessity. Ross-shire, comprising the districts of Ar-dross, Easter Ross, Ardmeanach or the Black Isle, Kintail, Strathcarron, and the island of Lewis, is the most extensive county in Scotland, and second only to Yorkshire as regards Great Britain. The county of Cromarty, on the other hand, is comparatively small. It is divided into ten portions, which are whimsically inserted into various parts of the larger county of Ross, like fragments of a more ancient rock in some newer geological formation. One of these parts is the original county of Cromarty, so called from <hi rend="italic">Cromba,</hi>  that is, crooked bay, from the windings of its shores, consisting of that portion which lies in the peninsula to the south of the Cromarty Frith, and which surrounds the county town. This part rises like a huge lump to a height of 470 feet above the level of the sea, which washes the base of its cliffs. As a county, it was very inconsiderable both in extent and in value. But by the straggling additions which were made to it towards the end of the seventeenth century, it was increased to fifteen times its former extent. Of these additions, one is that district surrounding Tarbat House, on the northern shore of Cromarty Bay ; and a second runs from the south side of Dornoch Frith to Moray Frith, cutting off that portion of the county of Ross which terminates in Tarbat Ness. Two more fragments are found lying on the north of the river Carron, which has its embouchure near Bonnar Bridge ; a fifth is that which runs northward from the burgh of Dingwall, taking in Castle Leod and part of Ben Weavish ; the sixth lies to the north of Loch Fannich, at some distance to the north-west of which a triangular morsel is found to the north of Loch Nid ; the eighth is that which stretches along the southern shore of Little Loch Broom ; and the ninth is the large district of Coygach, lying between the northern shore of Loch Broom and Sutherlandshire ; to which may be added the Summer Islands at the mouth of Loch Broom, which are about sixty miles distant from the town of Cromarty. As we have already mentioned under the article Cromarty, this strange arrangement of territory was produced by the influence of tllat great and powerfid proprietor, George viscount Tarbat, afterwards earl of Cromarty, who, wishing to have all his various lands included in one shire, got them annexed to his own county in 1685 and 1698. But these were not all, nor the most extraordinary, annexations which he accomplished. For, as a part of the county of Cromarty, we are compelled to notice Royston, or Caroline Park, locally situated within the county of Edinburgh, and but a couple</p><p>of miles from the Scottish capital. But such arrangements were by no means singular. The district of Ferintosh, belonging locally to Ross-shire, is in fact a part of Nairnshire; and from similar causes many of the houses in the Canongate of Edinburgh belong to different counties in Scotland, from their having been the town residences of Scottish noblemen whose estates lay in those different shires. By the addition of all those portions which we have enumerated, the extent of Cromarty is calculated to be equal to an area of 345 square miles, or about 220,800 imperial acres. It contains only one entire parish, that of Cromarty, the other parts of it being parochially connected lvith parishes belonging to Ross-shire. The two towns of Cromarty and Ullapool belong to it, and its whole population may be estimated at about 5000 or 6000 souls. It is judicially under the jurisdiction of the sheriff of Ross, the sheriff-court being held at Cromarty every alternate Friday; and it is politically united with Ross-shire in returning a member to parliament. It contains about 20,000 arable acres. It has a considerable trade in pork for the English market ; and at Cromarty there is a thriving manufactory of hempen cloth, which employs about two hundred individuals.</p><p>Having thus given a general notion of the county of Cromarty as distinct from that of Ross, we may now proceed to consider the united counties under one view. Ross has its name from <hi rend="italic">Ross,</hi>  a promontory, and probably from that of Tarbat Ness. The united shires lie between 57.8. and 58. 10. north latitude, and between 4. 0. and 5. 46. west longitude from Greenwich. From the extreme northern point of Coygach, to the southern extremity of the Ross-shire boundary, which lies to the north-east of Loch Hourn, in Inverness-shire, the distance may be about seventy-two miles ; whilst from Strath Oikel to the Cowrie Water the measurement is not more than thirty or thirty-five miles. The breadth from Tarbat Ness to the extreme western coast to the north of Gairloch is about eighty-five miles. The whole surface may be about 2424 square miles, or about 1,545,600 acres ; but to this must be added the Lewis, which contains four of the thirty-three parishes of which the united county of Ross and Cromarty consists. The boundaries are Sutherlandshire and Dornoch Frith on the north, and Moray Frith on the east, Inverness-shire on the south, and the Western Ocean on the west. On the eastern coast Cromarty Frith shoots inland from that of Moray through the narrow strait produced by those grand and picturesque headlands called the Sutors of Cromarty, and expands into a still and land-locked basin, capable of holding the whole navy of Great Britain. The headlands themselves are so lofty and precipitous, that it is not uncommon during gales of wind from the north-eastward, to see waves breaking upon them to the height of an hundred feet, whilst all within is smooth. Stowe, in his Chronicle, calls it “ an exceeding quiet and saue hauen ;” Boyce calls it “ the hail of seamen ;” and Buchanan is still more particular in his praise of it. It is rather more than five miles broad at the widest part, and its length is about eighteen. The depth averages from nine to twelve fathoms, but in the entrance it in some places exceeds thirty, a depth which nearly doubles that of Moray Frith, into which it opens. The continuity of outline of the western coast is interrupted by many bays and sea-lochs, which afford numerous havens of shelter. From south to north, these are Loch Alsh, with its two branches Loch Duich and Loch Ling ; Loch Carron, with its branch Loch Keeshorn ; Loch Tor-ridon, Gairloch, Loch Ewe, Loch Greinord, Little Loch Broom, Loch Broom, and Loch Enard. All these exhibit magnificent scenery. That of Loch Torridon, for example, is of the grandest and wildest character; as is likewise that of Loch Duich, rendered peculiarly interesting by the remains of the Castle of Eilean Donnan, the ancient stronghold of the Mackenzies, the Lords of Kintail. The outer</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>