<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>but we continue to be of the opinion that plain roofs are greatly superior in point of strength, and therefore should be adopted in cases where the main difficulty is to insure this necessary circumstance.</p><p>It would appear very neglectful to omit an account of the roofs put on round buildings, such as domes, cupolas, and the like. They appear to be the most difficult tasks in the carpenter’s art. But the difficulty lies entirely in the mode of framing, or what the French call the <hi rend="italic">trait de charpenterie.</hi>  The view which we are taking of the subject, as a part of mechanical science, has little connection with this. It is plain, that whatever form of a truss is excellent in a square building, must be equally so as one of the frames of a round one ; and the only difficulty is how to manage their mutual intersections at the top. Some of them must be discontinued before they reach that length, and common sense will teach us to cut them short alternately, and always leave as many, that they may stand equally thick as at their first springing from the base of the dome. Thus the length of the purlins, which reach from truss to truss, will never be too great.</p><p>The truth is, that a round building which gathers in at top, like a glass-house, a potter’s kiln, or a spire steeple, instead of being the most difficult to erect with stability, is of all others the easiest. Nothing can show this more forcibly than daily practice, where they are run up without centres and without scaffoldings ; and it requires gross blunders indeed in the choice of their outline to put them in much danger of falling from a want of equilibrium. In like manner, a dome of carpentry can hardly fall, give it what shape or what construction you will. It <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi>  fall, unless some part of it flies out at the bottom. An iron hoop round it, or straps at the joinings of the trusses and purlins, which make an equivalent to a hoop, will effectually secure it. And as beauty requires that a dome shall spring almost perpendicularly from the wall, it is evident that there is hardly any thrust to force out the walls. The only part where this is to be guarded against is where the tangent is inclined about forty or fifty degrees to the horizon. Here it will be proper to make a course of firm horizontal joinings.</p><p>We doubt not but that domes of carpentry will now be raised of great extent. The Halle du Bled at Paris, of two hundred feet in diameter, was the invention of an intelligent carpenter, the Sieur Moulineau. He was not by any means a man of science, but had much more mechanical knowledge than artisans usually have, and was convinced that a very thin shell of timber might not only be so shaped as to be nearly in equilibrio, but that, if hooped or firmly connected horizontally, it would have all the stiffness that was necessary ; and he presented his project to the magistracy of Paris. The grandeur of it pleased them, but they doubted bf its possibility. Being a great public work, they prevailed on the Academy of Sciences to consider it. The members who were competent judges were instantly struck with the justness of M. Moulineau’s principles, and astonished that a thing so plain had not been long familiar to every house-carpenter. It quickly became an universal topic of conversation, dispute, and cabal, in the polite circles of Paris. But the academy having given a very favourable report of their opinion, the project was immediately carried into execution, and soon completed ; and now stands as one of the great exhibitions of Paris.</p><p>The construction of this dome is the simplest thing that can be imagined. The circular ribs which compose it consist of planks nine feet long, thirteen inches broad, and three inches thick ; and each rib consists of three of these planks bolted together in such a manner that two points meet. A rib is begun, for instance, with a plank of three feet long standing between one of six feet and another of nine ; and this is continued to the head of it. No machinery was necessary for carrying up such small pieces, and the whole went up like a piece of bricklayer’s work. At various distances these ribs were connected horizontally by purlins and iron straps, which made so many hoops to the whole. When the work had reached such a height that the distance of the ribs was two thirds of the original distance, every third rib was discontinued, and the space was left open and glazed. When carried so much higher that the distance of the ribs is one third of the original distance, every second rib, now consisting of two ribs very near each other, is in like manner discontinued, and the void is glazed. A little above this the heads of the ribs are framed into a circular ring of timber, which forms a wide opening in the middle ; over which is a glazed canopy or umbrella, with an opening between it and the dome for allowing the heated air to get out. All who have seen this dome say that it is the most beautiful and magnificent object they have ever beheld.</p><p>The only difficulty which occurs in the construction of wooden domes is when they are unequally loaded, by carrying a heavy lanthorn or cupola in the middle. In such a case, if the dome were a mere shell, it would be crushed in at the top, or the action of the wind on the lanthorn might tear it out of its place. Such a dome must therefore consist of trussed frames. Mr Price has given a very good one in his plate OP, though much stronger in the trusses than there was any occasion for. This causes a great loss of room, and throws the lights of the lanthorn too far up. It is evidently copied from Sir Christopher Wren’s dome of St Paul’s Church in London ; a model of propriety in its particular situation, but by no means a general model of a wooden dome. It rests on the brick cone within it ; and Sir Christopher has very ingeniously made use of it for stiffening this cone, as any intelligent person will perceive by attending to its construction.</p><p>Fig. 28 presents a dome executed in the Register Office in Edinburgh by James and Robert Adam, and is very agreeable to mechanical principles. The span is fifty feet clear, and the thickness is only four and a half feet.</p><p>We cannot take leave of the subject without taking some notice of what we have already spoken of with commendation by the name of <hi rend="italic">Norman roofs.</hi>  We called them <hi rend="italic">Norman,</hi>  because they were frequently executed by that people soon after their establishment in Italy and other parts of the south of Europe, and became the prevailing taste in all the great baronial castles. Their architects were rivals to the Saracens and Moors, who about that time built many Christian churches ; and the architecture which we now call Gothic seems to have arisen from their joint labours.</p><p>The principle of a Norman roof is extremely simple. The rafters all abutted on joggled king-posts AF, BG, CH, &amp;c.</p><p>(fig. 29), and braces or ties were then disposed in the intervals. In the middle of the roof HB and HD are evidently ties in a state of extension, whilst the post CH is compressed by them. Towards the walls on each side,</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>