<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tinguished during the middle ages. All minstrels did not use the harp, and recite or compose romantic poetry ; but it cannot be denied that such was the occupation of the most eminent of the order. This Ritson has rather admitted than denied ; and the number of quotations which his industry has brought together, rendered such an admission inevitable.</p><p>Indeed, the slightest acquaintance with ancient romances of the metrical class, shows us that they were composed for the express purpose of being recited, or, more properly, chaunted to some simple tune or cadence for the amusement of a large audience. Our ancestors, as they were circumscribed in knowledge, were also more limited in conversational powers than their enlightened descendants ; and it seems probable, that in their public festivals, there was great advantage found in the presence of a minstrel who should recite some popular composition on their favourite subjects of love and war, to prevent those pauses of discourse which sometimes fall heavily on a company, even of the present accomplished age, and to supply an agreeable train of ideas to those guests who had few of their own. It is, therefore, almost constantly insinuated, that the romance was to be chaunted or recited to a large and festive society ; and in some part or other of the piece, generally at the opening, there is a request of attention on the part of the performer ; and hence, the perpetual “ Lythe and listen lordings free,” which in those, or equivalent words, forms the introduction to so many romances. As, for example, in the old poem of <hi rend="italic">Guy and Colbrand,</hi>  the minstrel speaks of his own occupation :</p><p>When meat and drink is great plentye,</p><p>Then lords and ladyes still will be,</p><p>And sit and solace lythe ;</p><p>Then it is time for ιnee to speake,</p><p>Of kern knights and kempes greate,</p><p>Such carping for to kytbe.</p><p>Chaucer, also, in his rhyme of Sir Thopas, assigns to the minstrels of his hero’s household the same duty of reciting romances of spiritual or secular heroes, for the good knight’s pastime while arming himself for battle :</p><p>" Do cum,” he sayd. “ my minestrales,</p><p>And jestours for to tellen tales</p><p>Anon in min arming.</p><p>Of romaunces that ben reales,</p><p>Of popes and of cardinales,</p><p>And eke of love-longing.”</p><p>Not to multiply quotations, we will only add one of some importance, which must have escaped Ritson’s researches ; for his editorial integrity was such, as rendered him incapable of suppressing evidence on either side of the question. In the old romance or legend of <hi rend="italic">True Thomas and the Queen of Elfland,</hi>  Thomas the Rhymer, himself a minstrel, is gifted by the Queen of the Faery with the faculties of music and song. The answer of Thomas is not only conclusive as to the minstrel’s custom of recitation, but shows that it was esteemed the highest branch of his profession, and superior as such to mere instrumental music :</p><p>“ To harp and carp Thomas wheresoever ye gon,</p><p>Thomas take the these with the”-</p><p>“ Harping,” he said, “ ken I non,</p><p>For tong is chefe of Mynstralse.”@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>We, therefore, arrive at the legitimate conclusion, that although, under the general term minstrels, were comprehended many who probably entertained the public only with instrumental performances, with ribald tales, with jugglery, or farcical representations, yet one class amongst them, and that a numerous one, made poetical recitation their chief, if not their exclusive occupation. The memory of these men was, in the general case, the depository of the pieces which they recited ; and hence, although a number of their romances still survive, very many more have doubtless fallen into oblivion.</p><p>That the minstrels were also the authors of many of these poems, and that they altered and enlarged others, is a matter which can scarcely be doubted, when it is proved that they were the ordinary reciters of them. It was as natural tor a minstrel to become a poet or composer of romances, as for a player to be a dramatic author, or <hi rend="italic">a</hi>  musician a composer of music. Whatever individual among a class, whose trade it was to recite poetry, felt the least degree of poetical enthusiasm in a profession so peculiarly calculated to inspire it, must, from that very impulse, have become an original author, or translator at least ; thus giving novelty to his recitations, and acquiring additional profit and fame. Bishop Percy, therefore, states the case fairly in the following passage : “ It can hardly be expected that we should be able to produce regular and unbroken annals of the minstrel art and its professors, or have sufficient information, whether every minstrel or bard composed himself, or only repeated, the songs he chaunted. Some probably did the one and some the other ; and it would have been wonderful indeed, if men, whose peculiar profession it was, and who devoted their time and talents to entertain their hearers with poetical compositions, were peculiarly deprived of all poetical genius themselves, and had been under a physical incapacity of composing those common popular rhymes, which were the usual subjects of their recitation.”@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  While, however, we acquiesce in the proposition, that the minstrels composed many, perhaps the greater part of the metrical romances which they sung, it is evident they were frequently assisted in the task by others who, though not belonging to this profession, were prompted by leisure and inclination to enter upon the literary or poetical department as amateurs. These very often belonged to the clerical profession, amongst whom relaxation of discipline, abundance of spare time, and impatience of the routine of ceremonious duties, often led individuals into worse occupations than the listening to or composing metrical romances. It was in vain that both the poems and the minstrels who recited them were, by statute, debarred from entering the more rigid monasteries. Both found their way frequently to the refectory, and were made more welcome than brethren of their own profession ; as we may learn from a memorable<hi rend="italic">Gest,</hi>  in which two poor travelling priests, who had been received into a monastery with acclamation, under the mistaken idea of their being minstrels, are turned out in disgrace, when it is discovered that they were indeed capable of furnishing spiritual instruction, but understood none of the entertaining arts with which the hospitality of their convent might have been repaid by itinerant bards.</p><p>Nay, besides a truant disposition to a forbidden task, many of the grave authors may have alleged, in their own defence, that the connexion between history and romance was not in their day entirely dissolved. Some eminent men exercised themselves in both kinds of composition ; as, for example, Maître Wace, canon of Caen, in Normandy, who, besides the metrical chronicle of <hi rend="italic">Le Brut,</hi>  containing</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Jamieson’s<hi rend="italic">Popular ΒaUαds,</hi>  vol. ii. p. 27. </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi><hi rend="italic">  Essay on the Ancient Minstrels,</hi>  p. till.</p><p>Another authority of ancient date, the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi>  of Bertrand Guesclin, distinctly attributes the most renowned romances to the composition of the minstrels by whom they were sung. As the passage will be afterwards more fully quoted, we must here only say, that after enumerating Arthur, Launcelot, Godfrey, Roland, and other champions, he sums up his account of them as being the heroes</p><p>De quoi cils minestriers font les nobles romans.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>