<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">main,</hi>  2 vols. 4to, Brussels, 1728; died in 1622. Considerations on Roads, 8vo, Lond. 1734. Phillips’s Disserta-’ tion concerning the High Roads, 8vo, Lond. 1737. Homer’s Inquiry into the State of the Roads, 1767. Lambert on the best Ascent of Roads, Ac. Berl. 1776. Meister on the Shortest Roads to Different Places, N. Comm. Gott. 1777. Edgeworth on Roads and Carriages. Edgeworth on Railroads. Young’s Natural Philosophy, ii. p. 203, Instruments for Making and Cleaning Roads. Communications to the Board of Agriculture, i. 1797, p. 119, Beat-son; 162, Wright; 176, Joseph ; 183, Hall ; 199, Wilkes on Concave Roads ; Erskine on Iron Roads ; 205, Wright on Watering Roads near London ; 207, Ellis on Washing Roads ; ii. 1800, p. 353, Cumming on Broad Wheels ; 474, Wilkes on Railways; vi. 1808, p. 182, Whetley; p. 464, Amos on Wheels; vii. 1811, p. 10, Cumming on the Origin of Bent Axle-Trees ; p. 30, Booth on Wheel-Carriages. Paterson’s Practical Treatise. Quarterly Review, May 1820, xxiii. p. 96. Macadam’s Remarks on the Present System of Road-making, with Observations deduced from Practice and Experience, with a view to a Revision of the Existing Laws, and the Introduction of Improvement in the Method of Making, Repairing, and Preserving Roads, and Defending the Road Funds from Misapplication, 6th edit. Lond. 1822, 8vo.    (l. l.)</p><p>ROAN, in the manège. A <hi rend="italic">roan</hi>  horse is one of a bay, sorrel, or black colour, with gray or white spots interspersed very thick. When this party-cbloured coat is accompanied with a black head and black extremities, he is called <hi rend="italic">α roan horse with a blackamoor’s head ;</hi>  and if the same mixture is predominant upon a deep sorrel, he is called <hi rend="italic">claret-roan.</hi></p><p>ROANNE, an arrondissement of the department of the Loire, in France, which extends over 697 square miles. It comprehends ten cantons, divided into 108communes, with, in 1836, 124,871 inhabitants. Tbe capital is the city of the same name on the left bank of the Loire, which is so far navigable. It is a well-built city, with broad streets, good houses, and fine quays on the bank of the stream, and contains 9910 inhabitants, who are employed in making linen, cotton, and woollen goods, buttons, gilt ware, and jewellery. It is a place of great transit commerce, from being the chief depot between Paris and Lyons, where the goods produced in the southern provinces can be transmitted to the capital by means of rivers and canals.</p><p>ROANOAK, an island of North America, near the coast of North Carolina. Here the English first attempted to settle in 1585, but were obliged to leave it for want of provisions. Long. 75. 0. E. Lat. 35. 40. N.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roanoak, a river of North America, which rises in Virginia, runs through Carolina, and at length falls into the sea, where it forms a long narrow bay called Albemarle Sound.</hi></p><p>ROBERT’S Isi.es, two large islands in the Pacific Ocean, with several smaller islets in their neighbourhood, discovered by Lieutenant Hergest in 1792. Long. 219. 47. E. Lat. 7. 53. S.</p><p>ROBERTSON, William, one of the greatest historians of modern times, was the son of the Rev. William Robertson, minister of Borthwick, in the county of Edinburgh, and of Eleanor, the daughter of David Pitcairne, Esq. of Dreghorn. He was descended from the Robertsons of Gladney, a branch of the family which for many</p><p>fenerations has possessed the estate of Struan in Perthshire.</p><p>le was born at Borthwick in the year 1721, and received his early education at Dalkeith school, under Mr Leslie, a classical teacher of much reputation. In 1733 his father became one of the ministers of Old Greyfriar’s Church in Edinburgh, and towards the close of the same year, the son commenced his academical studies. He speedily distinguished himself as a young man of superior talents and attain</p><lb/><p>ments. He obtained his license in 1741, and in 1743 he was appointed minister of Gladsmuir in the county of Haddington. In 1758 he was translated to Lady Yester⅛ parish in Edinburgh, and other preferments speedily followed. In 1759 he was appointed chaplain of Stirling Castle; in 1761, one of his Majesty’s chaplains in ordinary; and in 1762 he was elected principal of the university. In 1764 the office of historiographer to the king for Scotland was revived in his favour, and was accompanied with a salary of two hundred pounds a year. The emoluments arising from this accumulation of offices far exceeded what any Presbyterian clergyman in Scotland had previously enjoyed. About the period of his translation to Edinburgh he was created D. D.</p><p>We find it difficult to ascertain at what period were first unfolded the great and singular talents which destined Dr Robertson to be one of the first writers that rescued this island from the reproach of not having any good historians. We are, however, assured, that before tbe publication of any of his literary performances, even from his first appearance in public life, his abilities had begun to attract the notice of observing men ; and to his more intimate friends he discovered marks of such high-minded ambition, as, seconded by those abilities, could not have failed to carry him to tile first honours of his profession, in whatever sphere he had been placed, and whatever opposition he might have had to encounter.</p><p>The first theatre tllat offered for the display of his talents was the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland. It is the annual meetings of this court that produce to view men who would otherwise remain in the deepest obscurity. There the humble pastor, whose lot has been cast in the remotest corner of the Highland wilds, feels himself, for a time, on a footing of equality with the first citizen in the kingdom : he can there dispute with him the prize of eloquence, the most flattering distinction to a liberal mind ; a distinction which is naturally sought after with the greater eagerness in that assembly, as the simple establishment of the Church of Scotland has rendered it the only pre-eminence to which the greatest part of its members can ever hope to attain.</p><p>From the moment Dr Robertson first appeared in this assembly, he became the object of universal attention and applause. His speeches were marked with the same manly and persuasive eloquence that distinguishes his historical compositions ; and it was observed by all, that while his young rivals in oratory contented themselves with opening a cause, or delivering a studied harangue, he showed equal ability to start objections or to reply ; and that even his most unpremeditated effusions were not unadorned with those harmonious and seemingly measured periods which have been so much admired in his works of labour and reflection. He soon came to be considered as the ablest supporter of the cause which he chose to espouse, and was now the unrivalled leader of one of the great parties which have long divided the church of which he was a member. When we reflect upon this circumstance, and consider how much mankind are the same in every society, we shall be the less surprised to find in the literary works of Dr Robertson an acquaintance with the human heart, and a knowledge of the world, which we in vain look for in many other historians. The man who has spent his life in the difficult task of conducting the deliberations of a popular assembly, in regulating the passions, the interests, the prejudices, of a numerous faction, has advantages over the mere man of letters, which no ability, no study, no second-hand information, can ever compensate.</p><p>The first work which extended his reputation beyond the walls of the General Assembly was a sermon preached at Edinburgh in 1758 before the Society for Propagating Christian Knowledge, the subject of which was, “ The State</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>