<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>It is therefore diminished in the proportion of AC to AE, that is, in the proportion of radius to the cosine of the elevation, or in the proportion of the secant of elevation to the radius.</p><p>It is evident, that this law of diminution of the strain is the same whether the strain arises from a load on any part of the rafter, or from the weight of the rafter itself, or from any load uniformly diffused over its length, provided only that these loads act in vertical lines.</p><p>We can now compare the strength of roofs which have different elevations. Supposing the width of the building to be given, and that the weight of a square yard of covering is also given. Then, because the load on the rafter will increase in the same proportion with its length, the load on the slant-side BA of the roof will be to the load of a similar covering on the half AF of the flat roof, of the same width, as AB to AF. But the transverse action of any load on AB, by which it tends to break it, is to that of the same load on AF as AF to AB. The transverse strain therefore is the same on both, the increase of real load on AB being compensated by the obliquity of its action. But the strengths of beams to resist equal strains, applied to similar points, or uniformly diflused over them, are inversely as their lengths, because the momentum or energy of the strain is proportional to the length. Therefore the power of AB to withstand the strain to which it is really exposed, is to the power of AF to resist its strain as AF to AB. If, therefore, a rafter AG of a certain scantling is just able to carry the roofing laid on it, a rafter AB of the same scantling, but more elevated, will be too weak in the proportion of AG to AB. Therefore steeper roofs require stouter rafters, in order that they may be equally able to carry a roofing of equal weight per square yard. To be equally strong, they must be made broader, or placed nearer to each other, in the proportion of their greater length, or they must be made deeper in the subduplicate proportion of their length. The following easy construction will enable the artist not familiar with computation to proportion the depth of the rafter to the slope of the roof.</p><p>Let the horizontal line o/(fig. 4) be the proper depth of a beam whose length is half the width of the building ; that is, such as would make it fit for carrying the intended tiling laid on a flat roof. Draw the vertical line∕δ, and the line <hi rend="italic">ab</hi>  having the elevation of the rafter ; make <hi rend="italic">ag</hi>  equal to a/j and describe the semicircle <hi rend="italic">bdg ;</hi>  draw <hi rend="italic">ad</hi>  perpendicular to <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi>  then <hi rend="italic">ad </hi>is the required depth. The demonstration is evident.</p><p>We have now treated in sufficient detail what relates to the chief strain on the component parts of a roof, namely, what tends to break them transversely ; and we have enlarged more on the subject than what the present occasion indispensably required, because the propositions which we have demonstrated are equally applicable to all framings of carpentry, and are even of greater moment in many cases, particularly in the construction of machines. These consist of levers in various forms, which are strained transversely ; and similar strains frequently occur in many of the supporting and connecting parts. We shall give, in another article, an account of the experiments which have been made by different naturalists, in order to ascertain the absolute strength of some of the materials which are most generally framed together in buildings and engines. The house-carpenter will derive from them absolute numbers, which he can apply to his particular purposes by means of the propositions which we have now established.</p><p>We proceed, in the next place, to consider the other</p><lb/><p>strains to which the parts of roofs are exposed, in consequence of the support which they mutually give each other, and the pressures, or <hi rend="italic">thrusts,</hi>  as they are called in the language of the house-carpenter, which they exert on each other, and on the walls or piers of the building.</p><p>Let a beam or piece of timber AB (fig. 5) be suspended by two lines AC, BD ; or</p><p>let it be supported by two props AE, BF, which are perfectly moveable round their remote extremities E, F, or let it rest on the two polishçd planes K AH,</p><p>LBM. Moreover, let G be the centre of gravity of the beam, and let GN be a line through the centre of gravity perpendicular to the horizon. The beam will not be in equi-librio unless the vertical line GN either passes through P, the point in which the directions of the two lines AC, BD, or the directions of the two props EA, FB, or the perpendiculars to the two planes KAH, LBM intersect each other, or is parallel to these directions. For the supports given by the lines or props are unquestionably exerted in the direction of their lengths, and it is well known in mechanics that the supports given by planes are exerted in a direction perpendicular to those planes in the points of contact; and we know that the weight of the beam acts in the same manner as if it were all accumulated in its centre of gravity G, and that it acts in the direction GN perpendicular to the horizon. Moreover, when a body is in equilibrio between three forces, they are acting in one plane, and their directions are either parallel or they pass through one point.</p><p>The support given to the beam is therefore the same as if it were suspended by two lines which are attached to the single point P. We may also infer, that the points of suspension C, D, the points of support E, F, the points of contact A, B, and the centre of gravity G, are all in one vertical plane.</p><p>When this position of the beam is disturbed by any external force, there must either be a motion of the points A and B round the centres of suspension C and D, or of the props round these points of support E and F, or a sliding of the ends of the beam along the polished planes KAH and LBM ; and in consequence of these motions the centre ol gravity G will go out of its place, and the vertical line GN will no longer pass through the point where the directions of the supports intersect each other. If the centre of gravity rises by this motion, the body will have a tendency to recover its former position, and it will require force to keep it away from it. In this case the equilibrium may be said to be <hi rend="italic">stable,</hi>  or the body to have <hi rend="italic">stability.</hi>  But if the centre of gravity descends when the body is moved from tile position of equilibrium, it will tend to move still farther; and so far will it be from recovering its former position, that it will now fall. This equilibrium may be called a <hi rend="italic">tottering equilibrium.</hi>  These accidents depend on the situations of the points A, B, C, D, E, F ; and they may be determined by considering the subject geometrically. It does not much interest us at present ; it is rarely that tile equilibrium of suspension is tottering, or that of props is stable. It is evident, that if the beam were suspended by lines from the point P, it would have stability, for it would swing like a pendulum round P, and therefore would always tend towards the position of equilibrium. The intersection of the lines of support would still be at P, and the vertical line</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>