<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ally throw into the background the wilder passions and more stormy impulses of our nature, until they acquire an importance which not only justifies, but renders their introduction into any fictitious narrative which represents the peculiarities of the time, necessary ; and for this purpose, the calm and even march of the novel, and the detailed development both of sentiment and incident which it allows, is found to be admirably adapted. It is in the works of our novelists, therefore, rather than our dramatists, and in those passages in our essayists of Queen Anne’s time, in which they treat of past fashions, manners, whims, and humours, that we must look for the changes which society has undergone, and from which we must try to realize to ourselves the features which it exhibited at any particular period.</p><p>The novel, then, affords a wider field for accurate and complete delineation of plissions and feelings than the drama, and certainly one more in harmony with the dispositions of a modern public. In powerful effects no doubt it cannot compete with the stage. The whole range of novel or romance contains nothing, for instance, which in its tremendous impression, can be compared with the explosion of passion in the third act of Othello ; but, on the other hand, it has greatly the advantage in the impression of verisimilitude which it leaves behind, produced by the accumulation of many particulars and minute traits of character ; in pleasing interchanges of action and repose ; in the delineation of emotions, which the drama, speaking only to the eye and the ear, cannot lay before us ; in the descriptions of external scenery, which, in the hand of a writer of genius, are far more effective, when presented in words to the imagination, than when counterfeited to the eye upon the stage, even by all the united resources of the scene-painter and the mechanist ; and which, from the strong connection which exists between the state of our feelings and external influences, are found in the hands of a judicious novelist, to afford powerful materials for deepening the pervading tone of sentiment which he aims to produce ; just as in painting relief and effect are obtained by the tone and character of the background against which the figures are opposed. Another advantage obtained by the substitution of narrative fiction for the drama, was, that a much wider licence was obtained in the conduct of the plot. A good plot is no doubt as essential to the novel as the drama ; but the kind of plot which may be used with effect in each, and the manner in which the incidents are to be conducted, differ materially. A play in which every scene does not grow out of the preceding, and lead directly into the next, with a visible progress of plot, is in that respect faulty. On the contrary, in the novel and romance, as in real life, much is admissible which is episodical, which does not directly help forward nor produce the catastrophe, but merely tends to bring out some point of character in the personages represented, or to increase the air of verisimilitude in the main story, by the appearance of minute and literal correctness in the details. In the novel or romance, too, it has been generally remarked that the catastrophe maybe made to turn upon accident, but that this is inadmissible in the drama.@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi>Thus the catastrophe in the<hi rend="italic">Bride of Lammermoor,</hi>  where Ravenswood is swallowed up by a quicksand, is singularly grand in romance, but would be inadmissible in a drama. And on the same principle, Schiller has, in his <hi rend="italic">Fiesco, </hi>thought himself compelled to deviate from the actual truth of history, and to ascribe the Count’s death, not to an accidental stumble from a plank, but to the hand of the republican Verrina. In a novel, the real catastrophe would have been far more impressive in its moral effect than the imaginary one ; but Schiller held, and we think rightly, that in the drama nothing must be <hi rend="italic">accident,</hi>  but every thing <hi rend="italic">result.</hi></p><p>Although, as compared with the romance, tbe term novel</p><lb/><p>may be said to indicate a class of fictions dealing more witll calm feelings, and with manners and humours, than with strong passions, and deriving its interest more from the probability than the marvellous nature of its incidents, this definition is not to be taken too literally ; for there are many works which we might call novels, in as much as the scene is laid in modern times, and the general course of the incidents is that of every-day life, but in which the even tenor of the story is occasionally broken by scenes of powerful passion, or incidents of a mysterious and terrible character, elevating the composition for the time into the sphere of the romantic ; so that perhaps the word tale, as a middle term between the others, would most appropriately describe them. It has been doubted whether, although such a union of the common-place with tlle extraordinary, be not unfre-quently met with in the course of real life, a more cautious separation of these elements would not, on the whole, be most favourable to the effect of a narrative as a work of art ; and whether the attempt to blend them, does not produce in fiction, something of that illegitimate effect which is the result of the melo-drama on the stage. It is certain, however, that the tendency for some time past, and particularly since the school of fiction introduced by Sir Walter Scott, has been towards a mixture of the novel and romance in the same composition, so that broad comedy is often found alternating with the pathetic, the gaiety of a ball-room with midnight murders upon lonely heaths, and the disclosure of some piece of fashionable scandal standing side by side with the discovery of some secret and fearful crime. In the hands of our great masters of fiction, we admit the fine effect which these occasionally produce. Judiciously arranged, these opposites are the light and shadow of the composition ; but even in our greatest modern novelist, we could point out not a few instances in which this sort of contrast is carried too far ; while in many of his imitators, it is so regularly and mechanically introduced, that, as in the case of Mr. Puff’s stage arrangements, we can always predict that the discharge of cannon wilt be followed by soft music.</p><p>When the declining popularity of tlle pastoral and heroic romance of the seventeenth century, suggested the necessity of opening a new vein in fiction, it is probable that the stilted, unnatural, and exaggerated character of those effete compositions led the public taste, by a natural recoil of feeling, into the opposite extreme, viz. the selection of topics and characters from common, and even from vulgar life, and a literal adherence to nature, even at the risk of the sacrifice of art. For we pass over the tiresome and licentious love stories of Mrs. Aphra Behn, with the just remark of Sir Richard Steele, that the lady appears to have “ understood the practical part of love better than the speculative,” as well as those of her imitator, Mrs. Heywood, in which the struggle between the high sentimental character of the heroic romance, and the growing taste for a style of portraiture more true to the life, is very obvious, and come at once to the writer by whom the inspiration of reality was carried to its greatest perfection.</p><p>Defoe, (1661—1731) without high imagination, with no power of raising the passions, with little pathos and no eloquence, had yet that peculiar genius which enabled him to excel within the peculiar department which he chose for himself ; that of counterfeiting homely truth by fiction, and forging, as it were, the handw<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>ritιng of nature herself, with a dexterity which defied detection. Whether Defoe was led to the selection of his peculiar themes, by a real sympathy with roguery, (and his conduct in regard to the well-known imposture of Mrs. Veal’s Ghost would justify us in believing him to be like Gil Blas, “ tant soi peu fripon ;”) or by the influence of the Spanish romances of roguery, such as Lazaro de Tormes, Marcos de Obregon,</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> See some vuluable papers on Art in Fiction, ascribed, we believe with justice, to Sir L. Bulwer.<hi rend="italic">Monthly Chronicle,</hi>  Kos. i and ii.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>