<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the circumferences of the two circles whose radii are respectively <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">r + dr,</hi>  and two straight lines drawn from the centre to the extremities of a very small arc at P ; that is to say, we have <hi rend="italic">dm — dzdr.</hi>  But the distance of this element from the axis is y ; therefore the moment of inertia is <hi rend="italic">ffy<hi rend="sup">2</hi>dzdr.</hi>  Now, by the nature of the circle, <hi rend="italic">dz : dx : : r : y, </hi>whence <hi rend="italic">ydz — τdx,</hi>  and the double integral becomes <hi rend="italic">fydx ×frdr.</hi>  Now, on the supposition that <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  is constant, the integral <hi rend="italic">fydx</hi>  = σr<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  = area of the circle whose radius is r ; therefore the integration in respect of<hi rend="italic">dx</hi>  gives <hi rend="italic">stfr<hi rend="sup">3</hi>dr ; </hi>and on integrating this from <hi rend="italic">r =</hi>  0 to <hi rend="italic">r = a,</hi>  we get ulti-timately ¼ wα<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  for the moment of the circle whose radius is<hi rend="italic">a.    '</hi></p><p>Since in this case the mass M = &lt;rα<hi rend="sup">2</hi> = the area, we have ¼&lt;rα<hi rend="sup">4</hi> = ¼Mα<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, which is another expression for the moment of inertia of a circle in respect of one of its diameters.</p><p>IV.    To find the moment of inertia of a circle in respect of an axis perpendicular to its plane, and passing through its centre.</p><p>Supposing, as in the last proposition, the surface to be composed of elementary rings, we have <hi rend="italic">dm = dzdr,</hi>  whence <hi rend="italic">fridm = fridr × fdz</hi>  = 2&lt;r <hi rend="italic">fi<hi rend="sup">3</hi>dr</hi>  (since <hi rend="italic">fdz</hi>  = 2wr), the integral of which, from <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  = 0 to <hi rend="italic">r = a,</hi>  gives <hi rend="italic">fridrn</hi>  = ½wα<hi rend="sup">4 </hi>= ½Ma<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.</p><p>V.    To find the moment of inertia of a solid body generated by the revolution of a curve line in respect of the axis of rotation.</p><p>Let AB (fig. 5) be a section perpendicular to the axis of rotation OX, and meeting it in C, and make OC = <hi rend="italic">x.</hi>  Suppose the solid to be divided into thin slices by planes parallel to AB, and let <hi rend="italic">ab</hi>  be the section next to AB, so that Cc = <hi rend="italic">dx.</hi>  Let P be a point in the plane AB, and make CP = <hi rend="italic">r,</hi></p><p>Cp = r+<hi rend="italic">dr.</hi>  The length of the circumference described by P in one revolution is 2&lt;rr, therefore the mass of the ring comprised between AB and <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi>  and traced by the revolution of the points P andp, is <hi rend="italic">2vrdrdx ; </hi>and its distance from the axis is <hi rend="italic">r,</hi>  therefore the moment of inertia of the ring is 2wr<hi rend="sup">3</hi>drd⅛. Integrating this in respect of<hi rend="italic">r</hi>  from <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  = 0 to <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  = CA = <hi rend="italic">y,</hi>  we get <hi rend="italic">tyrfldx for</hi>  the moment of the slice comprised between the two sections of the solid, whose distances from O are <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">xJ<hi rend="sub">r</hi>dx.</hi>  Hence the moment of inertia of all the slices, or of the solid body, is <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">*fy*dx∙</hi></p><p>Applying this formula to a sphere whose radius = <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  we get from the equation <hi rend="italic">y<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  =z 2ax — χ<hi rend="sup">i</hi>, y' — 4a<hi rend="sup">1</hi>x<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  — 4ax<hi rend="sup">3 </hi></hi>+ ar<hi rend="sup">4</hi>, on substituting which, and integrating, we have <hi rend="italic">⅛srfy<hi rend="sup">i</hi>dx = gsra<hi rend="sup">2</hi>x<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  — ½ rnx<hi rend="sup">i</hi></hi>  + ⅛ra<hi rend="sup">5</hi>, which from<hi rend="italic">x</hi>  = 0 <hi rend="italic">to x = a</hi>  gives <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi rend="italic">vfy<hi rend="sup">i</hi>dx</hi>  = -⅛wα<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  for the hemisphere, and consequently the moment of inertia of the whole sphere = ⅛wα<hi rend="sup">5</hi>  = IM ∙ o<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, since M =∣wa<hi rend="sup">3</hi>.</p><p>The moment of inertia of a spheroid revolving about its shorter axis is¼M(o<hi rend="sup">2</hi>+A<hi rend="sup">2</hi>). See the calculation of<hi rend="italic">fa"dm </hi>and <hi rend="italic">ffldm</hi>  in this case in the article Precession, vol. xviii. p. 508.</p><p>In all the preceding examples, the density of the body has been supposed uniform, and =1. For bodies of different densities the formulæ must be multiplied in each case by the density. Thus, in the last example, the moment of inertia of a sphere whose radius = <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  and density = (, the moment of inertia in respect of one of the diameters is ⅛ <hi rend="italic">grξα<hi rend="sup">s</hi>.</hi></p><p>19. The examples which have now been given wili suffice to illustrate the method of computing the moments of inertia of bodies of any form in respect of particular axes ; and they render it obvious that the computation will in general be greatly facilitated when the mass is symmetrically disposed about the axis for which the inertia is to be computed. It is likewise evident that the amount of rotatory inertia depends on the position of the axis of rotation. Hence, for every point of a mass there must exist at least one axis in respect of which the inertia is less, or greater, than in respect of any other axis passing through that point. The axes for which the moments of inertia are the greatest or least possible are called <hi rend="italic">principal axes ;</hi>  and they possess some very remarkable properties of great importance in the theory of rotation. We now proceed to investigate the position and properties of the principal axes.</p><p>20.    The moments of inertia of a mass M being given in respect of three rectangular axes OX, OY, OZ (fig. 6) passing through O, to find the moment in respect of another axis OG given in position, and also passing through the origin O.</p><p>Let P be the position of a particle <hi rend="italic">dm;</hi>  through P draw PQ parallel to the axis OZ, meeting the plane XOY in Q, and draw QR parallel to OY, meeting OX in R; then OR = <hi rend="italic">x,</hi>  RQ = <hi rend="italic">y,</hi></p><p>QP = <hi rend="italic">z.</hi>  Also suppose the plane which passes through OG, and is perpendicular to XOY, to meet the plane XOY in OF, and let tlle angle XOF = <hi rend="italic">φ,</hi>  and the angle FOG = ∙ψ. The axis OG is entirely determined by these two angles, and consequently, when OG is given in position, <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  and ∙ψ are also given. In order to compute the moment of inertia in respect of the axis OG, it is convenient to refer the different points of the mass, as P, to a new system of rectangular axes, of which one is OG. To effect this, in the first place let OY be drawn perpendicular to OF in the plane XOY, and let P be referred to the axes OF, OY', OZ, and draw QR' perpendicular to OF. We have then OR' = a/, R'Q = <hi rend="italic">f,</hi>  QP = z, and the new co-ordinates expressed in terms of the former, and the angles <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  and ∙ψ are</p><p><hi rend="italic">x<hi rend="sup">,</hi> = x</hi>  cos. <hi rend="italic">φ + y</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">φ, y' = y</hi>  cos. p — <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">φ, z<hi rend="sup">,</hi></hi>  = z.</p><p>In the second place, we may pass in like manner from these to a third system of co-ordinates <hi rend="italic">x!', ↑f, z!',</hi>  of which <hi rend="italic">x"</hi>  is in the line OG, y" remains parallel to OY', and z" is perpendicular to OG in the plane FOG. We have, then, similarly,</p><p>∙r" = ar<hi rend="sup">,</hi>cos. ∙ψ + z<hi rend="sup">,</hi>sin. ∙ψ, y" = y', z"= √ cos. ∙ψ — a: sin. ∙ψ.</p><p>Substituting in these last equations the values of af, y', and z<hi rend="sup">,</hi>, given by the three former, we have</p><p><hi rend="italic">f' =χ</hi>  cos. p cos. ∙ψ + <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">&lt;ρ</hi>  cos. -ψ + <hi rend="italic">z</hi>  sin. -ψ, y" = y cos. <hi rend="italic">&lt;ρ — x</hi>  sin. <hi rend="italic">φ,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">z"</hi>  = 2 cos. ∙ψ — <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  cos. p sin. ∙ψ — y sin. p sin. -ψ.</p><p>If we now assume the distance of P from the axis OG to be <hi rend="italic">τ,</hi>  we shall have ri = y"<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + z*<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  ; whence, on forming from the two last equations the expression for<hi rend="italic">fridm </hi>=∕(y"<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  + z"<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)<hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  and, for the sake of abridging, putting</p><p><hi rend="sub">ι</hi>∕⅛<hi rend="sup">a</hi>&lt;∕m =<hi rend="italic">A,fιfldm</hi>  = B,yi<hi rend="sup">s</hi>rfra = C,<hi rend="italic">fχydm- D,fxzdrn = Ε,,fyzdrn =</hi>  F,</p><p>the expression for the moment of inertia in respect of the axis OG becomes</p><p><hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = A (sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  p + cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  p sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  -ψ)</p><p>+ B (cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> p + sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> p sin.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> ∙ψ) + C cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> ∙ψ — 2D cos. p sin. p cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi>∙ψ—2 E cos. p cos. -ψ sin. -ψ</p><p>— 2 F sin. p cos. -ψ sin. ∙ψ.</p><p>This expression for the moment of inertia in respect of the axis OG is given by Euler ( <hi rend="italic">Theoria Motus Corporum Solidorum,</hi>  p. 169).</p><p>21.    The values of the angles p and ∙ψ, which give the position of the axis for which the moment<hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  is a maximum or minimum, may be deduced from the above equation in the usual manner, that is to say, by differentiating successively for each of the variables, and making tlle differential co-efficient = 0. The differentiation in respect of p (supposing ∙ψ constant) gives the equation</p><p>, _ — (A — B) sin. pcos. p + D (cos.<hi rend="sup">2</hi> p — sin.<hi rend="sup">s</hi> p), tan. +---Ësin. p _ F cos. p</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>