<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ter Silvia a vestal virgin, by which she became bound to perpetual celibacy. According to the legend, this scheme proved abortive ; for Silvia became pregnant by the god Mars, and was delivered of twin sons. Amulius ordered the infants to be thrown into the river, and their mother to be buried alive ; the doom of a vestal virgin who should violate her vow of chastity. The river happened at that time to have overflowed its banks, so that the two infants were not carried into the middle of the stream, but drifted along the margin, till the basket which contained them became entangled in the roots of a wild vine, at the foot of the Palatine hill. At this time a she-wolf coming down to the river to drink, suckled the infants, and carried them to her den among the thickets hard by. Here they were found by Faustulus, the king’s herdsman, who took them home to his wife Laurentia, by whom they were carefully nursed, and named Romulus and Remus.</p><p>The two youths grew up, employed in the labours, the sports, and the perils of the pastoral occupation of their foster-father. But, like the two sons of Cymbeline, their royal blood could not be quite concealed. Their superior mein, courage, and abilities, soon acquired for them a decided superiority over their young compeers,and they became leaders of the youthful herdsman in their contests with robbers, or with rivals. Having quarrelled with the herdsmen of Numitor, whose flocks were accustomed to graze on the neighbouring hill Aventinus, Remus fell into an ambush, and w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>as dragged before Numitor to be punished. While Numitor, struck with the noble bearing of the youth, and influenced by the secret stirrings of nature within him, was hesitating what punishment to inflict, Romulus, accompanied by Faustulus, hastened to the rescue of Remus. On their arrival at Alba, the secret of their origin w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>as discovered, and a plan was speedily organized for the expulsion of Amulius, and the restoration of their grandfather Numitor to his throne. This was soon accomplished ; but the twin brothers felt little disposition to remain in a subordinate position in Alba, after the enjoyment of the rude liberty and power to which they had been accustomed among their native hills. They therefore requested from their grandfather permission to build a city on the banks of the Tiber, where their lives had been so miraculously preserved. Scarcely had this permission been granted when a contest .arose between the two brothers respecting the site, the name, and the sovereignty of the city which they were about to found. Romulus wished it to be built on the Palatine hill, and to be called by his name ; Remus preferred the Aventine, and his own name. To terminate their dispute amicably, they agreed to refer it to the decision of the gods by augury. Romulus took his station on the Palatine hill, Remus on the Aventine. At sun-rise Remus saw six vul∙ tures, and immediately afterwards Romulus saw twelve. The superiority was adjudged to Romulus, because he had seen the greater number, against which decision Remus remonstrated indignantly,on the ground that he had first received an omen.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>Romulus then proceeded to mark out the boundaries for the wall of the intended city. This was done by a plough with a brazen plough-share, drawn by a bull and a heifer, and so directed that the furrow should fall inward. The plough was lifted and carried over the spaces intended to be left for the gates ; and in this manner a square space was marked oβt, including the Palatine hill, and a small portion of the land at its base, termed <hi rend="italic">Roma quadrata.</hi>  This took place on the 21st of April, on the day of the festival of Pales, the goddess of shepherds. While the wall was beginning to rise above the surface, Remus, whose mind was still rankling with his discomfiture, leaped over it scornfully, saying, “ Shall such a wall as that keep your city!” Immediately Romulus, or, as others say, Celer, who had charge of erecting that part of the wall, struck him dead to the ground with the implement in his hand, exclaiming, “ So perish whosoever shall hereafter overleap these walls.” By this event Romulus was left the sole sovereign of the city ; yet he felt deep remorse at his brother’s fate, buried him honourably, and when he sat to administer justice, placed an empty throne by his side, with a sceptre and crown, as if acknowledging the right of his brother to the possession of equal power.</p><p>To augment as speedily as possible the number of his subjects, Romulus set apart in his new city a place of refuge, to which any man might flee, and be protected from bis pursuers. By this device the population increased rapidly in males ; but there was a great deficiency of females ; for the adjoining states, regarding the followers of Romulus as little better than a horde of brigands, refused to sanction intermarriages. But the schemes of Romulus were not to be so frustrated. In honour of the god Consus, he proclaimed games, to which he invited the neighbouring states. Great numbers came, accompanied by their families; and at an appointed signal, the Roman youth, rushing suddenly into the midst of the spectators, snatched up the unmarried women in their arms, and bore them off hy force. This outrage was immediately resented, and Romulus found himself involved in a war with all the surrounding states. Fortunately for Rome, though these states had sustained a common injury, they did not unite their forces in the common cause. They fought singly, and were each in turn defeated ; Cænina, Antemnæ, and Crustumerium, fell successively before the Roman arms. Romulus slew with his own hand, Aeron, king of Cænina, and bore off his spoils, dedicating them as <hi rend="italic">spoila opima,</hi>  to Jupiter Feretrius. The third part of the lands of the conquered towns was seized by the conquerors ; and such of the people of these towns as were willing to remove to Rome, were received as free citizens.</p><p>In the mean time, the Sabines, to avenge the insult which they had sustained, had collected together their forces under tile command of Titus Tatius, king of the Quirites, or people of the Sabine town of Cures. The Romans were unable to meet so strong an army in the field, and withdrew within their walls. They had previously placed their flocks in what they thought a place of safety, on the Capitoline hill, which, strong as it was by nature, they had still further secured by additional fortifications. Tarpeia, the daughter of the commander of that fortress, having fallen into the hands of the Sabines, agreed to betray the access to the hill, for the ornaments they wore upon their arms. At their approach she opened the gate, and as they entered, they crushed her to death beneath their shields. From her the clift of the Capitoline hill was called the Tarpeian rock. The attempt of the Romans to regain this place of strength brought on a general engagement. The combat was long and doubtful. At one time the Romans were almost driven into the city, which the Sabines were on the point of entering along with them, when fresh courage was infused into the fugitives, in consequence of Romulus vowing a temple to Jupiter Stator, and by a stream of water which rushed out of the temple of Janus, and swept away the Sabines from the gate. The bloody struggle was renewed during several successive days, with various fortune and great mutual</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> According to the interpretation of the Etruscan augurs, the twelve vultures seen by Romulus portended that the duration of the city would extend to twelve centuries ; and it may strike even an incredulous reader us remarkable, that the actual duration of Rome as a freι and imperial city coincided very nearly with the time assigned by this augury. It ended in the 1229th year of thecity, by the dethronemen<hi rend="sup">, </hi>of the last emperor Romulus Augustulus.</p><p>See Niebuhr, vol. i. p. 224. See also Gibbon, vol. vi. p. 136, Milmau<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ι edition.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>