<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Romanum, and said to have been the place where tlle comitia curiata were held from the time of Romulus.</p><p>At this time the body, afterwards known by the name of the plebs, or plebeians, had no existence, the entire population being composed of patrician houses, with their members and dependents, in other words, of patrons and clients, the patrons alone being full citizens, and known as the people. In a very short time a population of a different character began to appear, composed of strangers who came to settle in the country, and the inhabitants of conquered states brought forcibly to Rome, and obliged to unite to a certain extent with their conquerors. This population had, of course, no connexion with the houses, but only with the state politically. They could not become <hi rend="italic">members</hi>  of the houses ; they were not <hi rend="italic">dependents</hi>  on them ; and thus they came to form a body of an entirely new character, springing up in the midst of the privileged citizens. They were not permitted to intermarry with the houses, who were very tenacious of purity of blood ; and thus they belonged to no house, no curia, and no tribe, consequently they had no share in the public government nor in the public property. Their own property in their native country might have been diminished, or altogether lost in that war by which they had been subdued, in consequence of the law by which a third part of a conquered nation’s lands was seized by the conquerors; yet what the state might subsequently seize in war, even by their aid, did not become theirs, because they formed no integral part of the state as such, being <hi rend="italic">in</hi>  the state, but not q∕<hi rend="sup">,</hi>it∙ Such an inferior population, of a character, and occupying a position so anomalous, not slaves, yet not citizens, was the element from which arose the original plebs or commons of Rome.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>The only events recorded in the legend of Tullus Hostilius, to which any degree of credit can be attached, are those which refer to the Alban war and its consequences. It seems to be a fact, that at some indefinitely early period in the history of Rome, the honour of being head of the great confederacy of the thirty towns of Latium, which had Belonged to Alba, was transferred to the former city. This has been ascribed to the reign of Tullus ; and as no period to which it may with greater certainty be referred, can be pointed out, it may be regarded as an historical truth, accounted for in no unnatural manner by a national legend. The combat of the Horatii and the Curiatii appears to be chiefly a poetical episode, and one of a very high and spirit-stirring character, but may have had some foundation in fact. The death of Tullus is also legendary and imaginative. It seems to have been partly at least an Alban lay, from its indications of divine wrath falling upon Tullus on account of the desolate temples and deserted gods of tlle Alban mount. But the most important part of the narrative is that which records the reception into the state of the third tribe, the Luceres. In the legend, this is said to have taken place in consequence of the union of the Albans with the Roman people. There may be a considerable portion of truth in this statement, and it is perfectly consistent with the known facts of the case, as far as they bear upon the subject. The Luceres were held to be to a certain degree inferior to the other tribes, as was not unlikely to be the case with the descendants of a conquered people. All the patrician houses that traced their genealogy to the Albans belonged to the Luceres, such as the Julii, Quinctii, Servilii, Cælii, and several others of the most distinguished Roman houses. The explanation of the name</p><p>Luceres cannot be clearly given. Some derive it from the Lucumo who is said to have settled on the Cælian hill, and to have given it his name. If he founded a small city for his followers, and give it his official name, as he gave the hill his personal, the name of the town might be Lucerum; and when the Albans were located on that hill, and in that town, and raised to the condition of a tribe, they might be called Luceres from their new abode, and in order to sink the remembrance of Alba.</p><p>The most important event recorded in the period assigned to the reign of Ancus was the removal of roe conquered Latins to Rome, and the apportioning to them of a settled residence on the Aventine hill.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> This may be regarded as the origin of the Roman plebs, or commons, as distinguished from the patrician body, who were the true and original Populus Romanus. It cannot be too distinctly stated, nor too clearly and strongly remembered, that among the early Romans, the populus and the plebs were wholly and in every respect different. The populus was originally the whole body of the early inhabitants of Rome, both those of Romulian and those of Sabine origin. This body, consisting of senators or patres, curiæ, and houses, with tbeir members and dependants, was completely aristocratic in its aspect, and tolerated no degrading intermixtures. The plebs were originally the conquered Latins, who were in a measure incorporated into the mass of the nation, by being removed to the Roman territories, placed on the Aventine hill, and permitted to farm the land of the state, which latter arrangement is said to have been made by Ancus. They retained their personal freedom, but could neither become members of houses, nor in general would submit to be dependants. They grew up, therefore, along with the populus, a free, but unprivileged, and too often an oppressed population ; and though both despised, feared, and hated by the exclusive patrician populus, rapidly growing what they ultimately became, the real strength of Rome. Had it not been for the patriarchal principle pervading Rome, which caused the ties of kindred to be the only legitimate method of obtaining the full privileges of a citizen, these near residents might have been admitted at once, and all the subsequent fierce domestic broils might not have taken place ; but without these contests tlle nation might never have been knit into such compact strength, nor have been led to the formation of such a body of wise and well-digested laws.</p><p>In the constitution of the Roman state, Tarquinius made at least one alteration concerning the true nature of which, authors are by no means agreed. Some say that he added an hundred members to the ancient senate, which till then had amounted to no more than two hundred. These new senators were called fathers of the lesser houses, <hi rend="italic">(patres minorum gentium;)</hi>  and the old senators fathers of tbe greater houses, <hi rend="italic">(patres mηjοrurn gentium.)</hi>  If this account were entitled to implicit credit, we should regard it as referring to the admission of the Luceres into tbe full enjoyment of the rights and honours of citizenship. Yet this seems to have taken place during the reign of Hostilius, when he brought the conquered Albans to Rome. Perhaps a portion of each statement may be true. The Albans and Latins may have been settled on the Cælian hill, and formed into a tribe by Tullus ; but not raised to the senate till the accession of Tarquinius, who may have thought such a step necessary in order to secure the support of a large body of the state, his claims to the throne being so very question-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> It may be added, though here we are anticipating the regular course of events, that the great proportion of the Roman commons were conquered Latins. Besides receiving grants of a portion of their former lands, to be held by them as tenants at the will of the state, they had also the Aventine hill assigned to such of them as removed to Rome. The Aventine was not included within the walls of the original city, so that these half-citizens became the suburban neighbours of Rome rather than its inhabitants, enjoying its protection, sharing heavily in its burdens, exposed to a full proportion of all its dangers, but excluded from all its political rights and privileges. From such a condition no wonder that future contentions arose.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  See Niebuhr, vol. i p. 355.</p></body></text></TEI>