<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cylindrical pillar, which may be taken out of its mould. Now suppose this pillar standing upright, and loaded above. The supports arising from the cement act obliquely, and the load tends either to force them asunder laterally, or to make them slide on each other : either of these things happening, the whole is crushed to pieces. The resistance of fibrous materials to such a strain is a little more intricate, but may be explained in a way very similar.</p><p>A piece of matter of any kind may also be destroyed by wrenching or twisting it. We can easily form a notion of its resistance to this kind of strain by considering what would happen to the cylinder of small shot if treated in this way.</p><p>And, lastly, a beam, or a bar of metal, or piece of stone or other matter, may be broken transversely. This will happen to a rafter or joist supported at the ends when overloaded, or to a beam having one end stuck fast in a wall and a load laid on its projecting part. This is the strain to which materials are most commonly exposed in roofs ; and, unfortunately, it is the strain which they are the least able to bear ; or rather it is the manner of application which causes an external force to excite the greatest possible immediate strain on the particles. It is against this that tile carpenter must chiefly guard, avoiding it when in his power, and in every case diminishing it as much as possible. It is necessary to give the reader a clear notion of the great weakness of materials in relation to this transverse strain. But we shall do nothing more, referring him to the articles Strain, and Stress, and Strength.</p><p>Let ABCD (fig. 1) represent the side of a bcam projecting horizontally from a wall in which it is firmly fixed, and let it be loaded with a weight W appended to its extremity. This tends to break it j and the least reflection will convince any person, that if the beam is equally strong throughout, it will break in the line CD, even with the surface of the wall. It will open at D, while C will serve as a sort of joint, round which it will turn. The cross section through the line CD is for this reason called the <hi rend="italic">section offracture ;</hi>  and the horizontal line drawn through C on its under surface is called the <hi rend="italic">axis t&gt;f fracture.</hi>  The fracture is made by tearing asunder the fibres, such as DE or FG. Let us suppose a real joint at C, and that the beam is really sawed through along CD, and that in place of its natural fibres, threads are substituted all over the section of fracture. The weight now tends to break these threads, and it is our business to find the force necessary for this purpose.</p><p>It is evident that DCA may be considered as a bended lever, of which C is the fulcrum. If <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  be the force which will just balance the cohesion of a thread when hung on it so that the smallest addition will break it, we may find the weight which will be sufficient for this purpose when hung on at A, by saying, AC : CD <hi rend="italic">—f: φ,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  will be the weight which will just break tlιe thread, by hanging <hi rend="italic">φ</hi>  by CD</p><p>the point A. This gives us <hi rend="italic">φ = f × -~-τ∙</hi>  If the weight</p><p>LA</p><p>be hung on at <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  the force just sufficient for breaking the CD</p><p>same thread will be =∕× In like manner, the force <hi rend="italic">φ, </hi>which must be hung on at A in order to break an equally</p><p>CF</p><p>strong or an equally resisting fibre at F, must be <hi rend="italic">=f ×</hi></p><p>And so on of all the rest.</p><p>If we suppose all the fibres to exert equal resistances at the instant of fracture, we know, from the simplest elements of mechanics, that the resistance of all the particles in the line CD, each acting equally in its own place, is the same as if all the individual resistances were united in the middle point <hi rend="italic">g.</hi>  Now this total resistance is the resistance or strength <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  of each particle, multiplied by the number of particles. This number may be expressed by the line CD, because we have no reason to suppose that they are at unequal distances. Therefore, in comparing different sections together, the number of particles in each are as the sections themselves. Therefore DC may represent the number of particles in the line DC. Let us call this line the depth of the beam, and express it by the symbol <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  And since we are at present treating of roofs whose rafters and other parts are commonly of uniform breadth, let us call AH or BI the breadth of the beam, and express it by Z&gt;, and let CA be called its length Z. We may now express the strength of the whole line CD by <hi rend="italic">f × d,</hi>  and we may suppose it all concentrated in the middle point <hi rend="italic">g.</hi>  Its mechanical energy, therefore, by which it resists the energy of the weight <hi rend="italic">w, </hi>applied at the distance Z, is<hi rend="italic">f×</hi>  CD × C <hi rend="italic">g,</hi>  whilst the momentum of <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  is <hi rend="italic">wχ</hi>  CA. We must therefore have <hi rend="italic">f</hi>  X CD × <hi rend="italic">Cg = w×</hi>  C A, or ∕&lt;Z × ½&lt;Z = teZ, and<hi rend="italic">fd∙.w = l</hi>  : ½&lt;Z, or <hi rend="italic">fd∙.w </hi>= 2 Z : &lt;Z. That is, twice the length of the beam is to its depth as the absolute strength of one of its vertical planes to its relative strength, or its power of resisting this transverse fracture.</p><p>It is evident, that what has been now demonstrated of the resistance exerted in the line CD, is equally true of every line parallel to CD in the thickness or breadth of the beam. The absolute strength of the whole section of fracture is represented by<hi rend="italic">fdb,</hi>  and we still have 2 Z : rZ= ∕iZZ∣  : <hi rend="italic">w ; </hi>or twice the length of the beam is to its depth as the absolute strength to the relative strength. Suppose the beam twelve feet long and one foot deep ; then whatever be its absolute strength, the twenty-fourth part of this will break it if hung at its extremity.</p><p>But even this is too favourable a statement. All the fibres are supposed to act alike in the instant of fracture. But this is not true. At the instant that the fibre at D breaks, it is stretched to the utmost, and is exerting its whole force. But at this instant the fibre at <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  is not so much stretched, and it is not then exerting its utmost force. If we suppose the extension of the fibres to be as their distance from C, and the actual exertion of each to be as their extensions, it may easily be shown (see Strength and Strain), that the whole resistance is the same as if the full force of all the fibres were united at a point <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  distant from C by one third of CD. In this case we must say, that the absolute strength is to the relative strength as three times the length to the depth ; so that the beam is weaker than by the former statement in the proportion of two to three.</p><p>Even this is more strength than experiment justifies, and we can see an evident reason for it. When the beam is strained, not only are the upper fibres stretched, but the lower fibres are compressed. This is very distinctly seen, if we attempt to break a piece of cork cut into the shape of a beam. This being the case, C is not the centre of fracture. There is some point c which lies between the fibres which are stretched and those that are compressed. This fibre is neither stretched nor squeezed, and this point is the real centre of fracture ; and the lever by which a fibre D resists, is not DC, but a shorter one Dc, and the energy of the whole resistances must be less than by the second statement. Till we know the proportion between the dilatability and compressibility of the parts, and the relation</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>