<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rant to engage in ∏terary tasks of any kind. The mystical portion of the romance of the <hi rend="italic">Round Table</hi>  seems derived from the same source. It may also be mentioned, that the audacious, and sometimes blasphemous assertions, which claimed for these fictions the credit due even to the inspired writings themselves, were likely to originate amongst Roman Catholic churchmen, who were but too familiar with such forgeries for the purpose of authenticating the legends of their superstition. One almost incredible instance of this impious specious of imposture occurs in the history of the <hi rend="italic">Saint Graal,</hi>  which curious mixture of mysticism and chivalry is ascribed by the unfearing and unblushing writer to the second person of the Trinity.</p><p>Churchmen, however, were by no means the only authors of these legends, although the <hi rend="italic">Sires Clercs,</hi>  as they were sometimes termed, who were accounted the chronicles of the times in which they lived, were usually in orders ; and although it appears that it was upon them that the commands of the soveregins whom they served often imposed the task of producing new romancesunderthe usual disguise of ancient chronicles translated from the learned languages, or otherwise collected from the ruins of antiquity. As education became improved, and knowledge began to be more generally diffused, individuals among the laity, and those of no mean rank, began to feel the necessity, as it may be called, of putting into a permanent form the “thick-coming fancies” which gleam along the imagination of men of genius. Sir Thomas Malony, who compiled the <hi rend="italic">Morte D’Arthur </hi>from French originals, was a person of honour and worship; and Lord Berners, the excellent translator of Froissart, and author of a romance called <hi rend="italic">The Chevalier de la Cygne,</hi>  is an illustrious example that a nobleman of high estimation did not think his time misemployed on this species of composition. Some literary fame must therefore have attended these efforts ; and perhaps less eminent authors might, in the latter ages, receive some pecuniary advantages. The translator of <hi rend="italic">Perceforest,</hi>  formerly mentioned, who appears to have been an Englishman or Fleming, in his address to the warlike and invincible nobility of France, holds the language of a professional author, who expected some advantage besides that of pleasing those whom he addressed ; and who expresses proportional gratitude for the favourable reception of his former feeble attempts to please them. It is possible, therefore, that the publishers, these lions of literature, had begun already to admit the authors into some share of their earnings. Other printers, like the venerable Caxton, compiled themselves, or translated from other languages, the romances which they sent to the press ; thus uniting in their own persons the three separate departments of author, printer, and publisher.</p><p>The prose romance did not, in the general conduct of the story, where digressions are heaped on digressions, without the least respect to the principal narrative, greatly differ from that of their metrical predecessors, being to the full as tedious and inartificial ; nay, more so, in proportion as the new romances were longer than the old. In the transference from verse to prose, and the amplification which the scenes underwent in the process, many strong, forcible, and energetic touches of their original author have been weakened, or altogether lost ; and the reader misses with regret someof the redeeming bursts of rude poetry which, in theme-trical romance, make amends for many hundred lines of bald and rude versification. But, on the other hand, the prose romances were written for a more advanced stage of society, and by authors whose language was much more copious, and who certainly belonged to a more educated class than the ancient minstrels. Men were no longer satisfied with hearing of hard battles and direful wounds ; they demanded at the hand of those who professed to entertain them, some insight into nature, or at least into manners; some description of external scenery, and a greater regard to probability both in respect of the characters which are introduced, and the events which are narrated. These new demands the prose romances endeavoured to supply to the best of their power. There was some attention shewn to relieve their story, by the introduction of new characters, and to illustrate these personages by characteristic dialogue. The lovers conversed with each other in the terms of metaphysical gallantry, which were used in real life; and from being a mere rhapsody of warlike feats, the romance began to assume the nobler and more artificial form of a picture of manners. It is in the prose folios of <hi rend="italic">Lancelot du Lac, Perceforest,</hi>  and others, that antiquaries find recorded tile most exact accounts of fights, tournaments, feasts, and other magnificent displays of chivalric splendour ; and as they descend into more minute description than the historians of the time thought worthy of their pains, they are a mine from which the painful student may extract much valuable information. This, however, is not the full extent of their merit. These ancient books, amid many pages of dull repetition and uninteresting dialogue, and notwithstanding the langour of an inartificial, protracted, and confused story, exhibit from time to time passages of deep interest, and situations of much novelty, as well as specimens of spirited and masculine writing. The general reader, who dreads the labour of winnowing out these valuable passages from the sterile chaff through which they are scattered, will receive an excellent idea of the beauties and defects of the romance from Tressan’s <hi rend="italic">Corps &lt;1Extraits de Romans de Chevalerie, </hi>from Mr. Ellis’s <hi rend="italic">Specimens of Early English Romances, </hi>and Mr. Dunlop’s <hi rend="italic">History of Fiction.</hi></p><p>These works continued to furnish the amusement of the most polished courts in Europe, so long as the manners and habits of chivalry continued to animate them. Even the sagacious Catherine of Medicis considered the romance of <hi rend="italic">Perceforest</hi>  as the work best qualified to form the manners and amuse the leisure of a young prince ; since she impressed on Charles IX. the necessity of studying it with attention. But by degrees the progress of new opinions in religion, the promulgation of a stricter code of morality, together with the important and animating discussions which began to be carried on by means of the press, diverted the public attention from these antiquated legends. The Protestants of England, and the Huguenots of France, were rigorous in their censure of books of chivalry, in proportion as they had been patronized formerly under the Catholic system; perhaps because they helped to arrest men’s thoughts from more serious subjects of occupation. The learned Ascham thus inveighs against the romance of <hi rend="italic">Morte D’Arthur,</hi>  and atthe same time acquaints us with its having passed out of fashion : “ In our forefathers’ tyme, when papestrie, asastandyng poole, covered and overflowed all Englande, fewe bookes were read in our tongue, savyng certaine bookes ofch ivalrie,as they said for pastime and pleasure; which, as somc say, were made in monasteries by idle monks, or wanton chanons. As, for example, <hi rend="italic">Lα Morte D’Arthur,</hi>  the whole pleasure of which booke standeth in two spcciall poyntes, in open manslaughter, and bold baw-drye : in which booke they are counted the noblest knightes thatdokill most men without anyquarrell, and commit foulest adulteries by sutlest shiftes; as Sir Launce!ote, with the wife of King Arthur his master ; Sir Tristram, with the wife of King Marke his uncle ; Sir Lamerocke, with the wife of King Lote, that was his own aunt. This is good stuffe for wise men to lauglιe at, or honest men to take pleasure at: yet I know, when God’s Bible was banished the court, and <hi rend="italic">La Morte D'Arthur</hi>  received into the prince’s chamber.”@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>The brave and religious La Noue is not more favourable to the perusal of romances than the learned Ascham ; at-</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1 </hi><hi rend="italic">Works </hi>of Roger Ascham, p. 254. 4to. edition.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>