<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the arrangement of this elevation which distributes them over the surface of the earth. This appears to be accomplished with considerable regularity; and, except the great desert of Kobi on the confines of Chinese Tartary, we do not remember any very extensive tract of ground that is deprived of those channels for voiding the superfluous waters; and even there they are far from being redundant.</p><p>The courses of rivers give us the best general method for judging of the elevation of a country. Thus it appears  that Savoy and Switzerland are the highest grounds of Europe, from whence the ground slopes in every direction. From the Alps proceed the Danube and the Rhine, whose courses mark the two great valleys, into which many lateral streams descend. The Po also and the Rhone come from the same head, and with a steeper and shorter course find their way to the sea through valleys of less breadth and length. On the west side of the valleys of the Rhine and the Rhone the ground rises pretty fast, so that few tributary streams come into them from that side; and from this gentle elevation France slopes to the westward. If a line, nearly straight, but bending a little to the northward, be drawn from the head of Savoy and Switzerland all the way to Solikamskoy in Siberia, it will nearly pass through the most elevated part of Europe; for in this tract most of the rivers have their rise. On the left go off the various feeders of the Elbe, the Oder, the Wesel, the Niemen, the Duna, the Neva, the Dwina, the Petzora. On the right, after passing the feeders of the Danube, we see the sources of the Sereth and Pruth, the Dniester, the Bog, the Dnieper, the Don, and the mighty Volga. The elevation, however, is extremely moderate; and it appears from the levels taken with the barometer by the Abbé Chappe d’Anteroche, that the head of the Volga is not more than 470 feet above the surface of the ocean. And we may observe here, by the by, that its mouth, where it discharges its waters into the Caspian Sea, is undoubtedly lower by many feet than the surface of the ocean. (See Pneumatics. ) Spain and Finland, with Lapland, Norway, and Sweden, form two detached parts, which have little symmetry with the rest of Europe.</p><p>A chain of mountains begins in Nova Zembla, and stretches due south to near the Caspian Sea, dividing Europe from Asia. About three or four degrees north of the Caspian Sea it bends to the south-east, traverses Western Tartary, and passing between the Tengis and Zaizan lakes, it then branches to the east and south. The eastern branch runs to the shores of Korea and Kamtschatka. The southern branch traverses Turkestan and Thibet, separating them from India, and at the head of the kingdom of Ava joins an arm stretching from the great eastern branch, and here forms the centre of a very singular radiation. Chains of mountains issue from it in every direction. Three or four of them keep very close together, dividing the continent into narrow slips, which have each a great river flowing in the middle, and reaching to the extreme points of Malacca, Cambodia, and Cochin-china. From the same central point proceeds another great ridge due east, and passes a little north of Canton in China. We called this a singular centre; for though it sends off so many branches, it is by no means the most elevated part of the continent. In the triangle which is included between the first southern ridge (which comes from between the lakes Tengis and Zaizan), the great eastern ridge, and its branch which almost unites with the southern ridge, lie the Boutan and part of Thibet; and the many little rivers which occupy its surface flow southward and eastward, uniting a little to the north of the centre often mentioned, and then pass through a gorge eastward into China. The higher grounds (if we except the ridges of mountains which are boundaries) of the continent seem to be in the country of the Calmucs, about 96° east from London, and latitude 43° or 45° north. It is represented as a fine though sandy country, having many little rivers which lose themselves in the sand, or end in little salt lakes. This elevation stretches north-east to a great distance; and in this tract we find the heads of the Irtish, Selenga, and Tunguskaia (the great feeders of the Oby), the Olenitz, the Lena, the Yana, and some other rivers, which all go off to the north. On the other side we have the great river Amur, and many smaller rivers, whose names are not familiar. The Hoangho, the great river of China, rises on the south side of the great eastern ridge we have so often mentioned. This elevation, which is a continuation of the former, is somewhat of the same complexion, being very sandy, and at present is a desert of prodigious extent. A great ridge of mountains begins at the south-east corner of the Euxine Sea, and proceeds eastward, ranging along the south side of the Caspian, and, still advancing, unites with the mountains first mentioned in Thibet, sending off some branches to the south, which divide Persia, India, and Thibet. From the south side of this ridge flow the Euphrates, Tigris, Indus, and Ganges, and from the north the ancient Oxus and many unknown streams.</p><p>Of the rivers of Africa we still know but little. The Nile indeed is perhaps better known than any river out of Europe; and of its source and progress we have given a full account in a separate article. See Nile.</p><p>By the register of the weather kept by Mr Bruce at Gondar in 1770 and 1771, it appears that the greatest rains fall about the beginning of July. He says that at an average each month after June it doubles its rains. The ca-lish or canal is opened at Cairo about the 9th of August, when the river has risen fourteen peeks (each twenty-one inches), and the waters begin to decrease about the 10th of September. Hence we may form a conjecture concerning the time which the latter employs in coming from Abyssinia. Mr Bruce supposes it nine days, which would require a velocity of not less than fourteen feet in a second; a thing past belief, and inconsistent with all our notions. The general slope of the river is greatly diminished by several great cataracts; and Mr Bruce expressly says that he might have come down from Sennaar to the cataracts of Syene in a boat, and that it is navigable for boats far above Sennaar. He came from Syene to Cairo by water. We apprehend that no boat would venture down a stream moving even six feet in a second, and none could row up if the velocity was three feet. As the waters begin to decrease about the 10th of September, we must conclude that the water then flowing past Cairo had left Abyssinia when the rains had greatly abated. Judging in this way, we must still allow the stream a velocity of more than six feet. Had the first swell at Cairo been noticed in 1770 or 1771, we might have guessed better. The year that Thevenot was in Egypt, the first swell of eight peeks was observed on the 28th of January. The calish was opened for fourteen peeks on the 14th of August, and the waters began to decrease on the 23d of September, having risen to twenty-one and two-third peeks. We may suppose a similar progress at Cairo corresponding to Mr Bruce’s observations at Gondar, and date every thing five days earlier.</p><p>The frame-work (so to call it) of America is better known, and is singular.</p><p>A chain of mountains begins, or at least is found, in longitude 110° west of London, and latitude 40° north, on the northern confines of the kingdom of Mexico, and, stretching southward through that kingdom, forms the ridge of the neck of land which separates North from South America, and keeping almost close to the shore, ranges along the whole western coast of South America, terminating at Cape Horn. In its course it sends off branches, which after separating from it for a few leagues, rejoin it again, enclosing valleys of great extent from north to south, and of prodi-</p></body></text></TEI>