<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>himself to the utmost to alleviate these visitations of suffering; and while so engaged, his sympathies were called forth afresh by a dreadful plague which carried away vast multitudes at Rome. These disastrous events deeply grieved the benignant heart of Titus, and he strove incessantly to lighten the weighty calamities which pressed so heavily upon the empire. In the midst of these exertions and anxieties, he was seized with fever, against the fatal effects of which neither the skill of physicians nor the strength of his constitution could avail. After a short reign of two years ten months and a few days, he died in the forty-second year ofhis age, leaving behind him the reputation of being, if not the happiest, at least the best of monarchs.</p><p>Flavius Domitian, the younger brother of Titus, now ascended the vacant throne without opposition. On his first accession to imperial power, he seemed desirous of emulating the conduct of his brother. He paid the strictest attention to justice, bestowing a large portion of his time in hearing causes that had been appealed, and shewing himself ready to reverse every inequitable sentence. Pretending great disregard for wealth, he refused to accept the property bequeathed to him, distributing it among the natural heirs. To prevent his chief officers of state from receiving bribes, he bestowed upon them large sums, that they might be raised above the reach of temptation. He was, at the same time, remarkably liberal in granting donations, and providing the most expensive shows and amusements to the people. He confirmed all the grants made by his predecessors to the soldiers, and increased their pay, thus securing their favour and support. All the public buildings which Titus had begun he caused to be finished, sparing no expenditure to have them completed in the most splendid manner.</p><p>Having by these popular displays and manifestations secured the favour of the army and the populace, Domitian began to throw aside the mask which he had for a short time uneasily worn. Vanity and timidity seemed to bc the leading elements of his character. The first led him to be inordinately desirous of obtaining popular applause, or even private flattery, however gross ; the second rendered him incapable of performing any noble exploit, constantly afraid of public danger or private conspiracies, and consequently cruel to excess, when his victims were completely in his power. For it is an obvious truth, that cowardice and cruelty are inseparably allied ; and the opposite is equally true, that the bravest man is also the most merciful. The vanity of Domitian made him desirous of a military triumph ; and in order to obtain it he made an expedition into Gaul, against the Catti, a warlike German tribe which had invaded the province. Without having even seen the enemy, he demanded a triumph ; and the servile senate granted the request of their weak and inglorious sovereign.</p><p>The intelligence of the really glorious exploits of Agricola in Britain, excited the envy of Domitian; and he recallcd that celebrated general, under a pretence of appointing him to the government of Syria. Agricola was too prudent to require a triumph, and retired into private life, which, however, he did not long enjoy, his death being hastened, as some suspect, by the guile of the emperor. He was soon afterwards involved in a more formidable war, in consequence of an irruption of the Daci and Getæ, who, under the command of their brave king Decebalus, crossed the Roman frontiers, and defeated the armies sent to oppose them. Domitian had now an opportunity of acquiring the renown of a warrior, but he wanted a warrior’s heart. He did indeed march against the invader in person, taking care to turn his course so as to encounter the less-dreaded Marcomanni, by whom he was nevertheless defeated. Not daring to come to an engagement with the Daci, he actually purchased a peace, agreeing to pay Decebalus an annual sum of money, provided he w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ould withdraw from the Roman dominions. This war is memorable, as being the first in which the northern barbarians attacked the empire not only with impunity, but with success; the pernicious precedent being thus established of purchasing peace, not with steel, but gold, in direct contrast to the old Roman usage.</p><p>In proportion as Domitian became truly despicable, did be increase in the most absurd and proposterous vanity. He now deified himself, and commanded his own statue to be worshipped as a god, at the very time that his mind was agitated with constant dread of plots against his life. Surrounded with spies and informers, he became more and more cruel, reviving the law of treason, and putting into terrific force al 1 its bloody provisions. An unsuccessful revolt of the army in Upper Germany gave an opportunity to the timid yet sanguinary tyrant to indulge his ferocity, by putting to death all whom he suspected of disaffection. About the same time, a persecution was commenced against the Christians, partly because they refused to worship the statue of the emperor, and partly because his ignorant and superstitious mind had formed some vague notion of their connexion with the Jews, coupled with the dread, not yet either extinct or understood, of the appearance of a person born in Judea, who was to obtain the empire of the world. In this persecution several persons of illustrious birth and station perished, among whom was Flavius Clemens, a relation of the emperor; which shews that Christianity was beginning to make progress among the higher ranks of society.</p><p>But the end of this weak, vain, and cruel tyrant drew near. In order to secure the support of the army, he had augmented the pay of the troops one-fourth ; and in order to meet the increased expense, he increased the number of those judicial murders, by the law of treason, which caused the property of the victims to be confiscated and become his own. He was in the habit of inscribing on a roll the names of those persons whom he designed to put to death, and kept it carefully in his own possession, treating them, in the meanwhile, with the most flattering attention. This fatal roll was one day taken from under the cushion on which he was reclining asleep, by a child who was playing about the apartment, and who carried it to the empress. She was struck with astonishment and alarm at finding her own name on the dark record, together with the names of others apparently highest in his favour. To them she communicated the knowledge of their danger ; and they immediately resolved to preserve their own lives by destroying that of Domitian. This was accordingly done, notwithstanding all the precautions which cowardice and cunning coιdd suggest; and, witll the connivance ofthe prætorian prefect, Domitian perished by the daggers of Stephanus and Parthenius, officers of his own household.</p><p>He was the last of the emperors commonly described as “the twelve Cæsars;” although, in reality, the Cæsarean family terminated with Nero, and even previously its continuation had been only in the female line. Marcus Cocceius Nerva was chosen by an unanimous vote of the senate, on the very day of Domitian’s death, that they might anticipate any attempt of the prætorian guard to make an emperor. He was of foreign extraction, though a naturalized citizen and senator of Rome, and owed his elevation to the throne solely to his stainless reputation. He commenced his reign by punishing informers, redressing grievances, repealing iniquitous statutes, enacting good laws, and dispensing favours with boundless liberality. He had made a resolution that no senator should be put to death by his command ; but this, together with proofs of equal unwillingness to inflict punishment, encouraged the turbulent to indulge in their evil practices. An insurrection broke out in the prætorian guard, and to appease it Nerva was obliged to yield up the murderers of Domitian to their vengeance. Feeling his inability to control these seditious troops, he resolved to adopt as his colleague and successor in the empire Marcus Ulpius Trajan, by whose firmness and decision they might</p></body></text></TEI>