<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rence in 1723, of the writings on the motion of rivers. From them we have extracted the <hi rend="italic">only precise observations </hi>which are to be found in the whole work.</p><p>The Po Grande receives no river from Stellata to the sea, and its slope in that interval is found most surprisingly uniform, namely, six inches in the mile (reduced to English measure). The breadth in its great freshes is 759 feet at Lago Scuro, with a very uniform depth of thirty-one feet. In its lowest state (in which it is called <hi rend="italic">Po Magra),</hi>  its breadth is not less than 700, and its depth about ten and a half.</p><p>The Rheno has a uniform declivity from the Ponte Emilio to Vigarano of fifteen inches per mile. Its breadth in its greatest freshes is 189 feet, and its depth nine.</p><p>Signor Corrade in his report says, that in the state of the great freshes the velocity of the Rheno is most exactly four fifths of that of the Po.</p><p>Grandi says, that, according to many observations of his own, a great fresh in the Rheno employs twelve hours to come from Ponte Emilio to Vigarano, which is thirty miles. This is a velocity of forty-four inches per second. And, by Corrade<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s proportion, the velocity of the Po Grande must be fifty-five inches per second.</p><p>Montanari’s observation gives the Po Magra a velocity of thirty-one inches per second.</p><p>Let us compare these velocities with the velocities calculated by Du Buat’s formula.</p><p>The hydraulic mean depths <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  and D of the Rheno and Po in the great freshes, deduced from the above measures, are 98∙6 and 344 inches; and their slopes s and S are 5⅛¾ and ttj¼stj. This will give</p><p>307 (√D-0∙1)</p><p><hi rend="sub">v</hi>,g_L √g + χ∙6—θ'<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  (*<hi rend="sup">z</hi>D—0-1) =52-176 inches, and</p><p>307(√5-0∙l)    , _</p><p>√sL√s~+W ~ <hi rend="sup">θ</hi>"<hi rend="sup">3 (Vd</hi>~ °<hi rend="sup">-1)</hi> = <hi rend="sup">4θ</hi>'<hi rend="sup">727 inche8</hi>∙</p><p>These results differ very little from the velocities above mentioned. And if the velocity corresponding to a depth of thirty-one feet be deduced from that observed by Mon-tanari in the Po Magra ten feet deep, on the supposition that they are in the proportion of <hi rend="italic">Vd,</hi>  it will be found to be about fifty-three and a half inches per second.</p><p>This comparison is therefore highly to the credit of the theory, and would have been very agreeable to Du Buat had he known it, as we hope it is to our readers.</p><p>We have collected many accounts of water-pipes, and made the comparisons, and we flatter ourselves that these have enabled us to improve the theory. They shall appear in their proper place ; and we may just observe here, that the two-inch pipe, which we formerly spoke of as conveying the water to Dunbar, should have yielded only 25∣ Scotch pints per minute by the formula, instead of 27 ; a small error.</p><p>We have, therefore, no hesitation in saying, that this single formula of the uniform motion of water is one of the most valuable presents which natural science and the arts have received during the course of this century.</p><p>307</p><p>A table containing the values of    —7 <hi rend="sup">,</hi>  . . . „  ready</p><p><hi rend="sup">b</hi>    √s-L√s+1∙6    <hi rend="sup">,</hi></p><p>calculated for every declivity that can occur in water-pipes, canals, or rivers, is given in the article Water-works. Aided by this, which supersedes the only difficult part of the computation, a person can calculate the velocity for any</p><p>proposed case in less than five minutes.</p><p>We have now established in some measure a Theory of Hydraulics, by exhibiting a general theorem which expresses the relation of the chief circumstances of all such motions as have attained a state of permanency, in so far as</p><p>this depends on the magnitude, form, and slope of the channel. This permanency we have expressed by the term train, saying that the stream is <hi rend="italic">in train.</hi></p><p>We proceed to consider the subordinate circumstances contained in this theorem; such as, 1st, The forms which nature or art may give to the bed of a running stream, and the manner of expressing this form in our theorem. 2d, The gradations of the velocity, by which it decreases in the different filaments, from the axis or most rapid filament to the border ; and the connection of this with the mean velocity, which is expressed by our formula. 3d, Having acquired some distinct notions of this, we shall be able to see the manner in which undisturbed nature works in forming the beds of our rivers, the forms which she affects, and which we must imitate in all their local modifications, if we would secure that permanency which is the evident aim of all her operations. We shall here learn the mutual action of the current and its bed, and the circumstances which insure the stability of both. These we may call the <hi rend="italic">regimen</hi>  or the <hi rend="italic">conservation</hi>  of the stream, and may say that it is <hi rend="italic">in regimen, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">in conservation.</hi>  This has a relation, not to the dimensions and the slope alone, or to the accelerating force and the resistance arising from mere inertia ; it respects immediately the tenacity of the bed, and is different from <hi rend="italic">the train.</hi></p><p>4th, These pieces of information will explain the deviation of rivers from the rectilineal course, the resistance occasioned by these deviations, and the circumstances on which the regimen of a winding stream depends.</p><p>§ 1. <hi rend="italic">Of the Forms of the Channel.</hi></p><p>The numerator of the fraction which expresses the velocity of a river in train has √<hi rend="italic">d</hi>  for one of its factors. That form, therefore, is most favourable to the motion which gives the greatest value to what we have called the hydraulic mean depth <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>  This is the prerogative of the semicircle, and here <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is equal to half the radius ; and all other figures of the same area are the more favourable, as they approach nearer to a semicircle. This is the form, therefore, of ail conduit-pipes, and should be taken for aqueducts which are built of masonry. Ease and accuracy of execution, however, have made engineers prefer a rectangular form ; but neither of these will do for a channel formed out of the ground. We shall soon see that the semicircle is incompatible with a regimen ; and if we proceed through the regular polygons, we shall find that the half hexagon is the only one which has any pretensions to a regimen ; yet experience shows us, that even its banks are too steep for almost any soil. A dry earthen bank, not bound together by grass roots, will hardly stand with a slope of forty-five degrees ; and a canal which conveys running waters will not stand with this slope. Banks whose base is to their height as four to three will stand very well in moist soils, and this is a slope very usually given. Tllis form is even affected in the spontaneous operations of nature, in the channels which she digs for the rills and rivulets in the higher and steeper grounds.</p><p>This form has some mathematical and mechanical properties which entitle it to some further notice. Let ABEC (fig. 12) be such a trapezium, and AHGC the rectangle of equal width and depth. Bisect HB and EG by the verticals FD and KI, and draw the verticals 5B, eE. Because AH : HB = 3 : 4, we have AB = 5, and BD = 2, and FD = 3, and BD + DF = B A. From these premises it follows, that the trapezium ABEC</p><p>has the same area with the rect</p><p>angle FDIK ; for HB being bi</p><p>sected in D, the triangles AOF,</p><p>BOD are equal. Also the border</p><p>ABEC, which is touched by the</p><p>passing stream, is equal to FDIK.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>