<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>confining his levies to the wealthier citizens, as had always hitherto been the case, he raised it almost entirely from among the very lowest class in the state, the <hi rend="italic">capite censi, </hi>the indigent, the desperate, and the mercenary. An army formed of such materials was a fitting instrument for accomplishing any design, inasmuch as it was utterly destitute of every moral virtue and every patriotic feeling, owing no allegiance except that enforced by military discipline, or purchased by occasional indulgence in military excesses. This most unpropitious innovation secured for the time the ascendency of Marius and the popular party ; but it laid the foundation of that military despotism which ultimately destroyed the last lingering remains of Roman liberty ,∙ as indeed it must do sooner or later when the military spirit becomes purely mercenary, the love of country expires, and the citizen is lost in the soldier.</p><p>This dangerous innovation might not have been so completely confirmed, had it not been for a new, and most formidable foe with which the republic was at this juncture threatened. The Cimbri and Teutones, two of those northern nations which, occasionally bursting from their forests, overran contiguous countries, exterminated the native inhabitants, and became the origin of new races and nations, had penetrated into the Roman provinces, and come into contact with the armies of the republic. In Styria they defeated the consul Papirius Carbo ; in Gaul, Junius Silanus had no better fortune ; and, finally, the two consuls, Manlius and Cæpio, were routed with immense slaughter, eighty thousand men perishing in the conflict. The tidings of this defeat caused the utmost consternation at Rome ; and such was the military reputation of Marius, that both senate and people concurred in nominating him a second time to the consulship, even before the expiration of his first year of command. He immediately levied new forces ; and in the extreme terror of the republic, no opposition was made to his enrolment of great numbers of the city populace, by which this innovation was confirmed, and the precedent established, of mustering troops from the very dregs of society, and whose character was altogether base and mercenary. For a time, however, tlle tide of the Cimbrian war rolled past, and spent its force on Gaul, though still continuing to threaten Italy. During this interval, Marius continued to increase his army, and to perfect the discipline of the new recruits, his tenure of the consulship being prolonged for four successive years, in consequence of the continuation of the same dread which had at first caused his illegal reinstatement in that office. In his fourth year, the Teutones having entered the Roman territories, were defeated by Marius, near Aix, with immense slaughter, more than two hundred thousand of the invaders having perished. Next year he was equally successful against the Cimbri, in a battle fought near the Po ; in which, however, his colleague Catulus, and, what more annoyed him, Sylla, shared the honours of the victory.</p><p>Marius had now enjoyed the consulship for the unprecedented term of five successive years, and might have retired with an unrivalled reputation ; but the possession of power had only stimulated him with the eager desire of prolonging his enjoyment of it. Soon after his return to Rome he began to intrigue with the popular party, in order to obtain the consulship a sixth time, in opposition to his old rival Metellus ; and having formed a strict confederacy with the tribune Saturnius, and the praetor Glaucias, two demagogues of the most unprincipled character, partly by their aid, and partly by means of the most extensive bribery, he procured bis re-election to that dignity. There was now no check to the designs of the democratic faction, the people being led on by a tribune of the most abandoned and reckless character, and the senate being headed by an ambitious demagogue. But at length the extreme measures of Saturnius alarmed and disgusted even Marius ; and with his usual</p><p>force of character, he resolved to oppose the factious tribune. A great commotion ensued. Saturnius and Glaucias seized the Capitol, but were closely besieged, their supplies of water cut off, and being forced to surrender, they were condemned and executed as traitors. Thus did the extreme licentiousness of the popular faction compel even their own most powerful leader to interpose, and to put forth his iron strength to crush them as disturbers of the public peace, and enemies of their country’.</p><p>This interposition in behalf of the republic cost Marius nothing less than a temporary loss of that power of which he was so ambitious. After the expiration of the sixth consulship, he found himself unable to retain his influence; his old antagonist Metellus was recalled from banishment; and he withdrew into Asia in a species of voluntary exile. A temporary cessation from the civil broils which had convulsed Rome, gave leisure for the reformation of the state from some of the abuses which had been forcibly introduced, or had insensibly sprung up. Some salutary laws were enacted against the systematic oppression under which the provinces groaned. Another measure, also of a reforming character, led to a less propitious result. This was an attempt to control the conduct ofthe equestrian order, which had become hurtful to the community, especially since C. Gracchus bestowed upon them the judicative authority. They had also obtained the farming of the leases, and consequently the collection of the revenue in the provinces, by which means they were enabled not only to oppose every reform that was attempted in the provincial administration, being judges in their own cause, but also to hold the senate itself in a state of dependence. The tribune Livius Drusus procured the enactment of a law, the effect of which was to restore to the senatorial body the half of the judicative power ; but the means by which this law was passed, and by which it came into operation, involved an infringement of the constitution. Three hundred knights were added to tlle senate ; and from the body thus raised to six hundred, the judges were selected. Unhappily this tended more and more to render the senate an aristocracy of wealth, and thus to increase the chasm, already but too wide, between the wealthy and the poor classes of the community, and to prevent the growth of a middle class, one of the most fatal wants by which the republic was afflicted; a want which clearly indicated, and speedily caused, the total disruption of the social fabric.</p><p>But the most immediately disastrous subject of contention, was that which proposed the admission of all the Italian states in alliance with Rome, to the privileges of citizenship. Great numbers of the citizens of these states had either flocked to Rome upon losing their own property when conquered, or had been allured thither during the seditions of the Gracchi, by those popular leaders, with the view of strengthening their adherents, under the prospect of obtaining portions of the re-divided lands, or at least an idle maintenance from the gratuitous distribution of grain. To gratify these, and to procure a new accession of strength, Drusus proposed to admit all the Italian allies to the full rights of citizenship. This project roused the pride and the jealousy of the whole body of the people, who thought they foresaw in it the overthrow of all their peculiar privileges and powers, and who, however democratic at Rome, wished to be the aristocracy of all the world beside. The proposal was rejected by the unanimous voice of the people ; and Drusus himself was soon afterwards killed in a popular tuιmdt.</p><p>The Italian states, however, were not disposed to relinquish so easily the hopes which had been thus excited. They held private intercourse with each other, interchanged hostages, and prepared deliberately for a general revolt, unless their demands should be conceded. The chief states of this social alliance were the Marsi, the Pelagi, the Samnites, and the Lucanians. Having assumed arms, the allies sent to</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>