<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ment in that quarter would be at an end, and their formidable rival at the same time would have become their immediate neighbour.</p><p>An army under the command of the consul Appius Claudius was sent to the assistance of the Mamertines ; and notwithstanding the superior power of the Carthaginians at sea, the consul found means to elude their fleet, and to take possession of Messina. Several victories were soon afterwards gained by the Romans ; and Hiero, king of Syracuse, abandoned the Carthaginians, and formed an alliance with Rome. Agrigentum fell into the hands of the Romans after the defeat of a Carthaginian army, which had come to raise the siege, and the greater part of the interior of the island yielded to the power of Rome, while the fleets of Carthage kept possession of the sea-port towns, and thus maintained an equality. It was now evident to the Romans that the contest could come to no conclusion so long as their antagonists retained the supremacy of the sea ; and they directed their most strenuous endeavours towards the construction of a fleet.</p><p>Being aware of their inferiority in naval affairs, the Romans first availed themselves of a large Carthaginian vessel driven ashore in a storm, as a model ; and to counterbalance their deficiency in skill as mariners, they invented a machine called a <hi rend="italic">corvus,</hi>  which served both as a grappling-iron and a draw-bridge, the object of which was to enable them to come to close quarters, and encounter the Carthaginians man to man. Trusting to this new invention, the consul Duilius hazarded an engagement with the fleet of the enemy, rushed alongside their ships, locked them fast in the grapples of the corvus, and captured at the first onset, by boarding, no fewer than fifty gallies. The Carthaginian commander saved the remainder of his fleet by instant flight. To commemorate this their first naval victory, the Romans erected in the forum a column adorned with <hi rend="italic">rostra,</hi>  or beaks of ships. In a second naval action, fought near the island of Lipara, the Carthaginians lost eighteen vessels, of which eight were sunk and ten taken.</p><p>After the war had lasted about eight years, the Romans determined to invade Africa, being aware that the tyranny of Carthage had alienated many of the African nations. A fleet of three hundred and thirty ships was equipped for this daring attempt, and given to the consuls Regulus and Manlius. The Carthaginians were again defeated with great loss, sixty-four galleys being taken, and thirty destroyed. The victorious fleet was soon refitted, pursued its course, and landed the army near Clypea. A rapid succession of victories led the Romans to the very gates of Carthage. Tunis was taken, and the humbled enemy sought terms of peace. Regulus imposed demands so harsh, that they resolved to continue the war ; to which they were the more encouraged, by the opportune arrival of a band of Greek mercenaries under the command of Xanthippus, a Spartan of high military talents. The army being entrusted to his command, he completely changed its tactics, formed it on the Lacedemonian plan, and sought an engagement with the Romans. A great battle was fought, the Romans were completely routed, and Regulus himself taken prisoner. A Roman fleet sent to succour the army defeated the Carthaginian fleet in its course ; and the army, though reduced, routed the Carthaginians, no longer led by the brave Spartan. Being too weak, however, to remain in Africa, and distressed for want of provisions, the army embarked for Italy ; but a violent storm wrecked on the coast of Sicily not less than two hundred and ninety ships, with all on board. A second fleet was also destroyed in a storm ; and the Romans for a time abandoned the sea.</p><p>In Sicily Metellus defeated the Carthaginians with great slaughter ; and the Romans gaining the ascendency in that island, laid siege to Lilybæum. The Carthaginians, weakened and dispirited with their numerous losses, sent Regulus to Rome along witll their ambassadors, expecting that he would persuade the senate to grant a peace. Instead of this, he dissuaded the senate, and recommended war, though aware of the sufferings he would have to endure on his return to Carthage. Some historians relate, that on his return he was tortured to death in the most cruel manner; others say that he was merely retained in close confinement, and died a natural death before tlle conclusion of the war. Again was the contest renewed, and at first not to the advantage of Rome. One fleet was worsted in battle, and another entirely destroyed off the coast of Sicily. The command of the Carthaginian forces in Sicily was given to Hamilcar Barcas, father of the celebrated Hannibal. By his skill and conduct the sinking cause of his country was vigorously sustained, till it seemed as if Carthage might yet be victorious. The Carthaginians made a last desperate effort to supply him with forces, and fitted out a large fleet for that purpose. The Romans had also redoubled their exertions for the same reason. The two fleets met near the islands Ægates, and the fortunes of Rome prevailed. A decisive battle was fought; fifty of the Carthaginian ships were sunk, and seventy taken, the power of Carthage was laid prostrate, and the empire of the seas transferred to Rome. Carthage was now obliged to accept whatever terms of peace Rome thought proper to propose : these were, that they should evacuate all the islands in the Mediterranean, restore the Roman prisoners without ransom, and pay for the defraying of the expenses of the war a thousand talents of silver immediately, and two thousand two hundred in the space of ten years, in equal payments.</p><p>Thus ended the first Punic war, after a contest of nearly twenty-four years’ duration. Its vicissitudes had severely tried the strength and the resources of Rome ; but it extended her reputation and her political connexions very widely, preparing her for a career of foreign conquest. It awoke also in both republics, Rome and Carthage, an inextinguishable hatred of each other, such as could never be appeased but by the ruin of the one ; and it inspired Rome with a desire of foreign conquest and dominion, and of the wealth to be thus gained, which speedily introduced corruption into the state, along with that accumulation of power in the hands of a few families, which in every country long wars inevitably confer on able warriors. In this manner the seeds of Roman greatness and Roman decay were sown at once, and began to grow up side by side. Their further progress we shall afterwards have occasion to notice and explain.</p><p>The peace which Rome enjoyed at the termination of the first Punic war was of no lengthened duration. The first hostilities in which she was engaged were directed against Teuta, queen of Illyricum. The Illyrians had been successful in a war against the Ætolians ; and in the pride of their victory, they caused their fleets to scour tlle seas, and pillage those of every other nation without distinction, ln this piratical warfare some Roman ships were taken and plundered ; and the Illyrians laid siege to Issa, a city which had put itself under tlle protection of Rome. When the Roman ambassadors demanded restitution, and required Teuta to restrain her subjects from such piracies, she both returned a haughty answer, and procured the murder of the ambassadors. Upon this the Romans declared war against the Illyrians. In the course of the war they gained the naval supremacy over the Adriatic, subdued the Illyrians, and entered into alliance with the various states of Greece which had suffered from the depredations of the Illyrian pirates. This alliance was of the utmost importance to Rome, not only in opening the way for her future interference in the affairs of Greece and of Asia, but also in enabling her to divide her enemies, and prevent the formation of dangerous confederacies against her, when not prepared to meet them.</p><p>The Illyrian war had scarcely terminated when one of a</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>