<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that new aspect retained as much as possible. As the earliest principle of the structure of the Roman army was its division into centuries, so the same principle gave rise to an assembly of a new character, called the comitia centuriata, where the military principle predominated, and in which the whole population met. So much of a military character did this assembly at its origin bear, that it was not permitted to meet within the city, but in the Campus Martius, and it even bore the name of <hi rend="italic">exercitus urbanus.</hi></p><p>Tarquinius is stated to have added, not three new centuries bearing new names, to the equestrians, for that was prevented by the augur Navius, but three new centuries, forming a second series, and retaining the designation of the first three. These three double centuries of the Ramnenses, Titienses, and Luceres, were now recognised as distinctly six privileged bodies of voters, <hi rend="italic">sex suffragia,</hi>  of the new assembly. To these, which contained all the members of the houses, there were added by Servius twelve new centuries of knights,formed from the richest members of the plebeian community, and continuing, like the centuries below them, to belong to the thirty tribes of the commons. There were thus eighteen centuries of the most noble and wealthy persons in the state, who enjoyed the privilege of serving in the army on horseback ; known in their military character as the equites, and in their civil character as the equestrians, or, as we term them, the knights. Their distinction as an order was however posterior to their formation as the eighteen equestrian centuries in the comitia centuriata.</p><p>Proceeding on the military principle, the next point was to organise the foot soldiers of the state. This was done chiefly with reference to the value of the armour which individuals could afford to procure and wear in battle, because in the earliest ages of all nations, men armed themεelves as they best could, at their own expense, not that of the state, and consequently the richest were the best armed. As brass was the metal of which weapons of war, either offensive or defensive, were first formed, brass or copper, so many pounds weight, according to an estimate of the weight and value of the armour, formed the principle by which the successive classes were divided and arranged. Of these the first class contained all whose property amounted to, or exceeded, one hundred thousand pounds weight of copper. The soldiers of this class were required to be completely armed with greaves, coat of mail, helmet and shield of brass, besides the sword and the long pike. And as these were necessarily to advance in the front, and bear the shock of battle, and formed the flower of the troops, so their influence in the great military assembly was proportionate. They formed eighty centuries ; forty between the ages of fifteen and forty-five, to serve in the field ; and forty between forty-five and sixty, for the defence of the city. To this, the first class, the eighteen centuries of knights were added, so that it amounted in all to ninety-eight centuries. The second class contained those whose property fell beneath 100,000 asses, or pounds of copper, and above 75,000. These formed twenty centuries, and were less completely and expensively armed. The third class contained also twenty centuries, and its qualification was properly between 75,000 and 50,000 asses, or pounds of copper. Its armour was inferior to that of the preceding class. The fourth class contained those whose property was not beneath 25,000 asses ; it amounted to twenty centuries, and its soldiers were not required to provide more than a pike and a javelin. These four classes composed the main body or phalanx of the army, when it was drawn up in that order of battle previous to the formation of the legion. The fifth class consisted of those whose property was between 25,000 asses, and 12,500 ; it formed the slingers and archers, or light infantry of the army, and was divided into thirty centuries.</p><p>The poorest citizens, whose property fell short of 12,500</p><p>asses, were regarded as supernumeraries in this division. Those who had above 1500 asses were still regarded as taxpayers, <hi rend="italic">assidui,</hi>  and were formed into two centuries, called ιhe <hi rend="italic">accensi</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">velati.</hi>  They merely followed the army, and were only required to supply the places of those who fell. Below these came one century of the <hi rend="italic">proletarii,</hi>  whose property was between 1500 and 375 asses. These paid no taxes, had no military duty, and were only liable to be called on in great emergencies, as extraordinary levies, when arms were furnished to them at the public expense. One century more included all whose property, being less than 375 asses, was not worthy of being estimated, and who were called <hi rend="italic">capite censi,</hi>  and not liable to military service.</p><p>Three centuries of a different character completed the division, but these were not rated by their property, but by their occupation. These were,—one century of carpenters and smiths attached to the first class, and two of homblow-ers, <hi rend="italic">(cornicines),</hi>  and trumpeters, <hi rend="italic">(tubicines),</hi>  attached to the fourth class.</p><p>From this brief outline of the comitia centuriata, the new national constitution given to Rome by Servius Tullius, it will be seen that it was a proof of very remarkable political wisdom in that legislator. The new citizens of Rome had been rapidly increasing in numbers'and importance. A new tribe, the Luceres, had recently been raised to the possession of full political power. Three new equestrian centuries had been called into existence, though still in a subordinate position ; and the body ofthe commons, the plebeian body, augmented by the arrival of free citizens from recently conquered Latin states, was gradually rising in importance, so as to point to the necessity of its obtaining a recognised position in the state ; and at the same time to give to the hereditary patrician body no slight cause of alarm, lest it should soon become the most powerful body at Rome. By the Servian constitution, if we may so term it, tlle danger of any such revolution was averted by the admission of the plebs into a national council, without disturbing the proportions of influence due to the different bodies of which such a council was to be formed. The wealthiest men of the plebs would naturally be desirous of obtaining some share of that patrician dignity which they had enjoyed as Latins, before the annexation of their native states to Rome ; and this desire was met by the creation of twelve centuries of knights, added to the equestrian order from amongst the plebeian tribes. These twelve centuries constituted a <hi rend="italic">nobility,</hi>  but yet were so connected with the eighty centuries which formed the great body of the first class, that they could not degenerate into an oligarchy. The first class, again, being formed of the wealthiest persons in the state, though far the least numerous, prevented the government from becoming a democracy of that ultra kind, in which numbers form the <hi rend="italic">ruling element.</hi>  In truth, property formed the <hi rend="italic">mling element </hi>in the Servian constitution ; for the first class, containing ninety-eight centuries, even, without the addition of the <hi rend="italic">fahri,</hi>  formed the majority of the comitia centuriata, so that if all the centuries of that class were agreed on any point, it was carried without the votes of the other classes. The mere numbers ofthelower classes very greatly exceeded those of the first class ; but as property was assumed as the principle by which a century was to be formed, it required a great number of individuals to form a century of the requisite wealth. The proportion seems to have been regulated thus : the votes allotted to each class bore the same proportion to the collective sum of votes, as the taxable property of its members bore to the total taxable property of all the five classes ; while the number of the citizens contained in each, stood in an inverse ratio to the numbers which designated their property. Although, therefore, the plebeians were now admitted into the full rights of citizenship, and to a voice in the government, still the power of deciding was vested in those who possessed the chief rank, wealth, and that natu-</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>