<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>58.    As it is not necessary that tlle progressive motion of the centre of gravity be in a straight line, this formula enables us to determine the distances from the centre at which the planets may have received the single impulses which gave them at the same time their motions of revolution in their orbits, and of rotation round their axes. Thus, taking the case of the earth, and making R = the radius of its orbit, the circumference of the orbit is 2wR, and the part of this which is described by the centre of gravity, while tlle</p><p>2&lt;jr∏</p><p>earth revolves once about its axis, is θ=- <hi rend="italic">= s;</hi>  and by (18) <hi rend="italic">.ouO</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">fr<hi rend="sup">l</hi>dm</hi>  +- M = ∣  r<hi rend="sup">s</hi>  ; therefore<hi rend="italic">l = -~</hi>°<hi rend="sub">r</hi>  p — <hi rend="sup">r</hi>-. If we assume Dit.</p><p>r = 4000 miles, and R = 95,000,000 miles, this formula gives <hi rend="italic">l</hi>  = 24½ miles nearly.</p><p>59.    The direction of the force being PA (fig. 12), if a point be taken in the line AG between A and G, the motion of the point arising from the rotation of the body about the axis is in the first instant of time parallel to the direction of the progressive motion, and if <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  be its distance from G, the velocity due to both motions will be V + <hi rend="italic">rw.</hi>  But if the point be taken on the other side of G, the direction of the rotatory motion will be opposite to that of the progressive motion, and the velocity of the point will be V — <hi rend="italic">rw.</hi>  If therefore the point T be taken such that making GT = <hi rend="italic">r,</hi>  we have the equation V <hi rend="italic">— rw;</hi>  then, for a single instant, every point in the straight line passing through T perpendicular to HKL is at rest, or is carried as far back by the rotatory motion in the first instant of time, as it is carried forward by the progressive motion ; and, for a single instant, the double motion of the body may be regarded as a simple rotatory motion about that straight line. This point T is called the <hi rend="italic">centre of spontaneous rotation,</hi>  and the straight line passing through T, perpendicular to tlle plane HKL, is called the <hi rend="italic">axis of spontaneous ιotαtion∙</hi></p><p>60.    The preceding formulæ enable us to determine completely the two motions of translation and rotation when a ’force is applied to a single point of the free body ; we have now to determine what the effect will be when any number of forces given in magnitude and direction are applied to different points of the body ; and as it appears from what precedes, that during the first instant the two motions take place independently of each other, we shall first give the equations which fix the position of the centre of gravity of the moving body, and then those which define the rotatory motion, or determine the position of any point of the body with reference to its centre of gravity.</p><p>Let G be the centre of gravity of the body, M its mass, and let the motion be referred to three rectangular axes OX, OY, OZ. Let us now suppose forces given in magnitude and direction to be applied at the points A, A', A", &amp;c. of the body, and that each of them is resolved into three others respectively parallel to the directions of the axis, and let <hi rend="italic">p, q, r,</hi>  be the resolved forces applied at A ; <hi rend="italic">j∕, cf, r<hi rend="sup">,</hi>, </hi>the resolved forces applied at A', and so on ; also let P <hi rend="italic">—p </hi>+ ∕ + ∕∕' +, &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">Q. = q + &lt;f</hi>  + r∕'+, &amp;c., R = <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  + r' <hi rend="italic">+ r’</hi>  +, &amp;c. ; then, since the moving force is equal to the product of the mass into the velocity, and since by (56) the progressive motion resulting from the force applied at A is the same as if it had been applied to the centre of gravity, the velocity of the centre of gravity from the joint action of all the forces, in the directions OX, OY, OZ, will be re-</p><p>P Q R</p><p>spectively ∙^&gt; -yp —. But the resulting velocity is the</p><p>diagonal of the parallelopiped of which these component velocities are the sides ; therefore, denoting it by V, we have</p><p>v = ⅛√(P<hi rend="sup">t</hi>+Q<hi rend="sup">s</hi> + R<hi rend="sup">2</hi>)∙</p><p>To determine the direction of this velocity, let β, ,8, χ, be</p><lb/><p>the angles which its direction makes with the axis <hi rend="italic">x, y, z; </hi>then, since the forces P, Q, R meet in a point (the centre of gravity), we have</p><p>P <hi rend="sub">a</hi> Q    _ R</p><p>cos.α = <hi rend="sub">i3v</hi>,cos.∕3 = <hi rend="sub">s</hi>j<hi rend="sub">v</hi>, cos.<hi rend="sub">r</hi>=<hi rend="sub">j</hi>^<hi rend="sub">v</hi>.</p><p>These equations give the direction of the velocity ; hence, since V has already been found, the initial velocity of the centre of gravity and its direction are both completely determined.</p><p>61.    When the forces applied to the body are simply percussions, which cease to act after the first impact, and there is no resistance, no change will take place in the velocity or its direction during the second and succeeding instants, and the centre of gravity will describe a straight line with a uniform motion ; but if the forces continue to act after the motion has commenced, we must have recourse to the formulæ given by the principles of dynamics, which express the varied motion of a body subjected to the action of accelerating forces. At the end of the time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi>  reckoned from the commencement of the motion, let <hi rend="italic">x, y, z</hi>  be the co-ordinates of the element of the body <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  referred to the rectangular axes OX, OY, OZ ; then the velocity at that instant being expressed by the differential of the space described divided hy the element of the time, the components</p><p>of the velocity at the same instant will be ⅛ ⅞ ⅜. Now <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">j</hi>    dt dt dt</hi></p><p>the forces acting on the body, whatever be their nature, may always be decomposed into others parallel to the three axes ; suppose therefore P, Q, R to be the components of the accelerating forces in those directions acting on the point <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  then the increment of velocity being equal to tile force into the element of the time, if the particle <hi rend="italic">dm </hi>were entirely free, the velocities ^∙,    ⅛ would acquire</p><p>the increments <hi rend="italic">Pdt, Qdt,</hi>  RΛ in the instant <hi rend="italic">dt.</hi>  But the increments of velocity actually acquired in the instant <hi rend="italic">dt</hi></p><p>are the differentials of the velocities, or <hi rend="italic">d ∙ d∙ d ∙</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">’ dt' dt' df</hi></p><p>and therefore the velocities lost in consequence of the mutual connection of the particles are respectively</p><p>PΛ-d∙⅛QΛ-d∙⅛, RΛ-rf∙⅜ <hi rend="italic">dt    dt    dt</hi></p><p>Multiplying each of these expressions by <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  we get tlle quantities of motion due to the respective velocities. Now, according to a well-known principle of dynamics, the discovery of which is due to D’Alembert, the infinitely small quantities of motion lost in every instant by all the particles in consequence of their mutual connection must make equilibrium ; the integrals of the preceding expressions multiplied by <hi rend="italic">dm</hi>  must therefore be severally equal to zero, and we have accordingly (on effecting the operations indicated, and dividing by <hi rend="italic">dt)</hi>  the three equations</p><p><hi rend="italic">fPdm =J'<hi rend="sup">t</hi>^dm,fQ.dm=J^flm,fP.dm =J'<hi rend="sup">d</hi>Fflm.</hi></p><p>62.    In order to find the place of the centre of gravity at the end of the time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi>  let its co-ordinates at that instant be <hi rend="italic">x<hi rend="sub">l</hi>, yv <hi rend="sup">z</hi>ι</hi>  » then fr°<hi rend="sup">πl</hi>  the property of the centre of gravity we have</p><p>Mx<hi rend="sub">1</hi> =<hi rend="italic">fxdm,</hi>  My<hi rend="sub">1</hi>  =<hi rend="italic">fydm,</hi>  Mr, = <hi rend="italic">fzdm. </hi>Regarding the variables as functions of the time <hi rend="italic">t,</hi>  differentiating twice, and dividing each time by <hi rend="italic">dt,</hi>  we obtain</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="sup">m</hi>⅛=Λ*<hi rend="sup">m</hi>S-√5*</hi></p><p>"⅛=.∕3F'<hi rend="sup">fa</hi>∙</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>