<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>part of the arc of the circle. Making this comparison, he found these circumstances to be incompatible. He found that the section and swell at I, corresponding to an arc of a circle, gave a discharge nearly one fourth too great (they were as 405216 to 492142). Therefore the curve is sucn that AD is greater than DF, and that it is more incurvated at F than at A. He found, that making DA to DF as 10 to 9, and the curve FIA an arc of an ellipse whose longer axis was vertical, would give a very nice correspondence of the sections, velocities, and slopes. The whole extcnt of the swell, therefore, can never be double of AD, and must always greatly surpass AD ; and these limits will do very well for every practical question. Therefore, making DF nine tenths of AD, and drawing the chord AD, and making DI one half of D <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  we shall be very near the truth. Then we get the swell with sufficient precision for any point H between F and D, by making I'D<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  : FH<hi rend="sup">!</hi>  = ID : ΗΛ; and if H is between D and A, we get its distance from the tangent DA by a similar process.</p><p>It only remains to determine the swell produced in the waters of a river by the erection of a bridge or cleaning sluice, which contracts the passage. This requires the solution of</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. V. Given the depth, breadth, and slope of a river, to determine the swell occasioned by the piers of a bridge or sides of a cleaning sluice, which contract the passage by a given quantity, for a given length of channel.</hi></p><p>This swell depends on two circumstances.</p><p>1.    The whole river must pass through a narrow space, with a velocity proportionably increased ; and this requires a certain head of water above the bridge.</p><p>2.    The water, in passing the length of the piers with a velocity greater than that corresponding to the primary slope of the river, will require a greater slope in order to acquire this velocity.</p><p>Let V be the velocity of the river before the erection of the bridge, and K the quotient of the width of the river divided by the sum of the widths between the piers. If the length of the piers, or their dimension in the direction of the stream, is not very great, KV will nearly express the velocity of the river under the arches ; and if we suppose for a moment the contraction (in the sense hitherto used) to be nothing, the height producing this velocity will be K<hi rend="sup">s</hi>V<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>——. But the river will not rise so high, having already</p><p>a slope and velocity before getting under the arches, and V<hi rend="sup">s</hi></p><p>the height corresponding to this velocity is — ; thcrefore</p><p>the height for producing the augmentation of velocity is ]ζ2y2    y 2</p><p>---. But if we make allowance for contraction, we</p><p><hi rend="italic">'2g    %g</hi></p><p>must employ a co-efficient 2G less than <hi rend="italic">2g,</hi>  and we must multiply the height now found by    It will then become</p><p>,κ&lt;v≈^ ⅛ V.    <hi rend="sub">tllal</hi></p><p>t 2<hi rend="sub">ff</hi> 2√ 2G 2G<hi rend="sup">v</hi> '    <hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>the swell which must produce the augmentation of velocity.</p><p>With respect to what is necessary for producing the additional slope between the piers, let <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  be the natural slope of the river (or rather the difference of level in the length of the piers) before the erection of the bridge, and corresponding to the velocity V ; K¾j will very nearly express the difference of superficial level for the length of the piers, which is necessary for maintaining the velocity KV through the same length. The increase of slope therefore is jζ2p_<hi rend="italic">p = p</hi>  (K<hi rend="sup">s</hi>— 1). Therefore the whole swell will be</p><p>(fi+')&lt;<hi rend="sup">κ</hi>'-<hi rend="sup">,</hi>&gt;</p><lb/><p>These are the chief questions or problems on this subject whicn occur in the practice of an engineer ; and the solutions which we have given may in every case be depended on as very near the truth, and we are confident that the errors will never amount to one fifth of the whole quantity. We are equally certain, that of those who call themselves engineers, and who, without hesitation, undertake jobs of enormous expense, not one in ten is able even to guess at the result of such operations, unless the circumstances of the case happen to coincide with those of some other project which he has executed, or has distinctly examined ; and very few have the sagacity and penetration necessary for appreciating the effects of the distinguishing circumstances which yet remain. The society established for the encouragement of arts and manufactures could scarcely do a more important service to the public in the line of their institution, than by publishing in their transactions a description of every work of tllis kind executed in the kingdom, with an account of its performance. This would be a most valuable collection of experiments and facts. The unlearned practitioner would find among them something which resembles in its chief circumstances almost any project which could occur to him in his business, and would tell him what to expect in the case under his management ; and the intelligent engineer, assisted by mathematical knowledge, and the habit of classing things together, would frequently be able to frame general rules. To a gentleman qualified as was the Chevalier du Buat, such a collection would be inestimable, and might suggest a theory as far excelling his as he has excelled all other writers.</p><p>We shall conclude this article with some observations on the methods which may be taken for rendering small rivers and brooks fit for inland navigation, or at least for floatage. We get much instruction on this subject from what has been said concerning the swell produced in a river by weirs, bars, or any diminution of its former section. Our knowledge of the form which the surface of this swell affects will furnish rules for spacing these obstructions in such a manner, and at such distances from each other, that the swell produced by one shall extend to the one above it.</p><p>If we know the slope, the breadth, and the depth of a river, in the droughts of summer, and have determined on the height of the floodgates, or keeps, which are to be set up in its bed, it is evident that their stations are not matters of arbitrary choice, if we would derive the greatest possible advantage from them.</p><p>Some rivers in Flanders and Italy are made navigable in some sort by simple sluices, which, being shut, form magazines of water, which, being discharged by opening the gates, raises the inferior reach enough to permit the passage of the craft which are kept on it. After this momentary rise the keeps are shut again, the water sinks in the lower reach, and the lighters which were floated through the shallows are now obliged to draw into those parts of the reach where they can lie afloat till the next supply of water from above enables them to proceed. This is a very rude and imperfect method, and unjustifiable at this day, when we know the effect of locks, or at least of double gates. We do not mean to enter on the consideration of these contrivances, and to give the methods of their construction, in this place, but refer our readers to what has been already said on this subject in the article Navigation Inland, and to what will be said in the article Water-Works. At present we confine ourselves to the single point of husbanding the difterent falls in the bed of the river, in such a manner that there may be everywhere a sufficient depth of water ; and, in what we have to deliver on the subject, we shall take the form of an example to illustrate the application 01 the foregoing rules.</p><p>Suppose then a river forty feet wide and three feet deep</p></body></text></TEI>