<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Again did Stilicho by his superior tactics save his own army, and overthrow that of the enemy, enclosing them within such entrenched lines as they could not force, and reducing them to such distress that they were compelled to surrender at discretion. Radagaisus was put to death ; and the greater part of his army sold as slaves. Of this fresh tide of migrating barbarians, the portion which turned towards Gaul was more successful. They devastated the whole of that country, crossed the Pyrenees, and formed a settlement in Andalusia.</p><p>Stilicho was now suspected of a secret intercourse with Alaric, whom he had several times defeated, but always suffered to escape. A correspondence certainly existed between them ; and Stilicho even attempted to persuade Honorius to frame a treaty with Alaric, and to give him the province of Illyricum. In the midst of these political intrigues, Olympius found means to gain the confidence of Honorius, and procured the murder of the brave and able Stilicho, the deliverer of Italy. As if to prove the infatuation of guilt, Olympius next procured the murder of the wives and children of tlle barbarians throughout Italy, which, instead of weakening their power, strengthened it by the just resentment which so atrocious a deed awoke in their fierce, yet human bosoms. They immediately invited Alaric to head them in avenging the slaughter of their families ; and thus about thirty thousand brave and disciplined men were by one bloody and treacherous deed converted from auxiliaries into the most implacable foes, while the death of Stilicho encouraged Alaric to invade a country no longer defended by that renowned warrior, before whom his own martial genius had stood rebuked.</p><p>Delighted to see his great scheme so nearly within his reach, Alaric once more entered Italy and marched directly against Rome.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> By a skilful arrangement of his forces, he cut off all supplies, and the devoted city was soon subjected to the aggravated horrors of war, famine, and pestilence. Safe in his retreat at Ravenna, the emperor made no effort to save his capital ; and after suffering the most dreadful miseries, the senate purchased a cessation of hostilities and the retreat of the besieging army, by the payment of an enormous ransom. Alaric withdrew to Tuscany, and waited the ratification of this treaty by the emperor, being unwilling to come to extremities, under the hope of yet obtaining such an alliance with Honorius as should raise him to the command of the armies of the whole western empire, which he might govern in the name of thc emperor, as Stilicho had done. Honorius refused to ratify the treaty ; and Alaric once more invested Rome. In this second siege Alaric took measures to secure a more speedy triumph. He seized upon the harbour of Ostia, which contained the granaries for supplying the city ; and the Romans were compelled at once to capitulate. Still the conqueror modified his triumph, contenting himself with raising Attalus, præfect of the city, to the empire. Notwithstanding this virtual dethronement of Honorius, Alaric continued to negotiate with that feeble monarch, whose name bore a higher dignity than that of Attalus. Having again failed to obtain his wishes, he deposed Attalus, and marched against Rome, resolved no longer to control the strong impulse which had long urged him to the sack of Rome. The barbarian army once more approached the walls. During the darkness of night the Gothic slaves within the city seized one of the gates, and threw it open to their countrymen, setting fire to some adjacent houses to light their entrance and to begin the work of devastation, spoil, and carnage. For six successive days of horror the Goths were allowed to glut their furious appetites in the sack of the prostrate queen of the world, restrained only by their own respect for the churches, where numbers of tlle trembling inhabitants found a sanctuary.</p><p>It was not the intention of Alaric to destroy Rome, but rather tomake himself itssovereign. After he had attempted this by policy and intrigue, he accomplished it by force. His ambition now expanded with his success ; and he resolved to subjugate all Italy, pass into Sicily and add it to his conquest, thence into Africa, and annex it to his dominions, and thus to make himself the sovereign of the whole western empire. But while on his march through southern Italy for the accomplishment of these vast designs, he was suddenly smitten with a mortal malady, and died near Consentia. Before his death he gave orders that he should be interred in the channel of the small river Buscntinus. The river was turned aside by the labour of captives, the royal sepulchre dug in the vacant bed, the body, richly adorned with the spoils and trophies of Rome, was deposited, the waters were restored to their channel, and the prisoners who had executed the work were murdered, that it might not be known where he lay, and that the hand of man might never insult the ashes, and the foot of man never tread upon the grave, of Alaric the Goth, the conqueror of Rome.</p><p>After the death of Alaric, the command of the Gothic army devolved upon his brother Adolph, who, though not destitute of talents, possessed neither the tierce passions nor the high ambition of Alaric. He concluded a peace with Honorius, consenting to quit Italy upon condition of the princess Flacidia being given to him in marriage. This being done, he acted as a Roman general, led his forces into Gaul, and reconquered that country for the emperor. Thence he passed into Spain, and began a fierce war against the other barbarian nations by whom that country had been invaded ; but was murdered in the midst of his victorious career. His successor Wallia continued the war with equal vigour and success, till he subdued nearly all Spain, and founded the Gothic monarchy. Placidia was sent back to her brother Honorius, on the remonstrances of the emperor’s victorious general Constantius, at the head of a powerful army ; and she «’as afterwards given in marriage to the brave leader by whom she was thus recovered.</p><p>Constantius did not long enjoy his dignity ; and upon his death Placidia sought a retreat in the court of Theodosius, taking with her to Constantinople her two infant children Valentinian and Honoria. Within a few months after this event, which renewed the intercourse between the imperial families of the East and of the West, the emperor Honorius died of dropsy. The throne was immediately siezed by John, the Primicerius, or principal secretary of the late emperor. Thedosius II. who had succeeded his father Arcadius in the empire of the East, prepared to place his cousin on the throne of Rome. The eastern army took Aquileia, and obtaining possession of Ravenna, where the usurper then was, put him to death, and secured the Italian crown. After some little delay, the son of Honorius, an infant only six years old, was raised to the throne, by the name and title of Valentinian III., emperor of the West; the administration of affairs being conducted by his mother Placidia. It is worthy of remark, that both divisions of the Roman empire</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The state of Rome at that eventful period cannot be better described than in the language of Gibbon. “ It had attracted the vices of the universe, and the manners of the most opposite nations. The intemperance of the Gauls, the cunning and levity of the Greeks, the savage obstinacy of the Egyptians and Jews, the servile temper of the Asiatics, and the dissolute, effeminate prostitution of the Syrians, were mingled in the various multitude ; which, under the proud and false denomination of Romans, presumed to despise their fellow-subjects, and even their sovereigns, who dwelt bevond the urecincts of the<hi rend="smallcaps">Eteknal City.”</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>