<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>wife,” is generally acknowledged to be a most beautiful sepulchral monument.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> It consists of a round tower formed of immense blocks of Tiburtine stone fixed together without cement, and adorned with a Doric marble frieze finely sculptured. This beautiful tower was at one time turned into a fortress by the family of the Gætani. In tlle sepulchral vault was found the beautiful marble sarcophagus ofCecilia Metella, now in the Palazzo Farnese. Near the Porta San Paolo, in the “ Prati del Popolo Romano,” (“ the meadows of the Roman people,”) stands the grey pyramid of Caius Cestius. It rises about a hundred and twenty feet in height, and is entirely built of marble. Its form is graceful, and its appearance very picturesque. The “ Prati del Romano” are planted round with mulberry trees, and now form the burial place of foreigners, excluded by their religion from tlle other cemeteries. By far the greater part of the strangers interred here are English.</p><p>The extensive catacombs found about Rome owe their origin to the large excavations which were made by the Romans for obtaining pozzolano, an immense quantity of which they used, and exported for sand and mortar, and other purposes. These subterraneous labyrinths branch out many miles in various directions. Those under the church of St. Sébastian alone are said to have been explored to the extent of above fifteen miles. Those dreary regions afforded shelter to the first Christians during the dreadful persecutions which they suffered under the emperors. They were also used as sepulchres, but all the bones which they once contained have bcεn carried off as precious relics. The chambers are all square, with arched recesses, and rectangular gaps, both in the walls and flooring, to receive coffins.</p><p>It has been said that perhaps no city in the world abounds with such numbers of churches as Rome, or with fewer handsome ones as respects their architecture. Many of the old churches of Rome are still called basilica,@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> but that title properly belongs to the following seven, St. Peter’s, St. John Lateran’s, Santa Maria Maggiore’s, S. Paolo<hi rend="italic">fuori le muro, </hi>Sante Croce in Gierusalemme, S. Sebastiano, and S. Lorenzo <hi rend="italic">fuori le muro.</hi>  St. Peter’s is the finest church in the world, excelling all others, not only in magnitude but in beauty. It was projected by Pope Nicholas V. in the middle of the fifteenth century ; it was not, however, till the pontificate of Julius II. in 1506, that the first stone ofthe edifice was laid, and the whole building was not finished till the year 1621, during the pontificate of Paul V. No fewer than twenty-four popes, counting from Nicholas V., assisted in the erection of this magnificent structure. It is said to cover twenty acres, and to have cost many millions sterling. It is entirely built of Travertine stone, which looks as bright and fresh as if newly finished. The length of the building is 609 feet, and of the transept 500 feet, the height of the dome is 440 feet, the height of the nave 154, and its breadth 90 feet. The plan of the building was frequently changed. The original architect was Bræmante, but the greater part was from the design of Michael Angelo, which, however, has</p><lb/><p>unfortunately been marred by Paul V. and Carlo Moderni, justly stigmatized as “ a wretched plasterer from Como, who broke the sacred unity of the master-idea, and whom we must execrate for the Latin cross, the aisles, the attic, and the front.”@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> From the front of the church on either side, a grand semicircular colonnade, composed of four rows of columns, sweeps round and encloses the immense circular area, in the centre of which stands a noble Egyptian obelisk of red granite, between two most beautiful fountains. The general effect is greatly injured by the Vatican Palace, which is built on one side of St. Peter’s, overlooking the top of the colonnade, and destroying its uniformity. A covered portico extends along the whole breadth of the building, vaulted with gilt stuccos, and paved with various marbles. It lengthens on the eye by a grand succession of doors, niches, statues, and fountains, till the perspective terminates with the equestrian statue of Charlemagne. The nave is infinitely grand and sublime, and is impannelled with the rarest and richest marbles, and adorned with every art of sculpture and of taste.</p><p>The splendid canopy of the great altar, and the wreathed columns which support it, were formed out of the bronze taken from the Pantheon by Urban VIII. A double marble staircase leads down to the confessional or tomb of St. Peter, illuminated by more than a hundred never-dying lamps. His sepulchre is surrounded by a circular vault, which is lined with the tombs of popes, saints, emperors, and deposed or abdicated princes, among whom are the last of the Stuart family, the emperor Otho, &amp;c.</p><p>The stupendous dome, viewed in its design, its altitude, or even its decoration, is altogether unrivalled, and has justly been pronounced the triumph of modern architecture. A broad paved road leads up to the top of the church, and from thence the dome may be ascended by a succession of ingeniously contrived staircases. From the top an extensive prospect may be obtained of the beautiful amphitheatre of hills which encloses the Campagna. The summits of the loftier Apennines behind, wτeathed with snow ; the Tiber in its sinuous windings through the waste ; in the distance the blue waters of thc Mediterranean gleaming in the sunbeams; and, far beneath, Rome, with her churches, her palaces, her dark and distant ruins, the rich verdure, and golden fruit of the orange gardens of her convents, contrasting with the deep shade of their mournful cypresses.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi></p><p>The church or basilica of St. John Lateran was built by Constantine, and during many ages before the erection of St. Peter’s church, was regarded as the mother of churches, and head of the Christian world. It derived its name from Plautius Lateranus, the leader of the first and unsuccessful conspiracy against Nero.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> This church has been frequently rebuilt, enlarged, and improved, and the old architecture now lies completely concealed in the modern. It is a very large but by no means handsome building, and its architecture is deformed by many glaring defects.</p><p>The old basilica of St. Paul, founded by Constantine, and rebuilt by Honorius, contained a hundred and twenty pillars</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> There is a stem round tower of other days,</p><p>Firm as a fortress with its fence of stone.</p><p>Such as an enemy’s baffled strength delays,</p><p>Standing with half its battlements alone,</p><p>And with two thousand years of ivy grown,—</p><p>Tbe garland of eternity, where waves The green leaves over all by time o'erthrown.</p><p>What was this tower of strength ? Within its cave What treasure lay so lock'd, so hid ? A woman's grave.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Childe Hanld, c.</hi>  iv. st. 100.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> “ A<hi rend="italic">basilica</hi>  seems at first to have been part of a palace. It is sometimes represented as a simple portico. It then included the buildings which were afterwards annexed. Some of these buildings which had served as <hi rend="italic">basilica</hi>  for law and trade, became places of worship to the primitive Christians, and the first churches that were erected expressly for that worship, erected perhaps on the site of some ancient basilics, retained the same name."—<hi rend="italic">FοrsyΛ's Italy,</hi>  p. 87.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> Ibid. p. 195.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Rome in 19th Century, vol. ii. p. 277.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> Tacit. Ann. 15. Juvenal. Sat.x. 17.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>