<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>wished to blot, and his characters and his incidents are all calculated to call forth only the better feelings of our nature. <hi rend="italic">Virginibus puerisque</hi>  might have been his appropriate and uncontested motto.</p><p>The great novelists to whom we have alluded, and particularly Fielding, Smollett, and Sterne, had of course many imitators. But the minuteness of Richardson was found to be intolerable in any hands but his own, and his manner in this country at least, though not in France and Germany, was soon abandoned. Amongst the numerous imitations of Fielding's manner, most of which are now forgotten, the <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi>  of Cumberland (1752—1811), is probably the most respectable. Cumberland possessed that degree of talent which enabled him, both in dramatic composition, and in the novel, to produce performances which are read with pleasure, though they seldom rouse our interest, and never impress us with the idea of a creative genius. Accordingly, both his <hi rend="italic">Arundel</hi>  and his <hi rend="italic">Henry</hi>  have enjoyed a fair measure of popularity, particularly the latter, in which a story of tolerable interest is made the vehicle of displaying considerable acquaintance with English life in the lower ranks, derived from Cumberland's familiarity with such scenes in his early residence in Kent,—while the homeliness of these pictures is relieved by many rural landscapes perfectly English. The tale has the fault of <hi rend="italic">Pamela,</hi>  that aims at teaching virtue through scenes that border very closely on vice ; while, as Sir Walter Scott remarks, Cumberland reverses the usual process of courtship, and “ throws upon the softer sex the task of wooing, which is more gracefully as well as naturally the province of the man.” The characters’have little novelty; Cumberland was indebted for them to <hi rend="italic">Joseph Andrews,</hi>  and he took the idea of his plan and style from <hi rend="italic">Tam Jones.</hi>  Henry is another version of Joseph himself, which Cumberland somehow seems not to have perceived to be a caricature created in the mere spirit of parody; but the portrait of an amiable, enthusiastic, and yet absurd Methodist parson in <hi rend="italic">Ezekiel Daw,</hi>  has an air of originality, even when placed beside that of Parson Adams, by which it was obviously, suggested.</p><p>The imitations of Smollett’s manner were not numerous, and, with one exception, totally without mcrit. We allude to <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of a Guinea,</hi>  by Charles Johnstone, which appeared in 1761, in which a series of scenes and personages in different walks of life are brought before us through the somewhat inartificial method of making a coin, which shifts through the hands of successive proprietors, the historian of their follies and their vices ; a contrivance very inferior indeed to the ingenious machinery by which Asmo-deus unveils to Don Cleofas the secrets of-Spanish life. In <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of α Guinea,</hi>  the author seems to have had before him both Le Sage and Smollett as models ; but in the result he exhibits little of the gay good-humoured touch of the Frenchman, and nothing of the cordial merriment of the Scotchman. Where Le Sage painted follies, and Smollett frolics and absurdities, Johnstone, on whom some have conferred the high title of a prose Juvenal, delineated with a sarcastic and energetic brevity, the darkest vices and crimes of an age in which both political and domestic profligacy prevailed, and were paraded abroad with no ordinary degree of assurance. “ In Johnstone’s time,” says Sir Walter Scott, “ the reform which was introduced by the private virtues and patriotism of George III. had not commenced ; and he might well have said, with such an ardent temper as he seems to have possessed, ‘ Difficile est satyram non scribere.' He has accordingly indulged his wit to the utmost, and as most of his characters were living persons, then easily recognised, he held the mirror to nature even when it reflects such horrible features. His language is firm and energetic ; his power of personifying character striking and forcible, and the personages of his narrative move, breathe, and speak in all the freshness of life.” This is ldgh, and indeed we think, with deference, exaggerated praise. Who remembers or can name a single character which Johnstone has drawn, except perhaps his forcible but odious caricature of Whitefield ? What scene of real interest or passion has he painted in such a manner as to give it a home in our memories, like the better scenes of Fielding or Le Sage ? Not one : and indeed, bad as the age which he painted was, we believe he has greatly exaggerated its vices, or at least his one-sided views have led him to keep out of sight its redeeming points and countervailing virtues. Hence the impression the book leaves on the mind is one of oppression. It leads us along all the gloomy, and foul, and noisome passages of life, and we escape from it with the feeling of relief with which we would emerge from a vault in which the air was loaded with noxious vapour.</p><p>Sterne is perhaps the only one of our great novelists who has found an imitator of genius, in Mackenzie (1745-1831) ; for although in his <hi rend="italic">Man of the World,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Julia de Rou-bigne,</hi>  Mackenzie has deviated from the manner of Sterne, and formed a composite manner, in which the characteristics of several writers are blended with his own, yet there can be little doubt that the spirit of Sterne, in his pathetic passages, in a great measure inspired <hi rend="italic">The Man of Feeling,</hi>  and prompted that “ illustration of the richer and finer sensibilities of the human breast,” which Sir Walter Scott points out as the “ key-note” on which he formed his tales of fictitious woe. In some obvious respects, no doubt, Mackenzie improved upon his model ; as in rejecting the licem tiousness of Sterne’s wit, retrenching his episodical digressions, his numerous impertinencies, and intrusive buffoonery, and keeping the strain of feeling which he wishes to create more unbroken ; but as writers of genius, there surely can be no comparison between them. Mackenzie has none of those charming touches which hover with such a fine ambiguity between the pathetic and the humorous,— like Toby’s opening the window, and liberating the fly which had been buzzing about him all day,—and which operate, like spells, upon the heart. We fear, then, that the spirit of nationality, and the bias of private friendship, has led Sir Walter Scott somewhat to exaggerate the claims of Mackenzie, who, if he has less affectation in mere manner and style, seems to us to have more affectation of feeling than the author of <hi rend="italic">Tristram Shandy.</hi>  In fact, Mackenzie betrays in some passages of his novels a tendency towards that unhealthy sentimentalism which was afterwards carried to such a sickly excess by inferior imitators of Sterne. Such is certainly the case in what is commonly considered the most powerful, though, we think, the least pleasing of his works, <hi rend="italic">Julia de Roubigne. </hi>No doubt, if the chief aim of fiction were “ to send the hearers weeping to their beds,” Mackenzie might claim the merit of having attained it. But though the distresses of the story may be in themselves naturally pourtrayed, the constant monotony of melancholy which it presents to us is not so ; it is morbid and out of nature, and the feeling with which it is perused, which is that of exhaustion and uneasiness, shews that the writer has missed the great aim of fiction, which is to make even suffering minister to a soothing feeling of sympathy, and to leave upon the mind at the close a sentiment of consolation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Thc Man of the World</hi>  is exposed in some respects to the same objection. The suffering, the accumulation of misfortunes which are heaped upon the innocent Annes-leys, through the heartless villainy of Sindall, are too unmitigated. The story wants repose, relief, and sunshine. It is like an avenue of cypresses terminating in a tomb. <hi rend="italic">The Man of Feeling,</hi>  the first of Mackenzie’s productions, is, after all, the best. It is more unlaboured than the others, has more of the first freshness of the author’s mind about it ; and its brief manner, and quicker succession of situations,—for they can hardly be called incidents, relieve it from</p></body></text></TEI>