<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>purpose of binding it ; <hi rend="italic">for good stone, well broken, will always combine by its own roughness into a solid substance, </hi>with a smooth surface, that will not be affected by the vicissitudes of weather, or disfigured by the action of wheels, which, as they pass over it without a jolt, will consequently be incapable of doing it any considerable injury.</p><p>The experience of the year 1820 strongly confirmed the inutility and inconvenience of employing chalk with the stone. In January, when a hard frost was succeeded by a sudden thaw, a great number of roads broke up, and the wheels of the carriages penetrated into the original soil ; in particular, it was observed that all the roads of which chalk was a component part became nearly impassable ; and even roads made over chalky soils gave way in most places. But not one of the roads that had been thoroughly made after these directions was observed to give way. (P. 44—46.)</p><p>The tools required for lifting roads are, 1. Strong <hi rend="italic">picks, </hi>but short from the handle to the point ; 2. small <hi rend="italic">hammers, </hi>weighing about a pound, with a face the size of a shilling, well steeled, and with a short handle ; 3. <hi rend="italic">rakes,</hi>  with wooden heads, ten inches in length, and with iron teeth about two and a half inches long, and very strong, for raking out the large stones when the road is broken up, and tor keeping it smooth after it has been finished, and while it is consolidating ; 4. very light broad-mouthed <hi rend="italic">shovels,</hi>  to spread the broken stones, and to form the road.</p><p>The whole expense of lifting and newly forming a rough road, to the depth of four inches, has generally been from a penny to twopence per square yard, being more or less according to the quantity of stone to be broken. With proper tools, and by proper arrangements, stone may be broken for tenpence or a shilling per ton, including, in some cases, the value of the stone itself. A very material advantage of Mr Macadam’s method is the introduction of a much greater proportion of human labour, instead of the work of horses ; formerly one fourth of the whole expense was paid, in the district of Bristol, for men’s labour, and three fourths for that of horses ; now, on the contrary, one fourth only is paid for horses’ labour, and the other three to men, women, and children.</p><p>Mr Macadam argues very strongly against the old opinion of the necessity of placing a quantity of large stones as a foundation, to carry the road over a wet subsoil. He says, that whatever be the nature of the soil, if it be previously “ made quite dry,” and a covering impenetrable to rain placed over it, the thickness of the covering needs only to depend on its own capability of becoming impervious. Large stones, he says, will constantly work up by the agitation of the traffic on the road, and leave vacuities for the reception of water ; and the only way of keeping the stones in their places is to have them of a uniform size. A rocky bottom causes a road to wear out much the faster [acting, probably, as a lower millstone in facilitating the operation of grinding]. “ It is a known fact, that a road lasts much longer over a morass than when made over rock. In the neighbourhood of Bridgewater, for example, the materials consumed on a rocky road, when compared with those which are required for a similar road made over the naked surface of the soil, are in the proportion of seven to five.”</p><p>In the summer of 1819, upon some new roads made in Scotland, more than three feet of materials, of various dimensions, were laid down ; and more than two thirds of them, according to our author, were worse than wasted. In such an arrangement, the water generally penetrates to the bottom of the trench made to receive the road, and remains there to do mischief upon every change of weather.</p><p>To prevent such inconveniences, it is necessary, in wet soils, either to make drains to lower ground, or to raise the road above the general level, instead of making a trench to receive the stones ; and from the penetration of rain the solidity of the road itself must protect it. A well-made</p><lb/><p>road, not quite four inches in thickness, was found to have kept the earth below it dry in the parish of Ashton near Bristol but six, eight, or ten inches of materials are gcne-rally required to make a firm road ; being laid on in successive layers of about two inches in thickness, all well broken, well cleaned, and well sized. Sometimes, indeed, a much greater depth of stone than this is required : in a road, for example, which was made from Lewes to East Bourn, entirely upon Mr Macadam’s principles, as much as three feet of materials were required in many parts before the road could be sufficiently consolidated ; it was, however, ultimately made excellent, though at an expense of not much less than a thousand pounds a mile.</p><p>Mr Macadam maintains that the quantity of stone required for paving is fully sufficient to make an excellent gravel road in any part of the world ; and in almost every case, materials equally good can be obtained for roads at a still cheaper rate ; commonly, indeed, at one tenth of the expense of pavements. It is, however, in steep ascents that pavements are most objectionable ; at the north end of Blackfriars Bridge, more horses are said to fall and receive injury than at any other place in the kingdom. In the suburbs of Bristol the pavements have lately been converted into roads with great success. It is probable that neither the inhabitants of these suburbs nor their housemaids were much consulted on the occasion, although justice seems to require that the pedestrian order should not be altogether sacrificed to the equestrian without their consent ; but, in fact, the inhabitants of these <hi rend="italic">ci-devant</hi>  streets are said to be well satisfied with the change ; and we seem in danger, from the opposition of contending theories, of having all the streets of our cities dug up, and many of our country roads, on the other hand, encumbered with pavements. Mr Macadam received a new encouragement from parliament to the amount of L.4000.</p><p>We find some further confirmations and illustrations of Mr Macadam’s principles and precepts in the Report of the former Committee of the House of Commons, as reprinted in his Remarks.</p><p>This gentleman, it seems, arrived from America in the year 1783, at the time when many new roads were making in Scotland (p. 97) ; he was then appointed a commissioner of the roads, and studied the subject in that capacity there ; he afterwards resided chiefly in Bristol, and was induced to take charge of the roads of that district as a surveyor in 1816, because it was only in that situation that he could carry his principles into practice, and make the necessary experiments for establishing them. He observed in his travels, that the mixture of clay and chalk with the materials of roads was the almost universal cause of their failure ; and he convinced himself that, by a proper application of materials, a good road might be made in every country. His improvements have been very generally adopted in the west and the south of England, and principally under his own direction or under that of his family. They had superintended more than 300 miles of road, and twice as many more had been improved by their advice and influence. Sober, active, and well-informed sub-surveyors he considers as the most important of all materials for a good road ; and among the extrinsic arrangements which are often required, he thinks the union of different trusts into a single one the most likely to be generally beneficial.</p><p>The operation of washing gravel Mr Macadam has not found eligible, because it is more expensive than screening or sifting, and less effectual ; for about London the common gravel is not capable of being cleaned by any ordinary washing, though the Thames gravel, where it can be procured, is generally clean and serviceable. Coarse gravel broken, he says, is preferable to fine, as it consolidates more perfectly into a single mass. The old practice of putting a heap of unprepared gravel aioDg the middle of the road, and</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>