<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>written out, and exhibited in a conspicuous place where all might read them. Various amendments were proposed, and the ten tables again laid before the senate, the curiæ, and the centuries, and having received the sanction of both orders of the state, were received and recognized as the very fountain of all laws, public and private, to use the expression of Livy. Nothing but fragments of these laws, afterwards known by the name of the Laws of the Twelve Tables, have been preserved to us ; and even of these fragments, we cannot refer to more than those which relate to constitutional law, the origin and course of which we have been attempting to state and trace.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>Of these the most important which remain are the following. 1. That there should be an appeal to the people from the sentence of every magistrate. 2. That all capital trials should be conducted before the comitia centuriata. 3. That <hi rend="italic">privilegia,</hi>  or acts of pains and penalties against an individual, should be unlawful. 4. That the last decision of the people should supersede all former decisions on the same subject. 5. That the debtor whose person and property were pledged to his creditor, <hi rend="italic">nexus,</hi>  and he who remained the free master of both, <hi rend="italic">solutus,</hi>  should be equal in the sight of the law. 6. A sixth enactment, which unfortunately left matter for a grievance, and for future contentions, ordained, that there should be no legal marriages between the patricians and the plebeians ; and that, if a patrician married the daughter of a plebeian, his children should follow the condition of their mother, should not be subject to the paternal law like his legitimate children, and should not inherit his property if he died intestate.</p><p>By these laws the privileges and rights of the commons had, in certain points, been greatly promoted, and in many others secured on the firm basis of national laws. But not only were subjects of great importance left unsettled on any equal foundation ; these very laws, and the liberties of the entire community, were destined to encounter another peril of a formidable nature. The decemvirs had conducted matters so much to the satisfaction of the community, that when, at the expiration of their year, they requested a renewal of their office, on the ground that they had still two more tables to form, in order to complete their task, they were permitted to resume their powers without opposition. Appius Claudius, an old enemy of the commons, was one of the decemvirs, and was retained among them on their re-appointment. The possession of uncontrolled, irresponsible power, now began to display its usual consequences. The decemviri seemed resolved to change the government of Rome into a complete oligarchy, consisting of a council of ten, whose power should be absolutely supreme in every thing. They arrogated the right of superseding all other magistracies ; and at the conclusion of their second year they shewed no intention of resigning their offices, or of appointing their successors. Popular liberty seemed on the point of being finally overthrown, just when its establishment on a secure basis had been fondly anticipated.</p><p>Matters had nearly arrived at a crisis when a war arose, the Sabines and Æqui having united their forces, and being desirous to avail themselves of the contentions by which Rome was weakened. The combined forces ravaged the left bank of the Tiber, and the Æqui encamped on Algidus and pillaged the country around Tusculum. The decemvirs assembled the senate, obtained their authority to raise an army, at the head of which they placed three of their number, and sent it against the Sabines. Another was raised and sent against the Æqui, while Appius Claudius remained at Rome to provide for the safety of the city, and for the maintenance of the power of the decemvirs. Both armies suffered themselves to be defeated, and retired nearer to the city, dissatisfied rather than discomfited.</p><p>Meanwhile Appius chanced to see a beautiful maiden named Virginia, daughter of Lucius Virginius, a centurion in the army sent against the Æqui. The maiden had been betrothed to L. Icilius, one of the tribunes, and the author of the law known by his name. Her beauty inflamed the passions of the licentious Appius, and he caused one of his clients, M. Claudius, to seize her as his slave, intending, in this manner, to get the person of the damsel within his power. Intelligence was immediately sent to the camp to Virginius, who, obtaining leave of absence, hastened to Rome to protect his daughter. But in vain did he claim his daughter, in vain appeal to the sympathy of the people, in vain address himself to the better mind of Appius. The decemvir, blind to every thing but the beauty of Virginia, and deaf to all but the impulse of his own passion, passed sentence assigning the maiden to Claudius. Upon this Virginius, snatching up a butcher’s knife, exclaimed, “This is the only way left, my child, to keep thee free and unstained !” and plunged it to her heart ; then turning to Appius, he cried, “ On thee, and on thy head, be the curse of this innocent blood !” Appius ordered him to be seized, but in vain. Waving aloft the bloody knife, he burst through the multitude, flew to the gates, mounted a horse, and spurred headlong to the camp near Tusculum.</p><p>The wild and frantic aspect of Virginius, his attire stained with blood, and the bloody knife still held convulsively in his grasp, instantly drew a crowd of the soldiery around him. In brief but burning terms he told his tale, and called aloud for vengeance. One thrilling sentiment of sympathetic indignation filled every bosom ; they called to arms, plucked up their standards, and marching to Rome, seized on the Aventine. The army near Fidenæ caught a similar spirit, having received information of the bloody tragedy from Icilius. They likewise threw off the authority of their commanders, chose military tribunes to lead them, and hastening to Rome, joined their brethren on the Aventine Hill.</p><p>In the city all was tumult and terror. The decemvirs were unable to make head against the excited multitude, and the senate itself felt its power ineffectual to allay the tempest. They began to treat with the people and the army, yet with dilatoriness, hoping the ferment would abate, and they might still retain their power. But the people were in earnest. Leaving a strong body to defend the Aventine for the present, they marched in military array through the city, and once more posted themselves on the sacred mount <hi rend="italic">(Morts Sewer,)</hi>  followed by vast numbers of the plebeian party, men, women, and children. Then were the patricians compelled to yield, and the decemvirs resigned. The plebeians obtained also the restoration of the tribuneship and of the right of appeal, with a full indemnity for the authors of the sécession. The commons then returned to Rome, and re-occupied the Aventine; but along with it the Capitol also, as security that the terms of peace would be duly kept. The decemvirate was finally abolished, and the consulship restored ; with this additional provision, that whereas formerly one had been appointed by the patrician curiæ, both were now chosen in the centuries.</p><p>The new consuls were L. Valerius and M. Horatius, men who had shewn themselves to be favourable to the people. They wisely endeavoured to unite tlle two orders of the state on terms of perfect equality. A law proposed and passed by Valerius, formally acknowledged the commons of Rome to be the Roman people ; a plebiscitum, or decree of the commons, was to be binding on the whole people ; <hi rend="italic">quod tri-butim plel)esjussisset,populum teneret.</hi>@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  Such a popular decree, however, would not have passed into effect without the sanction of the senate, and of the curiæ ; but it was a mighty stride in advance towards the obtaining of a recognized and legal equality between the two great orders of the state.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  For an admirable view of these laws, see Arnold, vol. i. p. 253,<hi rend="italic">el seq<hi rend="sub">i</hi></hi></p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  Livy, iii. 55.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>