<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>cussion is therefore the point at which, if an obstacle were opposed sufficient to resist tlle rotation of the system, no motion would be communicated to the axis ; or, which is the same thing, if the axis were not fixed, the system would acquire from the shock no tendency to turn, the effect being the same as if the whole rotatory effort had been accumulated at that point.</p><p>Let HKL (fig. 8) be a section of the body perpendicular to the axis, and containing the centre of gravity G. Let O be the axis, and in the line OG take OP = <hi rend="italic">h = fridm</hi>  +- M∙OG, then P is the centre of percussion, and a force applied at P, in the plane HKL, and in the direction perpendicular to OP, will produce the same initial velocity of the centre of gravity G as if the body were free ; for as the force exerts no pressure on the axis or points of support, the initial velocity will be the same as if they were not there.</p><p>35.    The distance of the centre of percussion from the axis is always greater than the distance of the centre of gravity from the axis ; for the moment of inertia in respect of the axis passing through O being <hi rend="italic">fridm,</hi>  by (17) the moment of inertia in respect of the parallel axis passing through G is/<hi rend="italic">ridm —</hi>  M∙OG<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  ; therefore, since the moment of inertia is necessarily positive,<hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  M∙OG<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. But by the definition<hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  = M∙OG∙OP, therefore M∙OG∙GP tx. M∙OG<hi rend="sup">a</hi>, or OP OG.</p><p>36.    The property of the centre of percussion, that a force applied there produces no strain on the axis, may be rendered sensible by a simple experiment. If a straight line, or rod of uniform thickness, be suspended from one extremity, the centre of percussion is at the distance of two thirds of its length from the axis ; for the centre of gravity being at the middle of the line, OG = ½, so that if we call its mass M = 1, the formula OP = ∕r<hi rend="sup">2</hi>dm+-M∙OG becomes OP <hi rend="italic">= 2fridx,</hi>  which, on taking the integral from <hi rend="italic">x =</hi>  0 to <hi rend="italic">χ = l, </hi>gives GP = 'j∕∙ Now if the rod be held in the hand, and we give it a motion round the joint of the wrist only, and strike smartly against an obstacle with a point considerably nearer or more remote than two thirds of its length, we feel a painful shock or wrench in the hand ; but if we strike with that point which is exactly at two thirds of its length, we feel no such disagreeable strain.</p><p>37.    It is sometimes said that the point P, considered as the centre of percussion, is that with which the most violent blow is struck. But this is by no means true. P is that point of a body turning round O which gives a blow precisely equal to the progressive motion of thc body, and in the same direction. As we have already said, it is the point where we may suppose the whole rotatory momentum of the body accumulated. Every particle of the body is moving in a particular direction, with a velocity proportional to its distance from the axis of rotation ; and if the body were stopped in any point, each particle tending to continue its motion endeavours to drag the rest along with it. Whatever point we call the centre of percussion should have this property, that when it is stopped by a sufficient force, the whole motion and tendency to motion of every kind should be stopped ; so that if at that instant the supports of tlle axis were annihilated, the body would remain in absolute rest.</p><p>38.    The expressions in (29) for the stress on the axis have reference only to the initial movement of the body, and the forces which they represent are soon destroyed by the resistance of the axis. But when a body is in permanent rotation about a fixed axis, there is a strain exerted on the axis which depends only upon the centrifugal force of rotation, and which therefore continues as long as the rotation continues. This constant pressure is determined as follows : Since <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  is the angular velocity, and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  the distance</p><p>of a particle <hi rend="italic">dm</hi>  from the axis, the velocity of the particle <hi rend="italic">= rw;</hi>  and, by mechanics, the centrifugal force of a body moving in a circle is proportional to the square of the velocity divided by the radius ; therefore the centrifugal force of the particle <hi rend="italic">dm,</hi>  in the direction of the radius <hi rend="italic">r,</hi>  is <hi rend="italic">w<hi rend="sup">i</hi>rdrn. </hi>The resolved parts of this force in the directions OX and O Y (fig. 7) are <hi rend="italic">w<hi rend="sup">1</hi>xdm</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">uriydm ;</hi>  therefore, denoting the pressures in those directions on the pivot S by <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">q, </hi>and those on the pivot T by <hi rend="italic">p'</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">q',</hi>  we shall have, as in (29), the following equations (in which x<hi rend="sub">1</hi>  and<hi rend="italic">y<hi rend="sub">λ</hi></hi>  are the co-ordinates of the centre of gravity, and <hi rend="italic">h, h'</hi>  the distances of the pivots S and T respectively from O) to determine <hi rend="italic">p, p∕, q, f,</hi>  viz.</p><p><hi rend="italic">p + pf = wfxdm</hi>  = u&gt;<hi rend="sup">,</hi>Mx<hi rend="sub">1</hi>,<hi rend="italic">q + ∕ = wfydm</hi>  = w<hi rend="sup">s</hi>My<hi rend="sub">1</hi>,<hi rend="italic">ph + pfh' = wfxzdm, qh</hi>  + y'A' = <hi rend="italic">wfyzdm.</hi></p><p>If we suppose OZ to be one of the three principal axes passing through O, then <hi rend="italic">(22) fxzdm</hi>  = 0 and <hi rend="italic">fyzdm —</hi>  0 ; whence <hi rend="italic">pk + pfhf</hi>  = 0, ∣y∕&lt; + <hi rend="italic">tfhf</hi>  = 0. If, therefore, we further suppose <hi rend="italic">k</hi>  = 0, or that the origin of the co-ordinates is placed at S, we shall also have <hi rend="italic">p∕</hi>  = 0, <hi rend="italic">ff</hi>  = 0, whence the pivot T sustains no pressure, the whole being exerted on S.</p><p>If OZ, besides being a principal axis, also passes through the centre of gravity, then ι<hi rend="sub">1</hi> =0,<hi rend="italic">y<hi rend="sub">l</hi></hi>  = 0, whence <hi rend="italic">p + F =</hi>  0, <hi rend="italic">q + ff</hi>  = 0 ; and since jo' and <hi rend="italic">ff</hi>  vanish when OZ is a principal axis, therefore <hi rend="italic">p</hi>  = 0, <hi rend="italic">q —</hi>  0, so that no pressure is exerted on either of the pivots ; and if they were removed, the body would still continue to revolve about the same axis.</p><p>The forces thus determined are in some sort the inverse of those arising from the percussions found in (29), the values of <hi rend="italic">p + pf</hi>  being in this case expressed in terms of <hi rend="italic">x, </hi>and in the former in terms of <hi rend="italic">y ;</hi>  and the value of <hi rend="italic">q + ff, </hi>which in the case of the percussions was expressed in terms of .r, is here given in terms of <hi rend="italic">y.</hi></p><p>39.    In computing the effect of machines, it is often convenient to determine the situation of a point in which the whole mass of the machine might be concentrated without altering the rotatory effort. In the straight line OG (fig. 8) suppose a point Qto be taken, such that OQ<hi rend="sup">2</hi> =<hi rend="italic">fridm =</hi>  moment of inertia in respect of the axis O ; then, if the whole matter in the body were collected at Q, a force applied at any point P in the line OG, would produce exactly the same angular velocity as if applied to the same point of the body having its natural form. For if the whole mass M were concentrated at Q, tlle moment of inertia would become M∙OQ<hi rend="sup">,</hi>  (13), and thc moment of the force F applied at P is FOP; therefore the angular velocity (14) would be</p><p>F∙OP</p><p>MOQ** <hi rend="sup">t</hi>'<hi rend="sup">le an</hi>≈<hi rend="sup">u</hi>'<hi rend="sup">ar velθcit</hi>y produced by the force F∙OP</p><p>F applied at P, the body having its natural form, i<hi rend="sup">g</hi>yp<hi rend="sub">i</hi>^~' &gt;</p><p>therefore, since M∙0Q<hi rend="sup">,</hi> =<hi rend="italic">fridm,</hi>  the two expressions are equal, and the angular velocity is not altered hy supposing the whole mass concentrated at Q.</p><p>40.    The point Q is called the <hi rend="italic">centre of gyration</hi>  of the revolving mass; and since OQ = √<hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  +- M, its distance from the axis O is found by extracting the square root of the quotient which is obtained by dividing the moment of inertia by the mass of the body. It is also connected with the centres of gravity and percussion by a simple relation. Suppose P to be the centre of percussion, then (34) OP <hi rend="italic">= fridm</hi>  +∙ M ∙ OG, therefore OG ∙ OP = <hi rend="italic">fridm</hi>  +■ M = OQ<hi rend="sup">s</hi>  ; whence the distance of the centre of gyration from the axis of rotation is a mean proportional between the distances of the centre of gravity and percussion from the axis.</p><p>In a straight line or slender rod, as a working beam, or the spoke of a wheel in a machine, OQ is √¼ of its length ; for in this case <hi rend="italic">fridm = fridr = </hi><hi rend="italic">⅙</hi><hi rend="italic">  ri ;</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  being the whole length, M = <hi rend="italic">r:</hi>  therefore <hi rend="italic">Vf ridm</hi>  -+ M = r <hi rend="italic">V ⅜<hi rend="sup">,</hi></hi></p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>