<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>bility must have fallen into the hands of the combined forces ; but the tumultuous followers of Spartacus, longing for the pillage of the capital, compelled their leader to abandon his intention, and bend his course towards that devoted city. He was met and completely routed by tlle prætor Crassus, who thus acquired some renown in war, in addition to the influence which he possessed from his unequalled wealth. Pompey, on bis return from Spain, encountered and destroyed several scattered bodies of the gladiatorial army ; and thus, with his usual good fortune, obta⅛ed a claim to divide the honour with Crassus. From this period, these two powerful individuals cherished sentiments of envious rivalry against each other, the effect of which proved ruinous to the commonwealth.</p><p>The enormous wealth of Crassus enabled him to purchase the support of the people, by bestowing upon them large donations of money and corn. To counterbalance his influence, Pompey, although attached to thearistocratic party, proposed the repeal of some of Sylla’s laws, and the enactment of others of a more popular character ; in particular, the restoration of the powers and privileges of the tribunes. By these means he so ingratiated himself with the people, that, with powers never before entrusted to any general, he obtained the command of the armament prepared against the pirates by which the seas were so greatly infested. In this war he distinguished himself in a very remarkable manner, by his skill, courage, and activity, and raised himself to a height of power and of military fame, at that time beyond all rivalry.</p><p>During the progress of these events in Spain and Italy, Mithridates had renewed the war in Asia Minor. Lucullus, to whom the command in the Mithridatic war was now given, defeated the fleet of the Pontic king, relieved Cyzicus, and overthrew the combined forces of Mithridates and Tigranes in two great battles, bringing the struggle to the very brink of a successful conclusion. But the mutinous spirit of his own army, and the hostility which he aroused against himself, by his reform of the financial administration of the provinces, occasioned his recall. Pompey was next appointed to tlle command of the armies in Asia ; and thus again was he favoured by fortune to obtain the crowning glory of a victory already all but won. Mithridates finding all his efforts ineffectual, and being in danger of immediate captivity from the defection of his son-in-law, Tigranes, and the treason of his own son, Phraates, killed himself, that he might not fall into the hands of the Romans. After the conclusion of the war, Pompey spent some time in Asia, settling its affairs, and arranging it into different provincial districts. By the fall of Mithridates, and this settlement of Asiatic affairs, the republic may be considered to have reached the highest pitch of her power; but when the summit has been gained, the next step is inevitably downward. The very existence of the republic, as such, now depended, partly upon the caprice or the moderation of Pompey himself, partly upon the judicious or the erroneous measures which Crassus might adopt, in his endeavours to counterbalance the power of his mighty rival.</p><p>Unfortunately for Rome, the two rivals saw no better method of maintaining each his own influence in opposition to that of his antagonist, than by separately or jointly courting popularity. Pompey had led the way in tllis injudicious procedure, by his partial restoration of tne tribunitian power ; and this restoration was completed by the joint influence of him and Crassus during their united consulship. It had been found by ambitious men, that they could not obtain their objects of pursuit, whether those objects were chiefly aristocratic or democratic, without becoming demagogues ; and therefore unhappily it was considered by them necessary to re-establish in all its power an office, of which the very nature pointed it out for such a pernicious abuse.</p><lb/><p>But as extremes in all things meet, these very demagogues necessarily became an oligarchy ; and while they pretended to promote the interests of the people, such men as Pompey and Crassus engrossed the whole powers and emoluments of the state.</p><p>Before this rivalry had reached its crisis, and during the absence of Pompey in Asia, Rome was threatened with a new convulsion, and new competitors for public favour began to appear on the scene. Lucius Sergius Catilina, a young man of noble birth, but of desperate fortunes, and of the most depraved character, formed a conspiracy to destroy the chief men of the state, seize on all public property, restore the Marian faction, and, placing himself at its nead, to invest himself with supreme power. Not only the profligate of the youthful nobility, and the indigent of the populace, joined in this conspiracy, but even Crassus and Julius Csesar were accused ofhaving been so far implicated in it. After several failures and postponements, the conspiracy was partly detected, and partly forced into a premature disclosure by the failure of Cataline in his attempt to obtain the consulship, and the prudent preventive measures of his successful rival, Cicero, who also at that time began to act a distinguished part in public affairs. Not all the daring, nor all the secret attempts of Cataline could overawe, or elude the energy and vigilance of Cicero ; and at length the desperate and baffled conspirator fled from the city, and raised the standard of revolt in Etruria. His associates in Rome were seized and put to death, and he w’as himself defeated and slain in a desperate battle, after having performed deeds of the most determined valour. So highly had Cicero distinguished himself by his detection and suppression of this dangerous conspiracy, that the senate unanimously bestowed upon him the honourable title of <hi rend="italic">Father ofhis Country.</hi></p><p>During the progress, and in the suppression of this conspiracy, several very remarkable men had come prominently forward. These were Cicero, unmatched for eloquence, learning, and philosophical wisdom ; Cato, a true republican of the ancient mould, simple, severely virtuous, and uncompromising ; and Cæsar, unrivalled in the versatility, extent, and power of a genius, equally fitted to attain preeminence in the pursuits of literature, philosophy, politics, and war. The two former adhered to the aristocratic party in the state, who were headed by Pompey ; the latter made the democratic party the basis of his power, although he was himself descended from one of the most ancient and noble families of Rome. He had the address both to extricate himself from the conspiracy of Cataline, and to make himself at the same time the person to whom the survivors of that party looked for protection. From that period it was evident, that whatever might be the destinies of Rome, Cæsar must exercise a potent influence over them, for evil or for good.</p><p>The return of Pompey from Asia caused a renewal of the contest for power between that general and the party which sought to maintain the independence of the senate. Of this party, Cato, Lucullus, and Metellus, were the chief adherents; but their efforts only caused Pompey to throw his influence more into the popular scale, and thus unconsciously to promote the ambitious views of Cæsar. That sagacious man, perceiving the necessity of acquiring both the skill and the renown of a general, and having hitherto in a great measure abstained from military affairs, got himself appointed to the governorship of Lusitania, where he soon acquired a high reputation for warlike talents, and at the same time repaired his dilapidated fortunes.</p><p>During the absence of Cæsar, the contest between Pompey and Crassus continued, each endeavouring to weaken the influence of theother; and the independent party in the senate, led by Cato, and occasionally aided by Cicero, availing themselves of this struggle to diminish the undue power</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>