<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in water ; and we confine ourselves, in this place, to the mere effect which they will produce on the current of the river.</p><p>We gave the name of <hi rend="italic">weir</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">bar</hi>  to a dam erected across a river for the purpose of raising its waters, whether in order to take off a draft for a mill or to deepen the channel. Before we can tell the effect which they will produce, we must have a general rule for ascertaining the relation between the height of the water above the lip of the weir or bar, and the quantity of water which will flow over.</p><p>First, then, with respect to a weir, represented in fig. 20 and fig. 21. The latter figure more resembles their usual</p><lb/><p>form, consisting of a dam of solid masonry, or built of timber, properly fortified with shoars and banks. On the top is set up a strong plank FR, called the wasteboard or waster, over which the water flows. This is brought to an accurate level, of the proper height. Such voiders are frequently made in the side of a mill-course, for letting the superfluous water run off. This is properly the waster, or voider : it is also called an offset. The same observations will explain all these different pieces of practice. The following questions occur in course.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. 1. Given the length of an offset or wasteboard made in the face of a reservoir of stagnant water, and the depth of its lip under the horizontal surface of the water, to determine the discharge, or the quantity of water which will run over, in a second.</hi></p><p>Let A B be the horizontal surface of the still water, and F the lip of the wasteboard. Call the depth BF under the surface <hi rend="italic">h,</hi>  and the length of the wasteboard <hi rend="italic">l.</hi>  The water is supposed to flow over into another basin or channel, so much lower that the surface HL of the water is lower, or at least not higher, than F.</p><p>If the water could be supported at the height BF, BF might be considered as an orifice in the side of a vessel. In this case, the discharge would be the same as if the whole water were flowing witll the velocity acquired from the height ½BF, or ½A. And if we suppose that there is no contraction at the orifice, the mean velocity would be <hi rend="italic">V2g}<hi rend="sub">j</hi>h, =</hi>  √772 × ½Λ, in English inches, per second. The area of this orifice is <hi rend="italic">lh.</hi>  Therefore the discharge would be <hi rend="italic">lh</hi>  √772 × ½∕l, all being measured in inches. This is the usual theory ; but it is not an exact representation of the manner in which the efflux really happens. The water cannot remain at the height BF ; but in drawing towards the wasteboard from all sides it forms a convex surface AIH, so that the point I, where the vertical drawn from the edge of the wasteboard meets the curve, is considerably lower than B. But as all the mass above F is supposed perfectly fluid, the pressure of the incumbent water is propagated, in the opinion of Du Buat, to the filament passing over at F without any diminution. The same may be said of any filament between F and I. Each tends, therefore, to move in the same manner as if it were really impelled through an orifice in its place. Therefore the motions through every part of the line or plane IF are the same as if the water were escaping through an orifice IF, made by a sluice let down on the water, and keeping up the water of the reservoir to the level AB. It is beyond a doubt, says he, that the height IF must depend on the whole height BF, and that there must be a certain determin&lt; proportion between them. He does not attempt to dete mine this proportion theoretically, but says that his exp riments ascertain it with great precision to be the propo tion of one to two, or that IF is always one half of BF. t says, however, that this determination was not by an imm diate and direct measurement ; he concluded it from tl comparison of the quantities of water discharged under di ferent heights of the water in the reservoir.</p><p>We cannot help thinking that this reasoning is very d∣  fective in several particulars. It cannot be inferred, "fro the laws of hydrostatical pressure, that the filament at I pressed forward with all the weight of the column BI. Tl particle I is really at the surface ; and considering it as mal ing part of the surface of a running stream, it is subject&lt; to hardly any pressure, any more than the particles on tl surface of a cup of water held in the hand, while it is carriι round the axis of the earth and round the sun. Reasonir according to his own principles, and availing himself of h own discovery, he should have said that the particle at I hi an accelerating force depending on its slope only ; and the he should have endeavoured to ascertain this slope. The m∣ tion of the particle at I has no immediate connection with tl extremely different from what it is ; for this pressure aloι would give it the velocity which Du Buat assigns it. Now would give it the velocity which M. de Buat assigns it. Now is already passing through the point I with the velocity whit it has acquired in descending along the curve AI ; and th is the real state of the case. The particles are passir through with a velocity already acquired by a sloping cui rent ; and they are accelerated by the hydrostatical pressui of the water above them. The internal mechanism of the; motions is infinitely more complex than Du Buat here su, poses ; and on this supposition, he very nearly abandons tl theory which he has so ingeniously established, and adop the theory of Guglielmini, which he had exploded. At tl same time, we think that he is not much mistaken when 1 asserts that the motions are nearly the same as if a slui&lt; had been let down from the surface to I. For the filameι which passes at I has been gliding down a curved surfac and has not been exposed to any friction. It is perha, the very case of hydraulics where the obstructions are tl smallest ; and we should therefore expect that its motic will be least retarded.</p><p>We have therefore no hesitation in saying, that the fils ment at I is in the very state of motion which the theo would assign to it if it were passing under a sluice, as E Buat supposes. And with respect to the inferior filament without attempting the very difficult task of investigatir their motions, we shall just say, that we do not see any reι son for supposing that they will move slower than our auth∣ supposes. Therefore, though we reject his theory, we aι mit his experimental proposition in general ; that is, we aι mit that the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>  water which passes through the plane I moves with the velocity (though not in the same directioι with which it would have run through a sluice of the san depth ; and we may proceed with his determination of tl quantity of w ater discharged.</p><p>If we make BC the axis of a parabola BEGK, the velι cities of the filaments passing at I and F will be represen ed by the ordinates IE and FG, and the discharge by tl area IEGF. This allows a very neat solution of the prι blem. Let the quantity discharged per second be D, ar let the whole height BF be <hi rend="italic">h.</hi>  Let 2G be the quantil by which we must divide the square of the mean velocil in order to have the producing height. This will be le than <hi rend="italic">2g,</hi>  the acceleration of gravity, on account of the coι vergency at the sides and the tendency to convergence , the lip F. We formerly gave for its measure 702 inche instead of 772, and said that the inches discharged per s∣ cond from an orifice of one inch were 26∙49, instead of 27∙7</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>