<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>buildings. The tomb of Theodoric remains, and the pavement round it is on a level with all the others. The lower story is always full of water ; so is the lower story of the cathedral to the depth of three feet. The ornaments of both these buildings leave no room to doubt that they were formerly dry ; and such a building as the cathedral could not sink without crumbling into pieces.</p><p>It is by no means easy to account for all this. The depositions of the Po and other rivers must raise the ground ; and yet the rivers must still flo½<hi rend="sup">τ</hi> over all. We must conclude that the surface of the Adriatic is by no means level, and that it slopes like a river from the Lagoon of Venice to the eastward. In all probability it even slopes considerably outwards from the shore. This will not hinder the alternations of ebb and flow tide, as will be shown in its proper place. The whole shores of this gulf exhibit most uncommon appearances.</p><p>The last general observation which we shall make in this place is, that the surface of a river is not flat, considered athwart the stream, but convex ; this is owing to its motion. Suppose a canal of stagnant water ; its surface would be a perfect level. But suppose it possible, by any means, to give the middle waters a motion in the direction of its length, they must drag along with them the waters immediately contiguous. These will move less swiftly, and will in like manner drag the waters without them ; and thus the water at the sides being abstracted, the depth must be less, and the general surface must be convex across. The fact in a running stream is similar to this ; the side waters are withheld by the sides, and every filament is moving more slowly than the one next it towards the middle of the river, but faster than the adjoining filament on the land side. This alone must produce a convexity of surface. But besides this, it is demonstrable that the pressure of a running stream is diminished by its motion, and the diminution is proportional to the height which would produce the velocity with which it is gliding past the adjoining filament. This convexity must in all cases be very small. Few rivers have the velocity nearly equal to eight feet per second, and this requires a height of one foot only. An author quoted by M. Buffon says, that he has observed on the river Aveiron an elevation of three feet in the middle during floods ; but we suspect some error in the observation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">§ 4. Of the Windings of Rivers.</hi></p><p>Rivers are seldom straight in their course. Formed by the hand of nature, they are accommodated to every change of circumstance. They wind around what they cannot get over, and work their way to either side according as the resistance of the opposite bank makes a straight course more difficult ; and this seemingly fortuitous rambling distributes them more uniformly over the surface of a country, and makes them everywhere more at hand, to receive the numberless rills and rivulets which collect the waters of our springs and the superfluities of our showers, and to comfort our habitations with the many advantages which cultivation and society can derive from their presence. In their feeble beginnings the smallest inequality of slope or consistency is enough to turn them aside and make them ramble through every field, giving drink to our herds and fertility to our soil. The more we follow nature into the minutiæ of her operations, the more must w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>e admire the inexhaustible fertility of her resources, and the simplicity of the means by which she produces the most important and beneficial effects. By thus twisting the course of our rivers into ten thousand shapes, she keeps them long amidst our fields, and thus compensates for the declivity of the surface, which Would otherwise tumble them with great rapidity into the ocean, loaded with the best and richest of our soil. Without tllis, the showers of heaven would have little influence in supplying the waste of incessant evaporation. But as things are, the rains are kept slowly trickling along the sloping sides of our hills and steeps, winding round every clod, nay, every plant, which lengthens their course, diminishes their slope, checks their speed, and thus prevents them from quickly brushing off from every part of the surface the lightest and best of the soil. The fattest of our holm lands would be too steep, and the rivers would shoot along through our finest meadows, hurrying every thing away with them, and would be unfit for the purposes of inland conveyance, if the inequalities of soil did not make them change this headlong course for the more beautiful meanders which we observe in the course of the small rivers winding through our meadows. Those rivers are in general the straightest in their course which are the most rapid, and which roll along the greatest bodies of water : such are the Rhone, the Po, the Danube. The smaller rivers continue more devious in their progress, till they approach the sea, and have gathered strength from all their tributary streams.</p><p>Every thing aims at an equilibrium, and this directs even the rambling of rivers. It is of importance to understand the relation between the force of a river and the resistance which the soil opposes to those deviations from a rectilineal course ; for it may frequently happen that the general procedure of nature may be inconsistent with our local purposes. Man was set down on this globe, and the task of cultivating it was given him by nature, and his chief enjoyment seems to be to struggle with the elements. He must not find things to his mind, but he must mould them to his own fancy. Yet even this seeming anomaly is one of nature’s most beneficent laws ; and his exertions must still be made in conformity with the general train of the operations of mechanical nature ; and when we have any work to undertake relative to the course of rivers, we must be careful not to thwart their general rules, otherwise we shall sooner or later be punished for their infraction. Things will be brought back to their former state, if our operations are inconsistent with that equilibrium which is constantly aimed at, or some new state of things which is equivalent will soon be induced. If a well-regulated river has been improperly deepened in some place to answer some particular purpose of our own, or if its breadth has been improperly augmented, we shall soon see a deposition of mud or sand choke up our fancied improvements ; because, as we have enlarged the section without increasing the slope or the supply, the velocity must diminish, and floating matters must be deposited.</p><p>It is true, we frequently see permanent channels where the forms are extremely different from that which the waters would dig for themselves in an uniform soil, and which approaches a good deal to the trapezium described formerly. We’see a greater breadth frequently compensate for a want of depth ; but all such deviations are a sort of constraint, or rather are indications of inequality of soil. Such irregular forms are the works of nature ; and if they are permanent, the equilibrium is obtained. Commonly the bottom is harder than the sides, consisting of the coarsest of the sand and of gravel ; and therefore the necessary section can be obtained only by increasing the width. We are accustomed to attend chiefly to the appearances which prognosticate mischief, and we interpret the appearances of a permanent bed in the same way, and frequently form very false judgments. When we see one bank low and flat, and the other high and abrupt, we suppose that the waters are passing along the first in peace, and with a gentle stream, but that they are rapid on the other side, and are tearing away the bank ; but it is just the contrary. The bed being permanent, things are in equilibrio, and each bank is of a form just competent to that equilibrium. If the soil on both sides be uniform, the stream is roost rapid</p></body></text></TEI>