<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the still, neither too violent nor too weak. When the impregnated water begins to come over, and the still is very hot, the fire is lessened by gentle degrees, and the distillation continued till thirty pounds of water are come over, which is generally done in about four or five hours. This rose-water is to be poured again on a fresh quantity (forty pounds) of roses, and from fifteen to twenty pounds of water are to be drawn by distillation, following the same process as before. The rose-water thus made will be found, if the roses be good and fresh, and the distillation carefully performed, highly scented with the roses. It is then poured into pans either of earthen w are or of tinned metal, and left exposed for the night to the fresh air. The ottar or essence will be found in the morning congealed, and swimming on the top of the water ; and this is to be carefully separated and collected either with a thin shell or a skimmer, and poured into a phial. When a certain quantity has thus been obtained, the water and feces must be separated from the clear essence ; which, with respect to the first, will not be difficult to do, as the essence congeals with a slight cold, and the water may then be made to run off. If, after that, the essence is kept fluid by heat, the feces will subside, and may be separated ; but if the operation has been neatly performed, these will be little or none. The feces are as highly perfumed as the essence, and must be kept, after as much as possible of the essence has been skimmed from the rose-water. The remaining water should be used for fresh distillations, instead of common water, at least as far as it will go.</p><p>The above is the whole process, as given in the Asiatic Researches (vol. i. p. 332), of making genuine ottar of roses. Attempts, as the writer states, are often made to augment the quantity, though at the expense of the quality. Thus the raspings of sandal-wood, which contain a deal of essential oil, are used ; but the imposition is easily discovered, both by the smell, and because the essential oil of sandal-wood will not congeal in common cold. In other places they adulterate the ottar by distilling with the roses a sweet-scented grass, which colours it of a high clear green. This does not congeal in a slight cold. There are numerous other modes, far more palpable, of adulteration. The quantity of esential oil to be obtained from roses is very precarious, depending on the skill of the distiller, on the quality of the roses, and on the favourableness of the season. The colour of the ottar is no criterion of its goodness, quality, or country. The calyxes by no means diminish the quality of ottar, nor do they impart any green colour to it. They indeed augment the quantity, but the trouble neces* sary to strip them is such as to prevent their being often used.</p><p>The following is a simpler and less expensive process for preparing this delicate and highly valued perfume, but whether it be equally productive we know not. A large earthen or stone jar, or a large clean wooden cask, is filled with the leaves of the flowers of roses, well picked and freed from the seeds and stalks ; and as much spring-water as will cover them being poured into the vessel, it is set in the sun in the morning at sunrise, and allowed to stand till the evening, when it is removed into the house for the night. In the same way it is to be exposed for six or seven days successively. At the end of the third or fourth day a number of particles of a fine yellow oily matter is seen floating on the surface ; and these particles in the course of two or three days more collect into a scum, which is the ottar of roses. This is taken up by means of cotton tied to the end of a piece of stick, aud squeezed with the finger and thumb into a small phial, which is immediately well stopped ; and this is repeated for some successive evenings, or whilst any of this fine essential oil rises to the surface of the water.</p><p>ROSEHEARTY, a burgh of barony in the county of</p><lb/><p>Aberdeen, situated on the shores of the Moray Frith, and eighteen miles from Banff. The inhabitants, who amount to about 800, are mostly employed in fishing. It possesses a harbour, which may eventually become of importance, situated as it is on an exposed part of the coast, with a considerable depth of water. Its revenues amount to about L.100 yearly.</p><p>ROSENAU, a city of the Austrian kingdom of Hungary, in the province of the Hither Theiss, and circle of Gom∂r. It is situated on the river Sajo, and is the seat of a bishop, and of an episcopal seminary. It contains several churches, 680 houses, and 5400 inhabitants, trading in linen, paper, wood-ware, and ironmongery, and also producing good wine. Long. 20. 27. 13. Ë. Lat. 48. 39. 2. N.</p><p>ROSENGYN, one of the Banda Isles, about seven miles south-east of Lantore. Convicts were sent here when the island was in possession of the Dutch. The productions are nutmegs, mace, and yams ; and here a few cattle are also fed.</p><p>ROSETO, a small city of Italy, of the province of Prin-cipato Ulteriore, and of the kingdom of Naples. It was long celebrated from possessing in its church an image of the Virgin Mary, brought there, according to a legend, in a miraculous manner, which induced many pilgrims from all parts of Europe to resort to it for purposes of devotion, and to present very valuable offerings. It was taken and plundered by the French, and the venerated image having been obtained by a private individual, has been restored to its former place ; but the number of votaries has much diminished. The inhabitants amount to about 3000, who subsist principally in making holy trinkets, and from supplying lodging and provisions to the pilgrims who still resort to it.</p><p>ROSET TA, a town of Africa, in Egypt, is pleasantly situated on the west side of that branch of the Nile called by the ancients <hi rend="italic">Bolbitinum,</hi>  affirmed by Herodotus to have been formed by art ; the town and castle being on the right hand as you enter the river. Any one who sees the hills about Rosetta would judge that they had been the ancient barriers of the sea, and conclude that the sea has not lost more ground than the space between the hills and the water.</p><p>Rosetta is esteemed one of the most pleasant places in Egypt. It is about two miles in length, and consists only of two or three streets. The country about it is most delightful and fertile, as is the whole Delta on the other side of the Nile, exhibiting the most pleasant prospect of gardens, orchards, and corn-fields, excellently cultivated. This place is also famous for having produced the celebrated monument which, interpreted by Dr Young, led to the discovery of hieroglyphical literature, and threw new light on a subject of great antiquity. It consists of a black basalt, fragmented, which the French troops had found when digging the foundation of Fort St Julian ; and is inscribed, as far as it is entire, with the hieroglyphic or sacred, the demotic or enchorial, and the Hellenic or Greek character.</p><p>In the country to the north of Rosetta are delightful gardens, full of orange, lemon, and citron trees, and almost all sorts of fruits, with a variety of groves of palm-trees ; and when the fields are green with rice, it adds greatly to the beauty of the country. It is about twenty-five miles northeast of Alexandria, and a hundred north-west of Cairo. Long. 30. 45. E. Lat. 31. 30. N.</p><p>ROSICRUCIANS, the name of a sect of philosophers, called hermetical philosophers, who arose, as it has been said, or at least became first conspicuous, in Germany, in the beginning of the fourteenth century. They bound themselves together by a solemn secret, which they all swore inviolably to preserve; and obliged themselves, at their admission into the order, to a strict observance of certain established rules. They pretended to know all sciences, and chiefly medicine, of which they professed themselves</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>