<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>gious elevation. In one of these, under the equatorial sun, stands the city of Quito, in the midst of extensive fields of barley, oats, wheat, and gardens containing apples, pears, and gooseberries, and, in short, all the grains and fruits of the cooler parts of Europe; and although the vine is also there in perfection, the olive is wanting. Not a dozen miles from it, in the low countries, the sugar-cane, the indigo, and all the fruits of the torrid zone, find their congenial heat, and the inhabitants swelter under a burning sun. At a small distance on the other hand tower aloft the pinnacles of Pichincha, Corambourou, and Chimboraçao, crowned with never-melting snows.</p><p>The individual mountains of this stupendous range cut off therefore all communication between the Pacific Ocean and the inland continent; and no rivers are to be found on the west coast of South America which have any considerable length of course or body of waters. The country is drained, like Africa, in the opposite direction. Not 100 miles from the city of Lima, the capital of Peru, which lies almost on the sea-shore, and just at file foot of the high Cordilleras, arises out of a small lake the Maragnon or Amazons river, which, after running northward for about 100 miles, takes an easterly direction, and crosses nearly the broadest part of South America, and falls into the great western ocean at Para, after a course of not less than 4095 miles. In the first half of its descent it receives a few middle-sized rivers from the north, and from the south it receives the great river Combos, springing from another little lake not fifty miles distant from the head of the Maragnon, and enclosing between them a wide extent of country. It then receives the Yuta, the Yuerva, the Cuchi-vara, and Parana Mire, each of which is equal to the Rhine; and then the Madeira, which has flowed above 1300 miles. At their junction the breadth is so great that neither shore can be seen by a person standing up in a canoe; so that the united stream must be about six miles broad. In this form it rolls along through a flat country, covered with impenetrable forests, and most of it as yet untrodden by human feet. Mr Condamine, who came down the stream, says that all is silent as the desert, and the wild beasts and numberless birds crowd round the boat, eyeing it as some animal of which they did not seem afraid. The bed was cut deep through an equal and yielding soil, which seemed rich in every part, if he could judge by the vegetation, which was rank in the extreme. What an addition to the possible population of this globe! A narrow slip along each bank of this mighty river would equal in surface the whole of Europe, and would probably exceed it in general fertility; and although the velocity in the main stream was considerable, he observed that it was extremely moderate, nay almost still, at the sides; so that in those parts where the country was inhabited, the Indians paddled up the river with perfect ease. Boats could go from Para to near the mouth of the Madeira in thirty-eight days, which is nearly 1200 miles.</p><p>Not far from the head of the Maragnon, the Cordilleras send off a branch to the north-east, which reaches and ranges along the shore of the Mexican Gulf; and the Rio Grande de Sta Martha occupies the angle between the ridges.</p><p>Another ridge ranges with interruption along the east coast of Terra Firma, so that the whole waters of this country are collected into the Oroonoko. In like manner, the north and east of Brazil are hemmed in by mountainous ridges, through which there is no considerable passage; and the ground sloping backwards, all the waters of this immense tract are collected from both sides by many considerable rivers into the great river Paraguay, or Rio de la Plata, which runs down the middle of the country for more than 1400 miles, and falls into the sea through a vast mouth, in latitude 35°.</p><p>Thus the whole of South America seems as if it had been formerly surrounded by a mound, and been a great basin. The ground in the middle, where the Parana, the Madeira, and the Plata, take their rise, is an immense marsh, uninhabitable on account of its exhalations, and quite impervious in its present state.</p><p>The manner in which the continent of North America is watered, or rather drained, has also some peculiarities. By looking at the map, one will observe, first of all, a general division of the whole of the best-known part into two, by the valleys in which the beds of the rivers St Lawrence and Mississippi are situated. The head of this is occupied by a singular series of fresh-water seas or lakes, viz. the Lakes Superior and Michigan, which empty themselves into Lake Huron by two cataracts. This again runs into Lake Erie by the river Detroit, and the Erie pours its water into the Ontario by the famous Fall of Niagara, and from the Ontario proceeds the great river St Lawrence.</p><p>The ground to the south-west of the Lakes Superior and Erie is somewhat lower, and the middle of the valley is occupied by the Mississippi and the Missouri, which receive on both sides a number of smaller streams, and, having joined, proceed to the south under the name Mississippi. In latitude 37° this river receives into its bed the Ohio, a river of equal magnitude, and the Cherokee river, which drains all the country lying at the back of the United States, separated from them by the ranges of the Appalachian Mountains. The Mississippi is now one of the chief rivers on the globe, and proceeds due south till it falls into the Mexican Bay through several shifting mouths, which greatly resemble those of the Danube and the Nile, having run above 1200 miles.</p><p>The elevated country between this bed of the Mississippi and St Lawrence and the Atlantic Ocean is drained on the east side by a great number of rivers, some of which are very considerable, and of long course; because instead of being nearly at right angles to the coast, as in other countries, they are in a great measure parallel to it. This is more remarkably the case with Hudson’s river, the Delaware, Potomac, and Rappahannoc. Indeed the whole of North America seems to consist of ribs or beams laid nearly parallel to each other from north to south, and the rivers occupy the interstices. All those which empty themselves into the bay of Mexico are parallel and almost perfectly straight, unlike what are seen in other parts of the world. The westernmost of them all, the North river, as it is named by the Spaniards, is nearly as lone as the Mississippi.</p><p>For the length of the courses, and some peculiarities of the principal rivers, see Physical Geography.</p><p>PART I, —THEORY OF THE MOTION OF RIVERS AND <hi rend="smallcaps">canals.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">The importance of this subject needs no commentary. Every nation, every country, every city is interested in it. Our wants, our comforts, and our pleasures require a knowledge of it. We must conduct the water of rivers to the centre of our dwellings; we must secure ourselves against their ravages; we must employ them to drive those machines which, by compensating for our personal weakness, make a few able to perform the work of thousands; we employ them to water and fertilize our fields, to decorate our mansions, to cleanse and embellish our cities, to preserve or extend our demesnes, to transport from county to county every thing which necessity, convenience, or luxury, has rendered precious to man: for these purposes we must confine and govern the mighty rivers, we must preserve or change the beds of the smaller streams, draw off from them what shall water our fields, drive our machines, or supply</hi></p></body></text></TEI>