<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>friable tufa of which it is composed, and have thus both lowered the actual height and filled up the base. On the summit of this famous mount</p><p>-the Capitol,</p><p>Above the rest, lifted his stately bead ;</p><p>On the Tarpeian rock her citadel,</p><p>Impregnable.</p><p>Here also stood the temple of Jupiter Feretrius, the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus, and many other interesting objects. The temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus was one of the largest and most splendid of the ancient world. Its roof was of burnished gold, the pavement of the finest materials, the columns were of precious marbles, the doors of bronze overlaid with gold, the statues of ivory ; and many other objects of surpassing costliness and art embellished the whole interior.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> In the centre of the temple was the statue of Jupiter Capitolinus seated on a throne of gold, witll Juno on his left, and Minerva on his right side. This splendid edifice was destroyed during the civil wars between Marius and Sylla, but was shortly after rebuilt by the latter, who enriched it with the spoils of Greece. It was a second time destroyed by fire during the bloody conflict that took place in the Capitol between the partisans of Vitellius and Vespasian.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> The Capitol rose again from its ashes, with renewed splendour, and through the liberality of Vespasian, and especially of his son Domitian, it greatly surpassed its former magnificence. Its immense wealth appears to have remained untouched till the time of Honorius, when the necessities of that emperor forced him to lay hands upon the gold which ornamented it; and about seven years after his death, it was completely despoiled of its treasures by Genseric king of the Vandals. Of all the ancient splendours of the Capitoline hill, scarcely a vestige now remains. Its invulnerable citadel, its temples and golden statues, its triumphal arches and splendid porticoes, all have been swept away, and its very name is now almost lost in the semi-barbarous appellation, Campidoglio. At present the Capitoline mount is covered with buildings, which, although not devoid of elegance, are unworthy of a spot which was once so august.</p><p>At the base of the northern and principal ascent to the Capitol, are two colossal lionesses of Egyptian porphyry, pouring a stream of water into spacious basins of marhle; and at the top of the ascent are two ancient colossal statues of Grecian marble, representing Castor and Pollux standing by the side of their horses. Here we enter the square, supposed with great probability to be the <hi rend="italic">Intermontium,</hi>  in the centre of which stands the equestrian statue of Marcus Aurelius. In front, and on each side, are three palaces, erected by Michael Angelo ; that of the senators, the conservatori, and the statue gallery. The Museum Capitolinum contains a splendid collection of busts, statues, sarcophagi, &amp;c., and the staircase is lined with an old plan of Rome, which formed originally the pavement of a temple in the forum, but unfortunately it is not entire. Beneath the senators’ palace are the remains of an ancient edifice, supposed to have been the <hi rend="italic">Tabularium,</hi>  where the laws and public records were suspended on tables of bronze; and in its stables, cellars, and gardens, are considerable remains of the ancient fortifications of the citadel. Near the base of the Capitoline hill are the remains ofthe Mamertine prisons, built (according to Livy) by Ancus Martius. A lower cell, called the Tullianum, was added by Servius Tullius.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  There are still two dungeons remaining, an upper and a lower ; and</p><p>in ancient times, prisoners who were condemned to be strangled, or to die of hunger, were thrust down into the lower cell by a circular aperture called Robus. It was in these dungeons that Jugurtha was suffered to die of hunger.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Here the accomplices of Cataline, when, through the influence of Cicero’s eloquence, they were condemned to immediate death, were conducted from the senate house and strangled.@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> Here too Sejanus, the minister of Tiberius, met the just punishment of his crimes ;@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> here Perseus, the captive king of Macedonia, lingered in hopeless confinement ; and here Simon, the bravest of the Jewish leaders, was put to death, while Titus ascended in triumph to the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus.@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> The northern and highest summit of the Capitoline mount is occupied by the church and monastery of Ara Cæli; and on that part of the hill which lies towards the river, is the</p><p>steep Tarpeian,</p><p>The promontory whence the traitor's leap Cured all ambition.</p><p>The Aventine, well known for the unpropitious augury of Remus, is the most western of the seven hills. It is separated from the Palatine by tlle valley of the Circus Maximus, and the Tiber flows round its northern base. It has two distinct summits, which are divided by a valley. On this mount stood the famous temple of Diana, erected in the joint names of all the Latin tribes. Here also stood the temple of Juno Regina; the temple of the Bona Dea; the temple, portico, and library of Liberty, the first public library in Rome.@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi> But of these, and many other magnificent and celebrated edifices, no traces now remain, nor is their place supplied by any buildings, even of modern times, except some decaying churches and half deserted convents.</p><p>The Cælian, which is the most southern of the seven hills, is of a triangular form, and is crossed by the lofty and ruinous arches of Nero’s aqueduct It is stated by Tacitus, that this mount was originally called <hi rend="italic">Querquetulanus,</hi>  from the quantity of oak trees that grew upon it; and that it received its name from Cælius Vibenna, an Etruscan chief, who inhabited some part of it when he came to the succour of Tarquinius Priscus.@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi>  Tiberius commanded that it should be called Mons Augustus, but the intention was never carried into effect.@@<hi rend="sup">10</hi>  The name of Lateran has prevailed in modern times, derived from a senator named Lateranus, who had a splendid edifice upon it in the time of Nero.@@<hi rend="sup">11 </hi>Deserted as it now is, the Cælian mount was once covered with temples and monuments of magnificence; but of these splendid buildings every trace has long since vanished, and the surface of the hill is strewed over with shapeless ruins, of which the date, the author, and tlle object, are alike unknown. The only buildings worthy of particular attention are the curious and interesting church of San Stephano Ro-tondo, which is universally admitted to be an ancient temple, though antiquaries are by no means agreed respecting the name of its tutelar god ; and the sumptuous basilica of St. John Lateran, which stands on the eastern summit of the hill.</p><p>The Esquiline is more extensive than any of the rest, and more irregular in its form. It is partly covered witlι the buildings of modern Rome, and partly abandoned to desolation. The Esquiline hill was added to Rome by Servius Tullius, and it was in his flight from the senate-house, to his palace on the Esquiline, that he was murdered by the emissaries of Tarquin his son-in law. A street called <hi rend="italic">Vicus</hi></p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi><hi rend="italic">  Vide</hi>  description of it by Dion- Halicarnassus and Pliny ; Liv. lib. vi. cap. 29 ; Id. lib. iii. cap. 17; Liv. lib. xxxv. cap. 41.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> Tacit. Hist. lib. iii. cap. 71.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> Liv. lib. i. cap. 33; Varro de Ling. Lat. lib. iv. cap. 32.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Sallust de Bello. Jugurt∙</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> Sallust de Bello Catilin. cap. 55.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Dion. Cassius, lib. lviii. p. 885; Tacit. Annal, lib v. cap. 9.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> Plutarch's Life of Æmilius    Paulus ;    Josephus de Bello, Jud.    lib. vii. cap. 5.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi>Pliny vii. 30. xxxv. 2.; Mart. xii.    3. 5.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">9</hi>  Varro de Ling. Lat. lib. iv.    ; Tacit.    Ann. lib. iv. cap. 65.    </p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">10</hi>Sueton. in vita. Tiberii, cap. 48.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">11</hi>  Tacit. Annal, lib. xv. sect.    49, 60;    Juv. Sat. x. 15.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>