<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>from the plains to the mountains, and after the gathering of the harvest, tile Maremme are abandoned, on account of the malaria The leases in these districts are sometimes subset to smaller cultivators, and even subdivided into small fractions. But in other parts of the country leases are rarely granted ; land is almost all colonized, that is, farmed on the mezzeria principle, a system which is productive of the worst results. The general arrangement is, that the landowner shall receive from the coloni half the produce of the soil ; but there are many cases in which the amount received is not one-sixth of the produce. The coloni are generally in debt to their landlords, and are often in a state of insolvency.</p><p>The Roman states produce a supply of cattle sufficient for the ordinary consumption. Horses are exported, and there is a small importation of oxen and swine. The breed of sheep is improving, and the export of wool is considerable, and is rapidly increasing. Olive plantations were long one of the most productive investments ; but they are now less so than the cultivation of the white mulberry, which would spread widely were capital abundant. Vineyards have been too extensively planted, and now yield no return equivalent to the outlay. The culture of the wheat has diminished solely from the absence of external demand, and the consequent decline of prices. The instruments of husbandry employed are of the rudest kind. The heavy customs have prevented the introduction of improved implements, and the arts are too little advanced to allow their production at home. The principal impediments in the Roman states to agricultural improvements are, the political situation of the country ; the protecting system, which keeps all the producing powers in backwardness ; the want of capital ; the want of population in the Maremme, and the mezzeria system elsewhere ; the want of knowledge, and more especially of agricultural knowledge ; the extreme difficulty proprietors have in finding managers for their estates who are able and willing to introduce the improvements that have been adopted elsewhere ; mortmain, the heavy burden of taxation falling particularly on proprietors, agriculturists, and their productions, and the difficulty of sales from restricted relations.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi></p><p>The population of the Roman states in general is rather agricultural than manufacturing, and their manufactures serve only for the home consumption. There is little demand for them abroad. The papal government has made enormous sacrifices, by protections, prohibitions, and premiums, for the encouragement of what is called native industry ; but these measures, so far from increasing and improving manufacturing produce, have been the main causes of decline and decay. Their only effect has been to reward and to render permanent the most rude and ignorant processes of manufacture. Scarcely a valuable discovery has been introduced into their manufactories, and the looms are still such as were generally employed in the fourteenth century. Many a town in Great Britain, consisting only of 30,000 souls, produces a greater quantity of manufactured articles than the three million inhabitants of the pontifical states. The principal manufacture is that of woollens of ordinary quality. Rome is the chief seat of this manufacture, and the value of the fabrics produced annually, is calculated at 300,000 crowms, (L.60,000.) Next to woollens stands the manufacture of hats. They are well made every where, but especially at Rome, and to the amount of 200,000 crowns, (L.40,000.) There are silk manufactories in Rome, Bologna, Camerino, and Brugia ; but the trade is declining. Next in importance to woollen and silk manufactories, are those of tanned and dressed leather. Gloves are made in Rome and Bologna, to the extent of from 90,000 to 100,000 pairs annually. Roman musical strings enjoy a very ancient and deserved reputation. The annual quantity made amounts in value to 10,000 crowns. There are scarely any manufactories of cotton goods. The government has made great sacrifices to maintain an establishment at the Diocletian baths, but without success. The fabrics of hemp and flax are more numerous than those of cotton, but there are no factories ; all the goods produced are manufactured either in public schools, orphan asylums, or private houses. The other articles of manufacture are ropes and cordage, wax and tallow candles, paper, cream of tartar, liquorice juice, pig iron, copper manufactures, earthenware, and glass. An extensive trade was formerly carried on in alum, which was dug in large quantities in the mountains of Tolfa, but the introduction of artificial alum, by lowering the prices, has greatly diminished this trade. Riaw sulphur is found in large quantities and of excellent quality. After supplying the home consumption, both raw and refined sulphur are exported to the amount of four million lbs. giving an annual proceed of 120,000 crowns. The sulphuric manufactures of Bologna produce annually 50,000 lbs. of sulphuric, and 10,000 lbs. of nitric acid.</p><p>The trade of the Roman states is far from extensive or flourishing. The principal exports are com from Romagna and the frontier districts ; but this trade is diminishing. Sheep 50,000 yearly, swine 40,000, oxen 10,000. The export to England of Roman wool is become very considerable, and is increasing rapidly. The provinces on the west of the Apennines export from 800,000 to 900,090 lbs. of wool for Piedmont and France. A million lbs. of cheese go to Tuscany and Sardinia ; of lambs skins, about 400,000 lbs. are shipped to England, Piedmont, and Naples. Of horns and bones, there is an export of 15,000 lbs. ; of honey, 10,000 lbs. ; of skins, 100,000 lbs. ; of tallow, 200,000 lbs. ; of lard and fat, 150,000 lbs.; of hemp, 30 millions of lbs.; of white and brown rags, 3 millions lbs. ; of oil, 1 million lbs. ; of tobacco, 300,000 lbs., but the government monopoly is a great impediment to the extended cultivation of a plant to which the soil is well adapted. There is a large export of planks to Spain, America, and France, besides other articles.</p><p>The imports are to some extent affected by the circumstance, that a chain of mountains traverses the country, making the north-west almost inaccessible to the south, so that while one part of the state is exporting, another is im porting the same article. Colonial produce is received principally from England and France ; and the consumption is, of raw sugar, 10,000,000 lbs.; coffee, 1,600,000 lbs.; pepper, 1,000,000 lbs.; cocoa, 50,000 lbs.; cinnamon, 40,000 lbs.; cloves, 35,000 lbs.; and raw cotton, 150,000 lbs. Of other principal articles, the yearly imports are, from 40,000 to 50,000 sheep ; from 12,000 to 13,000 calves or oxen; 8000 to 9000 swine; 16,000 to 1.8,000 cows; some costly horses, principally for the capital ; hides, about 1,200,000 lbs.; raw skins, 50,000 lbs.; coarse wool for mattresses, 1,000,000 lbs. ; cheese, 1,300,000 lbs. ; butter, 70,000 lbs. ; wax, 700,000 lbs. ; cochineal and kernes, salt fish from England, 8,700,000 lbs.; about 3,000,000 lbs. more of pilchards, Sardinian salmon, &amp;c. are brought from Spain, France, Sicily, and Russia.</p><p>The tariff which regulates the import and export duties of the Pontifical states, is dated 28th April 1830.@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi></p><p>The prohibitions in the Roman states are not numerous. On imports they include the articles farmed, as salt, tobacco, alum, vitriol, playing cards, pictures, engravings, &amp;c.</p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  See the communication of one of the largest landed proprietors in the Roman States, in Dr. Bowring’s Report, &amp;c. p. 78, 79. <hi rend="sup">,</hi></p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>Report on the Statistics of the Roman States, by Dr. Bowring. 1837.</p></body></text></TEI>