<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tory not always inclining to the side of Rome. During this war there occurred an event which has engaged the pens of several controversial writers. The Roman army happening to be reduced to great straits, blocked up by the Quadi, and in want of water, were relieved, and their enemies entirely discomfitted by a sudden storm of rain, accompanied with thunder and lightning, which flashing fiercely in the faces of the barbarians, filled them with terror, and scattered them into headlong flight. This event was considered as miraculous, and it is said to have been immediately preceded by the prayers of the twelfth legion, which was composed of Christians, and which afterwards received the name of <hi rend="italic">the thundering legion.</hi></p><p>A peace, or rather a cessation of hostilities, followed the victory thus obtained, and the emperor having returned to Rome, triumphed along with his son Commodus. An insurrection which had broken out in Syria, probably hastened his return ; but Aurelius was not required to march against the rebel Avidius Cassius, who was killed by his own soldiers. The emperor treated the insurgents with great clemency, and took the family of Cassius under his protection, forbidding the senate to doom to death any who were suspected of being implicated in the rebellion.</p><p>Notwithstanding the general mildness of the personal character and the administration of Marcus Aurelius Antoninus, his memory is greatly disgraced by the systematic persecution against the Christians which he encouraged. It was not now merely the consequence of tumultuary violence, arising out of the intolerance of the idolatrous pagans, but was deliberately resolved upon, for reasons of state ; the philosophic emperor, although despising all religion in his stoic pride, yet strictly prohibiting all change from the religions and customs of former times. Among the most illustrious victims of imperial intolerance was Justin Martyr, celebrated for his writings in defence of Christianity.</p><p>The war against the German nations was soon renewed, and assumed the most formidable aspect. Not merely the tribes on the frontiers of the empire took up arms, but throughout the interior of all tlle northern nations there was a general commotion, a wide upheaving and unsettling of whole races, and a pressing forward of a living tide, which threatened to overwhelm every thing in its progress. This was in fact the first symptom of the great migration of nations, then beginning, and which ceased not till it completely subverted the Roman empire, filling it with a new population, whose descendants constitute the kingdoms of modern Europe.</p><p>In order to stem, if possible, the progress of this barbarian innundation, Aurelius again left Rome, and marched to Germany. His first efforts were crowned with success; but before he could follow them up, he was seized with a dangerous ill-’ness, which terminated his life, in the fifty-ninth yearofhisage. With Aurelius, the glory and the happiness of the Roman empire may be said to have expired, and that not uncharacteristically, in the reign of an emperor who was distinguished by considerable acquirements in learning, taste, philosophy, and by external respect for all religions, but real regard for none.</p><p>The commencement of the reign of Commodus, son of the late emperor, was rendered disgraceful by a treaty which he formed wdth the Marcomanni, and which he obtained chiefly through the influence of money. Notwithstanding the care which M. A. Antoninus had bestowed upon his education, he was ignorant to an extreme degree, having neither abilities nor inclination for profiting by the imperial example and instruction. On his return to Rome he speedily shewed the bias of his natural disposition, giving himself up to the most unrestrained indulgence in the grossest vices. That he might do so without impediment, he entrusted all power to Perennis, præfect of the prætorian guard, a man of stern and cruel temper, who was at last slain by his sol</p><lb/><p>diers for his severity. A conspiracy against the life of Corn-modus failed, and was followed by a long succession of judicial murders, to gratify the vengeance of the cowardly and vindictive tyrant. He was next threatened by a new danger of a very peculiar character. It had become customary for the licentious soldiery to desert in considerable numbers, especially in Gaul, and to roam about the country as bands of robbers and freebooters. A common soldier, named Maternus, put himself at the head of these banditti, and excited such terror, that he became an object of attention to considerable armies. Being surrounded, and in danger of ruin, Maternus formed the bold project of killing the emperor in the heart of his capital, and seizing the throne. Dispersing his adherents, they all hastened to Rome, individually or in small parties, and had nearly filled the city, when they were detected, and Maternus was put to death.</p><p>The cruelty and rapacity of Cleander, the freedman and new favourite of Commodus, excited a new insurrection, which nothing could allay, the prætorian cavalry being defeated in the streets by the populace, till the headof Cleander was, by the emperor’s command, thrown to the insurgents. In the mean time, Commodus was indulging his base tastes and appetites, not only by gross sensuality, but by endeavouring to rival the gladiators in their savage occupation. Being a very skilfιd archer, and of great personal strength, he delighted in killing wild beasts in the amphitheatre, and thus pretending to rival Hercules, In the gladiatorial contests, he publicly engaged so often, that he was the conqueror in 735 combats. Within the palace itself, a conspiracy was at length formed by Marcia, one of the emperor's concubines, his chamberlain, and the præfect of the prætorian guards. Poison was administered by Marcia, in a cup of wine ; and while under the influence of the deadly draught, he was assailed and strangled by a common wrestler, who had been prepared for that purpose.</p><p>Immediately upon the death of Commodus being known to the senate, they elected Publius Helvius Pertinax to the vacant throne ; a man of obscure birth, but of great personal merit, by which he had raised himself to a distinguished rank in the state, and in tlle estimation of all virtuous men. The undesired power thus offered to him, hc reluctantly accepted ; but prepared to use it for the general good of the empire. In order to accomplish this most desirable object, Pertinax was obliged to begin his reign by checking the lavish expenditure by which Commodus had sought to secure the support of the guards, and to introduce discipline and subordination into this turbulent band. This necessary reform was immediately followed by an insurrection, in which Pertinax was killed, after a brief reign of sixty-six days.</p><p>"During this scene of contest and blood, the citizens abstained as much as possible from all interference, though strongly attached to Pertinax ; and after his death they remained quiet in their houses, waiting the new master whom the prætorian guards might nominate. These seditious troops having fortified their quarters, waited also to see what the senate would do ; but finding themselves left in possession of imperial power, they issued a proclamation, offering the empire for sale to the highest bidder. Didius Julianus bccame the purchaser, and thus disgracefully acquired the throne. But the intelligence of these base and lawless transactions excited the indignation of the armies in the provinces, who considered themselves better entitled to appoint an emperor, than a factious band of only about ten thousand men. The army of Illyricum proclaimed their general, Septimius Severus; thatofSyria,Pescennius Niger; and that of Britain, Clodius Albinus. A bloody civil war was the inevitable consequence of so many competitors for the sovereignty. In the mean time, the wretched Didius was still the nominal emperor. But the rapid advance of Severus towards Rome alarmed the senate, who passed a</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>