<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>days, completely annihilated his army, and subdued his dominions. It was in giving an account of this brief war, that he used the famous words, <hi rend="italic">Veni, vidi, vici. “ I</hi>  came, saw, conquered.”</p><p>During Cæsar’s delay in Egypt, and expedition into Pontus, great disturbances had broken out in Rome ; to remedy which he repaired thither with his usual promptitude and speed. Upon his arrival, he was again nominated dictator, and strenuously applied himself to the reform of the abuses which had been committed in his absence by ill-judging and intemperate partisans. No proscriptions followed his arrival, no blood was shed, no injustice perpetrated ; and this clemency, so different from the conduct of Sylla and Ma.fus, induced numbers of the most distinguished men of what had been the independent party in the senate, to return to Rome, and there to renew the semblance of a regular form of government. He then turned his attention to Africa, where a strong body of his antagonists had been drawn together by Cato and the sons of Pompey. The struggle was severe, but not protracted. A decisive battle was fought at Thapsus, where the Pompeian party were completely overthrown. Despair filled the hearts of the routed leaders. Cato died by his own hand in Utica ; Scipio, being intercepted in his flight, stabbed himself and fell into the sea, while Cæsar’s men were boarding his galley ; and Juba, king of Numidia, and his general Petreius, fell by each other’s bands in single combat. The two sons of Pompey escaped and fled to Spain, where they endeavoured once more to rekindle the embers of the expiring war.</p><p>Upon his return victorious from Africa, Cæsar was received at Rome both by senate and people with great adulation, and he celebrated his triumph with uncommon pomp and splendour. He was again created dictator for ten years, and honours were heaped on him with lavish hand. Again did he renew his acts of clemency and generosity to all who had been opposed to him, thus confirming his popularity and consolidating his [lower.</p><p>But Pompey’s sons, Cneius and Sextus, having collected a considerable force in Spain, Cæsar found himself once more obliged to quit Rome. The two armies met in the plains of Munda, and prepared for the final struggle with all the energy of hope on the one side, and on the other of despair. So furious was the conflict, that Cæsar was compelled to put himself at the head of his favourite tenth legion, and to fight as a common soldier, not for victory merely, but for life. Victory at length declared for him ; a vast number of his most eminent and determined enemies fell in the battle, or in the flight, and among the latter was the eldest son of Pompey. With this sanguinary conflict the war was at once terminated, and Cæsar returned in full triumph to Rome.</p><p>Having now completed the subversion of the republic, Cæsar assumed the undivided sway of Rome, although he tolerated the continuation of the forms of republican government. In his own person he concentrated those offices which were requisite for the conduct of public affairs, such as the dictatorship, the consulate, and the offices of tribune, censor, and pontifex maximus. Thus possessed of all authority and power, he commenced a number of reforms, improvements, and public works of utility, which did honour to his genius, his judgment, and his spirit of enterprise. He reformed the calendar, and undertook to drain the Pontine marshes, to deepen the channel of the Tiber, to form a capacious harbour at Ostia, to cut a canal through the isthmus of Corinth, and to revenge the defeat of Crassus, by an expedition against the Parthians. In the midst of these schemes and undertakings he gave offence to the senate by his haughtiness, and to the people by his too evident assumption of regal dignity, and almost of the regal title. They could better brook the loss of liberty in reality than in appearance ; they retained their love of the form of the republic, when its spirit was gone ; they could not endure the name of king, while they were willing to submit to real monarchy under the name of a perpetual dictatorship.</p><p>Influenced by these feelings, a large body of the senators began to regard Cæsar as an usurper, and many even of the people, who had formerly supported him as their leader against the aristocratic party, became also disaffected. Mark Antony’s offer of a crown at tlle feast of the Lupercalia, put forth in all probability for the purpose of ascertaining the bias of the popular mind, was met hy such decided disapprobation, as to cause Cæsar himself to hesitate, and to wait for a more propitious juncture for the completion of his designs. Meanwhile, a conspiracy was formed for his destruction, and at the head of it were Brutus and Cassius, who had both experienced his clemency and additional marks ofhis favour. After having narrowly escaped detection, they resolved to strike the blow in the senate-house itself, on the ides of March. No sooner had he taken his seat than the conspirators crowded round him, preferring various requests, and one of them, apparently in extreme urgency, seized him by the robe. At this preconcerted signal, they all rushed upon him with their daggers, and Cæsar, perceiving resistance fruitless, muffled up his head in his mantle, and fell at tlle base of Pompey’s statue, pierced by three-and-twenty wounds. At this moment, Brutus waved aloft his bloody dagger, hailed thc senate, and in particular Cicero, and proclaimed aloud the recovered liberty of Rome.</p><p>But instead ofjoy and gratitude, a general terror pervaded the senate and the citizens. They had felt secure in the well-known clemency and the settled power of Cæsar ; they knew not what scenes of anarchy and bloodshed might follow his death, nor what might be tlle temper ofhis successor in the chief power. A dull dead calm brooded over the city for some days ; till, on the day of Cæsar’s funeral, Antony inflamed the smouldering passions of the populace to such a degree, that they burst into the senate house, tore up its benches, and raised an immense funeral pile for the body, sacked in their fury the houses of the conspirators, and wreaked their vengeance on al I of that party whom they could seize. Alarmed by these proceedings, the chief conspirators fled from the city, and prepared to vindicate their deed, and defend the republic by arms.</p><p>Previously to this tumult, Antony had concurred with Brutus and Cassius in passing an act of amnesty, granting forgiveness to all who had been implicated in any of the former proceedings. But having stirred up the populace, and being joined by Octavianus, or Octavms, the grand-nephew and heir of Cæsar, he now entered boldly on his turbulent and ambitious career. Brutus and Cassius retired to Macedonia and Syria, to which provinces they had been appointed, leaving Italy in the power of Antony and Octvaius. A jealousy soon arose between these two leaders of the revolutionary party ; and Octavius joining the senatc, Antony retired into Gaul, raised an army, and came to an engagement with the two consuls near Mutina, where he was defeated, but both the consuls fell in battle. Antony fled to Spain, and joined Lepidus ; but before renewing the war, he represented to Octavius that their hostilities would only secure the triumph of the senate and the conspirators. In consequence of this suggestion, Octavius, Antony, and Lepidus, came to an interview in a small island in the river Lavinus, not far from the modem city Bologna, and there formed a confederacy, called the “ second triumvirate.” In the course of their proceedings, these three ruthless men drew up a list of those whom they wished to be put to death, each, without compunction, permitting relation or friend to be proscribed, if required by the others. This bloody proscription was followed by tlle murder of not less than 300 senators, and 2000 ofthe equestrian order. Among the former was the illustrious Cicero, whose death was occa-</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>