<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>be kept in awe. The effect proved the wisdom of Nerva’s choice. So high was the cllaracter of Trajan, that no person could be named equally worthy of the empire; and even the seditious prætorian bands submitted without a murmur. This, as it was the best, was almost the last act of Nerva’s short reign. He was soon after seized with a fever,of which he died, having reigned only one year four months and nine days.</p><p>The peaceful and virtuous reign of Nerva was the harbinger of happy days to the Roman empire. The selection of Trajan prevented any contests for imperial power at the death of Nerva ; so that the new emperor entered without the necessity of bloodshed upon the discharge of his high functions. He was by birth a Spaniard, though of Italian extraction ; and had been early inured to the discipline of the army under his father, a commander of considerable reputation. When he himself became a general, he continued to practise the simple habits of a soldier, excelling his troops not in personal indulgences, but in courage and virtue. On the throne he continued to exhibit the same excellencies, only enhanced by the acquisition of a wider scope for their full development. Being superior to fear, it was natural that he should also be above harbouring suspicion. He therefore abolished the law of treason, <hi rend="italic">(judicia majestatis,)</hi>  and prepared to restore as much of the free Roman constitution as was compatible with the existence of a monarchy. He restored the elective power to the <hi rend="italic">comitia,</hi>  complete liberty of speech to the senate, and to the magistrates their former authority ; and yet he ruled thc empire with unrivalled firmness, holding the reins of power with a strong and steady hand. Of him it has been said, not in the language <hi rend="italic">of</hi>  panegyric, but of simple sincerity, that he was equally great as a ruler, a general, and a man : and only such a man could with safety, as emperor, have used the remarkable words, when giving a sword to the prefect of the prætorian guards, “Take this sword, and use it, if I have merit, for me; if otherwise, against me.”</p><p>Soon after the accession of Trajan, the Dacian monarch, Decebalus, sent to demand the tribute with which Domitian had purchased a disgraceful peace. This Trajan indignantly refused ; and levying an army, marched against the Dacians, who had already resumed their predatory incursions. The hostile armies soon came to an engagement, for both were equally eager ; and after a desperate struggle the Dacians were routed with dreadful carnage. But so great was the loss of the Romans, that for some time they were not able to follow up their victory. It was however decisive ; and the Dacians were compelled not only to forego their demands, but even to become tributaries to Rome. But unaccustomed to servitude, and led by their gallant king Decebalus, they mustered fresh forces as soon as they had somewhat recovered from their overthrow, and prepared for another contest. The warlike emperor was equally ready for the shock of arms. Not satisfied with expelling the invaders, he now determined to carry the war into the country of the enemy. For this purpose he erected a stupendous bridge over the Danube, with a strong fortification at each end, defeated the Dacians in every battle, marched into the heart of their country, and made himself master of the capital. Decebalus, despairing of success, killed himself, and Dacia was reduced to a Roman province, and secured in subjection by several colonies and standing camps. On his return from the Dacian war, the emperor was honoured with a triumph which lasted for the unprecedented period of 120 days.</p><p>The deepest stain which rests on the memory of Trajan is the sanction which he gave to the persecution of the Christians. This persecution ragedchieflyin the Asiaticprovinces, where Christianity was most prevalent ; and when Pliny the younger, at that time proconsul of Bithynia, wrote to Trajan for instructions respecting a matter which was causing the death of so many men who could not be convicted of any public crimes, the emperor returned an ambiguous answer, the purport of which was, “ that the Christians should not be sought for, nor indicted on anonymous information, but that on conviction they ought to be punished.” Such an answer was contrary to every principle of justice ; for if criminal, they ought to be sought for, if not criminal, they ought not to be punished. The persecution being somewhat discouraged, was gradually suffered to abate.</p><p>Trajan’s passion for military fame had been but excited, not satiated, by his Dacian conquests. He next directed his attention to the East, and resolved to wrest from the Parthians, the most dreaded foes of Rome, the empire of central Asia. The first scene ofhis glory was Armenia, which he speedily reduced to a Roman province. Hence he advanced into Mesopotamia, throwing across the rapid Tigris a bridge not less remarkable than that which spanned the Danube. The greatcr part of what had been the Assyrian empire was overrun by his conquering arms. Selucia yielded to his might ; Ctesiphon, the capital of the Parthian kingdom, could not resist his prowess ; all opposition appeared fruitless, and victory seemed the companion of his march. Following the course of the Tigris, he arrived at the head of the Persian gulf, where he fitted out a fleet, and sailed to the entrance of the Indian ocean. Having thus traced the steps of Alexander the Great, emulating his conquering career, and with almost equal celerity, he began to retrace his course, returned to Ctesiphon, and placed a new sovereign on the throne of Parthia.</p><p>Age had now' somewhat tamed his ambitious spirit, and seriously diminished the vigour of his hardy but overworn frame. He began to make preparations for his return to Rome, which he intended to be celebrated in a manner that should far outshine the most glorious triumphs of any of his imperial predecessors. But this triumph he was not destined to see. He had only reached Cilicia when he was seized with an illness which proved fatal, after a few days of paralytic stupor. During this period of comparative insensibility, the empress Plotina, who had accompanied him, contrived to procure Trajan’s signature to a will nominating as his successor in the empire P. Ælius Adrian, his cousin, who was at that time with the army.</p><p>Adrian having been declared emperor by the soldiers, immediately communicated to the senate the intelligence of Trajan’s death, and of his own accession, excusing his not having waited till their sentiments should be made known, by pleading the impatient impetuosity of his troops. The senate were but too happy that the army had made no worse choice, and gave their ready concurrence. Adrian not having either the ambition or the military talents of Trajan, was more desirous of securing peace than of extending the empire : he therefore abandoned all the conquests of his predecessor, broke down the bridge across the Tigris, and reduced the empire within the boundaries marked out by Augustus, witll the exception of Dacia. On his return to Rome the senate offered him a triumph, which he declined on his own account ; but as great preparations had already been made, the triumph was celebrated, the statue of Trajan occupying the most conspicuous position. The ashes of that imperial warrior were afterwards placed in a golden urn on the summit of a magnificent column, 140 feet high, erected in the Forum Trajani to commemorate his victories, and still known by the name of Trajan’s pillar.</p><p>But though Adrian was of a pacific disposition, he well knew what was required for the protection of the empire. He therefore restored the discipline of the army, and kept it in complete subordination. He also effected a general and vigorous reform in the internal administration of affairs, and displayed great personal aptitude forthe study of comprehensive politics. To him the jurisprudence of Rome was</p></body></text></TEI>