<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>petrated with impunity in all branches of the administration, he set himself vigorously to the dangerous task of effecting a thorough reform. He restored the privileges of the senate, and gave it once more an actual power in the government. The courts of law were also subjected to a most salutary reform, and rendered again, what they had long ceased to be, courts of justice. The insubordination of the army, which had been the main cause of so many bloody revolutions, he repressed with a firm and steady hand ; and restored in a great measure the discipline which had made it so powerful in its better days. He directed his attention also to the treasury, which had been quite exhausted by the corrupt and prodigal expenditure ofhis predecessors ; and in order to replenish its coffers, he regulated anew the tribute and custom-dues of the provinces, and imposed a number of taxes ; by which means, though he was accused of avarice, he placed once more the revenues of the empire on a stable basis, and restored them to a flourishing condition. The large sums thus raised Vespasian did not expend in revelry, neither did he hoard up in useless masses. He rebuilt the temple of Jupiter Capitolinus, which had been destroyed during the tumults that accompanied the fall of Vitellius; and adorned the city with many other public buildings of great elegance and splendour, thus evincing, that though rigorous and exact in his methods of amassing treasure, he knew, on proper occasions, how to use it with no parsimonious hand. Under him the empire began to breathe with fresh life, and to exhibit signs of prosperity and happiness, such as it had not known since the reign of Augustus. His son Titus being raised to the dignity of Cæsar, by which name the successor to the throne was designated, the peace and welfare of the empire seemed secured on a stable basis.</p><p>During the reign of Vespasian the arms of Rome were prosperous in various parts of the world. Several states bordering- on the Roman dominions were reduced by his generals to the condition of provinces. But the most celebrated, though not the most formidable war which distinguished his reign, was that in which he was engaged when he was called to the throne, the war against the Jews. This was conducted by his son Titus, after his departure to Rome to enter on the possession of imperial power. The events of this memorable war are so well known that they need not here be detailed. Suffice it to state, that after Jerusalem had been closely invested, the Jews refused all terms of capitulation, blindly trusted in some terrible interposition of divine power to save them and consume their enemies, butchered each other with inconceivable barbarity during every temporary cessation of warfare, endured the wildest extremes of famine, and after suffering every form and kind of misery, to a degree unparalleled in the world’s history, their city was taken, and together with their celebrated temple, was reduced to heaps of shapeless ruins; and such of them as survived these awful calamities were scattered over the face of the earth, and rendered a mockery, a proverb, and a reproach among nations. In consequence of this victory over the Jews, Titus and the emperor enjoyed together the honours of a splendid triumph, while the rich vessels of the temple of Jerusalem were in gorgeous procession borne in the train of the conquerors.</p><p>Soon after this triumph the Batavian war broke out, caused by the civil wars for the empire, and threatening Rome with the loss of a province. It was at length brought to a propitious conclusion by Cerealis, after several sharp encounters, and by a treaty rather than a conquest. The Roman arms were more successful in Britain, during the reign of Vespasian and his immediate successors, than they had previously been. In his younger days, the emperor had himself been engaged in British wars ; and being desirous of reducing the island completely under the Roman yoke, he gave the command to Cneius Julius Agricola, a man of extraordinary merit, a general and a statesman worthy of the best days of Rome. Not only the southern division ofthe island was subdued by this distinguished commander, but even the more remote regions of Caledonia, hitherto impervious to the Roman legions, were laid open. The gallant resistance of the brave Caledonians, under their leader Galgacus, was ineffectual ; their untaught valour could not withstand the steady discipline of the Roman army, and they sustained a severe overthrow at the base of the Grampians. The Roman fleet coasting along the shore, ascertained the insular character of Britain ; but so formidable were the mountain fastnesses of Caledonia, that Agricola did not attempt to penetrate farther into the country, contenting himself with constructing a chain of forts between the Friths of Clyde and Forth, to defend the southern districts, and to restrain the recoil and assaults of the unconquered Caledonians.</p><p>Thus glorious abroad, and beloved at home, Vespasian’s life began to draw near its termination. Feeling the effects of age and weakness, he retired to Campania, to enjoy the benefits of a purer air than that of Rome, together with some relaxation from the cares of state. There he was seized with a malady which his own sensations told him would speedily prove mortal. His anticipations proved true ; and he expired in the arms ofhis attendants, in the seventieth year of his age, and the tenth of his reign. It is worthy of remark, that Vespasian was the second of the Roman emperors that died a natural death, and the first that was succeeded by his son.</p><p>Titus Flavius Vespasian, the conqueror of Jerusalem, ascended in peace the peaceful throne ofhis father. The very first acts ofhis reign gave promise of a period of unexam-pledfelicity. Previously to that time he had indulged slightly in pleasures of a somewhat licentious character. From that hour he discarded all the ministers of his looser days, and being resolved to reform the state of public morals, began by reforming himself. Although strongly attached to the beautiful Berenice, daughter of Agrippa, the last king of Judea, he relinquished her society entirely, because he knew that such a connexion was disagreeable to the Roman senate and people. He abolished also the law of treason, under the sanction of which so many acts of tyranny had been committed; and he not only discountenanced, but severely punished, all spies and informers. His whole time was devoted to the duties of his high station ; his chief pleasure consisted in rendering services and kindnesses to his friends and to his people. His courtesy and benevolence would doubtless find ample scope ; yet it is recorded of him, that one evening recalling to mind the events of the day, and not finding that he had done any thing during its course beneficial to mankind, he exclaimed in accents of regret, “ My friends, I have lost a day !” This well-known exclamation, and the course of benevolent deeds by which it was accredited, procured for him the truly glorious title of <hi rend="italic">The delight of mankind.</hi></p><p>Yet the reign of that gentle-hearted and benignant emperor was signalised by some remarkable public calamities. In its first year Campania was laid waste by the most dreadful eruption of Vesuvius ever recorded. It devastated the surrounding country for many miles, overwhelming several cities, of which Herculaneum and Pompeii were the chief. The remains of these cities, excavated in modern times, have supplied inestimable stores to the antiquarian, and thrown great light upon the habits and customs of the Romans in domestic life/ Pliny, the celebrated naturalist and philosopher, lost his life in this eruption, being suffocated in consequence of allowing his curiosity to attract him too near the fearful and dangerous scene. This calamitous convulsion of nature was followed by a destructive conflagration at Rome, which raged for three days, and destroyed a great number of edifices, both public and private. Titus exerted</p></body></text></TEI>