<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>found to agree with the facts which the researches of so many active investigators of this curious subject have been able to ascertain. It is found, for example, and we will produce instances in viewing the progress of romance in particular countries, that the earliest productions of this sort, known to exist, are short narrations or ballads, which were probably sung on solemn or festive occasions, recording the deeds and praises of some famed champion of the tribe and country, or perhaps the history of some remarkable victory or signal defeat, calculated to interest the audience by the associations which the song awakens. These poems, of which very few can now be supposed to exist, are not without flashes of genius, but brief, rude, and often obscure, from real antiquity or affected sublimity of diction. The song on the battle of Brunanburgh, preserved in the <hi rend="italic">Saxon Chronicle,</hi>  is a genuine and curious example of this aboriginal style of poetry.</p><p>Even at tllis early period,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> there may be observed a distinction betwixt what may be called the<hi rend="italic">Temporal</hi>  and ⅛∣t-<hi rend="italic">ritual</hi>  romances ; the first destined to the celebration of worldly glory ; the second to recording the deaths of martyrs and the miracles of saints; both which themes unquestionably met with an almost equally favourable reception from their hearers. But although most nations possess, in their early species of literature, specimens of both kinds of romance, the proportion of each, as was naturally to have been expected, differs according as the genius of the people amongst whom they occur leaned towards devotion or military enterprise. Thus, of the Saxon specimens of poetry, which manuscripts still afford us, a very large proportion is devotional, amongst which are several examples of the spiritual romance, but very few, indeed, of those respecting warfare or chivalry. On the other hand, the Norman language, though rich in examples of both kinds of romances, is particularly abundant in that which relates to battle and warlike adventure. The Christian Saxons had become comparatively pacific, while the Normans were certainly accounted the most martial people in Europe.</p><p>However different the spiritual romance may be from the temporal in scope and tendency, the nature of the two compositions did not otherwise greatly differ. The structure of verse and style of composition was the same ; and the induction, even when the most serious subject was undertaken, exactly resembled that with which minstrels introduced their idle tales, and often contained allusions to them. Warton quotes a poem on the Passions, which begins,</p><p>I hereth one lutele tale, that Ich eu wille telle,</p><p>As wi vyndeth hit invrite in the godspelle,</p><p>Nuz hit nouht of Carlemeyne ne of tbe Duzpere,</p><p>Ac of Criste's thruurynge, &amp;c.</p><p>The temporal romances, on the other hand, often commenced by such invocations of the Deity, as would only have been in place when a much more solemn subject was to be agitated. The exordium of the Romance of <hi rend="italic">Ferum-bras</hi>  may serve as an example of a custom almost universal ;</p><p>God in glorye of mightis moost That all things made in sapience,</p><p>By virtue of Word and Holy Gooste,</p><p>Giving to men great excellence, &amp;c.</p><p>The distresses and dangers which the knight endured for the sake of obtaining earthly fame and his mistress’s favour, the saint or martyr was exposed to for the purpose of securing his rank in heaven, and the favour of some beloved and peculiar patron saint. If the earthly champion is in peril from monsters, dragons, and enchantments, the spiritual hero is represented as liable to the constant assaults of the whole invisible world, headed by the ancient dragon himself. If the knight is succoured at need by some favouring fairy or protecting genius, the saint is under the protection not only of the whole heavenly host, but of same one divine patron or patroness who is his especial auxiliary. Lastly, the conclusion of the romance, which usually assigns to the champion a fair realm, an abundant succession, and a train of happy years, consigns to the martyr his fane and altar upon earth, and in heaven his seat among saints and angels, and his share in a blessed eternity. It remains but to say, that the style and language of these two classes do not greatly differ, and that the composers of both employ the same structure of rhythm and of language, and draw their ideas and their incidents from similar sources ; so that, having noticed the existence of the spiritual romance, it is unnecessary for the present to prosecute this subject farther.</p><p>Another early and natural division of these works of fiction seems to have arranged them into <hi rend="italic">Serious</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Comical. </hi>The former were by far the most numerous, and examples of the latter are in most countries comparatively rare. Such a class, however, existed, as proper romances, even if we hold the comic romance distinct from the <hi rend="italic">Contes</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Fabliaux</hi>  of the French, and from such jocular English narratives as the <hi rend="italic">Wife Lαpt in Morals Skin, The Friar and the Boy,</hi>  and similar humorous tales ; of which the reader will find many examples in Ritson’s <hi rend="italic">Ancient English Poetry, </hi>and in other collections. The scene of these <hi rend="italic">gestes</hi>  being laid in low, or at least in ordinary life, they approach in their nature more nearly to the class of novels, and may perhaps be considered as the earliest specimens of tllat kind of composition. But the proper comic romance was that in which the high terms and knightly adventures of chivalry were burlesqued, by ascribing them to clowns or others of a low and mean degree. Such compositions formed, as it were, a parody on the serious romance, to which they bore the same proportion as the antimasque, studiously filled with grotesque, absurd, and extravagant characters, “ entering,” as the stage direction usually informs us, “ to a confused music,” bore to the masque itself, where all was dignified, noble, stately, and harmonious.</p><p>An excellent example of the comic romance is the <hi rend="italic">Tournament of Tottenham,</hi>  printed in Piercy<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s<hi rend="italic">Reliques,</hi>  in which a number of clowns are introduced practising one of these warlike games, which were the exclusive prerogative of the warlike and noble. They are represented making vows to the swan, the peacock, and the ladies ; riding a tilt on their clumsy cart horses,and encountering each other withplough-shares and flails; whilst their defensive armour consisted of great wooden bowls and troughs, by way of helmets and cuirasses. The learned editor seems to have thought this singular composition was like Don Quixote, with which he compares it, a premeditated effort of satire, written to expose the grave and fantastic manners of the serious romance. This is considering the matter too deeply, and ascribing to the author a more critical purpose than he was probably capable of conceiving. It is more natural to suppose that his only ambition was to raise a laugh, by ascribing to the vulgar the manners and exercises of the noble and valiant ; as in the well-known farce of <hi rend="italic">High Life Below Stairs,</hi>  the ridicule is not directed against the manners described, but against the menials who affect those that are only befitting their superiors. The <hi rend="italic">Hunting of the Hare,</hi>  published in the collection formed by the late industrious and accurate Mr. Weber, is a comic romance of the same order. A yeoman informs the inhabitants of a country hamlet that he has found a hare sitting, and invites them to come to course her. They attend, accordingly, with all the curs and mastiffs of their village, and the unsportsman-like manner in which the inexperienced huntsmen and their irregular pack conduct themselves, forms the interest of the piece. It can hardly be supposed the satire is directed against the sport of hunt-</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The religious romances of<hi rend="italic">llarlaαm</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Jehοuρkat</hi>  were composed by John of Damascus in the eighth century.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>