<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>But no religious order was to be established ; and every endowment of a school or college by a Roman Catholic should still be superstitious and unlawful. And no person should thenceforth be summoned to take the oath of supremacy, and the declaration against transubstantiation. Nor should Roman Catholics who had qualified, be removable from London and Westminster ; neither should any peer who had qualified be punishable for coming into the presence or palace of the king or queen. No papist whatever should be any longer obliged to register their names and estates, or to enrol their deeds and wills ; and every Roman Catholic who had qualified, might be permitted to act as a barrister, attorney, or notary. Still, however, Roman Catholics could not sit in parliament, because every member of parliament was required to take the oath of supremacy, and repeat and subscribe the declaration against transubstantiation. Nor could they vote at elections for members of the House of Commons in Great Britain, because, before voting, they must have taken the oath of supremacy. But Roman Catholics in Ireland were permitted to vote at elections, though they could not sit in parliament.</p><p>Most of the remaining restrictions upon Roman Catholics were removed by the Act 10 Geo. IV. cap. 7, entitled, “ An Act for the relief of his Majesty’s Roman Catholic subjecte,” and passed 13th April 1829. By this act it was provided that all the preceding enactments (except as hereinafter excepted) should be repealed ; and that from and after the commencement of the act, it should be lawful for any person professing the Roman Catholic religion, being a peer, or a member of the House of Commons, to sit and vote in either House, upon taking and subscribing the following oath, instead of the oath of supremacy, allegiance, and abjuration :</p><p>“ I, A, B, do sincerely promise and swear, that I w ill be faithful, and bear true allegiance to his Majesty, King , and will defend him to the utmost of my power, against all conspiracies and attempts whatever, which shall be made against his person, crown, or dignity ; and I will do my utmost endeavour to disclose and make known to his Majesty, his heirs and successors, all treasons and traitorous conspiracies which may be formed against him or them ; and I do faithfully promise to maintain, support, and defend, to the utmost of my power, the succession of the crown, which succession, by an Act entitled, ‘ An Act for the further limitation of the Crown, and better securing the rights and liberties of the subject,’ is, and stands limited to the Princess Sophia, Electress of Hanover, and the heirs of her body, being Protestants ; hereby utterly renouncing and abjuring any obedience or allegiance unto any other person claiming or pretending a right to the crown of this realm : and I do further declare, that it is not an article of my faith, and that I do renounce, reject, and abjure the opinion, that princes excommunicated or deprived by the pope, or any other authority of the see of Rome, may be deposed or murdered by their subjects, or by any person whatsoever ; and I do declare that I do not believe that the pope of Rome, or any other foreign prince, prelate, person, state, or potentate, hath or ought to have any temporal or civil jurisdiction, power, superiority, or pre-eminence, directly or indirectly, within this realm. I do swear that I will defend to the utmost of my power, the settlement of property within this realm, as established by the laws : and I do hereby disclaim, disavow', and solemnly abjure any intention to subvert the present church establishment, as settled by law within this realm ; and I do solemnly swear that I will never exercise any privilege to which I am or may become entitled, to disturb or weaken the Protestant religion or Protestant government in the United Kingdom ; and I do solemnly, in the presence of God, profess, testify, and declare, that I do make this declaration, and every part thereof, in the plain and ordinary sense of the words of this oath, without any evasion, equivocation, or mental reservation whatsoever. So help me God.”</p><p>The other principal provisions of the Act are in substance as follows.</p><p>Roman Catholics, upon taking the oath above recited, shall be entitled to vote at elections for members of the House of Commons.</p><p>Roman Catholics may hold civil and military offices under his Majesty, except the office of Lord High Chancellor of Great Britain and, Ireland, Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, or High Commissioner to the General Assembly of the Church of Scotland.</p><p>Roman Catholics to be eligible to become members of lay corporations, upon taking the oath hereby appointed, and such other oaths as may now by law be required of persons becoming membcrs of such corporations ; but such members are not to vote or join in the presentation or appointments to any ecclesiastical benefice.</p><p>No oath to be required from any Roman Catholic to enable him to hold any real or personal property, other than such as may be tendered to any other subjects ; and the oath to be taken by Roman Catholic naval and military officers, to be taken at the same time, and in the same manner as the oaths now required by law from other subjects.</p><p>The Roman Catholic faith in Ireland is professed by more than four-fifths of the people, or, as ascertained in 1834, 6,427,712, out of a total population of 7,943,940; and in Great Britain, though the numbers are not precisely known, they are believed, according to the most moderate calculation, to fall little short of 1,000,000 ; by some they are even estimated at little short of 2,000,000 ; and according to the Catholic Directory, the number of Roman Catholic chapels in England and Wales, in 1839, amounted to 453 ; in Scotland, to79; or, altogether in Great Britain, to 532. Of that number no less than 90 are in Lancashire alone, and 29 inYorkshire ; while Rutland and Huntingdon are the only counties of England where there is none. Besides numerous smaller seminaries, they possess ten colleges ; viz. St. Edmund’s, Old Hall Green, Ware, in Hertfordshire ; Ushawy Durham; St. Mary’s, Birmingham; St. Peter’s and St. Paul’s, both at Prior Park, Bath ; Stony-hurst, Lancashire ; Ampleforth, York; St.Gregory’s, Downside, Bath; German College, Broadway, Worcestershire; St. Mary’s, at Blairs, on Deeside, Aberdeenshire ; and a new college has been nearly finished at Sutton Coldfield, Lancashire. They already number eighteen nunneries and convents : Mecklegate bar, York ; Hammersmith, Middlesex ; Bishop’s House, Winchester ; Taunton Lodge, Somerset ; New Hall, Chelmsford, Essex ; Spettisbury House, Blandford ; Stanbrook Hall, Worcester ; Caverswall Castle, Staffordshire ; Clare Lodge, Yorkshire ; St. Mary’s Priory, Leamington, Warwickshire ; Ashton Hall, Staffordshire ; Llanherne, South Cornwall ; Carmel House, Darlington, Durham ; Court House, Bridgewater, Somerset ; Sales-house, Westbury, Wiltshire ; Hartbury Court, Gloucester ; Presentation, Manchester ; St. Margaret’s, Edinburgh.</p><p>In Ireland the Roman Catholics have a regular hierarchy of archbishops, bishops, deans, &amp;c., and have under them an establishment of upwards of 2000 parochial clergy. England is divided into four, and Scotland into three districts, each under the superintendence of a vicar apostolic, bearing the title of a bisbop <hi rend="italic">in partibus ethnicorum.</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>