<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>more formidable character commenced with the Cisalpine Gauls. Tribes of that great people had repeatedly served as mercenaries against Rome during the Etruscan and Samnite wars. After the conclusion of these wars, the Romans subdued the Livonian Gauls, and planted a colony in their country near Lena. A new influx of the Transalpine Gauls gave courage to their countrymen to renew the war, and a furious contest soon began. The Gauls were at length defeated with great slaughter near Clusium ; and the Romans following up their success, invaded the Gallic country around the Po. The Gauls were again defeated by Marcellus, and compelled to sue for peace, which the Romans granted, establishing at the same time colonies at Placentia and Cremona. It seems worthy of record, that the number of men capable of bearing arms throughout the Roman dominions in Italy, as ascertained by the levies of that dangerous juncture, amounted to 800,000.</p><p>Meanwhile the Carthaginians had been making great exertions to recruittheir strength for another struggle with their great rival. Being prohibited from extending their influence in Sicily, they had sought compensation by attempting the subjugation of Spain. The command of their armies in Spain had devolved upon Hannibal, the son of that Hamilcar who had distinguished himself towards the close of the former war in Sicily. The father of Hannibal had made him swear perpetual hostility to Rome ; and from his boyhood his mind had been continually engaged in devising the ruin of that detested city. He had prosecuted his conquests in Spain with the view of obtaining a veteran army, and a source of auxiliary supply from the warlike nations in that country ; and when his designs were matured, he laid siege to Saguntum, which was understood to be under the protection of Rome. Having treated with contempt the remonstrances of the Roman ambassadors, he took possession of this city. The senate of Carthage having approved of his conduct, war was declared, and both parties prepared for the impending conflict, well knowing that its progress must be sanguinary, and the result ruinous to the one or the other of the rival republics. (As this war is detailed at some length in the article Carthage, we must refer to it for a more particular account of the contest.)</p><p>Hannibal having completed his preparations, set out from Spain, for the invasion of Italy, at the head of a veteran army of 50,000 foot, and 9000 horse. He rapidly traversed Gaul, crossed the Rhone, and commenced the passage of the Alps, led by Insubrian guides. This almost impracticable attempt he achieved in fifteen days ; and, on mustering his army in the plains of Insubria, found it reduced to 20,000 foot, and 6000 horse. His army was soon considerably increased by the Gallic nations ; and, in a comparatively slight encounter near the Ticinus, he worsted the consul Scipio, and soon afterwards completely defeated Sempronius near the Trebia. The victorious Carthaginian then advanced towards Rome, devastating the country through which he was maιching, and making it his object to</p><p>irritate the impetuous spirit of the consul Flaminius. In this he was completely successful, and having drawn him into an ambush at the lake Thrasymenus, entirely defeated him. The consul himself fell in the battle, with 15,000 of his bravest troops, and a great number were taken prisoners. Such was the fury of the encounter, that the combatants were insensible of the shock of an earthquake which happened during the engagement.</p><p>Rome was now in a state of great alarm, having suffered successive defeats in Italy itself, and seeing the victor pursuing his course unchecked through the land. Fabius Maximus was chosen dictator, and immediately adopted a totally different plan of opposing the enemy. He studiously avoided battle, kept his army on the hills, watched Hannibal, cut off his supplies, and did every thing calculated to wear out an invading army, which is necessarily</p><lb/><p>remote from its supplies. By this skilful policy he both saved his own army, and greatly harassed that of his antagonist; and from it was sumamed Cunctator, tlle Delayer.</p><p>The Romans having recovered from their consternation, raised another levy of troops, augmenting their armies to 87,000 men, under the command of Terentius Varro and Æmilius Paullus, of whom the former was rash and headstrong, the latter a cautious imitator of Fabius. Availing himself of the impetuosity of Varro, Hannibal obtained his wish in a general engagement near Cannae in Apulia, where, by his superior skill, he inflicted on the Romans the most dreadful overthrow they had ever sustained since the battle of Alia. The consul Æmilius, and about 45,000 men, of the very flower and strength of his army, were left dead on the field, and about 10,000 were taken in the pursuit. Rome seemed now open to the conqueror ; but his army had suffered too severely to venture on so hazardous an enterprise, and he turned aside to Campania, and wintered in Capua.</p><p>It was manifestly Hannibal’s object to encourage the states of Southern, or Lower Italy, to revolt against Rome, that he might recruit his forces from among them, and so be enabled to continue the war with renewed strength. To a considerable extent he was successful, especially among the Lucanians, Bruttians, Apulians, and even Campanians. He sent Mago to Carthage, to urge them to transmit supplies with all possible despatch, that he might follow up his blow, before Rome should have recovered from her consternation. But though the Barcine party predominated in the Carthaginian senate, such was the influence of the opposite faction, that he obtained only a very limited number of supplies ; and these were to be sent to Spain, whence he might draft a corresponding number of the veteran troops stationed there. This, indeed, was part of Hannibal’s original plan, that he might have at least one resource beyond the caprice of faction, though greatly too remote from the scene of action to be immediately or securely available.</p><p>At Rome the greatest exertions were made to remedy the disastrous consequences of the terrible defeat of Cannae. All ranks and every age, from the boy of seventeen to the retired veteran, were enrolled ; and nearly all the gold ornaments worn by persons of wealth and distinction, were voluntarily given up to meet the exigencies of the state. In a short time an army was raised, superior in numbers to that commanded by Hannibal ; and the celebrated Marcellus was placed at its head. In vain had Hannibal waited at Capua for supplies from Africa ; none were sent, and he was obliged to prepare to contend singly against Roman courage and Roman despair. He sustained a check at Nola ; and not long afterwards Marcellus inflicted on him a partial defeat, by which the courage of the Romans was greatly restored. The tide of success began now to recede from Hannibal. He was unable to prevent the Romans from besieging and taking Capua, though he both attempted to storm their camp, and, failing in that, marched to Rome, to call away their armies for the defence of tile city. They disregarded his threatening demonstration, continued the siege, took the city, and inflicted severe punishment on tlle Capuans.</p><p>The fall of Capua was highly injurious to Hannibal, tending to discourage other Italian states from joining an ally who could not protect them against the fierce vengeance of' Rome. On this account he failed to obtain supplies to his waning army, while the Romans speedily replaced every loss with fresh recruits. These hopes being frustrated, Hannibal entered into an alliance with Philip king of Macedon ; but here the fortunes and the policy of Rome likewise prevailed. The Illyrian war had caused the Romans to be regarded as protectors by the Grecian states, who, a</p></body></text></TEI>