<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and to the squire the solid riches of his good sense, and his peculiar humour ; that humour, which, as it exists in Cervantes, is among the rarest of human qualities,—the very poetry of the comic, founded on tender sympathy with all forms of existence, though displaying itself in sportive reflection ; and issuing not in superficial laughter, but in still smiles, the source of which lies far deeper.</p><p>The characters and fortunes of these contrasted companions he has linked together in such a way, as to impress on the mind the feeling, how indispensable each is to each, as the complement of the other,—the learning, high-mindedness, and strong imagination of the knight as the creative and moving power in human life ; the practical good sense, and even selfishness, of the squire as the controlling force ; from the judicious union of which opposites arises the harmony, and from their separation the discords of society. He paints also, with great knowledge of human life, the effect which these reciprocal influences, constantly exerted on each other through vicinity and a common pursuit, have in modifying even the original character itself, and gradually making the enthusiast more rational, and the common-place man of the world more imaginative. The sound philosophy, the impartial and kindly spirit with which Cervantes has wrought out this conception, in whichjustice is done at once to the higher and the more common elements of our nature ; the flood of humour with which he surrounded it,—which has tempted many a one since the days of Philip IV. to imitate the pantomime of the student on the banks of the Manzanares,—are as obvious to the least refined of readers, as they are models of art worthy of the admiration and profound study of every writer of fiction. Like human life itself, the story unites and harmonizes the opposite extremes of the pathetic and the ludicrous, the vulgar and the elevated,—for from the midst of the comic ground-work, the striking scenes in the Sierra Morena, the episode of Cardenio and Dorothea, the story of the captive, the sweet pastoral of Marcelia, the marriage of Camacho, and many other passages, rise up, rich in pathos, grandeur, or imagination ; so that, in fact, there is no work in which, while the aim at first might appear to be to destroy the romance of life, passages of more purely romantic beauty are to be found. The truth is, that Cervantes, though anxious to explode avicious tastein literature, was far enough from wishing to direct his satire against the creations of high imagination, or against the spirit of chivalry. The admiration he expressed for Amadis and Palmerin shews, that he was not insensible to the beauties by which even this branch of literature was occasionally redeemed. His own adventurous career of glory and misfortune had, no doubt, deeply impressed upon his mind the contrast between the dreams of imagination and the realities of life ; he saw the poetical capabilities which such a contrast afforded,—and he has painted them with an unshrinking, and some may think a merciless hand. But, even beneath the veil of ridicule with which he has invested his crazed and battered hero, we perceive his own unextinguishable love of the exalted principles by which he is actuated ; and the abiding impression which remains with us after the comic effect of the romance has passed away, is, that truth and nobleness of character will continue to command our love and veneration, though displayed in actions with which the world cannot sympathize, and placing their possessor in situations which excite our ridicule, even while his motives attract our admiration.</p><p>Cervantes seems to have intended his moral novels, <hi rend="italic">(Novelas Exemplares),</hi>  to be to Spain what the short tales of Boccaccio and his followers had been to Italy, only with the advantage of a purer morality. They are unequal;</p><p>some being mere satirical trifles, such as the <hi rend="italic">Licentiadο Vidriera;</hi>  others, like the <hi rend="italic">Jealous Estremaduran,</hi>  (which English readers will recognize in the common farce of the Padlock), the <hi rend="italic">Gipsy,</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">Spanish English Lady,</hi>  highly interesting in themselves, and characteristic of Spanish manners, laying open to us, as Sismondi says, the hearts and houses of its inhabitants. One novel, the <hi rend="italic">Tiaflngidα, </hi>(Pretended Aunt,) though undoubtedly written by Cervantes, was not included in the original collection, probably from the disagreeable nature of the subject.</p><p>The remaining work of fiction by Cervantes, the <hi rend="italic">Persi-les</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Sigisrnunda,</hi>  is only remarkable as the last work which he wrote, and as being quite as absurd and extravagant as any of those romances of chivalry against which his powerful satire had been directed. No work has occasioned agreater division of opinion. While someof the Spanish critics speak of it in terms of extravagant praise, it is described by Viardot, a French critic, as “a tissue of episodes interlaced with each other, like those of one of Calderon’s intrigues, consisting of extravagant adventures, silly rencontres, astounding prodigies, preposterous characters, and extravagant sentiments.” It retains little or nothing, indeed, of Cervantes, but the charm of his style. Yet, like Corneille placing his <hi rend="italic">Nicomede</hi>  before the <hi rend="italic">Cid,</hi>  or Milton his <hi rend="italic">Paradise Regained</hi>  before his <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost,</hi>  Cervantes seems to have given the preference to this child of his old age over the master-piece of his manhood.</p><p>The fashion of short novels in the Italian taste, which had been introduced by Cervantes, was followed by Lope, Canizares, Zayas, Montalvan, and by a host of imitators, whose very names the Spanish critic Lampillas declares that he is unable to enumerate. The loss of the catalogue is little to be regretted ; for even among the names which are known, it would be difficult to point out one, even including the great Lope, which rises above mediocrity. Nature, indeed, seems to have given Cervantes his revenge, for the triumph of his rival in the drama, by the failure of Lope as a novelist,—for in this department, the talent and rich invention which he displayed on the stage appeared in a great measure to desert him. The best of his novels is the <hi rend="italic">Fortunas de Diana,</hi>  (Fortunes of Diana), first printed in the Filoména in 1621; next to which we should place his <hi rend="italic">El Zeloso hasta Morir,</hi>  (Jealousy till death); but truth to say, neither are remarkable. Indeed, if we except Cervantes, the same remark which we have ventured to make on Lope is generally applicable to the Spanish novelists. Nearly in proportion to the success of the nation in the creation of an original drama, is its signal deficiency in original contributions to the literature of romance. It is not often, indeed, as Tieck remarks in his preface to Bulow’s <hi rend="italic">Nοvellenbuch,</hi>@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>that the dramatic and novellistic power are found combined in a national literature to the same extent as in England.</p><p>In fact, the only species of prose fiction, with the exception of <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote,</hi>  in which the Spaniards have displayed any thing like original invention, is in the novels written in what is called the <hi rend="italic">Gusto Picaresco,</hi>  or the romances of roguery, of which the first example of any merit, and, with one exception, the best of the whole series, was furnished by the <hi rend="italic">Lazaro de Tarmes</hi>  of the celebrated Don Diego de Mendoza, and is said to have been written by him while a student at Salamanca, and first printed in 1553. It is rather singular, no doubt, to find a man of rank devoting himself to these pictures of want and miserable knavery, or a nation affecting so much external pomp and ceremony relishing these exposures of the real filth, meanness, or starvation which often lurked under the cloak of the whiskered Knight of Calatrava. But the Spanish character is distin</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Das Novellenbuch, Oder hundert Novellen naeh alten Italienischeπ, Spanischen, Franzosichen, Lateinischen, Englischen, und Deut-schen, bearbeitet von Eduard von Bulow. Leipzig, 1834. An excellent authology, from the shorter literature of romance in the above languages ; and not a mere translation, but in many cases a dexterous rificciameι∣to, true to the spirit, while avoiding the dullness or indecency of the original.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>