<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>with the tradition that his very coming to Rome was caused by the pride of the privileged and hereditary order of Lucumones, who had excluded him from participating in the honours to which he thought himself entitled both by birth and merit. Finding at Rome also a patrician class, in the possession of hereditary powers and privileges, he not unnaturally regarded them with jealousy, and endeavoured to call into being a counterbalancing power, by which his influence might not only be maintained, but rendered predominant. The policy pursued by all the kings ofthe Etruscan line entirely accords with this view, so as to give it at least an air of great probability.</p><p>The twelve Etruscan cities which had acknowledged the dominion of Tarquinius, revolted on hearing of his death. They were speedily reduced to subjection by Servius, for which military success he was decreed a triumph by the people. But his triumphs in war were not to be compared with his triumphs in peace. Finding the population of Rome increasing rapidly, he enlarged the pomœrium, or sacred boundary of the city. When first formed by Romulus, the pomœrium included merely the Palatine hill and a portion of the plain at its base. It was extended by Numa so as to include the Capitoline and Quirinal hills, in consequence of which the Sabine town became completely incorporated with the Roman. Servius again enlarged it, so as to bring within its compass the Viminal and Esquiline hills, in addition to those which were the appropriate seats of the great tribes. He finished the work begun by Tarquinius, by building the walls of the city of hewn stone ; and where the hills which he had included in the new addition to the city sloped gently down towards the plain, he fenced them by a large mound of earth, and a moat from which the earth of the mound was dug. For the purpose of consolidating more firmly the union of the races of which the nation was composed, he built the temple of Diana on the Aventine hill, which was to be the chief abode of the Latin population recently brought to Rome. This temple constituted a monument ofthe league between the Roman people and the thirty confederate Latin towns; and, although Romans, Sabines, and Latins sacrificed there in common, yet, as Rome was now recognised as the head of the confederation, tile Romans were allowed to have the precedency.</p><p>But the most important achievements of Servius Tullius, were his alterations of, and additions to, the constitutional principles of the state. Incidental notices have already been given respecting the origin and development of the Roman constitution, so far as the obscurity of the traditional narratives and poetic legends have furnished scope for the treatment of such topics. To these we shall subsequently advert ; but we must now prosecute the historical narrative, so far as it can be called historical ; for there is no part of ancient Rome that more evidently abounds with poetic legends than the conclusion of the kings, and the first years ofthe commonwealth. Fortunately there is no absolute necessity to discard the poetic legends ; for however destitute they may be of what is termed historical truth, there can be no question but that they present a very accurate and lively picture of the times and events in which they are said to have taken place.</p><p>Servius Tullius had given his two daughters in marriage to the two sons of Tarquinius Priscus. These daughters were of tempers very unlike, as were also their husbands. The elder, Tullia, was of a gentle disposition, her younger sister fierce, imperious, and ambitious. Aruns Tarquinius was of a mild and quiet character, his brother Lucius proud, restless, and domineering. To counteract these tempers, Servius had given the gentle princess to the ambitious prince, and made the haughty damsel wife to the mild husband. But this dissimilarity of temper did not produce the effect which he had expected. The fiery tempered of each couple became dissatisfied with the one of gentler nature ; the milder wife and husband perished by the crimes of their aspiring mates, who were speedily united in a second shameless marriage. Then did the aspiring temper of the one urge on the haughty and ambitious heart of the other, till they resolved to make way to the throne by the murder of the good old man, their king and father. To this attempt Lucius was encouraged by the unconcealed dissatisfaction ofthe patricians with the influence obtained by the plebeians in the new constitution. Their dissatisfaction was increased by a rumour that Servius intended to abolis!)The monarchical form altogether, and divide the sway between two consuls, one to be chosen from the patrician,and onefrom the plebeian body. Having formed a strong faction among the patricians, Tarquinius went to the senate-house, seated himself in the royal chair, and summoned the senators to meet king Tarquinius. Servius having heard the rumour, hastened to the senate-house, accused Tarquinius of treason, and laid hold of him to remove him from the royal chair. The usurper instantly seized the old man, dragged him to the door, and threw him with great force down tlle steps. There he lay for a few moments stunned and bleeding with the fall ; then rising slowly staggered away towards his palace. Some ruffians employed by Tarquinius, pursued, overtook, and killed him, leaving the body lying bleeding in the street. Meantime, tidings of what was going on had reached Tullia, who immediately mounted her chariot, drove to the senate-house, and saluted Tarquinius as king. He bade her withdraw from such a tumult; and she, on her return, passed along the same street where lay the bleeding body of her newly murdered father. The mules shrunk, the charioteer stopped short, and pointed out the appalling spectacle. In a loud and imperious tone of voice she commanded him to drive on ; the chariot wheels rolled over the yet warm form, crushing and mangling it as they proceeded, till the spurting blood stained the robes of the more than parricide. From that hour, in remembrance of that hideous scene, the street was called the Vicus Sceleratus, or Wicked Street.</p><p>Tarquinius having thus obtained forcible possession ofthe throne, declined to submit to the form of an election, or to make the customary appeals to the comitia curiata for the ratification of his kingly power. He seized the crown as if it were hereditary ; and seemed resolved to rule without the concurrence of any of the great assemblies. But as he had been raised to the throne by the aid of the patricians, his first act was to gratify them by repealing the privileges which Servius had granted to the plebeians. He suppressed the institution ofthe comitia centuriata, and even prohibited the meetings of the country tribes at the paganalia. But this was only the beginning of his tyranny. He depressed the commons or plebeians ; but he had no intention to permit the power of the patricians to become too strong, especially as he was himself but too well aware of their treachery to the former king. He therefore surrounded himself witll a bodyguard, the ready instruments of his oppression ; and, under colour of justice, banished or put to death, on false accusations, all who were either too powerful or too wealthy to be trusted, or whom he suspected of disaffection to himself. In this manner he reduced the patricians into a state of subjection almost as deep as that into which they had assisted him to reduce the plebeians.</p><p>Being now possessed of nearly despotic powet, he turned his attention to the enlargement ofhis kingdom. He gave his daughter in marriage to Octavius Mamilius of Tusculum, the most powerful of the Latin chiefs ; and partly by intrigues, partly by force, he procured Rome to be acknowledged the head of the Latin confederacy. Herdonius, the only man who dared to oppose his proud demeanour, he caused to be put to death by false accusations, and completely incorporated the Latin troops with those of Rome. The Hernici were also included in this confederacy. One</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>