<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Although the yarn thus produced was of superior strength to hand-spun yarn, yet, as it was attended with additional cost in the manufacture, the invention was laid aside.</p><p>The next part of the invention was in the application of locomotive power to the machinery of the rope-work. Part of this consisted in the application of an endless rope, reaching from end to end of the rope-walk, and moved with considerable speed, to any of the machines, whether stationary like the fore-end wheels, or changing position like the sledges. The application of the endless rope to the sledge was effected by passing a turn round suitable grooved wheels fixed to the sledge, and capable of giving motion to its machinery. By this machinery great advantages were gained, as each revolution of the strands and the rope, and the proper motion of the sledge, were predetermined and fixed by changes of wheels. For this purpose tables were made out to show what wheels were to be used for each kind of rope. Instead of two hundred men, the number usually employed in closing a twenty-one inch cable, fourteen only were required ; and they, with the help of the steam-engine, which was only of eight horse power, were able to coil away the rope when made.</p><p>1799. In the same month Mr Mitchell obtained a patent for a “ method of manufacturing cables, hawsers, or shroud-laid ropes, and other cordage, on scientific principles.”</p><p>These principles consisted in combining by twisting the integral yarns of a strand, in numbers of two, three, or more, previous to their being formed into the strand, and thereby lessening the strain on the external yarns when ultimately formed into a rope. The strain on the external yarns would doubtless be by this method lessened, but the number of yarns exposed to external injury would, at the same time, be increased. The ropes formed on this principle were by the patentee termed selvagee cordage.</p><p>1799. August 20th, Mr Huddart look out a patent for an improvement on his apparatus of 1793. In this the registering apparatus, instead of being moved up the walk, was, like Mr Chapman’s press-blocks, fixed to the tackle-board, and the machinery for twisting thc strands was stationary, and also contained apparatus for winding the strands upon reels as they were formed.</p><p>1799.    In the same month Mr Grimshaw obtained a patent for improvements in rope-machinery, which consisted, first, in dressing the hemp preparatory to spinning; secondly, in winding up the yarn ; thirdly, in preparing the yarns for tarring ; and, fourthly, in laying the ropes or cordage. The first step appears to be best entitled to notice. The hemp in this was conducted to rotatory hackles through conical fluted rollers, by which means the hemp was equally mixed.</p><p>1800.    July 1st, Mr Huddart took another patent for further improvements in the manufacture of cordage. “ A considerable expense,” says the patentee, “ is attached to having the tarred yarns wound upon bobbins ; and also the tar, especially when the ropes are laid in cold weather, is not sufficiently incorporated amongst the yarns to render it compact for durability, whether registered or laid in the common way. In order to obviate these inconveniences, I have invented a method of registering the strands of ropes during the operation of tarring the yarns, which may be effected in the following manner. The white yarns must be wound separately on reels or bobbins, and placed upon a frame or otherwise, so tllat the yarns may be delivered from them with as small and equal a tension as possible, and to pass under rollers, or through holes, or between separating rods of wood or metal, to be guided into the tar, when sufficiently heated in the kettle, and thence to the register, separate from each other, to prevent entanglement, until they enter the tube, which must be placed at the end of the tar-kettle opposite to that where the bobbins of white yarns are placed. The registering tube now acts in a double capacity, viz. in forming the strand fair, as in ordinary</p><p>cases, and in acting as a nipper to squeeze out the superfluous tar. The strands are now twisted as before, and the twisting forces out some more tar, which must be cleared off by making the strand pass through the common adjustable nipper plate.”</p><p>1801. July 16th, Mr William Hoard obtained a patent for “ a portable machine for manufacturing ropes and cordage of any length in a short space, particularly adapted for shipping.” This machine consists of separate reels, one containing the full length and number of yarns for a strand, from which reel they are drawn out to such distance as the two reels can conveniently be placed asunder, and are attached to the other, which is then empty, one of the reels being in a sledge or moveable frame. The process then begins by twisting the intermediate length of strand, until the reels have approached to each other the usual proportional space, namely, one fifth. The length of strand thus made is then wound up on the second described reel, and so much is let off from the first reel as to admit of their being at their greatest distance asunder, which proecss is necessarily continued until the whole strand be made, and wound up on the second reel. Lastly, three strands thus made have their ends united to a fourth reel placed opposite to them at its greatest convenient distance. By these four reels, the process of making the rope is carried on similarly to that of making a strand, except in the use of a top to regulate the progress of the twist of the rope in its approach to the three strand reels.</p><p>In 1801, Mr Archibald Thompson of Plough Court, Lombard Street, took out a patent for “ certain new or improved machinery, for the purpose of spinning rope yarn and sailcloth yarn, and for laying and making ropes and cordage.” Mr Thompson’s invention includes the whole process of spinning, tarring, and laying the cordage. Preparatory to spinning, he draws out the hemp into a long sliver, by different sets of chain hackles, moving with progressively greater speed ; and in the end the sliver is spun by a spindle with its plyer and bobbin into a thread. The threads remain wound up on their bobbins until wanted to be made into a rope, tarred or untarred. The bobbins are then, according to the number of yams wanted in a strand, placed so as to form two circles of the same diameter, round an open cylinder consisting of three hoops or rings, distant from each other the length of a bobbin, and placed near to one end of a long horizontal axis ; and, if the rope be to be tarred, thc yarns are led through a ring of a few inches diameter, near that end of the described open cylinder which has the spare length of axis projecting from it. The yams are then diverged in different degrees, so as to form, when passed longitudinally through an open cylindrical frame of several feet in length, so many different concentric circles round the axis mentioned, as there are different shells or concentric coats of yarns in the strand ; and from the further extremity of this last-mentioned cylindrical frame, the yarns are concentrated to one focus at the extremity of the axis, which is there concave, and has an opening through which the yarns pass to the machine which is to twist them into a strand, and draw them forward to be coiled up within itself. At the focal point described, there are nippers to express the tar from the yarns, which is put into them in the following manner, viz. the last-mentioned open cylinder, between the ring from which the yarns enter to it, and the perforation of the axis where they concentre and quit it, lies over a tar-kettle, and has a portion of its lower half immersed in the tar, just so far as to imbue either the whole or any portion of the yams with tar, as may be deemed expedient. This cylinder must, of course, turn round with such a convenient degree of speed as not to let the yarns be drawn off the cylinder before it comes in their rotation to pass through the tar. When the full length of strand is made, the twist of which is principally given by the revo-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>