<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of both. But upon the return of Cæsar, this contest was brought to a termination. The two rivals began to perceive that their power was in danger of being equalled, if not surpassed by a third ; and Cæsar, to lull their jealousy asleep, till his own designs should be matured, pointed out to them the risk they incurred of merely ruining each other, if they did not speedily compose their differences. He at first paid most court to Pompey, as his most formidable rival, and affected devotion to his cause, till by his aid, seconding his own rising fame, he procured the consulship. During his tenure of that office, he still more increased his popularity by the enactment of several salutary laws, and some of more ambiguous character. In particular, he carried an Agrarian law for the distribution of large tracts of land in Campania among the indigent people, and had the address, in spite of the opposition ofthe senate, to induce both Pompey and Crassus to aid him in passing it, and to act as commissioners in the distribution, thus sharing the odium of the measure, while the entire popularity remained his own.</p><p>The schemcs of Cæsar required a new element for their further development. He well knew that he could not gain the supreme power without an army to support his pretensions, or depend on an army without having previously made it completely his own. It was therefore necessary for him to obtain the command of a warlike province, and that, if possible, adjacent to Rome. Gaul was exactly suited to his purpose ; and he now directed his efforts to the obtaining of that appointment. Neither Pompey nor Crassus seems to have penetrated his views ; and a secret but strict alliance was formed between these three powerful and ambitious men, commonly known by the name of “ the first triumvirate.” The province of Gaul was allotted to Cæsar for a term of five years, while Pompey and Crassus remained at Rome ; and the compact between Cæsar and Pompey was confirmed by the latter marrying the daughter of the former.</p><p>To complete the triumph of the triumvirs over the independent party in the senate, Cato was appointed to the government of Cyprus, and Cicero was banished through the intrigues of the infamous Clodius, who had obtained permission to relinquish his patrician rank, that he might be eligible for the tribuneship ; an example which was afterwards repeatedly followed by designing demagogues. After having accomplished this object, Clodius became so troublesome even to his own party, that to keep him in check, Pompey procured the recall of Cicero from exile, which he could not effect without the strenuous aid of the tribune Milo.</p><p>In the mean time, Cæsar had arrested the migration of the Helvetians, expelled the Germans from Gaul, subdued the Belgæ, the Aquitani, the Nervii, and other warlike Gaulish nations, and had also both penetrated into Germany itself, and crossed the sea to Britain, till then almost unknown to the Romans. By these exploits he raised his military reputation to an equality with that of Pompey himself, and formed a hardy and well-disciplined veteran army, entirely devoted to his will. Nor was he inattentive to the course of events at Rome. He found means to maintain his influence there to such a degree as to rouse the dormant jealousy of his rivals, and almost to precipitate the struggle. A reconciliation, however, took place ; and he obtained a renewal of his command in Gaul for another term of five years, while Crassus chose Syria for his province, and Pompey Spain and Africa. Crassus appears to have chosen Syria for the purpose of gratifying his passion for the acquisition of wealth ; and Pompey preferred those provinces which he could govern by his lieutenants, while he remained at Rome to rule the republic.</p><p>This new arrangement was not destined to a lengthened existence. On his arrival in Asia, Crassus found himself compelled to enter into hostilities with the Parthians, to whose vicinity the overthrow of Mithridates had extended the sway of the republic in that continent. Even to the best of the Roman generals, the Parthians would have proved a formidable foe ; but Crassus was altogether destitute of the military talents necessary for the conduct of such a war. His army was entirely routed in Mesopotamia, and himself taken prisoner and put to death soon after the battle, by the Parthian general Surena.</p><p>About the same time died Cæsar’s daughter, the wife of Pompey ; and thus not only was the triumvirate dissolved by the death of Crassus, but the alliance between the two survivors was greatly weakened by the death of Julia, who had possessed considerable influence over both her father and her husband. The period for tlle termination of Cæsar’s command in Gaul had nearly arrived; and all things seemed to indicate the approach of a mortal crisis.</p><p>Each party strove to throw on bis rival the odium of beginning the fatal contest; and its actual commencement was for a time retarded by their mutual machinations. At length it began by Cæsar’s demanding permission to hold the consulship while absent. This was strenuously opposed by Pompey, and advocated by Cæsar’s partizans, Curio, Marcus Antonius, and Quintus Cassius, tribunes of the people. Curio succeeded in placing Pompey in what is termed, “ a false position,” by proposing that both he and Cæsar should resign their offices and retire into private life, which he averred that Cæsar was willing to do. Repeated but insincere offers were made by both parties for an accommodation ; but the senate at length passed a decree, commanding Cæsar to disband his army before a certain specified day, under the penalty of being declared a public enemy. The two tribunes, Antony and Cassius, interposed their veto ; but their prerogative was violcntly set aside, and the decree passed hy a large majority. Upon this Antony and Cassius fled from the city disguised as slaves, and sought refuge in the camp of Cæsar, who shewed to his soldiers the tribunes thus insulted by his enemies at Rome.</p><p>The conduct of Cæsar had hitherto appeared to be chiefly defensive, that of Pompey and his party aggressive. It had now become necessary for Cæsar either to relinquish his long-cherished visions of ambition, or to become the assailant. He had completely foreseen and anticipated the crisis. At the head of but a small division of his army, not sufficient to create alarm, he had approached the banks of the Rubicon, the boundary of Italy proper, on the side of Cisalpine Gaul, and which he could not cross in a hostile manner without avowing himself a traitor to his country. His schemes were ripe fbr execution, his enemies were thoroughly roused, concealment was no longer practicable, his troops had declared their readiness to support their general and avenge the wrongs of the tribunes, all things urged him to the crisis ; but the dark destinies of file fateful hour hung heavy upon Cæsar’s spirit.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> He retired early from a supper where he had entertained some of his principal officers, and paced to and fro on the banks of the Rubicon, in the deep silence of midnight, oppressed with thought. It probably was not the ruin to himself, should he now hesitate, still less the perils of the undertaking ; it was the long, black, direful train of miseries tllat must sweep remorselessly over his country and the world, all summed up, concentrated, and rendered almost visibly present in the one simple and brief act of that most awful hour, this it was that shook and appalled the heart of even the mighty Cæsar. He at length exclaimed, “ the die is cast,” sprung furiously across the slender stream, and spread to the morning breeze the banner of civil war.</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  See Suetonius in Vita Jul. Cæs.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>