<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>seen that the weight of the roof, which we may call W, is to the horizontal thrust at C as BF to EC ; and if we ex-</p><p>W × EC</p><p>press tllis thrust by T, we have T = —<hi rend="sub">sτi</hi>—. We may Br</p><p>at present consider BC as a lever moveable round the joint B, and pulled at C in the direction EC by the horizontal thrust, and held back by the string pulling in the direction CD. Suppose that the forces in the directions EC and CD are in equilibrio, and let us find the force S by which the string CD is strained. These forces must, by the property of the lever, be inversely as the perpendiculars drawn from the centre of motion on the lines of their direction. Therefore BG : BE=T : S, andS =T X = W × J⅛∣∣.</p><p>Therefore the strain upon each of the ties DA and DC is always greater than the horizontal thrust or the strain on a simple tie-beam. This would be no great inconvenience, because the smallest dimensions that we could give to these ties, so as to procure sufficient fixtures to the adjoining pieces are always sufficient to withstand this strain. But although the same may be said of the iron straps which make the ultimate connections, there is always some hazard of imperfect work, cracks, or flaws which are not perceived. We can judge with tolerable certainty of the soundness of a piece of timber, but cannot say so much of a piece of iron. Moreover, there is a prodigious strain excited on the king-post when BG is very short in comparison of BE, namely, the force compounded of the two strains S and S on the ties DA and DC.</p><p>But there is another defect from which the straight tie-beam is entirely free. All roofs settle a little. When this roof settles and the points B and D descend, the legs BA, BC must spread further out, and thus a pressure outwards is excited on the walls. It is seldom therefore that this kind of roof can be executed in this simple form, and other contrivances are necessary for counteracting this supervening action on the walls. Fig. 27 is one of the best which</p><p>we have seen, and is executed with great success in the circus or equestrian theatre (now, 1809, a concert-room) in Edinburgh, the width being sixty feet. The pieces EF and ED help to take off some of the weight, and by their greater uprightness they exert a smaller thrust on the walls. The beam DrZ is also a sort of truss-beam, having something of the same effect. Mr Price has given another very judicious one of this kind (British Carpenter, plate IK, fig. C), from which the tie-beam may be taken away, and there will remain very little thrust on the walls. Those which he has given in the following plate, K, are, in our opinion, very faulty. The whole strain in these last roofs tends to break the rafters and ties transversely, and the fixtures of the ties are also not well calculated to resist the strain to which the pieces are exposed. We hardly think that these roofs could be executed.</p><p>It is scarcely necessary to remind the reader, that in all that we have delivered on this subject, we have attended only to the construction of the principal rafters or trusses.</p><p>In small buildings all the rafters are of one kind ; but in great buildings the whole weight of the covering is made to rest on a few principal rafters, which are connected by beams placed horizontally, and either mortised into them or scarfed on them. These are called <hi rend="italic">purlins.</hi>  Small rafters aro laid from purlin to purlin ; and on these the laths for tiles, or the skirting-boards for slates, are nailed. Thus the covering does not immediately rest on the principal frames. This allows some more liberty in their construction, because the garrets can be so divided that the principal rafters shall be in the partitions, and the rest left unencumbered This construction is so far analogous to that of floors which are constructed with girders, binding, and bridging joists.</p><p>It may appear presuming in us to question the propriety of this practice. There are situations in which it is unavoidable, as in the roofs of churches, which can be allowed to rest on some pillars. In other situations, where partition-walls intervene at a distance not too great for a stout purlin, no principal rafters are necessary, and the whole may be roofed with short rafters of very slender scantling. But in a great uniform roof, which has no intermediate supports, it requires at least some reasons for preferring this method of carcass-roofing to the simple method of making all the rafters alike. The method of carcass-roofing requires the selection of the greatest logs of timber, which are seldom of equal strength and soundness with thinner rafters. In these the outside planks can be taken off, and the best part alone worked up. It also exposes to all the defects of workmanship in the mortising of purlins, and thc weakening of the rafters by tllis very mortising ; and it brings an additional load of purlins and short rafters. A roof thus constructed may surely be compared with a floor of similar construction. Here there is not a shadow of doubt, that if the girders were sawed into planks, and these planks laid as joists sufficiently near for carrying the flooring boards, they will have the same strength as before, except so much as is taken out of the timber by the saw. This will not amount to one-tenth part of the timber in the binding, bridging, and ceiling joists, which are an additional load, and all the mortises and other joinings are so many diminutions of the ctrength of the girders ; and as no part of a carpenter’s work requires more skill and accuracy of execution, we are exposed to many chances of imperfection. But, not to rest on these considerations, however reasonable they may appear, we shall relate an experiment made by one on whose judgment and exactness we can depend.</p><p>Two models of floors were made, eighteen inches square, of the finest uniform deal, which had been long seasoned. The one consisted of simple joists, and the other was framed with girders, binding, bridging, and ceiling joists. The plain joists of the one contained the same quantity of timber with the girders alone of the other, and both were made by a most accurate workman. They were placed in wooden trunks eighteen inches square within, and rested on a strong projection on the inside. Small shot was gradually poured in upon the floors, so as to spread uniformly over them. The plain joisted floor broke down with 487 pounds, and the carcass floor with 327. The first broke without giving any warning, and the other gave a violent crack when 294 pounds had been poured in. A trial had been made before, and the loads were 341 and 482 ; but the models having been made by a less accurate hand, it was not thought a fair specimen of the strength which might be given to a carcass floor.</p><p>The only argument of weight which we can recollect in favour of the compound construction of roofs is, that the plain method would prodigiously increase the quantity of work, would admit nothing but long timber, which would greatly add to the expense, and would make the garrets a mere thicket of planks. We admit this in its full force ;</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>