<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>two members to the Irish parliament till the Union. Here are all the buildings connected with the local administration of justice. The county court-house is a spacious and well-arranged edifice, with an elegant Grecian-Doric portico in front. The county prison, built on the radiating plan, contains accommodations for upwards of a hundred prisoners, and has a tread-mill. The county infirmary, which also contains a fever hospital and infirmary, admits an average of three hundred patients annually. The modern ecclesiastical buildings are not remarkable for architectural elegance. The parish church is a neat structure. The old court-house has been converted into a Roman Catholic chapel. The town is a place of very limited trade, except in that of grain, large quantities of which are sent to Lanesborough to be exported thence by means of the Royal Canal or the Shannon. The population in 1831 was 3306. That of other towns the number of whose inhabitants exceeded 1000, was Boyle, the largest and most commercial in the county, 3433 ; Strokestoun, 1548 ; and Elphin, in which there is a poor cathedral to a very wealthy diocese, and a diocesan school, 1507. That part of the town of Athlone on the Shannon, in which the fortified magazines and works intended for the defence of the pass of the Shannon have been built, is on the Roscommon side of the river. The greater part of the town of Ballinasloe, celebrated for its great annual fair of sheep and horned cattle, is also in this county, (c. p.)</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roscommon, </hi><hi rend="italic">Wentworth Dillon, Earl of,</hi>  a celebrated poet of the seventeenth century, was the son of James Dillon, earl of Roscommon, and was born in Ireland, under the administration of the first Earl of Strafford, who was his uncle, and from whom he received the name of <hi rend="italic">Wentworth</hi>  at his baptism. He passed his infancy in Ireland ; after which the Earl of Strafford sent for him into England, and placed him at his own seat in Yorkshire, under the tuition of Dr Hall, afterwards bishop of Norwich, who instructed him in Latin, without teaching him the common rules of grammar, which he could never retain in his memory, though he learned to write in that language with classical elegance and propriety. On the Earl of Strafford’s being impeached, he went to complete his education at Caen in Normandy; and after some years he travelled to Rome, where he became acquainted with the most valuable remains of antiquity, and in particular was well skilled in medals, and learned to speak Italian with such grace and fluency that he was frequently taken for a native. He returned to England soon after the Restoration, and was made captain of the band of pensioners ; but a dispute with the lord privy-seal about a part of his estate obliged him to resign his post, and revisit his native country, where the Duke of Ormond appointed him captain of the guards. He was unhappily very fond of gaming ; and as he was returning to his lodgings from a gaming-table in Dublin, he was attacked in the dark by three ruffians, who were employed to assassinate him. The earl defended himself with such resolution, that he had despatched one of the aggressors, when a gentleman passing that way took his part, and disarmed another, on which the third sought his safety in flight. This generous assistant was a disbanded officer of good family and fair reputation, but reduced to poverty ; and his lordship rewarded his bravery by resigning to him his post of captain of the guards. Heat length returned to London, when he was made master of the horse to the Duchess of York, and married the Lady Frances, the eldest daughter of Richard earl of Burlington, and the widow of Colonel Courtney. Here he distinguished himself by his wτitings ; and, in imitation of those learned and polite assemblies with which he had been acquainted abroad, he began to form a society for refining and fixing the standard of the English language, in which his great friend Dryden was a principal assistant. This scheme, however, was entirely defeated by the religious commotions which ensued on King</p><lb/><p>James’s accession to the throne. In 1683 he was seized with the gout ; and being too impatient of pain, he permitted a bold French empiric to apply a repelling medicine, in order to give him immediate relief. This drove the distemper into his bowels, and in a short time put a period to his life. He died in the month of January 1684, and was buried with great pomp in Westminster Abbey.</p><p>His poems, which are not numerous, are in the body of English poetry collected by Dr Johnson. His Essay on Translated Verse, and his translation of Horace’s Art of Poetry, have been much commended. Upon the latter, Waller addressed a poem to his lordship when he was seventy-five years of age. “ In the writings of this nobleman we view,” says Fenton, “ the image of a mind naturally serious and solid ; richly furnished and adorned with all the ornaments of art and science ; and these ornaments unaffectedly disposed in the most regular and elegant order. His imagination might probably have been more fruitful and sprightly, if his judgment had been less severe ; but that severity (delivered in a masculine, clear, succinct style) contributed to make him so eminent in the didactical manner, that no man with justice can affirm he was equalled by any of our nation, without confessing at the same time that he is inferior to none. In some other kinds of writing his genius seems to have wanted fire to attain the point of perfection ; but who can attain it ?” He was a man of an amiable disposition, as well as a good poet ; as Pope, in his Essay on Criticism, has testified in the following lines :</p><p>Roscommon not more learned than good,</p><p>With manners generous as his noble blood :</p><p>To him the wit of Greece and Rome was known,</p><p>And every author's merit but his own.</p><p>We must allow of Roscommon, what Fenton has not mentioned so distinctly as he ought, and what is yet very much to his honour, that he is perhaps the only correct writer in verse before Addison ; and that, if there are not so many or so great beauties in his composition as in those of some contemporaries, there are at least fewer faults. Nor is this his highest praise. For Pope has celebrated him as the only moral writer of King Charles’s reign.</p><p>Unhappy Dryden ! in all Charles’s days,</p><p>Roscommon only boasts unspotted lays.</p><p>“ Of Roscommon’s works,” as Dr Johnson has remarked, “ the judgment of the public seems to be right. He is elegant, but not great ; he never labours after exquisite beauties, and he seldom falls into gross faults. His versification is smooth, but rarely vigorous ; and his rhymes are remarkably exact. He improved taste, if he did not enlarge knowledge, and may be numbered among the benefactors to English literature.</p><p>ROSE. See Rosa.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RosΕ of Jericho,</hi>  so called because it grow<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s in the plain of Jericho, though it did not originally flourish there. It has perhaps been so named by travellers who did not know that it was brought from Arabia Petræa. Rose-bushes are frequently found in the fields about Jericho ; but they are of a specics much inferior to those so much extolled in Scripture, the flowers of which some naturalists pretend to have in their cabinets.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Roses, </hi><hi rend="italic">Ottar</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Essential Oil of,</hi>  is obtained from roses by simple distillation. A quantity of fresh roses, for example forty pounds, is put in a still with sixty pounds of water, the roses being left as they are with their calyxes, but with the stems cut close. The mass is then well mixed together with the hands, and a gentle fire is made under the still ; when the water begins to grow hot, and fumes to rise, the cap of the still is put on, and the pipe fixed ; the chicks are then well luted with paste, and cold water put on the refrigeratory at top. The receiver is also adapted at the end of the pipe ; and the fire is continued under</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>