<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>We are naturally led to consider in order the following articles.</p><p>1.    The effects of permanent additions of every kind to the waters of a river, and the most effectual methods of preventing or removing inundations.</p><p>2.    The effects of weirs, bars, sluices, and keeps of every kind, for raising the surface of a river ; and the similar effects of bridges, piers, and every thing which contracts the section of the stream.</p><p>3.    The nature of canals ; how they differ from rivers in respect of origin, discharge, and regimen, and what conditions are necessary for their most perfect construction.</p><p>4.    Canals for draining land, and drafts or canals of derivation from the main stream. The principles of their construction, so that they may suit their intended purposes; and the change which they produce on the main stream, both above and below the point of derivation.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Of the Effects of Permanent Additions to the Waters of a River.</hi></p><p>From what has already been said, it appears that to every kind of soil or bed there corresponds a certain velocity of current, too small to hurt it by digging it up, and too great to allow the deposition of the materials which it is carrying along. Supposing this known for any particular situation, and the quantity of water which the channel must of necessity discharge, we may wish to learn the smallest slope which must be given to this stream, that the waters may run with the required velocity. This suggests,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Pbob. I.</hi>@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  Given the discharge D of a river, and V its velocity of regimen : required the smallest slope r, and the dimensions of its bed.</p><p>Since the slope must be the smallest possible, the bed must have the form which will give the greatest mean depth <hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  and should therefore be the trapezium formerly described ; and its area and perimeter are the same with those of a rectangle whose breadth is twice its height A. These circumstances gives us the equation γ = 2A<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. For</p><p>the area of the section is twice the square of the height, and the discharge is the product of this area and the velocity. Therefore    = A and    = the breadth δ.</p><p>The formula of uniform motion gives √<hi rend="sup">,</hi>s — L<hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  + 1∙6</p><p>297 (√rf-0∙1) <hi rend="sub">τ</hi> , <hi rend="sub">j</hi><hi rend="italic">e</hi>  /5 o .    . ∙. ι</p><p>= ----=--—. Instead of √&lt;Z— 0∙ 1, put lts equal</p><p>V + 0∙3(√tf-0∙1)</p><p>— 0∙l, and every thing being known in the second</p><p>side of this equation, we easily get the value of ί by a few trials after the following manner : Suppose that the second side is equal to any number, such as 9. First suppose that √s is = 9, whence s = 81. Then the hyperbolic logarithm of √81 + 1∙6 or √82∙6 is 2∙21. Therefore we have <hi rend="italic">V s </hi>■— L√i+l∙6 = 9 — 2∙21 = 6∙79 ; whereas it should have been = 9. Therefore say 6∙79 : 9 = 9 : 11∙9 nearly. Now suppose that <hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  is = 11∙9, whence <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  = 141∙6. Then L√l41∙6+1∙6 = L√143<hi rend="sup">7</hi>2=2∙482 nearly, and 11∙9-2∙482 = 9∙408, whereas it should be 9. Now we find that changing the value of<hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  from 9 to 11∙9 has changed the answer from 6∙79 to 9∙408, or a change of 2∙9 in our assumption has made a change of 2∙6l8 in the answer, and has left an error of 0∙408. Therefore say 2∙618 : 0∙408 = 2∙9 : 0∙452. Then taking 0∙452 from 11∙9, we have, for our next assumption or value of <hi rend="italic">Vs,</hi>  Il∙448, whence <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  = 13l∙L Now 131*1 + 1∙6 = 132∙7, and L √132∙7 = 2∙444 nearly, and 11<hi rend="sup">-</hi>448 — 2∙444 = 9∙004 in place of 9, whence it is inferred that this last value of √s = 11 ∙ 448 is sufficiently exact. This may serve as a specimen of the trials by which we may avoid an intricate analysis.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. II. Given the discharge D, the slope </hi><hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  and the velocity V, of permanent regimen, to find the dimensions of the bed.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  be the width and <hi rend="italic">y</hi>  the depth of the channel, and</p><p>S the area of the section. This must be = ?, which is</p><p>therefore = <hi rend="italic">xy.</hi>  The denominator <hi rend="italic">s</hi>  being given, we may make <hi rend="italic">Vs —</hi>  L <hi rend="italic">Vs</hi>  + 1∙6 = +<hi rend="sup">,</hi>B, and the formula of mcan</p><p>velocity will give V =    — 0<hi rend="sup">,</hi>3 (√5—0∙l),</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">√<hi rend="sup">b</hi></hi></p><p>which we may express thus: V = (√√—0∙1) Qyβ—0∙3^,</p><p>V    -    V</p><p>which gives —-<hi rend="italic">=(Vd-</hi>0-1); and,finally, —-</p><p>+ 0∙l=√f∕∙</p><p>Having thus obtained what we call the mean depth, we may suppose the section rectangular. This gives <hi rend="italic">d=-~^-.</hi></p><p>Thus we have two equations, <hi rend="italic">S = xy</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">d = </hi>—r=-∙ <hi rend="italic">x+2y</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">∕i</hi>  g ∖  2    g</p><p>From which we obtain <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  = V    <hi rend="italic">—^~^^2d'</hi>  ^nd</p><p>g</p><p>having the breadth <hi rend="italic">x</hi>  and area S, we have <hi rend="italic">y— -.</hi>  And then</p><p>we may change this for the trapezium often mentioned.</p><p>These are the chief problems on this part of the subject, and they enable us to adjust the slope and channel of a river which receives any number of successive permanent additions by the influx of other streams. This last informs us of the rise which a new supply will produce, because the additional supply will require additional dimensions of the channel ; and as this is not supposed to increase in breadth, the addition will be in depth. The question may be proposed in the following problem.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Prob. III. Given the slope </hi><hi rend="italic">s,</hi>  the depth and the base of a rectangular bed (or a trapezium), and consequently the discharge D, to find how much the section will rise if the discharge be augmented by a given quantity.</p><p>Let A be the height after the augmentation, and <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  the width for the rectangular bed. We have in any uniform</p><p>V</p><p>current <hi rend="italic">Vd =    --</hi>(- 0∙1. Raising this to a square,</p><p>√B~ °'<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p>and putting for <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  and V their values —    and and</p><p>.    297    <hi rend="sub">τ</hi>, ,    <hi rend="italic">wh</hi></p><p>making — 0∙3 = K, the equation becomes</p><p>∕ D ∖*</p><p>= (    + 0T ] . Raising the second member to a square,</p><p>and reducing, we obtain a cubic equation, to be solved in the usual manner.</p><p>But the solution would be extremely complicated. We may obtain a very expeditious and exact approximation from this consideration, that a small change in one of the dimensions of the section will produce a much greater change in the section and the discharge than in the mean</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>In these problems and examples the measures are expressed in French inches. For English inches the co-efficient 307 must be used in place of 297∙</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>