<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Therefore the mean depth, which is the quotient of the area divided by the border, is the same in both ; and this is the case, whatever is the width BE at the bottom, or even though there be no rectangle such as 6BEe interposed between the slant sides.</p><p>Of all rectangles, that whose breadth is twice the height, or which is half of a square, gives the greatest mean depth If, therefore, FK be double of FD, the trapezium ABEC, which has the same area, will have the largest mean depth of any such trapezium, and will be the best form of a channel for conveying running waters. In this case, we have AC = 10, AH = 3, and BE = 2. Or we may say that the best form is a trapezium, whose bottom width is <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">r</hi>l of</hi>  the depth, and whose extreme width is <hi rend="sup">1</hi>¼<hi rend="sup">,</hi>. This form approaches very near to that which the torrents in the hills naturally dig for themselves in uniform ground, where their action is not checked by stones which they lay bare, or which they deposit in their course. This shows us, and it will be fully confirmed by and by, that the channel of a river is not a fortuitous thing, but has a relation to the consistency of the soil and velocity of the stream.</p><p>A rectangle, whose breadth is ¼ of the depth of water, will therefore have the same depth with a triangle whose surface width is ⅝ of its vertical depth ; for this is the dimensions when the rectangle ⅛BEe is taken away.</p><p>Let A be the area of the section of any channel, <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  its width (when rectangular), and <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  its depth of water. Then</p><p>a</p><p>what we have called its mean depth, or rf, will be --„ ,,</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">r</hi>    w</hi>  + 2 Λ</p><p>= —=r∙ Or if <hi rend="italic">g</hi>  expresses the ratio of the width to <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  + 2 A    <hi rend="sup">71</hi></p><p>the depth of a rectangular bed, that is, if <hi rend="italic">q</hi>  = -y, we have</p><p>a very simple and ready expression for the mean depth,</p><p>either from the width or depth. For <hi rend="italic">d = —<hi rend="sup">w</hi>  ■ ,</hi>or <hi rend="italic">d = <hi rend="sup">r</hi>l + <hi rend="sup">2</hi></hi></p><p>g<hi rend="sup">h</hi></p><p>«7 + 2</p><p>Therefore, if the depth were infinite, and the width finite,</p><p>we should have <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  = 4y ; or if the width be infinite, and the</p><p>depth finite, we have <hi rend="italic">d = h.</hi>  And these are the limits of the values of <hi rend="italic">d;</hi>  and therefore in rivers whose width is always great in comparison of the depth, we may without much error take their real depth for their hydraulic mean depth. Hence we derive a rule of easy recollection, and w<hi rend="sup">τ</hi>hich will at all times give us a very near estimate of the velocity and expense of a running stream, viz.<hi rend="italic">that the velocities are nearly as the square roots of the depths. </hi>We find this confirmed by many experiments of Miche-lotti.</p><p>Also, when we are allowed to suppose this ratio of the velocities and depths, that is, in a rectangular canal of great breadth and small depth, we shall have the quantities discharged nearly in the proportion of the cubes of the velocities. For the quantity discharged <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is as the velocity and area jointly, that is, as the height and velocity jointly, because when the width is the same the area is as the height. Therefore, rve have <hi rend="italic">d==h v.</hi>  But, by the above remark, <hi rend="italic">h == ν'.</hi>  Therefore, <hi rend="italic">d = v<hi rend="sup">3</hi>  ;</hi>  and this is confirmed by the experiments of Bossut, vol. ii. 236. Also, because <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  is as <hi rend="italic">v h,</hi>  when <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  is constant, and by the above remark (allowable when <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  is very great in proportion to <hi rend="italic">h) v</hi>  is as √<hi rend="italic">h,</hi></p><p>we have <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  as <hi rend="italic">h∙Jh,</hi>  or ∕t-, or the squares of the discharges proportional to the cubes of the heights in rectangular beds, and in their corresponding trapeziums.</p><p>1. Knowing the mean depth and the proportion of the</p><p>width and real depth, we can determine the dimensions of 2&lt;∕</p><p>the bed, and we have <hi rend="italic">w = q d</hi>  + 2 <hi rend="italic">d,</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">h = d</hi>  -1--.</p><p><hi rend="italic">g</hi>  1</p><p>2.    If we knew the area and mean depth, we can in like&lt; manner find the dimensions, that is, <hi rend="italic">w</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">h ;</hi>  for A = <hi rend="italic">w h,</hi></p><p>and <hi rend="italic">d = </hi><hi rend="sup">w</hi><hi rend="sub">j</hi><hi rend="sup">h</hi><hi rend="sub">ci</hi>. ; therefore ro = ± ∕    — 2 A +</p><p><hi rend="italic">w + 2h</hi>     4d<hi rend="sup">s</hi>    <hi rend="italic">2d</hi></p><p>3.    If <hi rend="italic">d</hi>  be known, and one of the dimensions be given,</p><p>we can find the other ; for <hi rend="italic">d = —-, ‰</hi>  gives <hi rend="italic">w — ~-i w</hi>  + 2 A <hi rend="sup">o</hi>    <hi rend="italic">h—d</hi></p><p>an<hi rend="sub">d</hi>Λ = -⅛.<hi rend="italic">w</hi>—2 <hi rend="italic">d</hi></p><p>4.    If the velocity V and the slope s for a river in train be given, we can find the mean depth ; for V =</p><p>(-----... — 0∙3) (√&lt;∕- 0∙1). Whence we</p><p>∖√s-L√s+l∙6    ∕</p><p>V</p><p>deduce √d—0∙1 =-<hi rend="sub">5</hi>=--</p><p>___θ.g</p><p>√s — L√ s + 1∙6)</p><p>and √&lt;∕ = to this quantity + 0∙1.</p><p>5.    We can deduce the slope which will put in train a river whose channel has given dimensiofis. We make</p><p>307(√rf-0-l)_ _ <hi rend="sub">v</hi>,<hi rend="sub">s τhis sh</hi>θ<hi rend="sub">uld be</hi>  _ ^<hi rend="sub">s</hi>_ V + 0∙3 (√d-0∙l)</p><p>L√s + 1∙6, which we correct by trials, which will be exemplified when we apply these doctrines to practice.</p><p>Having thus established the relation between the different circumstances of the form of the channel to our general formula, we proceed to consider,</p><p>§ 2. <hi rend="italic">The Gradations of Velocity from tlœ middle of the Stream to the sides.</hi></p><p>The knowledge of this is necessary for understanding the regimen of a river ; for it is the velocity of the filaments in contact with the bed which produces any change in it, and occasions any preference of one to another in respect of regimen or stability. Did these circumstances not operate, the water, true to the laws of hydraulics, and confined within the bounds which have been assigned them, would neither enlarge nor diminish the area of the channel. But this is all that we can promise of waters perfectly clear, running in pipes or hewn channels. But rivers, brooks, and smaller streams, carry along waters loaded with mud or sand, which they deposit wherever their velocity is checked ; and they tear up, on the other hand, the materials of the channel wherever their velocity is sufficiently great. Nature, indeed, aims continually at an equilibrium, and works without ceasing to perpetuate her own performances, by establishing an equality of action and re-action, and proportioning the forms and direction of the motions to het agents, and to local circumstances. Her work is slow but unceasing ; and what she cannot accomplish in a year she will do in a century. The beds of our rivers have acquired some stability, because they are the labour of ages; and it is to time that we owe those deep and wide valleys which receive and confine our rivers in channels, which are now consolidated, and with slopes which have been gradually moderated, so that they no longer either ravage our habitations or confound our boundaries. Art may imitate nature, and, by directing her operations (which she still carries on according to her own imprescriptible laws) according to our views, we can hasten her progress, and accomplish our purpose, during the short period of human life. But we can do this only by studying the unalterable laws of mechanism These are presented to U3 by spontaneous nature. Fre-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>