<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb07-19-r01-0074-02" facs="eb07_19_Page_085.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RASTALL</label>
John, a printer and miscellaneous writer, <hi rend="sub">s</hi> was born in London, probably about the end of the fifteenth century, and educated at Oxford. Returning from the university, he settled in the metropolis, and commenced printer,</p><p>“ then esteemed,” says Wood, “ a profession fit for any scholar or ingenious man.” He married the sister of Sir Thomas More, with whom, we are told, he was very intimate, and whose writings he strenuously defended. From the title-page of one of his books, he appears to have lived in Cheapside, at the sign of the Mermaid. He died in the year 1536 ; and left two sons, William and John ; the first of whom became a judge in Queen Mary’s reign, and the other a justice of peace. This John Rastall, the subject of the present article, was a zealous Papist ; but Bale says that he changed his religion before his death. He wrote, 1. <hi rend="italic">Natura naturota.</hi> This Pits calls a copious and ingenious comedy, describing Europe, Asia, and Africa ; with cuts. What sort of a comedy this was, it is not easy to conceive. Probably it is a cosmographical description, written in dialogue, and therefore styled a <hi rend="italic">comedy.</hi> 2. The Pas-tyme of the People ; the cronycles of diverse realmys, and most especially of the realm of England, brevely compiled and emprinted in Cheapesyde, at the sign of the mearmaid, next Pollysgate, <hi rend="italic">cum privilegio,</hi> folio. 3. <hi rend="italic">Ecclesia Johan-nis RastoH,</hi> 1542, was one of the prohibited books in the reign of Henry VIII. 4. <hi rend="italic">Legum Anglicanarum vocabula explicata,</hi> French and Latin, London, 1567, 8vo ; and some other works.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>