<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb07-19-r01-0098-03" facs="eb07_19_Page_109.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>REGION</label>
in <hi rend="italic">Geography,</hi> a large extent of land, inhabited by many people of the same nation, and inclosed within certain limits or bounds.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Region, in</hi> <hi rend="italic">Physiology,</hi> is taken for a division of our atmosphere, which is divided into the upper, middle, and lower regions.</p><p>The upper region commences from the tops of the mountains, and reaches to the utmost limits of the atmosphere. In this region reign perpetual and equable calmness, clearness, and serenity. The middle region is that in which the clouds reside, and where meteors are formed, extending from the extremity of the lowest to the tops of the highest mountains. The lowest region is that in which we breathe, which is bounded by the reflection of the sun’s rays, or by the height to which they rebound from the earth. See Atmosphere.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ethereal Region,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Cosmography,</hi> is the whole extent of the universe, in which is included all the heavenly bodies, and even the orb of the fixed stars.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Elementary</hi> <hi rend="italic">REGiot;,</hi> according to the Aristotelians, is a sphere terminated by the concavity of the moon’s orb, comprehending the atmosphere of the earth.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Region, in</hi> <hi rend="italic">Anatomy,</hi> a division of the human body, otherwise called <hi rend="italic">cavity,</hi> of which anatomists reckon three, viz. the upper region, or that of the head ; the middle region, or that of the thorax or breast ; and the lower, being that of the abdomen or belly.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>