<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0059.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0053-05" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUEZ</label>,
a ſmall ſea-port town, ſituated near the northern extremity of the Red Sea, and about 30 hours journey eaſt from Cairo. The country around it is a ſandy plain, without the ſmalleſt ſpot of verdure. The only water which can be drunk is brought from El-Naba, or the ſpring, at the diſtance of three hours journey ; and it is ſo brackiſh, that without a mixture of rum it is inſupportable to Europeans. The town itſelf is a collection of miſerable ruins, the khans being the only solid buildings ; yet from March till June, the seaſon when the Jidda and Yambo fleet arrives, the town becomes crowded ; but after its departure nobody remains except the governor, who is a Mamlouk, 12 or 14 persons who form his houſehold, and the garrison. The fortreſs is a defenceleſs heap of ruins, which the Arabs conſider as a citadel, becauſe it contains six braſs lour pounders, and two Greek gunners, who turn their heads aside when they fire. The harbour is a wretched quay, where the ſmalleſt boats are unable to reach the ſhore, except at the higheſt tides. There, however, the merchandiſe is embarked, to convey it over the banks of sand to the vessels which anchor in the road. This road, ſituated a league from the town, is ſeparated from it by a ſhore which is left dry at low water; <hi rend="italic">it</hi> has no works for its defence, ſo that the vessels which Μ. Volney tells us he has ſeen there, to the number of 28 at a time, might be attacked without oppoſition ; for the ships themſelves are incapable of reſiſtance, none having any other artillery than four ruſty ſwivels.</p><p>Suez has always been, notwithſtanding its local diſadvantages, a place of great trade, on account of its geographical ſituation. It was by the gulph of Suez that the commodities of India were formerly conveyed to Europe, till the diſcovery of the paſſage by the Cape of Good Hope converted that trade into a new channel. As the iſthmus of Suez, which ſeparates the Red Sea from the Mediterranean, is not more than 57 miles, it has been frequently propoſed to join theſe two ſeas together by a canal. As there are no mountains nor remarkable inequalities of ſurface, this plan would at firſt view appear eaſy to be executed. But though the difference of levels would not prevent a junction, the great difficulty ariſes from the nature of the correſponding coasts of the Mediterranean and the Red Sea, which are of a low and ſandy soil, where the waters form lakes, ſhoals, and moraſſes, ſo that vessels cannot approach within a conſiderable diſtance. It will therefore be found ſcarcely poſſible to dig a permanent canal amid theſe ſhifting sands : not to mention, that the ſhore is deſtitute of harbours, which muſt be entirely the work of art. The country beſides has not a drop of freſh water, and to ſupply the inhabitants, it muſt be brought as far as from the Nile.</p><p>The beſt and only method therefore of effecting this junction, is that which has been already ſucceſsfully practiſed at different times ; which is, by making the river itſelf the medium of communication, for which the ground is perfectly well calculated ; for Mount Mokattam ſuddenly terminating in the latitude of Cairo, forms only a low and ſemicircular mound, round which is a continued plain from the banks of the Nile as far as the point of the Red Sea. The ancients, who early underſtood the advantage to be derived from this ſituation, adopted the idea of joining the two ſeas by a canal connected with the river. Strabo<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Lib. xvii.</p></note> * observes, that this was firſt executed under Sesoſtris, who reigned about the time of the Trojan war ; and this work was ſo conſiderable as to occaſion it to be remarked, “ that it was 100 cubits (or 170 feet) wide, and deep enough for large veſſels.” After the Greeks conquered the country, it was reſtored by the Ptolemies, and again renewed by Trajan. In ſhort, even the Arabs themſelves followed theſe examples. “ In the time of Omar ebn el Kattab (says the hiſtorian El Makin), the cities of Mecca and Medina ſuffering from famine, the Calif ordered Amrou governor of Egypt to cut a canal from the Nile to Kolzoum, that the contributions of corn and barley appointed for Arabia might be conveyed that way.”</p><p>This canal is the ſame which runs at preſent to Cairo, and loſes itſelf in the country to the north-eaſt of Berket-el- Hadj, or the Lake of the Pilgrims.</p><p>The place on the west coast of the gulph of Suez, where the children of Iſrael are ſuppoſed to have entered it, is called B <hi rend="italic">adua,</hi> about six miles to the north of Cape Korondel, on the other ſide of the gulph, as we are informed in a letter from the ingenious Edward Wortley Montague, F. R. S. to Dr Watfon, containing an account of his journey from Cairo to the Written Mountains in the desert of Sinai. Oppoſite to Badea is a ſtrong current which ſets to the oppoſite ſhore, about ſouth-eaſt, with a whirlpool called <hi rend="italic">Binque Pheraone,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">well</hi> or <hi rend="italic">pool of Pharaoh,</hi> being the place where his hoſt is ſaid to have been deſtroyed. We are told by the ſame gentleman, that the Egyptian ſhore from Suez to Badea is ſo rocky and ſteep, that there was no entering upon the gulph but at one of theſe two places.<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0060.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0054"/>
The British nation, we believe, never attempted to carry on commerce with any of the ports of the Red Sea beyond Jidda, till, on the ſuggeſtion of Mr Bruce, in 1776, ſome Britiſh merchants at Bengal equipped two or three veſſels for Suez, laden with piece-goods of Bengal and coast manufactures. The command of the veſſels was committed to Captain Greig, a meritorious ſeaman ; and the management of the goods was entruſted to Mr Straw, a gentleman distinguiſhed for his mercantile knowledge. The ſale turned out to advantage ; but ſuch great expences were incurred in making preſents to the bey of Cairo and Suez, as to consume the whole profits gained by the ſale of the cargo. The great purpoſe of the expedition was, however, accompliſhed, as a firman was obtained from the government of Cairo to trade by the way of Suez. In conſequence of this, three ſhips went to Suez the following year, and as many in 1778. The opening of this trade alarmed the jealouſy of the East India Company ; they applied to our government, and orders were given to relinquiſh this promiſing commerce. Theſe orders reached Egypt ſooner than Bengal, and the conſequence was fatal to the unfortunate adventurers who viſited Suez that year (1779). By a plan concerted between the beys, a large body of Bedouin Arabs attacked the caravan paſſing from Suez to Cairo with goods valued at 12 lacks of rupees. The goods were plundered, the Europeans were ſtripped and left naked in the desert, expoſed to the burning rays of the ſun, without a drop of water to quench their thirſt, or food to ſupport life. Moſt of them died, and ſome of their bodies were afterwards found mangled and disfigured by wolves. We have been favoured with a particular account of the ſufferings of our countrymen by a correſpondent, which, we are sorry, we have not room to inſert. Thoſe who wish to obtain a more full account may conſult the Annual Registor 1781 or 1782.</p></div></body></text></TEI>