<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0059.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0053-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUETONIUS <hi rend="smallcaps">tranquillus</hi></label>
 (Caius), a famous Latin hiſtorian, was born at Rome, and became ſecretary to the emperor Adrian, about the 118th year of the Chriſtian era; but that poſt was taken from him three years after, when ſeveral persons fell under that prince’s diſpleaſure for not ſhowing the empreſs Sabina all the reſpect ſhe deſerved. During his diſgrace he composed many works, which are lost. Thoſe now extant are his Hiſtory of the XII firſt Emperors, and a part of his Treatiſe of the Illuſtrious Grammarians and Rhetoricians. Pliny the Younger was his intimate friend, and perſuaded him to publish his books. His Hiſtory of the XII Roman Emperors has been much commended by moſt of our polite ſcholars. He repreſents, in a continued series of curious and inteeſting particulars, without any digreſſions or reflections, the actions of the emperors, without omitting their vices, which he expoſes with all their deformity, and with the ſame freedom mentions the good qualities of the very ſame persons ; but the horrid diſſoluteneſs and obſcene actions he relates of Tiberius, Caligula, Nero, &amp;c. have made ſome ſay, that he wrote the lives of the emperors with the ſame licentiouſneſs with which they lived. The edition of this hiſtory procured by Grævius at Utrecht in 1672, with the excellent Commentaries of Torrentius and Caſaubon, and the notes oſ ſome other learned critics, is much eſteemed. Burman alſo publiſhed an edition in two vols 4to with notes.</p></div></body></text></TEI>