<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0057.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0051-15" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUCCESSION</label>,
in metaphyſics, the idea which we get by reflecting on the ideas that follow one another in our mind ; and from the ſucceſſion of ideas we get the idea of <hi rend="italic">time.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> n⁰ 93. and 209.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Succession,</hi> in law. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Descent.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Succession</hi> <hi rend="italic">to the Crown.</hi> See <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Hereditary</hi> <hi rend="italic">Right.—</hi> From the days of Egbert, the firſt ſole monarch of England, even to the preſent, the four cardinal maxims mentioned in that article have ever been held conſtitutional canons of ſucceſſion. It is true, as Sir William Blackſtone obſerves, this ſucceſſion, through fraud or force, or ſometimes through neceſſity, when in hoſtile times the crown deſcended on a minor or the like, has been very frequently ſuſpended ; but has generally at laſt returned back into the old hereditary channel, though ſometimes a very conſiderable period has intervened. And even in thoſe inſtances where this ſucceſſion has been violated, the crown has ever been looked upon as hereditary in the wearer of it. Of which the usurpers themſelves were ſo ſenſible, that they for the moſt part endeavoured to vamp up ſome feeble ſhow of a title by deſcent, in order to amuſe the people, while they gained the poſſeſſion of the kingdom. And, when poſſeſſion was once gained, they conſidered it as the purchaſe or acquiſition of a new eſtate of inheritance, and tranſmitted, or endeavoured to tranſmit it, to their own poſterity by a kind of hereditary right of uſurpation. (See <hi rend="italic">Black. Com. ν.</hi> i. 197—217.) From the hiſtorical view there given, it appears, that the title to the crown is at preſent hereditary, though not quite ſo abſolutely hereditary as formerly : and the common ſtock, or anceſtor, from whom the deſcent muſt be derived, is alſo different. Formerly, the common ſtock was King Egbert ; then William the Conqueror; afterwards, in James I.’s time, the two common ſtocks united ; and ſo continued till the vacancy of the throne in 1688 : now it is the Princeſs Sophia, in whom the inheritance was veſted by the new king and parliament. Formerly, the deſcent was abſolute, and the crown went to the next heir without any reſtriction : but now, upon the new ſettlement, the inheritance is conditional ; being limited to ſuch heirs only, of the body of the Princeſs Sophia, as are Proteſtant members of the church of England, and are married to none but Proteſtants.</p><p>And in this due medium conſiſts the true conſtitutional notion of the right of ſucceſſion to the imperial crown of theſe kingdoms. The extremes between which it ſteers are each of them equally deſtructive of thoſe ends for which ſocieties were formed and are kept on foot. Where the magistrate, upon every ſucceſſion, is elected by the people, and<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0058.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0052"/>
may by the expreſs proviſion of the laws be depoſed (if not puniſhed) byhis ſubjects, this may found like the perfection of liberty, and look well enough when delineated on paper; but in practice will be ever productive of tumult, contention, and anarchy. And, on the other hand, divine indefeaſible hereditary right, when coupled with the doctrine of unlimited pasſive obedience, is ſurely of all conſtitutions the moſt thoroughly ſlaviſh and dreadful. But when ſuch an hereditary right as our laws have created and veſted in the royal ſtock, <hi rend="italic">is</hi> closely interwoven with thoſe liberties which are equally the inheritance of the ſubject ; this union will form a conſtitution, in theory the moſt beautiful of any, in practice the moſt approved, and, we truſt, in duration the moſt permanent.</p><p>In France the ſucceſſion to the monarchy was limited to heirs male (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Salic) ;</hi> but in Navarre the crown was inherited by the heir of line, whether male or female. The caſe ſtands thus: Philip the Fourth, king of France, ſurnamed <hi rend="italic">the Fair,</hi> in the year 1285 eſpoused Jane queen of Navarre in her own right ; and as king consort of this latter kingdom added the title of Navarre to his former one of France. Louis X. ſon and heir oſ Philip and Jane (ſurnamed H <hi rend="italic">utin,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Boisterous),</hi> ſucceeded to both crowns. By Margaret his firſt wife, who had been crowned queen of Navarre, he left one daughter Joan or Jane. His ſecond wife Clementia was pregnant at the time of his deceaſe, and was delivered of a poſthumous ſon, whom moſt of the French annaliſts recognize as John I. of France, though he lived no longer than three weeks. On his death the kingdom of France paſſed to Philip V. (ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Long),</hi> and that of Navarre (to which the Salic law could by no conſtruction extend) to Joanna the only child and heir of Louis and Margaret. From Joanna, in lineal ſucceſſion, the kingdom of Navarre paſſed to Jane d'Αlbret, mother of Henry IV. of France, and wife of Anthony of Vendoſme, who as king confort wore the crown of Navarre. On the acceſſion of Henry to the kingdom of France, the two monarchies were united, and the four ſucceeſting princes aſſumed the joint titles. But if ever the monarchy be reſtored in France, Mary, princeſs royal and daughter of Louis XVI. will have the same right to the throne of <hi rend="smallcaps">Navarre</hi> that her uncle has to the throne of France ; for ſhe is the undoubted heir of line of the great and illuſtrious Henry IV.</p></div></body></text></TEI>