<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0052.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0046-12" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STURNUS</label>,
the <hi rend="smallcaps">Starling</hi>; agenus of birds belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">paſſeres.</hi> The beak is ſubulated, depressed, and ſomewhat blunt ; the superior mandible is entire, and ſomewhat open at the edges ; the noſtrils are marginated above ; and the tongue is ſharp and emarginated. There are 15 ſpecies according to Dr Latham ; the vulgaris, capenſis, ludovicianus, militaris, cellaris, carunculatus, gallinaceus, ſericeus, viridis, olivaceus, moritanicus, loyca, dauuricus, junceti, and mexicanus.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">vulgaris,</hi> or common ſtarling, is the only ſpecies of the ſturnus that is indigenous. The weight of the male of this ſpecies is about three ounces ; that of the female rather leſs. The length is eight inches three quarters: the bill is brown or yellow, but in old birds generally yellow<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Latham's Synopsis, vol. iii.</p></note>. The whole plumage is black, very reſplendent, with changeable blue, purple, and copper : each feather marked with a pale yellow ſpot. The lesser coverts are edged with yellow, and ſlightly gloſſed with green. The quill-feathers and tail duſky : the former edged with yellow on the exterior side ; the last with dirty white. The legs of a reddiſh brown.</p><p>The ſtare breeds in hollow trees, eaves of houſes, towers, ruins, cliffs, and often in high rocks over the ſea, ſuch as that of the iſle of Wight. It lays four or five eggs, of a pale- greeniſh aſh-colour ; and makes its neſt of ſtraw, ſmall fibres of roots, and the like. In winter, ſtares aſſemble in vast flocks : they collect in myriads in the fens of Lincolnſhire, and do great damage to the fen-men, by rootling on the reeds, and breaking them down by their weight ; for reeds are the thatch of the country, and are laid up in harveſt with great care. Theſe birds feed on worms and infects ; and it is ſaid that they will get into pigeon-houſes, for the ſake of ſucking the eggs. Their fleſh is ſo bitter as to be ſcarce eatable. They are fond of following oxen and other large cattle as they feed in the meadows, attracted, it is ſaid, by the infects which flutter round them, or by thoſe, perhaps,<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0053.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0047"/>
which ſwarm in their dung, or in meadows in general. From this habit is derived the German name <hi rend="italic">Rinder Staren,</hi> They are alſo accuſed of feeding on the carcaſes that are exposed on gibbets ; but it is probably in ſearch only of insects. They live ſeven or eight years, or even longer, in the domestic ſtate. The wild ones cannot be decoyed by the call, becauſe they regard not the ſcream of the owl. A method has been diſcovered of taking entire families, by fixing to the walls and the trees where they lodge pots of earthen ware of a convenient form, which the birds often prefer to place their neſts in. Many are alſo caught by the gin and draw-net. In ſome parts of Italy it is common to employ tame weaſels to drag them out of their neſts, or father their holes ; for the artifice of man conſiſts in employing one enslaved race to extend his dominion over the rest.</p><p>The ſtare, it is ſaid, can be taught to ſpeak either French, German, Latin, Greek, &amp;c. and to pronounce phraſes of ſome length. Its pliant throat accommodates itſelf to every inflection and every accent. It can readily articulate the letter R, and acquires a fort of warbling which is much ſuperior to its native ſong. This bird is ſpread through an extensive range in the ancient continent. It is found in Sweden, Germany, France, Italy, the Iſle of Malta, the Cape of Good Hope, arid is everywhere nearly the ſame ; whereas thoſe American birds which have been called ſtares, preſent a great diverſity of appearance.</p></div></body></text></TEI>