<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0058.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0052-10" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUCKLING</label>
(Sir John), an English poet and dramatic writer, was the ſon of Sir John Suckling, comptroller of the houſehold to king Charles I. and born at Witham in Eſſex in 1613. He discovered an uncommon propenſity to the acquiring of languages, inſomuch that he is reported to have ſpoken Latin at five years of age, and to have written it at nine. When he was grown up, he travelled ; but seems to have affected nothing more than the character of a courtier and fine gentleman ; which he ſo far attained, that he was allowed to have the peculiar happineſs of making every thing he did become him. In his travels he made a campaign under the great Guſtavus Adolphus ; and his loyalty, if not his valour, appeared in the beginning of our civil wars ; for, after his return to England, he raiſed a troop of horſe for the king’s ſervice entirely at his own charge ; and mounted them ſo completely and richly, that they are ſaid to have coſt him 12,000 l. This troop, with Sir John at its head, behaved ſo ill in the engagement with the Scots, upon the English borders, in 1639, as to occasion the famous lampoon compoſed by Sir John Mennis ; “ Sir John he got him an ambling nag,” &amp;c. This ballad, which was ſet to a briſk tune, was much ſung by the parliamentarians, and continues to be ſung to this day. This diſaſtrous expedition, and the ridicule that attended it, was ſuppoſed to have haſtened his death ; being ſeized by a fever, of which he died, at 28 years of age. He was a ſprightly wit, and an eaſy versifier, but no great poet. His works, conſiſting of a few poems, letters, and plays, have nevertheleſs gone through ſeveral editions.</p></div></body></text></TEI>