<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0091.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0085-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SURCHARGE OF <hi rend="smallcaps">the Forest,</hi></label>
 is when a commoner puts more beaſts in the foreſt than he has a right to. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Forest.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SURCHARGE of Common,</hi> is a diſturbance of common of paſture, by putting more cattle therein than the paſture and herbage will ſuſtain, or the party hath a right to do. This injury can only happen where the common is appendant or appurtenant, and of courſe limitable by law ; or where, when in groſs, it is expreſsly limited and certain; for where a man hath common in groſs, s <hi rend="italic">ans nombre,</hi> or without stint, he cannot be a ſurcharge. In this caſe indeed there muſt be left ſufficient for the lord’s own beaſts.</p><p>The uſual remedies for ſurcharging the common are by the lord’s diſtraining the ſurplus number, or by his bringing an action of trespaſs, or by a ſpecial action on the caſe, in which any commoner may be plaintiff. The ancient and moſt effectual method of proceeding is by writ of admeaſurement of paſture.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Writ of Second SURCHARGE, de ſecunda ſuperoneratione,</hi> is given by the ſtatute of Weſtm. 2. 13 Edw. I. cap. 8. when, after the admeaſurement of paſture hath aſcertained the right, the ſame defendant ſurcharges the common again ; and thereby the sheriff is directed to inquire by a jury whether the defendant has in fact again ſurcharged the common; and if he has, he ſhall then forfeit to the king the ſupernumerary cattle put in, and alſo ſhall pay damages to the plaintiff.</p></div></body></text></TEI>