<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0043.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0037-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STROMBOLI</label>,
the moſt northern of the Lipari islands. It is a volcano, which conſtantly diſcharges much fire and ſmoke. It riſes in a conical form above the ſurface of the ſea. On the eaſt side it has three or four little craters ranged near each other, not at the ſummit, but on the declivity, nearly at two thirds or its height. But as the ſurface of the volcano is very rugged, and interſected with hollow ways, it may be naturally concluded, that at the time of ſome great eruption, the ſummit and a part of this side fell in, as muſt have happened alſo to Veſuvius; consequently, the common chimney is at this day on the declivity, although always in the centre of the whole base. It is inhabited notwithſtanding its fires ; but care is taken to avoid the proximity of the crater, which is yet much to be feared. “ I was aſſured (says Μ. de Luc) by an Engliſhman, who, like me, had the curiosity to viſit theſe iſles, that the fine weather having invited him and his company to land at Stromboli, they aſcended a volcano, whole craters at that time threw out nothing ; but that while they were attentively viewing them, unapprehensive of any danger, they were ſuddenly ſaluted by such a furious diſcharge, as to be obliged to retreat with precipitation, and not without one of the company being wounded by a piece of ſcoria.” Of all the volcanoes recorded in hiſtory, Stromboli ſeems to be the only one that burns without ceasing. Etna and Veſuvius often lie quiet for many months, and even years, without the leaſt appearance of fire ; but Stromboli is ever at work, and for ages paſt has been looked upon as the great lighthouſe of theſe ſeas. E.Long. 15.45. N. Lat. 30. 0.</p></div></body></text></TEI>