<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0052.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0046-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STUKELY</label>
(Dr William), a celebrated antiquarian, descended from an ancient family in Lincolnſhire, was born at Holbech in 1687, and educated in Bennet college, Cambridge. While an under-graduate, he often indulged a strong propenſity to drawing and deſigning ; but made phyſic his principal ſtudy, and firſt began to practiſe at Boſton in his native country. In 1717 he removed to London, where, on the recommendation of Dr Mead, he was ſoon after elected a fellow of the Royal Society ; he was one of the firſt who revived that of the antiquarians in 1718, and was their ſecretary for many years during his reſidence in town. In 1729 he took holy orders by the encouragement of archbishop Wake ; and was ſoon after presented by lord-chancellor King with thc living of All Saints in Stamford. In 1741 he became one of the founders of the Egyptian ſociety, which brought him acquainted with the benevolent duke of Montague, one of the members ; who prevailed on him to leave Stamford, and preſented him to the living of St George the Martyr, Queen Square. He died of a ſtroke of the palſy in 1765. In his phyſical capacity, his Diſſertation on the Spleen was well received ; and his <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium Curioſum,</hi> the firſt fruit of his juvenile excurſions, was a good specimen of what was to be expected from his riper age. His great learning, and profound researches into the dark remains of antiquity, enabled him to publiſh many elaborate and curious works : his friends uſed to call him the <hi rend="italic">arch-druid</hi> of his age. His diſcourſes, intitled <hi rend="italic">Palaeographica Sacra,</hi> on the vegetable creation, beſpeak him a botaniſt, philoſopher, and divine.</p></div></body></text></TEI>