<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0053.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0047-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STYLEPHORUS <hi rend="smallcaps">chordatus,</hi></label>
 a genus of fiſhes belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">apodes</hi><note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Plate CCCCLXXXVI.</p></note> <hi rend="italic">.</hi> This very curious genus was diſcovered by Dr Shaw, who read a deſcription of it before the Linnæan Society in the year 1788. The eyes are fixed on cylindrical pillars which lie cloſe together. The roſtrum, or narrow part which is terminated by the mouth, is connected to the back part of the head by a flexible leathery duplicature, which permits it either to be extended in ſuch a manner that the mouth points directly upwards, or to fall back ſo as to be received into a sort of caſe, formed by the upper part of the head. There are three pairs of branchiae lituate under tire throat.<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Transactions of the Linnaean Society, vol. i.</p></note> The pectoral fins are ſmall; the dorſal fin runs from the head to within about an inch and a half of the tail ; the caudal fin is ſhort, and is furniſhed with five remarkable ſpines. The body is extremely long, and compreſſed very much, and gradually diminishes as it approaches the tail, which terminates in a proceſs or ſtring of an enormous length, and finiſhes in a very fine point. This ſtring, or caudal proceſs, ſeems to be ſtrengthened throughout its whole length, or at leaſt as far as the eye can trace it, by a fort of double fibre or internal part. The ſtylephorus chordatus is a native of the West Indian Sea. It was taken between the iſlands of Cuba and Martinico, near a ſmall duller of little iſlands about nine leagues from ſhore, and was ſeen ſwimming near the ſurface. The whole length of this uncommon animal from the head to the extremity of the caudal proceſs is about thirty-two inches, of which the proceſs itſelf meaſures twenty-two.</p></div></body></text></TEI>