<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0078.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0072-08" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUMPTUARY <hi rend="smallcaps">laws</hi></label>
 <hi rend="italic">(Leges Sumptuariae),</hi> are laws made to reſtrain exceſs in apparel, coſtly furniture, eating, &amp;c.</p><p>Moſt ages and nations have had their ſumptuary laws ; and ſome regain them ſtill, as the Venetians, &amp;c. But it is obſerved, that no laws are worſe executed than ſumptuary laws. Political writers have been much divided in opinion with reſpect to the utility of theſe laws to a ſtate. Monteſquieu obſerves, that luxury is neceſſary in monarchies, as in France, but ruinous to democracies, as in Holland. With regard to England, whoſe government is compounded of both ſpecies, it may ſtill be a dubious queſtion, ſays judge Blackſtone, how far private luxury is a public evil ; and as ſuch cognizable by public laws.</p><p>The ſumptuary laws of that ancient Locrian legiſlator Zaleucus are famous : by theſe it was ordained, that no woman ſhould go attended with more than one maid in<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0079.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0073"/>
the ſtreet except ſhe were drunk : that ſhe ſhould not go out of the city in the night, unleſs ſhe went to commit fornication : that ſhe ſhould not wear any gold or embroidered apparel, unleſs ſhe propoſed to be a common ſtrumpet ; and that men ſhould not wear rings or tiſſues except when they went a whoring, &amp;c.</p><p>Among the Romans, the ſumptuary laws were very numerous : By the <hi rend="italic">Lex Orcha,</hi> the number of gueſts at feaſts was limited, though without any limitation of the charges : by the Fannian law, made 22 years afterwards, it was enacted, that more than 10 <hi rend="italic">aſſes</hi> ſhould not be ſpent at any ordinary feaſt : for the ſolemn feaſts, as the Saturnalia, &amp;c. an hundred aſſes were allowed ; ten of which, Gellius informs us, was the price of a ſheep, and a hundred of an ox. By the Didian law, which was preferred 18 years after, it was decreed, that the former ſumptuary laws ſhould be in force, not only in Rome, but throughout all Italy ; and that for every tranſgreſſion, not only the matter of the feast, but all the gueſts too, ſhould be liable to the penalty.</p><p>The Engliſh have had their ſhare of ſumptuary laws, chiefly made in the reigns of Edw. III. Edw. IV. and Henry VIII. againſt ſhoes with long points, ſhort doublets, and long coats ; though all repealed by ſtatute 1 Jac. I. c. 25. As to excels in diet, there remains still one law unrepealed. Under King Henry IV. Camden tells us, pride was got ſo much into the foot, that it was proclaimed, that no man ſhould wear ſhoes above six inches broad at the toes. And their other garments were ſo ſhort, that it was enacted, 25 Edw. IV. that no perſon, under the condition of a lord, ſhould, from that time, wear any mantle or gown, unleſs of such length, that, ſtanding upright, it might cover his privy members and buttocks.</p></div></body></text></TEI>