<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0090.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0084-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SURAT</label>,
a city of Indoſtan, belonging to Britain, on the weſtern coaſt of the peninſula, a little to the northward of Bombay, and about 16 miles up the river Tappee. It is but of modern date, and is a moſt remarkable inſtance of the power of trade to bring wealth and population to any ſpot where it can be brought to settle. Towards the middle of the laſt century this place was only the resort of a few merchants, who, under the ſhelter of an old inſignificant caſtle, laid the firſt foundations of a city now almoſt as large and fully as populous as London within the walls, and containing many fine buildings of Indian architecture, which is partly Gentoo and partly Moriſque. Thoſe of the greateſt note are ſo contrived, that the gateway is defenſible againſt any hidden irruption of a few armed men. The private apartments lie backwards for the conveniency of the women, of whom the Moors are remarkably jealous. They are fond of having one room, in the midſt of which a fountain keeps playing, and which, by its noiſe, lulls them to ſleep, and refreſhes the room by its coolneſs ; but thus a damp is produced, which would be very dangerous to Europeans. They have alſo generally a ſaloon with fountains playing in it, which, with the variegated flower-beds, in which they are very curious, makes a beautiful proſpect. During the intenſe heats of summer they have country retirements a little way out of town, where they reſide, or go in parties to amuſe themſelves. The ſtreets are irregularly laid out ; but have one property which renders it agreeable to walk in them, viz. that a competent width being left at bottom, the upper ſtories of the houſes project over one another in ſuch a manner, that people may with eaſe converſe from them ; by which means the ſtreet is agreeably ſhaded, at the ſame time that a proper ventilation is not impeded, but rather promoted. The ſhops, notwithſtanding the vaſt trade carried on in this great and populous city, have a very mean appearance, owing to the dealers keeping their goods in warehouſes, and selling by ſamples.</p><p>No place is better ſupplied with proviſions than the city of Surat while its communication with the country remains open. Beſides the unbounded importation, by which every article is brought here in great abundance, the natural productions of the ſoil are excellent, though leſs cheap than in other parts of India, as at Bengal eſpecially ; yet in that place, though the cattle and poultry are bought originally at a very low rate, they turn out very dear by the time they are fed for the table. Here, however, all kinds of eatables may be had at a reaſonable price, ready for immediate uſe, and as good as can be found anywhere. The wheat of Surat is famous all over India for its Angular ſubſtance, white- neſs, and taſte ; and its sallads and roots are likewiſe of an excellent quality. There are alſo many kinds of wild-fowl and other game to be had at an easy rate ; but for wines and ſpirituous liquors they depend moſtly on importation.</p><p>Surat was ſurrounded with a wall in a ſhort time after it had assumed the form of a town. The fortification, however, was meant only to prevent the incurſions of the Mahrattas, who had twice pillaged it ; ſo that the place was by no means capable of ſtanding any regular siege. Even the caſtle appears but a poor defence, being mounted with cannon here and there, without any order, or wiithout any thing like an attempt towards military architecture.</p><p>In this city, before the Eaſt India company became inveſted with the poſſeſſion of Bombay, was the presidency of their affairs on the weſtern coaſt. For this purpoſe they had a factory eſtabliſhed there with great privileges by the Mogul government ; and even after the preſidency was eſtabliſhed at Bombay, they continued a factory here at one of the beſt houſes in the city ; which yet not being ſpacious enough to contain their effects, they hired another at ſome diſtance from it, and nearer the water-ſide, which was called the new factory. In the mean time, the city flouriſhed, and became the centre of all the Indian trade, being much more frequented ſor the ſake of foreign merchandize than for cither the natural productions or manufactures of the country, though they alſo made a conſiderable part of its commerce. In ſhort, there was ſcarce any article of merchandize but what was to be found at all times in Surat, almoſt as readily as in London itſelf. While the Mogul government was in its vigour, there was ſuch a ſhow of juſtice kept up, as induced merchants of all religions and denominations to take up their reſidence in the city. The Gentoos eſpecially reſorted thither, in order to avoid the oppreſſions of their own government. Great care indeed was taken that no very flagrant acts of oppreſſion ſhould be committed ; ſo that, in what ſometimes happened, appearances were at leaſt kept up ; and the oppreſſions of government were chiefly owing to the animoſities and rivalſhip of the merchants themſelves. As an inſtance of the meat extent to which commerce was puſhed in Surat, we ſhall here quote from Mr Groſe, what is ſaid by Captain Hamilton of a merchant named A <hi rend="italic">bdulgafour,</hi> viz. “ That he drove a trade equal to the Eaſt India company : for he had known him fit out in a year above 20 sail of ſhips, between 300 and 800 tons, none of which had leſs of his own ſtock than L. 20,000, and ſome of them L. 25,000. After that foreign ſtock was ſent away, it behoved him to have as much more of an inland ſtock for the following year’s market.” On the deceaſe of this merchant, the government ſeized on a million of his money; and his grandſon was not only deprived of all that he possessed, but barbarouſly murdered through the envy and treachery of his brother merchants, and the rapacity of the governor.</p><p>The city of Surat was taken and ruined by the Portugueſe in 1520; and it was not till after this misfortune that it became ſuch a celebrated emporium. All the Indian merchants who had been accuſtomed to trade thither contributed to re-eſtabliſh it ; but it was not till near a century after that it became the general staple of Indian and<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0091.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0085"/>
European merchandize ; when the Dutch appearing in the Indian ocean, had deprived the Portugueſe of all their conqueſts on that coaſt, and almoſt entirely ruined their trade. The Engliſh eſtabliſhed a factory here in 1609, the Dutch in 1616, and the French in 1665. In proceſs of time, the Indian ſeas being greatly infeſted by pirates, a naval officer was appointed by the Mogul to keep them in awe. This officer was named <hi rend="italic">Siddee</hi><note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> When the Abyſſinian ſlaves are promoted to any office under the Mogul government, they are called <hi rend="italic">Siddees</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> .</hi></p></note> <hi rend="italic">(A) Muſſoot,</hi> who had been chief of an Ethiopian colony settled at Rajapore. Here he had collected ſome veſſels of conſiderable force, and carried on some trade, till he was dispoſſeſſed by the Mahrattas ; upon which he repaired to Bombay, and afterwards to Surat, where he was appointed admiral on that ſtation to the Mogul, with a yearly revenue of about L. 36,000 Sterling. Though he had no power, independent of the marine, he ſeized on the caſtle, encroached on the town, and appropriated to himſelf a third part of its revenues, under pretence of arrears due in his appointed revenue. Another third was paid to the Mahrattas, to prevent their depredations upon trade in the open country ; but they, not ſatisfied with this ſtipulation, watched an opportunity to plunder the town, which was kept in ſubjection by Siddee Muſſoot till his death, which happened in 1756.</p><p>Siddee Muſſoot was ſucceeded by his ſon, who ſoon rendered himſelf very diſagreeable to the inhabitants. In 1758 the Engliſh factory was greatly oppreſſed by him, and the black merchants treated ſtill worſe ; on which the latter applied to Mr Ellis the Engliſh chief at that time, desiring him to recommend it to the preſidency of Bombay to take the caſtle by force out of the hands of the uſurper. This propoſal proving agreeable, Admiral Pococke, who was then with his ſquadron at Bombay, readily concurred in ſupporting the expedition. The enterprize was conducted with the usual ſucceſs attending the Britiſh arms ; and Captain Maitland the conductor took poſſeſſion of the caſtle with its revenue in name of the Eaſt India company, who were confirmed in the government by grants from the Mogul.</p></div></body></text></TEI>