<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="gri_33125011196348_0069.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0063-02"
                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <p><label>SUICIDE</label>, the crime of ſelf-murder, or the perſon who commits
                    it.</p>
                <p>We have often wiſhed to see a hiſtory of crimes drawn up by a man of ability and
                    reſearch. In this hiſtory we would propose that the author ſhould describe the
                    crimes peculiar to different nations in the different ſtages of society, and the
                    changes which they undergo in the progreſs of civilization. After having
                    arranged the hiſtorical facts, he might, by comparing them with the religion and
                    the knowledge of the people, deduce ſome important general concluſions, which
                    would lead to a diſcovery of the cauſe of crimes, and of the remedy moſt proper
                    to be applied. Some crimes are peculiar to certain ſtages of ſociety, ſome to
                    certain nations, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Suicide is one of thoſe crimes which we are led to believe not common among
                    ſavage nations. The firſt inſtances of it recorded in the Jewiſh hiſtory are
                    thoſe of Saul and Ahitophel ; for we do not think the death of Samſon a proper
                    example. We have no reaſon to ſuppoſe that it became common among the Jews till
                    their wars with the Romans, when multitudes ſlaughtered themſelves that they
                    might not fall alive into the hands of their enemies. But at this period the
                    Jews were a moſt deſperate and abandoned race of men, had corrupted the religion
                    of their fathers, and rejected that pure ſyſtem which their promiſed Meſſiah
                    came to Jeruſalem to announce.</p>
                <p>When it became remarkable among the Greeks, we have not been able to diſcover ;
                    but it was forbidden by Pythagoras, as we learn from Athenæus, by Socrates and
                    Ariſtotle, and by the Theban and Athenian laws. In the earlieſt ages of the
                    Roman republic it was ſeldom committed ; but when luxury and thc Epicurean and
                    Stoical philoſophy had corrupted the ſimplicity and virtue of the Roman
                    character, then they began to ſeek ſhelter in suicide from their misfortunes or
                    the effects of their own vices.</p>
                <p>The religious principles of the bramins of India led them to admire suicide on
                    particular occaſions as honourable. Accustomed to abſtinence, mortification, and
                    the contempt of death, they conſidered it as a mark of weakneſs of mind to
                    ſubmit to the infirmities of old age. We are informed that the modern Gentoos,
                    who ſtill in moſt things conform to the cuſtoms of their anceſtors, when old and
                    infirm, are frequently brought to the banks of rivers, particularly to<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196348_0070.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0064"/> thoſe of the
                    Ganges, that they may die in its ſacred ſtreams, which they believe can wash
                    away the guilt oſ their sins.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Sullivan's Phil. Rhap. vol. ii.</p></note> But the
                    maxims of the bramins, which have encouraged this practice, we are aſſured by Mr
                    Hol well, are a corruption of the doctrines of the Shaſtah, which poſitively
                    forbid suicide under the ſeverest puniſhment.<note anchored="false" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Holwell's Interesting Events,
                            &amp;c. vol. i.</p></note> The practice which religion or affection has
                    eſtabliſhed among the Gentoos for women at the death of their huſbands to burn
                    themſelves alive on the funeral pile, we do not think ought to be conſidered as
                    ſuicide, as we are not anxious to extend the meaning of the word; for were we to
                    extend it thus far, it would be as proper to apply it to thoſe who chooſe rather
                    to die in battle than make their escape at the expence of their honour. Thus we
                    ſhould condemn as ſuicides the brave Spartans who died at Thermopylæ in defence
                    of their country : we ſhould alſo be obliged to apply the ſame diſgraceful
                    epithet to all thoſe well-meaning but weak-minded Christians in this iſland, who
                    in the laſt century choſe rather to die as martyrs than comply with commands
                    which were not morally wrong. According to the Gentoo laws, “ it is proper for a
                    woman after her husband’s death to burn herſelf in the fire with his corpie.
                    Every woman who thus burns ſhall remain in paradiſe with her husband three crore
                    and fifty lacks of years. If ſhe cannot, ſhe muſt in that caſe preſerve an
                    inviolable chaſtity. If ſhe remain chaſte, ſhe goes to paradiſe ; and if ſhe do
                    not preſerve her chaſtity, ſhe goes to hell.”</p>
                <p>A cuſtom ſimilar to this prevailed among many nations on the continent of
                        America<note anchored="false" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Robertson's America.</p></note>. When a chief died, a certain number of
                    his wives, of his favourites, and of his ſlaves, were put to death, and interred
                    together with him, that he might appear with the ſame dignity in his future
                    ſtation, and be waited upon by the ſame attendants. This perſuaſion is ſo deeply
                    rooted, that many of their retainers offer themſelves as victims; and the ſame
                    cuſtom prevails in many of the negro nations in Africa.</p>
                <p>If we can believe the hiſtorians oſ Japan, voluntary death is common in that
                    empire. The devotees of the idol Amida drown themſelves in his preſence,
                    attended by their relations and friends, and ſeveral of the prieſts, who all
                    conſider the devoted perſon as a ſaint who is gone to everlaſting happineſs.
                    Such being the ſuppoſed honours appropriated to a voluntary death, it is not
                    ſurprising that the Japaneſe anxiouſly cheriſh a contempt of life.<note anchored="false" n="4" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Raynal's
                            History of the East and West Indies, vol. i.</p></note> Accordingly it
                    is a part of the education of their children “ to repeat poems in which the
                    virtues of their anceſtors are celebrated, an utter contempt of life is
                    inculcated, and ſuicide is ſet up as the moſt heroic oſ actions.”</p>
                <p>A notion ſeems alſo to have prevailed among the ancient Scythian tribes, that it
                    was pusillanimous and ignoble for a man whoſe ſtrength was wasted with diſeaſe
                    or infirmity, ſo as to be uſeleſs to the community, to continue to live. It was
                    reckoned an heroic action voluntarily to ſeek that death which he had not the
                    good fortune to meet in the field of battle. Perversion of moral feeling does
                    not ſpring up, we hope, ſpontaneouſly in any nation, but is produced by ſome
                    peculiarities of ſituation. A wandering people like the Scythians, who roamed
                    about from place to place, might often find it impoſſible to attend the ſick, or
                    to ſupply from theſe precarious ſtore the wants of the aged and infirm. The aged
                    and infirm themſelves, no longer able to ſupport the character of warriors,
                    would find themſelves unhappy. In this way the practice of putting to death ſuch
                    perſons as were uſeleſs to the community might originate, and afterwards be
                    inculcated as honourable ; but he who put an end to his infirmities by his own
                    hand, obtained a character ſtill more illuſtrious.</p>
                <p>The tribes of Scandinavia, which worſhipped Odin the “ father of ſlaughter,” were
                    taught, that dying in the field of battle was the moſt glorious event that could
                    befal them. This was a maxim ſuited to a warlike nation. In order to eſtabliſh
                    it more firmly in the mind, all were excluded from Odin’s feaſt of heroes who
                    died a natural death. In Aſgardſk ſtood the hall of Odin ; where, ſeated on a
                    throne, he received the souls of his departed heroes. This place was called V
                        <hi rend="italic">alhalla,</hi> signifying “ the hall of thoſe who died by
                    violence.” Natural death being thus deemed inglorious, and puniſhed with
                    excluſion from Valhalla the paradiſe of Odin, he who could not enjoy death in
                    the field of battle was led to ſeek it by his own hands when ſickneſs or old age
                    began to aſſail him. In ſuch a nation ſuicide muſt have been very common.</p>
                <p>As ſuicide prevailed much in the decline of the Roman empire, when luxury,
                    licentiouſneſs, profligacy, and falſe philoſophy, pervaded the world, ſo it
                    continued to prevail even after Chriſtianity was eſtabliſhed. The Romans, when
                    they became converts to Chriſtianity, did not renounce their ancient prejudices
                    and falſe opinions, but blended them with the new religion which they embraced.
                    The Gothic nations also, who ſubverted the Roman empire, while they received the
                    Chriſtian religion, adhered to many of their former opinions and manners. Among
                    other criminal practices which were retained by the Romans and their conquerors,
                    that of suicide was one ; but the principles from which it proceeded were
                    explained, ſo as to appear more agreeable to the new ſyſtem which they had
                    eſpouſed. It was committed, either to ſecure from the danger of apoſtacy, to
                    procure the honour of martyrdom, or to preſerve the crown of virginity.</p>
                <p>When we deſcend to modern times, we lament to find ſo many inſtances of ſuicide
                    among the moſt poliſhed nations, who have the best opportunities of knowing the
                    atrocity of that unnatural crime. The Engliſh have long been reproached by
                    foreigners for the frequent commiſſion of it ; and the “ gloomy month of
                    November” has been ſtigmatized as the ſeaſon when it is moſt common. But this
                    diſgraceful imputation, we think, may be juſtly attributed, not to the greater
                    frequency of the crime in England than in other places, but to the cuſtom of
                    publiſhing in the newspapers every inſtance of ſuicide which is known. Mr Moore,
                    who lately publiſhed a full inquiry into this ſubject, was at great pains to
                    obtain accurate information concerning the perpetration of this crime in
                    different countries.<note anchored="true" n="5" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>[mu] Mercier Tableau Paris.</p></note> Mercier, who wrote in 1782,
                    ſays, that the annual number of ſuicides in Paris was then about 150. He does
                    not tell us how he came by the information ; but we have the authority of the
                    Abbé Fontana for asserting, that more perſons put an end to their lives in Paris
                    than in London. The Abbé had this information from the lieutenant of the police.
                    Mr Moore was informed by one of the principal magiſtrates of Geneva, that in
                    that city, which contains about 25,000 inhabitants, the average number of
                    ſuicides is about eight. The average number of ſuicides, from what cauſe ſoever,
                    for the laſt 28 years, has been 32 each year for London, Southwark, and
                    Weſtminſter. In Edinburgh, which contains 80,000 inhabitants, we are convinced
                    the average number of ſuicides does not exceed <hi rend="italic">four.</hi> Mr
                    Moore found, from the accounts with which he was favoured by the ſeveral
                    coroners of the county of Kent, that for the laſt 18 years the number has been
                    upwards of 32 each year. Kent is ſuppoſed to contain 200,000 inhabitants, and
                    London 800,000. It is eaſy therefore to see, that in the metropolis many
                    inſtances of ſuicide muſt occur which are never the ſubject of legal inquiry,
                    and conſequently never made known to the world. Whereas in the country towns and
                    villages of Kent it is ſcarcely poſſible to conceal ſuch an action as
                        ſelf-murder<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0071.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0065"
                    /> from the knowledge of the whole neighbourhood. The calculation therefore
                    reſpecting Kent we may receive as true, while we must increaſe the average
                    number in London very conſiderably. Mr Moore computes the average number of
                    suicides in England every year at a thousand ; but the principles on which he
                    founds this opinion are ſo imperfect and vague, that we do not think it can be
                    depended on as coming near the truth.</p>
                <p>It might lead to ſome intereſting concluſions to compare together, not only the
                    number of suicides in different countries, but also the rank and principles, the
                    ſex and age, of thoſe unhappy persons by whom it has been committed. Mercier
                    ſays, that at Paris it was the lower ranks who were moſt commonly guilty of it ;
                    that it was moſtly committed in garrets or hired lodgings ; and that it
                    proceeded from poverty and oppreſſion. A great many, he says, wrote letters to
                    the magiſtrates bcfore their death. Mr Moore’s correſpondent from Geneva
                    informed him, that from the year 1777 to 1787 more than 100 suicides were
                    committed in Geneva<note anchored="true" n="6" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>[mu] Moore's Full Inquiry into the Causes of Suicide.</p></note>;
                    that two thirds of theſe unfortunate persons were men ; that few of the clerical
                    order have been known to commit it ; and that it is not ſo much the end of an
                    immoral, irreligious, diſſipated life, as the effect of melancholy and poverty.
                    By the information obtained from the coroners of Kent, it appears, that of the
                    32, three-fourths have deſtroyed themſelves by hanging ; that the proportion of
                    males to females has been about two-thirds of the former ; that no one ſeason of
                    the year is more diſtinguished tor this crime than another ; and that suicide is
                    upon the increaſe. Our accounts reſpecting the city of London are very imperfect
                    ; but we think ourſelves intitled to conclude, that suicide is more common among
                    the great and wealthy than among the lower ranks, and that it is uſually the
                    effect of gaming and diſſipation.</p>
                <p>Thoſe who have inquired into the cauſes of suicide in Britain have enumerated
                    many phyſical as well as moral cauſes. They have aſcribed it to the variableneſs
                    of our climate, to the great uſe of animal food, to ſtrong ſpirituous liquors,
                    to tea, and to the ſulphureous exhalations of the pit-coal uſed as fuel, which
                    are ſaid to produce a depreſſion of ſpirits and nervous affections. Of our
                    climate, we have no cauſe to complain, nor have we any reaſon to impute any of
                    our vices to its influence. There are many climates much more unfavourable where
                    suicide is ſcarcely known. That an exceſſive quantity of groſs animal food, or
                    of ſtrong liquors, or of tea, will powerfully affect the human conſtitution, we
                    will not deny : but before we conſider theſe as cauſes, it muſt firſt be
                    determined, whether thoſe who are guilty of self-murder be much addicted to them
                    ; and if they are, whether there be not other cauſes much more violent in their
                    nature which have operated on their mind ; for we ought not raſhly to attribute
                    vicious effects to any of thoſe things which ſeem to have been created on
                    purpoſe for the comfort or convenience of man. We are rather ſurpriſed to find
                    that coal is mentioned even as a diſtant cauſe of ſuicide ; for it is one of the
                    bleſſings of our iſland : and a good coal fire we have always found rather
                    conducive to good ſpirits than injurious to them.</p>
                <p>Among the moral cauſes which are ſuppoſed to co operate in producing ſuicide in
                    Britain, the freedom of our conſtitution and laws is reckoned one. That rational
                    liberty ſhould have any tendency to encourage crimes of any kind, a Chriſtian
                    philosopher can never allow ; for ſuch an opinion is totally diſcountenanced by
                    enlightened views of nature. Mercier has aſeribed the frequency of ſuicide in
                    Paris to the oppreſſion of the late government. Now it appears ſomewhat
                    extraordinary, that suicide in one country ſhould be occaſioned by liberty, and
                    in another by the want oſ it. One of theſe opinions muſt be falſe, and it is
                    ſurely not difficult to diſtinguiſh which.</p>
                <p>Humanity would in moſt caſes diſpoſe us to to conclude, that ſuicide is the
                    effect of inſanity, were there not ſo many inſtances of cool deliberate
                    ſelf-murder. That ſuicide is an unnatural crime, which none but a madman would
                    commit, compaſſion indeed may ſuppoſe : but the murder of a wife, a father, or a
                    child, are also unnatural ; yet compaſſion does not teach us in all caſes to
                    aſcribe ſuch a crime to madneſs. Paſſion may often ariſe to ſuch a height of
                    outrage as to be ſcarcely diſtnguiſhable from madneſs in its ſymptoms and its
                    effects; yet we always make a diſtinction between that madneſs which ariſes from
                    diseaſe and that which is owing to a violent perturbation of mind. If a person
                    be capable of managing his wordly affairs, of making a will, and of diſpoſing of
                    his property, immediately before his death, or after he formed the resolution of
                    dying by his own hands, ſuch a man is not to be conſidered as inſane.</p>
                <p>But though a regard for truth prevents us from aſcribing ſuicide in all caſes to
                    inſanity, we muſt aſcribe it either to inſanity or to vicious passion. Theſe two
                    diviſions, we imagine, will comprehend every ſpecies of it, whether ariſing from
                    melancholy, <hi rend="italic">tædium vitae</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ennui,</hi>
                    diſappointment in schemes of ambition or love, pride, gaming, or a deſire to
                    avoid the ſhame of a public execution ; paſſions which are often increaſed by
                    falſe views of God, of man, and of a future ſtate, arising from deiſm and
                    infidelity. If theſe be the cauſes of ſuicide in modern time, what a disgraceful
                    contrail do they form to thoſe principles which actuated many of the ancient
                    philoſophers,the Gentoos,the Japaneſe, and the worshippers of Odin ? When they
                    committed ſuicide, they committed it from principle, from a belief of its
                    lawfulneſs, and the hope of being rewarded for what they judged an honourable
                    ſacrifice. But in modern times, we are sorry to ſay, when it is not the effect
                    of madneſs, it is the effect of vice : and when it is the effect of vice, it
                    proves that the vicious paſſions are then indulged to the higheſt degree ; for
                    there is no crime which a man can commit that is ſo ſtrong a ſympton of the
                    violence of particular paſſions. It is from not attending to this circumſtance,
                    that it has been found ſo difficult to refute the arguments in favour of
                    ſuicide. If the criminality of ſuicide be confined merely to the violent action,
                    many apologies may be made for it ; but if it be conſidered solely as the effect
                    of vice, as the ſtrongeſt ſymptom of ungoverned paſſion, he who undertakes its
                    defence muſt undertake the defence of what all men will loudly condemn<note
                        anchored="true" n="7" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                                rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> Several of the heathens entertained a very
                            juſt ſenſe of the atrocity of ſuicide. Quintus Curtins introduces Darius
                            with the following ſpeech, when he had loſt his empire : “ I wait (ſays
                            the unfortunate monarch) the iſſue of my fate : you wonder, perhaps,
                            that I do not terminate my own life ; but I chooſe rather to die by the
                            crime of another than by my own.</p><p>We cannot refuſe ourſelves the
                            pleaſure oſ preſenting to our readers the following beautiful paſſage
                            upon this ſubject from Fitzoſborne’s letters:<note anchored="true"
                                place="margin" type="authorial"> Letter lv. </note> “ I am perſuaded
                            (ſays this elegant writer) this diſguſt of life is frequently indulged
                            out of a principle of mere vanity. It is eſteemed as a mark of uncommon
                            refinement, and as placing a man above the ordinary <pb n="66"/> level
                            of his ſpecies, to ſeem ſuperior to the vulgar feelings of happineſs.
                            True good ſenſe, however, moſt certainly consists not in deſpiſing, but
                            in managing our stock of life to the best advantage, as a cheerful
                            acquieſcence in the measures of Providence is one of the strongeſt
                            ſymptoms of a well constituted mind. Self-wearineſs is a circumſtance
                            that ever attends folly ; and to condemn our being is the greateſt, and
                            indeed the peculiar infirmity, of human nature. It is a noble ſentiment
                            which Tully puts into the mouth of Cato, in his Treatiſe upon old Age ;
                                <hi rend="italic">Non lubet mihi.</hi> (ſays that venerable Roman )
                                <hi rend="italic">deplorare vitam, quod multi, et ii docti, Sœpe
                                Jecerunt ; neque me vixisse paenitet : quoniam ita vixi, ut non
                                frustra me natum exstimem.</hi></p><p>“ It is in the power, indeed,
                            of but a very ſmall portion of mankind to act the ſame glorious part
                            that afforded ſuch high ſatisfaction to this diſtinguiſhed patriot ; but
                            the number is yet far more inconſiderable of thoſe who cannot, in any
                            station, ſecure themſelves a ſufficient fund of complacency to render
                            life juſtly valuable. Who is it that is placed out ot the reach of the
                            highest of all gratifications, thoſe of the generous affections, and
                            that cannot provide for his own happineſs, by contributing ſomething to
                            the welfare of others? As this diſease of the mind generally breaks out
                            with moſt violence in thoſe who are ſuppoſed to be endowed with a
                            greater delicacy of taste and reaſon than is the uſual allotment of
                            their fellow-creatures, one may ask them, whether there is any ſatiety
                            in the purſuits of uſeful knowledge ? or, if one can ever be weary of
                            benefiting mankind ? Will not the fine arts ſupply a laſting feaſt to
                            the mind ? or, can there be wanting a pleaſurable enjoyment, ſo long as
                            there remains even one advantageous truth to be diſcovered or confirmed
                            ? To complain that life has no joys, while there is a single creature
                            whom we can relieve by our bounty, aſſist by our counsels, or enliven by
                            our preſence is, to lament the lots of that which we poſſeſs, and is
                            just as rational as to die for thirſt with the cup in our hands. But the
                            misfortune is, when a man is ſettled into a habit of receiving all his
                            pleaſures from the mere selfiſh indulgences, he wears out of his mind
                            the reliſh of every nobler enjoyment, at the ſame time that his powers
                            of the ſenſual kind are growing more languid by each repetition. It is
                            no wonder, therefore, he ſhould fill up the meaſure of his
                            gratifications long before he has completed the circle of his duration ;
                            and either wretchedly sit down the remainder of his days in diſcontent,
                            or raſhly throw them up in deſpair.”</p></note>
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p>
                <p>It is unneceſſary then to enter particularly into the argu<pb
                        facs="gri_33125011196348_0072.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0066"/>ments of
                    thoſe caſuiſts who have undertaken the deſpicable office of advocates for the
                    crime of ſuicide. Their talents might ſurely have been employed more uſefully to
                    the world, and more honourably to themſelves, than in pleading for a crime
                    which, if it were committed by every man to whom their principles would make it
                    lawful, would totally destroy ſome of the nobleſt virtues, fortitude, patience,
                    and reſignation ; nay, would deſtroy ſociety itſelf, and teach us to deſpiſe the
                    opinion that this world is a state of preparation for another. “ I came into
                    life without my own conſent, and may I not quit it at pleaſure?” (say the
                    advocates for ſuicide). If, becauſe we came into life without our own conſent,
                    we might quit it at pleaſure, why may we not ſpend our life alſo as we pleaſe ?
                    Why may we not rob and murder, and commit every kind of crime, if <hi
                        rend="italic">mere inclination</hi> is to be the rule of action ? Thus upon
                    the principles of ſuicide the highwayman and murderer may reaſon, and every man
                    may find a ſufficient apology for any crime which he is tempted to commit. Or
                    this abſurdity may be otherwiſe anſwered ; As we came into life without our own
                    conſent, we must have come with the conſent of ſome other being ; and logic
                    ſays, that with the conſent of that Being only can we lawfully quit it.</p>
                <p>It is ſufficient shortly to say, that ſuicide is contrary to the strongeſt
                    principle of the human conſtitution, ſelf-preſervation ; that it is rebellion
                    againſt God ; that it is cruelty to the feelings and reputation, and often takes
                    away the ſubſiſtence of a wife, a child, or a father ; that it proves a want of
                    fortitude to brave misfortunes ; that it delivers only from imagined to plunge
                    into real evils. We may add, that almoſt every inſtance of ſuicide of which we
                    have heard was raſh, imprudent, and premature, interrupted a uſeful life, or
                    prevented a more honourable death. Had Cato’s pride permitted him to yield
                    himſelf to the generality of Cæsar, his character and his influence might have
                    contributed to retard the ſlavery of his country, which his death tended to
                    hasten. Had Brutus and Cassius not executed the fatal reſolution which they had
                    formed, of dying by their own hands in case of misfortune, the battle of
                    Philippi might have had a very different iſſue. Had Hannibal ſurrendered himſelf
                    to the Romans, inſtead of ſwallowing person, he would have gained more glory in
                    braving their tortures than he won in the battle of Cannæ ; for to die
                    innocently and heroically is the greateſt exertion of human fortitude.</p>
                <p>As ſuicide was deemed a crime by the moſt illuſtrious and virtuous of the Greek
                    and Roman philoſophers, it was conſidered as a crime by the laws, and treated
                    with ignominy. By the law of Thebes suicides were to have no honours paid to
                    their memory<note anchored="true" n="8" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*
                            Petite Comment. in Leges Atticas, p. 523.</p></note> *. The Athenian law
                    ordained the hand which committed the deed to be cut off, and burned apart from
                    the rest of the body. The body was not buried with the uſual solemnites, but was
                    ignominiouſly thrown into ſome pit. In Cea and Maſſilia (the ancient <hi
                        rend="italic">Marseilles),</hi> it was conſidered as a crime againſt the
                    state ; and it was therefore neceſſary for thoſe who wiſhed to destroy
                    themſelves to obtain permiſſion from the magiſtrates.<note anchored="true" n="9" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Plutarch on the Virtues of
                            Women.</p></note> * Plutarch acquaints us, that an unaccountable paſſion
                    for suicide ſeized the Mileſian virgins ; from indulging which they could not be
                    prevented by the tears and entreaties of parents and friends : but what
                    perſuaſion and entreaty could not effect was accompliſhed by very different
                    means. A decree was issued, “ that the body of every young woman who hanged
                    herſelf ſhould be dragged naked through the ſtreets by the same rope with which
                    she had committed the deed.” This wise edict put a complete flop to the
                    extraordinary frenzy, and ſuicide was no longer committed by the virgins of
                    Miletus.</p>
                <p>In the early part of the Roman hiſtory there ſeems to have been ſeldom occaſion
                    for framing any laws againſt ſuicide. The only inſtance recorded occurs in the
                    reign of Taiquinius Priſcus. The ſoldiers who were appointed to make drains and
                    common ſewers, thinking themſelves diſgraced by ſuch ſervile offices, put
                    themſelves to death in great numbers. The king ordered the bodies of all the
                    ſelf-murderers to be expoſed on croſſes, and this put an effectual ſtop to the
                    practice. It is doubtful whether there was any ſtanding law againſt ſuicide
                    during the exiſtence of the republic ; but during the reign of the emperors it
                    was thought proper to lay it under certain regulations, though not abſolutely to
                    condemn it as a crime.<note anchored="false" n="10" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Lib. xlviii. Tit. xxi. par. 3.</p></note> In
                    Juſtinian’s Digeſts there is a law, by which it was enacted, “ that if persons
                    accuſed, or who had been found guilty, of any crime ſhould make away with
                    themſelves, their effects ſhould be<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0073.tif"
                        xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0067"/> confiscated." But this punishment only took
                    place when confiscation of goods happened to be the penalty appointed by the law
                    for the crime of which the self-murderer was accuſed or found guilty, and was
                    not inflicted for suicide committed in any other circumſtances.</p>
                <p>When the Chriſtian church had extended its juriſdiction in the Roman empire, it
                    was decreed in the ſixth century, that no commemoration ſhould be made in the
                    euchariſt for ſuch as destroyed themſelves ; neither ſhould their bodies be
                    carried out to burial with pſalms, nor have the usual ſervice ſaid over them.
                    This eccleſiaſtical law continued till the reformation, when it was admitted
                    into the ſtatute code of England by the authority of parliament. As an
                    additional puniſhment, however, confiſcation of land and goods ſeems to have
                    been adopted from the Danes, as we learn from Bracton<note anchored="true" n="11" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* De Legibus et Consuetudinibus
                            Angliae, Lib. iii. Tract. II.</p></note> *. At preſent the puniſhment
                    consiſts in confiſcating all the perſonal property of a <hi rend="italic">ſelo
                        de Je</hi> for the uſe of the crown, and in excluding his body from
                    interment in conſecrated ground. The warrant of the coroner requires that the
                    body ſhould be buried in ſome public highway, and a ſtake driven through it to
                    increaſe the ignominy.</p>
                <p>To inquire into the prevalence and cauſes of crimes, in order to diſcover the
                    moſt judicious methods of preventing them, is the duty of the patriot and the
                    Chriſtian. Suicide, we find, is a common and an increaſing evil: but it is a
                    difficult matter to find an effectual remedy ; for what motives can be held out
                    ſufficient to influence that man’s mind who is deaf to the voice of nature
                    speaking within him, and to the voice of nature’s God declaring that he is
                    stationed at a post which it is his duty to maintain? His reputation and
                    property are indeed within the reach of the laws, his body may be treated with
                    ignominy, and his property confiſcated ; but this puniſhment will not be a
                    preventive, even if it could be always inflicted ; and that it is ſeldom
                    inflicted, though the laws have decreed it, is well known. The humanity of the
                    preſent age diſpoſes us to ſympathiſe with the relations of the deceaſed,
                    inſtead of demanding that the ſentence of the law ſhould be executed. It is a
                    generally received opinion, and a juſt one, that puniſhments decreed by human
                    laws ſhould be directed only againſt ſuch crimes as are injurious to society ;
                    but when it is hence inferred, that ſuicide ought not to be ſubject to the
                    cognizance of human laws, every rule of logic is violated. There is no man,
                    however mean in ſtation and in talents, whoſe life may not, on ſome occaſions,
                    be uſeful to the community at large ; and to conclude, that a perſon who fancies
                    himſelf uſeleſs may therefore lawfully put a period to his life, is as falſe
                    reaſoning as it would be to conclude, that by killing a poor man, who lives on
                    the public, we ſhould perform an action not only innocent but meritorious, as we
                    ſhould thereby free ſociety from one of its burdens.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
