<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0048.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0042-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STUCCO</label>,
in building, a compoſition of white marble pulveriſed, and mixed with plaſter of lime ; and the whole being lifted and wrought up with water, is to be uſed like common plaſter : this is called by Pliny <hi rend="italic">marmoratum opus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">albarium opus.</hi></p><p>A patent has been granted to Mr B. Higgins for inventing a new kind of ſtucco, or water-cement, more firm and durable than any heretofore. Its composition, as ex-<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0049.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0043"/>
tracted from the specification ſigned by himſelf, is as follows : “ Drift-ſand, or quarry<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> “ This is commonly called <hi rend="italic">pit-ſand.</hi></p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> sand, which conſists chiefly of hard quartoſe flab faced grains with ſharp angles ; which is the freest, or may be most eaſily freed by waſhing, from clay, ſalts, and calcareous, gypſeous, or other grains leſs hard and durable than quartz ; which contains the ſmalleſt quantity of pyrites or heavy metallic matter inſeparable by waſhing ; and which ſuffers the ſmalleſt diminution of its bulk in waſhing in the following manner—is to be preferred before any other. And where a coarſe and a fine sand of this kind, and correſponding in the size of their grains with the coarſe and fine ſands hereafter deſcribed, cannot be eaſily procured, let ſuch sand of the foregoing quality be choſen as may be ſorted and cleanſed in the following manner :</p><p>“ Let the sand be ſifted in ſtreaming clear water, thro’ a ſieve which ſhall give paſſage to all ſuch grains as do not exceed owe-sixteenth of an inch in diameter ; and let the stream of water and the ſifting be regulated ſo that all the sand, which is much finer than the Lynn-ſand commonly uſed in the London glaſs-houſes, together with clay and every other matter ſpecifically lighter than sand, may be washed away with the ftream, whilſt the purer and coarſer sand, which passes through the ſieve, ſubſides in a convenient receptacle, and whilſt the coarſe rubbiſh and rubble remain on the ſieve to be rejected.</p><p>“ Let the sand which thus ſubſides in the receptacle be waſhed in clean ſtreaming water through a finer ſieve, ſo as to be further cleanſed and ſorted into two parcels ; a coarſer, which will remain in the ſieve which is to give paſſage to ſuch grains of sand only as are leſs than one-thirtieth of an inch in diameter, and which is to be ſaved apart under the name of <hi rend="italic">coarſe sand;</hi> and a finer, which will pass thro’ the ſieve and ſubſide in the water, and which is to be ſaved apart under the name of fine sa <hi rend="italic">nd.—</hi> Let the coarſe and the fine sand be dried ſeparately, either in the ſun or on a clean iron-plate, ſet on a convenient surface, in the manner of a ſand-heat<note anchored="true" n="2" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b) "</hi> The sand ought to be ſtirred up continually until it is dried, and is then to be taken off; for otherwiſe the evaporation will be very flow, and the sand which lies next the iron plate, by being overheated, will be diſcoloured.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(b).</hi></p><p>“ Let lime be choſen<note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(c) “ The preference given to ſtone-lime is founded on the preſent practice in the burning of lime, and on the cloſer texture of it, which prevents it from being ſo ſoon injured by expoſure to the air as the more ſpongy chalklime is ; not on the popular notion that ſtone-lime has ſomething in it whereby it excels the beſt chalk in the cementing properties. The gypſum contained in lime-ſtone remains unaltered, or very little altered, in the lime, after the burning ; but it is not to be expected that clay or martial matter ſhould be found in their native ſtate in well-burned lime ; for they concrete or vitrify with a part of the calcareous earth, and constitute the hard grains or lumps which remain undiſſolved in weak acids, or are ſeparable from the slaked lime by ſifting it immediately through a ſieve.</p></note> (c) which is ſtone-lime, which heats the moſt in slaking, and slakes the quſekeſt when duly watered ; which is the fresheſt made and cloſeſt kept ; which diſſolves in diſtilled vinegar with the leaſt efferveſcence, and leaves the ſmalleſt reſidue inſoluble, and in this reſidue the ſmalleſt quantity of clay, gypſum, or martial matter.</p><p>“ Let the lime choſen according to theſe important rules be put in a braſs-wired ſieve to the quantity of 14 pounds. Let the ſieve be finer than either of the foregoing ; the finer, the better it will be : let the lime be slaked<note anchored="true" n="4" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(d)</hi> “ This method of impregnating the water with lime is not the only one which may be adopted. It is, however, preferred before others, becauſe the water clears the ſooner in conſequence of its being warmed by the slaking lime ; and the gypſeous part of the lime does not diffuſe itſelf in the water ſo freely in this way as it does when the lime is slaked to fine powder in the common method, and is then blended with the water ; for the gypſeous part of the lime slakes at firſt into grains rather than into fine powder, and will remain on the ſieve after the pure lime has paſſed through, long enough to admit of the intended ſeparation ; but When the lime is otherwiſe slaked, the gypſeous grains have time to slake to a finer powder, and paſſing through the ſieve, dissolve in the water along with the lime. I have imagined that other advantages attended this method of preparing the lime-water, but I cannot yet speak of them with preciſion.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(d)</hi> by plunging it in a butt filled with ſoft water, and raising it out quickly and ſuffering it to heat and fume, and by repeating this plunging and railing alternately, and agitating the lime, until it be made to pass through the ſieve into the water ; and let the part of the lime which does not eaſily paſs through the ſieve be rejected : and let freſh portions of the lime be thus uſed, until as many<note anchored="true" n="5" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(e)</hi> “ If the water contains no more acidulous gas than is uſually found in river or rain water, a fourth part of this quantity of lime, or leſs, will be ſufficient.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(e)</hi> ounces of lime have paſſed through the ſieve as there are quarts of water in the butt. Let the water thus impregnated ſtand in the butt cloſely covered<note anchored="true" n="6" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(f)</hi> “ The calcareous crust which forms on the ſurface of the water ought not to be broke, for it aſſists in excluding the air, and preventing the abſorption of acidulous gas whereby the lime-water is spoiled.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(f)</hi> until it becomes clear ; and through wooden<note anchored="true" n="7" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(g)</hi> "Braſs-cocks are apt to colour a part of the liquor.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(g)</hi> cocks placed at different heights in the butt, let the clear liquor be drawn off as faſt<note anchored="true" n="8" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">( h)</hi> “ Lime-water cannot be kept many days unimpaired, in any veſſels that are not perfectly air-tight. If the liquor be drawn off before it clears, it will contain whiting, which is injurious ; and if it be not instantly uſed after it is drawn limpid from the butt into open veſſels, it will grow turbid again, and depoſit the lime changed to whiting by the gas absorbed from the air. The calcareous matter which ſubſides in the butt reſembles whiting the more nearly as the lime has been more ſparingly employed ; in the contrary circumstances, it approaches to the nature of lime ; and in the intermediate state, it is fit for the common composition of the plaſterers for inside stucco.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(h)</hi> and as low as the lime ſubſides, for uſe. This clear liquor I call the <hi rend="italic">cementing liquor</hi><note anchored="true" n="9" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(I) “ At the time of writing this specification, I preferred this term before that of lime-water, on grounds which I had not ſufficiently examined,</p></note> (I). The freer the water is from ſaline matter, the better will be the cementing liquor made with it.<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0050.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0044"/>
" Let 56 pounds of the aforeſaid choſen lime be flaked, by gradually ſprinkling on it, and eſpecially on the unflaked pieces, the cementing liquor, in a cloſe<note anchored="true" n="10" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(κ.) “ The vapour which ariſes in the flaking of lime contributes greatly to the flaking of theſe pieces which lie in its way ; and an unnecessary waſte of the liquor is prevented, by applying it to the lime heaped in a pit or in a veſſel, which may reſtrain the iſſue of the vapour, and direct it through the maſs. If more of the liquor ſhe uſed than is neceſſary to slake the lime, it will create error in weighing the flaked powder, and will prevent a part of it from paſſing freely thro’ the ſieve. The liquid is therefore to be uſed ſparingly, and the lime which has eſcaped its action is to be ſprinkled apart with freſh liquor.</p></note> (κ) clean place. Let the flaked part be immediately<note anchored="true" n="11" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(l)</hi> “ When the aggregation of the lumps of lime is thus broken, it is impaired much ſooner than it is in the former state, becauſe the air more freely pervades it.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(l)</hi> ſifted through the laſt-mentioned fine braſs-wired ſieve : Let the lime which paſſes be uſed inſtantly, or kept in air-tight veſſels, and let the part of the lime which does not paſs through the ſieve be rejected<note anchored="true" n="12" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(m)</hi> “ Becauſe it conſiſts of heterogeneous matter or of ill-burnt lime ; which laſt will slake and paſs through the sieve, if the lime be not immediately lifted after the flaking, agreeable to the text.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(m).</hi> —This finer richer part of the lime which paſſes through the ſieve I call <hi rend="italic">purified lime.</hi></p><p>“ Let bone-aſh be prepared in the uſual manner, by grinding the whiteſt burnt bones, but let it be ſifted, to be much finer than the bone-aſh commonly sold for making cupels.</p><p>“ The moſt eligible materials for making my cement being thus prepared, take 56 pounds of the coarſe sand and 42 pounds of the fine sand ; mix them on a large plank of hard wood placed horizontally ; then ſpread the sand ſo that it may ſtand to the height of six inches, with a flat ſurface on the plank ; wet it with the cementing liquor ; and let any ſuperfluous quantity of the liquor, which the sand in the condition deſcribed cannot retain, flow away off the plank. To the wetteſt sand add 14 pounds of the putrefied lime in ſeveral ſuccessive portions, mixing and beating them up together in the mean time with the inſtruments generally uſed in making fine mortar : then add 14 pounds of the bone-aſh in ſucceſſive portions, mixing and beating all together. The quicker and the more perfectly theſe materials are mixed and beaten together, and the ſooner the cement thus formed is uſed, the better<note anchored="true" n="13" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(n)</hi> “ Theſe proportions are intended for a cement made with ſharp sand, for incruſtation in expoſed ſituations, where it is neceſſary to guard againſt the effects of hot weather and rain. In general, half this quantity of bone-aſhes will be found sufficient ; and although the incruſtation in this latter caſe will not harden deeply ſo ſoon, it will be ultimately ſtronger, provided the weather be favourable.</p><p>“ The injuries which lime and mortar ſuſtain by expoſure to the air, before the cement is finally placed in a quieſcent ſtate, are great ; and therefore our cement is the worſe for being long beaten, but the better as it is quickly beaten until the mixture is effected, and no longer.</p></note> (<hi rend="smallcaps">n</hi>) it will be. This I call the <hi rend="italic">water-cement coarſe-grained,</hi> which is to be applied in building, pointing, plaſtering, ſtuccbing, or other work, as mortar and ſtucco now are ; with this difference chiefly, that as this cement is ſhorter than mortar or common ſtucco, and dries ſooner, it ought to be worked expeditiouſly in all caſes; and in ſtuccoing, it ought to be laid on by sliding the trowel upwards on it ; that the materials uſed along with this cement in building, or the ground on which it is to be laid in ſtuccoing, ought to be well wetted with the cementing liquor in the inſtant of laying on the cement; and that the cementing liquor is to be uſed when it is neceſſary to moiſten the cement, or when a liquid is required to facilitate the floating of the cement.</p><p>“ When ſuch cement is required to be of a finer texture, take 98 pounds of the fine sand, wet it with the cementing liquor, and mix it with the purified lime and the bone- aſh in the quantities and in the manner above deſcribed ; with this difference only, that 15 pounds of lime, or<note anchored="true" n="14" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(o) “ The quantity oſ bone-aſhes is not to be increaſed with that of the lime ; but it is to be leſſened as the exposure and purpoſes of the work will admit.</p></note> (o) thereabouts, are to be uſed inſtead of 14 pounds, if the greater part of the sand be as fine as Lynn sand. This I call <hi rend="italic">water-cement fine-grained.</hi> It is to be uſed in giving the laſt coating, or the finiſh to any work intended to imitate the finer-grained ſtones or ſtucco. But it may be applied to all the uſes of the water-cement coarſe grained, and in the ſame manner.</p><p>“ When for any of the foregoing purpoſes of pointing, building, &amp;c. ſuch a cement is required much cheaper and coarſer-grained, then much coarſer clean sand than the foregoing coarſe sand, or well-waſhed fine rubble, is to be provided. Of this coarſe sand or rubble take 56 pounds, of the foregoing coarſe sand 28 pounds, and of the fine sand 14 pounds ; and after mixing theſe, and wetting them with the cementing liquor in the foregoing manner, add 14 pounds, or ſomewhat leſs, of the<note anchored="true" n="15" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(P) "Becauſe leſs lime is neceſſary, as the sand is coarſer.</p></note> (p) purified lime, and then 14 pounds or ſomewhat leſs of the bone-ash, mixing them together in the manner already described. When my cement is required to be white, white sand, white lime, and the whiteſt bone-aſh are to be choſen. Grey sand, and grey bone-aſh formed of half-burnt bones, are to be choſen to make the cement grey ; and any other colour of the cement is obtained, either by chooſing coloured sand, or by the admixture of the necessary quantity of coloured talc in powder, or of coloured, vitreous, or metallic powders, or other durable colouring ingredients commonly uſed in paint.</p><p>“ To the end that ſuch a water-cement as I have deſcribed may be made as uſeful as it it poſſible in all circumſtances ; and that no perſon may imagine that my claim and right under theſe letters-patent may be eluded by divers variations, which may be made in the foregoing proceſs without producing any notable defect in the cement ; and to the end that the principles of this art, as well as the art itſelf, of making my cement, may be gathered from this ſpecification and perpetuated to the public ; I ſhall add the following observations ;</p><p>“ This my water-cement, whether the coarſe or fine grained, is applicable in forming artificial ſtone, by making alternate layers of the cement and of flint, hard ſtone, or<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0051.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0045"/>
brick, in moulds of the figure of the intended ſtone, and by expoſing the maſſes ſo formed to the open<note anchored="true" n="16" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(q)</hi> “ But they muſt not be expoſed to the rain until they are almoſt as ſtrong as freſh Portland ſtone ; and even then they ought to be ſheltered from it as much as the circumſtances will admit. Theſe ſtones may be made very hard and beautiful, with a ſmall expence of bone-aſh, by ſoaking them, after they have dried thoroughly and hardened, in the lime liquor, and repeating this proceſs twice or thrice, at diſtant intervals of time. The like effect was experienced in incruſtations.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(q.)</hi> air to harden.</p><p>“ When ſuch cement is required for water<note anchored="true" n="17" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(κ) “ In my experiments, mortar made with terras-powder, in the uſual method, does not appear to form ſo ſtrong a cement for water-fences as that made, according to the ſpecification, with coarse sand ; and I ſee no more reaſon for avoiding the uſe of sand in terras-mortar, than there would be for rejecting ſtone from the embankment. The bone- aſhes meant in this place are the dark grey or black sort. I am not yet fully ſatisfied about the operation of them in this inſtance.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(r)</hi> fences, two-thirds of the preſcribed quantity of bone-ashes are to be omitted ; and in the place thereof an equal meaſure <hi rend="italic">of</hi> powdered terras is to be uſed ; and if the sand employed be not of the coarseſt sort, more terras muſt be added, ſo that the terras ſhall be by weight one-ſixth part of the weight of the sand.</p><p>“ When ſuch a cement is required of the fineſt grain<note anchored="true" n="18" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(s) “ The qualities and uſes of ſuch fine calcareous cement are recommended chiefly for the purpoſe of ſmoothing and finiſhing the ſtronger cruſtaceous works, or for waſhing walls to a lively and uniform colour. For this laſt intention, the mixture muſt be as thin as new cream, and laid on brilkly with a bruſh, in dry weather ; and a thick and durable coat is to be made by repeated waſhing ; but is not to be attempted by uſing a thicker liquor ; for the coat made with this laſt is apt to ſcale, whilſt the former endures the weather much longer than any other thin calcareous covering that has been applied in this way. Fine yellow-ochre is the cheapeſt colouring-ingredient for ſuch waſh, when it is required to imitate Bath-ſtone, or the warm-white ſtones.</p></note> (s) or in a fluid form, ſo that it may be applied with a bruſh, flint powder, or the powder of any quartoſe or hard earthy ſubstance, may be uſed in the place of sand ; but in a quantity ſmaller, as the flint or other powder is finer ; ſo that the flint-powder, or other ſuch powder, ſhall not be more than six times the weight of the lime, nor less than four times its weight. The greater the quantity of lime within theſe limits, the more will the cement be liable to crack by quick drying, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa.</hi></p><p>“ Where ſuch sand as I prefer cannot be conveniently procured, or where the sand cannot be conveniently waſhed and ſorted, that sand which moſt reſembles the mixture of coarse and fine sand above preſcribed, may be uſed as I have directed, provided due attention is paid to the quantity of the lime, which is to be greater<note anchored="true" n="19" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(T) “ If ſea-ſand be well waſhed in freſh water, it is as good as any other round sand.</p></note> (T) as the quantity is finer, and <hi rend="italic">vice verſa.</hi></p><p>“ Where sand cannot be eaſily procured, any durable ſtony body, or baked earth groſsly powdered<note anchored="true" n="20" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(U) “ The cement made with theſe and the proper quantities of purified lime and lime-water, are inferior to the beſt, as the grains of theſe powders are more periſhable and brittle than thoſe of sand. They will not therefore be employed, unleſs for the ſake of evaſion, or for want of sand : in this latter caſe, the finer powder ought to be waſhed away.</p></note> (u), and ſorted nearly to the sizes above preſcribed for sand, may be uſed in the place of sand, meaſure for meaſure, but not weight for weight, unleſs ſuch groſs powder be as heavy ſpecifically as sand.</p><p>“ Sand may be cleanſed from every ſofter, lighter, and leſs durable matter, and from that part of the sand which is too fine, by various methods preferable<note anchored="true" n="21" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(x) “ This and the next paragraph is inſerted with a view to evaſions, as well as to ſuggeſt the eaſier and cheaper methods which may be adopted in certain circumſtances, by artiſts who underſtand the principles which I endeavoured to teach.</p></note> (x), in certain circumstances, to that which I have deſcribed.</p><p>“ Water may be found naturally free from fixable gas, ſelenite, or clay ; ſuch water may, without any notable inconvenience, be uſed in the place of the cementing liquor ; and water approaching this ſtate will not require ſo much lime as I have ordered to make the cementing liquor ; and a cementing liquor ſufficiently uſeful may be made by various methods of mixing lime and water in the deſcribed proportions, or nearly ſo.</p><p>“ When ſtone-lime cannot be procured, chalk-lime, or ſhell-lime, which beſt reſembles ſtone-lime, in the characters above written of lime, may be uſed in the manner deſcribed, except that fourteen pounds and a half of chalklime will be required in the place of fourteen pounds of ſtone-lime. The proportion of lime which I have preſcribed above may be increaſed without inconvenience, when the cement or ſtucco is to be applied where it is not liable to dry quickly ; and in the contrary circumſtance, this proportion may be diminiſhed ; and the defect of lime in quantity or quality may be very advantageouſly ſupplied<note anchored="true" n="22" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>(Y) “ This practice is noticed, as the remedy which may be uſed for the defects ariſing from evasive meaſures, and as the method of giving ſpongy incruſtations containing bone-ashes the greateſt degree of hardneſs.’’</p></note> (Y), by cauſing a conſiderable quantity of the cementing liquor to ſoak into the work, in ſucceſſive portions, and at diſtant intervals of time, ſo that the calcareous matter of the cementing liquor, and the matter attracted from the open air, may fill and ſtrengthen the work.</p><p>“ The powder of almoſt every well-dried or burnt animal ſubstance may be uſed inſtead of bone-aſh ; and ſeveral earthy powders, eſpecially the micaceous and the metallic ; and the elixated aſhes of divers vegetables whoſe earth will not burn to lime ; and the aſhes of mineral fuel, which are of the calcareous kind, but will not burn to lime, will anſwer the ends of bone-aſh in ſome degree.</p><p>“ The quantity of bone-aſh deſeribed may be lessened without injuring the cement, in thoſe circumſtances eſpecially which admit the quantity of lime to be leſſened, and in thoſe wherein the cement is not liable to dry quickly. And the art of remedying the defects of lime may be advantageouſly practised to ſupply the deficiency of bone-aſh, eſpecially in building, and in making artificial ſtone with this cement.<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0052.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0046"/>
</p></div></body></text></TEI>