<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0056.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0050-20" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUBSCRIPTION</label>,
in general, ſignifies the signature put at the bottom of a letter, writing, or inſtrument.</p><p>In commerce, it is uſed for the ſhare or intereſt which particular perſons take in a public ſtock or a trading com-<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0057.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s06-0051"/>
pany, by writing their names, and the ſhares they require, in the books or regiſter thereof</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Subscription</hi> to articles of faith is required of the clergy of every eftabliſhed church, and of ſome churches not eftabliſhed. Whether ſuch ſubſcription ſerves any good purpoſe, in a religious or theological view, is a very doubtful queſtion. It may be neceſſary in an eſtabliſhment, as a teſt of loyalty to the prince, and of attachment to the conſtitution, civil and eccleſiaſtical, but it cannot produce uniformity of opinion. As all language is more or leſs ambiguous, it becomes difficult, if not impoſſible, to determine in what ſenſe the words of long eftabliſhed creeds are to be interpreted ; and we believe that the clergy of the churches of England and Scotland ſeldom conſider themſelves as fettered by the Thirty-nine Articles, or the Confeſſion of Faith, when compoſing instructions either for their reſpective pariſhes or for the public at large. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Independents.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Subscription,</hi> in the commerce of books, ſignifies an engagement to take a certain number of copies of a book intended to be printed, and a reciprocal obligation of the bookſeller or publiſher to deliver the laid copies, on certain terms.—Theſe ſubſcriptions, which had their rise in England about the middle of the laſt century, were lately very frequent in France and Holland, and are now very common among ourſelves.</p></div></body></text></TEI>