<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-s01-1000-01" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_1063.jp2" type="entry"><p><label>SAFRANINE</label>, in chemistry, the azonium compounds of symmetrical diamino-phenazine and containing the ring system annexed:—</p><p>They are obtained by the joint oxidation of one molecule of a paradiamine with two molecules of a primary amine; by the condensation of para-aminoazo compounds with primary amines (O. Witt, <hi rend="italic">Ber.,</hi> 1877, 10, p. 874), and by the action of para-nitrosodialkylanilines with secondary bases such as diphenylmetaphenylenediamine. They are crystalline solids showing a characteristic green metallic lustre; they are readily soluble in water and dye red or violet. They are strong bases and form stable monacid salts. Their alcoholic solution shows a yellow-red fluorescence.</p><p>Phenosafranine is not very stable in the free state; its chloride forms green plates. It can be readily diazotized, and the diazonium salt when boiled with alcohol yields aposafranine or benzene induline, C <hi rend="sub">18</hi> H <hi rend="sub">12</hi> N <hi rend="sub">2</hi> F. Kehrmann showed that aposafranine could be dia-zotized in the presence of cold concentrated sulphuric acid, and the diazonium salt on boiling with alcohol yielded phenylphenazonium salts. Aposafranone, C <hi rend="sub">18</hi> H <hi rend="sub">12</hi> N <hi rend="sub">2</hi> O, is formed by heating aposafranine with concentrated hydrochloric acid. These three compounds are perhaps to be represented as ortho- or as paraquinones (see papers by F. Kehrmann, O. Fischer and E. Hepp; R. Nietzki and others, <hi rend="italic">Βer.,</hi> 1895 et seq.). The “ safranine ” of commerce is a tolusafranine. The first aniline dye-stuff to be prepared on a manufacturing scale was <hi rend="italic">mauυeine,</hi> C <hi rend="sub">27</hi> H <hi rend="sub">25</hi> N <hi rend="sub">4</hi> Cl which was obtained by Sir W. H. Perkin by heating crude aniline with potassium bichromate and sulphuric acid. It is a N-phenylsafranine (see Indulines).</p></div></body></text></TEI>