<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-s01-1013-01"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_1076.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SAINT ALBIN, ALEXANDER CHARLES OMER ROUSSELIN DE CORBEAU</label>, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Comte de</hi> (1773-1847), French politician, was born in Paris,
                        of a noble Dauphinois family, and was educated at the Collège d’Harcourt. He
                        embraced the revolutionary ideas with enthusiasm. As civil commissioner at
                        Troyes he was accused of terrorism by some, and by the revolutionary
                        tribunal of moderation. He was imprisoned for a short time in 1794. On his
                        release the Citoyen Rousselin entered the ministry of the interior, and
                        under the Directory he became secretary-general, and then civil commissioner
                        of the Seine. Attached to the party of Bernadotte, he was looked on with
                        suspicion by the imperial police, and during the later years of the empire
                        spent his time in retirement at Provence. During the Hundred Days, however,
                        he served under Carnot at the ministry of the interior. Under the
                        Restoration he defended Liberal principles in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Constitutionnel,</hi> of which he was the founder. Although
                    Louis Philippe had been his friend since the days of the Revolution, he accepted
                    no office from the monarchy of July. He retired from the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Constitutionnel</hi> in 1838, and died on the 15th of June 1847. His chief
                    works deal with the soldiers of the Revolution. They are: <hi rend="italic">Vie
                        de Lazare Hoche</hi> (2 vols., 1798); <hi rend="italic">Notice historique
                        sur le général Marbol</hi> (1800); <hi rend="italic">M. de Championnel</hi>
                    (1860) ; and notices of others posthumously published by his son, Hortensius de
                    Saint Albin, as <hi rend="italic">Documents relatifs à la Révolution Française .
                        . .</hi> (1873).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
