<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0210.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0204-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SUTHERLAND</label>,
one of the moſt northerly counties of Scotland. Including Strathnavern, it borders on Caithneſs to the north and north-eaſt, is bounded by the ocean on the north, the country of Assynt on the west, Roſs on the ſouth, and by the German ſea on the eaſt and ſouth-eaſt. It ſtretches about 70 miles in length, and 40 in breadth ; is generally hilly, tho' in many parts arable ; well watered with ſmall rivers and ſtreams replete with fiſh, and exhibiting about 60 lakes, the habitation of various fiſh, ſwans, ducks, geeſe, &amp;c. One of the largeſt of theſe is Lochſhin, extending 18 miles in length. Some of them are interſperſed with ſmall verdant islands, which in ſummer yield a very agreeable proſpect. On the coaſt are many commodious harbours, and all the bays ſwarm with fiſh ; nay, the ſea in this place produces ſome valuable pearls. Sutherland affords iron-ſtone, free- ſtone, lime-ſtone, and ſlate, in abundance. Here are alſo quarries of marble, and mines of coal, though the people life turf and peat for fuel. Lead ore, impregnated with ſilver, and even ſome gold, hath been found in this province, together with cryſtals and pebbles.</p><p>The air is ſo temperate, and the ſoil ſo good, that ſaffron has here been brought to perfection. Many parts of the country are remarkably fruitful in corn, and the paſturage is excellent everywhere, Besides three great foreſts, there are many ſmaller woods in Sutherland, abounding with deer and other game. On the hills are fed numerous flocks of ſheep and black cattle ; ſmall, yet ſweet and juicy. There is one bird peculiar to this ſhire, called <hi rend="italic">knag,</hi> which reſembles a parrot, and digs its neſt with its beak in the trunks of oaks. The northern part, called <hi rend="italic">Strathnavern,</hi> and ſeparated from the rest by a ridge of mountains, is bounded on the north by the Deucaledoaian ſea, on the west by the channel called the <hi rend="italic">Minch,</hi> on the eaſt by Caithneſs, and on the ſouth by Aſſynt. The length of it, from eaſt to west, amounts to 34 miles; but the breadth from north to ſouth does not exceed 12 in ſome places. It is very hilly ; and the mountains are ſo high, that the ſnow remains on the tops of them till mid- ſummer. It is watered by Navern, from whence it derives its name : as this diſtrict gives a title to the eldeſt ſon of the earl of Sutherland. Here are ſeveral woods, frequented by deer and other game, which the people take great delight in hunting. Iron-mines have been worked in ſome places, but to no great advantage. Strathnavern has many freſh water lakes or lochs ; the chief of which arc Loch Navern and Loch Lyel : there are ſeveral iſlands on the northern coaſt ; and in various parts of the country we see monuments of victories obtained over the Danes or other foreign invaders. Sutherland boaſts of ſome towns, and a great many villages. The people are numerous, hardy, bold, and enterprising ; courteous to ſtrangers ; cheerful, open, frugal, and induſtrious. They, as well as their neighbours of Caithneſs, ſpeak the language, and wear the garb, uſed in the Lowlands of Scotland. They carry on a conſiderable ſalmon-f\iſhery. They drive a traffic with their black cattle, ſheep, and horſes, at the neighbouring fairs ; but export their corn, barley, ſalt, coal, ſalmon, ſalted beef, butter, cheeſe, wool-ſkins, hides, and tallow. Here are proviſions of all sorts in plenty ; and ſo cheap through all this country, that a gentleman may keep houſe and live much more ſumptuously for 200 l. a-year than he can live for three times the money in the ſouth of England.</p></div></body></text></TEI>