<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196348_0197.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0191-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SURNAME</label>,
that which is added to the proper name for diſtinguiſhing perſons and families. It was originally diſtinguiſhed from s <hi rend="italic">irname,</hi> which denotes the name of the sir <hi rend="italic">e</hi> or progenitor : thus Macdonald, Robertſon are firnames expreſſing the ſon of Donald, the ſon of Robert. The word <hi rend="italic">ſurname,</hi> again, signified ſome name ſuperadded to the proper name to diſtinguiſh the individual, as Artaxerxes <hi rend="italic">Longimanus,</hi> Harold <hi rend="italic">Harefoot,</hi> Malcolm <hi rend="italic">Canmore.</hi> From this it is evident that every ſirname was a ſurname, though the reverſe was not ſo. In modern times they are confounded ; and as there is now no occaſion to preſerve the diſtinction, Dr Johnſon has rejected the word s <hi rend="italic">irname</hi> altogether. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Name.</hi></p><p>Surnames were introduced among all nations at an early</p><p>period, and ſeem to have been formed at firſt by adding the name of the father to that of the ſon. This was the practice among the Hebrews, as appears from the scriptures. Caleb is denominated the ſon of Jephunneh, and Joſhua the ſon of Nun. That the ſame thing was cuſtomary among the Greeks, every one who has read the poems of Homer muſt remember. We have an inſtance of it in the very firſt line of the Iliad : Αχιλληος Πηληιαϛεω, "Achilles the ſon of Peleus.”</p><p>This is perhaps the general origin of ſurnames, for it has been common among moſt nations<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> This might be ſupported by examples borrowed from many nations. The old Normans uſed <hi rend="italic">Fitz,</hi> which signifies ſon ; as Fitzherbert, Fitzsimmons, the ſon of Herbert, the ſon of Simmons. The Iriſh uſed O <hi rend="italic">;</hi> as O''Neal, the ſon of Neal. The Scotch Highlanders employed <hi rend="italic">Mac ;</hi> as Macdonald, the ſon of Donald. The Saxons added the word <hi rend="italic">ſon</hi> to the end of the father’s name, as Williamſon.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi></p><p>The Romans generally had three names. The firſt called <hi rend="italic">praenomen</hi> anſwered to our Chriſtian name, and was intended to diſtinguiſh the individuals of the ſame family ; the second called <hi rend="italic">nomen</hi> correſponded to the word <hi rend="italic">clan</hi> in Scotland, and was given to all thoſe who were ſprung from the ſame ſtock ; the third called <hi rend="italic">cognomen</hi> expreſſed the particular branch of the tribe or clan from which an individual was ſprung. Thus Publius Cornelius Scipio, <hi rend="italic">Publius</hi> correſponded to our names John, Robert, William ; <hi rend="italic">Cornelius</hi> was the name of the clan or tribe, as Campbell was formerly the name of all the Duke of Argyle’s clients, and Douglas the name of the retainers of the Duke of Hamilton’s progenitors. <hi rend="italic">Scipio</hi> being added, conveyed this information, that Publius, who was of the tribe of the Cornelii, was of the family of the Scipios, one of the branches or families into which that tribe was divided. Reſpecting the three names which were common among the Romans, we may ſay that the firſt was a name and the other two ſurnames.</p><p>Du Cheſne obſerves, that ſurnames were unknown in France before the year 987, when the lords began to aſſume the names of their demeſnes. Camden relates, that they were firſt taken up in England, a little before the conquest, under King Edward the Confeſſor : but he adds, they were never fully eſtabliſhed among the common people till the time of Edward II. ; till then they varied with the father’s name ; if the father, <hi rend="italic">e. gr.</hi> was called <hi rend="italic">Richard,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Roger,</hi> the ſon was called <hi rend="italic">Richardſon,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Hodgſon ;</hi> but from that time they were ſettled, ſome ſay, by act of parliament. The oldeſt ſurnames are thoſe we find in Domeſday-Book, moſt of them taken from places, with the addition of <hi rend="italic">de ;</hi> as Godeſeidus <hi rend="italic">de</hi> Mannevilla, Walterus <hi rend="italic">de</hi> Vernon, Robert <hi rend="italic">de</hi> Oyly, &amp;c. Others from their fathers, with <hi rend="italic">filius,</hi> as Gulielmus <hi rend="italic">filius</hi> Oſberni ; others from their offices, as Eudo <hi rend="italic">Dapifer,</hi> Gulielmus <hi rend="italic">Camerarius,</hi> Giſlebertus <hi rend="italic">Cocus,</hi> &amp;c. But the inferior people are noted simply by their Chriſtian names, without any ſurnames at all.</p><p>They ſeem to have been introduced into Scotland in the time of William the Conqueror by the Engliſh who accompanied Edgar Atheling when he fled into that kingdom. Theſe had their proper ſurnames, as Moubray, Lovell, Liſle, uſing the particle <hi rend="italic">de</hi> before them ; which makes it probable that theſe ſurnames had been derived from the lands which their anceſtors or they themſelves had poſſeſſed. In Kenneth Il’s. time in 800. the great men had indeed begun to call their lands by their own names ; but the ordinary diſtinctions then uſed were only perſonal, and did not deſcend to ſucceeding generations, ſuch as thoſe employed by the Hebrews and Greeks : For example, <hi rend="italic">John the son of William</hi>; or the names of office, as Stewart ; or accidental diſtinctions from complexion or ſtation, as Black,<pb facs="gri_33125011196348_0198.tif" xml:id="eb03-18-s07-0192"/>
White, Long, Short ; or the name of their trade, as Taylor, Weaver.</p><p>It was long before any ſurnames were uſed in Wales, except that of ſon, as Evan ap Rice, Evan the ſon of Rice ; Evan ap Howel, Evan the ſon of Howel : but many of them have at length formed ſeparate ſurnames, as the Engliſh and Scots, by leaving out the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> in <hi rend="italic">ap,</hi> and joining the <hi rend="italic">p</hi> to the father’s name: thus Evan ap Rice becomes Evan Price ; Evan ap Howel, Evan Powel.—We are told, ſurnames were unknown in Sweden till the year 1514, and that the common people of that country uſe none to this day ; and that the ſame is the caſe with the vulgar Iriſh, Poles, and Bohemians.</p><p>When we come to inquire into the etymology of ſurnames, we must allow that many of them were originally ſignificant of the qualities of mind, as Bold, Hardy Meek ; ſome of the qualities of body, as Strong, Low, Short ; others expreſſive of the trade or profeſſion followed by the perſons to whom they were applied, as Baker, Smith, Wright ; Butler, Page, Marſhal. But the greatest number, at leaſt of the ancient ſurnames, were borrowed from the names of places. Camden ſays, that there is not a village in Normandy but has given its name to ſome family in England, He mentions as examples, Percy, Devereux, Tankervil, Mortimer, Warren, &amp;c. They were introduced with William the Conqueror. Several have been derived from places in the Netherlands, as Gaunt, Tournay, Grandiſon ; and many from the names of towns and villages in England and Scotland, as Wentworth, Markham, Murray, Aberdeen. Many have been formed from the names of animals, as quadrupeds, birds, fiſhes ; from vegetables, and parts of vegetables, as trees, ſhrubs, flowers, and fruits ; from minerals of different kinds. Others are formed from ſuch a variety of accidents that it is impoſſible to particularize them.</p></div></body></text></TEI>