<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:18Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a fair commerce with Africa, and all the bleſſings which might be expected to attend it. Conſiderable advantages appeared hereby likely to reſult to Great Britain, not only from our obtaining ſeveral commodities cheaper, but alſo from opening a market for Britiſh manufactures, to the increaſing demands of which it is difficult to aſſign a limit. From this connection, Africa was likely to derive the ſtill more important benefits of religion, morality, and civilization. To accompliſh theſe purpoſes, it was neceſſary for the company to poſſeſs a tract of land, as a repoſitory for their goods, and which the Africans might cultivate in peace, ſecure from the ravages of the ſlave-trade. It had been aſcertained, beyond a doubt, that the climate and soil of Africa were admirably ſuited to the growth of ſugar, ſpices, coffee, cotton, indigo, rice, and every other ſpecies of tropical produce. The company propoſed to inſtruct the natives to raise theſe articles, and to ſet them the example, by a ſpirited cultivation, on its own account. Directions were given to the company’s commercial agent to puſh forward a trade, in a mode preſcribed, in the preſent produce of Africa. Meaſures were taken for cultivating, on the company’s account, the moſt profitable tropical produce ; and in particular, a perſon of long experience in the West Indies was ordered to begin a ſugar plantation. A mineralogiſt and botaniſt were likewiſe engaged to go out and explore the country for new articles of commerce.</p><p>Every thing being thus ſettled upon the moſt equitable and benevolent principles, the ſhips sailed with the Britiſh coloniſts, to whom, in March 1792, were added 1131 blacks from Nova Scotia. The native chiefs being reconciled to the plan, and made to underſtand its beneficent tendency towards their people, the colony proceeded to build <hi rend="italic">Free-Town,</hi> on a dry and rather elevated ſpot on the ſouth ſide of the river. It occupied between 70 and 80 acres, its length being about one- third of a mile, and its breadth nearly the ſame ; and it contained near 400 houſes, each having one-twelfth of an acre annexed, on which a few vegetables were raised. There were nine ſtreets running from north-west to ſouth- eaſt, and three cross ſtreets, all 80 feet wide, except one of 160 feet, in the middle of which were all the public buildings. Theſe conſiſted of a governor’s houſe and offices ; a large ſtore-houſe ; a large hoſpital ; six or eight other houſes, offices, and shops, occupied by the company’s ſervants ; and a church capable oſ containing 800 people. The coloniſts at firſt ſuffered much from the rainy ſeaſon, againſt which it was not in their power to provide ſufficient protection ; but at the end of it they recovered in a great meaſure their health and ſpirits, and proceeded with alacrity to execute the various purpoſes of their ſettlement. To excite emulation in culture, the government gave premiums to those coloniſts who raiſed the greateſt quantities of rice, yams, eddoes, cabbages, Indian corn, and cotton, reſpectively. To limit the exceſſes of the ſlave-trade, and gain the favour of the neighbouring chiefs, the directors inſtructed the governor and council to redeem any native from the neighbourhood, who ſhould be unjuſtly sold either to or by a Britiſh ſubject. The ſervants of the company conducted themſelves with the utmoſt propriety, being ſober, moral, and exemplary ; and from the labours of the clergymen were derived ſervices highly important in every point of view. Before the end of two years</p><p>from the inſtitution of the colony, order and induſtry had begun to ſhow their effects in an increaſing proſperity. The woods had been cut down to the diſtance of about three Engliſh miles all round the town. By theſe means the climate had become healthier, and ſickneſs had diminiſhed. The fame of the colony had spread not only along the whole weſtern coaſt of Africa,but alſo to parts far diſtant from the coaſt ; embaſſies had been received of the moſt friendly nature from kings and princes ſeveral hundred miles diſtant ; and the native chiefs had begun to send their children to the colony, with full confidence, to be taught reading, writing, and accounts, and to be brought up in the Chriſtian religion. In a word, it was not without grounds that the directors looked forward to that joyful period when, by the influence of the company’s meaſures, the continent of Africa ſhould be reſcued from her preſent ſtate of darkneſs and miſery, and exhibit a delightful ſcene of light and knowledge, of civilization and order, of peaceful induſtry and domeſtic comfort. On their beneficent exertions they hoped with confidence for the bleſſing of Providence ; they were countenanced and ſupported by the Britiſh government ; and upon the breaking out of the preſent war, the French Convention authoriſed one of their agents to write to the directors, requeſting a full account of the deſign of the inſtitution, and the names of the ſhips employed in their ſervice, and aſſuring them of the good wiſhes of the French government to ſo noble an undertaking. How completely that government fulfilled its promiſe is very generally known. Having vindicated the rights of man in Europe by the violation of every principle of truth and juſtice, they determined by the ſame means to give light and liberty to the Africans ; and that they have fully carried their determination into effect will be ſeen by the following extract of a letter from Mr Afzelius, the company’s botaniſt, dated Sierra Leona, 15th November 1794. “The French have been here and have ruined us. They arrived on the 28th of September laſt, early in the morning, with a fleet conſiſting of one large ſhip, two frigates, two armed brigs, and one cutter, together with two large armed merchant ſhips, taken by them at the Isles de Loss, an Engliſh ſlave factory to the north of our colony, and which they have alſo deſtroyed and burnt. So well had they concealed their nation, that we took them at firſt for Engliſh. They had Engliſh- built veſſels, which were rigged in the Engliſh way. They ſhowed the Engliſh flag, and had their ſailors, at leaſt thoſe we ſaw on deck, dreſſed like Engliſh. In ſhort, we did not perceive our miſtake till we obſerved them pointing their guns. We had not ſtrength ſufficient to resist, and therefore our governor gave orders, that as ſoon as they ſhould begin to fire, the Britilh flag ſhould be ſtruck, and a flag of truce hoiſted. Accordingly this was done, but ſtill they continued firing, and did much damage, both within and without the town . They killed two people and wounded three or four. But, as we did not underſtand the meaning of this proceeding, we asked them for an explanation ; and they anſwered us, that we ſhould diſplay the flag of liberty, as a proof of our ſubmiſſion. We aſſured them that it ſhould already have been done, if we had had any, which terminated the hoſtilities from the ſhips. In the mean time, moſt of the inhabitants had fled from the the town, having taken with them as much of their</p></body></text></TEI>