<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>firſt to chaſtiſe Albert of Brandenburgh, who had refuſed to be included in the treaty of Paſſau, and whoſe cruel exactions in that part of Germany called loudly for redreſs.</p><p>The French, however, were not deceived by theſe arts. Henry immediately gueſſed the true object of Charles’s armament, and reſolved to defend his conqueſts with vigour. The defence of Metz, againſt which it was foreſeen the whole weight of the war would be turned, was committed to Francis of Lorraine, duke of Guile, who poſſeſſed in an eminent degree all the qualities that render men great in military command. He repaired with joy to the dangerous ſtation ; and many of the French nobility, and even princes of the blood, eager to diſtinguiſh themſelves under ſuch a leader, entered Metz as volunteers. The city was of great extent, ill fortified, and the ſuburbs large. For all theſe defects the duke endeavoured to provide a remedy. He repaired the old fortifications with all poſſible expedition, labouring with his own hands ; the officers imitated his example ; and the ſoldiers, thus encouraged, cheerfully submitted to the moſt ſevere toils ; he erected new works, and he levelled the ſuburbs with the ground. At the same time he filled the magazines with proviſions and military  stores, compelled all uſeleſs perſons to leave the place, and laid waſte the neighbouring country; yet ſuch were  his popular talents, as well as his arts of acquiring an aſcendant over the minds of men, that the citizens not only refrained from murmuring, but ſeconded him with no leſs ardour than the ſoldiers in all his operations— in the ruin of their eſtates, and in the havoc of their public and private buildings.</p><p>Meanwhile the emperor continued his march towards Lorraine, at the head of 60,000 men. On his approach Albert of Brandenburgh, whoſe army did not exceed 20,000, withdrew into that principality, as if he intended to join the French king ; and Charles, notwithstanding the advanced ſeaſon, it being towards the end of October, laid ſiege to Metz, contrary to the advice of his moſt experienced officers.</p><p>The attention of both the beſiegers and the beſieged was turned for ſome time towards the motions of Albert, who ſtill hovered in the neighbourhood, undetermined which ſide to take, though reſolved to ſell his ſervice. Charles at laſt came up to his price, and he joined the imperial army. The emperor now flattered himſelf that nothing could resist his force; but he found himſelf deceived. After a ſiege of almoſt 60 days, during which he had attempted all that was thought poſſible for art or valour to effect, and had loſt upwards of 30,000 men by the inclemency of the weather, diſeaſes, or the ſword of the enemy, he was obliged to abandon the enterpriſe.</p><p>When the French ſallied out to attack the enemy’s rear, the imperial camp was filled with the ſick and wounded, with the dead and the dying. All the roads by which the army retired were ſtrewed with the ſame miſerable objects ; who, having made an effort beyond their ſtrength to eſcape, and not being able to proceed, were left to periſh without aſſiſtance. Happily that, and all the kind offices which their friends had not the power to perform, they received ſrom their enemies. The duke of Guiſe ordered them all to be taken care of, and ſupplied with every necessary ; he appointed</p><p>phyſicians to attend, and direct what treatment was proper for the ſick and wounded, and what refreſhments for the feeble ; and ſuch as recovered he ſent home, under an eſcort of ſoldiers, and with money to bear their charges. By theſe acts of humanity, leſs common in that age, the duke of Guiſe completed that heroic character which he had juſtly acquired by his brave and ſucceſsful defence of Metz.</p><p>The emperor’s misfortunes were not confined to Germany. During his reſidence at Villach, he had been obliged to borrow 200,000 crowns of Coſmo de Medici ; and ſo low was his credit, that he was obliged to put Coſmo in poſſeſſion of the principality of Piombino as a ſecurity for that inconsiderable ſum ; by which means he loſt the footing he had hitherto maintained in Tuſcany. Much about the ſame time he loſt Sienna. The citizens, who had long enjoyed a republican government, roſe againſt the Spaniſh garriſon, which they had admitted as a check upon the tyranny of the nobility, but which they found was meant to enslave them ; forgetting their domeſtic animoſities, they recalled the exiled nobles ; they demoliſhed the citadel, and put themſelves under the protection of France.</p><p>To theſe unfortunate events one ſtill more fatal had almoſt ſucceeded. The ſevere adminiſtration of the viceroy of Naples had filled that kingdom with murmuring and diſſatisfaction. The prince of Salerno, the head of the malecontente, fled to the court of France. The French monarch, after the example of his father, applied to the grand ſignior ; and Solyman, at that time highly incensed againſt the houſe of Auſtria on account of the proceedings in Hungary, ſent a powerful fleet into the Mediterranean, under the command of the corſeir Dragut, an officer trained up under Barbaroſſa, and ſcarce inferior to his maſter in courage, talents, or in good fortune. Dragut appeared on the coaſt of Calabria at the time appointed ; but not being joined by the French fleet according to concert, he returned to Conſtantinople, after plundering and burning ſeveral places, and filling Naples with conſternation.</p><p>Highly mortified by ſo many diſaſters, Charles retired into the Low Countries, breathing vengeance againſt France : and here the war was carried on with conſiderable vigour. Impatient to efface the ſtain which his military reputation had received before Metz, Charles laid ſiege to Terouane ; and the fortifications being in diſrepair, that important place was carried by aſſault. Heſdin alſo was inveſted, and carried in the ſame manner. The king of France was too late in assembling his forces to afford relief to either of theſe places ; and the emperor afterwards cautiouſly avoided an engagement.</p><p>The imperial arms were leſs ſucceſsful in Italy. The viceroy of Naples failed in an attempt to recover Siena; and the French not only eſtabliſhed themſelves more firmly in Tuſcany, but conquered part of the iſland of Corsica. Nor did the affairs of the houſe of Auſtria go on better in Hungary during the courſe of this year. Iſabella and her son appeared once more in Tranſylvania, at a time when the people were ready for revolt, in order to revenge the death oſ Martinuzzi, whoſe loss they had ſeverely felt. Some noblemen of eminence declared in favour of the young king ; and the baſhaw of Belgrade, by Solyman’s order, espousing his cause,</p></body></text></TEI>