<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ought to be paid to the weather, so that when there is an immediate prospect of rain, a sufficient quantity of leaves may be gathered to ſerve the worms two or three days. In this country, the leaves of the black or red mulberry tree may be preſerved good for food, although kept four or five days, by the following method; When new gathered, lay them looſely in glazed earthen veſſels, place theſe in a cold place, well aired, not expoſed to drought.</p><p>The utmoſt attention muſt be paid to preſerve the place where ſilk worms are kept as clean as poſſible: the houſe or room muſt be well ventilated, that no noxious vapours be accumulated. By ſome experiments of Μ. Faujas de St Fond, which are recorded in his hiſtory of Languedoc, it appears that the ſilk worm is much injured by foul air. All decayed leaves muſt be removed from them, as it is now well known that they emit bad air in great abundance.</p><p>@@One of the most difficult brandies of the management of ſilk worms has hitherto been the cleaning without bruising them. To avoid this inconvenience, the peaſants in France and Italy frequently allow the whole litter to remain without ever cleaning them, which is the cauſe of that unwholeſome ſtench that has been ſo often remarked by thoſe who viſit the places for rearing ſilk worms in theſe countries. This difficulty may be effectually removed by providing a net, or, what would be ſtill better, a wire-bottomed frame, wrought into large meſhes like a riddle. Have that made of a ſize exactly ſufficient to cover the wooden box in which the worms are kept. When you mean to ſhift them, ſpread freſh leaves into the wire baſket ; and let it down gently over the worms till it comes within their reach. They no ſooner perceive the freſh food than they abandon the rubbiſh below, and creep through the meſhes, ſo as to fix themſelves upon the leaves ; then by gently raiſing the freſh baſket, and drawing out the board below (which ought to be made to flip out like the flip bottom of a bird’s cage), you get off all the excrements and decayed leaves, without incommoding the worms in the smalleſt degree ; and along with the litter you will draw off an inch or two in depth of the fouleſt mephitic vapours. To get entirely rid of theſe, the board, when thus taken out, ſhould be carried without doors, and there cleaned ; and the flip board immediately replaced to receive all the excrements and offals. After it is replaced, the wire frame that had been elevated a little, may be allowed to deſcend to a convenient diſtance above the board without touching it. Thus will there be left a vacant space for the mephitic air to fall below the worms, ſo as to allow them to inhabit a wholeſome region of the atmoſphere.</p><p>When a freſh ſupply of food is to be given before cleaning, the wire frame ought to be let down as cloſe to the board as can be ſafely done, and another wire- bottomed frame put over it, with freſh leaves, as before deſcribed. When the worms have abandoned that in their turn, let the slip-board, together with the lower wire frame, be drawn out and removed, and ſo on as often as neceſſary. To admit of this alternate change, every table, conſiſting of one slip-board, ought to have two ſets of wire-bottomed frames of the ſame ſize ; the slip board to be always put into its place immediately after it is cleaned, and the wire frames reſerved to be afterwards placed over the other. By this mode of management, it is probable that the worms would be ſaved from the diseases engendered by the mephitic air, and the numerous deaths that are the consequence of it avoided.</p><p>Dr Anderſon, to whom we have already acknowledged our obligations, and to whom this country has been much indebted for valuable works on agriculture, the fiſheries, &amp;c. adviſes thoſe who have the management of ſilk worms to ſtrew a thin ſtratum of freſh flaked quicklime upon the slip-board each time it is cleaned, immediately before it is put into its place. This would absorb the mephitic gas, for as ſoon as it is generated it would deſcend upon the ſurface of the quicklime. Thus would the worms be kept continually in an atmoſphere of pure air @@(c). Were the walls of the apartments to be frequently waſhed with quicklime and water, it would tend much to promote cleanlineſs at a ſmall expence, and augment the healthineſs of the worms as well as that of the perſons who attend them.</p><p>When the ſilk worm refuſes its food, and leaves silky traces on the leaves over which it paffes, it is a proof that it is ready to begin its cocoon. It is now neceſſary to form a new receptacle, which is commonly done by pinning together papers in the ſhape of inverted cones with broad baſes. ‘‘ This method (ſays Mr Swayne@@), where there are many worms, is exceedingly tedious, waſtes much paper, and uſes a large number of pins ; beſides, as the ſilk worm always weaves an outer covering or defenſive web before it begins the cocoon or oval ball, I apprehended that it cauſed a needleſs waſte of ſilk in forming the broad web at the top. The method I make uſe of is, to roll a ſmall piece of paper (an uncut octavo leaf, ſuch as that of an old magazine, is</p><p>@@@[mu] Bee, N⁰ 95.</p><p>@@@[mu] Transactions of the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, vol. vii. p. 12.</p><p>@@@(c) To put this queſtion beyond a doubt, Mr Blancard made the following comparative experiments, which were ſeveral times repeated. “ I procured (says he) four glaſs jars nine inches high and five in diameter, doling the mouth with cork ſtoppers. After which I placed in each of them, in their ſecond life (ſo <hi rend="italic">mue may</hi> be tranſlated which means the ſtage between the different ſickneſſes), twelve ſilk worms, which were fed four times a-day ; and. which I confined in this kind of priſon all their life, without taking away either their dead companions or their ordure or litter. I ſprinkled with chalk the worms of only two of theſe jars, and kept the two others to compare with them.</p><p>“ In thoſe without lime, I never obtained neither more nor leſs than three ſmall and imperfect cocoons (<hi rend="italic">chiques ou bouffard),</hi> and in the two that were ſprinkled with lime, I had very often twelve, and never leſs than nine fine full-sized firm cocoons.”</p><p>This experiment affords the moſt ſatisfactory proof of the utility of this proceſs. From a number of trials he found, that even when the worms were covered with a very large proportion of lime, they never were in any way. incommoded by it.</p></body></text></TEI>