<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:09Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which the Engliſh call the \<hi rend="italic">.</hi> Theſe monkeys are very fierce, untameable, and bite dreadfully. There is a variety of a ferruginous or reddiſh bay colour, which the Indians call the <hi rend="italic">king of the monkeys :</hi> it is large, and as noiſy as the former. The natives eat this ſpecies, as well as ſeveral other forts of monkeys, but are particularly fond of this. Europeans will alſo eat it, eſpeciaHy in thoſe parts of America where food is ſcarce : when it is ſcalded in order to get off the hair, it looks very white ; and has a reſemblance ſhocking to humanity, that of a child of two or three years old when crying (c).</p><p>31.	The quato, ſapajus paniſcus, or four-fingered monkey, has a long flat face, of a ſwarthy fleſh colour: the eyes are funk in the head ; ears like the human ; limbs of a great length, and uncommonly ſlender : the hair is black, long, and rough. There are only four ſingers on the hands, being quite deſtitute of a thumb ; five toes on the feet. The tail is long ; and naked below, near the end. The body is ſlender ; about a foot and a half long ; the tail near two feet, and ſo prehenſile as to ſerve every purpoſe of a hand. They inhabit the neighbourhood of Carthagena, Guiana, Braſil, and Peru ; aſſociate in vaſt herds ; and are ſcarce ever ſeen on the ground. Dampier deſcribes their gambols in a lively manner: “ There was (ſays he) a great company dancing from tree to tree over my head, chattering, and making a terrible noiſe and a great many grim fact's and antic geſtures ; ſome broke down dry sticks and flung them at me, others ſcattered their urine and dung about my ears : at laſt one bigger than the reſt came to a ſmall limb juft over my head, and leap, ing directly at me, made me leap back ; but the monkey caught hold of the bough with the tip of its tail, and there continued ſwinging to and fro, making mouths at me. The females with their young ones are much troubled to leap after the males ; for they have commonly two, one ſhe carries under her arm, the other fits on her back, and claps its two fore-paws about her neck : are very fallen when taken ; and very hard to be got when ſhot, for they will cling with their tail or feet to a bough as long as any life remains. When I have ſhot at one, and broke a leg or arm, I have pitied the poor creature to fee it look and handle the broken limb, and turn it from fide to fide.”—They are the moſt active of monkeys, and quite enliven the fo- reſts of America. In order to pass from top to top of lofty trees, whoſe branches are too diſtant for a leap, they will form a chain, by hanging down, linked to each other by their tails, and ſwinging in that manner till the loweſt catches hold of a bough of the next tree, and draws up the reſt ; and ſometimes they paſs rivers by the ſame expedient. They are ſometimes brought to Europe ; but are very tender, and ſeldom live long in our climate.</p><p>32.	The ſai, ſapajus, capucinus, or weeper, with a round and flat face, of a reddiſh brown colour, very deformed : the hair on the head and upper part of the body black, tinged with brown ; beneath and on the</p><p>limbs tinged with red : tail black, and much longer than the head and body : the young exceſſively deformed ; their hair very long, and thinly diſperſed.—In the Bri- tiſh Muſeum are ſpecimens of old and young. M. de Buffon has a variety with a white throat. Inhabits Surinam and Braſil : appear as if it was always weeping ; of a melancholy diſpoſition ; but very full of imitating what it sees-done. Theſe probably are the monkeys Dampier ſaw in the Bay of All Saints, which he ſays are very ugly, and ſmell ſtrongly of muſk. They keep in large companies ; and make a great chattering, eſpeciaHy in ſtormy weather ; reſide much on a ſpecies of tree which bears a podded fruit, which they feed on.</p><p>33.	Sapajus fatuellas, or horned ſapajou, has two tufts of hair on the head, reſembling little horns : Is beardleſs. Inhabits South America. The face, ſides, belly, and fore-parts of the thighs are brown ; the top of the head, middle of the back, tail, legs, and poſterior parts of the thighs, are black ; the nails are long and rather blunt ; the tail is prehenſile and twiſted ſpirally. Perhaps of the ſame ſpecies with the ſimia apella or capuchin (Gm.). This, in all probability, is one of the factitious ſpecies, purpoſely deformed, by exhibitors of wild beaſts, to impoſe on the public.</p><p>34.	Saimiri, ſapajus ſciureus, or orange monkey, has no beard ; the hinder part of the head is prominent ; and the nails on the four toes of the hind paws are narrow and pointed. It inhabits South America, and is the moſt beautiful of all the ſapajous ; its movements are graceful ; its ſize ſmall ; its colour a brilliant yellow ; its viſage round, with large vivacious eyes, ſurrounded by ſteſh-coloured rings ; it has hardly any forehead ; the noſe is elevated at the baſe, and flattened at the point : the mouth is ſmall, the face flat and naked, and the ears are garniſhed with hair, and a little pointed ; the tail is only half prehenſile : It ſtands with eaſe on two feet, but commonly walks on all four.</p><p>V.	<hi rend="smallcaps">Sagoins, Sagoini.</hi> Theſe have long tails, which are proportionally longer than thoſe of the ſapajous, ſtraight, flaccid, entirely covered with hair, and not prehenſile ; that is, incapable of laying hold of any object : the cheeks have no pouches ; and the buttocks, which are covered with hair, have no calloſitres : the partition between the noſtrils is very thick, and the apertures are placed on the ſides of the nose. The females do not menſtruate. This race of animals is only found in America.</p><p>35.	The ſaki, ſagoinus pithecia, or fox-tailed monkey, with a ſwarthy face, covered with ſhort white down : forehead and ſides of the face with whitiſh, and pretty long hair : body with long duſky brown hairs ; white or yellowiſh at their tips : hair on the tail very long and buſhy ; ſometimes black, iometimes reddish : belly and lower part of the limbs a reddiſh white : length from noſe to tail near a foot and a half : tail longer, and like that of a fox : hands and feet black, with claws inſtead of nails. Inhabits Guiana.</p><p>36.	The ſanglin, ſagoinus iacchus, or ſtriated mon-</p><p>(c) <hi rend="italic">Ulloa's Voy.</hi> I. 113. <hi rend="italic">Des Marchais,</hi> III. 311, ſays, they are excellent eating, and that a <hi rend="italic">ſoupe aux siuges </hi>will be found as good as any other, as ſoon as you have conquered the averſion to the <hi rend="italic">bouilli</hi> of their heads, which look very like thoſe of little children.</p></body></text></TEI>