<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>tween the two hanks, which ſerves for a head-band to tie them.</p>
            <p>You muſt obſerve that your water be juſt in a proper degree of heat. When it is too
                hot, the thread is dead, and has no body ; when it is too cold, the ends which form
                the thread do not join well, and form a harſh ill-qualified ſilk.</p>
            <p>You muſt change the water in your baſon four times a-day for your dupions and
                choquette, and twice only for good cocoons when you wind fine ſilk ; but if you wind
                coarſe ſilk, it is neceſſary to change it three or four times. For if you were not
                to change the water, the ſilk would not be ſo bright and gloſſy, becauſe the worm
                contained in the cocoons foul it very conſiderably. You muſt endeavour as much as
                poſſible to wind with clear water, for if there are too many worms in it, your ſilk
                is covered with a kind of dust which attracts the moth, and deſtroys your ſilk.</p>
            <p>You may wind your ſilk of what ſize you pleaſe, from one cocoon to 1000 ; but it is
                difficult to wind more than 30 in a thread. The nicety, and that in which conſiſts
                the greateſt difficulty, is to wind even ; becauſe as the cocoon winds off, the end
                is finer, and you muſt then join other cocoons to keep up the ſame ſize. This
                difficulty of keeping the ſilk always even is ſo great, that (excepting a thread of
                two cocoons, which we call such) we do not ſay a ſilk of three, of four, or of ſix
                cocoons ; but a ſilk of three to four, of four to five, of fix to ſeven cocoons. If
                you proceed to a coarſer, ſilk, you cannot calculate ſo nicely as to one cocoon more
                or leſs. We ſay, for example, from 12 to 15, from 15 to 20, and ſo on.</p>
            <p>What number of worms are neceſſary to produce a certain quantity of ſilk has not been
                aſcertained. And as different perſons who wished to determine this point have had
                different reſults, the truth ſeems to be, that from various circumſtances the ſame
                number of worms may produce more ſilk at one time than at another. It is related in
                the ſecond volume of the Tranſactions of the Society for encouraging Arts, &amp;c.
                that Mrs Williams obtained nearly an ounce and a half of ſilk from 244 cocoons. Mr
                Swayne from 50 cocoons procured 100 grains. Miſs Rhodes obtained from 250 of the
                largeſt cocoons, three quarters of an ounce and a dram. From a paper in the ſecond
                volume of the American Tranſactions, which we have before referred to in the courſe
                of this article, we are informed that 150 ounces oſ good cocoons yield about 11
                ounces of ſilk from five to ſix cocoons : if you wind coarſer, ſomething more. But
                what appears aſtoniſhing, Mr Salvatore Bertezen, an Italian, to whom the Society for
                encouraging Arts, &amp;c. adjudged their gold medal, raiſed five pounds of excellent
                ſilk from 12,000 worms.</p>
            <p>The cocoons produce a thread of very unequal length ; you may meet with ſome that
                yield 1200 elk, whilſt others will ſcarcely afford 200 ells. In general, you may
                calculate the production of a cocoon from 500 to 600 ells in length.</p>
            <p>As there is every reaſon to hope that the ſilk manufacture will ſoon be carried on
                with ardour in this country, and to a great extent, we are happy to learn that the
                ſilk-loom has been much improved lately by Mr Sholl of Bethnal-Green. It appears
                from the evidence of ſeveral gentlemen converſant in that branch of ſilk weaving to
                which this loom is particularly adapted,@@ that</p>
            <p>the advantages oſ this conſtruction are, the gaining light, a power of ſhortening the
                porry occaſionally, ſo as to suit any kind of work, being more portable, and having
                the gibbet firmly fixed, together with the diminution of price ; which, compared
                with the old loom, is as five pounds, the price of a loom on the old conſtruction,
                to three pounds ten ſhillings, the price of one of thoſe contrived by Mr Sholl ; and
                that, as the proportion of light work is to ſtrong work as nine to one, this sort of
                loom promiſes to be of very conſiderable advantage, particularly in making modes, or
                other black work.</p>
            <p>As a plate of this loom, with proper references, will render its advantages moſt
                intelligible, we ſhall ſubjoin theſe : Plate CCCCLXVI. A, A, The fills; B, B, The
                breaſt-roll poſts : C, The cut tree; D, F), The uprights ; E, The burdown ; F, The
                batton ; G, The reeds; H, The harneſs ; I. The breaſt-roll ; K, The cheeſe; L, The
                gibbet: M, The treddles ; N, The tumblers ; 0, Short eounter-meſhes ; P, Long
                counter- meſhes ; Q, The porry ; R, R, Cane roll poſts ; S, The cane-roll ; T, The
                weight bar and weight ; U, U, Counter-weights ; W, The breaking rod ; X, X, Crois
                rods.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">SILK-Worm.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Silk.</hi></p>
            <p>SILPHA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Carrion-beetle,</hi> in natural hiſtory ; a genus of
                animals belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">inſectae,</hi> and to the order
                of <hi rend="italic">coleopterae.</hi> The antennæ are clavated ; the clava are
                perfoliated ; the elytra marginated ; the head is prominent; and the thorax
                marginated. There are 94 ſpecies, of which ſeven only are natives of Britain and
                Ireland. I. The <hi rend="italic">veſpillo.</hi> The margin of the thorax broad. The
                ſhells abbreviated, black, with two yellow belts. The thighs of the hind legs large,
                with a ſpine near their origin. Length near one inch. It infeſts dead bodies. 2. The
                    <hi rend="italic">biphuſtulata,</hi> is black ; the antennæ are long and ſmall,
                and there are two red ſpots on the middle of each ſhell. The length is one-third of
                an inch. 3. The <hi rend="italic">pustulala,</hi> is black and oblong : there are
                four brown ſpots on the ſhells : the length is one-fifth of an inch. It lives on
                trees. 4.@@ The <hi rend="italic">quadripunctata.</hi> The head, antennæ, and legs
                black- Margin oſ the thorax and ſhells are of a pale yellow, with four black ſpots.
                The length half an inch. It is found in Cain-wood, near Hampſtead. 5. The <hi
                    rend="italic">ſabuloſa,</hi> is black ; the antennæ are ſhort and globular ;
                there are five striae on each ſhell. The ſhells and wings are ſhort. There are five
                joints on the two firſt feet, four on the rest. It lives in sand. 6. The <hi
                    rend="italic">aquatica,</hi> is brown, with a green bronze tinge. There are four
                ribs on the thorax. On each ſhell there are 10 ſtriae. The length is one-fifth of an
                inch. 7. The <hi rend="italic">pulicaria,</hi> is black and oblong ; the ſhells are
                abbreviated ; the abdomen is rounded at the extremity ; the thorax and ſhells are
                ſcarce marginated ; the length is one line. It is found frequently running on
                flowers.</p>
            <p>SILPHIUM, in botany ; A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of ſyngeneſia, and to
                the order of polygamia neceſſaria ; and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the
                49th order, <hi rend="italic">compositae.</hi> The receptacle is paleaceous ; the
                pappus has a two-horned margin, and the calyx is ſquarroſe. There are eight ſpecies
                ; the laciniatum, terebinthinum, perfoliatum, connatum, aſterisicum, trifoliatum,
                ſoldaginoides, and trilobatum. The firſt six of theſe are natives of North
                America.</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Transactions of the Society for encouraging Arts, &amp;c. vol. viii.</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Berkenhout, vol. i.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
