<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>an ingenious mechanic ; who, though deriving no advantages from learning, by unwearied perſonal attendance found means to engage a few perſons of rank and fortune to meet at Peele’s coffeehouſe in Fleetſtreet, and to adopt a plan for promoting arts and manufactures.</p><p>The office-bearers of this ſociety are a preſident, 12 vice-presidents, a ſecretary, and regiſter. Their proceedings are regulated by a body of rules and orders eſtabliſhed by the whole ſociety, and printed for the uſe  of the members. All queſtions and debates ate determined by the holding up of hands, or by ballot if required; and no matter can be confirmed without the assent of a majority at two meetings. They invite all the world to propoſe ſubjects for encouragement ; and whatever is deemed deſerving attention, is referred to the consideration of a committee, which, after due inquiry and deliberation, make their report to the whole ſociety, where it is approved, rejected, or altered. A list is printed and publiſhed every year of the matters for which they propoſe to give premiums ; which premiums are either ſums of money, and thoſe ſometimes very considerable ones ; or the ſociety’s medal in gold or ſilver, which they conſider as the greateſt honour they can beſtow. All poſſible care is taken to prevent partiality in the diſtribution of their premiums, by deſiring the claimants names to be concealed, and by appointing committees (who when they find occaſion call to their aſſiſtance the moſt ſkilful artiſts) for the ſtrict examination of the real merit of all matters and things brought before them, in conſequence of their premiums.</p><p>The chief objects of the attention oſ the Society for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce, in the application of their rewards, are ingenuity in the ſeveral branches of the polite and liberal arts, uſeful diſeoveries and improvements in agriculture, manufactures, mechanics, and chemiſtry, or the laying open of any ſuch to the public ; and, in general, all ſuch uſeful inventions, diſcoveries, or improvements (though not mentioned in the book of premiums), as may appear to have a tendency to the advantage of trade and commerce.</p><p>The following are ſome of the moſt important regulations of this ſociety. It is required that the matters; for which premiums are offered be delivered in without names, or any intimation to whom they belong ; that each particular; thing be marked in what manner each claimant thinks fit, ſuch claimant lending with it a paper ſealed; up, having on the outside a correſponding mark, and on the inside the claimant’s name and addreſs ; and all candidates are to take notice, that no claim for a premium will be attended to, unleſs the conditions of the advertiſement are fully complied with. No papers ſhall be opened but ſuch as ſhall gain premiums, unleſs where it appears to the ſociety abſolutely neceſſary for the determination, of the claim : all the rest ſhall be returned unopened, with the matters to which they belong, it inquired after by the marks within two years; after which time, if not demanded, they ſhall, be publicly burnt unopened at ſome meeting of the ſociety. All the premiums of this ſociety are deſigned for that part of Great Britain called England, the dominion of Wales, and the town of Berwick upon Tweed, unleſs, expreſsly mentioned to the contrary.</p><p>No perſon ſhall receive any premium, bounty, or encouragement, from the ſociety for any matter for which he has obtained or propoſes to obtain a patent. No member of this ſociety ſhall be a candidate for or intitled to receive any premium, bounty, or reward whatſoever, except the honorary medal of the ſociety.</p><p>The reſpectability of the members who compoſe it may be ſeen by perusing the list which generally accompanies their Tranſactions. In the laſt volume (vol. xii.) it occupies no leſs than 43 pages. Some idea may be formed of the wealth of this ſociety, by obſerving that the list of their premiums fills 96 pages, and amounts to 250 in number. Theſe conſiſt of gold medals worth from 30 to 50, and in a few inſtances to 100, guineas ; and ſilver medals valued at 10 guineas.</p><p>This ſociety is one of the moſt important in Great Britain. Much money has been expended by it, and many are the valuable effects of which it has been productive. Among theſe we reckon not only the diſcoveries which it has excited, but the inſtitution of other ſocieties on the ſame principles to which it has given birth ; and we do not heſitate to conclude, that future ages will conſider the founding of this ſociety as one of the moſt remarkable epochs in the hiſtory of the arts. We contemplate with pleaſure the beneficial effects which muſt reſult to this nation and to mankind by the diffuſion of ſuch inſtitutions ; and rejoice in the hope that the active minds of the people of Great Britain, inſtead of being employed as formerly in controverſies about religion, which engender ſtrife, or in discuſſions concerning the theory of politics, which lead to the adoption of schemes inconſiſtent with the nature and condition of man, will ſoon be more generally united into aſſociations for promoting uſeful knowledge and ſolid improvement, and for alleviating the diſtreſſes of their fellow-creatures.</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Society inſtituted at Bath for the Encouragement of Agriculture, Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce.</hi> It was founded in the year 1777 by ſeveral gentlemen who met at the city of Bath. This scheme met with a very favourable reception both from the wealthy and learned. The wealthy ſubſcribed very liberally, and the learned communicated many important papers. On application; to the London and provincial ſocieties inſtituted for the like purpoſes, they very politely offered their aſſiſtance. Seven volumes of their tranſactions have already been, publiſhed, containing very valuable experiments and obſervations, particularly reſpecting agriculture, which well deſerve the attention of all farmers in the kingdom. We have conſulted them with much ſatisfaction on ſeveral occaſions, and have frequently referred to them in the courſe of this work ; and therefore, with pleaſure, embrace the preſent opportunity' of repeating our obligations. We owe the ſame acknowledgments to the Society for the Improvement of Arts, &amp;c. of London.</p><p>3.	<hi rend="italic">Society for Working Mines;</hi> an aſſociation lately formed on the continent of Europe. This inſtitution aroſe horn the accidental meeting of ſeveral mineralogists at Skleno near Schemnitz in Hungary, who were collected in order to examine a new method of amalgamation. Struck with the ſhackles impoſed on mineralogy by monopolizers of new and uſeful processes, they thought no method ſo effectual to break them, as forming a ſociety, whoſe common labours ſhould be directed to fix mining on its ſureſt principles; and whoſe memoirs,</p></body></text></TEI>