<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tions ineffectual, he adviſed the Carthaginian rulers to purchaſe peace at the price of Sicily. Such a treaty was not likely to be obſerved longer than want of ſtrength ſhould curb the animoſity of the vanquiſhed party : when their vigour was recruited, Hannibal ſon of Hamilcar easily perſuaded them to reſume the conteſt, and for 16 years waged war in the heart of the Roman territories. Meanwhile Hiero conducted himſelf with ſo much prudence, that he retained the friendſhip of both parties, and preſerved his portion of Sicily in perfect tranquillity. He died in extreme old age, beloved and retpected both at home and abroad.</p><p>His granson Hieronymus, forſaking this happy line of politics, and contracting an alliance with Carthage, fell an early victim to the troubles which his own folly had excited. Once more, and for the laſt time, the Syracuſans found themſelves in poſſeſſion of their independence: but the times were no longer ſuited to ſuch a ſyſtem ; diſſenſions gained head, and diſtracted the public councils. Carthage could not ſupport them, or prevent Marcellus from under taking the siege of Syracuſe, immortalized by the mechanical efforts of Archimedes, and the immenſity of the plunder. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Syracuse.</hi></p><p>The Sicilians after this relinquiſhed all martial ideas, and during a long series of generations turned their attention ſolely to the arts of peace and the labours of agriculture. Their poſition in the centre of the Roman empire preſerved them both from civil and foreign foes, except in two inſtances of a ſervile war. The rapacity of their governors was a more conſtant and inſupportable evil. In this ſtate of apathy and opulence Sicily remained down to the 7th century of our era, when the Saracens began to diſturb its tranquillity. The barbarous nations of the north had before invaded and ravaged its coaſts, but had not long kept poſſeſſion. The Saracens were more fortunate. In 827 they availed themſelves of quarrels among the Sicilians to ſubdue the country. Palermo was choſen for their capital, and the ſtandard of Mahomet triumphed about 200 years. In 1038 George Maniaces was ſent by the Greek emperor with a great army to attack Sicily. He made good his landing, and puſhed his conqueſts with vigour : his ſucceſs aroſe from the valour of ſome Norman troops, which were at that time unemployed and ready to fell their ſervices to the beſt bidder. Maniaces repaid them with ingratitude ; and by his abſurd conduct gave the Muſſulmen time to breathe, and the Normans a pretext and opportunity of invading the Imperial dominions in Italy? Robert and Roger of Hauteville afterwards conquered Sicily on their own account, not as mercenaries ; for having ſubſtantially fettled their power on the continent, they turned their arms againſt this iſland in obedience to the dictates of zeal and ambition. After ten years ſtruggle, the Saracens yielded up the rich prize, and Robert ceded it to his brother Roger, who aſſumed the title of Great Earl of Sicily, ruled the ſtate with wiſdom, and ranks deſervedly among the greateſt characters in hiſtory. He raised himſelf from the humble ſtation of a poor younger ſon of a private gentleman, to the exalted dignity of a powerful monarch, by the ſole force of his own genius and courage ; he governed a nation of ſtrangers with vigour and juſtice, and transmitted his poſſeſſions undiſputed to his poſterity. Such an aſſemblage of great qualities is well intitled to our admiration.</p><p>He was ſucceeded by his ſon Simon, whole reign was ſhort, and made way for a second ſon called Roger. In 1127 this prince joined to his Sicilian poſſeſſions the whole inheritance of Robert Guiſcard (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Naples, </hi>n⁰ 23. ), and aſſumed the regal ſtyle. The greateſt part of his reign was taken up in quelling revolts in Italy, but Sicily enjoyed profound peace. In 1154 his ſon William aſcended the throne, and paſſed his life in war and confusion. William II. ſucceeded his father, and died without iſſue. Tancred, though baſely born, was elected his ſuccessor, and after him his ſon William III. who was vanquiſhed by Henry of Swabia. During the troubles that agitated the reign of his ſon the emperor Frederic, peace appears to have been the lot of Sicily. A ſhort lived ſedition, and a revolt of the Saracens, are the only commotions of which we read. For greater ſecurity, the Saracens were removed to Puglia 400 years after the conqueſt of Sicily by their anceſtors. Under Conrad and Manfred Sicily remained quiet ; and from that time the hiſtory of Sicily is related under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Naples,</hi> n⁰ 26, &amp;c.</p><p>At the death of Charles II. of Spain, his ſpoils became an object of furious contention ; and at the peace of Utrecht, Sicily was ceded to Victor duke of Savoy, who, not many years after, was forced by the emperor Charles VI. to relinquiſh that fine iſland, and take Sardinia as an equivalent. But as the Spaniards had no concern in theſe bargains, they made a hidden attempt to recover Sicily, in which they failed through the vigilance of the Engliſh admiral Byng. He deſtroyed their fleet in 1718, and compelled them to drop their ſcheme for a time. In 1734 the Spanifh court resumed their deſign with ſucceſs. The infant Don Carlos drove the Germans out, and was crowned king of the two Sicilies at Palermo. When he paſsed into Spain to take poſſeſſion of that crown, he transferred the Sicilian diadem to his ſon Ferdinand III. of Sicily and IV. of Naples, and it has ever ſince remained in the poſſeſſion of the same family.</p><p>Sicily is ſeparated, as we have already obſerved, from Italy by a narrow strait called the <hi rend="italic">Faro of Messina.</hi> This ſtrait is ſtill remarkable for the rapidity of its currents and the irregular ebbing and flowing of the ſea, which ſometimes rushes in with ſuch violence as to endanger ſhips riding at anchor. Anciently it was much more remarkable for Scylla and Charybdis, the one a rock, and the other a whirlpool, between which it was very dangerous to ſteer, and concerning which ſo many fables have been related by the ancients. Scylla is a rock on the Italian side, oppoſite to Cape Pylores, which runs out into the ſea on the Sicilian ſide. Mr Brydone informs us, that the navigation of the ſtraits is not even yet performed without danger. He informs us, that the noiſe of the current which ſets through the ſtraits may be heard for ſeveral miles, like the roaring of ſome large impetuous river confined between narrow banks. In many places the water roſe into whirlpools and eddies, which are dangerous to ſhipping. The current ſet exactly for the rock of Scylla, and would certainly have carried any thing thrown into it againſt that point. Our author, however, is by no means of opinion that the ſtrait is ſo dangerous as the ancients have repreſented it ; though he thinks that the ſtrait is now probably much wider than formerly, which may have diminiſhed the danger. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scylla.</hi> There are many ſmall rocks,</p></body></text></TEI>