<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>hay, ranged along the ſides. They manufacture their own clothes, and dye them with the <hi rend="italic">lichen omphaloides </hi>and <hi rend="italic">lichen parietinus,</hi> moſſes collected from the rocks. During ſummer the men paſs their time in tending their herds or in making hay, &amp;c. and the women in milking or in making butter and cheeſe. For their own uſe they milk both ewes and goats, and make cheeſe of the milk. Their diet conſiſts of milk, cheeſe, and butter : and their ordinary drink is whey ; though they have, by way of reserve, a few bottles of very ſtrong beer, which they uſc as a cordial when ſick. They are people of good underſtanding, wary, and circumſpect ; tall, thin, and of ſtrong conſtitutions. In the wintertime they deſcend into the <hi rend="italic">hen-dref,</hi> or “ old dwelling,” where they paſs their time in inactivity.</p><p>The view from the higheſt peak of Snowdon is very extenſive. From it Mr Pennant ſaw the county of Cheſter, the high hills of Yorkſhire, part of the north of England, Scotland, and Ireland; a plain view of the isle of Man; and that of Angleſea appeared like a map extended under his feet, with every rivulet viſible. Our author took much pains to have this view to advantage; ſat up at a farm on the west till about 12, and walked up the whole way. The night was remarkably fine and ſtarry ; towards morning the ſtars faded away, leaving an interval of darkneſs, which, however, was ſoon diſpelled by the dawn of day. The body of the ſun appeared moſt diſtinct, with the roundneſs of the moon, before, it appeared too brilliant to be looked at. The ſea, which bounded the weſtern part of the proſpect, appeared gilt with the ſun-beams, firſt in ſlender ſtreaks, and at length glowed with redneſs. The proſpect was diſcloſed like the gradual drawing up of a curtain in a theatre ; till at laſt the heat became sufficiently ſtrong to raiſe mills from the various lakes, which in a flight degree obſcured the proſpect. The ſhadow of the mountain extended many miles, and ſhowed its bicapitated form ; the Wyddfa making one head, and Crib y Distill the other. At this time he counted between 20 and 30 lakes either in Caernarvon or in Merionethſhire. In making another viſit, the ſky was obſcured very ſoon aſter he got up. A vaſt mist involved the whole circuit of the mountain, and the proſpect down was horrible. It gave an idea of numbers of abyſſes, concealed by a thick ſmoke furiouſly circulating around them. Very often a guſt of wind made an opening in the clouds, which gave a fine and diſtinct viſta of lake and valley. Sometimes they opened in one place, at others in many at once ; exhibiting a moſt ſtrange and perplexing fight of water, fields, rocks, and chaſms. They then cloſed again, and every thing was involved in darkneſs ; in a few minutes they would ſeparate again, and repeat the above-mentioned scene with infinite variety. From this proſpect our traveller deſcended with great reluctance ; but before he had reached the place where his horſes were left, he was overtaken by a thunder ſtorm. The rolling of the thunder-claps, being reiterated by the mountains, was inexpreſſibly awful ; and after he had mounted, he was in great danger of being ſwept away by the torrents which poured down in conſequence of a very heavy rain.</p><p>It is very rare (Mr Pennant obſerves) that the traveller gets a proper day to aſcend this hill : it indeed often appears clear ; but by the evident attraction of the</p><p>clouds by this lofty mountain, it becomes suddenly and unexpectedly enveloped in miſt, when the clouds have juſt before appeared very high and very remote. At times he obſerved them lower to hair their height ; and notwithſtanding they have been diſperſed to the right and left, yet they have met from both ſides, and united to involve the ſummit in one great obſcurity.</p><p>The height of Snowdon was meaſured, in 1682, by Mr Caſwell, with inſtruments made by Flamſtead : according to his menſuration, the height is 3720 feet ; but more modern computations make it only 3568, reckoning from the quay at Caernarvon to the higheſt peak. The ſtone that compoſes this mountain is exceſſively hard. Large coarſe cryſtals, and frequently cubic pyrites, are found in the fiſſures. An immenſe quantity of water ruſhes down the ſides of Snowdon and the neighbouring mountains, inſomuch that Mr Pennant ſuppoſes, if collected into one ſtream, they would exceed the waters of the Thames.</p><p>SNUFF, a powder chiefly made of tobacco, the uſe of which is too well known to need any deſcription here.</p><p>Tobacco is uſually the baſis of ſnuff ; other matters being only added to give it a more agreeable ſcent, &amp;c. The kinds of ſnuff, and their ſeveral names, are infinite, and new ones are daily invented ; ſo that it would be difficult, not to ſay impoſſible, to give a detail of them. We ſhall only ſay, that there are three principal ſorts: the firſt granulated ; the ſecond an impalpable powder ; and the third the bran, or coarſe part remaining alter ſiſting the ſecond sort.</p><p>“ Every profeſſed, inveterate, and incurable ſnuſſ- taker (ſays Lord Stanhope), at a moderate computation, takes one pinch in ten minutes. Every pinch, with the agreeable ceremony of blowing and wiping the noſe and other incidental circumſtances, conſumes a minute and a half. One minute and a half out of every ten, allowing 16 hours to a snuff-taking day, amounts to two hours and 24 minutes out of every natural day, or one day out of every ten. One day out of every 10 amounts to 36 days and a half in a year. Hence if we ſuppoſe the practice to be persiſted in 40 years, two entire years of the ſnuff-taker’s life will be dedicated to tickling his noſe, and two more to blowing it. The expence of ſnuff, ſnuff-boxes, and handkerchiefs, will be the subject of a ſecond eſſay ; in which it will appear, that this luxury encroaches as much on the income of the ſnuff-taker as it does on his time ; and that by a proper application of the time and money thus lost to the public, a fund might be conſtituted for the diſcharge of the national debt.” See <hi rend="smallcaps">Nicotiana.</hi></p><p>SNYDERS (Francis), a Flemiſh painter, born at Antwerp in 1579, and bred under his countryman Henry Van Balen. His genius firſt diſplayed itſelf in painting fruit : he afterwards attempted animals, huntings, &amp;c. in which he exceeded all his predeceffors. He also painted kitchens, &amp;c. and gave dignity to ſubjects that ſeemed incapable of it. He was made painter to Ferdinand and Iſabella, archduke and ducheſs, and became attached to the houſe of the cardinal infant of Spain. The king of Spain and the elector Palatine adorned their palaces with huntings by this artist. Rubens, Jordaens, and Snyders, uſed to co-operate in the enriching of each other’s pictures according to their</p></body></text></TEI>