<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſmall but ſplendid train of 100 perſons. He was met on the frontiers of France by the dauphin and the duke of Orleans, who offered to go into Spain, and remain there as hoſtages, till he ſhould reach his own dominions ; but Charles replied, that the king’s honour was sufficient for his ſafety, and proſecuted his journey without any other ſecurity. The king entertained him with the utmoſt magnificence at Paris, and the two young princes did not take leave of him till he entered the Low Countries ; yet he ſtill found means to evade his promiſe, and Francis continued to believe him ſincere.</p><p>The citizens of Ghent, alarmed at the approach of the emperor, who was joined by three armies, ſent ambaſſadors to implore his mercy, and offered to throw open their gates. Charles only condeſcended to reply,</p><p>“ That he would appear among them as a ſovereign and a judge, with the ſceptre and the ſword.” He accordingly entered the place of his nativity on the anniverſary of his birth ; and inſtead of that lenity which might have been expected, exhibited an awful example of his ſeverity. Twenty-six of the principal citizens were put to death ; a greater number were baniſhed ; the city was declared to have forfeited its privileges ; a new ſyſtem of laws and political adminiſtration was prescribed ; and a large fine was impoſed on the inhabitants, in order to defray the expence of erecting a citadel, together with an annual tax for the ſupport of a garriſon. They were not only deſpoiled of their ancient immunities, but made to pay, like conquered people, for the means of perpetuating their own ſlavery.</p><p>Having thus re-eſtabliſhed his authority in the Low Countries, and being now under no neceſſity of continuing that ſcene of falſehood and diſſimulation with which he had amuſed the French monarch, Charles began gradually to throw aſide the veil under which he had concealed his intentions with reſpect to the Milaneſe, and at laſt peremptorily refilled to give up a territory of ſuch value, or voluntarily to make ſuch a liberal addition to the ſtrength of an enemy by diminiſhing his own power. He even denied that he had ever made any promiſe which could bind him to an action ſo fooliſh, and ſo contrary to his own intereſt.</p><p>This tranſaction expoſed the king of France to as much ſcorn as it did the emperor to cenſure. The credulous ſimplicity of Francis ſeemed to merit no other return, after experiencing ſo often the duplicity and artifices of his rival. He remonſtrated, however, and exclaimed as if this had been the firſt circumſtance in which the emperor had deceived him. The inſult offered to his underſtanding affected him even more ſenſibly than the injury done to his intereſt ; and he diſcovered ſuch reſentment as made it obvious that he would ſeize on the firſt opportunity of revenge, and that a new war would ſoon deſolate the European continent.</p><p>Meanwhile Charles was obliged to turn his attention towards the affairs of Germany. The Proteſtants having in vain demanded a general council, preſſed him earneſtly to appoint a conference between a ſelect number of divines of each party, in order to examine the points in diſpute. For this purpoſe a diet was aſſembled at Ratiſhon: and ſuch a conference, notwithſtanding the oppoſition of the pope, was held with great ſolemnity in the preſence of the emperor. But the divines choſen to manage thc controverſy, though men of</p><p>learning and moderation, were only able to ſettle a few ſpeculative opinions, all points relative to worſhip and juriſdiction ſerving to inflame the minds of the diſputants. Charles, therefore, finding his endeavours to bring about an accommodation ineffectual, and being impatient to cloſe the diet, prevailed on a majority of the members to approve of the following edict of receſs; viz. that the articles concerning which the divines had agreed, ſhould be held as points decided ; that thoſe about which they had differed, ſhould be referred to the determination of a general council, or if that could not be obtained, to a national ſynod ; and ſhould it prove impracticable alſo to assemble a ſynod of Germany, that a general diet of the empire ſhould be called within 18 months, in order to give final judgment on the whole controverſy ; that, in the mean time, no innovations ſhould be attempted, nor any endeavours employed to gain proſelytes.</p><p>This diet gave great offence to the pope. The bare mention of allowing a diet, compoſed chiefly of laymen, to paſs judgment in regard to articles of faith, appeared to him no leſs criminal and profane than the worſt of thoſe hereſies which the emperor ſeemed ſo zealous to ſuppreſs. The Proteſtants alſo were diſſatisfied with it, as it considerably abridged the liberty which they at that time enjoyed. They murmured loudly againſt it ; and Charles, unwilling to leave any ſeeds of diſcontent in the empire, granted them a private declaration, exempting them from “whatever they thought injurious or oppreſſive in the receſs, and aſcertaining to them the full poſſeſſion of all their former privileges.</p><p>The ſituation of the emperor’s affairs at this juncture made theſe extraordinary conceſſions neceſſary. He foreſaw a rupture with France to be unavoidable, and he was alarmed at the rapid progreſs of the Turks in Hungary. A great revolution had happened in that kingdom. John Zapol Scæpus, by the aſſiſtance of Solyman, had wreſted from the king of the Romans a conſiderable part of the country. John died, and left an infant ſon. Ferdinand attempted to take advantage of the minority, in order to reposseſs himſelf of the whole kingdom ; but his ambition was diſappointed by the activity and addreſs of George Martinuzzi, biſhop of Waradin, who ſhared the regency with the queen. Senſible that he was unable to oppoſe the king of the Romans in the field, Martinuzzi ſatisfied himſelf with holding out the fortified towns, all of which he provided with every thing neceſſary for defence ; and at the ſame time he ſent ambaſſadors to Solyman, beſeeching him to extend towards the ſon that imperial protection which had ſo generouſly maintained the father on his throne. Ferdinand uſed his utmoſt endeavours to thwart this negotiation, and even meanly offered to hold the Hungarian crown on the ſame ignominious condition by which John had held it, that of paying tribute to the Porte. But the ſultan ſaw ſuch advantages from eſpouſing the intereſt of the young king, that he inſtantly marched into Hungary ; and the Germans, having formed the ſiege of Buda, were defeated with great ſlaughter before that city. Solyman, however, inſtead of becoming the protector of the infant ſovereign whom he had relieved, made uſe of this ſucceſs to extend his own dominions : he ſent the queen and her ſon into Tranſilvapia, which province he allotted them, and added Hungary to the Ottoman empire,</p></body></text></TEI>