<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſee. The environs are charming, but the ſtreets are narrow, and the houſes ill-built. The fine cathedral has one of the moſt conſiderable chapters in the kingdom ; and the biſhop, when the archbiſhop of Rheims was absent, had a right to crown the king. The caſtle, though ancient, is not that in which the kings of the firſt race reſided. Soiſſons is ſeated in a very pleaſant and fertile valley, on the river Aiſne, 30 miles weſt by north of Rheims, and 60 north-eaſt of Paris. E. Long. 3. 24. N. Lat. 49. 23.</p><p>SOKE, or Soκ. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Socage.</hi></p><p>SOKEMANS. See Soc and <hi rend="smallcaps">Socage.</hi></p><p>SOL. in muſic, the fifth note of the gamut, ut,<hi rend="italic"> re, mi, fa, ſol, la.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gamut.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sou,</hi> a French coin made up of copper mixed with a little ſilver, and is worth upwards of an Engliſh halfpenny, or the 23d part of an Engliſh ſhilling. The ſol when firſt ſtruck was equal in value to 1<hi rend="italic">2</hi> deniers Tournois, whence it was alſo called <hi rend="italic">douzain,</hi> a name it ſtill retains, tho’ its ancient value be changed ; the ſol having been ſince augmented by three deniers, and ſtruck with a puncheon of a fleur-de-lis, to make it current for 15 deniers. Soon after the old ſols were coined over again, and both old and new were indifferently made current for 15 deniers. In 1709, the value of the ſame ſols was raiſed to 18 deniers. Towards the latter end of the reign of Louis XIV. the ſol of 18 deniers was again lowered to 15; and by the late king it was reduced to the original value of <hi rend="italic">12.</hi> What it is at preſent poſterity may perhaps diſcover.</p><p>The Dutch have alſo two kinds of ſols: the one of ſilver, called s<hi rend="italic">ols de gros,</hi> and likewiſe <hi rend="italic">ſchelling;</hi> the other of copper, called alſo the st<hi rend="italic">uyver.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Sun,</hi> in aſtronomy, aſtrology, &amp;c. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy, </hi><hi rend="italic">passim.</hi></p><p>Son, in chemiſtry, is gold ; thus called from an opinion that this metal is in a particular manner under the influence of the ſun.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sol,</hi> in heraldry, denotes Or, the golden colour in the arms of ſovereign princes.</p><p>SOLÆUS, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Soleus,</hi> in anatomy, one of the extenſor muſcles of the foot, riſing from the upper and hinder parts of the tibia and fibula.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SOLAN-goose,</hi> in ornithology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Pelicanus.</hi></p><p>SOLANDRA, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">monodelphia,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">polyandria ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 38th order, <hi rend="italic">Tricocceœ.</hi> The calyx is ſimple; the capſule oblong, wreathed, and five-celled ; the ſeeds are many, diſpoſed in cells in a double order. The valves after maturity are divaricated, even to the baſe, and winged inwards by the partition. The only ſpecies is the <hi rend="italic">Lobata.</hi> This genus was firſt named <hi rend="italic">Solandra,</hi> in honour of Dr Solander, by Murray in the 14th edition of the <hi rend="italic">Systema Vegetabilium.</hi></p><p>SOLANUM, in botany : A genus of the <hi rend="italic">monogyηiα </hi>order, belonging to the <hi rend="italic">pentandria</hi> claſs of plants ; and in the natural method ranking under the 28th order, <hi rend="italic">Dundee.</hi> The calyx is inferior ; the corolla is rotate, and generally monophyllous ; the fruit a berry, bilocular, and containing many ſmall and flat ſeeds. Of this genus there are 66 ſpecies, moſt of them natives of the Eaſt and Weſt Indies. The moſt remarkable of which are the following.</p><p>I.	The <hi rend="italic">Dulcamara,</hi> a native of Britain and of Africa</p><p>is a slender climbing plant, riſing to six or more feet in height. The leaves are generally oval, pointed, and of a deep green colour ; the flowers hang in looſe cluſters, of a purple colour, and divided into five pointed ſegments. The calyx is purple, perſiſtent, and divided into five. The five filaments are ſhort, black, and inſerted into the tube of the corolla. The antheræ yellow, erect, and united in a point as uſual in this genus. The ſtyle is long, and terminates in an obtuſe ſtigma. The berry, when ripe, is red, and contains many flat yellowiſh ſeeds.</p><p>It grows in hedges well ſupplied with water, and flowers about the end of June. On chewing the roots, we firſt feel a bitter, then a ſweet, taſte ; hence the name. The berries are ſaid to be poiſonous, and may eaſily be miſtaken by children for currants. The st<hi rend="italic">ipites </hi>or younger branches are directed for uſe, and may be employed either freſh or dried : they ſhould be gathered in the autumn. This plant is generally given in decoction or infuſion. Razou directs the following: Take dried dulcamara twigs half a dram, and pour upon it 16 ounces of ſpring water, which muſt be boiled down to 8 ounces ; then ſtrain it. Three or four ten ſpoonfuls to be taken every four hours, diluted with milk to prevent its exciting a nauſea. Several authors take notice, that the dulcamara partakes of the milder powers of the nightſhade, joined to a reſolvent and ſaponaceous quality ; hence it promotes the ſecretions of urine, sweat, the menſes, and lochia. It is recommended in a variety of diſorders ; but particularly in rheumatisms, obſtructed menſes, and lochia, alſo in ſome obſtinate cutaneous diſeaſes.</p><p>2.	The <hi rend="italic">Nigrum,</hi> common in many places in Britain about dunghills and waſte places. It riſes to about two feet in height. The ſtalk herbaceous, the leaves alternate, irregularly oval, indented, and clothed with ſoft hairs. The flowers are white ; the berries black and ſhining. It appears to poſſeſs the deleterious qualities of the other nightſhades in a very hiqh degree, and even the ſmell of the plant is ſaid to cauſe ſleep. The berries are equally poiſonous with the leaves ; cauſing <hi rend="italic">cardialgia,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">delirium,</hi> and violent diſtortions of the limbs in children. Mr Getnker in 1757 recommended its internal uſe in old sores, in ſcrofulous and cancerous ulcers, cutaneous eruptions, and in dropſies. He says, that one grain infuſed in an ounce of water ſometimes produced a conſiderable effect ; that in the doſe of two or three grains it ſeldom failed to evacuate the firſt paſſages, to increaſe very ſenſibly the diſcharges by the ſkin and kidneys, and ſometimes to occaſion headach, drowſineſs, gid— dineſs, and dimneſs of fight. Mr Broomfield declares, that in caſes in which he tried this ſolanum, they were much aggravated by it ; and that in one caſe in the doſe of one grain it proved mortal to one of his patients ; therefore he contends its uſe is prejudicial. This opinion ſeems tacitly to be confirmed, as it is now never given internally. In ancient times it was employed externally as a diſcutient and anodyne in ſome cutaneous affections, tumefactions of the glands, ulcers, and diſorders of the eyes. The <hi rend="italic">ſolanum nigrum e rubrum,</hi> a native of the Weſt Indies, is called <hi rend="italic">guma</hi> by the negroes. It is ſo far from having any deleterious quality, that it is daily ſerved up at table as greens or ſpinnage. It has an agreeable bitter taſte.</p><p>3.	<hi rend="italic">Lycoperſcum,</hi> the love-apple, or tomato, cultivated in gardens in the warmer parts of Europe and in all tro-</p></body></text></TEI>