<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to maſs, for which purpoſe alone he left his apartment, he appeared perfectly indifferent about the event of the election. He joined no party, yet flattered all.</p><p>He knew early that there would be great diviſions in the conclave, and he was aware that when the leaders of the different parties were disappointed in their own views, they all frequently agreed in the election of ſome old and infirm cardinal, the length of whole life would merely enable them to prepare themſelves ſufficiently for the next vacancy. Theſe views directed his conduct, nor was he miſtaken in his hopes of ſucceſs.</p><p>Three cardinals, the leaders of oppoſite factions, being unable to procure the election which each of them wiſhed, unanimouſly agreed to make choice of Montalto. When they came to acquaint him with their intention, he fell into ſuch a violent fit of coughing that every perſon thought he would expire on the ſpot. He told them that his reign would laſt but a few days ; that, besides a continual difficulty of breathing, he wanted ſtrength to ſupport ſuch a weight, and that his ſmall experience rendered him very unfit for ſo important a charge. He conjured them all three not to abandon him, but to take the whole weight of affairs upon their own ſhoulders ; and declared that he would never accept the mitre upon any other terms : “ If you are resolved,” added he, “ to make me Pope, it will only be placing yourſelves on the throne. For my part, I ſhall be ſatisfied with the bare title. Let the world call me Pope, and I make you heartily welcome to the power and authority. The cardinals ſwallowed the bait, and exerted themſelves ſo effectually that Montalto was elected. He now pulled off the maſk which he had worn for 14 years. No ſooner was his election ſecured, than he ſtarted from his ſeat, flung down his ſtaff in the middle of the hall, and appeared almoſt a foot taller than he had done for ſeveral years.</p><p>When he was aſked, according to cuſtom, if he would accept of the Papacy, he replied, “ It is trifling to aſk whether I will accept what I have already accepted.— However, to ſatisfy any ſcruple that may ariſe, I tell you that I accept it with great pleaſure, and would accept another if I could get it ; tor I find myſelf able, by the Divine aſſiſtance, to manage two papacies.” His former complaiſance and humility diſappeared, together with his infirmities, and he now treated all around him with reſerve and haughtineſs. The firſt care of Sixtus V. the name which Montalto aſſumed, was to correct the abuſes, and put a ſtop to the enormities, which were daily committed in every part of the ecelesiaſtical ſtate. The lenity of Gregory’s government had introduced a general licentiouſneſs of manners, which burſt forth with great violence, after that Pontiff’s death. It had been uſual with former Popes to releaſe delinquents on the day of their coronation, who were therefore accuſtomed to ſurrender themſelves voluntary priſoners immediately after the election of the Pope. At preſent, however, they were fatally diſappointed.— When the governor of Rome and the keeper of St Angelo waited on his Holineſs, to know his intention in this particular, he replied, “ What have you to do with pardons, and releaſing of priſoners ? Is it not ſufficient that our predeceſſor has ſuffered the judges to remain unemployed theſe 13 years? Shall we alſo ſtain our pontificate with the ſame neglect of juſtice ? We have too long ſeen, with inexpreſſible concern, the prodi</p><p>gious degree of wickedneſs that reigns in the ſtate to think of granting pardons. Let the priſoners be brought to a ſpeedy trial, and puniſhed as they deſerve, to ſhow the world chat Divine Providence has called ns to the chair of St Peter, to reward the good, and chaſtiſe the wicked; that we bear not the ſword in vain, but are the miniſters of God, and a revenger to execute wrath on them that do evil.”</p><p>He appointed commiſſioners to inſpect the conduct of the judges, diſplaced thoſe who were inclined to lenity, and put others of ſevere diſpositions in their room. He offered rewards to any perſon who could convict them of corruption or partiality. He ordered the ſyndics of all the towns and signiories to make out a complete list of the diſorderly perſons within their diſtricts, and threatened the ſtrapado for the ſmalleſt omiſſion. In conſequence of this edict, the ſyndic of Albino was ſcourged in the market-place, becauſe he had left his nephew, an incorrigible libertine, out of his lift.</p><p>He made very ſevere laws againſt robbers and aſſaſsins. Adulterers, when diſcovered, ſuffered death; and they who willingly ſubmitted to the proſtitution of their wives, a cuſtom then common in Rome, received the ſame puniſhment. He was particularly careful of the purity of the female ſex, and never forgave thoſe who attempted to debauch them.</p><p>His execution of juſtice was as prompt as his edicts were rigorous. A Swiſs happening to give a Spaniſh gentleman a blow with his halberd, was ſtruck by him so rudely with a pilgrim’s ſtaff that he expired on the spot. Sixtus informed the governor of Rome that he was to dine early, and that juſtice muſt be executed on the criminal before he sat down to table. The Spaniſh ambaſſador and four cardinals intreated him not to disgrace the gentleman by suffering him to die on a gibbet, but to order him to be beheaded. “ He ſhall be hanged (replied Sixtus), but I will alleviate his diſgrace by doing him the honour to aſſiſt perſonally at lira death.” He ordered a gibbet to be erected before his own windows, where he continued fitting during the whole execution. He then called to his ſervants to bring in dinner, declaring that the act oſ juſtice which he had juſt ſeen had increaſed his appetite. When he roſe from table, he exclaimed, “ God be praiſed for the good appetite with which I have dined!”</p><p>When Sixtus aſcended the throne, the whole eccleſtaſtical ſtate was infeſted with bands of robbers, who, from their numbers and outrages, were exceedingly formidable ; by his prudent and vigorous conduct, however, he in a ſhort time extirpated the whole of theſe banditti.</p><p>Nor was the vigour of his conduct leſs conſpicuous, in his tranſactions with foreign nations. Before he had been pope two months he quarrelled with Philip II. of Spain, Henry III. of France, and Henry king of Navarre. His intrigues indeed in ſome meaſure influenced all the councils of Europe.</p><p>After his acceſſion to the pontificate he ſent for his family to Rome, with expreſs orders that they ſhould appear in a decent and modeſt manner. Accordingly, his sister Camilla came thither, accompanied by her daughter and two grandchildren. Some cardinals, in order to pay court to the pope, went out to meet her, and introduced her in a very magnificent dreſs. Sixtus pretended not to know her, and asked two or three</p></body></text></TEI>