<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:25Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ther b, the bulk of the added ingredient, ſuffers any change. We ſhall have occaſion
                by and by to reſume the consideration of this queſtion, which is of the firſt moment
                in the theory of ſpecific gravities, and has great influence in many tranſactions of
                commerce.</p>
            <p>This ſeries of ſpecific gravities is not ſo well fitted for commercial tranſactions.
                In theſe the uſual queſtion is, how many gallons oſ alcohol is there in a caſk, or
                ſome number of gallons of ſpirit ? and it is more directly anſwered by means of a
                table, formed by mixing the ingredients in aliquant parts of one conſtant bulk. The
                following table, conſtructed from the experiments of Mr Briſſon of the academy of
                Paris, and publiſhed in the Memoirs for 1769, is therefore inſerted.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>W.</cell>
                    <cell>A.</cell>
                    <cell>Density obſerved.</cell>
                    <cell>Density computed.</cell>
                    <cell>Condensation</cell>
                    <cell>Bulk of 10,000 grains.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>0,8371</cell>
                    <cell>O,837i</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,0000</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1</cell>
                    <cell>15</cell>
                    <cell>0,8527</cell>
                    <cell>0,8473</cell>
                    <cell>63</cell>
                    <cell><p>0,9937</p><p>O,9885</p></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>0,8674</cell>
                    <cell>0,8575</cell>
                    <cell>115</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>0,8815</cell>
                    <cell>0,8677</cell>
                    <cell>157</cell>
                    <cell>0,9844</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>I 2</cell>
                    <cell>0,8947</cell>
                    <cell>0,8778</cell>
                    <cell>189</cell>
                    <cell>0,98 I I</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>I I</cell>
                    <cell>0,9075</cell>
                    <cell>0,8880</cell>
                    <cell>214</cell>
                    <cell>0,9786</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>0,9199</cell>
                    <cell>0,8982</cell>
                    <cell>235</cell>
                    <cell>0,9765</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>0,9317</cell>
                    <cell>0,9084</cell>
                    <cell>251</cell>
                    <cell>o,9749</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>0,9427</cell>
                    <cell>0,9186</cell>
                    <cell>256</cell>
                    <cell>0,9744</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>0,9519</cell>
                    <cell>0,9287</cell>
                    <cell>243</cell>
                    <cell>0,9757</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>0,9598</cell>
                    <cell>0,9389</cell>
                    <cell>217</cell>
                    <cell>0,9783</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>I I</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>0,9674</cell>
                    <cell>0,9491</cell>
                    <cell>189</cell>
                    <cell>0,98 I I</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>0,9733</cell>
                    <cell>0,9593</cell>
                    <cell>144</cell>
                    <cell>0,9856</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                    <cell>0,9791</cell>
                    <cell>0,9695</cell>
                    <cell>99</cell>
                    <cell>0,9901</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>0,9852</cell>
                    <cell>0,9796</cell>
                    <cell>57</cell>
                    <cell>0,9943</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>15</cell>
                    <cell>I</cell>
                    <cell>0,9919</cell>
                    <cell>0,9898</cell>
                    <cell>21</cell>
                    <cell>0,9979</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>1,0000</cell>
                    <cell>1,0000</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,0000</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>In this table the whole quantity of ſpirituous liquor is always the ſame. The firſt
                column is the number of meaſures (gallons, pints, inches, &amp;c.) of water in the
                mixture ; and column 2d gives the meaſures of alcohol. Column 3d is the ſpecific
                gravity which was obſerved by Mr Briſſon. Column 4th is the ſpecific gravity which
                would have been obſerved if the ſpirits, or water, or both, had retained their
                ſpecific density unchanged. And the 5th column marks the augmentation of ſpecific
                gravity or density in parts of 10,000. A 6th column is added, ſhowiag the bulk of
                the 16 cubic meaſures of the two ingredients. Each meaſure may be conceived as the
                16th part of 10,000, or 625 ; and we may ſuppoſe them cubic inches, pints, gallons,
                or any solid meaſure.</p>
            <p>This table ſcarcely differs from Sir Charles Blagden’s ; and the very ſmall
                difference that may be obſerved, ariſes from Mr Briſſon’s having uſed an alcohol not
                ſo completely rectified. Its ſpecific gravity is 0,8371, whereas the other was only
                0,8250.</p>
            <p>Here it appears more diſtinctly that the condenſation is greateſt when the two
                ingredients are of equal bulk.</p>
            <p>Perhaps this ſeries of ſpecific gravities is as declarative as the other, whether or
                not there is a change of density induced on either of the ingredients. The whole
                bulk being always the ſame, it is plain that the</p>
            <p>ſucceſſive equal additions to one of the ingredients is a ſucceſſive equal
                abſtraction of the other. The change produced, therefore, in the weight of the
                whole, is the difference between the weight of the ingredient which is taken out and
                the weight of the equal meaſure of the other which ſupplies its place. Therefore, if
                neither ingredient changes its density by mixture, the weights of the mixtures will
                be in arithmetical progreſſion. If they are not, there is a variation of density in
                one or both the ingredients.</p>
            <p>We ſee this very clearly in the mixtures of water and alcohol. The firſt ſpecific
                gravity differs from the ſecond by 156, and the laſt differs from the preceding by
                no more than 81. Had neither of the densities changed, the common difference would
                have been 102. We obſerve alſo, that the augmentation of ſpecific gravity, by the
                ſucceſſive addition of a meaſure of water, grows leſs and leſs till 12 meaſures of
                water is mixed with 4 of alcohol, when the augmentation is only 58, and then it
                increaſes again to 81.</p>
            <p>It alſo appears, that the addition of one meaſure of water to a quantity of alcohol
                produces a greater change of density than the mixture of one meaſure of alcohol to a
                quantity of water. Hence ſome conclude, that the water diſappears by being lodged in
                the interſtices of the ſpirit. But it is more agreeable to the juſtest notions which
                we can form of the internal conſtitution of tangible bodies to ſuppoſe that the
                particles of water diminiſh the diſtances between the particles of alcohol by their
                ſtrong attractions, and that this diminution (exceedingly minute in itſelf ) becomes
                ſenſible on account oſ the great number or particles whoſe diſtances are thus
                diminiſhed. This is merely a probability founded on this, that it would require a
                much greater diminution of diſtances if it was the particles of water which had
                their diſtances thus diminiſhed. But the greater probability is, that the
                condenſation takes place in both.</p>
            <p>We have been ſo particular in our conſideration of this mixture, becauſe the law of
                variation of density has, in this inſtance, been aſcertained with ſuch precision by
                the elaborate examination of Sir Charles Blagden, ſo that it may ſerve as an example
                of what happens in almoſt every mixture of bodies. It merits a still farther
                diſcuſſion, becauſe it is intimately connected with the action of the corpuſcular
                forces; and an exact knowledge of the variations of diſtance between the particles
                will go far to aſcertain the law of action of theſe forces. But the limits of a Work
                like this will not permit us to dwell longer on this ſubject. We proceed therefore
                to give another uſeful table.</p>
            <p>The vitriolic or ſulphuric acid is of extensive uſe in manufactures under the name of
                oil of vitriol. Its value depends entirely on the ſaline ingredient, and the water
                is merely a vehicle for the acid. This, being much denſer than water, affects its
                ſpecific gravity, and thus gives us a method of aſcertaining its ſtrength.</p>
            <p>The ſtrongeſt oil of vitriol that can be eaſily manufactured contains 612 <hi
                    rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">20</hi> grains of dry acid,
                united with 387 <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">20</hi> grains of
                water, which cannot be ſeparated from it by diſtillation, making 1000 grains of <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">oil of vitriol.</hi> Its ſpecific gravity in this ſtate is
                1,877.</p>
            <p>The following table ſhows its ſpecific gravity at the temperature 55⁰, when diluted
                by the ſucceſſive addition of parts of water by weight.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
