<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Mellowness of tone.</cell>
                    <cell>Sprightly notes.</cell>
                    <cell>Plaintive notes.</cell>
                    <cell>Compass.</cell>
                    <cell>Execution.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Nightingale</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Sky-lark</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Wood-lark</cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>17</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Tit-lark</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>I 2</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Linnet</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Goldfinch</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Chaffinch</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Greenfinch</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Hedge-ſparrow</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4'</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Aberdavine or fiſkin</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Red-poll</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Thruſh</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Blackbird</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Robin</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Wren</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Reed ſparrow</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Black-cap, or Norfolk mock nightingale</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>SONNA, a book of Mahometan traditions, which all the orthodox muſſulmen are required
                to believe.</p>
            <p>SONNERATIA, in botany ; a genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic"
                    >icoſandria,</hi> and to the order of mon<hi rend="italic">οgynia.</hi> The
                calyx is cut into six ſegments ; the petals are six; the capſule is multilocular and
                ſucculent ; and the cells contain many ſeeds. The only ſpecies is the <hi
                    rend="italic">acida.</hi></p>
            <p>SONNET, in poetry, a compoſition contained in 14 verſes, viz. two ſtanzas or meaſures
                of four verſes each, and two of three, the eight firſt verſes being all in three
                rhimes.</p>
            <p>SONNITES, among the Mahometans, an appellation given to the orthodox muſſulmen or
                true believers ; in oppoſition to the ſeveral heretical sects, particularly the
                Shiites or followers of Ali.</p>
            <p>SOOJU, or Sov. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Dolichos.</hi></p>
            <p>SOONTABURDAR, in the Eaſt Indies ; an attendant, who carries a ſilver bludgeon in his
                hand about two or three feet long, and runs before the palanquin. He is inferior to
                the Chubdar ; the propriety of an Indian newaury requiring two Soontaburdars ſor
                every Chubdar in the train. The Chubdar proclaims the approach of viſitors, &amp;c.
                He generally carries a large ſilver ſtaff about five feet long in his hands : and
                among the Nabobs he proclaims their praiſes aloud as he runs before their
                palanquins.</p>
            <p>SOOT, a volatile matter ariſing from wood and other fuel along with the ſmoke ; or
                rather, it is the ſmoke itſelf condenſed and gathered to the ſides of the chimney.
                Tho’ once volatile, however, soot cannot be again reſolved into vapour ; but, if
                diſtilled by a ſtrong fire, yields a volatile alkali and empyreumatic oil, a
                conſiderable quantity of fixed matter remaining at the bottom of the diſtilling
                veſſel. If burnt in an open fire, it flames with a thick ſmoke, whence other foot is
                produced. It is uſed as a material for making ſal ammoniac, and as a manure. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> n⁰ 796.; and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Agriculture,</hi> n⁰ 20.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Sοοt-Black.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Colour-Making.</hi></p>
            <p>SOPHI, or SOFI, a title given to the emperor of</p>
            <p>Persia ; importing as much as wiſe, ſage, or philoſopher.</p>
            <p>The title is by ſome ſaid to have taken its riſe from a young ſhepherd named <hi
                    rend="italic">Sοphi,</hi> who attained to the crown of Persia in 1370 ; others
                derive it from the <hi rend="italic">ſophoi</hi> or ſages anciently called <hi
                    rend="italic">magi.</hi> Voſſius gives a different account of the word : sophi
                in Arabic, he obſerves, ſignifies <hi rend="italic">wool</hi> ; and he adds, that it
                was applied by the Turks out of deriſion to the kings of Perſia ever ſince Iſhmael’s
                time; becauſe, according to their ſcheme of religion, he is to wear no other
                covering on his head but an ordinary red woollen fluff; whence the Persians are alſo
                called <hi rend="italic">hetzelbaſchs,</hi> q. d. <hi rend="italic">red-heads.</hi>
                But Bochart assures us, that sophi in the original Perſian language, ſignifies one
                that is pure in his religion, and who prefers the ſervice of God in all things : and
                derives it from an order of religious called by the ſame name. The ſophis value
                themſelves on their illuſtrious extraction. They are deſcended in a right line from
                Houſſein, ſecond son of Ali, Mahomet’s couſin, and Fatima, Mahomet’s daughter.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sophis,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Sofees.</hi> a kind of order
                of religious among the Mahometans in Perſia, anſwering to what are otherwiſe called
                    <hi rend="italic">dervises,</hi> and among the Arabs and Indians <hi
                    rend="italic">faquirs.</hi> Some will have them called ſophis from a kind of
                coarſe camblet which they wear called <hi rend="italic">ſouf,</hi> from the city
                Souf in Syria, where it is principally manufactured. The more eminent of thoſe
                ſophis are complimented with the title s<hi rend="italic">chiek,</hi> that is, <hi
                    rend="italic">reverend,</hi> much as in Romiſh countries the religious are
                called <hi rend="italic">reverend fathers. </hi>Schiek sophi, who laid the
                foundation of the grandeur of the royal houſe of Perſia, was the founder, or rather
                the reſtorer of this order: Iſhmael, who conquered Perſia, was himſelf a sophi, and
                greatly valued himſelf on his being ſo. He choſe all the guards of his person from
                among the religious of this order; and would have all the great lords of his court
                ſophis. The king of Perſia is ſtill grandmaſter of the order; and the lords continue
                to enter into it, though it be now fallen under ſome contempt.</p>
            <p>SOPHISM, in logic, a ſpecious argument having the appearance of truth, but leading to
                falſehood. Sophiſms are reduced by Ariſtotle into eight claſſes, an arrangement so
                juſt and comprehenſive, that it is equally proper in preſent as in former times. 1.
                    <hi rend="italic">ignoratio elenchi, </hi>in which the ſophiſt ſeems to
                determine the queſtion, while he only does it in appearance. Thus the queſtion, “
                Whether excels of wine be hurtful?” ſeems to be determined by proving, that wine
                revives the ſpirits and gives a man courage: but the principal point is here kept
                out of sight ; for ſtill it may be hurtful to health, to fortune, and reputation. 2.
                    <hi rend="italic">Petitio principii,</hi> a begging of the queſtion, or taking
                for granted that which remains to be proved, as if any one ſhould undertake to prove
                that the soul is extended through all the parts of the body, becauſe it reſides in
                every member. This is affirming the ſame thing in different words. 3. Reaſoning in a
                circle ; as when the Roman Catholics prove the Scriptures to be the word of God by
                the authority of the church, and the authority of the church from the Scriptures. 4.
                    <hi rend="italic">Non causa pro cauſa,</hi> or the aſſigning of a falſe cauſe to
                any effect. Thus the ſuppoſed principle, that nature abhors a vacuum, was applied to
                explain the riſing of water in a pump before Galileo diſcovered that it was owing to
                the preſſure of the</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
