<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by Roſcommon and Mayo. It contains 5970 houſes, 41 pariſhes, 6 baronies, 1 borough, and sends 4 members to parliament, two for the county, and two for the borough of the ſame name, which is the only market- town in the county, and is ſeated on a bay of the ſame name, 30 miles west of Killalla, and 110 north-eaſt of Dublin. W. Long. 8. 26. N. Lat. 54. 13.</p><p>SLING, an inſtrument ſerving for caſting ſtones with great violence. The inhabitants of the Balearic iſlands were famous in antiquity for the dexterous management of the ſling : it is ſaid they uſed three kinds of slings, ſome longer, others ſhorter, which they uſed according as their enemies were either nearer or more remote. It is added, that the firſt ſerved them for a head-band, the ſecond for a girdle, and that the third they conſtantly carried in their hand.</p><p>SLINGING is uſed variouſly at ſea ; but chiefly for hoiſting up casks or other heavy things with  slings, <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> contrivances of ropes ſpliced into themſelves at either end, with one eye big enough to receive the caſk or whatever is to be slung. There are other slings, which are made longer, and with a ſmall eye at each end ; one of which is put over the breech of a piece of ordnance, and the other eye comes over the end of an iron crow, which is put into the mouth of the piece, to weigh and hoiſe the gun as they pleaſe. There are alſo slings by which the yards are bound faſt to the croſs-tree aloft, and to the head of the mast, with a ſtrong rope or chain, that if the tie ſhould happen to break, or to be ſhot to pieces in fight, the yard, nevertheleſs, may not fall upon the hatches.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SLIN</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">ging</hi><hi rend="italic"> a Man overboard,</hi> in order to ſtop a leak in a ſhip, is done thus : the man is truſſed up about the middle in a piece of canvas, and a rope to keep him from sinking, with his arms at liberty, a mallet in one hand, and a plug, wrapped in oakum and well tarred in a tarpawling clout, in the other, which he is to beat with all diſpatch into the hole or leak.</p><p>SLOANE (Sir Hans), baronet, eminently diſtinguiſhed as a physician and a naturaliſt, was of Scotch extraction, his father Alexander Sloane being at the head of that colony oſ Scots which King James I. ſettled in the north of Ireland, where our author was born, at Killieagh, on the 16th of April 1660. At a very early period, he diſplayed a ſtrong inclination for natural hiſtory ; and this propenſity being encouraged by a ſuitable education, he employed thoſe hours which young people generally loſe by purſuing low and trifling amuſements, in the ſtudy of nature, and contemplating her works. When about ſixteen, he was attacked by a ſpitting of blood, which threatened to be attended with conſiderable danger, and which interrupted the regular courſe of his application for three years ; he had, however, already learned enough of phyſic to know that a malady of this kind was not to be removed ſuddenly, and he prudently abſtained from wine and other liquors that were likely to increaſe it.</p><p>By ſtrictly obſerving this ſevere regimen, which in ſome meaſure he continued ever after, he was enabled to prolong his life beyond the ordinary bounds ; being an example of the truth of his own favourite maxim, that ſobriety, temperance, and moderation, are the beſt and moſt powerful preſervatives that nature has granted to mankind.</p><p>As ſoon as he recovered from this infirmity, he re</p><p>ſolved to perfect himſelf in the different branches of phyſic, which was the profeſſion he had made choice of ; and with this view he repaired to London, where he hoped to receive that aſſiſtance which he could not find in his own country.</p><p>On his arrival in the metropolis, he entered himſelf as a pupil to the great Stafforth, an excellent chemiſt, bred under the illuſtrious Stahl ; and by his inſtructions he gained a perfect knowledge of the compoſition and preparation of the different kinds oſ medicines then in uſe. At the ſame time, he ſtudied botany at the celebrated garden at Chelſea, aſſiduouſly attended the public lectures of anatomy and phyſic, and in short neglected nothing that he thought likely to prove ſerviceable to him in his future practice. His principal merit, however, was his knowledge of natural hiſtory ; and it was this part of his character which introduced him early to the acquaintance of Mr Boyle and Mr Ray, two of the moſt eminent naturaliſts of that age. His intimacy with theſe diſtinguiſhed characters continued as long as they lived ; and as he was careful to communicate to them every object of curioſity that attracted his attention, the obſervations which he occaſionally made often excited their admiration and obtained their applauſe.</p><p>After ſtudying four years at London with unremitting ſeverity, Mr Sloane determined to viſit foreign countries for farther improvement. In this view he ſet out for France in the company of two other ſtudents, and having croſſed to Dieppe, proceeded to Paris. In the way thither they were elegantly entertained by the famous M. Lemery the elder ; and in return Mr Sloane presented that eminent chemiſt with a ſpecimen of four different kinds of phoſphorus, of which, upon the credit of other writers, M. Lemery had treated in his book of chemiſtry, though he had never ſeen any of them.</p><p>At Paris Mr Sloane lived as he had done in London. He attended the hoſpitals, heard the lectures of Tournefort, De Verney, and other eminent masters ; viſited all the literati, who received him with particular marks of eſteem, and employed himſelf wholly in ſtudy.</p><p>From Paris Mr Sloane went to Montpelier ; and, being furniſhed with letters of recommendation from M. Tournesort to M. Chirac, then chancellor of that university, he found eaſy acceſs, through his means, to all the learned men of the province, particulaιly to M. Magnol, whom he always accompanied in his botanical excurſions in the environs of that city, where he beheld with pleaſure and admiration the ſpontaneous productions of nature, and learned under his inſtructions to claſs them in a proper manner.</p><p>Having here found an ample field for contemplation, which was entirely ſuited to his taſte, he took leave of his two companions, whom a curioſity of a different kind led into Italy.</p><p>After ſpending a whole year in collecting plants, he travelled through Languedoc with the ſame design ; and paſſing through Thoulouſe and Bourdeaux, returned to Paris, where he made a ſhort ſtay. About the end of the year 1684 he ſet out for England, with an intention of settling there as a physician. On his arrival in London, he made it his firſt buſineſs to viſit his two illuſtrious friends Mr Ray and Mr Boyle, in order</p></body></text></TEI>