<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:33Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>taining the ſpecific gravity of diſſolved ſalts. In one of them (not particularly
                narrated) he found that a quantity of diſſolved ſalt occupied the same bulk in two
                very different ſtates of dilution. We cannot pretend to reconcile this with our
                experiments. We have given theſe as they flood ; and we think them concluſive,
                becauſe they were ſo numerous and ſo perfectly confident with each other ; and their
                reſult is ſo general, that we have not found an exception. Common ſalt is by no
                means the moſt remarkable inſtance of condenſation. Vegetable alkali, ſal ammoniac,
                and ſome others, exhibit much greater condenſation.</p>
            <p>We thought this a proper opportunity of conſidering this queſtion, which is
                intimately connected with the principles of chemical ſolution, and was not perhaps
                conſidered in sufficient detail under the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Chemistry.</hi> We learn from it in general, that the quantities of ſalt in
                brines increaſe at ſomewhat a greater rate than their ſpecific gravities. This
                difference is in many cases of ſenſible importance in a commercial view. Thus an
                alkaline lixivium for the purpoſes of bleaching or ſoap-making, whoſe ſpecific
                gravity is 1,234, or exceeds that of water by 234, contains 361 ounces of ſalt in a
                cubic foot ; a ley, which exceeds the weight of water twice as much, or 468 ounces
                    <hi rend="italic">per</hi> cubic foot, contains 777 ounces of ſalt, which
                exceeds the double of 361 by 55 ounces more than 7 <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi>
                Hence we learn, that hydrometers for diſcovering the ſtrength of brines, having
                equal diviſions on a cylindrical ſtem, are very erroneous ; for even if the
                increments of ſpecific gravity were proportional to the quantities of ſalt in a
                gallon of brine, the diviſions at the bottom of the ſtem ought to be ſmaller than
                thoſe above.</p>
            <p>The conſtruction of the following table oſ ſtrengths from the above narrated ſeries
                of brines is sufficiently obvious. Column 1st is the ſpecific gravity as diſcovered
                by the balance or hydometer, and alſo is the number of ounces in a cubic foot of the
                brine. Col. 2d is the ounces of the dry ſalt contained in it.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="5"><hi rend="italic">Table of Brines of Common Salt.</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Weight Cub. Ft. Brine.</cell>
                    <cell>Salt in Cub. F.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Weight Cub. Ft. Brine.</cell>
                    <cell>Salt in Cub. F.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,000</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,115</cell>
                    <cell>170</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,008</cell>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,122</cell>
                    <cell>180</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,015</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,128</cell>
                    <cell>190</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,022</cell>
                    <cell>30</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,134</cell>
                    <cell>200</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,029</cell>
                    <cell>40</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,140</cell>
                    <cell>210</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,036</cell>
                    <cell>50</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1147</cell>
                    <cell>220</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,043</cell>
                    <cell>60</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,153</cell>
                    <cell>230</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,050</cell>
                    <cell>70</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,159</cell>
                    <cell>240</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,057</cell>
                    <cell>80</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,165</cell>
                    <cell>250</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,064</cell>
                    <cell>90</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,172</cell>
                    <cell>260</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,070</cell>
                    <cell>100</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,178</cell>
                    <cell>270</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,077</cell>
                    <cell>110</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,184</cell>
                    <cell>280</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,083</cell>
                    <cell>120</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,190</cell>
                    <cell>290</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,090</cell>
                    <cell>130</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,197</cell>
                    <cell>300</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,096</cell>
                    <cell>140</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,203</cell>
                    <cell>310</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,103</cell>
                    <cell>150</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,206</cell>
                    <cell>316</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1,109</cell>
                    <cell>160</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1,208</cell>
                    <cell>320</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>The table differs conſiderably from Mr Lambert’s. The quantities of ſalt
                correſponding to any ſpecific gravity are about <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">18</hi>th leſs than in his table But the reader will see that
                they correſpond with the ſeries of</p>
            <p>experiments above narrated; and theſe were but a few of many which all correſponded
                within an hundredth part. The cauſe iof the difference ſeems to be, that moſt kinds
                of common ſalt contain magneſian ſalts, which contain a very great proportion of
                water neceſſary for their cryſtallization. The ſalt which we uſed was of the pureſt
                kind, but ſuch as may be had from every ſalt work, by Lord Dundonald’s very eaſy
                proceſs, viz. by paſſing through it a ſaturated ſolution boiling hot, which carries
                off with it about <hi rend="superscript">4</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">5</hi>ths of
                all the bitter ſalts. Our aim being to aſcertain the quantities of pure ſea- ſalt,
                and to learn by the by its relation to water in reſpect of density, we thought it
                neceſſary to uſe the pureſt ſalt. We alſo dried it for ſeveral days in a ſtove, ſo
                that it contained no water not abſolutely neceſſary for its cryſtallization. An
                ounce of ſuch ſalt will communicate a greater ſpecific gravity to water than an
                ounce of a salt that is leſs pure, or that contains extraneous water.</p>
            <p>The ſpecific gravity 1,090 is that of ordinary pickles, which are eſtimated as to
                ſtrength by floating an egg.</p>
            <p>We cannot raiſe the ſpecific gravity higher than 1,206 by simply diſſolving ſalt in
                cold water. But it will become much denſer, and will even attain the ſpecific
                gravity 1,240 by boiling, then holding about 366 ounces in the cubic foot of hot
                brine. But it will depoſit by cooling, and when of the temperature 55⁰ or 60⁰,
                hardly exceeds 1,206. We obtained a brine by boiling till the ſalt grained very
                rapidly. When it cooled to 60⁰, its ſpecific gravity was 1,2063 ; for a veſſel which
                held 3506 grains of distilled water held 4229 of this brine. This was evaporated to
                dryneſs, and there were obtained 1344 grains of ſalt. By this was computed the
                number interpoſed between 310 and 320 in the table. We have however raiſed the
                ſpecific gravity to 1,217, by putting in no more ſalt than was neceſſary for thi$
                denſity, and uſing heat. It then cooled down to 60⁰ without quitting any ſalt ; but
                if a few grains of ſalt be thrown into this brine, it will quickly deposit a great
                deal more, and its denſity will decreaſe to 1,206. We find this to hold in all salts
                ; and it is a very inſtructive fact in the theory of cryſtallization ; it reſembles
                the effect which a magnet produces upon iron filings in its neighbourhood. It makes
                them temporary magnets, and cauſes them to arrange themſelves as if they had been
                really made permanent magnets. Juſt ſo a cryſtal already formed diſpoſes the reſt to
                cryſtallize. We imagine that this analogy is complete, and that the forces are
                ſimilar in both caſes.</p>
            <p>The above table is computed for the temperature 55⁰ ; but in other temperatures the
                ſtrength will be different on two accounts, viz. the expanſion of the brine and the
                diſſolving power of the water. Water expands about 40 parts in 1000 when heated from
                60⁰ to 212⁰. Saturated brine expands about 48 parts, or <hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">5</hi>th more than water; and this exceſs of
                expanſion is nearly proportional to the quantity of ſalt in the brine. If therefore
                any circumſtance ſhould oblige us to examine a brine in a temperature much above
                60⁰, allowance ſhould be made for this. Thus, ſhould the ſpecific gravity of brine
                of the temperature 130 (which is nearly half way between 60 and 212 ) be 1,140, we
                muſt increaſe it by 20 (half of 40 ) ; and having found the ſtrength 24
                correſponding to this corrected ſpecific gravity, we muſt correct it again by adding
                1 to the ſpecific gravity for every 45 ounces of ſalt.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
