<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>volution in the mother country, which has produced in all its dependencies anarchy
                and maſſacre, the condition of the negro-ſlaves was better than that of the bond-
                men among the ancient Germans. “ Thoſe of them who cultivated the plantations were
                attached to the ſoil, and could not be drawn off to pay debts, or be ſold ſeparately
                from the eſtate on which they lived. This gave them a laſting property in their huts
                and little ſpots of ground, which they might ſafely cultivate without dread of being
                turned out of posseſſion, or transferred contrary to their intereſt and feelings
                from one proprietor to another. They were under the protection of law as ſoon as
                they arrived in the colony. Proper misſionaries were appointed for the purpoſe of
                training them up to a certain degree of religious knowledge, and ample funds were
                allotted for the maintenance of thoſe eccleſiaſtics. On ill treatment received from
                his maſter, or on being deprived of his allowance of food and raiment, the ſlave was
                directed to apply to the king’s attorney, who was obliged to proſecute the maſter
                forthwith. That officer was alſo bound to proſecute, if by any other means he heard
                of the abuſe ; the law adding as the reaſon, <hi rend="italic">This we will to be
                    obſerved, to check the abuſe of power in the master."</hi></p>
            <p>We wiſh it were in our power to say, that in the Britiſh West India colonies ſlaves
                are equally protected by law as they were in the French iſlands under the old
                government, and that the ſame care is taken of their moral and religious
                improvement. This, however, we are afraid, cannot be ſaid with truth. In the iſland
                of Jamaica, before the paſſing of the <hi rend="italic">conſolidated slave act,
                </hi>not many years ago, a white man, whether proprietor or not, who had killed a
                negro, or by an act of ſeverity been the cauſe of his death, was, for the firſt
                offence, intitled to benefit of clergy, and not liable to capital puniſhment till a
                repetition of the crime.@@ By the preſent law, it is enacted, “ That if any perſon,
                whether owner or ſuperintendant of ſlaves, ſhall be convicted of having, by any act
                of paſſion or cruelty, occasioned the death of any negro, it ſhall be capital for
                the first offence : and for the greater ſecurity of the property, and as a check on
                thoſe who may have the puniſhment of ſlaves in their power, it is particularly
                required, that every ſurgeon or doctor belonging to each eſtate ſhall ſwear to the
                cauſe of the death of each negro, to the beſt of his knowledge and belief ; and if
                any negro dies, and is interred by the owner or overſeer, without the doctor’s
                having ſeen or been ſent for to ſuch negro, in this caſe, the owner or overſeer
                cauſing the negro to be ſo interred is liable to a proſecution for ſuch
                conduct.”</p>
            <p>This law muſt doubleſs be productive of good effects ; but being a colonial act, it
                cannot have the vigour of the <hi rend="italic">Code Noir;</hi> nor do we know of
                any attorney in the iſland who is <hi rend="italic">obliged</hi> to defend the
                rights of the negroes, or proſecute the maſter whoſe cruelty has by any means</p>
            <p>come to his knowledge. The juſtices and veſtry of cach pariſh are indeed conſtituted
                    <hi rend="italic">a council oſ protection,</hi> for the expreſs purpoſe of
                making full enquiry into the barbarities exerciſed on ſlaves, and bringing the
                authors to puniſhment at the public expence ; and by a new ſlave-act of Grenada, the
                juſtices are required annually to nominate three freeholders to be <hi rend="italic"
                    >guardians oſ the slaves, </hi>who are to take an oath to ſee the law duly
                executed @@*. Theſe are benevolent regulations ; but we doubt if protection can be
                ſo promptly afforded by a council of guardians as by an individual attorney who has
                no other employment. In ſome of the other Britiſh iſlands, we have been confidently
                told that the unfortunate ſons of Africa have no protection whatever againſt the
                tyranny of a sordid owner, or the caprice of a boyiſh overſeer @@<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(m) ; </hi>though it is added, that the humanity of many
                maſters more than ſupplies the want of laws in every reſpect but that of
                improvement, and that the attachment of others has in them a like effect. In ſome
                caſes good ſenſe, a regard for their reputation, and a well-informed conviction of
                their intereſt, induce men to treat their ſlaves with diſcretion and humanity. The
                ſlaves of many a planter posseſs advantages beyond what the labourer even of Britain
                enjoys @@*;” yet theſe advantages all depend upon the good will of his maſter ; and
                in no part of the Britiſh colonies are the ſlaves attached to the ſoil. This ſingle
                circumſtance, together with the total neglect of their moral and religious culture,
                makes their ſituation much leſs eligible than was that of the French ſlaves under
                the old government ; and affords a ſtriking proof of what the humane author whom we
                have just quoted well obſerves, that “ thoſe men and nations whom liberty hath
                exalted, and who therefore ought to regard it tenderly in others, are conſtantly for
                reſtrain- ing its bleſſings within their own little circle, and delight more in
                augmenting the train of their dependants than in adding to the rank of
                fellow-citizens, or in diffuſing the benefits of freedom among their
                neighbours.”</p>
            <p>Having given this ample detail of the rise and progreſs of ſlavery in the world, and
                ſhown that it has prevailed in every age, and under all religions, we ſhall now
                proceed to enquire whether a practice ſo general be in any inſtance lawful ; and if
                it be, how it muſt be modified, in order to be rendered consiſtent with the rights
                of man and the immutable laws of virtue.</p>
            <p>That in a ſtate of nature one man has a right to ſeize upon another, and to compel
                him by force to labour for his ſubſiſtence, is a position which we believe has never
                been ſeriouſly maintained. But independent communities ſtand to each other in the
                very ſame relation that individuals do in a ſtate of nature ; and therefore if in
                ſuch a ſtate the man of greater bodily ſtrength or mental ſagacity would have no
                right to convert his weaker neighbour into personal property, neither can</p>
           
            <p>@@@(M) In Barbadoes there is ſaid to be a law for the protection of ſlaves, which is
                the moſt insolent trifling with juſtice and humanity that the writer of this article
                has ever ſeen. It is enacted, forſooth, “ That if any man ſhall, of <hi
                    rend="italic">wantonness,</hi> or only of <hi rend="italic"
                    >bloody-mindedneſs,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">cruel intention, wilfully
                    kill</hi> a negro or other ſlave, if his own, he ſhall pay into the public
                treaſury <hi rend="italic">fifteen pounds Sterling !</hi> See <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dickson's Letters on Slavery,</hi> p. 4.</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] Neil's Observations on the Treatment of Negroes in the island of Jamaica.</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Edward's History of the West Indies, book iv. chap 5. </p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Ramsay's Essay, p. 66. and 91.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
