<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>holy water (whereby the devil mockes the papiſts), and  ſome preſent of a living thing unto him. There are likewiſe certaine daies and houres that they obſerve in this purpoſe. Theſe things being all ready and prepared, circles are made, triangular, quadrangular, round, double, or ſingle, according to the forme of the apparition they crave. When the conjured ſpirit appeares, which will not be while after many circumſtances, long prayers, and much muttering and murmurings of the conjurors, like a papiſt prieſt dispatching a hunting maſſe —how ſoone, I ſay, he appeares, if they have missed one jote of all their rites ; or if any of their feete once ſlyd over the circle, through terror of his fearfull apparition, he paies himſelf at that time, in his owne hand, of that due debt which they ought him, and otherwiſe would have delated longer to have pared him : I mean, he carries them with him, body and soule.” How the conjurors made triangular or quadrangular circles, his majeſty has not informed us, nor does he ſeem to imagine there was any difficulty in the matter. We are therefore led to ſuppoſe, that he learned his mathematics from the ſame ſyſtem as Dr Sacheverell, who, in one of his ſpeeches or fermons, made uſe of the following ſimile : “ They concur like parallel lines, meeting in one common centre.”</p><p>Another mode of conſulting ſpirits was by the beryl, by means of a ſpeculator or ſeer ; who, to have a complete ſight, ought to be a pure virgin, a youth who had not known woman, or at leaſt a perſon oſ irreproachable life and purity of manners. The method of ſuch consultation is this : The conjuror having repeated the neceſſary charms and adjurations, with the litany or invocation peculiar to the ſpirits or angels he wiſhes to call (for every one has his particular form), the ſeer looks into a cryſtal or beryl, wherein he will ſee the anſwer repreſented either by types or figures ; and ſometimes, though very rarely, will hear the angels or ſpirits ſpeak articulately. Their pronunciation is, as Lilly ſays, like the Iriſh, much in the throat. Lilly describes one of theſe beryls or cryſtals. It was, he ſays, as large as an orange, ſet in ſilver, with a croſs at the top, and round about engraved the names of the angels Raphael, Gabriel, and Uriel. A delineation of another is engraved in the frontiſpiece to Aubery’s Miſcellanies.</p><p>Theſe ſorcerers or magicians do not always employ their art to do miſchief; but, on the contrary, frequently exert it to cure diſeaſes inflicted by witches ; to diſcover thieves ; recover ſtolen goods ; to foretel future events, and the ſtate of abſent friends. On this account they are frequently called <hi rend="italic">white witches.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Magic, </hi>WITCHCRAFT, &amp;C.</p><p>Our forefathers were ſtrong believers when they enacted, by ſtatute 33 Hen. VIII. c. 8. all witchcraft and ſorcery to be felony without benefit of clergy ; and again, by ſtatute 1 Jac. I. c. 12. that all perſons invoking any evil ſpirit, or conſulting, covenanting with, entertaining, employing, feeding, or rewarding arty evil ſpirit; or taking up dead bodies from their graves to be uſed in any witchcraft, ſorcery, charm, or inchant- ment; or killing or otherwiſe hurting any perſon by ſuch infernal arts ; ſhould be guilty of felony without benefit of clergy, and ſuffer death. And if any perſon ſhould attempt by ſorcery to diſcover hidden treaſure,</p><p>or to reſtore ſtolen goods, or to provoke unlawful love, or to hurt any man or beaſt, though the ſame were not effected, he or ſhe ſhould ſuffer impriſonment and pillory for the firſt offence, and death for the ſecond. Theſe acts continued in force till lately, to the terror of all ancient females in the kingdom ; and many poor wretches were ſacrificed thereby to the prejudice of their neighbours and their own illuſions, not a few having by ſome means or other confeſſed the fact at the gallows. But all executions for this dubious crime are now at an end ; our legiſlature having at length followed the wiſe example of Louis XIV. in France, who thought proper by an edict to reſtrain the tribunals of juſtice from receiving informations of withcraſt. And accordingly it is with us enacted, by ſtatute 9 Geo. II. c. 5. that no proſecution ſhall for the future be carried on againſt any perſon for conjuration, witchcraft, ſorcery, or inchantment : But the miſdemeanor of perſons pretending to uſe witchcraft, tell fortunes, or diſcover ſtolen goods, by ſkill in the occult ſciences, is ſtill deſervedly puniſhed with a year’s impriſonment, and ſtanding four times in the pillory.</p><p>SOREX, the <hi rend="smallcaps">Shrew,</hi> in natural hiſtory; a genus of animals belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">mammalia,</hi> and order of f<hi rend="italic">erae.</hi> It has two long fore-teeth in the upper jaw, which are divided into two points ; in the lower jaw are two or four fore-teeth, the two middle ones, in the latter caſe, being ſhorter than the others : On each ſide in both jaws are two or more tuſks : The grinders are knobbed. The animals of this genus have in general thick clumſy bodies, and five toes on each of their feet ; the head reſembles that of the mole, being thick at the fore-head, much elongated, and ending in a conical ſnout, and having very ſmall eyes ; in other circumſtances of general figure they reſemble the murine tribe of quadrupeds. They burrow in the ground, ſome ſpecies living moſtly about the ſides of waters ; and most of them feeding on worms and infects. There are 16 ſpecies ; of which the moſt remarkable are,</p><p>1.	The <hi rend="italic">araneus,</hi> or field ſhrew-mouſe, with ſhort rounded ears ; eyes ſmall, and almoſt hid in the fur ; noſe long and ſlender, upper part the longeſt; head and upper part of the body of a browniſh red ; belly of a dirty white ; length from noſe to tail, two inches and a half ; tail one and a half. Inhabits Europe: lives in old walls and heaps of ſtones, or holes in the earth ; is frequently near hay-ricks, dung-hills, and neceſſary-houſes; lives on corn, insects, and any filth ; is often obſerved rooting in ordure like a hog ; from its food, or the places it frequents, has a diſagreeable ſmell ; cats will kill, but not eat it : it brings four or five young at a time. The ancients believed it was injurious to cattle; an error now detected. There ſeems to be an annual mortality of theſe animals in Auguſt, numbers being then found dead in the paths.</p><p>2.	The <hi rend="italic">ſocliens,</hi> or water-ſhrew, has a long ſlender noſe ; very minute ears ; very ſmall eyes, hid in the fur ; colour of the head and upper part of the body black ; throat, breaſt and belly, of a light aſh colour ; beneath the tail, a triangular duſky ſpot ; much larger than the laſt ; length, from noſe to tail, three inches three quarters ; tail, two inches. Inhabits Europe : long ſince known in England, but loſt till May 1768, when it was diſcovered in the fens near Reveſley Ab-</p></body></text></TEI>