<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>garithm of 0,73. from that of 1.068793,viz. 0,0288937, and take 0.0041393, the 40th
                part of the difference. Multiply this by 1, 2, 3, &amp;c. and add the logarithm of
                0,73 to each of the products. The ſums are the logarithms of the ſpecific gravities
                required. Theſe will be found to proceed ſo equably, that they may be interpolated
                ten times by a ſimple table of proportional parts without the ſmalleſt ſensible
                error. Therefore the ſtem may be divided into a hundred parts very ſenſible to the
                eye (each being nearly the 20th of an inch), and 400 degrees of ſpecific gravity
                obtained within the range, which is as near as we can examine this matter by any
                hydrometer. Thus the ſpecific gravities correſponding to n⁰ 26, 27, 28, 29, are as
                follow :</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>1st. Diff.</cell>
                    <cell>2d Diff.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell rows="2">26</cell>
                    <cell rows="2">0,93529</cell>

                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>895</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell rows="2">27</cell>
                    <cell rows="2">0,94424</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>904</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell rows="2">28</cell>
                    <cell rows="2">0,95328 </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>913</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>29</cell>
                    <cell>0,96241</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>Nay, the trouble of inſpecting a table may be avoided, by forming on a ſcale the
                logarithms of the numbers between 7300 and 1068,793, and placing along ſide of it a
                ſcale of the ſame length divided into 400 equal parts, numbered from 0 to 400. Then,
                looking ſor the mark ſhown by the hydrometer on this ſcale of equal parts, we see
                oppoſite to it the ſpecific gravity.</p>
            <p>We have been thus particular in the illuſtration of this mode of conſtruction,
                becauſe <hi rend="italic">it</hi> is really a beautiful and commodious inſtrument,
                which may be of great uſe both to the naturaliſt and to the man of buſineſs. — A
                table may be compriſed in 20 octavo pages, which will contain the ſpecific gravities
                of every fluid which can intereſt either, and anſwer every queſtion relative to
                their admixture with as much preciſion as the obſervations can be made. We therefore
                recommend it to our readers, and we recommend the very example which we have given
                as one of the moſt convenient. The inſtrument need not exceed eight inches in
                length, and may be contained in a pocket caſe of 2 inches broad and as many deep,
                which will alſo contain the ſcale, a thermometer, and even the table for applying it
                to all fluids which have been examined.</p>
            <p>It is unfortunate that no graduated hydrometer can be made ſo eaſily for the
                examination of the corrofive mineral acids @@<hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> Theſe
                muſt be made oſ glaſs, and we cannot depend on the accurate cylindric form of any
                glaſs item. But if any ſuch can be procured, the conſtruction is the ſame. The
                divided ſcale may either be on thin paper palled on the inside of the ſtem, or it
                may be printed on the ſtem itſelf from a plate, with ink made of a metallic calx,
                which will attach itſelf to the glaſs with a very moderate heat. We would recommend
                common white enamel, or arſenical glaſs, as the fitteſt material for the whole
                inſtrument; and the ink uſed, in taking the impreſſion of the ſcale, may be the ſame
                that is uſed for the low priced printing on Delft ware pottery. Firſt form the ſcale
                on the ſtem. Then, having measured the ſolid contents of the graduated part as
                exactly as poſſible, and determined on the general ſhape of the ball and
                counterpoiſe below, calculate its ſize, ſo that it may be a little leſs than ten
                times that of the</p>
            <p>ſtem. The glaſs blower can copy this very nearly, and join it to the ſtem. Then make
                two brines or other liquors, which ſhall have ſpecific gravities in the ratio of 10
                to 11. Load the inſtrument ſo that it may link to 0 in the lighteſt. When put into
                the heavieſt, it ſhould riſe to 10. If it does not riſe ſo high, the immerſed part
                is too ſmall. Let the glaſs blower enlarge the ball of the counterpoiſe a little.
                Repeat this trial till it be exact. Nothing now remains but to form the weights :
                And here we obſerve, that when the inſtrument is to have a very great range, as for
                examining all ſtates of the vitriolic acid, it has a chance of being very tottering
                when loaded with the greateſt weight on the top of ſo long a ſcale. To avoid this,
                Mr Quin and others have added ſome of. their weights below.— But this will not suit
                the preſent conſtruction, becauſe it will alter the proportion between the bulks of
                the ſtem and immerſed part. Therefore let theſe weights consiſt of cylinders of
                metal ſmall enough to go into the ſtem, and let them be ſoldered to the end of long
                wires, which will let them go to the bottom, and leave a ſmall hook or ring at top.
                Theſe can lie alongſide of the inſtrument in its caſe. This is indeed the beſt
                construction for every hydrometer, becauſe it makes it incomparably more ſteady. The
                inſtrument is poiſed by ſmall ſhot or mercury. But it will be much better to do it
                with Newton’s fuſible metal (three parts of tin, five parts of lead, and eight parts
                of biſmuth) in coarſe filings. When the exact quantity has been put in, the
                inſtrument may be ſet in a veſſel of oil, and this kept on the fire till all is
                completely melted. It ſoon freezes again, and remains fast. If this metal is not to
                be had, let a few bits of ſealing-wax be added to the mercury or ſhot, to make up
                the counterpoiſe. When heated, it will float a-top, and when it freezes again it
                will keep all faſt. Thus we ſhall make a very complete and cheap inſtrument.</p>
            <p> There is yet another method of examining the ſpecific gravities of fluids, firſt
                propoſed by Dr Wilſon, late profeſſor of aſtronomy in the university oſ Glaſgow.
                This is by a ſeries of ſmall glaſs bubbles, differing equally, or according to ſome
                rule, from each other in ſpecific gravity, and each marked with its proper number.
                When theſe are thrown into a fluid which is to be examined, all thoſe which are
                heavier than the fluid will fall to the bottom. Then holding the veſſel in the hand,
                or near a fire or candle, the fluid expands, and one of the floating bubbles begins
                to sink. Its ſpecific gravity, therefore, was either equal to, or a little leſs
                than, that of the fluid ; and the degree of the thermometer, when it began to sink,
                will inform us how much it was deficient, if we know the law of expansion of the
                liquor. Sets of theſe bubbles fitted for the examination of ſpirituous liquors, with
                a little treatiſe ſhowing the manner of uſing them, and calculating by the
                thermometer, are made by Mr Brown, an ingenious artiſt of Glaſgow, and are often
                used by the dealers in spirits, being found both accurate and expeditious.</p>
            <p>Alſo, though a bubble or two ſhould be broken, the ſtrength of ſpirits may easily be
                had by means of the remainder, unleſs two or three in immediate ſucceſſion</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> It would be worth while to try copper enamelled.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
