<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:27Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell cols="2">Specific Gravity.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Ol. Vit.</cell>
                    <cell>Water.</cell>
                    <cell><p>Obſerved.</p></cell>
                    <cell>Calculated.</cell>
                    <cell>Cond.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>× O</cell>
                    <cell>1,877</cell>
                    <cell>1.877</cell>
                    <cell>.00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>1,644</cell>
                    <cell>1,501</cell>
                    <cell>,143</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>1,474</cell>
                    <cell>1,350</cell>
                    <cell>,124</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>12</cell>
                    <cell>1,381</cell>
                    <cell>1,269</cell>
                    <cell>,112</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>1,320</cell>
                    <cell>1,219</cell>
                    <cell>,101</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>1,274</cell>
                    <cell>1,184</cell>
                    <cell>,090</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>24</cell>
                    <cell>1,243</cell>
                    <cell>1,159</cell>
                    <cell>,084</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>28</cell>
                    <cell>1,2 I I</cell>
                    <cell>1,140</cell>
                    <cell>,071</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>32</cell>
                    <cell>1,195</cell>
                    <cell>1,125</cell>
                    <cell>,070</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>36</cell>
                    <cell>1,183</cell>
                    <cell>1,113</cell>
                    <cell>,070</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>40</cell>
                    <cell>1,172</cell>
                    <cell>1,103</cell>
                    <cell>,070</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>50</cell>
                    <cell>1,148</cell>
                    <cell>1,084</cell>
                    <cell>,064</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>60</cell>
                    <cell>1,128</cell>
                    <cell>1,069</cell>
                    <cell>,059</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>Here is obſerved a much greater condenſation than in the mixture of alcohol and
                water. But we cannot aſſign the proportion of ingredients which produces the
                greateſt condenſation ; becauſe we cannot, in any caſe, say what is the proportion
                of the ſaline and watery ingredients. The ſtrongeſt oil of vitriol is already a
                watery ſolution; and it is by a conſiderable and uncertain detour that Mr Kirwan has
                aſſigned the proportion of 612 and 388 nearly. If this be the true ratio, it is
                unlike every other ſolution that we are acquainted with ; for in all ſolutions of
                ſalts, the ſalt occupies leſs room in its liquid form than it did when ſolid ; and
                here it would be greatly the reverſe.</p>
            <p>This ſolution is remarkable alſo for the copious emergence of heat in its dilutions
                with more water. This has been aſcribed to the great ſuperiority of water in its
                capacity for heat ; but there are facts which render this very doubtful. A veſſel of
                water, and another of oil of vitriol, being brought ſrom a cold room into a warm
                one, they both imbibe heat, and riſe in their temperature ; and the water employs
                nearly the ſame time to attain the temperature of the room.</p>
            <p>Aquafortis or nitrous acid is another fluid very much employed in commerce ; ſo that
                it is of importance to aſcertain the relation between its ſaline ſtrength and its
                ſpecific gravity. We owe alſo to Mr Kirwan a table for this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The moſt concentrated ſtate into which it can easily be brought is ſuch, that 1000
                grains of it conſiſts of 563 grains of water and 437 of dry acid. In this ſtate its
                ſpecific gravity is 1,557. Let this be called <hi rend="italic">nitrous
                add.</hi></p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Nitr. Ac.</cell>
                    <cell>Water.</cell>
                    <cell cols="3"></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>× O</cell>
                    <cell>1,557</cell>
                    <cell>1,557</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>I</cell>
                    <cell>1,474</cell>
                    <cell>1,474</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>1,350</cell>
                    <cell>1,273</cell>
                    <cell>0,077</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>11</cell>
                    <cell>1,269</cell>
                    <cell>1,191</cell>
                    <cell>o,078</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>1,214.</cell>
                    <cell>1,147</cell>
                    <cell>0,067</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>21</cell>
                    <cell>1,175</cell>
                    <cell>1,120</cell>
                    <cell>0,055</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>26</cell>
                    <cell>1,151</cell>
                    <cell>1,101</cell>
                    <cell>0,050</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>31</cell>
                    <cell>1,127</cell>
                    <cell>1,087</cell>
                    <cell>0,040</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>36</cell>
                    <cell>1,106</cell>
                    <cell>1,077</cell>
                    <cell>c,029</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>41</cell>
                    <cell>1,086</cell>
                    <cell>1,068</cell>
                    <cell>0,018</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>There is not the ſame uniformity in the denſities of this acid in its different
                ſtates of dilution. This ſeems owing to the variable proportion of the deleterious
                and vital air which compose this acid. It is more denſe in</p>
            <p>proportion as it contains more of the latter ingredient.</p>
            <p>The proportions of the aeriform ingredients of the muriatic acid are ſo very
                variable, and ſo little under our command, that we cannot frame tables of its
                ſpecific gravity which would enable us to judge of its ſtrength.</p>
            <p>It is a general property of theſe acids, that they are more expanſible by heat as
                they are more concentrated.</p>
            <p>There is another claſs of fluids which it would be of great conſequence to reduce to
                ſome rules with reſpect to ſpecific gravity, namely, the ſolutions oſ ſalts, gums,
                and reſins. It is intereſting to the philoſopher to know in what manner ſalts are
                contained in theſe watery ſolutions, and to diſcover the relation between their
                ſtrength and denſity ; and to the man of buſineſs it would be a moſt deſirable thing
                to have a criterion of the quantity of ſalt in any brine, or of extractible matter
                in a decoction. It would be equally deſirable to thoſe who are to purchaſe them as
                to thoſe who manufacture or employ them. Perhaps we might aſcertain in this way the
                value of ſugar, depending on the quantity of ſweetening matter which it contains ; a
                thing which at preſent reſts on the vague determination of the eye or palate. It
                would therefore be doing a great ſervice to the public, if ſome intelligent perſon
                would undertake a train of experiments with this view. Accuracy alone is required ;
                and it may be left to the philoſophers to compare the facts, and draw the
                conſequences reſpecting the internal arrangement of the particles.</p>
            <p>One circumſtance in the ſolution of ſalts is very general ; and we are inclined, for
                ſerious reaſons, to think it univerſal: this is a diminution of bulk. This indeed in
                ſome ſalts is inconſiderable. Sedative ſalt, for inſtance, hardly ſhows any
                diminution, and might be conſidered as an exception, were it not the ſingle
                inſtance. This circumſtance, and ſome conſiderations connected with our notions of
                this kind of ſolution, diſpoſe us to think that this ſalt differs in contraction
                from others only in degree, and that there is ſome, though it was not ſenſible, in
                the experiments hitherto made.</p>
            <p>Theſe experiments, indeed, have not been numerous. Thoſe of Mr Achard of Berlin, and
                of Dr Richard Watſon of Cambridge, are perhaps the only ones of which we have a
                deſcriptive narration, by which we can judge of the validity of the inferences drawn
                from them. The ſubject is not ſuſceptible of much accuracy ; for salts in their
                ſolid form are ſeldom free from cavities and ſhivery interſtices, which do not admit
                the water on their firſt immerſion, and thereby appear of greater bulk when we
                attempt to meaſure their ſpecific gravity by weighing them in fluids which do not
                diſſolve them, ſuch as ſpirits of turpentine. They alſo attach to themſelves, with
                conſiderable tenacity, a quantity of atmoſpheric air, which merely adheres, but
                makes no part of their compoſition. This eſcapes in the act of ſolution, being ſet
                at liberty by the ſtronger affinity of the water. Sal gem, however, and a few
                others, may be very accurately meaſured; and in theſe inſtances the degree of
                contraction is very conſtant.</p>
            <p>The following experiments of Dr Watſon appear to us the moſt inſtructive as to this
                circumſtance. A glaſs veſſel was uſed, having a ſlender cylindrical neck, and
                holding 67 ounces of pure water when filled to a cer-</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
