<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>rinth, and Argos. By diſtributing the money in a proper manner, he inflamed the inhabitants of theſe three cities againſt the Spartans ; and of all others the Thebans came into his terms with the greateſt readineſs. They ſaw that their antagoniſts would not of their own accord break with any of the ſtates of Greece, and did not chooſe to begin the war themſelves, becauſe the chiefs of the Perſian faction were unwilling to be accountable for the event. For this reaſon they perſuaded the Locrians to invade a ſmall diſtrict which lay in diſpute betwixt the Phocians and themſelves. On this the Phocians invaded Locris ; the Locrians applied to the Thebans, and the Phocians to the Spartans. The latter were glad of an opportunity of breaking with the Thebans ; but met with a much warmer reception than they expected. Their old general Lyſander, who had reduced Athens, was defeated and killed, with the loſs of 1000 men : on which diſaſter Ageſilaus was recalled, and obliged to relinquiſh all hopes of conquering the  Perſians. His return changed the fortune of the war ſo much, that all the ſtates began to grow weary of a conteſt from which nobody derived any advantage except the king of Perſia. In a ſhort time a treaty was concluded, known in hiſtory by the name of the peace <hi rend="italic">of Antalcidas.</hi> The terms of this treaty were highly diſadvantageous and diſhonourable to the Greeks @@*; for even the Spartans, though ſucceſsful in Greece, had loſt a great battle at ſea with the Perſian fleet under Conon the Athenian, which entirely broke their power in Aſia.</p><p>By the peace of Antalcidas, the government of Boeotia was taken from the Thebans, which they had for a long time enjoyed ; and by this they were ſo much provoked, that at firſt they abſolutely refuſed to accede to the treaty ; but as Ageſilaus made great preparations to invade them, they thought proper at laſt to comply. However, it was not long before a new war commenced, which threatened the total ſubverſion of the Spartan ſtate. As, by the peace of Antalcidas, the king of Perſia had in a manner guaranteed the ſovereignty of Greece to Sparta, this republic very ſoon began to exerciſe its power to the utmoſt extent. The Mantineans were the firſt who felt the weight of their reſentment, although they had been their allies and confederates. In order to have a pretence for making war againſt them, they commanded them to quit their city, and to retire into five old villages which, they ſaid, had ſerved their forefathers, and where they would live in peace themſelves, and give no umbrage to their neighbours. This being refuſed, an army was ſent againſt them to beſiege their city. The ſiege was continued through the ſummer with very little ſucceſs on the part of the Spartans ; but having during the winter ſeaſon dammed up the river on which the city flood, the water roſe to ſuch an height, as either to overflow or throw down the houſes ; which compelled the Mantineans to ſubmit to the terms preſcribed to them, and to retire into the old villages. The Spartan vengeance fell next on the Phliaſians and Olynthians, whom they forced to come into ſuch meaſures as they thought proper. After this they fell on the Thebans ; and, by attempting to ſeize on the Piraeum, drew the Athenians alſo into the quarrel. But here their career was flopped : the Thebans  had been taught the art of war by Chabrias the Athenian ; so that even Ageſilaus himſelf took the command</p><p>of the Spartan army in vain. At ſea they were defeated by Timotheus the ſon of Conon ; and by land the battle of Leuctra put an end to the ſuperiorſty which Sparta had held over Greece for near 500 years. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Leuctra.</hi></p><p>After this dreadful defeat, the Spartans had occaſion to exert all their courage and reſolution. The women and neareſt relations of thoſe who were killed is battle, inſtead of ſpending their time in lamentations, ſhook each other by the hand, while the relations of thoſe who had eſcaped from the battle hid themſelves among the women ; or if they were obliged to go abroad, they appeared in tattered clothes, with their arms folded, and their eyes fixed on the ground. It was a law among the Spartans, that ſuch as fled from battle ſhould be degraded from their honours, ſhould be conſtrained to appear in garments patched with divers colours, to wear their beards half-ſhaved, and to ſuffer any to beat them who pleaſed, without reſiſtance. At preſent, however, this law was diſpenſed with ; and Ageſilaus by his prudent conduct kept up the ſpirits of the people, at the ſame time that by his ſkill in military affairs he checked the progreſs of the enemy. Yet, during the lifetime of Epaminondas the Theban general, the war went on greatly to the diſadvantage of the Spartans; but he being killed at the battle of Mantinea, all parties became quickly deſirous of peace. Ageſilaus did not long ſurvive ; and with him, we may ſay, periſhed the glory of Sparta. Soon after this all the ſtates of Greece fell under the power of Alexander the Great ; and the Spartans, as well as the rest, having become corrupt and loſt their martial ſpirit, became a prey to domeſtic tyrants, and to foreign invaders. They maintained their ground, however, with great reſolution againſt the celebrated Pyrrhus king of Epirus ; whom they repulſed for three days ſucceſſively, though not without aſſiſtance from one of the captains of Antigonus, boon after this one of the kings of Sparta named <hi rend="italic">Agis,</hi> perceiving the univerſal degeneracy that had taken place, made an attempt to reſtore the laws and diſcipline of Lycurgus, by which he ſuppoſed the ſtate would be reſtored to its former glory. But though at firſt he met with ſome appearance of ſucceſs, he was in a ſhort time tried and condemned by the ephori as a traitor to his country. Cleomenes, however, who aſcended the throne in 216 B. C. accompliſhed the reformation which Agis had attempted in vain. He ſuppreſſed the ephori ; cancelled all debts ; divided the lands equally, as they had been in the time of Lycurgus ; and put an end to the luxury which prevailed among the citizens. But at laſt he was overborne by the number of enemies which ſurrounded him ; and being defeated in battle by Antigonus, he fled to Egypt, where he put an end to his own life. With him periſhed every hope of retrieving the affairs of Sparta : the city for the preſent ſell into the hands of Antigonus; after which a ſucceſſion of tyrants took place ; till at laſt all diſturbances were ended by the Romans, who reduced <hi rend="smallcaps">Macedon</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Greece</hi> to provinces of their empire, as has been related under theſe articles.</p><p>It remains now only to ſay ſomething concerning the character, manners, and cuſtoms of the Spartans, which, as they were founded on the laws of Lycurgus, may beſt be learned from a view of theſe laws.</p><p>The inſtitutions of Lycurgus were divided into 12</p><p>@@@[m]* See Persia. n⁰ 37.</p></body></text></TEI>