<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:18:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>and ſome Tartar tribes ſubdued: but these conqueſts were not permanent ; and we hear
                of no further communication between Ruſſia and Siberia till the time of John
                Baſilowitz II. It was opened again at that time by means of one Anika Strogonoſſ, a
                Russian merchant who had eſtabliſhed ſome ſalt-works at a town in the government of
                Archangel. This man carried on a trade with the inhabitants of the north-west parts
                of Siberia, who brought every year to the town above- mentioned large quantities of
                the fineſt furs. Thus he acquired a very conſiderable fortune in a ſhort time ; when
                at laſt the czar, perceiving the advantages which would accrue to his ſubjects from
                having a regular intercourſe with Siberia, determined to enlarge the communication
                which was already opened. With this view he ſent into Siberia a body of troops,
                which croſſed the Yugorian mountains, that form part of the north- eaſtern boundary
                of Europe. They ſeem, however, not to have paſſed the Irtiſh, or to have penetrated
                farther than the weſtern branch of the river Oby. Some Tartar tribes were laid under
                contribution, and a chief named <hi rend="italic">Tediger</hi> conſented to pay an
                annual tribute of 1000 fables. But this produced no laſting advantage to Ruſſia ;
                for, ſoon after, Yediger was defeated and taken priſoner by Kutchum Khan, a
                deſcendant of the great Jenghiz Khan : and thus the allegiance of this country to
                Ruſſia was diſſolved.</p>
            <p>For ſome time we hear of no further attempts made by the Russians on Siberia; but in
                1577 the foundation of a permanent conqueſt was laid by one Yermac Temofeeff, a
                Coſſack of the Don. This man was at firſt the head of a party of banditti who
                infeſted the Ruffians in the province of Caſan ; but being defeated by the troops of
                the czar, he retired with 6000 of his followers into the interior parts of that
                province. Continuing his courſe ſtill eaſtward, he came to Orel, the moſt eaſterly
                of all the Ruffian settlements. Here he took up his winter-quarters : but his
                reſtleſs genius did not ſuffer him to continue for any length of time in a ſtate of
                inactivity ; and from the intelligence he procured concerning the ſituation of the
                neighbouring Tartars of Siberia, he turned his arms towards that quarter.</p>
            <p>Siberia was at that time partly divided among a number of ſeparate princes, and
                partly inhabited by the various tribes of independent Tartars. Of the former Kutchum
                Khan was the moſt powerful ſovereign. His dominions conſiſted of that tract of
                coun</p>
            <p>try which now forms the ſouth-weſtern part of thc province of Tobolſk ; and ſtretched
                from the banks of the Irtiſh and Oby to thoſe of the Tobol and Tura. His principal
                reſidence was at Sibir, a ſmall fortreſs upon the river Irtiſh, not far from the
                preſent town of Tobolſk, and of which ſome ruins are ſtill to be ſeen. After a
                courſe of unremitted fatigue, and a ſeries of victories which almoſt exceed belief,
                but of which we have not room to give the detail, our intrepid adventurer
                diſpoſſeſſed this prince of his dominions, and ſeated himſelf on the throne of
                Sibir. The number of his followers, however, being greatly reduced, and perceiving
                he could not depend on the affection oſ his new ſubjects, he had recourſe to the
                czar of Muſcovy, and made a tender of his new acquiſitions to that monarch, upon
                condition of receiving immediate and effectual ſupport. This propoſal was received
                with the greateſt ſatisfaction by the czar ; who granted him a pardon for all former
                offences, and ſent him the required ſuccours. Yermac, however, being ſoon after
                drowned in an unſucceſsful excursion, the Russians began to lose their footing in
                the country. But freſh reinforcements being ſeaſonably ſent, they not only recovered
                their ground, but puſhed their conqueſts far and wide ; wherever they appeared, the
                Tartars were either reduced or exterminated. New towns were built, and colonies were
                planted on all ſides. Before a century had well elapſed, all that vaſt tract of
                country now called <hi rend="italic">Siberia,</hi> which ſtretches from the confines
                of Europe to the Eaſtern Ocean, and from the Frozen Sea to the preſent frontiers of
                China, was annexed to the Russian dominions.</p>
            <p>The air of Siberia is, in general, extremely piercing, the cold there being more
                ſevere than in any other part of the Ruffian dominions. The Siberian rivers are
                frozen very early, and it is late in the ſpring before the ice is thawed @@<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> If the corn does not ripen in Auguſt, there is little
                hope of a harveſt in this country ; and in the province of Jeniſeiſk it is ſometimes
                covered with ſnow before the peaſants can reap it. To defend the inhabitants againſt
                this extreme ſeverity of the climate, Providence ſeems more liberally to have dealt
                out to them wood for fuel and furs for clothing. As the winter’s day in the north
                parts of Siberia laſt but a few hours, and the ſtorms and flakes of ſnow darken the
                air ſo much, that the inhabitants, even at noon, cannot ſee to do any thing without
                artificial lights, they sleep away the greateſt part of that ſeaſon.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">@@@(a)</hi> M. Gmelin, M. Muller, and two other philoſophers,
                ſet out in the year 1733 to explore the dreary regions of Siberia, by deſire of the
                empreſs Anne of Ruſſia. After ſpending nine years and a half in obſerving every
                thing that was remarkable, they returned to Peterſburgh, ; and an account of this
                journey was publiſhed by M. Gmelin. In order to examine how far the froſt had
                penetrated into the ground, M. Gmelin, on the 18th of June, at a place called
                Jacutia, ordered the earth to be dug in high ground ; they found mould to the depth
                of 11 inches, under which they met with looſe fand to two feet and a half further,
                after which it grew harder, and at half a foot deeper ſo hard as ſcarce to give way
                to the tools ; ſo that the ground ſtill remained unthawed at not leſs than the depth
                of four feet. He made the ſame experiment in a lower ſituation ; the ſoil was 10
                inches deep, after that a looſe sand for two feet and ten inches, below which all
                was frozen and hard. At Jacutia the inhabitants preſerve in cellars ſeveral forts of
                berries, which they reckon among their dainties, perfectly good and freſh the whole
                year, though these cellars are ſcarce a fathom deep. At the fortreſs of Argun, in
                little more than 50 degrees of latitude, the inhabitants relate that, the earth in
                many places is never thawed above a yard and half, and that the internal cold of the
                earth will ſcarce permit a well to be dug, of which they bring an inſtance that
                happened not long before the author’s arrival at that place. They deſigned to ſink a
                well near a houſe at <pb n="453"> </pb>ſome diſtance from the river Argun, for which purpoſe they thawed the earth by
                degrees, and dug ſome fathoms till they had penetrated a fathom and half below the
                level of the river, but found no ſpring. Hence perhaps we may venture to affert,
                that beſides the great elevation of the earth in theſe countries, there is another
                cauſe, perhaps latent in the earth itſelf, of this extraordinary cold, naturally
                ſuggeſted to us by considering the cavity of an old ſilver mine at Argun, which
                being exhauſted of its ore, now ſerves the inhabitants in ſummer time for a cellar
                to keep their proviſions: this place is ſo extremely cold as to preſerve fleſh meats
                from putrefaction in the hotteſt ſummers, and to ſink the mercury in de Liſle’s
                thermometer to 146 and 147. The author travelling from Nerſchoi towards Argun, to
                viſit the works of the ſilver mines in that place, Auguſt 1735, <hi
                    rend="superscript">came</hi> to the river Orkija, near Soloniſchaia, on July the
                1st, from whence he arrived a little before dark at the village of Seventua, diſtant
                from the river 27 leagues. In this journey he and his fellow travellers for more
                than four leagues felt it vaſtly cold ; ſoon after they came into a warm air, which
                continued ſome leagues ; after which the cold returned ; and thus are travellers
                ſubjected to perpetual viciſſitudes of warmth and cold. But it is obſerved, in
                general, that the eaſtern parts are colder than the weitem, though ſituated in the
                same latitude ; for as in thoſe eaſtern regions ſome tracts of land are much colder
                than the rest, their effects muſt be felt by the neighbouring parts. And this
                conjecture is favoured by the thermometrical obſervations made with M. de L’Iſle’s
                inſtrument in all parts of Siberia, in which the mercury was depreſted to the 226th
                degree, even in thoſe parts that lie very much towards the ſouth, as in the
                territory of Selinga, which ſaid degree anſwers in Fahrenheit’s thermometer to about
                <hi rend="italic">55</hi>.5 below 0, but the ſame thermometer ſometimes
                indicated, a much greater cold. At the fort of Kiringa, on Feb. 10. 1738, at 8 in
                the morning, the mercury ſtood at 240, which anſwers nearly to 72 below 0 in
                Fahrenheit’s. On the 23d off the ſame month it was a degree lower. At the ſame
                place, December 11. at three in the afternoon, it ſtood at 254 in De Liſle’s
                thermometer, and very near 90 in Fahrenheit’s ; on December 29. at four in the
                afternoon; at 263 ; on November 27. at noon, at 270 ; January 9. at 275, which
                ſeveral depreſſions anſwer in Fahrenheit’s to 99.44, 107.73, and 113.65; on January
                5. at 5 in the morning, at 262, an hour after at 281, but at eight o’clock it
                returned to 250, and there remained till 6 in the afternoon, and then roſe by
                degrees till an hour before midnight, when it ſtood at 202. So that the greateſt
                depreſſion of the mercury anſwers in Fahrenheit’s thermometer to 120.76 degrees
                below 0, which is indeed very ſurpriſing, and what no body ever imagined before.
                While this cold laſted at Jenisea, the ſparrows and magpies fell to the ground,
                ſtruck dead, as it were, with the froſt, but revived if they were ſoon brought into
                a warm room. The author was told alſo that numbers of wild beaſts were found in the
                woods dead and ſtiff with the froſt, and ſeveral travellers had their blood and
                juices quite frozen in their veſſels. The air itſelf at that time was ſo dismal,
                that you would think it changed to ice, as it was a thick fog, which was not
                diſſipable by any exhalations, as in the ſpring and autumn, and the author could
                ſcarce ſtand three minutes in the porch of his houſe for the cold.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
