<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>St Laurence had ſuffered martyrdom. Such is the origin of the famous eſcurial near Madrid, the royal reſidence of the kings of Spain.</p><p>The firſt account oſ that fatal blow which France had received at St Quintin, was carried to Rome by the courier whom Henry had ſent to recal the duke of Guiſe. Paul remonſtrated warmly againſt the departure of the French army ; but Guiſe’s orders were peremptory. The arrogant pontiff therefore found it neceſſary to accommodate his conduct to the exigency of his affairs, and to employ the mediation of the Venetians, and of Coſmo de Mcdici, in order to obtain peace. The firſt overtures of this nature were eagerly liſtened to by the Catholic king, who ſtill doubted the juſtice of his cauſe, and conſidered it as his greateſt miſfortune to be obliged to contend with the Pope. Paul agreed to renounce his league with France; and Philip ſtipulated on his part, that the duke of Alva ſhould repair in perſon to Rome, and after aſking pardon of the holy father in his own name and in that of his maſter, for having invaded the patrimony of the church, ſhould receive abſolution ſrom that crime. Thus Paul, thro’ the ſuperſtitious timidity of Philip, only finiſhed an unpropitious war not without any detriment to the apoſtolic ſee, but ſaw his conqueror humbled at his feet : and ſo exceſſive was the veneration of the Spaniards in that age for the papal character, that the duke oſ Alva, the proudeſt man perhaps of his time, and accuſtomed from his infancy to converſe with princes, acknowledged, that when he approached Paul, he was ſo much overawed, that his voice failed, and his preſence of mind forſook him.</p><p>But though this war, which at its commencement threatened mighty revolutions, was terminated without occaſioning any alteration in thoſe ſtates which were its immediate object, it produced effects of conſiderable conſequence in other parts of Italy. In order to detach Octavio Farneſe, duke of Parma, from the French intereſt, Philip reſtored to him the city of Placentia and its territory, which had been ſeized by Charles V. and he granted to Coſmo de Medici the inveſtiture of Sienna, as an equivalent for the ſums due to him. By theſe treaties, the balance of power among the Italian ſtates was poiſed with more equality, and rendered leſs variable than it had been ſince it received the firſt violent ſhock from the invaſion of Charles VIII. and Italy henceforth ceaſed to be the theatre on which the monarchs of Spain, France, and Germany, contended for fame and dominion. Their hoſtilities, excited by new objects, ſtained other regions of Europe with blood, and made other ſtates feel, in their turn, the miſeries of war.</p><p>The duke of Guiſe, who left Rome the ſame day that his adverſary the duke of Alva made his humiliating ſubmiſſion to the Pope, was received in France as the guardian angel of the kingdom. He was appointed lieutenant-general in chief, with a juriſdiction almoſt unlimited ; and, eager to juſtify the extraordinary confidence which the king had repoſed in him, as well as to perform ſomething ſuitable to the high expectations of his countrymen, he undertook in winter the siege of Calais. Having taken that place, he next inveſted Thionville in the duchy of Luxembourg, one oſ the ſtrongeſt towns on the frontiers of the Netherlands; and forced it to capitulate after a ſiege of three weeks. But</p><p>the advantages on this quarter were more than balanced by an event which happened in another part of the Low Countries. The mareſchal de Termes governor of Calais, who had penetrated into Flanders and taken Dunkirk, was totally routed near Gravelines, and taken priſoner by count Egmont. This diſaſter obliged the duke of Guiſe to relinquiſh all his other ſchemes, and halten towards the frontiers of Picardy, that he might there oppoſe the progreſs of the enemy.</p><p>The eyes of all France were now turned towards the duke of Guiſe, as the only general on whoſe arms victory always attended, and in whoſe conduct as well as good fortune they could confide in every danger. His ſtrength was nearly equal to the duke of Savoy’s, each commanding about 40,000 men. They encamped at the diſtance of a few leagues from one another; and the French and Spaniſh monarchs having joined their reſpective armies, it was expected that, after the viciſſitudes of war, a deciſive battle would at laſt determine which of the rivals ſhould take the aſcendant for the future in the affairs of Europe. But both monarchs, as if by agreement, ſtood on the defenſive ; neither of them diſcovering any inclination, though each had it in his power, to reſt the deciſion of a point oſ ſuch importance on the iſſue of a ſingle battle.</p><p>During this ſtate of inaction, peace began to be mentioned in each camp, and both Henry and Philip diſcovered an equal diſpoſition to liſten to any overture that tended to re-eſtabliſh it. The private inclinations oſ both kings concurred with their political intereſts and the wiſhes of their people. Philip languiſhed to return to Spain, the place of his nativity ; and peace only could enable him, either with decency or ſafety, to quit the Low Countries. Henry was now deſirous of being freed from the avocations of war, that he might have leiſure to turn the whole force of his government towards ſuppreſſing the opinions of the reformers, which were ſpreading with ſuch rapidity in Paris and the other great towns, that they began to grow formidable to the eſtabliſhed church. Court-intrigues conlpired with theſe public and avowed motives to hasten the negotiation, and the abbey of Cercamp was fixed on as the place of congreſs.	</p><p>While Philip and Henry were making theſe advances towards a treaty which reſtored tranquillity to Europe, Charles V. whoſe ambition had ſo long diſturbed it, but who had been for ſome time dead to the world, ended his days in the monaſtery of St Juſtus in Eſtremadura, which he had choſen as the place of his retreat, as is particularly related Under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> V.</p><p>Aſter the death of Charles, the kingdom of Spain ſoon loſt great part of its conſequence. Though Charles had uſed all his intereſt to get his ſon Philip elected emperor of Germany, he had been totally diſappointed ; and thus the grandeur of Philip II. never equalled that of his father. His dominions were alſo considerably abridged by his tyrannical behaviour in the Netherlands. In conſequence of this, the United Provinces revolted; and after along and bloody war obtained their liberty@@*. In this quarrel Elizabeth of England took part againſt Philip, which brought on a war with Spain. The great loſſes he ſuſtained in theſe wars exhauſted the kingdom both of men and money, notwithſtanding the great ſums imported from America. Indeed, the diſcovery and conqueſt of that country hath much impoveriſhed, in-</p><p>@@@[m]* See United Provinces.</p></body></text></TEI>