<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and unknown place, as in one with which they are acquainted.</p><p>“ They likewiſe recommend to ſuch as would confirm or invalidate the above obſervations, to make all their experiments in the dark ; becauſe it has been hitherto ſuppoſed that the eyes of ſleep-walkers are oſ no uſe to them.”</p><p>SLEEPERS, in natural hiſtory, a name given to thoſe animals which sleep all winter ; ſuch as bears, marmots, dormice, bats, hedgehogs, ſwallows, &amp;c. Theſe do not feed in winter, have no ſenſible evacuations, breathe little or none at all, and moſt of the viſcera ceaſe from their functions. Some of theſe creatures ſeem to be dead, and others return to a ſtate like that of the fœtus before birth : in this ſtate they continue, till by new heat the fluids are attenuated, the animal is reſtored to life, and the functions begin where they left off.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sleepers,</hi> in a ſhip, timbers lying before and aft in the bottom of the ſhip, as the rungheads do : the lowermoſt of them is bolted to the rungheads, and the uppermoſt to the futtocks and rungs.</p><p>SLEIDAN (John), an excellent German hiſtorian, born of obſcure parents, in 1506, at Sleidan, a ſmall town on the confines of the duchy of Juliers. After ſtudying ſome time in his own country, together with his townſman the Earned John Sturmius, he went to France, and in 1535 entered into the ſervice of the cardinal and archbiſhop John du Bellay. He retired to Straſburg in 1542, where he acquired the eſteem and friendſhip of the moſt conſiderable perſons, particularly of James Sturmius ; by whoſe advice and assiſtance he was enabled to write the hiſtory of his own time. He was employed in ſome public negociations ; but the death of his wife, in 1555, plunged him into ſo deep a melancholy, that he lost his memory entirely, and died the year following. In 1555 came out, in folio, <hi rend="italic">De statu Religionis et Reipublicœ sub Carola Quintο, &amp;c. </hi>in 25 books ; from the year 1517, when Luther began to preach, to the year of its publication; which hiſtory was preſently tranſiated into moſt of the languages of Europe. Beſides this great work, he wrote, <hi rend="italic">De quatitur ſummis Imperiis, libri tres ;</hi> with ſome other hiſtorical and political pieces.</p><p>SLEIGHT <hi rend="italic">of </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Hand.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Legerdemain.</hi></p><p>SLEUT-HOUNDE, the ancient Scots name of the blood-hound. The word is from the Saxon sl<hi rend="italic">ot,</hi> “ the impreſſion that a deer leaves of its foot in the mire,” and <hi rend="italic">hound</hi> “ a dog” ; ſo they derive their name from following the track. See the article <hi rend="italic">BLOOD-Hound.</hi></p><p>SLESWICK, an ancient and conſiderable town of Denmark, and capital of a duchy of the ſame name in the province of Gottorp, with a biſhop’s ſee, ſecularized in 1586. Cloſe to it is the old palace of Gottorp, formerly the ducal residence, but at preſent inhabited by the ſtadtholder or governor. This town was once much more conſiderable than it is at preſent, having ſuffered greatly by the wars of Germany. It is ſeated on the gulph of Sley, where there is a good harbour, 60 miles north-west of Lubeck, and 125 ſouth-weſt of Copenhagen. E. Long. 10. 0. N. Lat. 54. 40.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sleswick,</hi> the duchy of, or <hi rend="italic">South Jutland,</hi> is about 100 miles in length and 60 in breadth. It is bounded on the north by North Jutland, on the eaſt by the Baltic Sea, on the ſouth by Holſtein, and on the weſt by</p><p>the ocean. It contains 14 cities, 17 towns, 13 caſtſes, 278 pariſhee, 1480 villages, 162 farms, 116 water mills, and 106 gentlemens ſeats. It is a pleaſant, fertile, populous country, and a ſovereign duchy. Formerly the king of Denmark had half of it, and the other belonged to the houſe of Holſtein-Gottorp ; but the former having conquered this duchy, had the poſſeſſion of it confirmed to him by the treaty of the north in 1720. In 1731, a prince of Bareith-Culmbach was made governor of this duchy, who reſides at Gottorp.</p><p>SLICH, in metallurgy, the ore of any metal, particularly of gold, when it has been pounded, and prepared for farther working.</p><p>The manner of preparing the slich at Chremnitz in Hungary is this ; they lay a foundation of wood three yards deep, upon this they place the ore, and over this there are 24 beams, armed at their bottoms with iron ; theſe, by a continual motion, beat and grind the ore, till it is reduced to powder : during this operation, the ore is covered with water. There are four wheels uſed to move theſe beams, each wheel moving six ; and the water, as it runs off, carrying ſome of the metalline particles with it, is received into ſeveral baſons, one placed behind another ; and finally, after having paſſed through them all, and depoſited ſome ſediment in each, it is let off into a very large pit, almoſt half an acre in extent ; in which it is ſuſſered to ſtand ſo long, as to depoſit all its ſediment, of whatever kind, and after this it is let out. This work is carried on day and night, and the ore taken away and replaced by more as often as occaſion requires. That ore which lies next the beams, by which it was pounded, is always the cleaneſt or richeſt.</p><p>When the slich is waſhed as much as they can, a hundred weight of it uſually contains about an ounce, or perhaps but half an ounce of metal, which is not all gold ; for there is always a mixture of gold and ſilver, but the gold is in the largeſt quantity, and uſually is two-thirds of the mixture : they then put the slich into a furnace with ſome limeſtone, and ſlacken, or the ſcoria of former meltings, and run them together. The firſt melting produces a ſubſtance called <hi rend="italic">lech ;</hi> this lech they burn with charcoal, to make it lighter, to open its body, and render it porous, after which it is called <hi rend="italic">rost; </hi>to this roſt they add sand in ſuch quantity as they find neceſſary, and then melt it over again.</p><p>At Chremnitz they have many other ways of reducing gold out of its ore, but particularly one, in which they employ no lead during the whole operation ; whereas, in general, lead is always neceſſary, after the before mentioned proceſſes. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Gold.</hi></p><p>SLIDING <hi rend="smallcaps">rule,</hi> a mathematical inſtrument, ſerving to work queſtions in gauging, meaſuring, &amp;c. without the uſe of compaſſes ; merely by the sliding of the parts of the inſtrument one by another, the lines and diviſions whereof give the anſwer by inspection.</p><p>This inſtrument is variously contrived, and applied by various authors, particularly Everard, Coggeſhall, Gunter, Hunt, and Partridge ; but the moſt common and uſeful are thoſe of Everard and Coggeſhall.</p><p>SLIGO, a county, in the province of Connaught, Ireland, 25 miles in length, and as much in breadth ; bounded on the eaſt by that of Leitrim, on the weſt by the county of Mayo, on the north and north weſt bv the weſtern ocean, and on the ſouth and ſouth-weſt</p></body></text></TEI>