<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:10Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>key, with a very round head : about the ears two very long full tufts of white hairs ſtanding out on each side: irides reddiſh : face a ſwarthy fleſh colour : ears like the human : head black : body ash coloured, reddiſh, and duſky ; the laſt forms ſtriated bars croſs the body : tail full of hair, annulated with aſh colour and black : body ſeven inches long ; tail near eleven : hands and feet covered with ſhort hairs : fingers like thoſe of a ſquirrel : nails, or rather claws, ſharp. Inhabits Braſil : feeds on vegetables ; will alio eat fiſh: makes a weak noiſe : very reſtleſs : often brought over to Europe.</p><p>37.	Pinche, ſagoinus oedipus, or red-tailed monkey, is beardleſs ; has a flowing head of hair, which hangs down on each side ; a red tail and ſharp claws. It has neither cheek-pouches nor calloſities on the buttocks. His tail is not prehenſile, and is more than twice the length of the head and body. The partition of the noſtrils is thick, and the apertures are placed at a side. The face, throat, and ears are black ; on the head are long white hairs. The muzzle is broad, and the face round. The hair on the body is pretty long; of a yellowish brown or reddiſh colour till near the tail, where it becomes orange; on the breaſt, belly, hands, and feet, it is white, and ſhorter than on the body. The tail, ſrom the origin to one-half of its length, is a vivid red, then browniſh red, and toward the point it is black. He is about nine inches in length, and walks on four feet. The females are not ſubject to the menſtrual evacuation.</p><p>38.	The marikina, ſagoinus roſalius, or ſilky monkey, is beardleſs ; has a very hairy head : the circumference of the face and the feet are red ; and the claws are ſharp and narrow. It inhabits South America. A briſk animal, leſs impatient of cold than the rest of this race : the body is of a yellowiſh white colour ; the nails on the thumbs and great toes are rounded ; the ears are naked, but are hidden beneath the fur : It has a round head, and a brown face, which is ſurrounded with a kind of mane of a bright red colour ; the hair on the body and tail is long, ſilky, and of a pale but vivid yellow colour, almoſt white, with a conſiderable tuft at the extremity of the tail. It walks on four feet, and is eight or nine inches in length, ſrom the muzzle to the rump ; and the tail is above 13 inches long. This ſpecies has the ſame manners and vivacity with the other ſagoins, but is more robuſt in conſtitution, as an individual lived five or six years in Paris, being kept in a warm room during winter.</p><p>39.	The mico, ſagoinus argenteus, or fair monkey, with a ſmall round head : face and ears of the moſt lively vermilion colour : body covered with moſt beautiful long hairs of a bright and silvery whiteneſs, of matchleſs elegance : tail of a ſhining dark cheſnut : head and body eight inches long; tail 12. Inhabits the banks of the Amazons ; diſcovered by M. de Condamine.</p><p>40.	The tamarin, ſagoinus Midas, or great-eared monkey, with a round head, ſwarthy, fleſh coloured, naked face : upper lip a little divided : ears very large, erect, naked, and almoſt ſquare : hair on the forehead upright and long ; on the body ſoft, but ſhaggy : the head, whole body, and upper part of the limbs black, except the lower part of the back, which is tinged with yellow : hands and feet covered with orange-coloured hairs, very fine and ſmooth ; nails long and</p><p>crooked : tad black, and twice the length of the body: teeth very white. It is of the ſize of a ſquirrel it inhabits the hotter parts of South America, and the iſle of Gorgona, ſouth of Panama, in the South Sea. There are, ſays Dampier, a great many little black monkeys ; at low-water they come to the ſea-side to take muscles and perriwinkles, which they dig out of the ſhells with their claws.</p><p>Besides theſe which we have deſcribed, there are a great many ſpecies which we have omitted. Thoſe who wish to be better acquainted with the simiae, may conſult Buffon, Pennant, and Gmelin’s edition of the Zoology of Linnæus by Mr Ker.</p><p>SIMILE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Similitude,</hi> in rhetoric, a compariſon of two things, which though different in other reſpects, yet agree in ſome one. The difference between a ſimile and compariſon is ſaid to conſiſt in this, that the ſimile properly belongs to whatever we call the quality of a thing, and the compariſon to the quantity. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Comparison</hi> ; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Oratory,</hi> n⁰ 118.</p><p>SIMILOR, a name given to an alloy of red copper and zinc, made in the beſt proportions, to imitate silver and gold.</p><p>SIMON <hi rend="smallcaps">Maccabeus,</hi> a celebrated leader and high- prieſt of the Jews, who, after rendering the moſt important ſervices to his country, was at laſt treacherouſly ſlain by his ſon-in-law. See <hi rend="italic">the Hiſlory oſ the Jews, n⁰</hi> 15.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Simon</hi><hi rend="italic"> Magus,</hi> or the Sorcerer, was a native of Gitton, a village of Samaria. According to the usual practice of the Aſiatics of that age, he visited Egypt, and there probably became acquainted with the ſublime myſteries taught in the Alexandrian ſchool, and learned thoſe theurgic or magical operations by means of which it was believed that men might be delivered from the power of evil demons. Upon his return into his own country, the author of the Clementine Recognitions relates, that he impoſed upon his countrymen by high pretenſions to ſupernatural powers. And St Luke atteſts, that this artful fanatic, uſing ſorcery, had bewitched the people of Samaria, giving out that he was <hi rend="italic">ſome great one;</hi> and that he obtained ſuch general attention and reverence in Samaria, that the people all gave heed to him from the leaſt to the greateſt, saying, “ This man is the great power oſ God.”'</p><p>By the preaching of Philip the Deacon, he was with other Samaritans converted to the Chriſtian faith, and admitted into the infant church by the ordinance of baptiſm. His conversion, however, ſeems not to have been real ; for, upon seeing the miraculous effects of the laying on of the apoſtle’s hands, he offered them money, saying, “ Give me also this power, that on whom- ſoever I lay hands he may receive the Holy Ghoſt.” He probably thought Peter and John magicians like himſelf, but better ſkilled in the art of deceiving the multitude.</p><p>Being ſharply reproved for this impiety, he ſeems by his anſwer to have been made ſenſible of his sin ; but his repentance, <hi rend="italic">if</hi> sincere, was oſ ſhort duration. Returning to his former practices of impoſture, he travelled through various provinces of the empire, oppoſing the progreſs of the goſpel ; and arriving at Rome, he led astray vaſt numbers of people by his pretended miracles. How long he lived in that metropolis of the world, or in what manner he died, we have no accounts</p></body></text></TEI>