<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:42Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>which would inſure to him for ſo conſiderable a period the important conqueſt which he had made on the German frontier, together with the greater part of the duke of Savoy’s dominions.</p><p>The Pope, when informed of this tranſaction, was no leſs filled with terror and aſtoniſhment than rage and indignation. But he took equal care to conceal his fear and his anger. He affected to approve highly of the truce; and he offered his mediation, as the common father of Chriſtendom, in order to bring about a definitive peace. Under this pretext, he appointed cardinal Rebibo his nuncio to the court of Bruſſels, and his nephew cardinal Caraſſa to that of Paris. The public instructions of both were the ſame ; but Caraſſa, beſides theſe, received a private cornmiſſion, to ſpare neither intreaties, promiſes, nor bribes, in order to induce the French monarch to renounce the truce and renew his engagements with the holy ſee. He flattered Henry with the conqueſt of Naples ; he gained by his addreſs the Guiſes, the queen, and even the famous Diana of Poictiers, ducheſs of Valentinois, the king’s miſtrels ; and they easily ſwayed the king himſelf, who already leaned to that ſide towards which they wiſhed to incline him. All Montmorency’s prudent remonſtrances were diſregarded ; the nuncio (by powers from Rome) abſolved Henry from his oath of truce ; and that weak prince ſigned a new treaty with the Pope ; which rekindled with freſh violence the flames oſ war, both in Italy and the Low Countries.</p><p>No ſooner was Paul made acquainted with the ſucceſs of this negotiation than he proceeded to the moſt indecent extremities againſt Philip. He ordered the Spaniſh ambaſſador to be impriſoned ; he excommunicated the Colonnas, becauſe of their attachment to the imperial houſe ; and he conſidered Philip as guilty of high treaſon, and to have forfeited his right to the kingdom of Naples, which he was ſuppoſed to hold of the holy ſee, for afterward affording them a retreat in his dominions.</p><p>Alarmed at a quarrel with the Pope, whom he had been taught to regard with the moſt ſuperſtitious veneration, as the vicegerent of Chriſt and the common father of Chriſtendom, Philip tried every gentle method before he made uſe of force. He even conſulted ſome Spaniſh divines on the lawfulneſs of taking arms againſt a perſon ſo ſacred. They decided in his favour ; and Paul continuing inexorable, the duke of Alva, to whom the negotiations as well as the war had been committed, entered the ecclesiaſtical ſtate at the head of 10,000 veterans, and carried terror to the gates of Rome.</p><p>The haughty pontiff, though ſtill inflexible and undaunted in himſelf, was forced to give way to the tears of the cardinals, and a truce was concluded for 40 days. Mean time the duke of Guiſe arriving with a ſupply of 20,000 French troops, Paul became more arrogant than ever, and baniſhed all thoughts from his mind but thoſe of war and revenge. The duke of Guiſe, however, who had precipitated his country into this war, chiefly from a deſire of gaining a field where he might diſplay his own talents, was able to perform nothing in Italy worthy of his former fame. He was obliged to abandon the ſiege of Civetella ; he could not bring the duke of Alva so a general engagement ; his army periſhed by diſeaſes ; and the Pope neglected to furniſh the neceſ</p><p>ſary reinforcements. He begged to be recalled ; and France ſtood in need of his abilities.</p><p>Philip, though willing to have avoided a rupture, was no ſooner informed that Henry had violated the truce of Vaucelles, than he determined to act with ſuch vigour, as ſhould convince Europe that his father had not erred in religning to him the reigns of government. He immediately assembled in the Low Countries a body of 50,000 men, and obtained a ſupply of 10,000 from England, which he had engaged in his quarrel ; and as he was not ambitious of military fame, he gave the command of his army to Emanuel Philibert duke of Savoy, one of the greateſt generals of that warlike age.</p><p>The duke of Savoy kept the enemy for ſome time in ſuſpenſe with regard to his deſtination ; at laſt he ſeemed to threaten Champagne; towards which the French drew all their troops ; then turning ſuddenly to the right, he advanced by rapid marches into Picardy, and laid ſiege to St Quintin. It was deemed in thoſe times a town of conſiderable ſtrength ; but the fortifications had been much neglected, and the garriſon did not amount to a fifth part of the number requisite ſor its defence : it muſt therefore have ſurrendered in a few days, if the admiral de Coligny had not taken the gallant reſolution of throwing himſelf into it with ſuch a body of men as could he collected on a ſudden. This he effected in ſpite of the enemy, breaking through their main body. The place, however, was cloſely inveſted; and the conſtable Montmorency, anxious to extricate his nephew out of that perilous ſituation, in which his zeal for the public had engaged him, as well as to ſave a town of ſuch importance, raſhly advanced to its relief with forces one half inferior to thoſe oſ the enemy. His army was cut in pieces, and he himſelf made priſoner.</p><p>The cautious temper of Philip on this occaſion ſaved France ſrom devaſtation, if not ruin. The duke of Savoy propoſed to overlook all inferior objects, and march ſpeedily to Paris, which, in its preſent conſternation, he could not have failed to make himſelf maſter of ; but Philip, afraid of the conſequences of ſuch a bold enterpriſe, deſired him to continue the ſiege of St Quintin, in order to ſecure a ſaſe retreat in caſe of any diſaſtrous event. The town, long and gallantly defended by Coligny, was at laſt taken by storm ; but not till France was in a ſtate of defence.</p><p>Philip was now ſensible that he had loſt an opportunity which could never be recalled, of diſtreſſing his enemy, and contented himſelf with reducing Horn and Catelet ; which petty towns, together with St Quintſh, were the ſole fruits of one of the moſt decisive victories gained in the 16th century. The Catholic king, however, continued in high exultation on account of his ſucceſs ; and as all his paſſions were tinged with superſtition, he vowed to build a church, a monaſtery, and a palace, in honour oſ St Laurence, on the day ſacred to whoſe memory the battle of St Quintin had been fought. He accordingly laid the foundation of an edifice, in which all theſe were included, and which he continued to forward at vaſt expence, for <hi rend="italic">22</hi> years. The ſame principle which dictated the vow directed the building. It was ſo formed as to reſemble a gridiron —on which culinary inſtrument, according to the legendary tale,</p></body></text></TEI>