<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:05Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>beſt edition of Sozomcnus is that of Robert Stephen in 1544. He has been tranſlated
                and publiſhed by Valeſius, and republiſhed with additional notes by Reading at
                London, 1720, in 3 vols folio.</p>
            <p>SPA, a town of Germany, in the circle of Weſtphaha and biſhopric of Liege, famous for
                its mineral waters, lies in E. Long. 5. 50. N. Lat. 50. 30. about 21 miles
                ſouth-eaſt from Liege, and 7 ſouth-weſt from Lomburg. It is ſituated at one end of a
                deep valley oh the banks of a ſmall rivulet, and is ſurrounded on all ſides by high
                mountains. The ſides of theſe mountains next to Spa are rude and uncultivated,
                preſenting a rugged appearance as if ſhattered by the convulſions of earthquakes ;
                but as they are ſtrewed with tall oaks and abundance of ſhrubs, the country around
                forms a wild, romantic, and beautiful landſcape. The acceſs to the town is very
                beautiful. The road winds over the mountains till it deſcends to their bottom, when
                it runs along a ſmooth valley for a mile or a mile and a hall.</p>
            <p>The town conſiſts of four ſtreets in form of a croſs, and contains about 400
                inhabitants. Spa has no wealth to boaſt of. If can ſcarcely furniſh the neceſſaries
                of life to its own inhabitants during the winter, and almoſt all the luxuries which
                are requiſite for the great concourſe of affluent viſitors during the ſummer are
                carried from Liege by women. Its only ſource of wealth is its mineral waters. No
                ſooner does the warm ſeaſon commence, than crowds of valetudinarians arrive, as well
                as many other perſons who are attracted ſolely by the love of amuſement, and ſome
                from leſs honourable motives. The inhabitants, who ſpend ſeven or eight months of
                the year without seeing the face of a ſtranger, wait for the return of this period
                with impatience. The welcome sound of the carriages brings multitudes from the town,
                either to gratify their curioſity, or to offer their ſervices in the hopes of
                ſecuring your employment while you remain at Spa. Immediately after your arrival
                your name and deſignation is added to the printed list of the annual viſitors ; for
                which you pay a ſtated ſum to the bookſeller, who has a patent for this purpoſe from
                the prince biſhop of Liege. This list not only enables one to know at a glance
                whether any friends or acquaintance are reſiding there, but alſo to diſtinguiſh
                perſons of rank and faſhion from adventurers, who ſeldom have the effrontery to
                inſert their names.</p>
            <p>There are two different ways of accommodating the viſitors at Spa with lodging and
                neceſſaries. People may either lodge at an hotel, where every thing is furniſhed
                them in a ſplendid and expenſive ſtyle ; or they</p>
            <p>may take up their reſidence in private lodgings, from which they may ſend for
                proviſions to a cook’s shop.</p>
            <p>Among the people who viſit Spa, there are many perſons of the firſt rank and faſhion
                in Europe. Perhaps indeed there is no place in Europe to which so many kings and
                princes resort ; but it is alſo viſited by many ſelf-created nobility, who, under
                the titles of counts, barons, marquiſes, and knights, contrive by their addreſs and
                artifices, to prey upon the rich and unexperienced.</p>
            <p>T'he manners eſtabliſhed at Spa are conducive both to health and amuſement. Every
                body riſes early in the morning, at six o’clock or before it, when a great many
                horſes ſtand ready ſaddled for thoſe who chooſe to drink the Sauveniere or
                Geronſtere waters at a little diſtance from Spa. After this healthy exerciſe a part
                of the company generally breakfaſt together at Vaux- hall, a magnificent and
                ſpacious building. At this place a number of card-tables are opened every forenoon,
                round which many persons assemble and play for stakes to a very conſiderable amount.
                A ball too is generally held once a week at Vauxhall, beſides two balls at the
                aſſembly rooms near the Pouhon in the middle of the town.</p>
            <p>The moſt remarkable waters at Spa are, 1. The Pou- hon, ſituated in the middle of the
                town ; 2. The Sauveniere, a mile and a half eaſt from it ; 3. Groiſheck, near to the
                Sauveniere; 4. Tonnelet, ſituated a little to the left of the road which leads to
                the Sauveniere ; 5. Geronſtere, two miles ſouth from Spa; 6. War- troz, near to the
                Tonnelet; 7. Sarts or Niveſet, in the diſtrict of Sarts ; 8. Chevron or Bru, in the
                principality of Slavelot ; 9. Couve; 10. Beverſe; 11. Sige; 12. Geremont. Theſe four
                laſt are near Malmedy.</p>
            <p>Dr Brownrigg was the firſt perſon who diſcovered that fixed air, or, as it is now
                generally called, <hi rend="italic">carbonic acid gas,</hi> forms a principal
                ingredient in the compoſition of the Spa waters, and actually ſeparated a quantity
                of this elaſtic fluid, by expoſing it to different degrees of heat from 110⁰ to 170⁰
                of Fahrenheit. From 20 ounces 7 drams and 14 grains apothecaries weight of the
                Pouhon water, he obtained 8 ounces 2 drams and 50 grains. Since June 1765, when Dr
                Brownrigg read a paper on this ſubject before thc Royal Society of London, the
                waters of Spa have been often analyſed, but perhaps by none with more accuracy than
                by Dr Aſh, who publiſhed a book on the chemical and medicinal properties of theſe
                waters in 1788. We ſhall preſent his analyſis of the five principal ſprings in the
                following tables</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Fountains.</cell>
                    <cell>Quantity of Water.</cell>
                    <cell>Ounce meaſures of Gas.</cell>
                    <cell>Solid contents.</cell>
                    <cell>Aerated Lime.</cell>
                    <cell>Aerated Magnesia</cell>
                    <cell>Aerated Mineral Alkali.</cell>
                    <cell>Aerated Iron.</cell>
                    <cell>Selenite.</cell>
                    <cell>Aerated Vegerab. Alkali.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Ounces.</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                    <cell>Grains.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Pouhon</cell>
                    <cell>33</cell>
                    <cell>35∙75</cell>
                    <cell>16.25</cell>
                    <cell>2.75</cell>
                    <cell>9.50</cell>
                    <cell>2.25</cell>
                    <cell>1.75</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell> </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Geronſtere</cell>
                    <cell>32.75</cell>
                    <cell>24.75</cell>
                    <cell>5.50</cell>
                    <cell>2.50</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>1∙75</cell>
                    <cell>0.75</cell>
                    <cell>0.50</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Sauveniere</cell>
                    <cell>32.50</cell>
                    <cell>33.50</cell>
                    <cell>3∙75</cell>
                    <cell>1.50</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>0.75</cell>
                    <cell>0.50</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>I.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Groisbeck</cell>
                    <cell>32.25</cell>
                    <cell>35.5O</cell>
                    <cell>5.25</cell>
                    <cell>1.50</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>I.</cell>
                    <cell>0.75</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Tonnelet</cell>
                    <cell>32.</cell>
                    <cell>40.75</cell>
                    <cell>2.00</cell>
                    <cell>0.25</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>0.75</cell>
                    <cell>I.</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                    <cell>—</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
