<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>to communicate to them the diſcoveries he had made in his travels. The latter he found at home, but the former had retired to Essex ; to which place Mr Sloane tranſmitted a great variety of plants and ſeeds, which Mr Ray has deſcribed in his Hiſtory of Plants, and for which he makes a proper acknowledgment.</p><p>About the year 1706 our author became acquainted with the celebrated Sydenham ; who ſoon contracted ſo warm an affection for him that he took him into his houſe, and recommended him in the ſtrongeſt manner to his patients. He had not been long in London before he was propoſed by Dr Martin Lister as a candidate to be admitted a member of the Royal Society, on the 26th of November 1684 ; and being approved, he was elected on the 21st of January following.</p><p>In 1685 he communicated ſome curioſities to the Society ; and in July the ſame year he was a candidate for the office of their aſſiſtant ſecretary, but without ſucceſs, as he was obliged to give way to the ſuperior intereſt of his competitor Dr Halley. On the 12th of April 1687, he was choſen a fellow of the college of phyſicians in London ; and the ſame year his friend and fellow traveller Dr Tancred Robinſon, having mentioned to the Society the plant called the sta<hi rend="italic">r of the earth, </hi>as a remedy newly diſcovered for the bite of a mad dog, Dr Sloane acquainted them that this virtue of the plant was to be found in a book called <hi rend="italic">De Grey’s Farriery ; </hi>and that he knew a man who had cured with it twenty couple oſ dogs. This obſervation he made on the 13th of July, and on the 12th of September following he embarked at Portſmouth for Jamaica with the duke of Albemarle, who had been appointed governor of that iſland. The doctor attended his grace in quality of phyſician, and arrived at Jamaica on the 19th of December following.</p><p>Here a new field was opened for freſh diſcoverſes in natural productions ; but the world would have been deprived of the fruits of them, had not our author, by incredible application, converted, as we may say, his minutes into hours. The duke of Albemarle died ſoon after he landed, and the ducheſs determined to return to England whenever an anſwer ſhould be received to the letter ſhe had ſent to court on that melancholy occaſion. As Dr Sloane could not think oſ leaving her grace in her diſtreſs, whilſt the reſt of her retinue were preparing for their departure he improved it in making collections of natural curioſities ; ſo that though his whole ſtay at Jamaica was not above fifteen months, he brought together ſuch a prodigious number of plants, that on his return to England Mr Ray was aſtoniſhed that one man could procure in one iſland, and in ſo ſhort a ſpace, ſo vaſt a variety.</p><p>On his arrival in London he applied himſelf to the practice of his profeſſion ; and ſoon became ſo eminent, that he was choſen phyſician to Christ’s Hoſpital on the 17th of October 1694 : and this office he held till the year 1730, when, on account of his great age and infirmities, he found it necessary to reſign. It is ſomewhat ſingular, and redounds much to the Doctor’s honour, that though he received the emoluments of his office punctually, becauſe he would not lay down a precedent which might hurt his ſucceſſors, yet he conſtantly applied the money to the relief of thoſe who were the greateſt objects of compaſſion in the hoſpital, that it might never be ſaid he enriched himſelf by giving</p><p>health to the poor. He had been elected ſecretary to the Royal Society on the 30 th of November 1693 ; and upon this occaſion he revived the publication of the Philoſophſeal Tranſactions, which had been omitted for ſome time. He continued to be the editor of this work till the year 1712; and the volumes which appeared during that period are monuments of his induſtry and ingenuity, many of the pieces contained in them being written by himſelf.</p><p>In the mean time he publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Catalogus Plantarum quae in Inſula Jamaica ſponte proveniunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">Seu Prodromi Historia Naturalis pars prima,</hi> which he dedicated to the Royal Society and College of Phyſicians. About the ſame time he formed the plan of a diſpenſary, where the poor might be furniſhed at prime coſt with ſuch medicines as their ſeveral maladies might require ; which he afterwards carried into execution, with the aſſiſtance of the preſident and other members of the college of phyſicians.</p><p>Our author’s thirſt for natural knowledge ſeems to have been born with him, ſo that his cabinet of curioſities may be ſaid to have commenced with his being. He was continually enriching and enlarging it ; and the fame which, in the courſe of a few years, it had acquired, brought every thing that was curious in art or nature to be firſt offered to him for purchaſe. Theſe acquiſitions, however, increaſed it but very ſlowly in compariſon of the augmentation it received in 1701 by the death of William Courten, Eſq; a gentleman who had employed all his time, and the greater part of his fortune, in collecting rarities, and who bequeathed the whole to Dr Sloane, on condition of his paying certain debts and legacies with which he had charged it. Theſe terms our author accepted, and he executed the will of the donor with the moſt ſcrupulous exactneſs ; on which account ſome people have ſaid, that he purchaſed Mr Courten’s curioſities at a dear rate.</p><p>In 1707 the firſt volume of Dr Sloane’s Natural Hiſtory of Jamaica appeared in folio, though the publication of the ſecond was delayed till 1725. By this very uſeful as well as magnificent work the materia medica was enriched with a great number of excellent drugs not before known. In 1708 the Doctor was elected a foreign member of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, in the room of Mr Tſchirnaus ; an honour ſo much the greater, as we were then at war with France, and the queen’s expreſs conſent was neceſſary before he could accept it. In proportion as his credit roſe among the learned, his practice increaſed among the people of rank : Queen Anne herſelf frequently conſulted him, and in her laſt illneſs was blooded by him.</p><p>On the advancement of George I to the throne, that prince, on the 3d of April 1716, created the Doctor a baronet, an hereditary title of honour to which no Engliſh phyſician had before attained ; and at the ſame time made him phyſician general to the army, in which ſtation he continued till 1727, when he was appointed phyſician in ordinary to George II. He attended the royal family till his death ; and was particularly favoured by Queen Caroline, who placed the greateſt confidence in his preſcriptions. In the mean time he had been unanimonſly choſen one of the elects of the college of phyſicians June 1. 1716, and he was elected preſident of the ſame body on September 30. 1719, an office which he held for ſixteen years. Du-</p></body></text></TEI>