<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:47Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the moſt conſiderable are the Ebro, formerly I<hi rend="italic">berus, </hi>Guadalavier, anciently <hi rend="italic">Turia,</hi> Guadalquiver or <hi rend="italic">Bcetis, </hi>Segura, and Xucar.</p><p>The Spaniards are zealous Romaniſts. Nowhere is there more pomp, farce, and parade, in what regards religion ; and nowhere leſs true Chriſtianity. Their zeal and their ſuperſtition exceed that of any other Roman Catholic country, unleſs perhaps we ſhould except Portugal. Nowhere did the inquiſition reign with greater terror; there being no ſubject who was not liable to be proſecuted by the <hi rend="italic">holy office,</hi> as it is called ; however, the powers of that tribunal are now greatly diminiſhed even in Spain. There are eight arehbiſhops in Spain, ſeven in America, and one in Aſia at Manilla ; each of which has his ſuffragan biſhops. The archbiſhop of Toledo is primate, chancellor of Caſtile, and, by virtue of his office, privy-counſellor. He is ſaid to have a revenue of 100,000 l. Sterling <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> or more. The king nominates all archbiſhops and biſhops ; and ſince 1753 all ſmall benefices are alſo in his gift. He has alſo lately obtained a power to tax eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſions, according to his pleaſure and the exigency of affairs. Though the reſt of the nation is poor, the clergy are immenſely rich, and their revenues of all kinds very great. Moſt of the towns and eſtates belong to them, and are exempt from all public burdens ; yet their avarice is inſatiable, eſpecially that of the Mendicant friars, though they profeſs poverty. Their commerce, which is free from all duties and impolis, is alſo a rich fund to them. Though the Spaniards are naturally men of wit and of an elevated genius, yet little progreſs in the ſciences is to be expected from them, while the clergy uſe their utmoſt efforts to keep them in ignorance, branding all literary researches with the name of heresy, and inveighing againſt the ſeats of the muſes as the ſchools of hell, where the devil teaches ſorcery. There are 22 univerſities, and ſeveral academies, in Spain ; but ſo conſtituted, and under ſuch reſtrictions, that they can never attain to any meaſure of true learning. There are few printing-houſes in Spain ; and moſt oſ the books in that language are publiſhed in other countries.</p><p>In regard to trade and manufactures, the Spaniards are far from making ſuch a figure as might be expected. Moſt of the laborious work in their husbandry, manufactures, and handicrafts, is performed by the French, eſpecially in the two Caſtiles and the midland provinces, the natives being either too lazy or too proud to ſtoop to ſuch employments. By theſe means, the French uſually return with large fortunes to their own country. The chief manufactures of Spain are thoſe of ſilk, wool, iron, copper, and other hardwares; but theſe fall far ſhort of the flouriſhing condition to which they might be brought: hence a great part of the treaſures of America go to the foreign merchants, who ſupply them with goods for that part of the world. However, it is certain, that Spain, ſince it hath had princes of the houſe of Bourbon upon the throne, hath improved its revenues, increaſed its forces by sea and land, and applied itſelf more than it did before to manufactures and husbandry ; having ſhaken off, in ſome meaſure, that idle indolent diſposition which rendered it ſo contemptible in the eyes of other nations ; but it will be a long time before they will be able to ſupply the wants of their own country, and thoſe of America, in any great</p><p>degree. Spain is extremely well ſituated for trade : but moſt of its produce is exported by foreigners, except what is carried to the Indies ; and even with regard to that trade, they are little better than factors to the Engliſh, French, Dutch, and Italians. Smuggling, which was formerly carried to a great height, is now in a great meaſure ſuppreſſed. Since the year 1750, the exportation of ſilver hath been allowed on the payment of 3 <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi> From 1735 almoſt to 1756, the flotas and galleons were discontinued, and the trade to America carried on in regiſter-ſhips, which any merchant might ſend, on permiſſion obtained from the council of the Indies : but then the flotas and galleons were reſtored. The Aſſogue ſhips are two veſſels which carry quicksilver on the king’s account to Vera Cruz. There is a company which has an excluſive grant for trading to the Caraccas ; and another for trading to Porto Rico, the Bay of Honduras, the province of Guatimala and Hiſpaniola ; but the Spaniſh part of the laſt, it is ſaid, hath been lately ceded to the French. One ſhip, and ſometimes two, sails annually from Manilla, in the iſland of Luconia, one of the Philippines, for Acapulco in Mexico : her cargo, which belongs to the convents, conſiſts of the principal commodities of that part of the world ; but the return from Acapulco is for the moſt part made in money, and amounts to a vaſt ſum, as appeared from the treaſure found on board the Acapulco ſhip taken by Lord Anſon. In return for the manufactures ſent to America, the Spaniards receive gold, ſilver, cochineal, indigo, the cocoa or chocolate nut, logwood and other dyeing woods, ſugar, tobacco, ſnuff, and other productions of that part of the world ; ſupplying moſt part of Europe and Aſia with the ſilver which they bring from thence in their galleons. In the time of the Moors and Goths, this kingdom was exceedingly populous. It is ſaid to have then contained between twenty and thirty millions ; whereas now it does not contain above nine : and this, among other cauſes, is owing to the pride and lazineſs of the inhabitants, want of manufactures and good regulations, neglect of the mines and agriculture, the expulſion of the Moors, the peopling of America, heavy taxes, the great number of convents, exceſſive venery, and the consequent infecundity of both ſexes. Their debauchery and sterility are partly occaſioned by their way of living ; for they make great uſe of ſpices, and drink a great deal of chocolate, and ſtrong wine mixed with brandy. The cauſes aſſigned for the want of people in Spain will account in ſome meaſure for its poverty ; notwithſtanding it is computed that it receives one year with another, ſetting aſide other ſums, above 26 millions of pieces of eight, in regiſtered gold and ſilver. As moſt of the manufactures that are ſent to America are furniſhed by Britain, France, Italy, and Holland, ſo a great part of the treaſure brought home by the galleons is paid to the merchants of thoſe nations.</p><p>The conſtitution of Spain is at preſent an abſolute hereditary monarchy, where the females inherit in default of the males. The king, in his title, enumerates moſt of the provinces and particular parts of the dominions he has been or is poſſeſſed of. In ſpeaking of him, he is commonly called his <hi rend="italic">Catholic Majeſty,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Catholic King.</hi> The hereditary prince is commonly ſtyled <hi rend="italic">Prince of Asturias,</hi> and the other royal children <hi rend="italic">Infants,</hi> The kings of Spain are never crowned; they</p></body></text></TEI>