<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>nations, prompted them to repair to Conſtantinople. There they explained to the emperor the origin of ſilk, as well as the various modes of preparing and manufacturing it, myſteries hitherto unknown, or very imperfectly underſtood in Europe ; and encouraged by his liberal promiſes, they undertook to bring to the capital a ſufficient number of thoſe wonderful infects, to whoſe labours man is ſo much indebted. This they accompliſhed, by conveying the eggs of the ſilk worm in a hollow cane. They were hatched by the heat of a dunghill, fed with the leaves of a wild mulberry tree, and they multiplied and worked in the ſame manner as in thoſe climates where they firſt became objects of human attention and care. Vaſt numbers of theſe infects were ſoon reared in different parts of Greece, particularly in the Peloponneſus. Sicily afterwards undertook to breed ſilk worms with equal ſuccess, and was imitated, from time to time, in ſeveral towns of Italy. In all theſe places extenſive manufactures were eſtabliſhed and carried on with ſilk of domeſtic production. The demand for ſilk from the eaſt diminiſhed of courſe, the ſubjects of the Greek emperors were no longer obliged to have recourſe to the Persians for a ſupply of it, and a conſiderable change took place in the nature of the commercial intercourse between Europe and India.</p><p>As ſilk is the production of a worm, it will be firſt neceſſary to give a deſcription of its nature and mode of manufacturing. But before we give any account of the moſt approved methods of managing ſilk worms in Europe, it will be proper to preſent a ſhort deſcription of the methods practiſed in China, the original country of the ſilk worm. Theſe are two : they either permit them to remain at liberty on mulberry trees, or keep them in rooms. As the fineſt ſilk is produced by worms confined in rooms, and as the firſt method is very Ample, it will suffice to describe the second.</p><p>To begin with the eggs, which are laid on large ſheets of paper, to which they firmly adhere. The ſheets are hung up on a beam of the room, with the eggs inward, and the windows are opened in the front to admit the wind ; but no hempen ropes muſt ever come near the worms or their eggs. After ſome days the ſheets are taken down, rolled up looſely with the eggs inward, and then hung up again, during the ſummer and autumn. At the end of December, or the beginning of January, the eggs are put into cold water, with a little ſalt diſſolved in it. Two days after they take them out, hang them up again, and when dry roll them a little tighter, and encloſe each ſeparately, ſtanding on one end in an earthen veſſel. Some put them into a lye made of mulberry tree aſhes, and then lay them ſome moments in snow-water, or elſe hang them up three nights on a mulberry tree to receive the ſnow or rain, if not too violent. The time of hatching them is when the leaves of the mulberry trees begin to open, for they are haſtened or impeded according to the different degrees of heat or cold to which they are expoſed. When they are ready to come forth, the eggs ſwell, and become a little pointed.</p><p>The third day before they are hatched, the rolls of paper are taken out of the veſſel, ſtretched out, and hung up with their backs toward the ſun, till they receive a kindly warmth ; and then being rolled up cloſe, they are ſet upright in a veſſel in a warm place. This is repeated the next day, and the eggs change to an aſh-</p><p>grey, They then put two ſheets together, and rolling them cloſe tie the ends.</p><p>The third day, towards night, the ſheets are unrolled and ſtretched on a fine mat, when the eggs appear blackiſh. They then roll three ſheets together, and carry them into a pretty warm place, ſheltered from the ſouth wind. The next day the people taking out the rolls, and opening them, find them full of worms like ſmall black ants.</p><p>The apartment choſen for ſilk worms is on a dry ground, in a pure air, and free from noiſe. The rooms are ſquare, and very cloſe, for the sake of warmth ; the door faces the ſouth, and is covered with a double mat, to keep out the cold ; yet there ſhould be a window on every side, that when it is thought neceſſary the air may have a free paſſage. In opening a window to let in a refreſhing breeze, care muſt be taken to keep out the gnats and flies. The room muſt be furniſhed with nine or ten rows of frames, about nine inches one above the other. On theſe they place ruſh hurdles, upon which the worms are fed till they are ready to ſpin ; and, to preſerve a regular heat, ſtove fires are placed at the corners of the room, or elſe a warming pan is carried up and down it ; but it muſt not have the leaſt flame or ſmoke. Cow-dung, dried in the sun is eſteemed the moſt proper fuel.</p><p>The worms eat equally day and night. The Chineſe give them on the firſt day forty-eight meals; that is, one every half hour ; the next thirty ; the third day they have ſtill leſs. As cloudy and rainy weather takes away their ſtomach, just before their repaſt a wiſp of very dry ſtraw, the flame of which muſt be all alike, is held over the worms to free them from the cold and moiſture that benumbs them, or elſe the blinds are taken from the windows to let in the full day-light.</p><p>Eating ſo often haſtens their growth, on which the chief profit of the ſilk worm depends. If they come to maturity in 23 or 25 days, a large ſheet of paper covered with worms, which at their firſt Coming from the eggs weigh little more than a drachm, will produce 25 ounces of ſilk ; but if not till 28 days, they then yield only 20 ounces ; and if they are a month or 40 days in growing, they then produce but ten.</p><p>They are kept extremely clean, and are often removed; and when they are pretty well grown, the worms belonging to one hurdle are divided into three, afterwards they are placed on six, and ſo on to the number of 20 or more ; for being full of humours, they muſt be kept at a due diſtance from each other. The critical moment for removing them is when they are of a bright yellow and ready to ſpin ; they muſt be ſurrounded with mats at a ſmall diſtance, which muſt cover the top of the place to keep off the outward air ; and becauſe they love to work in the dark. However, after the third day’s labour, the mats are taken away from one o’clock till three, but the rays of the ſun muſt not ſhine upon them. They are at this time covered with the ſheets of paper that were uſed on the hurdles.</p><p>The cocoon s are completed in ſeven days, after which the worm is metamorphoſed into a chryſalis ; the cocoons are then gathered, and laid in heaps, having firſt ſet apart thoſe deſigned for propagation upon a hurdle, in a cool airy place. The next care is to kill the moths in thoſe cones which are not to be bored. The best way of doing this is to fill large earthen veſſels with</p></body></text></TEI>