<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:04Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>a great one muſt have been kept in a barn or ware- house. The coming in of all foreign money was alſo prohibited, that corruption might not enter under the name of commerce. The moſt ancient method of dealing, viz. by barter, or exchange of one commodity for another, was preſerved by law in Sparta long after it had been out of date everywhere elſe. Intereſt was a thing forbidden in the Spartan commonwealth ; where they had alſo a law againſt alienation of lands, accepting preſents from foreigners, even without the limits of their own country, and when their authority and character might well ſeem to excuſe them.</p><p>XI. Such of the laws of Sparta as related to courts of juſtice may be brought under the 11th table. Thirty years muſt have paſſed over the head of him who had a right to concern himſelf in juridical proceedings. Young men were thought unfit for them ; and it was  even held indecent, and of ill report, for a man to have any fondneſs for law-ſuits, or to be buſying himſelf at the tribunals, when he had no affairs there of his own. By theſe rules Lycurgus thought to ſlrut out litigiouſneſs, and to prevent that multiplicity of ſuits which is always ſcandalous in a ſtate. As young people were not permitted to inquire about the laws of other countries, and as they were hindered from hearing judicial proceedings in their courts, ſo they were likewiſe forbidden to aſk any queſtions about, or to endeavour to diſcover, the reaſons of the laws by which themſelves were governed. Obedience was their duty ; and to that alone they would have them kept. Men of abandoned characters, or who were notoriouſiy of ill fame, loſt all right of giving their votes in reſpect of public affairs, or of ſpeaking in public aſſemblies ; for they would not believe that an ill man in private life could mean his country better than he did his neighbour.</p><p>XII. Till a man was 30 years old, he was not capable of ſerving in the army, as the beſt authors agree ; though ſome think that the military age is not well aſcertained by ancicnt writers. They were forbidden to march at any time before the full-moon ; the reaſon of which law is very hard to be diſcovered, if indeed it had any reaſon at all, or was not rather founded on ſome superſtitious opinion, that this was a more lucky conjuncture than any other. They were likewiſe forbidden to fight often againſt the ſame enemy ; which was one of the wiſeſt maxims in the political ſyſtem of Lycurgus : and Ageſilaus, by offending againſt it, deſtroyed the power of his country, and loſt her that authority which for many ages ſhe maintained over the reſt of Greece ; for, by continually warring againſt the Thebans, to whom he had an inveterate hatred, he at laſt beat them into the knowledge of the art of war, and enabled them, under the command of Epaminondas, to maintain for a time the principality of Greece. Maritime affairs they were forbidden to meddle with, though the neceſſity of things compelled them, in proceſs of time, to tranſgreſs this inſtitution, and by degrees to transfer to themſelves the dominion of the ſea as well as of the land: but, after the Peloponneſian war, they again neglected naval affairs, from a perſuaſion that ſailors and ſtrangers corrupted thoſe with whom they converſed. As they never fortified Sparta, they were not ready to undertake ſieges : fighting in the field was their proper province, and, while they</p><p>could overcome their enemies there, they rightly conceived that nothing could hurt them at home. In time of war, they relaxed ſomewhat of their ſtrict manner of living, in which they were singular. The true reaſon for this was, in all probability, that war might be leſs burdenſome to them ; for, as we have more than once obſerved, a ſtrong deſire to render them bold and warlike was the reigning passion of their legislator. They were forbidden to remain long encamped in the ſame place, as well to hinder their being ſurpriſed, as that they might be more troubleſome to their enemies, by waſting every corner of their country. They ſlept all night in their armour ; but their outguards were not allowed their ſhields, that, being unprovided of defence, they might not dare to ſleep. In all expeditions they were careful in the performance of religious rites ; and, after their evening-meal was over, the ſoldiers ſung together hymns to their gods. When they were about to engage, the king ſacrificed to the muſes, that, by their aſſiſtance, they might be enabled to perform deeds worthy of being recorded to lateſt times. Then the army advanced in order to the sound of flutes, which played the hymn of Caſtor. The king himſelf ſung the pæan, which was the ſignal to charge. This was done with all the ſolemnity imaginable ; and the ſoldiers were ſure either to die or conquer : indeed they had no other choice ; for if they fled they were infamous, and in danger of being ſlain, even by their own mothers, for diſgracing their families. In this conſiſted all the excellency of the Spartan women, who, if poſſible, exceeded in bravery the men, never lamenting over husbands or ſons, if they died honourably in the field ; but deploring the ſhame brought on their houſe, if either the one or the other eſcaped by flight. The throwing away a ſhield alſo induced infamy ; and, with reſpect to this, mothers, when they embraced their departing ſons, were wont to caution them, that they ſhould either return armed as they were, or be brought back ſo when they were dead ; for, as we have obſerved, ſuch as were ſlain in battle were nevertheleſs buried in their own country. When they made their enemies fly, they purſued no longer than till victory was certain ; becauſe they would ſeem to fight rather for the honour of conquering, than of putting their enemies to death. According to their excellent rules of war, they were bound not to ſpoil the dead bodies of their enemies ; but in proceſs of time, this, and indeed many other of their moſt excellent regulations, fell into deſuetude. He who overcame by ſtratagem, offered up an ox to Mars ; whereas he who conquered by force, offered up only a cock ; the former being eſteemed more manly than the latter. After 40 years ſervice, a man was, by law, no longer required to go into the field ; and conſequently, if the military age was 30 the Spartans were not held invalids till they were 70.</p><p>SPARTIANUS (Ælius), a Latin hiſtorian, who wrote the lives of Adrian, Caracalla, and four other Roman emperors. He lived under the reign of Diocleſian, about the year 290.</p><p>SPARTIUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Broom,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">diadelphia,</hi> and order of <hi rend="italic">decandria ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 32d order, <hi rend="italic">Papilionaceae.</hi> The stigma is longitudinal and woolly above : the filaments adhere to the germen. The calyx is produced downwards. There are 16 ſpecies,</p></body></text></TEI>