<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:07Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>of the <hi rend="italic">piſces saxatiles,</hi> or fiſh that haunts deep waters on bold rocky ſhores. They feed chiefly on ſhell-fiſh, which they comminute with their teeth before they ſwallow ; the teeth of this genus in particular being adapted for that purpoſe : the grinders are flat and ſtrong, like thoſe of certain quadrupeds : beſides which there are certain bones in the lower part of the mouth that aſſiſt in grinding their food. They are but a coarſe fiſh : they were known to the Romans, who did not eſteem them unleſs they were fed with Lucrine oyſters, as Martial informs us,</p><p><hi rend="italic">Non omnis laudem pretiumque </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Aurata</hi><hi rend="italic"> meretur,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Sed qui ſolus erit concha Lucrina cibus.</hi></p><p>Lib. xiii. Ep. 90.</p><p>3. The <hi rend="italic">dentatus,</hi> toothed ſea-bream, is black above, and of a ſilvery appearance below. The eyes and gills are very large. There are nine rows of teeth in the lower jaw, and one in the upper.</p><p>In the account of Captain Cook’s voyage publiſhed by Mr Forster, we are informed, that the giltheads are sometimes poiſonous, owing to their feeding on certain ſpecies of the raja, which have an extremely acrid and stimulating property.</p><p>SPASM, a convulſion. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Medicine,</hi> n⁰ 278.</p><p>SPATHA, in botany, a ſheath ; a ſpecies of calyx which burſts lengthwiſe, and protrudes a ſtalk ſupporting one or more flowers, which commonly have no perianthium or flower-cup.</p><p>SPATHACEÆ (from <hi rend="italic">ſpatha,</hi> “a ſheath”), the name of the ninth order in Linnaeus’s Fragments of a Natural Method, conſiſting of plants whoſe flowers are protruded from a ſpatha or ſheath. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Botany, </hi>p. 458.</p><p>SPATHELIA, in botany; a genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and to the order of trigynia. The calyx is pentaphyllous ; the petals are five ; the capſule is three-edged and trilocular ; the ſeeds ſolitary. There is only one ſpecies, the si<hi rend="italic">mplex,</hi> which is a native of Jamaica, and was introduced into the botanic gardens of this country in 1778 by Dr Wright, late of Jamaica.</p><p>SPAW. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Spa.</hi></p><p>SPAWN, in natural hiſtory, the eggs of fiſhes or frogs. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Fish</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Ran</hi>A.</p><p>SPAVEN ΓO. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scanto.</hi></p><p>SPAVIN, in the manege, a diſeaſe in horſes, being a ſwelling or ſtiffneſs, uſually in the ham, occaſioning a lameneſs. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Farriery,</hi> 29.</p><p>SPAYING, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Spading,</hi> the operation of caſtrating the females of ſeveral kinds of animals, as ſows, bitches, &amp;c. to prevent any further conception, and promote their fattening. It is performed by cutting them in the mid flank, on the left side, with a ſharp knife or lancet, taking out the uterus, and cutting it off, and ſo ſtitching up the wound, anointing the part with tar, and keeping the animal warm for two or three days. The uſual way is to make the inciſion aslope, two inches and a half long ; that the fore-finger may be put in towards the back, to feel for the ovaries, which are two kernels as big as acorns on both sides of the uterus, one of which is drawn to the wound, and  thus both taken out.</p><p>SPEAKER <hi rend="italic">of the Houſe of Commons,</hi> a member of the houſe elected by a majority of votes thereof to act</p><p>as chairman or preſident in putting queſtions, reading briefs, or bills, keeping order, reprimanding the refractory, adjourning the houſe, &amp;c. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Parliament.</hi></p><p>SPEAKING, the art or act of expreſſing one’s thoughts in articulate sounds or words. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Grammar, Language, Reading,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Oratory,</hi> Part iv.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SPEAKING-Trumpet.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Trumpet.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">SPEAR-Mint,</hi> in botany. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mentha.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SPEAR-Wort.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ranunculus.</hi></p><p>SPECIAL, ſomething that is particular, or has a particular deſignation ; from the Latin speci<hi rend="italic">es,</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi rend="italic">general,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">genus.</hi></p><p>SPECIES, in logic, a relative term, expreſſing an idea which is compriſed under ſome general one called a <hi rend="italic">genus.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Logic,</hi> n⁰ 68.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Species,</hi> in commerce, the ſeveral pieces of gold, ſilver, copper, &amp;c. which having paſſed their full preparation and coinage, are current in public. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Money.</hi></p><p>SPECIFIC, in philoſophy, that which is peculiar to any thing, and distinguiſhes it from all others.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Specifics,</hi> in medicine. By specifics is not meant ſuch as infallibly and in all patients produce ſalutary effects. Such medicines are not to be expected, becauſe the operations and effects of remedies are not formally inherent in them, but depend upon the mutual action and reaction of the body and medicine upon each other ; hence the various effects of the same medicine in the ſame kind of diſorders in different patients, and in the ſame patient at different times. By ſpecific medicines we underſtand ſuch medicines as are more infallible than any other in any particular diſorder.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sprcific</hi><hi rend="italic"> Gravity,</hi> is a term much employed in the diſcuſſions of modern phyſics. It expreſſes the weight of any particular kind of matter, as compared with the weight of the ſame bulk of ſome other body of which the weight is ſuppoſed to be familiarly known, and is therefore taken for the ſtandard of companion. The body generally made uſe of for this purpoſe is pure water. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Hydrostatics,</hi> Sect. III.</p><p>The ſpecific gravity of bodies is a very intereſting queſtion both to the philoſopher and to the man of buſineſs. The philoſopher considers the weights of bodies as meaſures of the number of material atoms, or the quantity of matter which they contain. This he does on the ſupposition that every atom of matter is of the ſame weight, whatever may be its ſensible form. This ſupposition, however, is made by him with caution, and he has recourſe to ſpecific gravity ſor aſcertaining its truth in various ways. This shall be conſidered by and by. The man of buſineſs entertains no doubt of the matter, and proceeds on it as a sure guide in his most intereſting tranſactions. We meaſure commodities of various kinds by tons, pounds, and ounces, in the ſame manner as we meaſure them by yards, feet, and inches, or by buſhels, gallons, and pints ; nay, we do this with much greater confidence, and prefer this meaſurement to all others, whenever we are much intereſted to know the exact proportions of matter that bodies contain. The weight of a quantity of grain is allowed to inform us much more exactly of its real quantity of uſeſul matter than the moſt accurate meaſure of its bulk. We ſee many circumſtances which can vary the bulk of a quantity of matter, and theſe are frequently ſuch as we can-</p></body></text></TEI>