<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:24:22Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>neceſſary for bringing all things again into equilibrium. We refer the curious reader
                to the ingenious theory of the Abbé Boſcovſeh for an excellent illuſtration of this
                ſubject ( <hi rend="italic">Theor. Phil. Nat.</hi> de Solutione Chemica).</p>
            <p>This queſtion is no leſs important to the man of buſineſs. Till we know the
                condenſation of thoſe metals by mixture, we cannot tell the quantity of alloy in
                gold and ſilver by means of their ſpecific gravity ; nor can we tell the quantity of
                pure alcohol in any ſpirituous liquor, or that of the valuable ſalt in any ſolution
                of it. For want of this knowledge, the dealers in gold and ſilver are obliged to
                have recourſe to the tedious and difficult teſt of the aſſay, which cannot be made
                in all places or by all men. It is therefore much to be wiſhed, that ſome persons
                would inſtitute a ſeries of experiments in the moſt intereſting caſes : for it muſt
                be obſerved, that this change of denſity is not always a ſmall matter ; it is
                ſometimes very conſiderable and paradoxical. A remarkable inſtance may be given of
                it in the mixture of braſs and tin for bells, great guns, optical speculums, &amp;c.
                The ſpecific gravity of caſt braſs is nearly 8,oc6, and that of tin is nearly 7,363.
                If two parts of braſs be mixed with one of tin, the ſpecific gravity is 8,917 ;
                whereas, if each had retained its former bulk, the ſpecific gravity would have been
                only 7,7.93</p>
            <p>2×8,006+7,363 </p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">= 3 A</hi> mixture of equal parts</p>
            <p>ſhould have the ſpecific gravity 7,684 ; but it is 8,441. A mixture of two parts tin
                with one part braſs, inſtead of being 7,577, is 8,027.</p>
            <p>In all theſe caſes there is a great increaſe of ſpecific gravity, and conſequently a
                great condenſation of parts or contraction of bulk. The firſt mixture of eight cubic
                inches of braſs, for inſtance, with four cubic inches of tin, does not produce 12
                cubic inches of bell-metal, but only 10<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">2 </hi>nearly, having ſhrunk <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">5</hi>. It would appear that the diſtances of the braſs
                particles are moſt affected, or perhaps it is the braſs that receives the tin into
                its pores ; for we find that the condenſations in theſe mixtures are nearly
                proportional to the quantities of the braſs in the mixtures. It is remarkable that
                this mixture with the lighteſt of all metals has made a compoſition more heavy and
                denſe than braſs can be made by any hammering.</p>
            <p>The moſt remarkable inſtance occurs in mixing iron with platina. If 10 cubic inches
                of iron are mixed with of platina, the bulk of the compound is only 9<hi
                    rend="superscript">3</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi> inches. The iron therefore
                has not ſimply received the platina into its pores : its own particles are brought
                nearer together. There are ſimilar reſults in the ſolution of turbith mineral, and
                of ſome other ſalts, in water. The water, inſtead of riſing in the neck of the
                veſſel, when a ſmall quantity of the ſalt has been added to it, ſinks conſiderably,
                and the two ingredients occupy leſs room than the water did alone.</p>
            <p>The ſame thing happens in the mixture of water with other fluids and different fluids
                with each other : But we are not able to trace any general rule that is obſerved
                with abſolute preciſion. In moſt caſes of fluids the greateſt condenſation happens
                when the bulks of the ingredients are nearly equal. Thus, in the mixture of alcohol
                and water, we have the greateſt condensation when 16<hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2 </hi>ounces of alcohol are mixed with 20 ounces
                of water, and the condenſation is about <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi
                    rend="subscript">30</hi> of the whole bulk of the ingredients. It is extremely
                va</p>
            <p>rious in different ſubſtances, and no claſſification of them can be made in this
                reſpect,</p>
            <p>A diſsertation has been publiſhed on this ſubject by Dr Hahn of Vienna, intitled <hi
                    rend="italic">De Efficacia Mixtionis in mutandis Corporum Voluminibus,</hi> in
                which all the remarkable inſtances of the variation of denſity have been collected.
                All that we can do (as we have no directing principle) is to record ſuch inſtances
                as are of chief importance, being articles of commerce.</p>
            <p>The firſt that occurs to us is the mixtures oſ alcohol and water in the compoſition
                of ſpirituous liquors. This has been conſidered by many with great care. The moſt
                ſcrupulous examination of this, or perhaps of any mixture, has been lately made by
                Dr Blagden (now Sir Charles Blagden) of the Royal Society, on the requiſition of the
                Board of Exciſe. He has publiſhed an account of the examination in the Philoſophical
                Tranſactions of London in 1791 and 1792. We ſhall give an account of it under the
                article <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Spirituous</hi><hi rend="italic"> Liquors ;</hi>
                and at preſent only ſelect one column, in order to ſhow the condenſation. The
                alcohol was almoſt the ſtrongeſt that can be produced, and its ſpecific gravity,
                when of the temperature 60⁰, was 0,825. The whole mixtures were of the ſame
                temperature.</p>
            <p>Column I. contains the pounds, ounces, or other meaſures by weight, of alcohol in the
                mixture. Column 2. contains the pounds or ounces of water. Column 3. is the ſum of
                the bulks of the ingredients, the bulk of a pound or ounce of water being accounted
                1. Column 4. is the obſerved ſpecific gravity of the mixture, taken from Dr
                Blagden's diſſertation. Column 5. is the ſpecific gravity which would have been
                obſerved if the ingredients had each retained its own ſpecific gravity. This we
                calculated by dividing the ſum oſ the two numbers of the firſt and ſecond columns by
                the correſponding number of the third. Column 6. is the difference of column 4. and
                column 5. and exhibits the condenſation.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>A.</cell>
                    <cell>W.</cell>
                    <cell>Volume.</cell>
                    <cell>Sp. Grav<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> obſerved.</cell>
                    <cell>Sp. Grav<hi rend="superscript">y</hi> calculated.</cell>
                    <cell>Condenſation.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>0</cell>
                    <cell>24,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8250</cell>
                    <cell>0,8250</cell>
                    <cell>00</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>1</cell>
                    <cell>25,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8360</cell>
                    <cell>0,8320</cell>
                    <cell>40</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>2</cell>
                    <cell>26,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8457</cell>
                    <cell>0,8383</cell>
                    <cell>74</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>3</cell>
                    <cell>27,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8543</cell>
                    <cell>0,8443</cell>
                    <cell>100</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>4</cell>
                    <cell>28,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8621</cell>
                    <cell>0,8498</cell>
                    <cell>123</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>5</cell>
                    <cell>29,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8692</cell>
                    <cell>0,8549</cell>
                    <cell>143</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>6</cell>
                    <cell>30,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8757</cell>
                    <cell>0,8597</cell>
                    <cell>160</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>7</cell>
                    <cell>31,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8,817</cell>
                    <cell>0,8642</cell>
                    <cell>175</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>8</cell>
                    <cell>32,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8872</cell>
                    <cell>0,8684</cell>
                    <cell>188</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>9</cell>
                    <cell>33,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8923</cell>
                    <cell>0,8724</cell>
                    <cell>199</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>10</cell>
                    <cell>34,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,8971</cell>
                    <cell>0,8761</cell>
                    <cell>216</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>I I</cell>
                    <cell>35,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9014</cell>
                    <cell>0,8796</cell>
                    <cell>218</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>I 2</cell>
                    <cell>36,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9055</cell>
                    <cell>0,8829</cell>
                    <cell>226</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>13</cell>
                    <cell>37,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9093</cell>
                    <cell>0,8860</cell>
                    <cell>233</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>14</cell>
                    <cell>38,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9129</cell>
                    <cell>0,8891</cell>
                    <cell>238</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>15</cell>
                    <cell>39,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9162</cell>
                    <cell>0,8919</cell>
                    <cell>243</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>16</cell>
                    <cell>40,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9193</cell>
                    <cell>0,8946</cell>
                    <cell>247</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>17</cell>
                    <cell>41,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9223</cell>
                    <cell>0,8971</cell>
                    <cell>252</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>18</cell>
                    <cell>42,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9250</cell>
                    <cell>c,8996</cell>
                    <cell>254</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>43,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9276</cell>
                    <cell>0,9019</cell>
                    <cell>257</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>44,2424</cell>
                    <cell>0,9300</cell>
                    <cell>0,9041</cell>
                    <cell>259</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>19</cell>
                    <cell>20</cell>
                    <cell>43,0303</cell>
                    <cell>0,9325</cell>
                    <cell>0,9063</cell>
                    <cell>262</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
