<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:18Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>this money be reſtored to the owners ; and if I hear they are defrauded of it, I will myſelf return from the other side of the Pyrenees, and oblige you to make them reſtitution.” The pope found the neceſſity of ſubmitting, and paid from his own treaſury the ſum demanded.</p><p>A body of experienced and hardy ſoldiers, conducted by ſo able a general, eaſily prevailed over the king of Caſtile, whole ſubjects were ready to join the enemy againſt their oppreſſor. Peter fled from his dominions, took ſhelter in Guſenne, and craved the protection of the prince of Wales, whom his father had inveſted with the ſovereignty of the ceded provinces, under the title of the <hi rend="italic">principality of Aquitaine.</hi> The prince promiſed his aſſiſtance to the dethroned monarch ; and having obtained his father’s conſent, he levied an army, and ſet out on his enterpriſe.</p><p>The firſt loſs which Henry of Traſtamara ſuffered from the interpoſition of the prince of Wales, was the recalling of the companies from his ſervice; and ſo much reverence did they pay to the name of Edward, that great numbers of them immediately withdrew from Spain, and insiſted under his ſtandard. Henry, however, beloved by his new ſubjects, and ſupported by the king of Arragon, was able to meet the enemy with an army of 100,000 men, three times the number of thoſe commanded by the Black Prince : yet du Gueſclin, and all his experienced officers, adviſed him to delay a deciſive action ; ſo high was their opinion of the valour and conduct of the Engliſh hero ! But Henry, truſting to his numbers, ventured to give Edward battle on the banks of the Ebro, between Najara and Navarette ; where the French and Spaniards were defeated, with the loſs of above 20,000 men, and du Gueſclin and other officers of diſtinction taken priſoners. All Caſtile ſubmitted to the victor ; Peter was reſtored to the throne, and Edward returned to Guienne with his uſual glory ; having not only overcome the greateſt general of his age, but reſtrained the moſt blood-thirſty tyrant from executing vengeance on his priſoners.</p><p>This gallant warrior had ſoon reaſon to repent of his connections with a man like Peter, loſt to all ſenſe of virtue and honour. The ungrateful monſter refuſed the ſtipulated pay to the Engliſh forces. Edward abandoned him : he treated his ſubjects with the utmoſt barbarity ; their animoſity was rouſed againſt him ; and du Gueſclin having obtained his ranſom, returned to Caſtile with the count of Traſtamara, and ſome forces levied anew in France. They were joined by the Spaniſh malecontents ; and having no longer the Black Prince to encounter, they gained a complete victory over Peter in the neighbourhood of Toledo. The tyrant now took refuge in a caſtle, where he was ſoon after beſieged by the victors, and taken priſoner in endeavouring to make his eſcape. He was conducted to his brother Henry ; again it whom he is ſaid to have ruſhed in a tranſport of rage, diſarmed as he was. Henry slew him with his own hand, in reſentment of his cruelties ; and, though a baſtard, was placed on the throne of Caſtile, which he tranfmitted to his poſterity.</p><p>After the death of Peter the Cruel, nothing remarkable happened in Spain for almoſt a whole century; but the debaucheries of Henry IV. of Caſtile rouſed the reſentment of his nobles, and produced a moſt ſingular inſurrection, which led to the aggrandizement of the Spaniſh monarchy.</p><p>This prince, ſurnamed the <hi rend="italic">Impotent,</hi> though continually ſurrounded with women, began his unhappy reign in 1454. He was totally enervated by his pleaſures ; and every thing in his court conſpired to ſet the Caſtilians an example of the moſt abject flattery and moſt abandoned licentiouſneſs. The queen, a daughter of Portugal, lived as openly with her paraſites and her gallants as the king did with his minions and his miſtreſſes. Pleaſure was the only object, and effeminacy the only recommendation to favour : the affairs of the ſtate went every day into diſorder ; till the nobility, with the archbiſhop of Toledo at their head, combining againſt the weak and flagitious adminiſtration of Henry, arrogated to themſelves, as one of the privileges of their order, the right of trying and paſſing ſentence on their ſovereign, which they executed in a manner unprecedented in hiſtory.</p><p>All the malecontent nobility were ſummoned to meet at Avila : a ſpacious theatre was erected in a plain without the walls of the town : an image, repreſenting the king, was ſeated on a throne, clad in royal robes, with a crown on its head, a ſceptre in its hand, and the ſword of juſtice by its side. The accuſation againſt Henry was read, and the ſentence of depoſition pronounced, in preſence of a numerous aſſembly. At the cloſe of the firſt article of the charge, the archbiſhop of Toledo advanced, and tore the crown from the head of the image ; at the cloſe of the ſecond, the Conde de Placentia ſnatched the ſword of juſtice from its side; at the cloſe of the third, the Conde de Benavente wreſted the ſceptre from its hand ; and at the cloſe of the laſt, Don Diego Lopez de Stuniga tumbled it headlong from the throne. At the ſame instant, Don Alphonſo, Henry’s brother, a boy of about twelve years of age, was proclaimed king of Caſtile and Leon in his ſtead.</p><p>This extraordinary proceeding was followed by a civil  war, which did not ceaſe till ſome time after the death of the young prince, on whom the nobles had beſtowed the kingdom. The archbiſhop and his party then continued to carry on war in the name of Iſabella the king’s ſiſter, to whom they gave the title of <hi rend="italic">Infanta ;</hi> and Henry could not extricate himſelf out of theſe troubles, nor remain quiet upon his throne till he had ſigned one of the moſt humiliating treaties ever extorted from a ſovereign ; he acknowledged his ſiſter Iſabella the only lawful heireſs of his kingdom, in prejudice to the rights of his reputed daughter Joan, whom the malecontents affirmed to be the offspring of an adulterous commerce between the queen and Don la Cueva. The grand object of the malecontent party now was the marriage of the princeſs Iſabella, upon which, it was evident, the ſecurity of the crown and the happineſs of the people muſt in a great meaſure depend. The alliance was ſought by ſeveral princes : the king of Portugal offered her his hand ; the king of France demanded her for his brother, and the king of Arragon for his ſon Ferdinand. The malecontents very wiſely preferred the Arragonian prince, and Iſabella prudently made the ſame choice; articles were drawn up ; and they were privately married by the archbiſhop of Toledo.</p></body></text></TEI>