<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>by the Rev. Dr Smith of Campbelton and others, but chiefly by the Rev. Dr Stewart of
                Luſs, by the appointment and at the expence of the ſociety : and as ſoon as the
                remaining part can be got ready, the whole will be ſold at ſo low a price as the
                poor may without difficulty afford. This plan the ſociety have judiciously choſen,
                in order to prevent diſcontent and murmuring ; effects which the diffuſion oſ the
                Scriptures ought never to produce ; but which could not possibly have been
                prevented, had the diſtribution been gratuitous, and of courſe partial.</p>
            <p>For ſome years paſt the funds of the ſociety have rapidly accumulated, from the very
                liberal donations of ſeveral individuals. </p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Lady Glenorchy</cell>
                    <cell>L. 5,000</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>By a perſon unknown</cell>
                    <cell>10,000</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Lord Van Vryhouven of Holland</cell>
                    <cell>20,000 </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Miſs Gray of Teasses</cell>
                    <cell>3,500</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>In conſequence of theſe great additions to their ſtock, inſinuations have been thrown
                out that the ſociety have become ſo wealthy as to be at a loſs for proper objects on
                which to beſtow their increaſed revenue. If ſuch an opinion be <hi rend="italic"
                    >ſeriouſly</hi> entertained by any one, we muſt beg him to remember, that the
                ſociety have erected and endued no leſs than 323 ſchools for religion, the firſt
                principles of literature and induſtry, at the annual expence of L. 3214, 10s.
                Sterling ; and that at theſe ſeminaries are educated from 14,000 to 15,000 children
                ; who, but for the means of inſtruction thus obtained, would in all probability be
                bred up in ignorance and idleneſs : That they employ 12 miſſionary miniſters and
                catechiſts in remote parts of the Highlands and iſlands, or among the ignorant
                Highlanders ſettled in the great towns of Scotland, at the annual expence of L. 296
                : That they beſtow a burſary or penſion of L. 15 <hi rend="italic">per annum</hi> on
                each of six ſtudents of divinity having the Gaelic language : That they employ two
                miſſionary miniſters and one ſchoolmaſter among the Oneida and Stockbridge Indians
                of North America (being the deſtination of certain legacies bequeathed to them for
                that purpoſe), at the annual expence of L. 140. Such is their fixed ſcheme of annual
                expenditure, amounting in all to L.3740, 10s. Sterling—a ſum it will be acknowledged
                of very conſiderable magnitude. The whole of their incidental expences ariſing from
                the Gaelic tranſlation of the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament ; from annuities which
                they have to pay, in conſequence of ſums left them as reſiduary legatees ; from land
                and houſe-taxes ; ſrom enabling candidates for the office of ſchoolmaſter to come to
                Edinburgh for examination ; from furniſhing books to poor ſcholars in their various
                ſchools ; and from removing ſchoolmaſters from one ſtation to another, is generally
                about L. 875, which added to the former ſum makes the whole annual expence amount to
                L. 4615, 10 s.</p>
            <p>If it be inquired at what expence, in the <hi rend="italic">management </hi>of it,
                this extenſive and complicated charity is annually conducted, we are authoriſed to
                ſay, that the treaſurer,</p>
            <p>bookholder, and clerk, are allowed each L. 25 <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> the
                ſame ſalaries which were annexed to theſe offices from the commencement of the
                ſociety. The beadle or officer is allowed L. 12 <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi> No
                ſalary whatever is enjoyed by any of the other officers of the ſociety. The
                ſecretary, comptroller, accountant, and librarian, although ſubjected, ſome of them
                eſpecially, to no ſmall expence of time and labour, have no pecuniary recompenſe or
                emolument. Theirs are labours of love, for which they ſeek and expect no other
                reward than the consciouſneſs of endeavouring to promote the beſt intereſts of
                mankind. The whole amount of the expence of managing the buſineſs of the ſociety,
                including the above ſalaries, and coals, candle, ſtationary ware, poſtages, and
                other incidents, exceeds not at an average L. 115 <hi rend="italic">per annum.</hi>
                From this ſtatement it appears, that hitherto at leaſt the directors have been at no
                loſs for important objects within the proper ſphere of their inſtitution on which to
                beſtow their increaſed funds. They have, it is true, the diſpoſal of very
                conſiderable ſums for promoting the objects of the inſtitution ; but they are ſo far
                from accumulating wealth, that every year their expenditure, notwithſtanding the
                late increaſe of their capital, exceeds rather than falls ſhort of their income.
                They have depended upon a kind Providence and a generous public to refund theſe
                anticipations of their revenue, and hitherto they have never been diſappointed.</p>
            <p>Thus has the Society for Propagating Chriſtian Knowledge proceeded for almoſt a
                century. It was founded by the pious exertions of a few private individuals, whoſe
                names are unknown to the world ; and its funds, by faithful and judicious
                management, as well as by generous contributions, have now become of ſuch magnitude,
                as to excite the hope that they will be productive of the moſt valuable effects. The
                benefits ariſing from public ſocieties, it is well known, depend entirely upon the
                management of their directors. If ſo, the advantages which have accrued from this
                ſociety inside it to the praiſe and gratitude of the nation. While eager to increaſe
                the number of ſchools, the ſociety have not been inattentive to their proſperity. In
                the year 1771 Mr Lewis Drummond, a gentleman in whom they placed great confidence,
                was commiſſioned by them to viſit their ſchools, and to make an exact report of
                their ſtate and circumſtances. Again, in the year 1790, a commiſſion was granted to
                the Rev. Dr Kemp, one of the miniſters of Edinburgh and ſecretary to the ſociety, to
                viſit all the ſchools on their eſtabliſhment. This laborious and gratuitous task he
                accompliſhed in the courſe of four ſummers with much ability and care, and highly to
                the ſatisfaction of the ſociety. At his return he communicated a variety of
                important information reſpecting the ſtate of the Highlands and iſlands, and the
                means neceſſary for their improvement in religion, literature, and induſtry ; an
                abſtract of which was publiſhed by the ſociety in appendixes to the anniverſary
                sermons preached before them in the years 1789, 90, 91, and 92 @@(c).</p>
            <p>@@@(c) It is well known, that the number of Roman Catholics in the Highlands is
                conſiderable ; but it muſt give much pleaſure to the Proteſtant reader to be
                informed, that the ancient malignant ſpirit of Popery has in that diſtrict given
                place to mildneſs and liberality. This is chiefly owing to the gentleman who
                ſuperintends the prieſts in that quarter, whoſe mind is enlightened by ſcience and
                learning. So far from being hoſtile to the views of the ſociety, he recommended to
                his clergy to promote them. They accordingly received the secretary with much
                politeneſs ; exhorted the people to ſend their children to the Proteſtant ſchools to
                be inſtructed in literature, to be taught to read the Scriptures in their own
                language, and to be made acquainted with thoſe great principles of religion in which
                all Chriſtians are agreed. What a bleſſed reformation!</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
