<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:20:56Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>to do everything in his power to render the exiſtence of that being happy both in the
                preſent life and in that which is to come. If this duty be conſcientiouſly
                diſcharged, the parent has a manifeſt right to the gratitude, love, and reaſonable
                obedience, of his child ; but he cannot, in consequence of any duty performed, claim
                a right to transfer that child as property to the uncontrolled diſpoſal of any
                private master ; for this plain reaſon, that the man who is conſidered as the
                private property of another, cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed to enjoy happineſs in
                this world, and is under many temptations to do what muſt neceſſarily render him
                miſerable in the next. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Moral Philosophy,</hi> n⁰ 138.</p>
            <p>If criminals cannot be lawfully reduced to a ſtate of abſolute private slavery, much
                leſs ſurely can it be lawful to reducc insolvent debtors and priſoners of war co
                that ſtate. Many a virtuous man, who has contracted debts with the fairest proſpcct
                of paying them, has been ſuddenly rendered inſolvent by fire, by ſhipwreck, or by
                the bankruptcy of others with whom he was neceſſarily engaged in the courſe of his
                trade. Such a man can be conſidered in no reſpect as criminal. He has been indeed
                unfortunate ; but it would be grossly unjuſt, as well as ſhockingly cruel, to add to
                his misfortune by reducing him to a ſtate to which we have juſt ſeen that the vileſt
                felon cannot be reduced without a violation of the laws of morality. Fraudulent
                bankrupts indeed, of whom we daily ſee many, might with great propriety and the
                ſtricteſt justice be compelled to extenuate their debts by labouring for the benefit
                of thoſe whom they have injured ; and criminals of other deſcriptions might be made
                to work for the benefit of the public : but in both cafes the taste to be performed
                ſhould be aſcertained by the law, and the perſons of the labourers be protected by
                the ſtate. lf ſuch can be called slaves, their slavery is undoubtedly confident with
                every principle of virtuc and religion ; for they ſuffer nothing but the due reward
                of their deeds. Priſoners of war, however, can upon no honeſt principle be reduced
                even to this ſtate of mitigated bondage ; tor they are ſo far from incurring guilt
                by fighting for their country, that even to their enemies their courage and conduct
                in ſuch a cauſe muſt appear worthy of reward. A victorious general has certainly a
                right to prevent the prhoners taken in battle from again drawing their ſwords
                against him during the continuance of the war ; but there are many ways by which
                this, may be done effectually without chaining the unfortunate captives to the oar,
                or selling them like cattle to private purchaſers, by whom they may be treated with
                capricious cruelty, and driven to the perpetration of the greateſt crimes.</p>
            <p>To theſe concluſions, and the reaſoning on which they are built, we are aware it may
                be objected, that if private ſlavery were in every inſtance unlawful and in-
                conſistent with the fundamental principles of morality, it would not have prevailed
                among the ancient patriarchs, and far leſs have been authoriſed by the Jewiſh
                law.</p>
            <p>In reply to this objection, it may be obſerved, that Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob,
                though excellent men, were not characters abſolutely perfect ; that as their
                practice does not authoriſe polygamy or inceſt among us, it will not authoriſe the
                reducing of our fellow-creatures to a ſtate of hopeleſs ſervitude; and that from the
                circumſtances of the age in which they lived, many things</p>
            <p>were permitted to them, and were indeed harmleſs, which are forbidden to us, and
                would now be pernicious. The character oſ Abraham appears to have been much more
                perfect than that of his ſon or grandſon ; and was certainly equal, if not ſuperior,
                to that of any ether mere man of whom we read either in profane or even in ſacred
                hiſtory. We are to remember, however, that he was born amidſt idolaters, and was
                probably an idolater himſelf till enlightened by the inſpiration of Jehovah, and
                called from his kindred and from his father’s houſe. Before his converſion, he muſt
                have had much cattle and many ſlaves, which conſtituted the riches of that early
                period ; and his caſe would indeed have been peculiarly hard, had he been commanded
                to diveſt himſelf of his ſervants, and to depart into a ſtrange country very thinly
                inhabited, without people to protect his flocks and herds from beaſts of prey. Nor
                would his loſs have contributed in any degree to the benefit of his ſlaves, who, as
                the ranks of men were then adjuſted, could not long have preſerved their liberty.
                Had they not been forcibly reduced to their former ſtate by their idolatrous
                countrymen, which in all probability they would have been, they muſt have ſoon
                submitted to it, or periſhed by hunger. Let it be remembered, too, that the
                bond-ſervants of Abraham, though conſtituting the moſt valuable part of his
                property, were not conſidered as a ſpecies of inferior beings, but were treated
                rather as childeren than as ſlaves. This is evident from his ſpeaking of the ſteward
                of his houſe as his heir, when complaining to God of the want of ſeed. Indeed the
                manner in which this circumſtance is mentioned, ſhows that it was then the general
                practice to conſider domeſtic ſlaves as members of the family ; for the patriarch
                does not ſay, “ I will leave my ſubſtance to this Eliezer of Damaſcus;” but his
                words are, “ Behold to me thou haſt given no ſeed; and, lo! one born in my houſe is
                    <hi rend="italic">my</hi> heir @@*. From this mode of expreſſion we are ſtrongly
                inclined to think that captives taken in war were in that age of ſimplicity
                incorporated into the family or tribe of the conqueror, as they are ſaid to be at
                preſent among the North American Indians, to ſupply the place of thoſe who had
                fallen in battle. If ſo, ſlavery was then a very mild thing, unattended with the
                evils which are now in its train, and muſt often have been highly beneficial to the
                captive.</p>
            <p>The other part of the objection appears at firſt sight more formidable : but perhaps
                a little attention to the deſign of the Moſaic economy may enable us to remove it
                even more completely than this. We need not inform our theological readers, that one
                great purpoſe for which the poſterity of Abraham were ſeparated from the heathen
                nations around them, was to preſerve the knowledge of the true God in a world run
                headlong into idolatry. As idolatry appears to have had ſomething in its forms of
                worſhip extremely captivating to rude minds, and as the minds of the Iſraelites at
                the era of their departure from Egypt were exceedingly rude, every method was taken
                to keep their ſeparation from their idolatrous neighbours as complete as poſſible.
                With this view they were commanded to sacrifice the animals which their Egyptian
                maſters had worſhipped as gods, and were taught to conſider hogs and ſuch other
                creatures as the heathen offered in ſacrifice, when celebrating their myſtical and
                magic rites, as too unclean to be eaten or even to be touched. Of this di-</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Gen. xv. 3. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
