<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tion, was built by the empreſs Helena : and near it is an ancient ſtructure, ſaid to be the remains of a palace where the Greek council was held when Smyrna was the metropolis of Aſia Minor. They alſo ſhow the ruins of an amphitheatre, where it is ſaid St Polycarp, the firſt biſhop, fought with lions.</p><p>This city is about four miles in circumference, and nearly of a triangular form ; but the side next the mountain is much longer than the other sides. The houſes are low, and moſtly built with clay-walls, on account of the earthquakes to which the country is ſubject ; but the caravanſeras and ſome other of the public buildings have an air of magnificence. The ſtreets are wide, and almoſt a continued bazar, in which a great part of the merchandize of Europe and Asia is expoſed to ſale, with plenty of provisions ; though theſe are not ſo cheap as in many other parts of Turkey, on account of the populouſneſs of the place, and the great reſort of foreigners. It is ſaid to contain 15,000 Turks, 10,000 Greeks, 1800 Jews, 200 Armenians, and 200 Franks. The Turks have 19 moſques ; two churches belong to the Greeks; one to the Armenians; and the Jews have eight ſynagogues. The Romaniſts have three convents. There is alſo one of the fathers Della Terra Santa. Here resides an archbiſhop of the Greek church ; a Latin biſhop who has a ſalary from Rome, with the title of biſhop of Smyrna <hi rend="italic">in partibus infidelium; </hi>and the Engliſh and Dutch factories have each their chaplain.</p><p>The walks about the town are extremely pleaſant, particularly on the well side of Frank ſtreet, where there are ſeveral little groves of orange and lemon trees, which being always clothed with leaves, blossoms, and fruit, regale ſeveral of the ſenſes at the ſame time. The vines which cover the little hills about Smyrna afford both a delightful proſpect and plenty of grapes, of which good wine is made. Theſe hills are agreeably intersperſed with fertile plains, little forests of olives and other fruit-trees, and many pleaſure-houſes, to which the Franks uſually retire during the ſummer. In the neighbourhood of Smyrna is great plenty of game and wild-fowl, and particularly deer and wild-hogs. The ſea alſo abounds with a variety of good fiſh. The European Chriſtians are here allowed all imaginable liberties, and uſually clothe themſelves after the European manner.</p><p>The chief commerce of this city consiſts in raw silk, ſilk-ſtuffs, grograms, and cotton yarn.</p><p>However, the unhealthfulneſs of the situation, and more eſpecially the frequent earthquakes, from which, it is ſaid, they are ſcarcely ever free for two years together, and which have been felt 40 days ſucceſſively, are an abatement of the pleaſure that might otherwiſe be enjoyed here. A very dreadful one happened in June 1688, which overthrew a great number oſ the houſes ; and the rock opening where the caſtle stood, ſwallowed  up, and no leſs than 5000 perſons periſhed on this occasion.</p><p>In the year 1758, ſo deſolating a plague raged here, that ſcarcely a sufficient number of the inhabitants ſurvived to gather in the fruits of the earth. In the year 1772, three-fourth parts of the city were conſumed by ſire; and six years after it was visited by the moſt dreadful earthquakes, which continued from the 25th of June</p><p>to the 5th of July ; by which ſucceſſive calamities the city has been ſo much reduced, that its former conſequence is never likely to be reſtored.</p><p>The ladies here wear the oriental dreſs, conſiſting of large trowlers or breeches, which reach to the ancle ; long veſts of rich ſilk or velvet, lined in winter with coſtly furs ; and round their waiſt an embroidered zone with claſps of ſilver or gold. Their hair is plaited, and deſcends down the back often in great profuſion. The girls have ſometimes above twenty thick tresses, besides two or three encircling the head as a coronet, and ſet off with flowers and plumes of feathers, pearls, or other jewels. They commonly ſtain it of a cheſnut colour, which is the moſt desired. Their apparel and carriage are alike antique. It is remarkable that the trowſers are mentioned in a fragment of Sappho as part of the female dreſs.</p><p>SMYRNIUM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexanders</hi> : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">digynia ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 45th order, <hi rend="italic">Umbellatœ.</hi> The fruit is oblong and ſtriated ; the petals have a ſharp point, and are keel-ſhaped. There are five ſpecies : 1. The <hi rend="italic">perfoliatum,</hi> or perfoliate alexanders, which is a native of Candia and Italy ; 2. The <hi rend="italic">Ægyptiacum</hi> ; 3. The <hi rend="italic">aureum,</hi> or golden alexanders, which is a native of North America ; 4. The <hi rend="italic">integerrimum ; 5.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">oluſatrum,</hi> common alexanders, a native of Britain ; the leaves of which are cauline, ternate, petiolated, and ſerrated. It grows on the ſea- coaſt at Dunglas on the borders of Berwickſhire North Britain. Since the introduction of celery into the garden, the alexanders is almoſt forgotton. It was formerly cultivated for ſalading, and the young ſhoots or ſtalks blanched were eaten either raw or ſtewed. The leaves too were boiled in broths and ſoups. It is a warm comfortable plant to a cold weak stomach and was in much eſteem among the monks, as may be inferred by its ſtill being found in great plenty by old abbey walls.</p><p>SNAFFLE, in the manege, is a very ſlender bit- mouth without any branches, much uſed in England ; the true bridles being reſerved for war.</p><p>SNAIL, in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Helix</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Limax.</hi></p><p>SNAKE, in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Anguis</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Serpens.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Method oſ Preſervmg </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">SnaKESs.</hi> When the ſnake is killed, it muſt firſt be waſhed clean, and freed from all filth and naſtineſs ; then it is to be put into a glaſs of a proper fize, the tail firſt, and afterwards the reſt of the body, winding it in ſpiral aſcending circles, and diſposing the back, which is alway the moſt beautiful, outwardly. A thread, connected with a ſmall glaſs bead, is, by the help of a needle, to be passed through the upper jaw from within outwardly, and then through the cork of the bottle, where it muſt be faſtened ; by this means the head will be drawn into a natural poſture, and the mouth kept open by the bead, whereby the teeth, &amp;c. will be diſcovered : the glaſs is then to be filled with rum, and the cork ſealed down to prevent its exhalation. A label, containing the name and properties of the ſnake, is then to be affixed to the wax over the cork; and in this manner the ſnake will make a beautiful appearance, and may be preſerved a great number of years ; nor will the ſpirits impair or change the luſtre of its colours.</p></body></text></TEI>