<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:01Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>may enable them to ſupport the rank and diſcharge the duties of free men. This is doubtleſs the reaſon why it was not expreſsly prohibited by the divine Author of our religion, but ſuffered to vaniſh gradually before the mild influence of his Heavenly doctrines. It has vanished before theſe doctrines in moſt countries of Europe ; and we truſt that the time is at hand when our traffic in human fleſh with the inhabitants of Africa ſhall ceaſe ; and that the period is not very diſtant when the ſlaves in the West Indies ſhall be ſo much improved in moral and religious knowledge, as that they may be lately truſted with their own freedom. To ſet them free in their preſent ſtate of ignorance and depravity, is one of the wildeſt propoſals that the ardour of innovation has ever made. Such freedom would be equally ruinous to themſelves and to their maſters ; and we may  say of it what Cicero ſaid of ſome unſeaſonable indulgences propoſed to be granted to the ſlaves in Sicily ; Quae<hi rend="italic"> cum accidunt, nemo eſt, quin intelligat ruere illam rempublicam ; haec ubi veniunt, nemo est, qui ullam ſpem ſalutis reliquam eſſe arbitretur.</hi></p><p>SLAUGHTER. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Man-slaughter, Homicide, Murder, &amp;c.</hi></p><p>SLEDGE, a kind of carriage, without wheels, for the conveyance of very weighty things, as huge ſtones, bells, &amp;c. The sledge for carrying criminals, condemned for high treaſon, to execution, is called <hi rend="smallcaps">hurdle.  The</hi> Dutch have a kind of fledge on which they can carry a veſſel of any burden by land. It conſiſts of a plank of the length of the keel of a moderate ſhip, raiſed a little behind, and hollow in the middle; ſo that the sides go a little aſlope, and are furniſhed with holes to receive pins, &amp;c. The reſt is quite even.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sledge</hi> is a large ſmith’s hammer, to be uſed with both hands : of this there are two forts, the up-hand  sledge, which is uſed by under workmen, when the work is not of the largeſt sort ; it is uſed with both the hands before, and they ſeldom raiſe it higher than their head. But the other, which is called the about-ſledge, and which is uſed for battering or drawing out the largeſt work, is held by the handle with both hands, and ſwung round over their heads, at their arm’s end, to strike as hard a blow as they can.</p><p>SLEEP, that ſtate of the body in which, though the vital functions continue, the ſenſes are not affected by the ordinary impreſſions of external objects. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Dreams</hi> ; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Physiology,</hi> n⁰ 287.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SLEEP-Walker,</hi> one who walks in his ſleep. Many intances might be related of perſons who were addicted to this practice ; but it will be ſufficient to ſelect one remarkable inſtance from a report made to the Phydical Society of Lauſanne, by a committee of gentlemen appointed to examine a young man who was accuſtomed to walk in his ſleep.</p><p>“ The dispoſition to sleep-walking ſeems, in the opinion of this committee, to depend on a particular affection of the nerves, which both seizes and quits the patient dining ſleep. Under the influence of this affection, the imagination repreſents to him the objects that ſtruck him while awake, with as much force as if they really affected his senses ; but does not make him perceive any of thoſe that are actually presented to his ſenſes, except in ſo far as they are connected with the dreams which engrols him at the time. If, during this ſtate, the imagination has no determined purpose, he receives the impreſſion of objects as if he were awake;</p><p>only, however, when the imagination is excited to bend its attention towards them. The perceptions obtained in this ſtate are very accurate, and, when once received, the imagination renews them occaſionally with as much force as if they were again acquired by means of the ſenſes. Laſtly, theſe academicians ſuppoſe, that the impreſſions received during this ſtate of the ſenſes diſappear entirely when the person awakes, and do not return till the return of the ſame dispoſition in the nervous system.</p><p>"Their remarks were made on the Sieur Devaud, a lad thirteen years and a half old, who lives in the town of Vevey, and who is ſubject to that ſingular affection or disease called S<hi rend="italic">omnambulism</hi> or ſleep-walking. This lad poſſeſſes a ſtrong and robuſt conſtitution, but his nervous ſyſtem appears to be organiſed with peculiar delicacy, and to diſcover marks of the greateſt senſibility and irritability. His ſenſes of ſmell, taſte, and touch, are exquiſite ; he is ſubject to fits of immoderate and involuntary laughter, and he ſometimes likewiſe weeps without any apparent cause.</p><p>“ This young man does not walk in his ſleep every night ; ſeveral weeks ſometimes paſs without any appearance of a fit. He is ſubject to the diſeaſe generally two nights succeſſively, one fit laſting for ſeveral hours. The longeſt are from three to four hours, and they commonly begin about three or four o’clock in the morning.</p><p>“ The fit may be prolonged, by gently paſſing the finger or a feather over his upper lip, and this flight irritation likewiſe accelerates it. Having once fallen aſleep upon a ſtaircale, his upper lip was thus irritated with a feather, when he immediately ran down the ſteps with great precipitation, and reſumed all his accuſtomed activity. This experiment was repeated ſeveral times.</p><p>“ The young Devaud thinks he has obſerved, that, on the evenings previous to a fit, he is ſensible of a certain heavineſs in his head, but eſpecially of a great weight in his eyelids.</p><p>“ His ſleep is at all times unquiet, but particularly wſhen the fits are about to ſeize him. During his ſleep, motions are observable in every part of his body, with flatting and palpitations; he utters broken words, ſometimes sits up in his bed, and afterwards lies down again. He then begins to pronounce words more diſtinctly, he riſes abruptly, and acts as he is inſtigated by the dream that then posseſſes him. He is ſometimes in ſleep ſubject to continued and involuntary motions.</p><p>The departure of the fit is always preceded by two or three minutes of calm ſleep, during wſhich he ſnores. He then awakes rubbing his eyes like a perſon who has ſlept quietly.</p><p>“ It is dangerous to awaken him during the fit, eſpecially if it is done suddenly ; for then he sometimes falls into convulſions. Having riſen one night with the intention of going to eat grapes, he left the houſe, paſſed through the town, and went to a vineyard where he expected good cheer. He was followed by ſeveral perlons, who kept at ſome diſtance from him, one of whom  fired a piſtol, the noiſe of which inſtantly awakened him, and he fell down without ſenſe. He was carried home and brought to himſelf, when he recollected very well the having been awakened in the vineyard ; but nothing more, except the flight at being found there alone, which had made him swoon.</p><p>“ After the fits he generally feels a degree of laſſi-</p></body></text></TEI>