<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:20Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ſpread over all Europe, might offer to every adventurer the reſult of the researches, of which they are the object. By theſe means they ſuppoſed, that there would be a mats of information collected ; the intereſts of individuals would be loſt in the general intereſt ; and the one would materially aſſiſt the other. Impoſture and quackery would, by the ſame means, be baniſhed from a ſcience, which muſt be improved by philoſophy and experience; and the ſociety, they ſuppoſed, would find, in the confidence which they inſpired, the reward and the encouragement of their labours. They deſign, that the memoirs which they publiſh ſhall be ſhort and clear ; truth muſt be their balls, and every idle diſcuſſion, every foreign digreſſion, muſt be baniſhed ; politics and finance muſt be avoided, though the diſſertations may ſeem to lead towards them ; and they oblige themſelves to oppoſe the affectation of brilliancies, and the oſtentation of empty ſpeculation, when compared with plain, ſimple, and uſeful facts.</p><p>The object of the ſociety is phyſical geography ; mineralogy founded on chemiſtry; the management of ore in the different operations which it undergoes ; ſubterraneous geometry ; the hiſtory of mining ; founderies, and the proceſſes for the extraction of metals from the ores, either by fuſion or amalgamation, in every inſtance applied to practice. The end of this inſtitution is to collect, in the moſt extenſive ſenſe, every thing that can aſſiſt the operations of the miner, and to communicate it to the different members, that they may employ it for the public good, in their reſpective countries. Each member muſt conſider himſelf as bound to send to the ſociety every thing which will contribute to the end of its inſtitution ; to point out, with precision, the ſeveral facts and obſervations ; to communicate every experiment which occurs, even the unſuccessful ones, if the relation may ſeem to be advantageous to the public ; to communicate to the ſociety their examination of ſchemes, and their opinions on queſtions propoſed by it ; and to pay annually two ducats (about 18 s. 6 d.) to the direction every Eaſter. The ſociety, on the other hand, is bound to publiſh every novelty that ſhall be communicated to it ; to communicate to each member, at the member’s expence, the memoirs, designs, models, productions, and every thing connected with the inſtitution ; to answer all the neceſſary demands made, relating in any reſpect to mining ; and to give its opinion on every plan or project communicated through the medium of an honorary member.</p><p>The great centre of all intelligence is to be at Zellerfield in Hartz, Brunſwſick : but the ſociety is not fixed to any one ſpot ; for every particular ſtate ſome practical mineralogiſt is nominated as director. Among theſe are the names of Baron Born, M. Pallas, M. Charpentier, M. Prebra, and M. Henkel. Their office is to propoſe the members ; to take care that the views of the ſociety are pursued in the different countries where they reſide ; to anſwer the requeſts of the members of their country who are qualified to make them ; in caſe of the death of a director, to chooſe another ; and the majority is to determine where the archives and the ſtrong box is to be placed.</p><p>All the eminent mineralogists in Europe are members of this ſociety. It is erected on ſo liberal and ſo extenſive a plan, that we entertain the higheſt hopes of its ſucceſs ; and have only to add, that we wiſh much</p><p>to ſee the ſtudy of ſeveral other ſciences purſued in the ſame manner.</p><p>4.	<hi rend="italic">The Society for the Improvement of Naval Architecture,</hi> was founded in 1791. The object of it is to encourage every uſeful invention and diſcovery relating to naval architecture as far as ſhall be in their power, both by honorary and pecuniary rewards. They have in view particularly to improve the theories of floating bodies and of the reſiſtance of fluids ; to procure draughts and models of different veſſels, together with calculations of their capacity, centre of gravity, tonnage, &amp;c. ; to make obſervations and experiments themſelves, and to point out ſuch obſervations and experiments as appear beſt calculated to further their designs, and moſt deſerving thoſe premiums which the ſociety can bellow. But though the improvement of naval architecture in all its branches be certainly the principal object of this inſtitution, yet the ſociety do not by any means intend to confine themſelves merely to the form and ſtructure of veſſels. Every ſubordinate and collateral purſuit will claim a ſhare of the attention of the ſociety in proportion to its merits ; and whatever may have any tendency to render navigation more ſafe, ſalutary, and even pleaſant, will not be neglected.</p><p>This inſtitution owes its exiſtence to the patriotic diſpoſition and extraordinary attention of Mr Sewel a private citizen of London, who (though engaged in a line of buſineſs totally oppoſite to all concerns of this kind) has been led, by mere accident, to take ſuch occular notice of, and make ſuch obſervations on, the actual ſtate of naval architecture in this country, as naturally occurred to a man of plain underdtanding, zealous for the honour and intereſt of his country, and willing to bestow a portion of that time for the public good, which men of a different deſcription would rather have devoted to their own private advantage. His attention was the more ſeriouſly excited, by finding that it was the opinion of ſome private ſhip-builders, who, in a debate on the failure of one of our naval engagements, pronounced, that ſuch “ would ever be the caſe while that buſineſs (the conſtruction of our ſhips of war) was not ſtudied as a ſcience, but carried on merely by precedent ; that there had not been one improvement in our navy that did not originate with the French, who had naval ſchools and ſeminaries for the ſtudy of it ; and that our ſhips were not a match for thoſe of that nation either singly or in a fleet, &amp;c. &amp;c.”</p><p>In a ſhort time the ſociety were enabled to offer very conſiderable premiums for particular improvements in the conſtruction of our ſhipping, &amp;c. &amp;c. and alſo to encourage our philoſophers, mathematicians, and mechanics, to make ſatisfactory experiments, tending to aſcertain the laws of reſiſtance of water to ſolids of different forms, in all varieties of circumſtance. On this head the reward is not leſs than L. 100 pounds or a gold medal, Other premiums of 50, 30, and 20 guineas, according to the importance or difficulty of the particular ſubject or point of inveſtigation, are likewiſe offered, for different diſcoveries, inventions, or improvements. The terms of admiſſion into the ſociety are a ſubſcription of two guineas annually, or twenty guineas for life.</p><p>5.	<hi rend="italic">Society of Artists of Great Britain,</hi> which conſiſts of directors and fellows, was incorporated by charter in 1765, and empowered to purchaſe and hold hands, not</p></body></text></TEI>