<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:23:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>mangers, of that precious metal. In the time of the Romans this amazing plenty was very much diminiſhed ; however, their gleanings were by no means deſpicable, ſince in the ſpace of nine years they carried off 111,542 pounds of ſilver, and 4095 of gold, beſides an immenſe quantity of coin and other things of value. The Spaniards were always remarkable for their bravery, and ſome of Hannibal’s beſt troops were brought from thence. But as the Romans penetrated farther into the country than the Carthaginians had done, they met with nations whoſe love of liberty was equal to their valour, and whom the whole ſtrength of their empire was ſcarce able to ſubdue. Of theſe the moſt formidable were the Numantines, Cantabrians, and Aſturians.</p><p>In the time of the third Punic war, one Viriathus, a celebrated hunter, and afterwards the captain of a gang of banditti, took upon him the command of ſome nations who had been in alliance with Carthage, and ventured to oppoſe the Roman power in that part of Spain called <hi rend="italic">Lusitania,</hi> now Portugal. The praetor, named <hi rend="italic">Vetilius,</hi> who commanded in thoſe parts, marched againſt him with 10,000 men; but was defeated and killed, with the loss of 4000 of his troops The Romans immediately dispatched another praetor with 10,000 foot and 1300 horſe: but Viriathus having firſt cut off a detachment of 4000 of them, engaged the reſt in a pitched battle ; and having entirely defeated them, reduced great part oſ the country. Another praetor, who was ſent with a new army, met with the ſame fate ; ſo that, after the deſtruction of Carthage, the Romans thought proper to ſend a conſul named <hi rend="italic">Quintus Fabius,</hi> who defeated the Luſitanians in ſeveral battles, and regained two important places which had long been in the hands of the rebels. After the expiration of Fabius’s conſulate, Viriathus continued the war with his uſual ſucceſs, till the ſenate thought proper to ſend againſt him the conſul Q. Cæcilius Metellus, an officer of great valour and experience. With him Viriathus did not chooſe to venture a pitched battle, but contented himſelf with acting on the defenſive ; in conſequence of which the Romans recovered a great many cities, and the whole of Tarraconian Spain was obliged to ſubmit to their yoke. The other conſul, named <hi rend="italic">Servilianus,</hi> did not meet with the ſame ſucceſs ; his army was defeated in the field and his camp was nearly taken by Viriathus. Notwithſtanding the good fortune of Metellus, however, he could not withſtand the intrigues of his countrymen againſt him, and he was not allowcd to finiſh the war he had begun with ſo much ſucceſs. In reſentment for this he took all imaginable pains to weaken the army under his command: he diſhanded the flower of his troops, exhauſted the magazines, let the elephants die, broke in pieces the arrows which had been provided for the Cretan archers, and threw them into a river. Yet, after all, the army which he gave up to his ſuccessor Q. Pompeius, consiſting of 30,000 foot and 2000 horſe, was ſufficient to have cruſhed Viriathus if the general had known how to uſe it. But, inſtead of oppoſing Viriathus with ſucceſs, the imprudent conſul procured much more formidable enemies. The Termantians and Numantines, who had hitherto kept themſelves independent, offered very advantageous terms of peace and alliance with Rome ; but Pompeius insisted on their delivering up their arms. Upon this,</p><p>war was immediately commenced, The conſul with great confidence inveſted Numantia; but being repulſed with conſiderable loſs, he ſat down before Termantia, where he was attended with ſtill worſe ſucceſs. The very firſt day, the Termantines killed 700 of his legionaries ; took a great convoy which was coming to the Roman camp ; and having defeated a conſiderable body of their horſe, puſhed them from poſt to poſt till they came to the edge of a precipice, where they all tumbled down, and were daſhed to pieces. In the mean time Servilian, who had been continued in his command with the title of <hi rend="italic">proconſul,</hi> managed matters ſo ill, that Viriathus ſurrounded him on all ſides, and obliged him to ſue for peace. The terms offered to the Romans were very moderate ; being only that Viriathus ſhould keep the country he at that time poſſeſſed, and the Romans remain maſters of all the reſt. This peace the proconſul was very glad to ſign, and afterwards got it ſigned by the ſenate and people of Rome.</p><p>The next year Q. Pompeius was continued in his command againſt the Numantines in Farther Spain, while Servilius Cæpio, the new conſul, had for his province Hither Spain, where Viriathus had eſtabliſhed his new ſtate. Pompeius undertook to reduce Numantia by turning aſide the ſtrearn oſ the Durius, now the Douro, by which it was ſupplied with water ; but, in attempting this, ſuch numbers of his men were cut off, that, finding himſelf unable to contend with the enemy, he was glad to make peace with them on much worſe terms than they had offered of their own accord. The peace, however, was ratified at Rome; but in the mean time Cæpio, deſirous of ſhowing his proweſs againſt the renowned Viriathus, prevailed upon the Romans to declare war againſt him without any provocation. As Cæpio commanded an army greatly ſuperior to the Luſitanians, Viriathus thought proper to ſue for peace ; but finding that Cæpio would be ſatisfied with nothing leſs than a ſurrender at diſcretion, he resolved to ſtand his ground. In the mean time, the latter having bribed ſome of the intimate companions of Viriathus to murder him in his ſleep, he by that infamous method put an end to a war which had laſted 14 years, very little to the honour of the republic.</p><p>After the death of Viriathus, the Romans with like treachery ordered their new conſul Popilius to break the treaty with the Numantines. His infamous conduct met with the reward it deſerved ; the Numantines ſallying out, put the whole Roman army to flight with ſuch ſlaughter, that they were in no condition to act during the whole campaign. Mancinus, who ſucceeded Popilius, met with ſtill worſe ſucceſs ; his great army, conſiſting of 30,000 men, was utterly defeated by 4000 Numantines, and 20,000 of them killed in the purſuit. The remaining 10,000, with their general, were pent up by the Numantines in ſuch a manner that they could neither advance nor retreat, and would certainly have been all put to the sword or made priſoners, had not the Numantines, with a generoſity which their enemies never poſſeſſed, offered to let them depart upon condition that a treaty ſhould be concluded with them upon very moderate terms. This the conſul very willingly promiſed, but found himſelf unable to perform. On the contrary, the people, not ſatisfied with declaring his treaty null and void, ordered him to be delivered up to the Numantines. The latter refuſed to accept him, un-</p></body></text></TEI>