<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:21:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>when any of the unfortunate authors attempted to retaliate whoſe works he had perhaps juſtly cenſured.</p><p>Among other controverſies in which his engagements in this publication involved him, the moſt material in its conſequences was that occaſioned by his remarks on a pamphlet publiſhed by Admiral Knowles. That gentleman, in defence of his conduct on the expedition to Rochfort, publiſhed a vindication of himſelf ; which falling under the Doctor’s examination, produced ſome very ſevere ſtrictures both on the performance and on the character of the writer. The admiral immediately commenced a proſecution againſt the printer ; declaring at the ſame time that he deſired only to be informed who the writer was, that if he proved to be a gentleman he might obtain the ſatisſaction of one from him. In this affair the Doctor behaved both with prudence and with ſpirit. Deſirous of compromiſing the diſpute with the admiral in an amicable manner, he applied to his friend Mr Wilkes to interpoſe his good offices with his opponent. The admiral, however, was inflexible ; and juſt as ſentence was going to be pronounced againſt the printer, the Doctor came into court, avowed himſelf the author of the Strictures, and declared himſelf ready to give Mr Knowles any ſatisſaction he choſe. The admiral immediately commenced a freſh action againſt the Doctor, who was found guilty, fined L.100, and condemned to three months impriſonment in the King’s Bench. It is there he is ſaid to have written The Adventures of Sir Launcelot Greaves, in which he has deſcribed ſome remarkable characters, then his fellow-priſoners.</p><p>When Lord Bute was called to the chief adminiſtration of affairs, he was prevailed upon to write in defence of that nobleman’s meaſures ; which he did in a weekly paper called the <hi rend="italic">Briton.</hi> This gave riſe to the famous North Briton ; wherein, according to the opinion of the public, he was rather baffled. The truth is, the Doctor did not ſeem to poſſeſs the talents neceſſary for political altercation. He wanted temper and coolneſs ; and his friends accuſed his patron of having denied him the neceſſary information, and even neglected the fulfilling of ſome of his other engagements with him. Be that as it will, the Doctor is ſaid not to have forgotten him in his ſubſequent performances.</p><p>Beſides the Briton, Dr Smollet is ſuppoſed to have written other pieces in ſupport of the cauſe he eſpouſed. The Adventures of an Atom, in two volumes, are known to be his production.</p><p>His conſtitution being at laſt greatly impaired by a ſedentary life and aſſiduous application to ſtudy, he went abroad for his health in June 1763, and continued in France and Italy two years. He wrote an account of his travels in a series of letters to ſome friends, which were afterwards publiſhed in two volumes octavo, 1766. During all that time he appears to have laboured under a conſtant fit of chagrin. A very slight peruſal of theſe letters will ſufficiently evince that this obſervation is founded in fact, and is indeed a melancholy inſtance of the influence of bodily diſtemper over the beſt diſpoſition.</p><p>His relation of his travels is actually cynical ; for which Storne, in his Sentimental Journey, has animadverted on him under the character of Smelfungus. The Doctor lived to return to his native country: but his</p><p>health continuing to decline, and meeting with freſh mortifications and diſappnintments, he went back to Italy, where he died in October,21. 1771. He was employed, during the laſt years of his life, in abridging the Modern Univerſal Hiſtory, great part of which he had originally written himſelf, particularly the hiſtories of France, Italy, and Germany.</p><p>He certainly met with many mortifications and diſappointments ; which, in a letter to Mr Garrick, he thus feelingly expreſſes : “ I am old enough to have ſeen and obſerved, that we are all playthings of Fortune ; and that it depends upon ſomething as inſignificant and precarious as the toſſing up of a halfpenny, whether a man riſes to affluence and honours, or continues to his dying day ſtruggling with the difficulties and diſgraces of life.”</p><p>It would be needleſs to expatiate on the character of a man ſo well known as Dr Smollet, who has, beſides, given ſo many ſtrictures of his own character and manner of living in his writings, particularly in Humphrey Clinker ; where he appears under the appellation of <hi rend="italic">Mr Serle,</hi> and has an interview with Mr Bramble; and his manner of living is described in another letter, where young Melford is ſuppoſed to dine with him at his houſe in Chelſea. No doubt he made money by his connections with the bookſellers ; and had he been a rigid economiſt, or endued with the gift of retention (an expreſſion of his own), he might have lived and died very independent. However, to do juſtice to his memory, his difficulties, whatever they were, proceeded not from extravagance or want of economy. He was hoſpitable, but not oſtentatiouſly so ; and his table was plentiful, but not extravagant. No doubt he had his failings ; but ſtill it would be difficult to name a man who was ſo reſpectable for the qualities of his head, or more amicable for the virtues of his heart.</p><p>Since his death a monument has been erected to his memory near Leghorn, on which is inſcribed an epitaph written in Latin by his friend Dr Armſtrong, author of The Art of Preſerving Health, and many other excellent pieces. An inscription written in Latin was likewiſe inſcribed on a pillar erected to his memory on the banks of the Leven, by one of his relations.</p><p>To theſe memoirs we are extremely sorry to add, that so late as 1785 the widow of Dr Smollet was reſiding in indigent circumſtances at Leghorn. On this account the tragedy of Venice Preſerved was acted for her benefit at Edinburgh on the 5th of March, and an excellent prologue ſpoken on that occaſion.</p><p>The pieces inſerted in the poſthumous collection of Dr Smollet’s plays and poems are, The Regicide, a tragedy: The Repriſal, a comedy; Advice and Reproof, two ſatires ; The Tears of Scotland ; Verſes on a Young Lady; a Love Elegy, in imitation of Tibullus; two Songs ; a Burleſque Ode ; Odes to Mirth, to Sleep, to Leven Water, to Blue-ey’d Ann, and to Independence.</p><p>SMUGGLERS, perſons who import or export prohibited goods without paying the duties appointed by the law.</p><p>The duties of cuſtoms, it is ſaid, were originally inſtituted, in older to enable the king to afford protection to trade againſt pirates : they have ſince been continued as a branch of the public revenue. As duties</p></body></text></TEI>