<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:19:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>nal positions. Their ſmell reſembles that of hemp ; the fibres are whiter, but more dry and harſh than thoſe of hemp. The harſhneſs is owing to a greeniſh gluten which connects the fibres; and the white colour muſt always be obtained at the expence of having this kind of thread leſs ſupple ; when of its natural hue, ſt is very ſoft and flexible. This deſcription belongs chiefly to the ſide ; but it will alſo apply to the malva criſpa, Peruviana, and Mauritiana. The malva criſpa gave, however, the greateſt quantity of fibres, and its gluten was moſt copious. The fibres of the ſida abutilon, and the malva criſpa, are the longeſt and the ſtrongeſt ; thoſe of the Peruviana and Mauritiana are the ſhorteſt and weakeſt. The fibres of thoſe plants which had lost their leaves are leſs ſtrong, though of equal length with thoſe which had preſerved them.</p><p>SIDDEE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sedee : </hi>an Arabic title, by which the Abyssinians or Habaſhys are always diſtinguiſhed in the courts of Hindoſtan ; where, being in great repute for firmneſs and fidelity, they are generally employed as commanders of forts or in poſts of great truſt.</p><p>SIDEREAL <hi rend="smallcaps">year.</hi> See ASTRONOMY-Index</p><p>SIDERIA, in natural hiſtory, the name of a genus of cryſtals, uſed to expreſs thoſe altered in their figure by particles of iron. Theſe are of a rhomboidal figure, and compoſed only of six planes. Of this genus there are four known ſpecies. 1. A colourleſs, pellucid, and thin one ; found in conſiderable quantities among the iron ores of the foreſt of Dean in Glouceſterſhire, and in ſeveral other places. 2. A dull, thick, and brown one; not uncommon in the same places with the former. And, 3. A black and very gloſſy kind, a foſſil of great beauty ; found in the ſame place with the others, as also in Leiceſterſhire and Suſſex.</p><p>SIDE RITE, a ſubſtance diſcovered by Mr Meyer, and by him ſuppoſed to be a new metal ; but Meſſrs Bergman and Kirwan have diſcovered that it is nothing elſe than a natural combination of the phoſphoric acid with iron. Mr Klaproth of Berlin alſo came to the ſame concluſion, without any communication with Mr Meyer. It is extremely difficult to ſeparate this acid from the metal ; however, he found the artificial compound of phoſphoric acid and iron to agree in its properties with the calx ſideri alba obtained by Bergman and Meyer from the cold-ſhort iron extracted from the ſwampy or marſhy ores. The diſcovery of this ſubſtance, however, may be accounted an important affair in chemiſtry, as we are thus furniſhed with an in senſe quantity of phoſphoric acid, which might be applied to uſeful purpoſes if it could be ſeparated from the metal.</p><p>SIDERITIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ironwort,</hi> in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of didynamia,∙ and to the order of oymnoſpermia ; and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 42d order, V<hi rend="italic">erticillatae.</hi> The ſtamina are within the tube of the corolla. There are two ſtigmas, one of which is cylindrical and concave ; the other, which is lower, is membranous, ſhorter, and ſheathing the other. The ſpecies are 13.	1. The Canarienſis, or Canary</p><p>ironwort, which is a native of Madeira and the Canary iſlands ; 2. The Candicans, wſhich is alſo a native of Madeira ; 3. The Syriaca, a native of the Levant ; 4. The Perſoliata, a native of the Levant ; 5. The Montana, a native of Italy and Auſtria ; 6. The Elegans ; 7. The Romana, a native of Italy ; 8. The Incana, a</p><p>native of Spain ; 9. The Hyſſopifolia, a native of Italy and the Pyrenees ; 10. The Scordioides, a native of the ſouth of France; 11. The Hirſuta, which is indigenous in the ſouth of Europe; 12. The Ciliata; 13. The Lanata.</p><p>SIDEROXYLON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Iron-wood,</hi> in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of pentandria, and to the order of monogynia ; and in the natural ſyſtem ranging under the 43d order, <hi rend="italic">Dumoſae.</hi> The corolla is cut into 10 parts, the laciniæ or ſegments being incurvated alternately ; the ſtigma is ſimple ; the berry contains five ſeeds. There are ten ſpecies: 1. Mite ; 2. Inerme, ſmooth iron-wood ; 3. Melanophleum, laurelleaved iron-wood ; 4. Fcetidiſſimum ; 5. Cymoſum—- both natives of the Cape of Good Hope ; 6. Sericeum, ſilky iron-wood, a native of New South Wales ; 7. Tenax, ſilvery-leaved iron-wood, a native of Carolina ; 8, Lycioides, willow-leaved iron-wood, a native of North America; 9. Spinoſum, thorny iron-wood or argan, a native of Morocco ; 10. Decandrum.</p><p>The wood of theſe trees being very cloſe and ſolid, has given occaſion for this name to be applied to them, it being ſo heavy as to sink in water. As they are natives of warm countries, they cannot be preſerved in this country unless they are placed, the two former in a warm stove, the others in a green-houſe. They are propagated by ſeeds, when theſe can be procured from abroad.</p><p>SIDNEY (Sir Philip), was born, as is ſuppoſed, at Penſhurſt in Kent in the year 1554: His father was Sir Henry Sidney, an Iriſh gentleman, and his mother Mary the eldeſt daughter of John Dudley duke of Northumberland. He was ſent when very young to Chriſt- church college at Oxford, but left the univerſity at 17 to ſet out on his travels. After visiting France, Germany, Hungary, and Italy, he returned to England in 1575, and was next year ſent by Queen Elizabeth as her ambaſſador to Randolph emperor of Germany. On his return he viſited Don John of Auſtria, governor of the Netherlands, by whom he was received with great reſpect. In 1579, when Queen Elizabeth ſeemed on the point of concluding her long projected marriage with the duke of Anjou, Sir Philip wrote her a letter, in which he diſſuaded her from the match with unuſual elegance of expreſſion, as well as force of reaſoning, About this time a quarrel with the earl of Oxford occaſioned his withdrawing from court ; during which retirement he is ſuppoſed to have written his celebrated romance called <hi rend="italic">Arcadia.</hi></p><p>In 1585, after the queen’s treaty with the United States, he was made governor of Fluſhing and maſter of the horſe. Here he diſtinguiſhed himſelf ſo much both by his courage and conduct, that his reputation roſe to the higheſt pitch. He was named, it is pretended, by the republic of Poland as one of the competitors for that crown, and might even have been elected had it not been for the interference of the queen. But his illustrious career was ſoon terminated ; for in 1586 he was wounded at the battle of Zutphen, and carried to Arnheim, where he soon after died. His body was brought to London, and buried in St Paul’s cathedral. He is deſcribed by the writers of that age as the moſt perfect model of an accompliſhed gentleman that could be formed even by the wanton imagination of poetry or fiction. Virtuous conduct, polite converſation, heroic va-</p></body></text></TEI>