<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-18T21:22:44Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Lincolnſhire, and their fleſh of a finer grain. In conſequence of this abundance of black cattle, great quantities of cheeſe are made in it, of which that of Cheddar is thought equal to Parmeſan. In the hilly parts are found coal, lead, copper, and lapis calaminaris. Wood thrives in it as well as in any county oſ the kingdom. It abounds alſo in peaſe, beans, beer, cyder, fruit, wildfowl, and ſalmon ; and its mineral waters are celebrated all over the world.</p><p>The riches of this county, both natural and acquired, exceed thoſe of any other in the kingdom, Middlesex and Yorkſhire excepted. The woollen manufacture in all its branches is carried on to a very great extent ; and in ſome parts of the county great quantities of linen are made. If to theſe the produce of various Other commodities in which it abounds is added, the amount of the whole muſt undoubtedly be very great. Its foreign trade muſt alſo be allowed to be very extenſive, when it is conſidered that it has a large trade for ſea coal, and poſſeſſes, beſides other ports, that of Briſtol, a town of the greateſt trade in England, next to London.</p><p>Beſides ſmall ſtreams, it is well watered and ſupplied with fiſh by the rivers Severn, Avon, Parrel, Froome, Ax, Torre, and Tone. Its greateſt hills are Mendip, Pouldon, and Quantock, of which the firſt abounds in coal, lead, &amp;c. The rivers Severn and Parrel breed very fine ſalmon. The chief town is Briſtol.</p><p>SOMERTON, an ancient town in Somerſetſhire, from whence the county derives its name. It is 123 miles from London ; it has five ſtreets, containing 241 houſes, which are moſtly built of the blue ſtone from the quarries in the neighbourhood. It is governed by conſtables, and has a hall for petty ſeſſions. The market for corn is conſiderable, and it has ſeveral fairs for cattle. The church has what is not very frequent, an octa<hi rend="italic">ngular</hi> tower with six bells. N. Lat. 51.4. W. Long. 3.53.</p><p>SOMNAMBULI, perſons who walk in their ſleep. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Sleepwalkers.</hi></p><p>SOMNER (William), an eminent Engliſh antiquary, was born at Canterbury in 1606. His firſt treatiſe was The Antiquities of Canterbury, which he dedicated to Archbiſhop Laud. He then applied himself to the ſtudy of the Saxon language ; and having made himſelf maſter of it, he perceived that the old gloſſary prefixed to Sir Roger Twisden’s edition of the laws of King Henry I. printed in 1644, was faulty in many places; he therefore added to that edition notes and obſervations valuable for their learning, with a very uſeful gloſſary. His Treatiſe of Gavelkind was finiſhed about 1648, though not publiſhed till 1660. Our author was zealouſly attached to King Charles I. and in 1648 he publiſhed a poem on his ſufferings and death. His skill in the Saxon tongue led him to inquire into moſt of the European languages ancient and modern. He aſſiſted Dugdale and Dodlworth in compiling the <hi rend="italic">Monasticon Anglicanum.</hi> His Saxon Dictionary was printed at Oxford in 1659. died in 1669.</p><p>SON, an appellation given to a male child conſidered in the relation he bears to his parents. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Parent </hi>and <hi rend="smallcaps">Filial </hi><hi rend="italic">Piety.</hi></p><p>SONATA, in muſic, a piece or compoſition, intend</p><p>ed to be performed by inſtruments only; in which ſenſe it ſtands oppoſed to <hi rend="italic">cantata,</hi> or a piece deſigned for the voice. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cantata.</hi></p><p>The ſonata then, is properly a grand, free, humorous compoſition, diverſified with a great variety of motions and expreſſions, extraordinary and bold ſtrokes, figures, &amp;e. And all this purely according to the fancy of the compoſer ; who, without confining himſelf to any general rules of counterpoint, or to any fixed number or meaſure, gives a looſe to his genius, and runs from one mode, meaſure, &amp;c. to another, as he thinks fit. This ſpecies of compoſition had its rise about the middle of the 17th century ; thoſe who have moſt excelled in it were Baſſani and Corelli. We have ſonatas of i, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and even 8 parts, but uſually they are performed by a ſingle violin, or with two violins, and a thorough baſs for the harpſichord ; and frequently a more figured baſs for the bais viol, &amp;c.</p><p>There are a thouſand different ſpecies of ſonatas ; but the Italians usually reduce them to two kinds. <hi rend="italic">Suοnate de chiesa,</hi> that is, ſonatas proper for church muſic, which uſually begin with a grave ſolemn motion, suitable to the dignity and ſanctity of the place and the ſervice, after which they ſtrike into a briſker, gayer, and richer manner. Theſe are what they more peculiarly call ſonatas. S<hi rend="italic">uοnate de camera,</hi> or ſonatas for the chamber, are properly ſerieſes of ſeveral little pieces, for dancing, only compoſed to the fame tune. They usually begin with a prelude or little ſonata, ſerving as an introduction to all the rest : afterwards come the allemand, pavane, courant, and other ſerious dances ; then jigs, gavotε, minuets, chacons, passecailles, and other gayer airs : the whole compoſed in the ſame tune or mode.</p><p>SONCHUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">sow-thistle,</hi> in botany: A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">ſyngeneſia,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">polygamia aequalis</hi> ; and in the natural ſyſtem ranged under the 49th order, <hi rend="italic">Cοmpositae.</hi> The receptacle is naked; the calyx is imbricated, bellying and conical; the down of the seed is ſimple, feſſile, and very ſoft ; the ſeed is oval and pointed. There are 13 ſpecies ; the maritimus, paluſtris, fruticoſus, arvenſis, oleraceus, tenerrimus, plumieri, alpinus, floridanus, sibiricus, tataricus, tuberoſus, and canadeniis. Four of theſe are natives of Britain.— 1. <hi rend="italic">Palustris,</hi> marſh ſow-thistle. The ſtem is erect, from six to ten feet high, branched and hairy towards the top : the leaves are firm, broad, half pinnated, ſerrated, and ſharp-pointed ; the lower ones ſagittate at the baſe : the flowers are oſ a deep yellow, large, and diſperſed on the tops of the branches : the calyx is rough. It is frequent in marſhes, and flowers in July or Auguſt.— 2. <hi rend="italic">Arvenſis,</hi> corn ſow-thiſtle. The leaves are alternate, runcinate, and heart-ſhaped at the baſe ; the root creeps under ground ; the ſtem is three or four feet high, and branched at the top. It grows in corn fields, and flowers in Auguſt.— 3. <hi rend="italic">Oleraceus,</hi> common ſow-thiſtle. The ſtalk is ſucculent, piſtular, and a cubit high or more ; the leaves are broad, embracing the ſtem, generally deeply ſinuated, ſmooth or prickly at the edges; the flowers are of a pale yellow, numerous, in a kind of umbel, and terminal ; the calyx is ſmooth. It is frequent in waſte places and cultivated grounds.—4. <hi rend="italic">Alpinus,</hi> blue-flowered ſow-thiſtle. The ſtem is erect, purpliſh, branched, or ſimple, from three to six feet high : the leaves are large, ſmooth, and ſinu-</p></body></text></TEI>