<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-18T21:18:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>SIAM PROPER CONTD in which he who remains longeſt under it is eſteemed innocent. They have another
                proof, by ſwallowing pills, which their prieſts adminiſter with ſevere imprecations
                ; and the party who keeps them in his ſtomach without vomiting is thought to be
                innocent.</p>
            <p>All theſe trials are made in the preſence of the magiſtrates and people ; and the
                king himſelf frequently directs them to be performed, when crimes come before him by
                way of appeal. Sometimes he orders both the informer and priſoner to be thrown to
                the tigers : and the perſon that eſcapes by his not being ſeized upon by thoſe
                beaſts, is ſufficiently juſtified.</p>
            <p>They maintain the doctrine of tranſmigration, believing in a pre-exiſtent ſtate, and
                that they ſhall paſs into other bodies till they are ſufficiently purified to be
                received into paradiſe. They believe likewiſe that the ſoul is material, but not
                ſubject to the touch ; that it retains the human figure after quitting a body of
                that ſpecies ; and that when it appears to perſons with whom it was acquainted,
                which they ſuppoſe it to do, the wounds oſ one that has been murdered will then be
                viſible. They are of opinion that no man will be eternally punished ; that the good,
                after ſeveral tranſmigrations, will enjoy perpetual happineſs ; but that thoſe who
                are not reformed will be doomed to tranſmigration to all eternity. They believe in
                the exiſtence of a Supreme Being ; but the objects of their adoration are departed
                faints, whom they conſider as mediators or interceſſors for them ; and to the honour
                of this numerous tribe both temples and images are erected.</p>
            <p>The men of this country are allowed a plurality of women ; but excepting one, who is
                a wife by contract, the others are only concubines, and their children deemed
                incapable of any legal inheritance. Previous to every nuptial contract, an
                aſtrologer muſt be conſulted, who calculates the nativity of the parties, and
                determines whether their union is likely to prove fortunate or otherwiſe. When his
                prognoſtication is favourable, the lover is permitted to visit his miſtreſs three
                times, at the laſt of which interviews the relations being preſent, the marriage
                portion is paid, when, without any religious ceremony performed, the nuptials are
                reckoned complete, and ſoon after conſummated. A few days after the talapoin viſits
                the married couple, ſprinkles them with water, and repeats a prayer for their
                proſperity.</p>
            <p>The practice in Siam respecting funerals, is both to burs and bury the dead. The
                corpſe being laid upon the pile, it is ſuffered to burn till a conſiderable part is
                confirmed, when the remainder is interred in a burying- place contiguous to ſome
                temple. The reason which they give for not burning it entirely to aſhes is, that
                they ſuppoſe the deceaſed to be happy when part of his remains eſcapes the fire.
                Inſtead of a tombſtone, they erect a pyramid over the grave. It formerly was the
                cuſtom to bury treaſure with the corpſe ; but longer experience evincing, that the
                ſacrilegious light in which robbing the graves was conſidered did not prevent the
                crime, they now discontinue the ancient practice, and inſtead of treaſure bury only
                painted papers and other trifles.</p>
            <p>The two principal rivers are the Menan and the Mecon, which riſe in the mountains of
                Tartary, and run to the ſouth ; the former paſſing by the city of Siam, falls into
                the bay of the ſame name, in the 13th de</p>
            <p>gree of north latitude ; and the latter running through Laos and Cambodia, diſcharges
                itſelf into the Indian ocean in the 9th degree of north latitude.</p>
            <p>The capital of the country is Siam, called by the natives <hi rend="italic"
                    >Siyothoya,</hi> situated in the 101st degree of eaſt longitude, and in the 14th
                degree of north latitude, being almoſt encompaſſed by the branches of the river
                Menan. It is about 10 miles in circumference within the walls, but not a sixth part
                of the ground is occupied by buildings. In the vacant ſpaces there are near 300
                pagodas or temples, round which are ſcattered the convents of the prieſts and their
                burying-places. The ſtreets of the city are ſpacious, and ſome have canals running
                through them, over which is a great number of bridges. The houses stand on pillars
                of the bamboo cane, and are built of the ſame materials ; the communication between
                different families, during the winter ſeaſon, being carried on as in other tropical
                countries by means of boats. The grounds belonging to the ſeveral tenements are
                ſeparated by a palliſado, within which the cattle are houſed in barns, erected
                likewiſe upon pillars, to preſerve them from the annual inundation.</p>
            <p>SIBBALDIA, in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs oſ pentandria, and to
                the order of pentagynia ; and in the natural syſtem arranged under the 35th order,
                    <hi rend="italic">Senticoſae.</hi> The calyx is divided into ten ſegments. The
                petals are five, and are inſerted into the calyx. The ſtyles are attached to the
                side of the germens. The ſeeds are five. There are three ſpecies belonging to this
                genus, the <hi rend="italic">procumbens, erecta,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >altaica.</hi> The procumbens, or reclining sibbaldia, is a native of North
                Britain, having never been discovered in the ſouthern parts of the iſland. It grows
                on Ben-Lomond and Ben-Mor, within a mile of the ſummit. It is diſtinguiſhed by a
                procumbent or trailing ſtem ; by three leaves growing on the top of a ſmall
                footſtalk, which are triſid at the extremity, and ſomewhat hairy. The flowers are
                yellow, and bloſſom in July or Auguſt.</p>
            <p>SIBENICO, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sebenico,</hi> the name of a city and province of
                Dalmatia. The province of Sibenico runs along the ſea for more than 30 miles ;
                reaches in ſome places above 20 miles within land, and comprehends above 70 iſlands.
                The city of Sibenico is situated near the mouth of the river Cherca, in the Gulf of
                Venice,</p>
            <p>35 miles north of Spalatto, and 25 ſouth-eaſt of Zara. E. Long, 16⁰ 46', N. Lat. 440
                17'. It belongs to the Venetians. It is defended on one side by a caſtle, which held
                out againſt repeated attacks of the Turks, and towards the ſea by a fort.</p>
            <p>SIBERIA, a large country, comprehending the moſt northerly parts of the Russian
                empire in Asia. It is bounded on the eaſt by the eaſtem ocean ; on the ſouth by
                Great Tartary ; on the west by Ruſſia ; and on the north by the Frozen Ocean. It is
                about 2000 miles in length from eaſt to west, and 750 miles in breadth from north to
                south.</p>
            <p>At what time this country was firſt inhabited, or by whom it was peopled, we are
                entirely ignorant ; but writings have been found in it when it was diſcovered, which
                ſhows that it muſt have been early known to a civilized people @@*. The Ruffians,
                from whom we have received our knowledge, knew nothing of it before the middle of
                the 16th century. In the reign of John Bafilowitz I. indeed, an incursion had been
                made into Siberia,</p>
            <p>@@@[m]* Bell's Travels.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
