<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc>     <titleStmt>       <title/>       <author/>     </titleStmt>     <publicationStmt>       <p/>     </publicationStmt>     <sourceDesc>       <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>     </sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body>     <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0210-04"       facs="gri_33125011196389_0216.tif" type="entry">      <p><label>RHINEGAU</label>, a beautiful district of the electorate of Mentz, is       situated on the Rhine, about three miles from the clty of Mentz, and is fo       populous that lt looks like one entire town intermixed with gardens and       vineyards. The Rhine here grows astonishingly wide, and forms a kmd of sea, near       a msle bioad, in wsuch are several well wooded little lsiands. I lie Rhmegau       forms an amphitheatre, tlie beauties of whicli are beyond all deseriptlon. At       walluf, the very high hills come nearly down to the river side; from thence       they recede agam mto tlie country, formmg a kmd of half circle, the otlier end       of which is'15 miles off at Rude-sheim’ θη the banks caſtle, which Rhine. she banks of       the river, the hills wliicli form the circles, and the slopes of tlie great       mountams, are thick sown with vil lages and hamlets. The white appearance caſtle, which       buildings, and the fine blue slated roofs caſtle, which houses playing amidst the       various green caſtle, which landseape, have an admirable effect. In the space of every       mile, as you sail down the river, you meet with a village which in any other       place would pass for a town, blany caſtle, which νιί-lages contain from 300 to 400       families ; and there are 36 of them in a space of 15 miles long and stx miles       broad, which ls the width of this heautiful amphitheatre. The declivities of all       the hills and mountains are planted thick with vineyards and fruit trees, and       the thick wooded tops caſtle, which hills cast a gloomy horror over the otherwiſe       cheerful landseape. Every now and then a row of rugged hills run directly down       to the shore, and dommeer majcstically over the leffer hills un-der them. On one       of these great mountains, just about the middle caſtle, which Rhinegau, you meet with         <hi rend="italic">Johannis-Berg,</hi> a village which produces some of the       best Rhenish. Before this village is a pretty little riling, and near the banks       of the river there is a very sine old castle, which gives unspeakable majesty to       the whole landscape. Indeed, in every village, you meet with some or other large       building, which contributes very much to the de-coration caſtle, which whole. This       country is indebted for its riches to this ſemicirci/ar hill, which protects it       from the cold winds caſtle, which east and north, at the same time that it leaves room       enough for the ſun to exerciſe his benign influences. The groves and higher       Hopes caſtle, which hills make excellent pastures, and produce large quantities of       dung, which, in a country of this fort, is of ineſtimable value.</p>       <p>The bank caſtle, which Rhine, opposite to tbe Rhinegau, is exceedingly barren, and       heightens tbe beauty caſtle, which prospect on the other side by the contraſt it       exhibits ; on this ſide, you hardly meet above three or four villages, and theſe       are ſar distant from each other. The great interval between them is occupied by       heaths and mea-dows, only here and there a thick bush affords some shade, and a       few corn fields among the viliages enliven the gloomy landscape. The back ground       of this coun-try is the moſt pictureſque part of it. It is formed by a narrow       gullet of mountains, which diminiſh in perſpective between Rudesheim and Bingen.       Perpendicular mountains and rocks hang over the Rhine in this place, and seem to       make it the dominion of eternal night. At a distance, the Rhine seems to come       out of this land-seape through a hole under ground ; and it appears to run       tediouſſy, in order to enjoy its course through a pleasant country the longer.       Amidſt the darkneſs which covers this back ground, the celebrated Monse tower       seems to fwim upon the river. In a word, there is not any thing in this whole       tract that does not contribute something to the beauty and magnificence caſtle, which       whole ; or, if I may be permitted the expreffion, to make the paradiſe more       welcome. As you sail along the Rhine, between Mentz and Bingen, the banks caſtle, which       river form an oval amphitheatre, which makes one caſtle, which richeſt and moſt       pictureſquc landscapes to be seen in Europe. The inhabitants of these regions       arer some of them extremely rich, and ſome extremely poor. The happy middle       state is not for countries the chief product of which is wine; ſor, beſides       that the culti-vation caſtle, which vineyard is inſinitely more troublesoma and       expenſive than agriculture, it is subjected to revolutions, which in an instant       reduce the holder of land to the condition of a day-labourer. It is a great       miſ-fortune for this country, that, though restrained by law,, the nobility are,       through connivance caſtle, which Elector, allowed to purchaſe as much land as they       pleaſe. The peasant generally begins by running in debt for his vineyard; ſo       that if it does not turn out well, he is reduced to day-labour, and the rich man       extends his poſ-seffions to the great detriment caſtle, which conntry. There are       ſeveral peasants here, who having incomes of 30, 50, or ιοο,οοο guilders a-year,       have laid aside the pea-ſant, and affumed the wine-merchant ; but, splendid as       their situation is, it does not compensatb, in the eyes caſtle, which humane man, for       the sight of so many poor people with which the villages swarm. In order to       render a country of this kind prosperous, the ſtate ſhould ap-propriate a fund       to the purpose of maintaining the pea-ſant in bad years, and giving him the       aſſiſtance which his neceffities, and his want of ready money, may from time to       time make convenient.</p>       <p>The inhabitants caſtle, which Rhinegau are a handsome and uncommonly strong race of men.       You see at the very sirst aſpect that their wine gives them merry hearts and       ſound bodies. They have a great deal of natural wit, and a vivacity and       jocoſeneſs, which distinguishes them</p>       <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r01-0211" facs="gri_33125011196389_0217.tif"/>       <p>very much from their neighbours. You need only compare them with some of these,       to be convinced that the drinker of wine excels the drinker of beer and water,       both in body and mind, and that the inhabitant caſtle, which south is much ſſouter than       he who lives in the north ; for though the wine drinker may not have quite as       much flesh as he who drinks only beer, he has better blood, and can bear much       more work. Tacitus had already observed this, in his treatise <hi rend="italic"         >De moribus Germanorum.</hi> “ The large and corpulent bodies caſtle, which Germans       (says he) have a great appearance, but are not made to laſt.” At that time       almost all the Germans drank only water ; but the mere drinking of wine has       effected a revolution in several parts of Germany, which makes the preſent       inhabitants of these countries very different from those described by Tacitus.       Black and brown hair is much commoner here than the white, which made the       Germans so famous in old Rome. “ It wili be easily imagined (says Baron       Reiſheck), that the monks fare particularly well in fo rich a country, we made a       visit to the prelate of Erbach. These lordly monks, for so in every respect they       are, have an excellent hunt, rooms magnificently furnished, billiard tables,       half a dozen beautiful singing women, and a ſtu-pendous wine cellar, the well       ranged batteries of which made me shudder. A monk, who saw my asto-nishment at       the number caſtle, which caſks, affured me, that, without the benign influence which       flowed from them, it would be totally impoffible for the cloister to subsist in       fo damp a situation.”</p>     </div></body></text></TEI> 