<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb09-r01</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The lowest Fungi in which a sexual process has been observed are the Chytridiacese (<hi rend="italic">Polyphagus EugUnm),</hi>  the Mucorini, and the Entomophthorere. In these, when it occurs, it takes the form of conjugation, with the production of zygospores. Conjugation is here effected in essentially the same manner as that described above for the conjugation among the Alg;c, by the fusion of two similar sexual organs. Conjugation of planogametes has been observed by Sorokin in Tetrachytrium and in Haplocystis, probably belonging to the Chytridiacea?, a fact of some interest as it is the only case of this form of the sexual process known in the Fungi.</p><p>In Protomyces and the Ustilaginere a process takes place which appears to be of a sexual nature, resembling the conjugation of the Mucorini. Certain reproductive cells of an elongated form, termed <hi rend="italic">sporidia,</hi>  are produced, which become connected by a transverse canal so that they then resemble the letter H. No zygospore is formed, but the conjugated sporidia are its equivalent. The j question of the sexual nature of this process is still under discussion, but it is made highly probable by the fact that, in all fully investigated cases, the sporidia are incapable of independent j germination.</p><p>In the allied groups of the Peronosporeae and Saprolegnie® two kinds of sexual organs are present, male and female, which correspond to the antlieridia and oogonia of the Algae. The female organ is here also termed an oogonium, and, like that of the Alga;, it may produce one oosphere (Peronosporeae) or many (most Saprolegniese). The male organ is also usually termed an anthe-ridium, but it is sometimes spoken of as a <hi rend="italic">pollinodium</hi>  on account of the mode in which it effects the fertilization of the oosphere. In one of the plants allied to these groups—namely, in <hi rend="italic">Monoble- \ pharis spheerica,</hi>  according to Cornu—the protoplasm of the antheridium becomes differentiated into motile antherozoids ; this is the only case of the kind known among the Fungi. In the other members of these groups in which fertilization takes place the antheridium lies in contact with the oogonium, and produces at its apex a delicate tubular outgrowth, which bores its way through the wall of the oogonium and comes into contact witlvan oosphere ; the tube then opens, and protoplasm from the antheridium passes through into the oosphere and fuses with it to form an oospore.</p><p>In the Ascomycetes sexual organs are very commonly present, t but it is only in a few cases that a sexual process has been observed actually to take place. The sexual oi’gans differ considerably in their form in the different genera. In some (<hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>  Gymnoascus, Eremascus, Eurotium, Penicillium) the sexual organs are similar ; they are unicellular or multicellular hyphse, but in some the female organ, termed in the Ascomycetes the <hi rend="italic">ascogonium</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">carpo-gonium,</hi>  may be distinguished from the male organ, which is a pollinodial antheridium like that of the Peronosporese, in that it is wound into a close spiral. In others <hi rend="italic">{e.g.,</hi>  Erysiphese, Ascobolus, <hi rend="italic">Pyronema {Pezizd\ confluens)</hi>  the sexual organs are readily distinguishable. In the Erysipheae and in Pyronema the ascogonium is a single relatively large ovoid cell ; that of Pyronema produces a delicate tubular outgrowth, the trichogyne ; the antheridium also is unicellular, but it is more slender. In Ascobolus the ascogonium consists of a row of five or six relatively large cells ; the antheridium is a slender multicellular hypha. In all these cases the sexual organs are developed in such close proximity to each other that they come into contact. In other Ascomycetes belonging to the Discomycetous Lichens (Collema, Synechoblastus, Leptogium, Physma), and to the Pyrenomycetes (Polystigma), the antheridial filaments, termed <hi rend="italic">sterigmata,</hi>  are developed at a distance from the female organ in separate receptacles, <hi rend="italic">spermogonia. </hi>In this case the formation of male cells is a necessity. Accordingly cells, termed spermatia, are produced from the sterigmata by abstraction, which resemble the male cells of the Florideae in that they are non-motile and have a cell-wall.</p><p>With regard to the process of fertilization, it must be premised that in no Ascomycete is the protoplasm of the ascogonium ever differentiated into an oosphere. When the sexual organs are ascogonia and pollinodial antheridia, fertilization takes place by the fusion of the undifferentiated protoplasmic contents of the two organs, a mode of fertilization which recalls the conjugation in the Mucorini, and in the Conjugatie among the Algxe. This has only been observed to take place in Eremascus and in Pyronema; in the latter the antheridium applies its apex to the trichogyne of the ascogonium, the intervening walls are absorbed, and the protoplasm of the two organs coalesces. Although this process of fertilization resembles the conjugation occurring in the Mucorini, the product is very different. The product of conjugation in the Mucorini is a single cell, the zygospore ; the product of fertilization in the Ascomycetes is a “lumber of cells, termed <hi rend="italic">ciscospores</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">carpospores.</hi>  Thus in Eremascus the product of fertilization is a unicellular capsule, the <hi rend="italic">ascus,</hi>  in which eight ascospores are formed. In Pyronema the fertilized ascogonium enlarges and • gives rise to a number of outgrowths which produce asci; at the same time a number of h}<hi rend="sup">r</hi>plue grow up from below around the developing asci, some of which produce delicate filaments, termed</p><lb/><p><hi rend="italic">paraphyses,</hi>  which lie amongst the asci, whereas others form an investing wall. The result is the formation of a fructification, termed an <hi rend="italic">apothccium.</hi>  Within each ascus eight spores are formed.</p><p>In those Ascomycetes which have spermatia fertilization is effected, as in the Floride* among the Algie, by the fusion of a spermatium with the trichogyne. The result is the same as in Pyronema : the fertilized ascogonium gives rise to hyphee which bear asci, and these, together with sterile liyphse, form a fructification.</p><p>It is of interest to note the similarity between the products of fertilization in these Ascomycetes and in the Florideie. In both cases the female organ produces no differentiated oosphere, and in both cases the product of its fertilization is a many-spored fructification. It was pointed out, in speaking of the Floridese, that each carpospore is the equivalent of a fertilized oosphere (oospore) ; this holds good also with regard to the carpospores (ascospores) of  the Ascomycetes.</p><p>It may be that a similar sexual process takes place in the other forms mentioned above, viz., the Erysipheie, Penicillium, Sordaria, &amp;c., but it has not been observed ; in any case, the ascogonium in all these plants gives rise to asci and ascospores, and a more or less complex fructification is produced. But there is also some ground £ for believing that in some at least of these cases the sexual organs, c though morphologically differentiated, are functionless. For there 1 are clear indications of sexual degeneration in the Ascomycetes. j In some cases, for instance <hi rend="italic">{e.g.,</hi>  Chsetomium, Melanospora), no ( antheridium can be distinguished, but the ascogonium eventually produces asci nevertheless. In others <hi rend="italic">{e.g.,</hi>  Xylaria, as far as known at present) no male organ is produced, but there is an ascogonium which does not, however, give rise to asci; the asci, as well as the rest of the fructification, arise from the vegetative liyphiB. In others, again <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi>  Claviceps, Cordiceps, Pleospora), all trace of the sexual organs has disappeared, but a fructification containing ascospores is produced, as in Xylaria, from the vegetative hyphse. In others, finally, no ascospores are known, the only reproductive cells being the characteristic asexually produced stylospores.</p><p>In the remaining groups of Fungi, the Uredineae and the Basidio-mycetes, no sexual reproduction is known. In the Basidiomycetes no kind of sexual organ has been discovered. In the Uredinese spermatia are commonly produced, as in the Ascomycetes mentioned above, but no female organ is known ; however, fructifications termed <hi rend="italic">secidia</hi>  are in some cases developed. These resemble somewhat those of the Ascomycetes, but differ in that here the spores (<hi rend="italic">secidiospores)</hi>  are fonned by abstraction, and not in asci as in the Ascomycetes.</p><p>It may be suggested that the ascospores of the asexual Ascomycetes and the secidiospores of the Uredinese should not be included in an account of the sexual reproduction of the Fungi. It is true that these spores are asexually produced, but their evident homology with the sexually produced spores makes it inconvenient to treat of them apart. They differ from the sexually produced spores in that they are developed apogamously.</p><p>Under the name Archegoniata we may conveniently group together the Muscinese and the Vascular Cryptogams (Plerido-pliyta). The sexual organs, as also the process of fertilization, are essentially the same throughout. The female organ produces a single oosphere, and is termed an <hi rend="italic">archcgonium</hi>  ; it is essentially similar to the oogonium of the Tliallophytes, the only difference being that, whereas the archcgonium is multicellular, the oogonium is unicellular. The male organ, here also termed the antheridium, is likewise multicellular, and gives rise to a larger or smaller number of motile antherozoids. Fertilization is effected by the fusion of an antherozoid with the oosphere, which then clothes itself with a cell-wall and becomes an oospore.</p><p>In the Phanerogams the sexual organs are essentially of the nature of archegonia and of antheridia, but they are somewhat! modified and are called by other names. The female organ of the Gymnosperms, termed a <hi rend="italic">corpusculum,</hi>  closely resembles the archcgonium of the Archegoniata, and produces a single oosphere. In the Angiosperms, the female organ is much reduced, consisting only of three cells, one of which is the oosphere, the other two being the <hi rend="italic">synergicla</hi>  which assist in the process of fertilization ; the organ is termed the egg-apparatus. The male organ in the Phanerogams is a unicellular filament termed the pollen-tube ; its protoplasm does not undergo differentiation into antherozoids. The sexual organs of the Phanerogams recall those of the Perono-sporca; and the Saprolegnieae ; in both cases the female organ produces an oosphere, and in neither does the protoplasm of the antheridium produce antherozoids. The process of fertilization will be described subsequently.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Physiology of Reproduction</hi>.—From the fact that in even the most highly organized plants an isolated portion of one member is capable of producing, not merely a member like itself, but other members also, so that a new</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>