<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>eb09-r01</title><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>HEPSOLD, a family of German instrument makers. <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann Georg Repsold </hi>(1771-1830), was born at Wremen in Hanover on September 23, 1771, became an engineer and afterwards chief of the fire brigade in Hamburg, where he started business as an instrument maker early in the present century. He was killed by the fall of a wall during afire on January 14, 1830. The business has been continued by his sons Georg and Adolf and his grandsons Johannes and Oscar.</p><lb/><p>J. G. Repsold introduced essential improvements in the meridian circles by substituting microscopes (on Ramsden’s plan) for the verniers to read the circles, and by making the various parts perfectly symmetrical. For a number of years the tirm was foremost in this special branch and furnished meridian circles to the observatories at Hamburg, Königsberg, Pulkova, &amp;c.; later on the activity in this direction declined, while Pistor and Martins of Berlin rose to eminence in the manufacturing of transit circles. But after the discon-<hi rend="sup">!</hi> tinuance of this firm that of Repsold has again come to the front, not only in the construction of transit circles, but also of equatorial I mountings and more especially of heliometers (see<hi rend="smallcaps">Micrometer).</hi></p><lb/><p>REPTILES</p><lb/><p>\NTELIXN/EAN writers comprised the animals which popularly are known as Tortoises and Turtles, Crocodiles, Lizards and Snakes, Frogs and Toads, Newts and Salamanders, under the name of Oviparous Quadrupeds or four-limbed animals which lay eggs. Linnaeus, desirous of giving expression to the extraordinary fact that many of these animals pass part of their life in the water and part on land,@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  substituted the name of Amphibia for the ancient term. Subsequent French naturalists (Lyonnet@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  and Brisson@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi>) considered that the creeping mode of locomotion was a more general characteristic of the class than their amphibious habits, and consequently proposed the scarcely more appropriate name of Reptiles.</p><p>As naturalists gradually comprehended the wide gap existing between Frogs, Toads, ¿c., on the one hand, and the other Oviparous Quadrupeds on the other, they either adopted the name of <hi rend="italic">Batrachia</hi>  for the former and that of <hi rend="italic">Amphibia</hi>  for the latter, or they restricted the term <hi rend="italic">Amphibia</hi>  to Batrachians, calling the remainder of these creatures Reptiles. Thus the term <hi rend="italic">Amphibia</hi>, as used by various authors, may apply (1) to all the various animals mentioned, or (2) to Batrachians only—and thus it has been used in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Amphibia </hi>in the present work. The term Reptiles is used (1) by some for all the animals mentioned above, and (2) by others, as in the present article, for the same assemblage of animals after the exclusion of Batrachians. Other terms more or less synonymous with Amphibians and Reptiles in their different senses have been used by the various systematists, as we shall see hereafter.</p><p>Equally varying are the limits of the term “Saurians,” which occurs so frequently in every herpetological treatise. At first it comprised living Crocodiles and Lizards only, with which a number of fossil forms were gradually associated. As the characters and affinities of the latter became better known, some of them were withdrawn from the Saurians, and at present it is best to abandon the term altogether.</p><p>History and Literature.</p><p><hi rend="italic">a. The General Subject.</hi></p><p>By some feature of their organization or some peculiarity in their economy Reptiles have always forced themselves upon the observation of man or excited his imagination, so that certain kinds are mentioned in the earliest written records or have found a place among the fragments of the oldest relics of human art. Such evidences of a popular knowledge of Reptiles, however, form no part of a succinct review of the literature of the subject such as it is proposed to give here. We distinguish in it five periods :—(1) the Aristotelian; (2) the Linnaean (formation of a class <hi rend="italic">Amphibia</hi>, in which Reptiles and Batrachians are mixed); (3) the period of the elimination of Batrachians as one of</p><lb/><p>the Reptilian orders (Brongniart); (4) that of the separation of Reptiles and Batrachians as distinct subclasses ; (5) that of the recognition of a class <hi rend="italic">Reptilia</hi>  as part of the</p><p><hi rend="italic">Sauropsida</hi>  (Huxley).</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Aristotelian Period.</hi>—As in other branches of Ar zoology, we have to start with <hi rend="smallcaps">Aristotle, </hi>who was the first to deal with the Reptiles known to him as members of a distinct portion of the animal kingdom, and to point out the characteristics by which they resemble each other and differ from other vertebrate and invertebrate animals. As the plan of his work, however, was rather that of a comparative treatise of the anatomical and physiological characters of animals than their systematic arrangement and definition, his ideas about the various groups of Reptiles are not distinctly expressed, but must be gleaned from the terms which lie employs. And even when we make due allowance for the fact that we are in possession of only a part of his writings, we cannot but perceive that he paid less attention to the study of Reptiles than to that of other classes; this is probably due to the limited number of kinds with which he could be acquainted from the fauna of his own country, and to which only very few extra-European forms, like the Crocodile, were added from other sources. And, whilst we find in some respects a most remarkable accuracy of knowledge, there is sufficient evidence that lie neglected every-day opportunities of information, as if Reptiles had not been a favourite study. Thus, lie has not a single word about the metamorphoses of Batrachians, which he treats of in connexion with Reptiles.</p><p>Aristotle makes a clear distinction between the scute or scale of a Reptile, which he describes as &lt;£oXts, and that of a Fish, which lie designates as <hi rend="italic">Xen-is.</hi>  He mentions Reptiles (1) as oviparous quadrupeds with scutes, viz., Saurians and Chelonians; (2) as oviparous apodals, viz., Snakes ; (3) as oviparous quadrupeds without scutes, viz., Batrachians. He considered the first and second of these three groups as much more nearly related to each other than to the third. He says : —</p><p>“ The genus of Snakes resembles that of Lizards, nearly all the characters being common to both, if the Lizard be conceived of as prolonged and without legs. They possess scutes, and are similar to Lizards above and below, but they lack testicles; and, like Fishes, they possess two excretory ducts which coalesce, and the uterus is large and bipartite. In other respects their internal parts are like those of Lizards, save that all the intestines are long and narrow. The tongue is narrow, long, black, and very exsertile. It is a peculiarity of Snakes and Lizards that they possess a bifid tongue ; but the points of the tongue of Snakes are fine like hairs. All Snakes are “ carcharodont ” (have acute teeth); they have as many ribs as there are days in the month, viz., 30. Some say that Snakes recover the loss of an eye ; the tail is reproduced in Lizards and Snakes when cut off,” &amp;c.</p><p>Thus accurate statements and descriptions are sadly mixed with errors and stories of, to our eyes, the most absurd and fabulous kind. The most complete accounts are those of the Crocodile (chiefly borrowed from Herodotus) and of the Chameleon, which Aristotle evidently knew from personal observation, and which he had dis-</p><lb/><p>@@@    “*Polymorpha in liis amphibiis natura duplicem vitam plerisque coneessit. ”</p><p>@@@    <hi rend="italic">Théologie des Insectes de Lesser</hi>  (Paris, 1745), i. 91, note 5.</p><p>@@@    <hi rend="italic">Règne animal </hi><hi rend="italic">divisé en nev</hi><hi rend="italic">f </hi><hi rend="italic">classes</hi>(Paris, 1756).</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>