<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0499-02" facs="gri_33125011196389_0505.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSICRUCIANS</label>
a name affumed by a ſect or cabal of hermetical philoſophers ; who aroſe, as it has been ſaid, or at leaſt became firſt taken notice of, in Germany, in the beginning of the fourteenth century. They bound themſelves together by a ſolemn ſecret, which they all ſwore inviolably to preſerve ; and obliged themſelves, at their admiſſion into the order, to a ſtrict obſervance of certain eſtabliſhed rules. They pretended to know all ſciences, and chiefly medicine ; whereof they publiſhed themſelves the reſtorers. - They pretended to be maſters of abundance of important ſecrets, and, among others, that of the philoſopher’s ftυne ; all which they affirmed to have received by tradition from the ancient Egyptians, Chaldeans, the Magi, and Gymnoſo-phiſts. '1 hey have been diſtinguiſhed by ſeveral names, accommodated to the ſeveral branches of their doctrine. Becauſe they pretend to protract the period of human life, by means of certain noſtrums, and even to reſtore youth, they were called <hi rend="italic">Immortales</hi> ; as they pretended to know all things, they have been called <hi rend="italic">Iliuminati ;</hi> and becauſe they have made no appearance for ſeveral years, unlefβ the ſect of Illuminated which lately ſtarted up on the continent derives its origin from them, they have been called the <hi rend="italic">invijible brothers.</hi> Their ſociety i$</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0500" facs="gri_33125011196389_0506.tif"/>
<p>frequently ſigned by the letters F. R. C. which ſome among them interpret <hi rend="italic">fratres roris cοcti ;</hi> it being pretended, that the matter of the philoſophers Hone is dew concocted, exalted, &amp;c. Some, who are no friends to free-maſonry, make the preſent flouriſhing ſociety c*' .ree-mafons a branch of Roſicrucians ; or rather the Roſicrucians themſelves, under a new name or relation, viz. as retainers to building. And it is certain, there are ſome free-maſons who have all the characters of Roſicrucians ; but how the æra and original oſ ma-ſonry (ſee Masonry), and that of Roſicrucianiſm, here fixed from Naudæus, who has written expreſsly on the ſubject, conſiſt. we leave others to judge.</p><p>Notwithſtanding the pretended antiquity oſ the Roſicrucians, it is probable that the alchemiſts, Paracelſiſts, or fire-philoſophers, who ſpread themſelves through al∙ moſt all Europe about the cloſe of the iixteenth century, aſſumed about this period the obſcure and ambiguous title of Roſicrucian brethren, which commanded at firſt ſome degree of reſpect, as it ſeemed to be borrowed from the arms of Luther, which were a croſs placed upon a roſe. But the denomination evidently appears to be derived from the ſcience of chemiſtry. It is not compounded, ſays Moſheim, as many imagine, of the two words <hi rend="italic">roſa</hi> and <hi rend="italic">crux,</hi> which ſignify roſe and croſs, but of the latter of theſe words, and the Latin <hi rend="italic">rοs,</hi> which ſigniſies dew. Of all natural bodies, dew was deemed the moſt powerful diſſolvent of gold ; and the croſs, in the chemical language, is equivalent to light, becauſe the figure of a croſs -R exhibits, at the ſame time, the three letters of which the word ∕κx <hi rend="sup">,</hi> , or iight, is compounded. Now <hi rend="italic">lux</hi> is called, by this ſect, the leed or menftruum of the red dragon, or, in other words, that groſs and corporeal light which, when properly digeſted and modified, produces gold. Hence it follows, if this etymology be admitted, that a Roſicrucian philoſopher is one who, by the intervention and aſ-ſiſtance of the dew, ſeeks for light, or, in other words, the ſubſtance called the philoſopher’s ſtone. The true meaning and energy of this denomination did not eſcape the penetration and ſagacity of Gaſſendi, as appears by his <hi rend="italic">Examen Philoſophiai Fludclαηα,</hi> ſect. ιy. tom. iii. p. 261. And it was more fully explained by Renaudot, in his <hi rend="italic">Conferences Publiques,</hi> tom. iv. p. 87.</p><p>At the head of theſe fanatics were Robert Fludd, an Engliſh phyſician, Jacob Behmen, and Michael Mayer ; but if rumour may be credited, the preſent Illuminated have a head of higher rank. The common principles, which ſerve as a kind of centre of union to the Roſicrucian ſociety, are the following : They all maintain, that the diſſolution of bodies, by the power of fire, is the only way by which men can arrive at true wiſdom, and come to diſcern the firſt principles of things. They all acknowledge a certain analogy and harmony between the powers of nature and the doctrines of religion; and believe that the Deity governs the kingdom of grace by the ſame laws with which he rules the kingdom of nature ; and hence they are led to uſe chemical denominations to expreſs the truths of religion. They all hold, that there is a fort of divine energy, or foul, diffuſed through the frame of the uni-verſe, which ſome call the <hi rend="italic">argheus,</hi> others the <hi rend="italic">univerfal fpirit,</hi> and which others mention under different appellations. They all talk in the moſt ſuperſtitious manner of what they call the ſignatures of things, of the power</p><p>oſ the ſtars over all corporeal beings, and their particular influence upon the human race, of the efficacy of magic, and the various ranks and orders of demons — Theſe demons they divide into two orders, <hi rend="italic">ſylphs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gnomes ;</hi> which ſupplied the beautiful machinery of Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Rape oſ the Lock.</hi> I n fine, the Roſicrucians and all their fanatical deſcend'ants agree in throwing out the moſt crude incomprehenſrble notions and ideas, in the moſt obſcure, quaint, and unuſual expreſſions.—Moſh. Eccl. Hiſh vol. iv. p. 266, &amp;c. Engliſh edition, 8vo. See Beehmen and Theosophists.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>