<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0545-01"
                facs="gri_33125011196389_0551.tif" type="entry">

                <p><label>RUDDIMAN</label> (Thomas), one of the moſt eminent grammarians which
                    Scotland has produced, was born in October 1674 at Raggel, in the pariſh of
                    Boyndie and county of Banff. His father James Ruddiman was a farmer, and
                    ſtrongly attached to the houſe of Stuart.</p>
                <p>Mr Ruddiman was inſtructed in the principles oſ Latin grammar at the
                    pariſh-ſchool of Boyndie, where his application was fo vigorous, and his
                    progreſs ſo rapid, that he quickly ſurpaſſed all his claſs-fellows. Hi« maſter
                    George Moriſon, who was a ſkilful and attentive teacher, being unwilling to
                    check his ardour for learning, permitted him to follow the impulſe oſ his
                    genius, and to advance without waiting the flow progreſs of the other boys.</p>
                <p>The pleaſure which the youthful mind receives from vivid deſcription, though
                    wild and romantic, approaches to ecſtacy, and often makes an impreſſion which
                    remains indelible. While at ſchool, the firſt book which charmed the opening
                    mind of Ruddiman was Ovid’s Meta-morphoſes ; nor did he ceaſe to reliſh the
                    beauties of this author when his judgment was mature, for during the reſt of his
                    life Ovid was his favourite poet.</p>
                <p>At the age of ſixteen he became anxious to purſue his ſtudies at the univerſity
                    ; but his father thinking him too young, oppoſed his inclination. Hearing of the
                    competition trial, which was annually held at King’s College, Aberdeen, for a
                    certain number of burſaries on the foundation of that univerſity, Ruddiman’s
                    ambition was kindled. Without the knowledge of his father, and with only a
                    ſingle guinea in his pocket, which his fiſter had privately given him, he ſet
                    out ſor that place. On the road he was met by a company of gypſeys, who robbed
                    him of his coat, his ſhoes, his ſtcckings, and his guinea. This misfortune did
                    not damp his enterpriſing ſpirit : He continued his journey to Aberdeen,
                    preſented himſelf before the profeffors as a candidate ; and though he had
                    neither clothes to give him a decent appearance nor friends to recommend him, he
                    gained the firſt prize.</p>
                <p>After attending the univerſity four years, he obtained the degree of maſter of
                    arts ; an honour of which he was always proud. The theſis ſays, the diſputation
                    on this occaſion laſted <hi rend="italic">ab</hi> <hi rend="italic">aurora uſque ad ve/perum,</hi> i. e,</p>
                <p>ſrom morning till night.” Tho’ Ruddiman was only twenty year« of age when he
                    left the university, it ap. pears from a book intitled <hi rend="italic">Rhetomcorum Libri très,</hi> com-poſed before this period, but never
                    publiſhed, that he had then read the Roman claſſics with uncommon attention and
                    advantage.</p>
                <p>He was. ſoon after engaged as a tutor to the ſon of Robert Young, Eſq; of
                    Auldbar, the great grandſon of Sir Peter Young, who under the direction of
                    Buchanan had been preceptor of James Vi. His income here muſt have been very
                    ſmall, or his ſituation unplea-ſant ; for within a year be accepted the office
                    of ſchoolmaſter in the pariſh of Laurence-kirk The proſeſſion of ſchoolmaſter in
                    a country-pariſh at that period could, open no field ſor ambition, nor proſpect
                    of great emolument; for by an act of parliament paſſed in 1633 <hi rend="sub">t</hi> the ſalary appropriated to this office could not be increaſed above 200
                    merks Scots, or L. 1 1 : 2 : 2∣∙ Sterling. In diſcharging the duties of this
                    humble but important ſtation, it is probable that he uſed Simfon <hi rend="sup">,</hi> ⅜ <hi rend="italic">Rudimenta Grammati&lt;a,</hi> which was
                    then generally taught in the northern ſchools, and by which he himſelf had been
                    inſtructed in the principles of Latin grammar.</p>
                <p>When Ruddiman had ſpent three years and a half in this employment, the
                    celebrated Dr Pitcairne happening to paſs through Laurence-kirk, was detained in
                    that village by a violent ſtorm. Pitcairne wanting amuſement, inquired at the
                    hoſteſs if ſhe could procure any agreeable companion to bear him company at
                    dinner. She replied, that the ſchoolmaſter, though young, was ſaid to be
                    learned, and, though modeſt, ſhe waδ fore could talk. Pitcairne was delighted
                    with the con-verſation and learning of his new companion, invited him to
                    Edinburgh, and promiſed him his patronage.</p>
                <p>When Ruddiman arrived in Edinburgh, the advocates library, which had been
                    founded eighteen years before by Sir George Mackenzie, attracted his curio-ſity
                    and attention, and he was ſoon after appointed aſ-ſiſtant-keeper under Mr
                    Spottiſwoode the principal librarian. His ſalary for executing this laborious
                    office was L. 8 : 6 : 8. He had befides a ſmall honorary preſent from thoſe who
                    were admitted advocates for correcting their theſes : he was alſo paid ſor
                    copying manuſcripts for the uſe of the library. And the faculty, before hc had
                    held the office two years, were ſo highly pleaſed with his conduct, that they
                    made him a preſent of 50 pounds Scots, or L. 4 : 3 : 4 Sterling.</p>
                <p>During the fitting of the court of ſeſſion he attended the library from ten till
                    three. But this confinement did not prevent him from engaging in other laborious
                    duties : A part of his time was occupied in teaching young gentlemen the Latin
                    language. Some he attended at their lodgings, ſome waited upon him, and ſome
                    reſided in his own houſe. An exact lift of the names of thoſe who attended him,
                    expreſſing the date of their entry, and the ſums which he was to receive from
                    each, has been found in his pocket-book ; a curious relick, which is ſtill
                    preſerved.</p>
                <p>When Ruddiman’s merit as ä ſeholar became better known, his aſſiſtance was
                    anxiouſly ſolicited by thoſe who were engaged in literary publications.
                    Freebairne, a reſpectable bookſeller of that period, prevailed upon him to
                    correct and prepare , for the preſs Sir Robert Sibbald’s <hi rend="italic">Introduttio ad hi/loriam rerum a Romanis gejla-</hi> <hi rend="italic">rum in eα Borealis Britannia</hi> <hi rend="italic">parte qua ultra murum</hi></p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0546" facs="gri_33125011196389_0552.tif"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Picticum est.</hi> He received for his labour L.3 Sterling.
                    At the requeſt of Mr Spottiſwoode librarian, for L. 5 Sterling he contributed
                    his aid to the publication of Sir Robert Spottiſwoode’a Practiques of the Laws
                    of Scotland.</p>
                <p>In 1707 he commenced auctioneer, an employment not very ſuitatle to the
                    dignified character of a man of letters : but to this occupation he was probably
                    impelled by neceſſity ; for upon balancing his accounts at the end of the
                    preceding year, the whole ſurplus was L. 28, 2s. with proſpects of L. 236 : 7 :
                    6 Scots. Ruddiman had a family ; and ſeems to have been a ſtranger to that
                    fooliſh pride which has ſeduced ſome literary men into the opinion, that it is
                    more honourable to ſtarve than have recourſe to an occupation which men of rank
                    and opulence are accuſtomed to deſpiſe. The fame year he publiſhed an edition of <hi rend="italic">Voluſeni de Animi Tranquillitate Dialogue,</hi> to which
                    he prefixed the life of Voluſenus. Voluſenus or Wilſon was a learned Scotſman,
                    and had the honour to be patroniſed by Cardinal Wolſey (ſee Wilson). In 1709 he
                    publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Johnſtoni Cantici Solomonis Paraphraſis Poetica,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Johnſtoni Cantica</hi> with, notes, which he
                    dedicated in verſe to his friend and patron Dr Pitcairne. The edition conſiſted
                    of 200 copies. The expence of printing amounted to L. 5, 10s. Sterling, and he
                    ſold them at a ſhilling each copy.</p>
                <p>The philological talents of Ruddiman were next directed to a more important
                    object, in which they became more conſpicuous and uſeful. Freebairne the
                    bookſeller propoſed to publiſh anew edition of the Scot-tiſh tranſlation of
                    Virgil’s Æneid by Gawin Douglas biſhop of Dunkeld. Of the contributions which
                    ſome eminent characters of the age preſented, the moſt valuable were ſupplied by
                    Ruddiman. Freebairne acknowledged in general terms this obligation, but has not
                    done him the juſtice to inform the reader what theſe valuable contributions
                    were, and Ruddiman’s modeſty reſtrained him from publicly aſſerting his claim.
                    From the pocket-book which has been already mentioned, it appears that Ruddiman
                    corrected the work and wrote the gloſſary ; and there is ſtrong reaſon to
                    believe that he was the author of the 42 general rules for aſſiſting the reader
                    to underſtand the language of Douglas. To thoſe who wiſh to be acquainted with
                    the ancient language of this iſland, the gloſſary will be a treaſure, as it
                    forms a compendious dictionary of the Anglo-Saxon. For this elaborate work
                    Ruddiman was allowed L 8 : 6 : 8 Sterling.</p>
                <p>The reputation of Ruddiman had now extended to a diſtance. He was invited by the
                    magiſtrates of Dundee to be rector of the grammar-ſchool of that town ; but the
                    faculty of advocates, anxious to retain him, augmented his ſalary to. L. 30 : 6
                    : 8 Sterling, and he declined the offer.</p>
                <p>In 1711 he aſſiſtcd Biſhop Sage in publiſhing Drummond of Hawthornden’s works ;
                    and performed the fame favour to Dr Abercrombie, who was then preparing for the
                    preſs his Martial Atchievements.</p>
                <p>In 1713 he was deprived of his friend Dr Pitcairne. On this occaſion he
                    teſtified all the reſpect which friend-ſhip could inſpire to the memory of his
                    deceaſed patron and ſurviving family. He compoſed Pitcairne’s epitaph, and
                    conducted the ſale of his library, which was dilpoſed of to Peter the Great.</p>
                <p>In 1714 the Rudiments of the Latin tongue were publiſhed. Eighteen or nineteen
                    Latin grammars, compoſed by Scotchmen, had appeared before This period ; yet
                    ſuch is the intrinſic value of this little treatiſe, that it ſoon ſuperſeded all
                    other books on the ſubject, and is now taught in all the grammar-ſchools in
                    Scotland. It has alſo been tranſlated into other languages.</p>
                <p>He was next called upon to publiſh the works of Buchanan. The value of theſe he
                    enhanced much by an elaborate preface, his <hi rend="italic">Tabula Regum
                        Scotia Chronologica,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Propriorum Nominum
                        Interpretalio.</hi> The interpretation of proper names was highly requiſite
                    ; for Buchanan has ſo diſguiſed them in the Roman dreſs, that the original name
                    is ſcarcely diſcernible ; and the preface puts the reader on his guard againſt
                    the chronological errors and factious ſpirit of the hiſtory. Ruddiman alſo added
                    a learned diſſertation, intitled <hi rend="italic">De Metris Buchananais
                        Libellas,</hi> and ſubjoined annotations critical and political on the
                    Hiſtory of Scotland. As he eſpouſed the caufe of Queen Mary, he raiſed againſt
                    himſelf an hoſt of enemies, and gave occaſion to that celebrated controverſy
                    which has been carried on with much keenneſs and animoſity, and with little
                    intermiſſion, even to the preſent times. For this work Ruddiman was promiſed L.
                    40 Sterling.</p>
                <p>He had now been ſo long accuſtomed to ſuperintend the preſs, that he was led to
                    form the plan of erecting a printing-office himſelf <note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial" n="1"> It has long been an object of curio
                        ſity to aſcertain the time at which the art of printing was introduced into
                        Scotland. Mr Robertſon, the keeper of the records, has lately diſcovered a
                        patent of King James IV. which renders it certain that a printing-preſs was
                        firſt eſtabliſhed at Edinburgh during the year 1507, 30 years after Caxton
                        had brought it into England. See Printing, p. 522. </note>. Accordingly, in
                    the year 1715, he commenced printer in partnerſhip with his brother Walter, who
                    had been regularly bred to the bufineſs. Some years after he was appointed
                    printer to the univerſity, along with James Davidſon book-ſeller.</p>
                <p>The firſt literary ſociety formed in Scotland was inſtituted in the year 1718.
                    It probably derived its origin from the factious and turbulent ſpirit of the
                    times. The learned, anxious perhaps to find ſome reſpite from the political
                    diſſenfions of the day,. endeavoured to procure it in elegant amuſement; for one
                    of the fundamental articles of the new aſſociation was, that the “ affaire of
                    church and ſtate ſhould not be introduced.” Ruddiman and the maſters of the
                    high-ſchool had the honour to found this ſociety. They were afterwards joined by
                    Lord Kaimes.</p>
                <p>In 1725 the firſt part of his <hi rend="italic">Grammatica Latina
                        Inſtitutiones,</hi> which treated of etymology, was publiſhed. The ſecond
                    part, which explained the nature and principles of ſyntax, appeared in 1731. He
                    alſo wrote a third part on proſody, which is laid to be more copious and correct
                    than any other publication on the ſubject. When urged to give it to the public,
                    he ſaid dryly, “ The age has ſo little taſte, the ſale would not pay the
                    expence.” Of this work, he publiſhed an abridge-</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0547" facs="gri_33125011196389_0553.tif"/>
                <p>ment, to which he ſubjoined an abſtract of his pro-</p>
                <p>ſody.</p>
                <p>Ruddiman next engaged in the management of a newſpaper, an employment for which
                    his genius and in-duſtry ſeemed to render him well qualified. But thoſe 'who
                    ſhould expect either much information or amuſe-ment from this publication, would
                    perhaps be greatly diſappointed. The newſpaper which he conducted was the
                    Caledonian Mercury, and was eſtabliſhed in 1720 by William Rolland a lawyer^
                    Ruddiman acted only in 'the capacity of printer for five years ; but upon the
                    death of Mr Rolland in 1729, the property was tranf-'ferred to him, or to his
                    brother Walter and him con· 'junctly. This paper continued in the family of
                    Ruddi-^man till the year 1772, when it was ſold by the truſtees of his
                    grandchildren to Mr John Robertſon.</p>
                <p>The Caledonian Mercury was at firſt printed three times a week, on Monday,
                    ſueſday, and Thurſday, in a ſmall 4t0 of four pages, with two columns in each
                    page, and 50 lines in each column ; ſo that the whole paper contained only 400
                    lines. It now contains in its folio ſize 2480 lines.</p>
                <p>Mr Ruddiman, after the death of Mr Spottiſwoode librarian, remained for ſome
                    time in his former ſtation ; but was at length appointed keeper of the library,
                    tho’ without any increaſe oſ ſalary; and ſome years after Mr Goodal, the
                    defender of Queen Mary, ſucceeded him in the office of ſub-librarian.</p>
                <p>The aſſiduous application of Ruddiman, ſupported by ſuch learning, was intitled
                    to wealth, which now indeed flowed upon him in what was at that period deemed
                    great abundance. On the iſt of October i735, it appeared from an exact ſtatement
                    oſ his affairs, that he was worth L. 1882 : 5 : 2 Sterling ; and on the 20th of
                    May, the enſuing year, his wealth had increaſed to L. 1985 : 6 : 3 Sterling. In
                    1710 he valued his effects at L. 24 : 14 : 9 Sterling.</p>
                <p>In 1737 the ſchoolmaſters and teachers in Edinburgh formed themſelves into a
                    ſociety, in order to eſtabliſh a fund for the ſupport of their wives and
                    children. Of this ſcheme Ruddiman was an active promoter, and was choſen
                    treaſurer. Perhaps it was this aſſociation which in 1742 gave the idea to the
                    Scots clergy of forming their widows fund.</p>
                <p>In 1739 he publiſhed <hi rend="italic">Seleftus Diplomatum et Num'f-inatum
                        Scotiæ Theſaurus.</hi> This work was projected and begun by Anderſon (hence
                    called <hi rend="italic">Anderſon’s Diploma-ta),</hi> but was finiſhed by
                    Ruddiman. The preface, which is an excellent commentary on Anderſon’s
                    performance, was written by Ruddiman, and diſplays a greater extent of knowledge
                    than any of his other productions.</p>
                <p>As Ruddiman had imbibed from his father thoſe political principles which
                    attached him to the family of Stuart, he probably did not remain an unconcerned
                    ſpectator of the civil commotions which in τ 745 agitated Scotland. He did not,
                    however, take any active part in the rebellion. His principles, he has been
                    heard to ſay, induced him to be a quiet ſubject and a good citizen. He retired
                    to the country during the ſummer of 1745" ; and while his fellow-citizens were
                    ſpilling each ethers blood, he was more happily engaged in writing Critical
                    Obſervations on Burman’s Commentaries on Lucan’s Pharſalia. The Caledonian
                    Mercury was in the mean time marked with a jealous eye. His ſon, who had for
                    ſome time been the principal manager of that newſpaper, having copied a
                    paragraph which was reckoned ſeditious from an Engliſh paper, was impri∙ ſoned.
                    The ſolicitation of his father procured his re-leaſe : but it was too late ; for
                    the unhappy young man had contracted a diſtemper in the tolbooth of Edinburgh
                    which brought him to his grave.</p>
                <p>During the laſt ſeventeen years of his life Ruddiman was almoſt inceſſantly
                    engaged in controverſy. To this he w <hi rend="sup">τ</hi> as in ſome meaſure
                    compelled by the violent attacks which ſome critics of the times had
                    ſucceſſively made upon his works. He was firſt called upon by Benſon, auditor in
                    the exchequer, to determine the comparative merit of Buchanan and Johnſton as
                    poets. He gave a decided preference to Buchanan in perſpi-cuity, purity, and
                    variety of ſtyle ;■ but, like a candid critic, allowed Johnſton to be ſuperior
                    in the harmony of his numbers. His next antagoniſt was Logan, one of the
                    miniſters of Edinburgh, a weak illiterate man, but an obſtinate polemic. The
                    ſubject of conteſt was, whether the crown of Scotland was ſtrictly hereditary,
                    and whether the birth of Robert III. was legitimate ? Ruddiman maintained the
                    affirmative in both pointe, and certainly far ſurpaſſed his antagoniſt in the
                    powers of reaſoning. He proved the legitimacy of Robert by the public records of
                    the kingdom with a force of argument which admits of no reply ; but in
                    diſcuſſing the firſt queſtion (by which he was led to confider the conteſt
                    between Bruce and Baliol) he was not ſo ſucceſsful : for there are many
                    inſtances in the hiſtory of Scotland in whjch the brother ſucceeded to the crown
                    in preference to the ſon. He ſhowed, however, that the Scottiſh crown was at no
                    period properly elective; and that, according to the old licentious conſtitution
                    of the kingdom, the right of Bruce, who was the neareſt in blood to the royal
                    ſtock, was preferable to the claim of Baliol though deſcended ſrom the eldeſt
                    daughter.</p>
                <p>But the labours of Ruddiman did not end when the pen dropt from the feeble hand
                    of Logan. He was ſoon called upon to repel the attacks of Love ſchool-maſter of
                    Dalkeith, who maintained, in oppoſition to him, that Buchanan had neither
                    repented of his treatment oſ Queen Mary, nor had been guilty of ingratitude to
                    that prmceſs. That Buchanan ever repented there is reaſon to doubt. Whether he
                    was guilty of ingratitude, let the unbiaſſed determine, when they are aſſu-red
                    by authentic records that Mary conferred on him a penſion for life of 500
                    pounds.Scots.</p>
                <p>When Ruddiman had arrived at his eightieth year, and was almoſt blind, he was
                    aſſailed by James Man, mailer of an hoſpital at Aberdeen, with a degree of
                    rancour and virulence, united with ſome learning and ability, which muſt have
                    touched him in a ſenſible manner, and alarmed his fears for his reputation after
                    his deceaſe. He was called a <hi rend="italic">fimjhed pedant,</hi> a <hi
                        rend="italic"> furious calumniator,</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">corrupter
                        of Buchanan's works.</hi> The venerable old man again put on his armour,
                    entered the lifts, and gained a complete victory. Man, with all his acuteneſs,
                    could only point out twenty errors in two folio volμmes. Some of theſe were
                    typographical, ſome trifling, and ſome doubtful. Ruddiman, with much pleaſantry,
                    drew up againſt Man an account of 469 errors, conſiſting of 14 articles, of
                    which two or three may be produced as a ſpecimen. 1. Falſehoods and
                    prevarications,20. 2. Abſurdities, 69. 3. Paflages from</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0548" facs="gri_33125011196389_0554.tif"/>
                <p>claſſic authors which were miſunderſtood by Man, IO. The triumph which he gained
                    over this virulent adverſary he did not long enjoy ; for he died at Edinburgh on
                    the 19th of January 1757, in the 83d year of his age, and was buried in the Grey
                    Friars churchyard without any monument to diſtinguiſh his grave.</p>
                <p>He was three times married, but left behind him only one daughter, Aliſon, who
                    was married in 1747 to James Stewart, Eſq. He is ſuppoſed to have died worth L.
                    3000 Sterling.</p>
                <p>He was of the middle ſize, of a thin and ſtraight make, and had eves remarkably
                    piercing. Of his talents and learning his works afford the moſt ſatisfactory
                    proofs. His memory was tenacious and exact. He could repeat long paſſages of his
                    favourite poet Ovid, to the amount of 60 lines, and without omitting a word. He
                    was ſo great a maſter in the Latin language, that he has perhaps been equalled
                    by none ſince the days of Buchanan.</p>
                <p>Ruddiman has left a character unſtained by vice, and diſtinguiſhed by many
                    virtues. His piety was exemplary. He ſpent Sunday in religious employment; and
                    we are informed had prayers read to him every morning by his amanuenſis when the
                    infirmities of age required ſuch an aſſiſtant. He was frugal of his time,
                    neither indolent nor fond of amuſement ; and ſo remarkably temperate, that it is
                    ſaid he was never intoxicated. Though often forced into controverſy, and treated
                    with iuſolence, he never deſcended to ſcurrility and abuſe, nor cheriſhed
                    reſentment againſt his enemies. His candour was much admired in one inſtance in
                    the favourable character which he publiſhed in the Caledonian Mercury of his
                    antagoniſt Love <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial" n="2"> The
                        following character of Love was publiſhed in the Caledonian Mercury of the
                        24th of September 1750. “ On Thursday morning died at Dalkeith, after a
                        lingering illneſſs, in the 55th year of His age, Mr John Love, rector of the
                        grammar-ſchool there ; who, ſor his uncommon knowledge in claſſical
                        learning, his indefatigable diligence, and ſtrictneſs of diſcipline without
                        ſeverity, was juſtly accounted one of the moſt ſuſſicient maſters in this
                        country. This character is doubtleſs juſt ; though Love is now known to have
                        been the ſchool-maſter ſatirized by Smollett in the beginning of his
                        Roderick Random.</note>, after his deceaſe. Upon the whole, it muſt be
                    allowed that Ruddiman has been of great ſervice to claſſical literature, and an
                    honour to his native country.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
