<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0550-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0556.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>RULE</label>
in matters of literature, a maxim, canon, or precept, to be obſerved in any art or ſcience.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rule, in a moaaſtic ſenſe, a ſyſtem of laws or regulations, whereby religious houſes are governed, and which the religious make a vow, at their entrance, to obſerve. Such are the rules of the Auguſtins, Bene-dictins, Carthuſians, Franciſcans, &amp;c. See Augustins, &amp;c.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">RULEs oſ Court,</hi> in law, are certain orders made from time to time in the courts of law, which attorneys are bound to obſerve, in order to avoid confuſion ; and both the plaintiff and defendant are at their peril alſo bound to pay obedience to rules made in court relating to the cauſe depending between them,</p><p>It is to be obſerved, that no court will make a rule Tor any thing that may be done in the ordinary courſe ; and that if a rule be made, grounded upon an affidavit, the other fide may move the court againſt it, in order to vacate the ſame, and thereupon ſhall bring into court a copy of the affidavit and rule. On the breach and contempt of a rule of court an attachment lies ; but it is not granted for diſobedience to a rule, when the party has not been perſonally ſerved ; nor for difobeying a rule made by a judge in his chamber, which is not of force to ground a motion upon, unleſs the ſame be entered.</p><p>A rule of court is granted every day· the courts at Weſtminſter fit, to priſoners of the King’s-bench of Fleet priions, to go at large about their private affairs.</p><p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps"> Rule oſ Three.</hi></hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Arithmetic and Proportion.</hi></p><p>Rule, or <hi rend="italic">Ruler,</hi> an inſtrument oſ wood or metal, with ſeveral lines delineated on it ; of great uſe in</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0551" facs="gri_33125011196389_0557.tif"/>
<p>practical menſuration. When a ruler has the lines of chords, tangents, fines, &amp;c. it is called a <hi rend="italic">plane fcαle.</hi></p>
</div></body></text></TEI>