<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0500-04" facs="gri_33125011196389_0506.tif" type="entry">

<p><label>ROSLIN</label>
or Roskelvn, a place in the county of Mid Lothian in Scotland, remarkable for an ancient chapel and caille. The chapel was founded in 1446, by St Clare, prince of Orkney, for a provoſt, fix prebendaries, and two ſinging-boys. The outſide is ornamented with a multitude of pinnacles, and variety of ludicrous ſculptuie. The inſide is 69 feet long, the breadth 34, ſupported by two rows of cluſtered pillars, between ſeven and eight feet high, with an aiſle on each ſide. The arches are obtuſely Gothic. Theſe arches are continued acroſs the ſide-aiſles, but the centre of the church is one continued arch, elegantly divided into compartments, and finely ſculptured. The capitals of the pillars are enriched with foliage, and a variety of figures ; and amidſt a heavenly concert appears a cherubim blowing the ancient Highland bagpipes. The caille is ſeated on a peninſulated rock, in a deep glen far beneath, and acceſſible by a bridge of great height. This had been the ſeat of the great lamily of <hi rend="italic">Sinclair.</hi> Of this houſe was Oliver, favourite of James V. and the innocent cauſe of the loſs of the battle of Solway Moſs, by reaſon of the envy of the nobility on account of his being preferred to the command.</p>
<pb xml:id="eb03-16-r03-0501" facs="gri_33125011196389_0507.tif"/>
<p>Near this place the Engliſh received three defeats in one day under John de Segrave the Engliſh regent of Scotland in 1302. The Scots, under their generals Cummin and Fraſer, had reſolved to furpriſe Segrave ; with which view they began their march on the night of Saturday preceding the firſt Sunday of Lent, and reached the Engliſh army by break of day. Segrave, however, had time to have fallen back upon the other d!vifion which lay behind him ; but, either deſpiſing his enemies too much, or thinking that he would be diſho· noured by a retreat, he encountered the Scots ; the conſequence of which was, that he himſelf was made priſoner, and all his men either killed or taken, except i nch as fled to the other diviſion. As in this routed diviſion there had been no fewer than 300 knights, each of whom brought at leaſt five horſemen into the field, great part of the Scots inſantiy quickly furniſhed themſelves with their horſes ; but, as they were dividing the ſpoils, another diviſion oſ the Engliſh appeared, and the Scots were obliged to fight them alſo. The Engliſh, after a bloody engagement, were defeated a ſecond time; which was no ſooner done, than the third and moſt powerful diviſion made its appearance. The Scots were now quite exhauſted ; and, pleading the exceſſive labours they had already undergone, earneſtly requeſted their geperals to allow them to retreat while it was yet ip their power. Their two generals, who perhaps knew that to be impracticable, reminded them of the cauſe for which they were fighting, the tyranny of the Engliſh, &amp;c. and by theſe arguments prevailed upon them to fight a third time ; though, previous to the engagement, they were reduced to the cruel neceſſitv of putting all the common ſoldiers whom they had made pri-ſoners to the ſword. The victory of the Scots at this time was leſs complete than the other two had been ; ſince they could not prevent the retreat of the Engliſh to Edinburgh, nor Segrave from being reſcued from bis captivity.</p>
</div></body></text></TEI>