<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>direct combination of the two elements in the electric furnace. It forms very hard metallic-looking crystals, burns in oxygen and is not attacked by acids. Potassium ruthenate, KjRuOfHjO, obtained by fusion of the metal with caustic potash and nitre, crystallizes in prisms which become covered with a black deposit on exposure to moist air. It is soluble in water, giving an orange-red solution which becomes green on standing, and gradually deposits the hydrated pentoxide, RujOe-HiO (H. Debray and A. Toly, <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus,</hi>  1888, 106, p. 1494). The <hi rend="italic">per-ruthenate, </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">RRuO«, formed by the action of chlorine on the ruthenate, or of alkalis on the peroxide at 50° C., is a black crystalline solid which is stable in dry air but decomposes when heated strongly. On the nitroso, nitroso-ammonium and nitroso-diammonium compounds see C. E. Claus, </hi><hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi>  1856, 98, p. 317; A. Joly, <hi rend="italic">Comptes rendus,</hi>  1888, 107, p. 994; 1889, 108, pp. 854, 1300; 1890, in, p, 969; L. Brizard, ibid., 1896, 122, p. 730; 1896, 123, p. 182, The atomic weight of ruthenium was determined by A. Joly <hi rend="italic">(Comptes rendus,</hi>  1889, 188, p. 946), who obtained the values 101*5 and 101-3.</p><p>RUTHERFORD, MARK, the pen-name of William Hale White, English author, who was born at Bedford about 1830. His father, William White, a member of the nonconformist community of the Bunyan Meeting, removed to London, where he was well known as a doorkeeper of the House of Commons; he wrote sketches of parliamentary life for the <hi rend="italic">Illustrated Times,</hi>  papers afterwards collected by his son as <hi rend="italic">The Inner Life of the House of Commons</hi>  (1897). The son was educated for the Congregational ministry, but the development of his views prevented his taking up that career, and he became a clerk in the admiralty. He had already served an apprenticeship to journalism before he made his name as a novelist by th£ three books “ edited by Reuben Shapcott/’ <hi rend="italic">The Autobiography of Mark Rutherford</hi>  (1881), <hi rend="italic">Mark Rutherford’s Deliverance</hi>  (1885), and <hi rend="italic">The Revolution in Tanner’s Lane</hi>  (1887). Under his own name he translated Spinoza’s <hi rend="italic">Ethic</hi>  (1883). Later books are <hi rend="italic">Miriam’s Schooling, and other Papers</hi>  (1890), <hi rend="italic">Catherine Furze </hi>(2 vols., 1893), <hi rend="italic">Clara Hopgood</hi>  (1896), <hi rend="italic">Pages from a Journal, with other Papers</hi>  (1900), and <hi rend="italic">John Bunyan</hi>  (1905). Though for a long time little appreciated by the public, his novels— particularly the earlier ones—have a power and style which must always give his works a place of their own in the literary history of their time.</p><p>RUTHERFORD, WILLIAM GUNION (1853-1907), English scholar, was born in Peeblesshire on the 17th of July 1853. He was educated at St Andrews and Oxford, where he graduated in natural science, with a view to following the medical profession, which he abandoned in favour of a scholastic career. From 1883 to 1901 he was headmaster of Westminster school; and his death, on the 19th of July 1907, deprived classical scholarship in England of one of its most brilliant modern representatives. Rutherford devoted special attention to Attic idioms and the language of Aristophanes. His most important work, the <hi rend="italic">New Phrynichus</hi>  (1882), dealing with the Atticisms of the grammarian, was supplemented by his <hi rend="italic">Babrius </hi>(1883), a specimen of the later Greek, which was the chief subject of C. A. Lobeck’s earlier commentary (1820) on Phrynichus. His edition (1896-1905) of the Aristophanic scholia from the Ravenna MS. was less successful. Mention may also be made of his <hi rend="italic">Elementary Greek Accidence</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Lex Rex,</hi>  a list of cognate words in Greek, Latin and English.</p><p>RUTHERFURD (or Rutherpord), SAMUEL (c. 1600-1661), Scottish divine, was born about 1600 at the village of Nisbet, Roxburghshire. He went to college at Edinburgh in 1617, graduating M.A. in 1621, and two years afterwards was elected professor of humanity. On account of an alleged indiscretion before his marriage in 1626 he was dismissed his professorship in that year, but, after studying theology, he was in 1627 appointed minister of Anwoth, Kirkcudbrightshire, and soon took a leading place among the clergy of Galloway. In 1636 his first book, entitled <hi rend="italic">Exercitationes Apologeticae pro Divina Gratia</hi>—an elaborate treatise against Arminianism—appeared at Amsterdam. Its severe Calvinism led to a prosecution by the bishop, Thomas Sydserf, in the High Commission Court, first at Wigtown and afterwards at Edinburgh, with the result that Rutherfurd was deposed from his pastoral office, and sentenced to confinement in Aberdeen during the king’s pleasure.</p><p>His banishment lasted from September 1636 to February 1638, and the greater number of his published <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>  belong to this period of his life. He was present at the signing of the Covenant in Edinburgh in 1638, and at the Glasgow Assembly of the same year he was restored to his parish. In 1639 he was appointed professor of divinity in St Mary’s College, St Andrews. He only accepted the position on the condition that he should be allowed to act as colleague to Robert Blair in the church of St Andrews. He was sent up to London in 1643 as one of the eight commissioners from Scotland to the Westminster Assembly. Remaining at his post over three years, he did great service to the cause of his party. In 1642 he had published his <hi rend="italic">Peaceable and Temperate Plea for Paul’s Presbyterie in Scotland, </hi>and the sequel to it in 1644 on <hi rend="italic">The Due Right of Presbyteries </hi>provoked Milton’s contemptuous reference to “mere A. S. and Rutherfurd ” in his sonnet <hi rend="italic">On the New Forcers of Conscience under the Long Parliament.</hi>  In 1644 also appeared Rutherfurd’s <hi rend="italic">Lex Rex, a Dispute for the Just Prerogative of King and People, </hi>which gives him a recognized place among the early writers on constitutional law; it was followed by <hi rend="italic">The Divine Right of Church Government and Excommunication</hi>  (1646), and <hi rend="italic">Free Disputation against Pretended Liberty of Conscience</hi>  (1648), characterized by Bishop Heber as “ perhaps the most elaborate defence of persecution which has ever appeared in a Christian country.” Among his other works are the <hi rend="italic">Tryal and Triumph of Faith</hi>  (1645), <hi rend="italic">Christ Dying and Drawing Sinners to Himself </hi>(1647), and <hi rend="italic">Survey of the Spiritual Antichrist</hi>  (1648). In 1647 he returned to St Andrews to become principal of the New College there, and in 1648 and 1651 he declined successive invitations to theological chairs at Harderwijk and Utrecht. After the Restoration in 1660, his <hi rend="italic">Lex Rex</hi>  was ordered to be burned. He was deprived of all his offices, and on a charge of high treason was cited to appear before the ensuing parliament. His health utterly broke down, and he drew up, on the 26th of February 1661, a <hi rend="italic">Testimony,</hi>  which was posthumously published. He died on the 23rd of the following March.</p><p>The fame of Rutherfurd now rests principally upon his remarkable <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi>  which, to the number of 215, were first published anonymously by M'Ward, an amanuensis, as <hi rend="italic">Joshua Redivivus, or Mr Rutkerfoord's Letters,</hi>  in 1664. They have been frequently reprinted, the best edition (365 letters) being that by Rev. A. A. Bonar (1848), with a sketch of his life. In addition to the other works already mentioned, Rutherfurd published in 1651 a treatise, <hi rend="italic">De Divina Providentia,</hi>  against Molimsm, Socinianism and Arminianism, of which Richard Baxter, not without justice, remarked that “as the <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>  were the best piece so this was the worst he had ever read.”</p><p>See also a short <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>  by Rev. Dr Andrew Thomson (1884); Dr A. B. Grosart in <hi rend="italic">Representative Nonconformists ; </hi>Dr Alexander Whyte, <hi rend="italic">Samuel Rutherford and some of his Correspondents</hi>  (1894); Rev. R. Gilmour, <hi rend="italic">Samuel Rutherford</hi>  (1904).</p><p>RUTHERGLEN (locally pronounced <hi rend="italic">Rugleri),</hi>  a royal municipal and police burgh of Lanarkshire, Scotland. Pop. of royal burgh (1901) 18,279. It is situated on the left bank of the Clyde, 2| m. by the Caledonian railway S.E. of Glasgow, with the E. of which it is connected by a bridge. The parish church stands near the spire of the ancient church where, according to tradition, the treaty was made in 1297 with Edward I., by which Sir John Menteith undertook to betray Wallace to the English. The principal public building is the town hall, dating from 1861. The industries include collieries, chemical works, dye-works, cotton- and paper-mills, chair-making, tube-making, pottery, rope- and twine-works and some shipbuilding. It forms one of the Kilmarnock group of parliamentary burghs, with Dumbarton,"Port-Glasgow, Renfrew and Kilmarnock.</p><p>Rutherglen was erected into a royal burgh by David I. in 1126. It then included a portion of Glasgow, but in 1226 the boundaries were rectified so as to exclude the whole of the city. In early times it had a castle, which was taken by Robert Bruce from the English in 1313. It was kept in good repair till after the battle of Langside (1568), when it was burnt by order of the regent Moray. In 1679 the Covenanters published their “ Declaration and Testimony ” at Rutherglen prior to the battles of Drumclog and Bothwell Brig (1679).</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>