<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic">Expositio Symboli,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">Historia Eremitica</hi>  and the two original books of the <hi rend="italic">Hist. Eccl.</hi>  See also Migne, <hi rend="italic">Patrol,</hi>  (vol. xxi. of the Latin series). For the translations, see the various editions of Origen, Eusebius, &amp;c.</p><p>See W. H. Freeman tie in <hi rend="italic">Diet. Chr. Biog.</hi>  iv. 555-60; A. Ebert, <hi rend="italic">Allg. Gesch. d. Litt. d. Mittelalters im Abendlande,</hi>  i. 321-27 (Leipzig, 1889); G. Krüger in Hauck-Herzog’s <hi rend="italic">Real-encyk. für prol. Theol., </hi>where there is a full bibliography.</p><p>RUFUS, GAIUS VALGIUS, Lain poet, friend of Horace and Maecenas, and consul in 12 b.c. He was known as a writer of elegies and epigrams, and his contemporaries believed him capahle of great things in epic. The author of the panegyric on Messalla declares Rufus to be the only poet fitted to be the great man’s Homer. Rufus did not, however, confine himself to poetry. He discussed grammatical questions by correspondence, translated the rhetorical manual of his teacher Apollodorus of Pergamum, and began a treatise on medicinal plants, dedicated to Augustus. Horace addressed to him the ninth ode of the second book.</p><p>Fragments in R. Weichert, <hi rend="italic">Poetarum Latinorum Vitae el Carminum Reliquiae</hi>  (1830); R. Unger, <hi rend="italic">De C. Valgii Ruft Poematis</hi>  (1848);</p><p>O. Ribbeck, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der römischen Dichtung</hi>  (1889), ii.; M. Schanz, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der römischen Litteratur</hi>  (1899), ii. 1; Teuffel, <hi rend="italic">Hist, of Roman Literature</hi>  (Eng. trans., 1900), 241.</p><p>RUFUS, LUCIUS VARIUS (c 74-14 b.c.), Roman poet of the Augustan age. He was the friend of Virgil, after whose death he and Plotius Tucca prepared the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>  for publication, and of Horace, for whom he and Virgil obtained an introduction to Maecenas. Horace speaks of him as a master of epic and the only poet capable of celebrating the achievements of Vipsanius Agrippa <hi rend="italic">{Odes,</hi>  i. 6); Virgil (under the name of Lycidas, <hi rend="italic">Eel.</hi>  ix. 35) regrets that he had hitherto produced nothing comparable to the work of Varius or Helvius Cinna. From Macrobius <hi rend="italic">{Saturnalia,</hi>  vi. 1, 39; 2, 19) we learn that Varius composed an epic poem <hi rend="italic">De Morte,</hi>  some lines of which are quoted as having been imitated or appropriated by Virgil; Horace <hi rend="italic">{Sat.</hi>  i. 10, 43) probably alludes to another epic, and, according to the scholiast on <hi rend="italic">Epistles,</hi>  i. 16, 27-29, these three lines are taken bodily from a panegyric of Varius on Augustus. But his most famous literary production was the tragedy <hi rend="italic">Thyesles,</hi>  which Quintilian <hi rend="italic">{Inst. Oral.</hi>  x. 1, 98) declares fit to rank with any of the Greek tragedies. The didascalia (which is preserved in a Paris MS.) informs us that it was produced at the games celebrated (29 B.c.) by Augustus in honour of the victory at Actium, and that Varius received a present of a million sesterces from the emperor.</p><p>Fragments in E. Bahrens, <hi rend="italic">Frag. Poetarum Romanorum</hi>  (1886); monographs by A. Weichert (1836) and R. Unger (1870,. 1878, 1898);</p><p>M. Schanz, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der römischen Litteratur</hi>  (1899), ii. 1; Teuffel, <hi rend="italic">Hist. of Roman Literature</hi>  (Eng. trans., 1900), 223.</p><p>RUG, a term of Scandinavian origin (cf. Swed. <hi rend="italic">rugg,</hi>  rough hair; Norw. dial, <hi rend="italic">rugga,</hi>  rough), and probably connected with “ rough ” and “ rag,” originally for a kind of coarse woollen material, like frieze; hence it is used of a piece of thick material used as a wrap or covering for the knees or body in travelling or in bed, and especially for a thick mat or small-sized carpet laid on the floor (see Carpet).</p><p>RUGBY, a market town in the Rugby parliamentary division of Warwickshire, England, finely situated on a tableland rising from the S. bank of the Avon, near the Oxford Canal. Pop. of urban district (1901), 16,830. It is an important junction on the London &amp; North-Western railway, by which it is 82J m. N.W. from London; it is served also by the Great Central railway and by a branch of the Midland railway from Leicester.</p><p>The boys’ school, ranking as one of the most famous public schools in England, was founded and endowed under the will (1567) of Laurence Sheriff, a merchant grocer and servant to Queen Elizabeth, and a native either of Rugby or of the neighbouring village of Brownsover. The endowment consisted of the parsonage of Brownsover, Sheriff’s mansion house in Rugby, and one-third (8 acres) of his estate in Middlesex, near the Foundling Hospital, London, which, being let on building leases, gradually increased to about £5000 a year. The full endowment was obtained in 1653. The school originally stood opposite the parish church, and was removed to its present site on the S. side of the town between 1740 and 1750. In 1809 it was rebuilt from designs by Henry Hakewill (1771-1830); the chapel, dedicated to St Lawrence, was added in 1820. At the tercentenary of the school in 1867 subscriptions were set on foot for founding scholarships, building additional schoolrooms, rebuilding or enlarging the chapel and other objects. The chapel was rebuilt and reconsecrated in 1872, and further additions were made in 1898. A swimming bath was erected in 1876; the Temple observatory, containing a fine equatorial refractor by Alvan Clark, was built in 1877, and the Temple reading-room with the art museum in 1878. The workshops underneath the gymnasium were opened in 1880, and a new big school and class-rooms were erected in 1885. From about 70 to 1777 the numbers attending the school have increased to nearly 600. A great impulse was given to the progress of the school during the headmastership of Thomas Arnold, 1827-42. Among Arnold’s successors were Archibald Campbell Tait and Frederick Temple, both afterwards archbishops of Canterbury.</p><p>The parish church of St Andrew was rebuilt from designs by W. Butterfield and reconsecrated in 1879. A tower and spire were added in 1895. An aisle commemorates John Moultrie (1799-1874), rector, widely known as the “ poet pastor.” The church of Holy Trinity is by Sir G. G. Scott, and the Roman Catholic church of St Marie by A. W. Pugin. Trade is mainly agricultural; there is a large cattle market, and several fairs are held annually.</p><p>The early history of Rugby is obscure, but a settlement of the Danes is presumed from the name, and from the neighbouring tract of Dunsmore Heath (Danesmoor). Rugby was originally a hamlet of the adjoining parish of Clifton-on-Dunsmore? and is separately treated of as such in Domesday Book. Ernaldus de Bosco (Ernald de Bois), lord of the manor of Clifton, seems to have erected the first chapel in Rugby, in the reign of Stephen, about 1140. It was afterwards granted by him, with certain lands, to endow the abbey of St Mary, Leicester, which grant was confirmed by his successors and by royal charter of Henry II. In the second year of King John (1200) a suit took place between Henry de Rokeby, lord of the manor of Rugby, and Paul, abbot of St Mary, Leicester, which resulted in the former obtaining possession of the advowson of Rugby, on condition of homage and service to the abbot of Leicester. By virtue of this agreement the chapel was converted into a parish church and the vicarage into a rectory.</p><p>RUGE, ARNOLD (1802-1880), German philosopher and political writer, was born at Bergen, in the island of Rügen, on the 13th of September 1802. He studied at Halle, Jena and Heidelberg, and became an adherent of the party which sought to create a free and united Germany. For his zeal he was confined for five years in the fortress of Kolberg, where he studied Plato and the Greek poets. On his release in 1830 he published <hi rend="italic">Schill und die Seinen,</hi>  a tragedy, and a translation of <hi rend="italic">Oedipus in Colonus.</hi>  Ruge settled in Halle, where in 1837 with E. T. Echtermeyer he founded the <hi rend="italic">Hallesche Jahrbücher für deutsche Kunst und Wissenschaft.</hi>  In this periodical he discussed the questions of the time from the point of view of the Hegelian philosophy. The <hi rend="italic">Jahrbücher</hi>  was detested by the orthodox party in Prussia; and was finally suppressed by the Saxon government in 1843. In Paris Ruge tried to act with Karl Marx as co-editor of the <hi rend="italic">Deutsch-Französische Jahrbücher,</hi>  but had little sympathy with Marx’s socialistic theories, and soon left him. In the revolutionary movement of 1848 he organized the Extreme Left in the Frankfort parliament, and for some time he lived in Berlin as the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Die Reform.</hi>  The Prussian government intervened and Ruge soon afterwards left for Paris, hoping, through his friend Alexandre Ledru-Rollin, to establish relations between German and French republicans; but in 1849 both Ledru-Rollin and Ruge had to take refuge in London. Here, in company with Giuseppe Mazzini and other advanced politicians, they formed a “ European Democratic Committee.” From this Ruge soon withdrew, and in 1850 went to Brighton, where he supported himself by teaching and writing. In 1866 and 1870 he vigorously</p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>