<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>has been picked out with recessed arches, the tenderness of its scheme of colour, combine to produce an exquisite effect. It is a melancholy reflection that M. de Sévilly, whom his wife and Marie Antoinette combined to surprise with this <hi rend="italic">chef-d’œuvre,</hi>  was guillotined, and that his wife, whose sitting-room it was, was condemned to die with him and with Madame Élisabeth de France, whom they had befriended, but was saved, against her will, by the princess, who made a false declaration as to her condition. She had two subsequent husbands, and lost them both in little more than two years. She herself lived less than five years after her delivery by the fall of Robespierre. There is no information as to Rousseau’s later life. The last known mention of him is in 1792.</p><p>ROUSSILLON, one of the old provinces of France. It now forms the greater part of the department of Pyrénées Orientales <hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi>  It was bounded S. by the Pyrenees, W. by the county of Foix, N. by Languedoc and E. by the Mediterranean. The province derived its name from a small place near Perpignan, the capital, called Ruscino (Rosceliona, Castel Rossello), where the Gallic chieftains met to consider Hannibal’s request for a conference. The district formed part of the Roman province of Gallia Narbonensis from 121 b.c. to a.d. 462, when it was ceded with the rest of Septimania to Theodoric II., king of the Visigoths. His successor, Amalaric, on his defeat by Clovis in 531 retired to Spain, leaving a governor in Septimania. In 719 the Saracens crossed the Pyrenees, and Septimania was held by them until their defeat by Pippin in 756. On the invasion of Spain by Charlemagne in 778 he found the borderlands wasted by the Saracenic wars, and the inhabitants hiding among the mountains. He accordingly made grants of land to Visigothic refugees from Spain, and founded several monasteries, round which the people gathered for protection. In 792 the Saracens again invaded France, but were repulsed by Louis,king of Aquitaine,whose rule extended overall Catalonia as far as Barcelona. The different portions of his kingdom in time grew into allodial fiefs, and in 893 Suniaire II. became the first hereditary count of Roussillon. But his rule only extended over the eastern part of what became the later province. The western part, or Cerdagne, was ruled in 900 by Miron as first count, and one of his grandsons, Bernard, was the first hereditary count of the middle portion, or Bésalu. In mi Raymond-Bérenger III., count of Barcelona, inherited the fief of Bésalu, to which was added in 1117 that of Cerdagne; and in 1172 his grandson, Alfonso II., king of Aragon, united Roussillon to his other states on the death of the last count, Gerard II. The counts of Roussillon, Cerdagne and Bésalu were not sufficiently powerful to indulge in any wars of ambition. Their energies had been devoted to furthering the welfare of their people. Under the Aragonese monarchs the progress of the united province still continued, and Collioure, the port of Perpignan, became a centre of Mediterranean trade. But the country was destined to pay the penalty of its position on the frontiers of France and Spain in the long struggle for ascendancy between these two powers. By the treaty of Corbeil (1258) Louis IX. surrendered the sovereignty of Roussillon and the ancient countship of Barcelona to Aragon, and from that time until the 17th century the province ceased to belong to France. James I. of Aragon had wrested the Balearic Isles from the Moors and left them with Roussillon to his son James (1276), with the title of king of Majorca. The consequent disputes of this monarch with his brother Pedro III. of Aragon were not lost sight of by Philip III. of France in his quarrel with the latter about the crown of the Two Sicilies. Philip espoused James’s cause and led his army into Spain, but retreating died at Perpignan in 1285. James then became reconciled to his brother, and in 1311 was succeeded by his son Sancho, who founded the cathedral of Perpignan shortly before his death in 1324. His successor James II. refused to do homage to Philip VI. of France for the seigniory of Montpellier, and applied to Pedro IV. of Aragon for aid. Pedro not only refused it, but on various pretexts declared war against him, and seized Majorca and Roussillon in 1J44. The province was now again united to Aragon, and enjoyed peace until 1462. In this year the disputes between John II. and his son about the crown of Navarre gave Louis XI. of France an excuse to support John against his subjects, who had risen in revolt. Louis turned traitor, and the province having been pawned to him for 300,000 crowns, was occupied by the French troops until 1493, when Charles VIII. restored it to Ferdinand and Isabella. During the war between France and Spain (1496-98) the people suffered equally from the Spanish garrisons and the French invaders. But dislike of the Spaniards was soon effaced in the pride of sharing in the glory of Charles V., and in 1542, when Perpignan was besieged by the dauphin, the Roussillonnais remained true to their allegiance. Afterwards the decay of Spain was France’s opportunity, andon the revolt of the Catalans against the Castilians in 1641, Louis XIII. espoused the cause of the former, and the treaty of the Pyrenees in-1659 secured Roussillon to the French crown.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.—</hi><hi rend="italic">Privilèges et titres relatifs aux franchises, institutions et propriétés communales du Roussillon et de la Cerdagne depuis le XI<hi rend="sup">s</hi>  siècle jusqu'en 1600</hi>  (1878); Auguste Brutails, <hi rend="italic">Étude sur la condition des populations rurales du Roussillon au moyen âge </hi>(1891). See also the publications of the <hi rend="italic">Société agricole, scientifique et littéraire des Pyrénées Orientales</hi>  (1834 fol.).</p><p>ROUTH, EDWARD JOHN (1831-1907), English mathematician, was born at Quebec on the 20th of January 1831. At the age of eleven he came to England, and after studying under A. de Morgan at University College, London, entered Peterhouse, Cambridge, in 1851. In the mathematical tripos three years later he was senior wrangler, beating J. Clerk Maxwell, who, however, tied with him for the Smith’s prize. Elected a fellow of his college, he devoted himself to teaching, and quickly proved himself one of the most successful mathematical “ coaches ” ever known at Cambridge. In thirty years, of some 700 pupils who passed through his hands 500 became wranglers; and for twenty-two successive years, from 1861 to 1882, the senior wrangler was trained by him. He made considerable contributions to scientific literature, and among his publications were: <hi rend="italic">An Analytical View of Newton’s Principia,</hi>  with Lord Brougham (1855); an <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Stability of a given State of Motion,</hi>  which won the Adams’ prize in 1877; and treatises on the <hi rend="italic">Dynamics of Rigid Bodies,</hi>  on <hi rend="italic">Analytical Statics,</hi>  and on the <hi rend="italic">Dynamics of a Particle.</hi>  He died at Cambridge on the 7th of June 1907.</p><p>ROUTH, MARTIN JOSEPH (1755-1854), English classical scholar, was born at South Elmham, Suffolk, on the 18th of September 1755. He was educated at Queen’s College, Oxford, and subsequently elected to a fellowship at Magdalen, of which society he became president in 1791. He died at Oxford on the 22nd of December 1854, and retained his physical and intellectual powers to the last. He was the author of editions of the <hi rend="italic">Euthydemus</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">Gorgias</hi>  of Plato (1784), to which Dindorf declared himself indebted for his first ideas of Greek criticism, and of Bishop Burnet’s <hi rend="italic">History of his Own Time</hi>  (2nd ed., 1833) and <hi rend="italic">History of the Reign of King James the Second</hi>  (1852). Routh was also an authority on patristic literature, his <hi rend="italic">Reliquiae Sacrae</hi>  (2nd ed., 1846-48), a collection of the fragments of the Fathers of the 2nd and 3rd centuries, and <hi rend="italic">Scrip-tor um ecclesiaslicorum opuscula praecipua quaedam</hi>  (2nd ed., 1840) being valuable contributions to ecclesiastical knowledge.</p><p>See <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine,</hi>  1855; T. W. Burgon, <hi rend="italic">Lives of Twelve Good Men</hi>  (1888).</p><p>ROUTLEDGE, GEORGE (1812-1888), English publisher, was bom at Brampton in Cumberland on the 23rd of September 1812. He gained his earliest experience of business with a bookseller at Carlisle. Proceeding to London in 1833, he started in business for himself as a bookseller in 1836, and as a publisher in 1843, making his first serious success by reprinting the Biblical commentaries of an American writer, Albert Barnes. His fame as a publisher, however, rests chiefly upon the enormous number of cheap books which he issued. A series of shilling volumes called the “ Railway Library ” was an immense success, including as it did Mrs Harriet Beecher Stowe’s <hi rend="italic">Uncle Tom’s Cabin,</hi>  and he also published in popular</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>