<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>propaganda most offensive to Rumanian nationalism. An <hi rend="italic">trade</hi>  of the sultan Abdul Hamid had in 1906 recognized the existence of the Kutzo-Vlachs as a religious body <hi rend="italic">(millet), </hi>forming an integral part of the Rumanian Church. This decision was regarded by the Greeks as a blow to their own interests, and Greek revolutionary bands were accused of persecuting the Kutzo-Vlachs. (See also Macedonia.) Even before 1906 there was keen rivalry between Greece and Rumania, and the “ Macedonian question ” was the underlying cause of the disputes which, arising ostensibly from quite trivial causes, led temporarily to the rupture of diplomatic relations between Gieece and Rumania in 1905, 1906 and 1910.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.—No scientific history of Rumania was published up to the 20th century, but the task of collecting and editing original documents was partially carried out by the Rumanian Academy and by private students, especially after 1880. The so-called </hi><hi rend="italic">Chronicle of Hurul</hi>  is a modern forgery, and up to the 14th century the only valid authorities are Slavonic, Hungarian and Byzantine chroniclers. Thenceforward a great mass of material is available. It is partly incorporated in the yearly <hi rend="italic">Annalele</hi>  of the Academy, 2nd series, from 1880; and in the 30 volumes of E. de Hurmuzaki’s <hi rend="italic">Documente privitore relative la istoria Românilor</hi>  (Bucharest, 1876, &amp;c.). Other important original documents, or works containing such documents, are Verantius's 16th-century <hi rend="italic">De situ Transylvaniae, Moldavia*, et Transalpinae,</hi>  in Kovachich’s <hi rend="italic">Scriptores rerum Hungari-carum minores</hi>  (Budapest, 1798); G. Urechia’s late 16th-century <hi rend="italic">Chronique de Moldavie,</hi>  ed. J. Picot (Paris, 1878); Rumanian text in Old Slavonic characters, with French translation and notes,of great value; the 17th-century <hi rend="italic">Opere Complete</hi>  of Miron Costiu, ed. V. A. Urechia (Bucharest, 1886); A. M. del Chiaro, <hi rend="italic">Istoria dette moderne rivoluzioni della Valachia con la descrizione del paese</hi>  (Venice, 1878); the early 18th-century <hi rend="italic">Operele principeluï D. Cantemirü, </hi>issued by the Academy (Bucharest, 1872, &amp;c.); N. Iorga, <hi rend="italic">Acte fi fragmente cu privire la istoria Românilor</hi>  (Bucharest, 1895-97); M. Kogalniceanu, <hi rend="italic">Cronicele Româniï</hi>  (Bucharest, 1872-74); J. L. Carra, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de Moldavie et de Valachie, avec une dissertation sur l'état actuel de ces deux Provinces</hi>  (Jassy, 1777); A. M. Blanc de Lanautte, <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur l'état ancien et actuel de la Moldavie, présenté à S. A.S. le prince A. Ypsilanti en 1787</hi>  (Bucharest, 1902); D. A. Sturdza, <hi rend="italic">Acte fi documente relative la istoria renasccreï Româniï </hi>(Bucharest, 1900, &amp;c.) ; ibid., <hi rend="italic">Scrierile fi cuvîntarile luï /. C. Brationu </hi>(Bucharest, 1903, &amp;c.). On the Phanariote period see P. Eliade, <hi rend="italic">De l'influence française sur l'esprit public en Roumanie. Les origines. Étude sur l'état de la société roumaine à l'époque des règnes phanariotes </hi>(Paris, 1898). For a general history of Rumania, see V. À. Urechia, <hi rend="italic">Istoria Românilor</hi>  (Bucharest, 1891, &amp;c., 8 vols.); A. D. Xenopol, <hi rend="italic">Istoria Romînilor din Dacia Traiand</hi>  (Jassy, 1888-93, 6 vols.— abridged French edition entitled <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Roumains,</hi>  2 vols., Paris, 1896); and P. Negulescu, <hi rend="italic">Histoire du droit et des institutions de la Roumanie</hi>  (Paris, 1898, &amp;c.). Sketches of Rumanian history are given in A. Sturdza, <hi rend="italic">La terre et les races roumaines</hi>  (Paris, 190g) ; and W. Miller, <hi rend="italic">The Balkans</hi>  (London, 1896). For a,comprehensive bibliography of Rumanian history, see N. Iorga’s introduction to vol. x. of the Hurmuzaki collection; vol. xxii. of the <hi rend="italic">Annalele', Bibliografia Românéscâ veche 1508-1830,</hi>  by C. Bianu and H. Hodos (Bucharest, 1903, &amp;c.); and D. Onciul, <hi rend="italic">Originile principatelor române</hi>  (Bucharest, 1898).    (H. Tr. ; X.)</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Language</hi></p><p>* Rumanian@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> is, geographically, an isolated eastern member of the group of Romance languages<hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi>  being severed from all the rest by countries in which the predominant speech is Slavonic or Magyar. It represents the original rustic Latin of the Roman provincials in Moesia and Dacia, as modified by centuries of alien rule. Structurally, its Latin characteristics have been well preserved; but its vocabulary has undergone great changes, becoming so far Slavonized that the ratio of words of Slavonic origin to words of Latin origin is approximately as three to two; large numbers of loan-words have also been added from Turkish, Greek, Magyar and other sources. It is noteworthy, however, that where Latin words have survived they are sometimes purer than in the Romance languages of the West</p><lb/><p><hi rend="italic">(e.g.</hi>  Lat. <hi rend="italic">domina</hi>  is better represented by Rum. <hi rend="italic">domnd, “</hi>  lady,” than by Ital. <hi rend="italic">donna,</hi>  Span, <hi rend="italic">dona,</hi>  Port, <hi rend="italic">dona,</hi>  Fr. <hi rend="italic">dame).</hi>  Some words indeed@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>  such as<hi rend="italic">laudare,</hi>  to praise, <hi rend="italic">ducere,</hi>  to lead— retain unaltered the forms under which they were used by Virgil and Cicero. A feature of the language which distinguishes it from all other members of the group, and appears to be of even higher antiquity than the word-forms above mentioned, is the retention of a suffix article—<hi rend="italic">e.g.frate,</hi>  brother, <hi rend="italic">fratele,</hi>  the brother; <hi rend="italic">zi,</hi>  day, <hi rend="italic">ziua,</hi>  the day. This usage seems to have survived from the pre-Roman period. A similar suffix article is retained in Albanian, which almost certainly represents the original language of the Thraco-Illyrian tribes (see Albania) ; and these tribes belonged to the same ethnical and linguistic group as the Daco-Moesians represented by the Vlachs.</p><p>Rumanian orthography remained in a transitional state throughout the 19th century. The Latin alphabet is used, with special signs to represent sounds borrowed from Slavonic, &amp;c. All the unaccented vowels except <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  are pronounced as in Italian ; <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  has the same phonetic value as in Old Slavonic ( — French <hi rend="italic">é)</hi>  and is often similarly preiotized ( = in <hi rend="italic">yet),</hi>  notably at the beginning of all words except neologisms. The accented vowels <hi rend="italic">ê</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">6</hi>  are pronounced as <hi rend="italic">ea</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">oa (bétra,</hi>  rock,= <hi rend="italic">peatra', morte,</hi>  death,— <hi rend="italic">moarte)-, </hi>they are written in full, as diphthongs, at the end of a word and sometimes in other positions. The sound of the Slavonic £1 (a guttural y) Js represented by <hi rend="italic">d, e</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">8,</hi>  though these letters occur as frequently in words of Latin origin <hi rend="italic">(e.g. cînd *= quando)</hi>  as in those derived from Slavonic; 3K is represented by a or <hi rend="italic">t,</hi>  having the nasal sound of <hi rend="italic">un</hi>  in French; ï and <hi rend="italic">ü</hi>  at the end of a word are mute or short. Of the consonants, <hi rend="italic">c</hi>  followed by <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">i — ch</hi>  (as in <hi rend="italic">church), </hi>otherwise, <hi rend="italic">k', 4</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">4</hi>  resembles the English <hi rend="italic">j; g</hi>  is hard before <hi rend="italic">e</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">i,</hi>  otherwise soft; <hi rend="italic">h</hi>  is guttural, as <hi rend="italic">ch</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">loch', j</hi>  is pronounced as in French; <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  as in Russian; 7 or (Slav. HI) as <hi rend="italic">sh;*l</hi>  or / (Slav, n,) as <hi rend="italic">is</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">tz-, w</hi>  is wanting. The remaining consonants have the same phonetic values as in English.</p><p>Rumanian is highly inflected. It possesses two regular substantive declensions and six cases, the vocative being in common use. The large class of heterogeneous nouns which are masculine in the singular and feminine in the plural constitute what is sometimes, called the neuter declension. There are three regular conjugations, distinguished (as in Latin) according to the termination of the present infinitive in <hi rend="italic">a, e</hi>  or t; <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  (1) <hi rend="italic">a ara</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">arare,</hi>  to plough, (2) <hi rend="italic">a crede</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">credere,</hi>  to believe, (3) <hi rend="italic">a dormi</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">dormire,</hi>  to sleep. Verbs ending in f, however, are sometimes classed as a fourth conjugation. The second form of the present infinitive <hi rend="italic">(arare, credere, dormire)</hi>  is used as a noun. The so-called “ simple perfect <hi rend="italic">" (perfectul simplu)</hi>  has often the force of an aorist. Compound tenses are formed by the addition of certain particles and of the auxiliary verbs—<hi rend="italic">a </hi><hi rend="italic">ave,</hi>  to have, <hi rend="italic">a fi,</hi>  to be, and <hi rend="italic">a voi,</hi>  to will. For the passive voice, <hi rend="italic">a fi</hi>  is used, with the past participle of the required verb. All tenses of reflexive verbs except the imperative and present participle are formed by prefixing the pronoun which indicates the object to the verb, in the dative or genitive case (abbreviated) as the verb may require; but in the reflexive imperative and present participle the verb precedes the pronoun; <hi rend="italic">e.g. a propune,</hi>  to propose, <hi rend="italic">a fi propune, </hi>to propose to oneself, but <hi rend="italic">propune ft,</hi>  propose to yourself.</p><p>The accentuation of Rumanian, though complex, is governed by certain broad principles, except in the case ol neologisms, many of w<hi rend="sup">r</hi>hich have been borrowed from French and Italian without change of accent. Nouns retain the accent of the nominative singular in all cases and in both numbers<hi rend="italic">(e.g. copnlâ,</hi>  girl, vocative pi ur. <hi rend="italic">copïlelor),</hi>  except when a diminutive or augmentative suffix is added ; the accent then shifts to the suffix. The language is very rich in diminutive and augmentative forms; <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi>  the name <hi rend="italic">I6n</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Ioan</hi>  (John), has the diminutives <hi rend="italic">Ionicä, Ionita, Ionascu, Ianache, Ienachel,</hi>  &amp;c. In verbs—apart from a few exceptional tenses—the accent falls on the first syllable of the inflectional suffix, <hi rend="italic">e.g. eu dorm, </hi>I sleep, but <hi rend="italic">eü dormissent,</hi>  I had slept. For the sake of euphony, a vowel is frequently interpolated between two consonants; <hi rend="italic">e.g. </hi>in masculine nouns terminating in a consonant, an interpolated <hi rend="italic">u </hi>precedes <hi rend="italic">I</hi>  to form the suffix article <hi rend="italic">(om,</hi>  man, <hi rend="italic">om-u-l,</hi>  the man).</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.—(1) Dictionaries: A. deCihac,</hi><hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire d'étymologie daco-roumaine</hi>  (2 vols., Frankfort, 1870-79), valuable for non-Latin elements; B. P. Hâçdëu, <hi rend="italic">Etymologicum magnum Romaniae </hi>(Bucharest, Academia Romänä, 1887, &amp;c.); F. Damé, <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire roumain-français</hi>  (Paris, 1896); S. Pu^cariu, <hi rend="italic">Etymologisches Wörterbuch der rumänischen Sprache</hi>  (Heidelberg, 1905, &amp;c.); I. A. Candréa-Hecht and O. Densusianu, <hi rend="italic">Dicfionar general al limbeï române</hi>  (Bucharest, 1909, &amp;c.) ; 1. Dalametra, <hi rend="italic">Dictfonar Macedoromän </hi>(Bucharest, Academia Romänä, 1906).    (2) Grammars, &amp;c. :</p><p>T. Cipariu, <hi rend="italic">Gramatec'a limbeï romane</hi>  (Bucharest, 1870-77); 1. Nädejde, <hi rend="italic">Gramateca limbeï române</hi>  (Bucharest, 1884), id,, <hi rend="italic">Istoria limbet fi literatureï române</hi>  (Jassy, 1886); B. P. Hâçdeu, <hi rend="italic">Cuvent*</hi></p><lb/><p>@@@<hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>  the so-called Daco-Rumanian<hi rend="sub">;</hi>  spoken by the vast majority of Rumans over the whole of Rumania, in Transylvania, Bukovina, the Banat, Bessarabia, and some districts of Servia and Bulgaria bordering on the Danube. The two most important dialects are the Istro-Rumaqjan, spoken in part of 1 stria but rapidly becoming extinct, and the Macedo-Rumanian, spoken by the Kutzo-Vlachs (see Vlachs). The Istro-Rumanian forms, as it were, a link-now completely severed—between the Romance of the Balkans and the Romance of the West. In the Macedo-Rumanian there are no Magyar loan-words, but there is a large Albanian element, and Greek loan-words are more numerous than Slavonic.</p><lb/><p>@@@Apart from certain instances in which the Latin form has been artificially restored in comparatively modern times. (See under <hi rend="italic">Literature.)</hi></p><lb/></body></text></TEI>