<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>part being left rough. Similar work exists at Arak-el-Emir in Palestine (151B.C.). The finest examples are those of the walls of the temple at Jerusalem, and at Hebron, where the stones are of immense size and the rustication projects sometimes over a foot. The Crusaders’ castles in Palestine are all boldly rusticated, but the projecting portions have been worked over with a chisel in diagonal lines, and this enables them to be distinguished from the earlier masonry. In the five-sided tower at Nuremberg and the Burg-Capelle at Rothenburg, the rustication has a decorative value, so that in later work it was employed for the quoin-stones of towers. The masonry of the Palazzo Vecchio, and of the Pitti, Strozzi and Riccardi palaces, all in Florence, and of other palaces in Siena and Volterra, is rusticated. Rustication was employed in terraces and grottos in Italy, where on account of its extravagances it gave rise to the term “ grotesque.” In the later Renaissance the edges of the stone were bevelled off, with a sunk joint in addition; and the treatment was known as vermiculatcd, if in imitation of earth burrowed by worms; marine, if with small shell holes; stalactitic, if carved in imitation of lime deposits, &amp;c. In Italy the projecting portions were sometimes worked into facets. Rustication was introduced into England by Inigo Jones, who, in old Somerset House, York Stairs Watergate, the gateway of the Botanical Garden at Oxford, and elsewhere, used it only in alternate courses, his example being followed by other architects of the Renaissance. The term is now applied to the ashlar blocks of masonry which alternate with the circular drums of columns in many public buildings.</p><p>RÜSTOW, FRIEDRICH WILHELM (1821-1878), Swiss soldier and military writer, was a Prussian by birth. He entered the service of his native country, and served for some years, until the publication of <hi rend="italic">Der Deutsche Militärstaat vor und während der Revolution</hi>  (Zürich, 1850) brought him official condemnation. He was sentenced by a court-martial to a long term of fortress imprisonment, but succeeded in escaping to Switzerland. He obtained military employment in the service of the Republic, and in 1857 was major on the engineer staff. Three years later he accompanied Garibaldi in the famous expedition against the two Sicilies as colonel and chief of the staff, and to him must be ascribed the victories of Capua (19th Sept. i860) and the Voltumo (ist Oct. i860). At the end of the campaign he once more settled down at Zürich. At the outbreak of the war of 1870 he offered his services to Prussia, but was not accepted. In 1878, on the foundation of a military professorship at Zürich, Rüstow applied for the post, and, on its being given to another officer, lost heart and committed suicide.</p><p>Two younger brothers, both Prussian soldiers, were also distinguished men. The elder, Alexander (1824-1866), is remembered for his work <hi rend="italic">Der Küstenkrieg</hi>  (Berlin, 1848); the younger, Caesar (1826-1866), was one of the foremost experts of his time in the design and construction of military rifles, and the writer of several treatises on that subject, of which we may mention <hi rend="italic">Die Kriegshandfeuerwaffen</hi>  (Berlin, 1857-64). Both Alexander and Caesar fell on the field of battle in the war of 1866, at Königgrätz and Dermbach respectively.</p><p>Amongst F. W. Rüstow’s works, which covered nearly every branch of the military art, a large number must be mentioned. Historical—<hi rend="italic">Heerwesen und Kriegführung Julius Casars</hi>  (Gotha, 1855; 2nd ed., Nordhausen, 1862), <hi rend="italic">Kommentar zu Napoleon III.’s Geschichte Julius Casars</hi>  (Stuttgart, 1865-67), <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Griechischen Kriegswesens</hi>  (in collaboration with Köchly, Aarau, 1852k <hi rend="italic">Militär. Biographen (David, Xenophon, Montluc)</hi>  (Zürich, 1858), <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Infanterie</hi>  (Gotha, 1857-58; 3rd ed., 1884), <hi rend="italic">Die Ersten Feldzüge Napoleons 1796-1797</hi>  (Zürich, 1867), <hi rend="italic">Der Krieg von 1805 in Deutschland und Italien</hi>  (Frauenfeld, 1854), <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Ungarischen Insurrektionkrieges 1848-49</hi>  (Zürich, i860), reminiscences of i860 in Italy (Leipzig, 1861) and monographs on the campaigns of 1848-49 in Italy (Zürich, 1849) and the Crimean War (Zürich, 1855-56). Critical and General—<hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Taktik</hi>  (Zurich, 1858; 2nd ed., 1868), <hi rend="italic">Kriegspolitik und Kriegsgebrauch</hi>  (Zürich, 1876), <hi rend="italic">Militär-IIandwörterbuch</hi>  (Zürich, 1859), <hi rend="italic">Die Feldherrnkunst des XIX Jahrhunderts.</hi>  (Zürich, 1857; 3rd ed., 1878-79), <hi rend="italic">Der Krieg und seine Mittel</hi>  (Leipzig, 1856). He also wrote <hi rend="italic">Annalen des Königreichs Italien</hi>  (Zürich, 1862-63).</p><p>See Zernim, “ F. W. Rüstow,” in <hi rend="italic">Unsere Zeit.</hi>  vol. 2 (Leipzig, 1882).</p><p>RUTEBEUF, or Rustebuef (fl. 1245-1285), French <hi rend="italic">trouvère, </hi>was bom in the first half of the 13th century. His name is nowhere mentioned by his contemporaries. He frequently plays in his verse on the word Rutebeuf, which was probably a <hi rend="italic">nom de guerre,</hi>  and is variously explained by him as derived from <hi rend="italic">rude bœuf</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">rude œuvre.</hi>  He was evidently of humble birth, and he was a Parisian by education and residence. Paulin Paris thought that he began life in the lowest rank of the minstrel profession as a <hi rend="italic">jongleur.</hi>  Some of his poems have autobiographical value. In <hi rend="italic">Le Mariage de Rutebeuf </hi>he says that on the 2nd of January 1261 he married a woman old and ugly, with neither dowry nor amiability.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi>  In the <hi rend="italic">Complainte de Rutebeuf</hi>  he details a series of misfortunes which have reduced him to abject destitution. In these circumstances he addresses himself to Alphonse, comte de Poitiers, brother of Louis IX., for relief. Other poems in the same vein reveal that his own miserable circumstances were chiefly due to a love of play, particularly a game played with dice, which was known as <hi rend="italic">griesche.</hi>  It would seem that his distress could not be due to lack of patrons, for his metrical life of Saint Elizabeth of Hungary was written by request "of Erard de Valéry, who wished to present it to Isabel, queen of Navarre; and he wrote elegies on the deaths of Anccau de l’Isle Adam, the third of the name, who died about 1251, Eude, comte de Nevers (d. 1267), Thibaut V. of Navarre (d. 1270), and Alphonse, comte de Poitiers (d. 1271), which were probably paid for by the families of the personages celebrated. In the <hi rend="italic">Pauvreté de Rutebeuf</hi>  he addresses Louis IX. himself.</p><p>The piece which is most obviously intended for popular recitation is the Zhï <hi rend="italic">de FHerberic,</hi>  a dramatic monologue in prose and verse supposed to be delivered by a quack doctor. Rutebeuf was also a master in the verse <hi rend="italic">conte,</hi>  and the five of his <hi rend="italic">fabliaux</hi>  that have come down to us are gay and amusing. The matter, it may be added, is sufficiently gross. The adventures of <hi rend="italic">Frère Denyse le cordelier,</hi>  and of <hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">u</hi>  la dame qui alla trois fois autour du moûtier,”</hi>  find a place in the <hi rend="italic">Cent Nouvelles nouvelles.</hi></p><p>Rutebeuf’s serious work as a satirist probably dates from about 1260. His chief topics are the iniquities of the friars, and the defence of the secular clergy of the university of Paris against their encroachments; and he delivered a series of eloquent and insistent poems (1262, 1263, 1268, 1274) exhorting princes and people to take part in the crusades. He was a redoubtable champion of the university of Paris in its quarrel with the religious orders who were supported by Pope Alexander IV., and he boldly defended Guillaume de Saint-Amour when he was driven into exile. The libels, indecent songs and rhymes condemned by the pope to be burnt together with the <hi rend="italic">Périls des derniers temps</hi>  attributed to Saint-Amour, were probably the work of Rutebeuf. The satire of <hi rend="italic">Renart le Bcs-tourné,</hi>  which borrows from the Reynard cycle little but the names under which the characters are disguised, was directed, according to Paulin Paris, against Philip the Bold. To his later years belong his religious poems, and also the <hi rend="italic">Voie de Paradis,</hi>  the description of a dream, in the manner of the <hi rend="italic">Roman de la Rose.</hi></p><p>The best work of Rutebeuf is to be found in his satires and verse <hi rend="italic">contes.</hi>  A miracle play of his, <hi rend="italic">Le Miracle de Théophile, </hi>is one of the earliest dramatic pieces extant in French. The subject of Theophilus, the Cilician monk who made a pact with the devil, which was afterwards returned to him by the intervention, of the Virgin, was a familiar one with the story-tellers of the middle ages. Rutebeuf can claim no priority in the choice of the subject, which had been treated dramatically in the Latin piece ascribed to the nun Hroswitha of Gandersheim, but his piece has considerable importance in dramatic history.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Œuvres</hi>  of Rutebeuf were edited by Achille Jubînal in 1839 (new edition, 1874); a more critical edition is by Dr Adolf Kressner</p><p>@@@It has been suggested that Brunetto Latini was thinking of Rutebeuf when he wrote in his<hi rend="italic">Livre du Trésor*.</hi>  ” Le Rire, le jeu, voilà la vie du jongleur, qui se moque de lui-même, de sa femme, de ses enfants, de tout le monde.”</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>