<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-10T23:11:54Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ST IVES, a seaport and borough of west Cornwall, England, is situated at the west entrance of the beautiful St Ives Bay on the Bristol Channel, 7 miles north of Penzance. The older streets are narrow and irregular, but on the slopes above there are modern terraces with good houses. The town takes its name from St Hya or Ia, an Irish virgin who is said to have arrived in the bay in the 5th century. The parish church of St Andrew is in the Early Perpendicular style of the 15th century. In the churchyard is an ancient cross recently restored. A town-hall was erected in 1832. The town is the headquarters of the pilchard fishery. The port has suffered greatly from the accumulation of sand. A stone pier was built by Smeaton in 1767 ; a breakwater was commenced in 1816 but abandoned; and a wooden pier, which was commenced in 1865, is still unfinished. Formerly the town was called Pendenis or Pendunes. Its charter of incorporation, granted by Charles I. in 1639, was forfeited in 1685, but was renewed by James II. in 1686. From the reign of John until 1832 it sent two members to parliament, and one from 1832 until 1885, when it was merged in the St Ives division of the county. The population of the municipal borough (area, 1890 acres) in 1871 was 6965, and in 1881 it was 6445.</p><p>ST JEAN BAPTISTE, a suburb of Montreal, Canada, under a separate municipality. It lies north-north-east of Mount Royal Park and is hardly a mile from the centre of the city. The population in 1881 was 5874.</p><p>ST JEAN D’ACRE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Acre.</hi></p><p>ST JEAN D’ANGÉLY, a town of France, the chef-lieu of an arrondissement in the department of Charente-Inférieure, on the right bank of the Boutonne (a right-hand affluent of the Charente) and on the railway from Taille- bourg (12 miles south-west) to Niort (30 miles north). The town, which is badly planned and built, contains the remains of a Benedictine abbey, destroyed in 1568; the existing church corresponds to but a part of the large old abbey church erected in the 13th century. The harbour admits vessels of 30 to 40 tons burden, and wine and brandy are exported. The population was 6538 in 1881 (7279 in the commune).</p><p>St Jean owes its origin to a castle of the 7th century, which the dukes of Aquitaine used as a lodge for boar-hunting in the neighbouring forest of Angeri. Pippin, son of Louis le Debonnaire, turned it into a monastery, where he deposited the head of John Baptist. This relic attracted hosts of pilgrims ; a town grew up, took the name St Jean d’Angeri, afterwards d’Angély, was fortified in 1131, and in 1204 received from Philip Augustus a communal charter. The possession of the place was disputed between French and English in the Hundred Years’ War, and between Catholics and Protestants at a later date. Louis XIII. took it from the Protestants in 1629 and deprived it of its fortifications, its privileges, and its very name, which he wished to change into Bourg-Louis.</p><p>ST JOHN, capital of St John county and the largest city of the province of New Brunswick, is strikingly situated at the mouth of the river of the same name, in 45 14 6 ' N. lat. and 66° 3' 30" W. long (see vol. xvii., plate IV.). It stands on an elevated rocky peninsula which projects into the harbour for a considerable distance. The latter, which is protected by batteries and never freezes, is well equipped with wharves and docks, and is capable of accommodating ships of the largest size. Its. entrance is guarded by Partridge Island, lying 2 miles south of the city, and containing the quarantine hospital and lighthouse. About 1<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">4</hi> miles north of the lighthouse is situated the Beacon, and below the town east of the channel is the breakwater, 2250 feet long. The St John river enters the harbour through a rocky and sharply defined gorge, 100 yards wide and about 400 long, having a total fall of about 17 feet, which is passable to ships for forty-five minutes during each ebb and flow of the tide. The river has alternately an inward and an outward fall twice</p><p>every twenty-four hours, the high-water tide level immediately below the gorge being 6 to 8 feet higher than the average level above the gorge. The river is here spanned by a stanch suspension bridge 640 feet long and 100 feet above low-water level, and a cantilever railway bridge, 2260 feet long, with a river span of 825 feet, was opened</p><p>in 1885. The city, approached from the sea, presents a bold and picturesque appearance, and, next to Quebec, possesses more natural beauty than any other town in Canada. There are three large public squares, and the streets (lighted with gas and the electric light) are regularly laid out. The water supply is derived from Little river, 5 miles distant, and brought to the city by three separate mains with an aggregate capacity estimated at 10,000,000 gallons daily; the present daily consumption (including that of the city of Portland) is 5,000,000 gallons. The works, which are owned by the city, cost $992,326. The water supply of St John (West) is derived from Spruce Lake. St John (East) has also an admirable sewerage system.</p><p>On the 20th of June 1877 two-fifths of St John (about 200 acres) were destroyed by a fire, which in nine hours burned over $27,000,000 worth of property. The city was quickly rebuilt, and on a much grander scale, many brick and stone edifices taking the place of the old landmarks, which were principally composed of wood. The chief buildings are—the Roman Catholic cathedral, Trinity, St Andrew’s, the Stone, St David’s, the Centenary, Germain Street Baptist, and Leinster Street Baptist churches, the custom-house, post-office, city-hall, savings bank, Wiggins’s Orphan Asylum, Victoria skating-rink, lunatic asylum, Victoria and Madras schools, the Masonic and Oddfellows’ halls, the young men’s Christian association building, the general public, the epidemic, and the marine hospitals, the court-house, jail, police office, and mechanics’ institute (with a reading-room, library, and museum). There are thirty-three places of worship (Church of England 6, Roman Catholic 3, Presbyterian 7, Wesleyan Methodist 5, Baptist 6, Congregationalist 1, Methodist Episcopal 1, Christian Brethren 1, Disciples of Christ 2, and Christ- adelphians 1); the educational institutions consist of a grammar-school, a Madras school, Baptist seminary, and</p></body></text></TEI>