<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-10T23:13:13Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>about 1200 Angolares, descendants of a shipload of Angola slaves wrecked at Sete
                Pedras in 1544, who still retain their Bunda speech and peculiar customs.</p>
            <p>St Thomas was discovered about the close of 1470 by the Portuguese navigators João de
                Santarem and Pero de Escobar, who in the beginning of the following year discovered
                Annobom (“Good Year”). They found St Thomas uninhabited. The first attempts at
                colonization were João de Paiva’s in 1485 ; but nothing permanent was accomplished
                till 1493, when a body of criminals and of young Jews torn from their parents to be
                baptized were sent to the island, and the present capital was founded by Alvaro de
                Carminha. Considerable progress had been made by the 16th century ; but in 1567 the
                settlement was attacked by the French, and in 1574 the Angolares began those raids
                which only ended with their subjugation in 1693. In 1595 there was a slave revolt ;
                and from 1641 to 1844 the Dutch, who had plundered the capital in 1600, held
                possession of the island. The French did great damage in 1709 ; and in the course of
                the century internal anarchy reduced St Thomas to a deplorable state.</p>
            <p>See Dr Greeff’s papers in <hi rend="italic">Petermann’s Mitteilungen,</hi> 1884, and
                    <hi rend="italic">Globus,</hi> 1882, vol. xlii.</p>
            <p>SAINT-VICTOR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Paul de</hi> (1827-1883), one of the chief masters
                of a very ornate style in recent French literature, was born at Paris in 1827 and
                died there in 1883. He was of noble birth and inherited the title of count, but
                rarely used it, his political principles being democratic. Saint-Victor began as a
                dramatic critic on the <hi rend="italic">Pays</hi> in 1851 and subsequently wrote in
                many journals. In 1870, during the last days of the second empire, he was made
                inspector-general of fine arts. Almost all Saint-Victor’s work consists of reprinted
                articles, the best known, and on the whole the best, being the collection entitled
                    <hi rend="italic">Hommes et Dieux</hi> (1867). His death interrupted the
                publication of an elaborate work, partly reprinted, partly developed from formerly
                printed papers, entitled <hi rend="italic">Les Deux Masques, </hi>in which the
                author intended to survey the whole dramatic literature of ancient and modern times.
                Saint-Victor’s actual critical faculty was considerable, though rather onesided ;
                but his position in French literature is likely to be, in an inferior degree,
                something like that of Mr Ruskin in English. He owed a good deal to Théophile
                Gautier, but he carried ornateness to a pitch far beyond Gautier’s, —a pitch which
                may sometimes deserve the epithet “ barbaric.”</p>
            <p>ST VINCENT, an island in the West Indies, discovered by Columbus in 1498, is situated
                in 13° 10' N. lat. and 60° 57' W. long., 100 miles to the west of Barbados; it is 18
                miles in length, 11 in breadth, and has an area of 132 square miles. Volcanic hills
                cross the island from north to south, intersected by beautiful and fertile valleys.
                In the north-west is the Souffriere, a volcanic mountain (3000 feet), of which the
                last violent eruption was in 1812 ; the crater is 3 miles in circumference and 500
                feet in depth. The climate is humid and tolerably healthy (average rainfall nearly
                80 inches). In 1627, when Charles I. granted St Vincent to the earl of Carlisle, it
                was peopled by Caribs; in 1672 it was given to Lord Willoughby, and in 1722 was
                granted, along with other islands, to the duke of Montagu by George I. After
                hostilities with the French and Caribs, it passed definitively to Great Britain in
                1783. Immigrants were afterwards introduced and plantations cultivated ; the chief
                products are sugar, rum, molasses, and arrowroot. The capital is Kingstown
                (population, 5593), the total population of the island being 42,200, including 2700
                Europeans and 30,000 Africans. The island was formerly under the general government
                of the Windward Islands, Barbados being headquarters ; but in 1885 Barbados was made
                a separate government, and Grenada, St Vincent, Tobago, and St Lucia were placed
                under a governor. The legislative council of St Vincent is composed of official
                members and others nominated by the crown. In 1883 the revenue and expenditure were
                respectively £34,509 and £32,962, the debt being £2840. The tonnage entered and
                cleared was 172,989, the imports</p>
            <p>and exports being valued at £148,286 and £166,752 respectively (sugar exports, 9250
                tons).</p>
            <p>ST VINCENT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John Jervis, Earl</hi> (1734-1823), a
                distinguished naval officer, was born at Meaford, Staffordshire, on 9th January
                1734. His father was counsel and solicitor to the admiralty and treasurer of
                Greenwich hospital. Young Jervis was destined for the law, but early showed such a
                strong predilection for the sea that he ran away from school in order to become a
                sailor. Accordingly in 1748 he was placed on board the “Gloucester” under Commodore
                Townsend. Six years later he rose to be lieutenant, and in 1759 he distinguished
                himself so much at the siege and capture of Quebec that he was promoted to the rank
                of commander. In the following year he was made a post-captain. He commanded the “
                Foudroyant ” in July 1778, when the memorable <hi rend="italic">rencontre</hi> took
                place between Admiral Keppel and Count d’Orvilliers, and bore a very distinguished
                part in that action. In 1782, while in command of the same vessel, he captured the
                French ship “ Pégase,” of 74 guns and 700 men, off Brest Harbour, and was rewarded
                for his exploit by being made Knight Companion of the Bath. In 1784 he entered
                parliament as member for Launceston, and he afterwards sat for Yarmouth. Conjointly
                with Sir Charles Grey, Jervis was appointed to command an expedition sent out in
                1793 against the French Caribbee islands, and, though the rainy season and the
                yellow fever prevented the full success of the British, they were able to obtain
                possession of Martinique and St Lucia, and to hold Guadaloupe for a short time. In
                1795 Jervis became full admiral and succeeded Lord Wood in command of the British
                fleet in the Mediterranean, where he rendered important service in blockading the
                French fleet in Toulon, and protecting English trade in the Levant. On 14th February
                1797 he won his most celebrated victory. With only fifteen ships of the line, seven
                frigates, and two sloops he encountered off Cape St Vincent a Spanish fleet of
                twenty-six sail of the line, twelve frigates, and a brig, and completely defeated
                it, capturing four of the enemy’s largest ships. For this great triumph, which had a
                most important effect on the prosecution of the war, Jervis was created a peer by
                the title of Earl St Vincent. He still further distinguished himself some months
                later by his resolute and sagacious conduct in repressing a mutiny in his fleet when
                off Cadiz. In June 1799 he resigned his command in consequence of ill-health, but
                was shortly afterwards placed at the head of the Channel fleet. On the formation of
                the Addington ministry in 1801 he was made first lord of the admiralty, and in that
                important office, which he held for three years, the great capacity for business
                with which he was endowed by nature shone forth in all its lustre. By means of the
                celebrated commission of naval inquiry he was enabled to expose a vast extent of
                corruption in the public service and to lay the foundation of a system of economical
                administration. He grappled boldly -with the monstrous and deep-rooted abuses
                brought to light, and by his vigour, honesty, and energy succeeded in rectifying
                them. In 1806, at the age of seventy-two, Lord St Vincent was again called upon to
                take the command of the Channel fleet and to head an expedition to the court of
                Portugal, in which he displayed great talents and address. Advanced age and impaired
                health led to his final retirement from public life in 1807, but he survived till
                13th March 1823, when he died in his ninetieth year.</p>
            <p>See Brenton, <hi rend="italic">Life of Earl St Vincent</hi> ; Lord Brougham, <hi
                    rend="italic">Statesmen of the Times of George III.</hi></p>
            <p>ST VITUS’S DANCE, @@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Chorea,</hi> a disorder of the</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> This name was originally employed in connexion with
                those remarkable epidemic outbursts of combined mental and physical excitement which
                for a time prevailed among the inhabitants of some parts of Germany in the Middle
                Ages. It is stated that sufferers from <pb n="202"/>this dancing mania were wont to resort to the
                chapels of St Vitus (more than one in Swabia), the saint being believed to possess
                the power of curing them. The transference of the name to the disease now under
                consideration was a manifest error, but so closely has the association now become
                that the original application of the term has been comparatively obscured.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
