<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-10T23:11:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>SAIL, SAILCLOTH, SAILMAKING. A sail is a sheet of canvas (or other material of the
                requisite flexibility and strength) by the action of the wind on which, when spread
                out or extended, a vessel is moved through the water. Sails are supported and
                extended by means of masts, yards, gaffs, booms, bowsprit—all technically termed
                “spars”—and stays or slanting ropes. In the first experiments for impelling vessels
                by sails the least complicated form, that of a single square sail erected on a
                single mast, was no doubt adopted. To the quadrangular the triangular sail would
                soon be added; and single sails of both these forms are known to have been used at
                very early periods. Subsequently the trapeziform and trapezoidal sails also came
                into use. As vessels increased in size, thereby requiring a greater surface of
                canvas to impel them, it became necessary to use not only more sails but also an
                increased number of masts; and the number and disposition of the several kinds of
                sails could be almost indefinitely varied according to the ideas of navigators, the
                services required of the vessels, the places in which they were employed, and the
                size of the crews. Thus a great variety of rig naturally arose. Leaving out of
                account the many nondescript styles adopted in the case of boats and small craft,
                all modern vessels may, for general purposes, be considered as belonging to one or
                other of the following categories—cutter, schooner, three-masted schooner,
                brigantine, brig, barquetine, barque, or full square-rigged ship; but the cardinal
                distinction is that by which they are classified as <hi rend="italic"
                    >square-rigged</hi> or <hi rend="italic">fore-and-aft-rigged</hi> (compare <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Seamanship</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Ship).</hi> These
                expressions can be easily explained by reference to any three-masted ship. The mast
                nearest the bow or head is known as the fore-mast, the next abaft or nearest the
                middle of the ship as the main-mast, and the third or that nearest the stern as the
                mizzen-mast. Each mast consists of several sections, that attached to the hull being
                called the lower or standing- mast, the next above that the top-mast, the next the
                topgallant-mast, above which may rise a pole or royal-mast. On each of these masts,
                and at right angles with it, is a yard denominated “ square,” which is hung (slung)
                by the middle and balanced. These yards are named according to their situation,
                those placed on the fore and main standing-masts being called respectively the fore
                and main lower-yards, that on the mizzen the cross-jack-yard; the yards on the
                top-masts are called the top-sail-yards, those on the top-gallant-masts the
                top-gallant-yards, and those on the royal-masts the royal-yards. To each of these
                yards a sail is <hi rend="italic">bent</hi> or attached, taking its name from the
                yard; thus the principal sail upon the fore-lower-yard is called the fore-course or
                fore-sail; the next above, upon the fore-top-sail-yard, is the fore-top-sail; above
                which, upon the fore-top-gallant-yard, is the fore-top-gallant-sail; and above all,
                upon the fore-royal-yard, is the fore-royal. In like manner on the main-mast we have
                the main-course or main-sail, main-top-sail, main-top-gallant-sail, and the
                main-royal. Similar appellations are given to those on the mizzen-mast; in large
                merchant-ships, by means of a sky-sail-pole, a sail termed “sky-scraper” is
                sometimes set above the royals, but not so frequently as formerly. Such square sails
                can be placed at right angles to the direction of the keel of the ship, a position
                given to them when going before the wind ; the same sails can also, by means of
                braces, be placed obliquely to the keel with a side wind, commonly termed by seamen
                “ on a wind ” or “ by the wind.” In addition to these there are sails between the
                masts, set either on gaffs (unbalanced) or on stays, also others beyond the
                extremities of the ship, extended principally by means of the bowsprit, which, in
                addition to supporting the fore-mast by a stay, also supports the jib and
                flying-jib-booms for extending the sails still farther</p>
            <p>forwards ; the means for extending the after-sail are the driver or spanker-boom and
                the gaff. Sails extended or set on gaffs and on stays are called “fore-and-aft,” and
                are generally or approximately in a vertical plane passing through the keel ; but a
                certain degree of obliquity can be given them by easing off the sheet or aft lower
                corner of the sail. A ship fitted as above described would be termed
                “square-rigged,” the square sails predominating both in importance and in number. A
                square-rigged line- of-battle ship would be supplied with the following descriptions
                of sails @@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> :—</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Square.</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Fore-and-Aft.</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Fore-course or fore-sail.</cell>
                    <cell>Flying-jib.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>,, top-sail.</cell>
                    <cell>Jib.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>,, top-gallant-sail.</cell>
                    <cell>Second jib.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>,, royal.</cell>
                    <cell>Fore-gaff-sail.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Main-course or main-sail.</cell>
                    <cell>,, try-sail (storm-sail).</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>,, top-sail.</cell>
                    <cell>Main-gaff-sail.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>,, top-gallant-saiL ,, royal.</p><p>Mizzen-top-sail.</p></cell>
                    <cell>„ try-sail (storm-sail).</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>Mizzen-try-sail (storm-sail).</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>Spanker.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>„ top-gallant-sail.</cell>
                    <cell>Stay-sail-fore (storm-sail).</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>,, royal. Studding-sail-fore.</p><p>,, ,, top.</p><p>,, „
                            top-gallant.</p><p>,, sail-main-top-gallant.</p></cell>
                    <cell>„ „ top.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">In the fore-and-aft-rig the principal sails are of course</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>fore-and-aft ; a cutter (vessel</cell>
                    <cell>with one mast) when fully</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">equipped carries the following :—</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Fore-and-Aft.</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="italic">Square.</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell><p>Jib-top-sail.</p><p>Jib.</p><p>Fore-sail.</p><p>Boom-main-sail.</p><p>Gaff-top-sail.</p></cell>
                    <cell>Square-sail (set flying).</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>The several sides of a sail have separate names applied to them, the upper part or
                side being known as the “ head,” the lower part as the “ foot ”; the sides in
                general are called “ leeches,” but the weather or side edge where the wind enters
                the sail, of any but a square-sail, is called the “luff,” and the other edge the
                “after-leech.” The two top corners are “earings,” but the top corner of a jib,
                &amp;c. (triangular, one corner only), is the “head”; the two bottom corners are in
                general “ clews ”; and the weather clew of a fore- and-aft-sail or of a course while
                set is the “ tack.”</p>
            <p>The relative importance of particular sails in the working of a ship varies according
                to conditions of weather, and is a matter for the judgment of the officer in
                command. The following table, however, shows approximately what sails are commonly
                set “ by the wind,” presuming that the effect on the ship in relation to her
                stability is safe :—</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>winds as commonly distinguished.</cell>
                    <cell>Sails commonly set “by the wind.”</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell><p>Light airs </p><p>Light winds </p><p>Light breezes ... Moderate breezes
                            Fresh breezes ...</p><p>Strong breezes ...</p><p>Moderate
                            gales...</p><p>Fresh gales </p><p>Strong gales </p><p>Heavy gales
                            </p><p>Storms.</p></cell>
                    <cell><p> Courses, top-sails, top-gallant-sails, royals,</p><p>spanker, jib,
                            flying-jib, and all light sails.</p><p>Royals and flying-jib taken in,
                            in a sea way, to two reefs in the top-sails.</p><p>Single-reefed
                            top-sails, and top-gallant-sails, in much sea, two reefs in the
                            top-sails to taking in top-gallant-sails.</p><p>Double-reefed top-sails
                            to treble-reefed topsails, reefed spanker, and jib.</p><p>Close-reefed
                            top-sails, reefed courses, to tak- ing in spanker, jib, fore and mizzen
                            top- sail.</p><p>Reefed courses, close-reefed main-top-sail,
                            fore-stay-sail, mizzen-try-sail, to taking in the
                            main-sail.</p><p>Close-reefed main-top-sail, storm stay-sails, to storm
                            stay-sails or close-reefed main-topsail only.</p></cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Some ships (merchant-liners) have two jibs, inner
                and outer, and <pb n="35"/>their top-sails also in two parts, upper and lower or cap-top-sails, an arrangement
                    which makes it easier to reduce or shorten sail; they also have a mizzen course
                    (cross-jack), and carry several light stay-sails so as to catch every breath of
                    wind.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
