<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-23T18:49:53Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>behaviour of Spain, he made a treaty with France against Philip. But he could not remain faithful for long, and, siding first with one and then with the other, he found himself in almost the same straits as his grandfather, when death put an end to his ambitions and failures in 1630. The first care of his son <hi rend="smallcaps">Victor Amadeus</hi> was to free himself from the double burden of his enemy and his ally, so he concluded peace in 1631. In 1635, however, Richelieu determined to drive the Spaniards out of Italy, and offered the duke the alternatives of war or Milan. He gave but a half-hearted assent to the schemes of France, and, without gaining Milan, died in 1637, leaving by his wife Christina of France Francis Hyacinth, a minor, who only survived till the following year, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Emmanuel </hi>II., whose legitimacy was unfortunately rather doubtful. The regency of Christina resembled that of Yolande in the same need for guarding her son’s interests against the pretensions of his uncles, Louis XIII. and the princes of Savoy. But fortune favoured her, and on the duke’s reaching his majority in 1648 the wars of the Fronde occupied all the attention of Mazarin. The brunt of the conflict with Spain consequently fell upon Savoy, and was borne not ingloriously until the conclusion of peace. Charles Emmanuel occupied the remaining part of his reign in repairing the ravages caused by twenty-four years of warfare, and died in 1675, leaving an only son, <hi rend="smallcaps">Victor Amadeus</hi> II., whose minority was as peaceful as his father’s had been the reverse. He married Mary of Orleans, the daughter of Henrietta of England, and consequently the legitimate heiress to the English crown on the death of Anne and on the exclusion of the Pretender. For a time he united with Louis XIV. in persecuting the Protestants, but the overbearing behaviour of his ally made him join the coalition of Augsburg in 1690. His campaign against Louis was carried on with varying results until 1695, when he accepted proposals of peace. This defection led to the peace of Ryswick in 1697, and in reward he received from Louis the territories then occupied by France. In 1700 he sided with France against Austria, but, an extension of territory in the Milanese not being granted by Louis, he went over to the enemy in 1703. The generalship of his relative Prince Eugene proved too much for the French, and in 1706 they were defeated before Turin and driven across the frontier. The peace of Utrecht afterwards confirmed the duke in the possession of the places granted on his joining the coalition, including the long-coveted Montferrato, and endowed him besides with the crown of Sicily. Austrian influences now replaced Spanish in the peninsula, and Charles VI. persuaded him to exchange his kingdom for that of Sardinia. This was accordingly effected in 1720 by the treaty of Madrid, and afterwards proved the very salvation of the house of Savoy. In 1730 the king abdicated in favour of his son, in order to marry the countess of San Sebastian, at whose instigation he afterwards tried to regain the crown, but he died in 1732.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Emmanuel</hi> III. continued his father’s intrigues to obtain possession of Milan, and joined the league of France and Spain against Austria in 1732. But he used the victories of the allied forces over the imperialists in such a half-hearted way that it seemed as if he did not wish to break finally with Austria. In the end he only gained from the treaty, which he signed in 1739, the Novarese and Tortona, instead of Milan. The death of Charles VI. in 1740 gave him the chance of expelling the Austrians from Italy, but, though he at first claimed Milan from Maria Theresa, he ended in 1742 by espousing her cause. The complete defeat of the French in 1747 led to the treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle, by which Charles Emmanuel received the Upper Novarese and Vigevano, after which he remained at peace until bis death in 1773. His son</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Victor Amadeus</hi> III. succeeded him, and devoted the early years of his reign to the improvement of the administration and the reorganization of his army. The time soon came for him to use the weapon he had created, and on the outbreak of the Revolution in France he headed the coalition of Italian princes against her. The house of Savoy thus assumed the headship of Italy, but for the time without much gain, for Napoleon’s brilliant victories of 1796 ended in the peace of Paris, by which Savoy, along with Nice, was given to France. Victor Amadeus died shortly afterwards, and was succeeded by his son <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Emmanuel</hi> IV. The fever of the Revolution spread to Piedmont, and in 1798 nothing was left to the king but to retire to Sardinia. In 1802 he abdicated in favour of his brother, <hi rend="smallcaps">Victor Emmanuel</hi> I., who, in his island kingdom, protected by the English fleet, became the symbol of the coalition against France. The king returned to Turin in 1814, and in the following year took possession again of Savoy. The anti-revolutionary measures which were adopted by the Italian princes on their return caused a spirit of rebellion to spring up among their subjects. The freedom of the individual and the unity of the nation thus came to be considered objects to be attained at one and the same time. The influence of Austria was paramount in the Peninsula, but an insurrection broke out at Turin in 1820 demanding war with her, and, rather than embroil himself both with his people and with Austria, Victor Emmanuel abdicated in favour of his brother, <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles Felix.</hi> The general insurrection was suppressed, and for the next few years Italy suffered everything possible at the hands of various petty princes, whose fears and weakness left them no weapon but persecution. In 1831 Charles Felix died without issue, and in him the elder branch of the family ended. He was succeeded by <hi rend="smallcaps">Charles AlberT, </hi>of the line of Savoy-Carignano, which was founded by Thomas Francis, son of Charles Emmanuel the Great, and grandfather of Prince Eugene. The first care of Charles Albert was to reorganize his military and naval forces in readiness for the conflict with Austria which he foresaw. At the same time he put down the conspiracies which would have forced his hand, among which the most famous was that of Mazzini and Ramorino in 1834. The French revolution of 1848 fanned the embers of Italian patriotism, and Charles Albert, without any aid, began the War of Independence. Victory at first followed his arms, but he was defeated at last by the Austrians at Custozza. In the next year he was again driven into war with the Austrians, and, after his defeat at Novara, he abdicated in favour of his son, <hi rend="smallcaps">Victor Emmanuel</hi> II. From this point the history of the house of Savoy has been told in the article  <hi rend="smallcaps">Italy</hi> (vol. xiii. pp. 489 <hi rend="italic">sq.).	</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(h. b. b.)</hi></p><p>SAVOY. For the French departments of Savoy and Upper Savoy see <hi rend="smallcaps">Savoie</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Savoie, HauTE-.</hi></p><p>SAW. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Saws.</hi></p><p>SÁWANTWÁRI, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Sawuntwarrie,</hi> a native state forming the southern part of the Concan division of the Bombay presidency, India, and lying between 15° 37' and 16° 16' N. lat. and between 73° 36' and 74° 21' E. long. It has a total area of about 900 square miles, and is bounded on the north and west by Ratnagiri district, on the east by the Sahyádri Mountains, and on the south by the Portuguese territory of Goa. The general aspect of the country is strikingly picturesque. Its surface is broken and rugged, interspersed with densely-wooded hills; in the valleys are gardens and groves of cocoa-nut and betel-nut palms. Sáwantwári has no rivers of any considerable size; the chief streams are the Karli on the north and the Terekhol on the south, both navigable for small craft. The climate is humid and relaxing, with an average annual rainfall of over 130 inches. The forests and wooded</p></body></text></TEI>