<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-23T18:48:49Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>£3,632,838 in 1878-79. The export and import trade is estimated to circulate £10,000,000 a year. The population has increased since 1870 from 9000 to about 15,000.</p><p>As the city of São Vicente, the first permanent Portuguese settlement in Brazil, began to decline from its position as capital of the southern provinces, Santos, founded by Braz Cuba in 1543-46, gradually took its place. In the 17th century it was besieged by the Dutch and English. The provincial assembly passed an enactment by which the city was to be called Cidade de Bonifacio in honour of José Bonifacio d’Andrade e Silva, the national patriot, to whom it had given birth, but the older name of Santos held its ground.</p><p>SÃO LEOPOLDO, a German colony in the province of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil, founded in 1824. It is connected with Porto Alegre by rail and also by the Rio do Jinos, a small but deep and navigable river. The inhabitants of the town and sixteen neighbouring settlements number in all about 20,000, and are engaged in cattle-breeding and in the culture of grain, arrow-root, and sugar. </p><p>SAÔNE. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Rhone.</hi></p><p>SAÔNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Haute-,</hi> a department in the north-east of France, formed in 1790 from the northern portion of Franche Comté, and traversed by the river Saône. Situated between 47° 14' and 48° 1' N. lat. and between 5° 21 and 6° 49' E. long., it is bounded N. by the department of the Vosges, E. by the territory of Belfort, S. by Doubs and Jura, and W. by Côte-d’Or and Haute- Marne. On the north-east, where they are formed by the Vosges, and to the south along the course of the Ognon the limits are natural. The highest point of the department is the Ballon de Servance (3900 feet), and the lowest the confluence of the Saône and Ognon (610 feet). The general slope is from north-east to south-west, the direction followed by those two streams. In the north-east the department belongs to the Vosgian formation, consisting of pine-clad mountains of sandstone and granite ; but throughout the greater part of its extent it is composed of limestone plateaus 800 to 1000 feet high pierced with crevasses and subterranean caves, into which the rain water disappears to issue again as springs in the valleys 200 feet lower down. In its passage through the department the Saône receives from the right the Amance and the Salon from the Langres plateau, and from the left the Coney, the Lanterne (augmented by the Breuchin which passes by Luxeuil), the Durgeon (passing Vesoul), and the Ognon. The north-eastern districts are cold in climate and have an annual rainfall ranging from 36 to 48 inches. Towards the south-west the characteristics become those of the Rhone valley generally. At Vesoul and Gray the rainfall only reaches 24 inches per annum.</p><p>Out of a total of 1,319,570 acres 664,846 are arable, 375,999 under forest, 153,278 natural meadows and orchards, and 31,752 vineyards. The agricultural population numbers 180,893 out of a total of 295,905. They possess 22,331 horses, 152,609 cattle, 63,000 sheep, 72,678 pigs, 7094 goats, more than 19,000 dogs, and 15,915 beehives (40 tons 15 cwts. of honey in 1881). Wheat is the staple crop—2,727,425 bushels in 1883 ; next come oats, 3,188,322 bushels; potatoes, 8,175,673 bushels; wine, mostly of middling quality, 4,887,652 gallons (average vintage for the last ten years 6,086,652 gallons) ; rye, 449,308 bushels ; barley, 396,940 ; meslin, 276,251 ; buckwheat, 63,945; maize, 64,924; millet, 154 ; colza, 456 tons ; beetroot, 26,365 tons ; pulse, 5662 bushels ; hemp, linen, tobacco, hops. The woods, which cover more than a quarter of the department, are composed of firs in the Vosges and beech trees, oaks, wych elms, and aspens in the other districts. Kirschwasser is manufactured at Fougerolles from the native cherries. The industrial population number 51,477 ; 550 workmen raise 143,842 tons of iron-ore yearly ; copper, silver, and manganese exist in the department, and gold occurs in the bed of the Ognon. Rock-salt mines yield annually 11,000 tons of salt and the materials for a considerable manufacture of sulphuric, hydrochloric, and nitric acids, sulphate of soda, chloride of lime, and Epsom and Glauber salts. Coal mines, with their principal centre at Ronchamp, give employment to more than 2000 workmen, and in 1883 yielded 212,680 tons of coal. Peat, limestone, plaster,</p><p>building-stone, marble, porphyry, granite, syenite, and sandstone are all worked in the department. The green porphyry pedestal of Napoleon’s sarcophagus at Les Invalides and the syenite columns of the Grand Opera in Paris were cut at Servance. Οf the many mineral waters of Haute-Saône the best known are the hot springs of Luxeuil, which, with their sixteen saline and two chalybeate sources, discharge over 127,000 gallons in the 24 hours and are used for bathing and drinking. Besides forty-seven iron-working establishments (smelting furnaces, foundries, and wire-drawing mills, producing in 1883 4875 tons of iron smelted by wood-fuel, 286 tons of refined iron and 1040 tons of sheet-iron, &amp;c.), Haute- Saône possesses copper-foundries, engineering works, steel-foundries, and factories for producing tin plate, nails, pins, files, saws, screws, shot, chains, agricultural implements, locks, spinning machinery, edge tools, &amp;c. Window-glass is manufactured by 105 workmen and glass wares by 300, pottery and earthenware by 220 to 230. There are also about 100 brick and tile works; the paper-mills employ 329 hands, and the 21 cotton-mills (66,700 spindles and 2518 looms, of which 154 are hand-looms) upwards of 2000. Printworks, fulling mills, hosiery factories, and straw-hat factories are also of some account ; as well as sugar-works, dye-works, saw-mills, starch-works, chemical works, oil-mills, tanyards, and flour-mills. The department exports wheat (893,000 bushels), cattle, iron, wood, pottery, kirschwasser, and cooper’s wares. The Saône provides a navigable channel of 40 miles, which is about to be connected with the Moselle and the Meuse by the Canal de l’Est in course of construction along the valley of the Coney. Gray is the great emporium of the water-borne trade, estimated at 200,000 tons per annum. The department has 186 miles of national roads, 3313 miles of other roads, and 235 miles of railway—the Paris-Mulhouse and Nancy-Gray railways, crossing at Vesoul, and various other lines. There are three arrondissements,—Vesoul, Gray (7254 inhabitants in the town), Lure (4360),—28 cantons, 583 communes. Haute-Saône is in the district of the 7th corps d’armée, and in its legal, ecclesiastical, and educational relations depends on Besançon. Luxeuil (4376 inhabitants), the most important place after the subprefectures, is celebrated for its abbey, founded by St Columban in 590.</p><p>SAÔNE-ET-LOIRE, a department of the east central region of France formed in 1790 from the districts of Autunois, Brionnais, Chalonnais, Charollais, and Mâconnais previously belonging to Burgundy. Lying between 46° 9' and 47° 9' N. lat., 3° 37' and 5° 27' E. long., it is bounded on the N. by the department of Côte d’Or, E. by that of Jura, S.E. by Ain, S. by Rhone and Loire, W. by Allier and Nièvre. The two streams from which it takes its name bound the department on the south-east and on the west respectively. Between these the continental watershed between the Mediterranean and the Atlantic called the Charollais Mountains runs south and north. Its altitude (2500 feet on the south) diminishes to the north in the direction of Côte-d’Or. The culminating point of the department is in the heights of Morvan, on the border of Nièvre (2960 feet). The lowest point, where the Saône leaves the department, is under 550 feet. The Saône crosses the department from north to south, and receives on its right the Dheune, followed by the Canal du Centre and the Grosne, and on its left the Doubs and the Seille. The Loire only receives one important affluent from the right, the Arroux, which is increased by the Bourbince, whose valley is followed by the Canal du Centre. The average temperature is slightly higher at Mâcon than at Paris—the winters being colder and the summer hotter. The yearly rainfall (32 inches, increasing towards the hilly districts) is distributed over 135 days; there are 25 days of snow and 27 of storm.</p><p>Of a total area of 2,116,311 acres (this is one of the largest of the French departments) 1,079,395 are arable, 371,866 forest, 292,287 natural meadows and orchards, and 106,111 vineyards. In 1880 the live-stock comprised 26,000 horses, 6000 asses and mules, 75,000 bulls and oxen, 150,000 cows and heifers, 56,000 calves, 216,000 sheep, 175,000 pigs, 50,000 goats, 35,000 beehives (yielding 214 tons of honey and 52 tons of wax). The white Charollais oxen are one of the finest French breeds, equally suitable for labour and fattening. No fewer than 366,252 of the inhabitants of the department out of a total of 625,559 depend on agriculture. In 1883 there was produced 3,678,276 bushels of wheat, 22,890 meslin, 1,022,037 rye ; in 1880 210,375 bushels of barley, 754,875 buckwheat, 809,325 maize, 101,970 millet, 2,107,187 oats, 13,359,307 potatoes, 38,500 pulse, 70,936 tons of beetroot, 206 tons hemp, 195</p></body></text></TEI>