<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-05-23T18:48:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>mind. Invested with this subtile frame, they, for the sake of fruition, connect
                themselves ever anew with Nature, thus, as it were, creating for themselves ever new
                forms of material existence; and it is only on his attaining perfect knowledge,
                whereby the ever-changing modes of intelligence cease to be reflected on him, that
                the Purusha is liberated from the miseries of Samsara.</p>
            <p>The reputed founder of this school is the sage Kapila, to whom tradition ascribes the
                composition of the fundamental text-book, the <hi rend="italic">(Sânkhya-sûtra,</hi>
                or) <hi rend="italic">Sânkhya-pravachana, @@</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"
                    >1</hi> as well as the <hi rend="italic">Tattva-samAsa,</hi> a mere catalogue of
                the principles. That the Sutras have undergone subsequent modifications might be
                inferred from the fact that they twice refer to the opinion of Pahchaśikha, who
                elsewhere is stated to have received his instruction from Asuri, the disciple of
                Kapila, as well as from the sage himself, of the commentaries on the Sutras, that by
                Vijnâna Bhikshu, @@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> a writer probably of the 16th
                century, is the most approved. An independent treatise by the same author, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Sânkhya-sâra, @@</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">2
                </hi>consisting of a prose and a verse part, is probably the most valuable
                compendium of Sânkhya doctrines. Another admirable and highly-esteemed treatise is
                Iśvara-krishna’s <hi rend="italic">Sârikhya-kârikâ,@@</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript">3 </hi>which gives, in the narrow compass of
                seventy-five ślokas, a lucid and complete sketch of the system. Though nothing
                certain is known regarding its author, @@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> this work
                must be of tolerable antiquity, considering that it was commented upon by Gaudapada,
                    @@<hi rend="superscript">5 </hi>the preceptor of Govinda, who, on his part, is
                said to have been the teacher of Sankaracharya.</p>
            <p> (4) The <hi rend="italic">Yoga</hi> system is merely a schismatic branch of the
                preceding school, holding the same opinions on most points treated in common in
                their Sûtras, with the exception of one important point, the existence of God. To
                the twenty-five principles <hi rend="italic">(tattva) </hi>of the Nirîśvara Sânkhya,
                the last of which was the <hi rend="italic">Purusha,</hi> the Yoga adds, as the
                twenty-sixth, the <hi rend="italic">Nirguna Purusha,</hi> or Self devoid of
                qualities, the Supreme God of the system. Hence the Yoga is called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Seśvara</hi> (theistical) <hi rend="italic">Sânkhya.</hi> But over
                and above the purely speculative part of its doctrine, which it shares with the
                sister school, the theistic Sankhya has developed a complete system of mortification
                of the senses—by means of prolonged apathy and abstraction, protracted rigidity of
                posture, and similar practices, —many of which are already alluded to in the
                Upanishads,—with the view of attaining to an ecstatic vision of, and reunion <hi
                    rend="italic">(yoga)</hi> with, the Supreme Spirit. It is from this portion of
                the system that the school derives the name by which it is more generally known. The
                authoritative Sutras of the Yoga, bearing the same title as those of the sister
                school, viz., <hi rend="italic">Sânkhya-pravachana,</hi> but more commonly called
                    <hi rend="italic">Yoga-śâstra,</hi> are ascribed to Patanjali, who is perhaps
                identical with the author of the “great commentary” on Pânini. The oldest commentary
                on the Sutras, the <hi rend="italic">Pâtahjala-bhâshya,</hi> is attributed to no
                other than Vyâsa, the mythic arranger of the Veda and founder of the Vedânta. Both
                works have again been commented upon by Vâchaspati-miśra, Vijnâna-bhikshu, and other
                writers.</p>
            <p>(5)(6) The <hi rend="italic">Nyâya @@6</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Vaiśeshika</hi> are
                but separate branches of one and the same school, which supplement each other and
                the doctrines of which have virtually become amalgamated into a single system of
                philosophy. The special part taken by each of the two branches in the elaboration of
                the’system may be briefly stated in Dr Röer’s words :—“ To the Nyâya belong the
                logical doctrines of the forms of syllogisms, terms, and propositions; to the
                Vaiśeshikas the systematical explanation of the categories (the simplest
                metaphysical ideas) of the metaphysical, physical, and psychical notions, — which
                notions are hardly touched upon in the Nyaya-sutras. They differ in their statement
                of the several modes of proof,—the Nyaya asserting four modes of proof (from
                perception, inference, analogy, and verbal communication), the Vaiseshikas admitting
                only the two first ones.” The term Nyaya <hi rend="italic">(ni-âya,</hi> “in-going,”
                entering), though properly meaning “analytical investigation,” as applied to
                philosophical inquiry generally, has come to be taken more commonly in the narrower
                sense of “logic,” because this school has entered more thoroughly than any other
                into the laws and processes of thought, and has worked out a formal system of
                reasoning which forms the Hindu standard of logic.</p>
            <p>The followers of these schools generally recognize seven categories <hi rend="italic"
                    >(padârtha)</hi>:—substance <hi rend="italic">(dravya),</hi> quality <hi
                    rend="italic">(guna),</hi> action <hi rend="italic">(karma), </hi>generality <hi
                    rend="italic">(sâmânya),</hi> particularity <hi rend="italic">(viśesha),</hi>
                intimate relation <hi rend="italic">(sarnavâya),</hi> and non-existence or negation
                    <hi rend="italic">(abhâva).</hi> Substances, forming the substrata of qualities
                and actions, are of two kinds:— eternal (without a cause), viz., space, time, ether,
                soul, and the atoms of mind, earth, water, fire, and air; and non-eternal, com</p>
            <p>prising all compounds, or the things we perceive, and which must have a cause of
                their existence. Causality is of three kinds :— that of intimate relation (material
                cause); that of non-intimate relation (between parts of a compound); and
                instrumental causality (effecting the union of component parts). Material things are
                thus composed of atoms <hi rend="italic">(anu), i.e.,</hi> ultimate simple
                substances, or units of space, eternal, unchangeable, and without dimension,
                character- ized only by “ particularity <hi rend="italic">(viśesha). ” </hi>It is
                from this predication of ultimate “ particulars ” that the Vaiseshikas, the
                originators of the atomistic doctrine, derive their name. The Nyâya draws a clear
                line between matter and spirit, and has worked out a careful and ingenious system of
                psychology. It distinguishes between individual or living souls <hi rend="italic"
                    >(jîvâtman),</hi> which are numerous, infinite, and eternal, and the Supreme
                Soul <hi rend="italic">(Paramâtman),</hi> which is one only, the seat of eternal
                knowledge, and the maker and ruler <hi rend="italic">(Îśvara)</hi> of all things. It
                is by his will and agency that the unconscious living souls (soul-atoms, in fact)
                enter into union with the (material) atoms of mind, &amp;c., and thus partake of the
                pleasures and sufferings of mundane existence. On the Hindu syllogism compare Prof.
                Cowell’s notes to Colebrooke’s <hi rend="italic">Essays,</hi> i. p. 314.</p>
            <p>The original collection of <hi rend="italic">Nyâya-sâtras</hi> is ascribed to Gotama,
                and that of the <hi rend="italic">Vaiśeshika-sûtras</hi> to Kanada. The etymological
                meaning of the latter name seems to be “little-eater, particle- eater,” whence in
                works of hostile critics the synonymous terms <hi rend="italic">Kana-bhuj</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">Kana-bhaksha</hi> are sometimes derisively applied to him,
                doubtless in allusion to his theory of atoms. He is also occasionally referred to
                under the name of Kâśyapa. Both sutra-works have been interpreted and supplemented
                by a number of writers, the commentary of Viśvanâtha on the Nyâya and that of
                Śankara-miśra on the Vaiśeshika Sûtras being most generally used. There are,
                moreover, a vast number of separate works on the doctrines of these schools,
                especially on logic. Of favourite elementary treatises on the subject may be
                mentioned Ke^ava- misra’s <hi rend="italic">Tarka-bhâshâ,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tarka-sangraha, @@</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">7</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bhâshâ- parichheda. @@8</hi> A large and important book on logic
                is Ganges’s <hi rend="italic">Chintâmani,</hi> which formed the text-book of the
                celebrated Nuddea school of Bengal, founded by Raghunatha-śiromani about the
                beginning of the 16th century. An interesting little treatise is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Kuswmâhjali, @@</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">9</hi> in which
                the author, Udayana Acharya (about the 12th century, according to Prof. Cowell)
                attempts, in 72 couplets, to prove the existence of a Supreme Being on the
                principles of the Nyâya system.</p>
            <p>As regards the different heretical systems of Hindu philosophy, there is no occasion,
                in a sketch of Sanskrit literature, to enter into the tenets of the two great
                anti-Brahmanical sects, the Jainas and Buddhists. While the original works of the
                former are written entirely in a popular (the Ardha-mâgadhi) dialect, the northern
                Buddhists, it is true, have produced a considerable body of literature, @@<hi
                    rend="superscript">10</hi> composed in a kind of hybrid Sanskrit, but only a few
                of their sacred books have as yet been published; @@<hi rend="superscript">11</hi>
                and it is, moreover, admitted on all hands that for the pure and authentic Bauddha
                doctrines we have rather to look to the Pali scriptures of the southern branch. Nor
                can we do more here than briefly allude to the theories of a few of the less
                prominent heterodox systems, however interesting they may be for a history of human
                thought.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Chârvâkas,</hi> an ancient sect of undisguised materialism, who
                deny the existence of the soul, and consider the human person <hi rend="italic"
                    >(purusha)</hi> to be an organic body endowed with sensibility and with thought,
                resulting from a modification of the component material elements, ascribe their
                origin to Brihaspati; but their authoritative text-book, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bârhaspatya-sûtra,</hi> is only known so far from a few- quotations.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Pâncharâtras,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Bhâgavatas,</hi> are an
                early Vaishnava sect, in which the doctrine of faith, already alluded to, is
                strongly developed. Hence their tenets are defended by Ramanuja, though they are
                partly condemned as heretical in the Brahma-sutras. Their recognized text-book is
                the <hi rend="italic">Nârada-Pahcharâtra. @@</hi>12 According to their theory the
                Supreme Being (Bhagavat, Vâsudeva, Vishnu) became four separate persons by
                successive production. While the Supreme Being himself is indued with the six
                qualities of knowledge, power, strength, absolute sway, vigour, and energy, the
                three divine persons successively emanating from him and from one another represent
                the living soul, mind, and consciousness respectively.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Pâśupatas,</hi> one of several Saiva (Mâheśvara) sects, hold
                the Supreme Being <hi rend="italic">(Îśvara),</hi> whom they identify with Śiva, to
                be the creator and ruler of the world, but not its material cause. With the Sânkhyas
                they admit the notion of a plastic material cause, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pradhâna</hi>; while they follow Patanjali in maintaining the existence of a
                Supreme God.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Transl. by J. R. Ballantyne ; 2d ed. by F. Hall.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> Edited by F. Hall.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> Edited by F. Hall.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> Edited by C. Lassen, 1832. Translations by II. T.
                Colebrooke and J<hi rend="subscript">z</hi> Davies.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> One writer makes him the pupil of Panchaśkha, whilst
                another even identifies him with Kalidasa ; <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi> F. Hall, <hi
                    rend="italic">Sankhyasdra,</hi> p. 29.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@5</hi> Transl. by II. H. wilson. A Chinese translation of a
                commentary resembling that of Gaudapada is said to have been made during the Ch’en
                dynasty, 557-583 <hi rend="smallcaps">A.d.</hi> (M. Muller, <hi rend="italic"
                    >India,</hi> p. 360).</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@6</hi> Besides Colebrooke’s <hi rend="italic">Essay,</hi>
                with Cowell’s notes, see Ballantyne's translation of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tarka-Sangraha</hi> anil the introduction to Roer’s translation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bhâshaparichheda,</hi> and his article, <hi rend="italic">Z. D. M.
                    O.,</hi> xxi.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@7</hi> Edited and translated by J. R. Ballantyne.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@8</hi> Edited and translated, with commentary, by E.
                Röer.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@9</hi> Edited and translated, with commentary, by E. B.
                Cowell.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@10 </hi>See B. H. Hodgson, <hi rend="italic">The Languages,
                    Literature, and Religion of Nepal and Tibet.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@</hi><hi rend="superscript">11</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    > Lalita-vistara,</hi> edited and partly translated by Râjendralâla Mitra; <hi
                    rend="italic">Mahâ- vastu,</hi> edited E. Senart; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vajra-parichheda,</hi> edited M. Müller; <hi rend="italic">Saddharma-
                    pundarîka,</hi> translated by E. Burnouf (“Lotus de la bonne loi”); and II.
                Kern, <hi rend="italic">Sacred Books of the East.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="superscript">12</hi> Edited by K. M. Banerjea.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
