<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-23T18:46:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>his great “ machines,” as French art slang calls them. Much more noteworthy as well as more frequent are the sudden touches which he gives. The bishops are “cuistres violets”; M. de Caumartin “ porte sous son manteau toute la fatuité que M. de Villeroy étale sur son baudrier"; another politician has a “mine de chat fâché ”; a third is hit off as “comptant faire” (“he would still be doing,” though Saint-Simon certainly did not know that phrase). In short, the interest of the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs,</hi> independent of the large addition of positive knowledge which they make, is one of constant surprise at the novel and adroit use of word and phrase. It is not superfluous to inform the English reader that some of Macaulay’s most brilliant portraits and sketches of incident are adapted and sometimes almost literally translated from Saint-Simon.</p><p>The 1st edition of Saint-Simon (some scattered pieces may have been printed before) appeared in 1788. It was a mere selection in three volumes and was much cut down before it was allowed to appear. Next year four more volumes made their appearance, and in 1791 a new edition, still further increased. The whole, or rather not the whole, was printed in 1829-30 and reprinted some ten years later. The real creator of Saint-Simon, as far as a full and exact text is concerned, was M. Chéruel, whose edition in 20 volumes dates from 1856 and was reissued again revised in 1872. So immense, however, is the mass of Saint- Simon’s MSS. that still another recension has been found necessary, and is now being published by M. de Boislisle in the series of <hi rend="italic">Grands Écrivains,</hi> but with M. Chéruel's sanction and assistance. Even this, as above noted, will not exhaust available Saint-Simoniana, and it may be doubted whether it will be possible for many years to place a complete edition on the shelves. It must, however, be admitted that the matter other than the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> is of altogether inferior interest and may be pretty safely neglected by any one but professed antiquarian and historical students. For criticism on Saint-Simon there is nothing better than Sainte-Benve’s two sketches in the 3d and 15th volumes of the <hi rend="italic">Causeries du Lundi.</hi> The latter was written to accompany M. Chéruel's 1st edition. In English by far the most accurate treatment is in a recent Lothian prize essay by E. Cannan (Oxford and London, 1885).	(G. SA.)</p><p>ST THOMAS, one of the Danish West India Islands, lies 36 miles east of Porto Rico (Spanish) and 40 north- north-west of St Croix (Danish), with its principal town (Charlotte Amalie) in 18° 20' 27" N. lat. and 64° 55' 40" W. long. It is 13 miles long from east to west, with an average breadth of 3, and is estimated to have an area of 33 square miles. The highest point, West Mountain, is 1586 feet above the sea. Previous to the abolition of slavery in 1848 the island was covered with sugar plantations and dotted with substantial mansions; but now a few vegetables, a little fruit, and some guinea grass are all that it produces. Greengroceries are imported from the United States, poultry and eggs from the neighbouring islands. Nor is the exceptional position which St Thomas has hitherto enjoyed as a commercial depot any longer secure; the value of the imports in 1880 was less than one-half of what it was in 1870, and the merchants of Venezuela, Porto Rico, San Domingo, Hayti, &amp;c., who used to purchase in St Thomas, now go direct to the markets of the United States and Europe. The Royal Mail Company, which at an early date chose the island as the principal rendezvous for its steam-packets in that part of the world, and whose example was followed by other important lines, removed its headquarters to Barbados in 1885. The harbour lies about the middle of the south coast and is nearly landlocked ; its depth varies from 36 to 18 feet. A floating dock, 250 feet in length, was completed in 1875 ; there is in addition a steam-slip capable of taking up a vessel of 1200 tons. Along the north side of the harbour lies Charlotte Amalie, popularly known as St Thomas, the only town on the island. In 1880 the inhabitants of the island numbered 14,389 (males 5757, females 8632), of whom about a sixth are white, of various nationalities; the rest have nearly all more or less of Negro blood. English has gradually become almost the exclusive language of the educated classes, and is used in the schools and churches of all the various communities. The curious Creole speech of the Negroes, which contained a mixture of broken Dutch, Danish, English, &amp;e., though it was reduced to writing by the Moravian missionaries subsequent to 1770, is rapidly dying out.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> About a third of the population are Roman Catholics, and the rest mainly Protestants of the Lutheran, Dutch Reformed, Moravian, and English Episcopal Churches. The Jewish community, 500 or 600 strong, has a synagogue. There are in the town two</p><p>hospitals, a public reading-room and library, a Government college (1877), a Roman Catholic college (St Thomas), a Moravian school, and a small theatre. A quarantine lazaretto is maintained on Lighthouse or Muhlenfeldt Point. The general health of the town is good. The climate varies little all the year round, the thermometer seldom falling below 70° or rising above 90°. In the “ hurricane ” months—August, September, and October—south winds, accompanied by sultry heat, rain, and thunder, are not uncommon ; throughout the rest of the year the wind blows between east and north. Earthquakes are not unfrequent, but they do little damage in comparison with cyclones, which sometimes sweep over the island.</p><p>St Thomas was discovered by Columbus in 1493, and at that time was inhabited by two tribes, the Caribs and the Arrowauks. In 1657 it was colonized by the Dutch, and after their departure for New York it was held by the English in 1667. The Danish West India and Guinea Company took possession in 1671, and some eight years later began the introduction of slave labour. It was succeeded in 1685 by the so-called Brandenburgh Company, the principal shareholders of which were Dutch. The colony was strengthened by French refugees from St Christopher’s after the revocation of the edict of Nantes. The neutrality of Denmark led to the prizes of the various belligerents being brought to its port for sale. In 1754 the king of Denmark took the management of the colony into his own hands, and in 1764 he threw open the port to vessels of all nations. The neutrality of Denmark again favoured it in the war of 1792; and it became the only market in the West Indies from which the products of the colonies could be conveyed to the north of Europe. In 1801 the island was held by the British for ten months, and it was again in their possession from the latter part of 1807 to 1815. At that time the harbour was three or four times a year the rendezvous for homeward-bound English ships, from 200 to 400, as the case might be, which waited there for their convoys. The South American War of Independence led a number of Spaniards to settle at St Thomas. A great but temporary stimulus was given to its commerce during the American Civil War. In 1871 the Danish Government removed the headquarters of their West India possessions from St Croix to St Thomas.</p><p>ST THOMAS (Portuguese, <hi rend="italic">São Thomé),</hi> a volcanic island in the Gulf of Guinea (West Africa), lies immediately north of the equator and in 6° 40' E. long. From the Gaboon, the nearest point of the mainland, the distance is 166 miles, and from the Cameroons 297. The extreme length of the island is 32 miles and the breadth from west to east 21; the area is estimated at 355 square miles. From the coast it rises pretty uniformly towards the lofty and verdant mountains, in the midst of which the peak of St Thomas towers to a height of 6000 feet. At least a hundred streams great and small rush down the mountainsides through deep-cut ravines, many of them forming beautiful waterfalls, such as those of Blu-blu, &amp;c., on the Agua Grande. The bi-seasonal climate of the tropics obtains a comparatively normal development on the island, which, however, has a very evil repute of unhealthiness, probably owing to the fact that the chief town occupies a peculiarly malarial site on the coast. The first object of European cultivation in St Thomas was sugar, and to this the colony owed its prosperity in the 16th century; but now it is quite displaced by coffee and cocoa, introduced in the beginning of the 19th century. In 1879-80 the export of coffee was 3,778,580 ft) and of cocoa 1,026,746 ft). Vanilla and cinchona bark both succeed well, the latter between 1800 and 3300 feet of altitude. Though nearly the whole surface of the island is fitted for cultivation, only about a fifth part is really turned to account. Along with Principe, St Thomas forms a Portuguese province, to which are attached the little island of Rolas and the petty fort of Ajuda on the Guinea coast.</p><p>The town of St Thomas, the capital of the province, is situated on the north-east coast of the island, and the neighbouring districts form the only well-peopled region. In 1878 the population in the island was 18,266, of whom 1200 were white. The great bulk consisted of a mixture of Negroes from various parts of the West Coast, mainly introduced as slaves, and now all using a Negro Portuguese—“lingua de S. Thomé.” On the south-west coast are</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> See specimens and analysis by Dr E. Pontoppidan, in <hi rend="italic">Ztschr. f. Ethnol.,</hi> Berlin, 1881.</p></body></text></TEI>