<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-10T23:19:39Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>esque church and cloister (12th century), and was the birthplace of the architect Juan de Herrera.</p><p>SANTANDER <hi rend="italic">(Partus Blendium, Fanum S. Andreæ), </hi>capital of the above province, 316 miles by rail from Madrid, is the seat of a bishopric and one of the chief seaports of Spain. The population in 1877 numbered 41,000, having almost doubled in the preceding quarter of a century, and the trade of the port has increased in an even greater proportion. The town is situated on the inside of a rocky peninsula, which separates it from the Bay of Biscay and forms a magnificent harbour from 2 to 3 miles wide and 4 miles long. The entrance is at the eastern extremity of the promontory, and, though somewhat difficult for sailing vessels in certain winds, has depth of water sufficient for the largest ships. The total burthen of the vessels entered in 1882 amounted to 104,449 tons British and 500,342 tons of other nations. The chief exports consisted of iron ore (20,966 tons) to Great Britain, and wine (191,400 galls.) and olive oil (8000 galls.) to France. The city is divided into an upper and a lower town, and contains few buildings of interest. The cathedral was originally a Gothic structure, but has been so altered by later additions that little of the old work remains. In the crypt, or Capilla del Cristo de Abajo, there is a font of Moorish workmanship which has some interest. The castle of S. Felice contains a prison which was probably the first example of the radiating system of construction. Besides these buildings there are the theatre, which was formerly a convent, the hospital, and the Jesuits’ church. The city is essentially modern, and its chief features are its well-built houses, its quays, and its factories. In addition to the manufactures of the province mentioned above, Santander has gas-works, phosphorus, sulphuric acid, and sail manufactories, and a large cigar factory, formerly a convent, where over 1000 hands are employed. Besides being a trading port Santander is also a watering-place which enjoys peculiar advantages of climate. The bathing establishment of the Sardinero, on the seaward side of the strip of land the town is built on, offers all the attractions usual to Continental watering-places. There is communication by rail with Madrid and by steamer with Liverpool, London, and Hamburg, as well as with Havana and the seaports of Spain.</p><p>The port was in 1753 made one of the “puertos habilitados” or ports privileged to trade with America, and in 1755 it was created a “ciudad.” Charles V. landed here in 1522 when he came to take possession of the Spanish crown, and from this port Charles I. of England embarked on his return from his ill-fated visit <hi rend="italic">incognito</hi> in search of a wife. The city was sacked by the French under Soult in 1808 ; but so little gratitude did the people show to their English allies that it was with the greatest difficulty supplies were found for the troops.</p><p>SANTAREM, a city and bishop’s see of Portugal, in the province of Estremadura, on the declivities of the right bank of the Tagus, 46<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">2</hi> miles by rail from Lisbon. It lias the ruins of an old castle, well known in Portuguese history as a royal residence, especially in the Middle Ages, and several of its churches are of historic and architectural interest. A considerable trade is carried on, and the population was 7001 in 1878.</p><p>Santarem, so named after a certain St Irene, is identified with the ancient Scallabis Præsidium Julium. The death of Diniz I., and the birth, abdication, anti death of Don Henrique the cardinal king, all occurred in the city ; it gave its name to João de Santarem, one of the 15th-century navigators ; and Fernando I. and Cabral, discoverer of Brazil, were buried within its walls. The Miguelists were completely routed here by Napier and Villaflor in 1834.</p><p>SANTAREM, a city of Brazil, at the head of a comarca in the province of Para, is situated on the right bank near the mouth of the Rio Tapajós, a right-hand tributary of the Amazon. It is a clean and neat-looking place, with rows of whitewashed houses in the European town, clusters of palm-thatched huts in the Indian suburb, a large church, the ruins of a stone fort, and, standing apart,</p><p>the municipal buildings with the court-house. As the Rio Tapajós is navigable for steamers to the rapids, 170 miles above Santarem, and for boats to within a short distance of Diamantino, the town carries on a considerable trade with Matto Grosso and the country along the banks. The population and importance of the place, originally founded by a Jesuit missionary for his converts in 1661, and made a city in 1848, are steadily increasing.</p><p>SANTERRE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean Baptiste</hi> (1650-1717), French painter, born at Magny near Pontoise in 1650, was a pupil of Bon Boulogne. He began life as a portrait- painter, but refused to paint any except those who pleased his taste; he was incapable of managing the large compositions then in vogue, but enjoyed for half a century a great reputation as a painter of the nude. He had opened his studio to a class of young girls, to whom he gave lessons, and who served him as models. Much, however, of Santerre’s work of this class was destroyed by himself in a fit of lively repentance after a serious illness which attacked him late in life. He died at Paris on November 21, 1717. His paintings, in consequence of his extreme care in choice of vehicles and pigments, have stood well. His Portrait of a Lady in Venetian Costume (Louvre), and his Susanna at the Bath (Louvre, engraved by Porporati), the diploma work executed by him in 1704, when he was received into the Academy, give a good impression of Santerre’s taste and of his elaborate and careful method. SAN THIAGO. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Cape Verd Islands,</hi> vol. v. p. 60. SANTIAGO, the capital of Chili, and the chief town of a province of its own name (now 5223 square miles in extent, reduced in 1883 by the formation of the new province of O’Higgins), is situated in 33° 26' 42" S. lat. and 70° 40' 36" W. long., at a height of about 1830 feet above the sea, in a wide and beautiful plain between the main range of the Andes and the less elevated heights of Cuesta del Prado, 115 miles east of Valparaiso by rail. In the centre of the city rises the rocky hill of Santa Lucia, with</p><p>its two fortresses,—recently converted into a pleasure- ground, with theatres, restaurants, and monuments; and immediately to the north-north-west and north-east are those known as Colina, Renca, and San Cristóbal. The snow-clad range of the Andes, in which the summits of La Chapa and Los Amarillos are conspicuous, is visible from Santiago. A turbid mountain stream, the Mapocho, flows west through the heart of the city to join the Colina and ultimately the Maipú or Maipo; its floods were sometimes, as in 1609 and 1783, the cause of great damage till the construction of a solid embankment was undertaken</p></body></text></TEI>