<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-05-23T18:48:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>lar lyrics that was accessible to the collectors, or seemed to them worthy of being
                preserved. The question as to the exact period when the hymns were collected cannot
                be answered with any approach to accuracy. For many reasons, however, which cannot
                be detailed here, scholars have come to fix on the year 1000 B.C. as an approximate
                date for the collection of the Vedic hymns. From that time every means that human
                ingenuity could suggest was adopted to secure the sacred texts against the risks
                connected with oral transmission. But, as there is abundant evidence to show that
                even then not only had the text of the hymns suffered corruption, but their language
                had become antiquated to a considerable extent, and was only partly understood, the
                period during which the great mass of the hymns were composed must have lain
                considerably further back, and may very likely have extended over the earlier half
                of the second millenary, or from about 2000 to 1500 B.C.</p>
            <p>As regards the people which raised for itself this imposing monu- ment, the hymns
                exhibit it as settled in the regions watered by the mighty Sindhu (Indus), with its
                eastern and western tributaries. The land of the five rivers forms the central home
                of the Vedic people ; but, while its advanced guard has already debouched upon the
                plains of the upper Gangâ and Yamuna, those who bring up the rear are still found
                loitering far behind in the narrow glens of the Kubhâ (Cabul) and Gomati (Gomal).
                Scattered over this tract of land, in hamlets and villages, the Vedic Aryas are
                leading chiefly the life of herdsmen and husbandmen. The numerous clans and tribes,
                ruled over by chiefs and kings, have still constantly to vindicate their right to
                the land but lately wrung from an inferior race of darker hue ; just as in these
                latter days their kinsmen in the Far West are ever on their guard against the fierce
                attacks of the dispossessed red-skin. Not unfrequently, too, the light-coloured
                Aryas rage internecine war with one another,—as when the Bliaratas, with allied
                tribes of the Panjab, goaded on by the royal sage Visvamitra, invade the country of
                the Tritsu king Sudas, to be defeated in the “ten kings’ battle,” through the
                inspired power of the priestly singer Vasishtha. The priestly office has already
                become one of high social importance by the side of the political rulers, and to a
                large extent an hereditary profession; but it does not yet present the baneful
                features of an exclusive caste. The Aryan housewife shares with her husband the
                daily toil and joy, the privilege of worshipping the national gods, and even the
                triumphs of song-craft, some of the finest hymns being attributed to female
                seers.</p>
            <p>The religious belief of the people consists in a system of natural symbolism, a
                worship of the elementary forces of nature, regarded as beings endowed with reason
                and power superior to those of man. In giving utterance to this simple belief, the
                priestly spokesman has, however, frequently worked into it his own speculative and
                mystic notions. Indra, the stout-hearted ruler of the cloud-region, receives by far
                the largest share of the devout attentions of the Vedic singer. His ever-renewed
                battle with the malicious demons of darkness and drought, for the recovery of the
                heavenly light and the rain-spending cows of the sky, forms an inexhaustible theme
                of spirited song. Next to him, in the affections of the people, stands Agni (ignis),
                the god of fire, invoked as the genial inmate of the Aryan household, and as the
                bearer of oblations, and mediator between gods and men. Indra and Agni are thus, as
                it were, the divine representatives of the king (or chief) and the priest of the
                Aryan community ; and if, in the arrangement of the Sarnhitâ, the Brahmanical
                collectors gave precedence to Agni, it was but one of many avowals of their own
                hierarchical pretensions. Hence also the hymns to Indra are mostly followed, in the
                family collections, by those addressed to the Viśve Devâh (the “all-gods”) or to the
                JIaruts (Mavors, Mars), the warlike storm-gods and faithful companions of Indra, as
                the divine impersonation of the Aryan free- men, the <hi rend="italic">viś</hi> or
                clan. But, while Indra and Agni are undoubtedly the favourite figures of the Vedic
                pantheon, there is reason to believe that these gods had but lately supplanted
                another group of deities who play a less prominent part in the hymns, viz., Father
                Heaven (Dyaus Pitar, Zϵύς πατήρ<hi rend="italic">,</hi> Jupiter); Varuna (ουρανος),
                the all- embracing firmament; Mitra (Zend. Mithra), the genial light of day; and
                Savitar (Saturnus) or Sfirya <hi rend="italic">(ήϵλιος),</hi> the vivifying sun.</p>
            <p>Of the Brahmanas that were handed down in the schools of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bahvrichas (i.e.,</hi> “possessed of many verses”), as the followers of the
                Rigveda are called, two have come down to us, viz., those of the Aitareyins and the
                Kaushitakins. The <hi rend="italic">Aitarcya-brdhmana @@</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript">1 </hi>and the <hi rend="italic">Kaushîtaki-</hi> (or
                    <hi rend="italic">Sânkhâyana-) brâhmana</hi> evidently have for their groundwork
                the same stock of traditional exegetic matter. They differ, however, considerably as
                regards both the arrange- ment of this matter and their stylistic handling of it,
                with the exception of the numerous legends common to both, in which the discrepancy
                is comparatively slight. There is also a certain amount of material peculiar to each
                of them. The Kaushîtaka is, upon the whole, far more concise in its style and more
                systematic in its arrangement—merits which would lead one to infer that it</p>
            <p>is probably the more modern work of the two. It consists of thirty chapters <hi
                    rend="italic">(adhyâya)</hi>; while the Aitareya has forty, divided into eight
                books (or pentads, <hi rend="italic">panchakd,</hi> of five chapters each). The last
                ten adhyayas of the latter work are, however, clearly a later addition,—though they
                must have already formed part of it at the time of Pânini (c. 400 B.C. ?), if, as
                seems probable, one of his grammatical sfitras, regulating the formation of the
                names of Brahmanas, consisting of thirty and forty adhyayas, refers to these two
                works. In this last portion occurs the well-known legend (also found in the
                Śânkhâyana-sûtra, but not in the Kaushitaki- brahmana) of Śunahśepa, whom his father
                Ajigarta sells and offers to slay, the recital of which formed part of the
                inauguration of kings. While the Aitareya deals almost exclusively with the Soma
                sacrifice, the Kaushitaka, in its first six chapters, treats of the several kinds of
                    <hi rend="italic">haviryajna,</hi> or offerings of rice, milk, ghee, &amp;c.,
                whereupon follows the Soma sacrifice in this way, that chapters 7-10 contain the
                practical ceremonial and 11-30 the recitations <hi rend="italic">(śastra)</hi> of
                the hotar. Sayana, in the introduction to his commentary on the work, ascribes the
                Aitareya to the sage Mahidâsa Aitareya (son of Itara), also mentioned elsewhere as a
                philosopher ; and it seems likely enough that this person arranged the Brahmana and
                founded the school of the Aitareyins. Regarding the authorship of the sister work we
                have no information, except that the opinion of the sage Kaushîtaki is frequently
                referred to in it as authoritative, and generally in opposition to the Paingya—the
                Brahmana, it would seem, of a rival school, the Paingins.</p>
            <p>Each of these two Brahmanas is supplemented by a “ forest- portion,” or Aranyaka. The
                    <hi rend="italic">Aitareyâranyaka. @@2</hi> is not a uniform production. It
                consists of five books <hi rend="italic">(âranyaka),</hi> three of which, the first
                and the last two, are of a liturgical nature, treating of the ceremony called <hi
                    rend="italic">mahâvrata</hi> or great vow. The second and third books, on the
                other hand, are purely speculative, and are also styled the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bahvricha-brâhmana-upanishad.</hi> Again, the last four chapters of the second
                book are usually singled out as <hi rend="italic">the Aitareyopanishad, @@</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript">3 </hi>ascribed, like its Brahmana (and the first
                book), to Mahidasa Aitareya ; and the third book is also referred to as the <hi
                    rend="italic">Samhitâ- upanishad.</hi> The fourth and fifth books are doubtless
                of later origin, being composed in sutra-form. Even native authorities exclude them
                from the sacred canon, and ascribe them to Asva layana and Saunaka respectively, of
                whom more further on. As regards the <hi rend="italic">Kaushîtaki-dranyaka,</hi> our
                MS. material is not yet sufficient to enable us to determine its exact extent and
                arrangement. It would, however, seem that there are two different recensions of this
                treatise, a shorter one, consisting of nine, and a longer one of fifteen,
                adhy&amp;yas. Four of these, variously placed at the beginning or end, or after the
                second adhyaya, constitute the highly interesting <hi rend="italic">Kaushîtaki-
                    (brâhmana·) upawishad, @@4</hi> of which we possess two different recensions.
                The remaining portions of the Aranyaka seem to correspond, to some extent, to the
                ceremonial sections of the Aitareya-âranyaka.</p>
            <p>Of <hi rend="italic">Kalpa-sûtras,</hi> or manuals of sacrificial ceremonial,
                composed for the use of the liotar prjest, two different sets are in existence, the
                    <hi rend="italic">Âśvaldiyana-</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sânkhâyana-sûtra.</hi> Each of these works follows one of the two Brahmanas of
                the Rik as its chief authority, viz., the Aitareya and Kaushitaka respectively. Both
                consist of a <hi rend="italic">Śrauta</hi>- and a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Grihya-sûtra.</hi> Âśvalâyana seems to have lived about the same time as
                Panini,—his own teacher, Saunaka, who com- pleted the Rik-prâtiśâkhya, being
                probably intermediate between the great grammarian and Yaska, the author of the
                Nirukta. Saunaka himself is said to have been the author of a Srauta-sfitra (which
                was, however, more of the nature of a Brahmana) and to have destroyed it on seeing
                his pupil’s work. A Grihya-sfitra is still quoted under his name by later writers.
                The Asvalayana Srauta-sûtra @@ <hi rend="superscript">5</hi> consists of twelve, the
                Grihya @@<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> of four, adhyayas.</p>
            <p>Regarding Śankhayana still less is known ; but he, too, was doubtless a comparatively
                modern writer, who, like Asvalâyana, founded a new school of ritualists. Hence the
                Kausliitaki-brahmana, adopted (and perhaps improved) by him, alsogoes under his
                name, just as the Aitareya is sometimes called Asvalayana-bralimana. The Śankhayana
                Śrauta-sûtra consists of eighteen adhyayas. The last two chapters of the work are,
                however, a later addition, @@<hi rend="superscript">7 </hi>while the two preceding
                chapters, on the contrary, present a com- paratively archaic, brahmana-like
                appearance. The Grihya-sûtra<hi rend="superscript">7 </hi>consists of six chapters,
                the last two of which are likewise later appendages. The <hi rend="italic">Sâmbavya
                    Grihya-sûtra,</hi> of which a single MS.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Edited, with an English translation, by M. Haug, 2
                vols., Bombay, 18G3. An edition in Roman transliteration, with extracts from the
                commentary, has been published by Th. Aufrecht, Bonn, 1879.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@2</hi> Edited, with Säyana’s commentary, by Räjcndralftla
                Mitra, in the <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Indica,</hi> 1875-76. The first three
                books have been translated by F. Max Miiller in <hi rend="italic">Sacred Books of
                    the East,</hi> vol. i.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> Edited and translated by Dr Röer, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibl. Ind.</hi> The last chapter of the second book, not being
                commented upon by Sâyana, is probably a later addition.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> Text, commentary', and translation published by E.
                B. Cowell, in the <hi rend="italic">Bibl</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Ind. </hi>Also a
                translation bv F. Max Müller in <hi rend="italic">Sacred Books of the East,</hi>
                vol. i.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@5</hi> Both works have been published with the commentary
                of Gftrgya Nârâyana, by native scholars, in the <hi rend="italic">Bibl. Ind.</hi>
                Also the text of the Grihya, with a German translation by A. Stenzler.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@5</hi> Both works have been published with the commentary
                of Gftrgya Nârâyana, by native scholars, in the <hi rend="italic">Bibl. Ind.</hi>
                Also the text of the Grihya, with a German translation by A. Stenzler.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@6</hi> See A. Weber’s analysis, <hi rend="italic">Ind.
                    Studien,</hi> ii. p. 288 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> This work, with its
                commentaries, is only accessible in manuscript.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@7</hi> Edited, with a German translation, by H. Oldenberg
                    <hi rend="italic">(Ind. Stud.,</hi> vol. xv.), who also gives an account of the
                S&amp;mbavya Grihya.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
