<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-05-23T18:47:06Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Saltmaking is by no means an unhealthy trade, some slight soreness of the eyes being
                the only affection sometimes complained of ; indeed, the atmosphere of steam
                saturated with salt in which the workmen live seems specially preservative against
                colds, rheumatism, neuralgia, &amp;c. It is said that wages are rather better and
                employment more regular in Worcestershire than in Cheshire.</p>
            <p>The parliamentary commission above referred to was appointed with a view to the
                investigation of the causes of the disastrous subsidences which are constantly
                taking place in all the salt districts, and the provision of a remedy, ft led to no
                legislative action ; but the evil is recognized as a grave one. At Northwich and
                Winsford scarcely a house or a chimney stack remains straight. Houses are keyed up
                with “shaps,” “ face plates,” and “bolts,” and only kept from falling by leaning on
                one another. The doors and windows have become lozenge-shaped, the walls bulged, and
                the floors crooked. Buildings have sunk,—some of them disappearing altogether. Lakes
                have been formed where there was solid ground before, and incalculable damage done
                to property in all quarters. At the same time it is difficult to see how this
                grievance can be remedied without inflicting serious injury, almost ruin, upon the
                salt trade. The workings in Great Britain represent the abstraction of rather more
                than a cubic mile of rock every five years, and of this by far the larger part is in
                Cheshire.</p>
            <p>Manley gives the following statistics of the production of salt in England for 1881
                :—</p>
            <table cols="4">
                <row>
                    <cell rows="4">Cheshire</cell>
                    <cell>Northwich </cell>
                    <cell>500,000</cell>
                    <cell>tons</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Winsford </cell>
                    <cell>1,000,000</cell>
                    <cell>,,</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Middlewich </cell>
                    <cell>30,000</cell>
                    <cell>,,</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Wheelock and Lawton</cell>
                    <cell>100,000</cell>
                    <cell>,,</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Staffordshire</cell>
                    <cell>Shirleywick and Weston on-Trent</cell>
                    <cell>4,000</cell>
                    <cell>,,</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell rows="2">Worcestershire</cell>
                    <cell>Droitwich</cell>
                    <cell>115,000</cell>
                    <cell>,,</cell>
                </row>
                <row><cell>Stoke Prior</cell>
                    <cell>105,000</cell>
                    <cell>,,</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell/><cell>Total </cell>
                    <cell>1,854,000</cell>
                    <cell>,,</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>He also gives the following details of the salt exported for years ending Dec. 31,
                1881 to 1883 inclusive, quoted from the archives of the Salt Chamber of Commerce,
                whence the importance of the salt trade in England may be judged :—</p>
            <table cols="5">
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2"/>
                    <cell>1881.</cell>
                    <cell>1882.</cell>
                    <cell>1883.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">From Liverpool:— </cell>
                    <cell>Tons.</cell>
                    <cell><p>Tons.</p></cell>
                    <cell><p>Tons.</p>
                        </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell rows="11"/>
                    <cell>To United States</cell><cell>228,891</cell><cell>223,602</cell>
                    <cell>239,459</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>,, British North America</cell><cell>80,784</cell>
                    <cell>81,716</cell>
                    <cell>99,352</cell></row>
                    <row><cell>„ West Indies and South
                            America</cell>
                    <cell>15,556</cell>
                    <cell>23,953</cell>
                    <cell>
                        <p>  25,413</p>
                    </cell></row>
                
                <row><cell>,, Africa</cell><cell>25,181</cell>
                    <cell>34,287</cell>
                    <cell>36,896</cell></row>
                <row><cell>„ East Indies</cell><cell>324,109</cell>
                    <cell>274,866</cell>
                    <cell>316,327</cell></row>
                <row><cell>,, Australia</cell><cell>23,872</cell>
                    <cell>17,232</cell>
                    <cell>10,860</cell></row>

                <row>
                    <cell>,, Baltic and North Europe</cell><cell>100,957</cell>
                    <cell>116,509</cell>
                    <cell>107,978</cell></row> 
                <row><cell>,, France and Mediterranean </cell><cell>1,187</cell>
                    <cell>5,001</cell>
                    <cell>2,803</cell></row>
                <row><cell>,,
                    Holland and Belgium</cell> <cell>67,780</cell>
                    <cell>67,334</cell>
                    <cell>72,353</cell></row>
                <row><cell>Coastwise</cell><cell>41,653</cell>
                    <cell>32,462</cell>
                    <cell>46,753</cell> </row>
                <row><cell>Total from Liverpool</cell><cell>909,970</cell><cell>876,962</cell><cell>958,194</cell>
                            </row>
                <row><cell cols="2">From Runcorn</cell> <cell>148,122</cell><cell>146,716</cell><cell>141,021</cell></row>
                <row>
                    <cell cols="2">„ Western Dock </cell><cell>85,545</cell><cell>68,147</cell><cell>87,954</cell></row>
                        <row><cell/><cell>Grand total</cell> 
 
                    <cell>1,143,637</cell>
                    <cell>1,091,825</cell> <cell>1,187,169</cell>
                </row>
          </table>
               
                    <p>(F. M. L.)</p>
                
  
            <p><hi rend="italic">Ancient History and Religious Symbolism.—</hi>Indispensable as the
                use of salt appears to us, it must have been quite unattainable to primitive man in
                many parts of the world. Thus the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey </hi>(xi. 122 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.)</hi> speaks of inlanders (in Epirus ?) who do not know the
                sea and use no salt with their food. In some parts of America, and even of India
                (among the Todas), salt was first introduced by Europeans ; and there are still
                parts of central Africa where the use of it is a luxury confined to the rich.
                Indeed, where men live mainly on milk and flesh, consuming the latter raw or
                roasted, so that its salts are not lost, it is not necessary to add sodium chloride,
                and thus we understand how the Numidian nomads in the time of Sallust and the
                Bedouins of Hadramant at the present day never eat salt with their food. On the
                other hand, cereal or vegetable diet calls for a supplement of salt, and so does
                boiled meat. The important part played by the mineral in the history of commerce and
                religion depends on this fact; at a very early stage of progress salt became a
                necessary of life to most nations, and in many cases they could procure it only from
                abroad, from the sea-coast, or from districts like that of Palmyra where salty
                incrustations are found on the surface of the soil. Sometimes indeed a kind of salt
                was got from the ashes of saline plants <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi> by the
                Umbrians, Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">Met.,</hi> ii. p. 459), or by pouring the
                water of a brackish stream over a fire of (saline) wood and collecting the ashes, as
                was done in ancient Germany (Tac., <hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi> xiii. 57), in Gaul,
                and in Spain (Plin., <hi rend="italic">H. N.,</hi> xxxi. 7, 82 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.);</hi> but these were imperfect surrogates. Among inland peoples a salt
                spring was regarded as a special gift of the gods. The Chaonians in Epirus had one
                which flowed into a stream where there were no fish; and the legend was that
                Heracles had allowed their forefathers to have salt instead of fish (Arist., <hi
                    rend="italic">ut supra).</hi> The Germans waged war for saline streams,</p>
            <p>and believed that the presence of salt in the soil invested a district with peculiar
                sanctity and made it a place where prayers were most readily heard (Tac., <hi
                    rend="italic">ut sup.).</hi> That a religious significance was attached to a
                substance so highly prized and which was often obtained with difficulty is no more
                than natural. And it must also be remembered that the habitual use of salt is
                intimately connected with the advance from nomadic to agricultural life, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e</hi>., with precisely that step in civilization which had most
                influence on the cults of almost all ancient nations. The gods were worshipped as
                the givers of the kindly fruits of the earth, and, as all over the world “bread and
                salt” go together in common use and common phrase, salt was habitually associated
                with offerings, at least with all offerings which consisted in whole or in part of
                cereal elements. This practice is found alike among the Greeks and Romans and among
                the Semitic peoples (Lev. ii. 13); Homer calls salt “ divine,” and Plato names it “a
                substance dear to the gods” <hi rend="italic">(Timæus,</hi> p. 60 ; comp. Plutarch,
                    <hi rend="italic">Sympos.,</hi> v. 10). As covenants were ordinarily made over a
                sacrificial meal, in which salt was a necessary element, the expression “a covenant
                of salt” (Numb, xviii. 19) is easily understood ; it is probable, however, that the
                preservative qualities of salt were held to make it a peculiarly fitting symbol of
                an enduring compact, and influenced the choice of this particular element of the
                covenant meal as that which was regarded as sealing an obligation to fidelity. Among
                the ancients, as among orientals down to the present day, every meal that included
                salt had a certain sacred character and created a bond of piety and guest friendship
                between the participants. Hence the Greek phrase άλας Καί τράπεδαυ </p>
            <p>παραβαίυειν, the Arab phrase “there is salt between us,” the expression “to eat the
                salt of the palace” (Ezra iv. 14, Rev. Ver.), the modern Persian phrase <hi
                    rend="italic">namak harâm,</hi> “untrue to salt,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>
                disloyal or ungrateful, and many others.</p>
            <p>It has been plausibly conjectured that the oldest trade routes were created for
                traffic in salt; at any rate salt and incense, the chief economic and religious
                necessaries of the ancient world, play a great part in all that we know of the
                ancient highways of commerce. Thus one of the oldest roads in Italy is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Via Salaria, </hi>by which the produce of the salt pans of Ostia
                was carried up into the Sabine country. Herodotus’s account of the caravan route
                uniting the salt-oases of the Libyan desert (iv. 181 <hi rend="italic">sq.)</hi>
                makes it plain that this was mainly a salt-road, and to the present day the caravan
                trade of the Sahara is largely a trade in salt. The salt of Palmyra was an important
                element in the vast trade between the Syrian ports and the Persian Gulf (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Palmyra,</hi> vol. xviii. p. 200), and long after the glory of
                the great merchant city was past “the salt of Tadinor” retained its reputation
                (Mas'ûdi, viii. 398). In like manner the ancient trade between the AEgean and the
                coasts of southern Russia was largely dependent on the salt pans at the mouth of the
                Dnieper and on the salt fish brought from this district (Herod., iv. 53; Dio Chrys.,
                p. 437). In Phoenician commerce salt and salt fish—the latter a valued delicacy in
                the ancient world—always formed an important item. The vast salt mines of northern
                India were worked before the time of Alexander (Strabo, v. 2, 6, xv. 1, 30) and must
                have been the centre of a widespread trade. The economic importance of salt is
                further indicated by the almost universal prevalence in ancient and mediaeval times,
                and indeed in most countries down to the present day, of salt taxes or of Government
                monopolies, which have not often been directed, as they were in ancient Rome, to
                enable every one to procure so necessary a condiment at a moderate price. In
                oriental systems of taxation high imposts on salt are never lacking and are often
                carried out in a very oppressive way, one result of this being that the article is
                apt to reach the consumer in a very impure state largely mixed with earth. “The salt
                which has lost its savour” (Mat. v. 13) is simply the earthy residuum of such an
                impure salt after the sodium chloride has been washed out.</p>
            <p>Cakes of salt have been used as money in more than one part of the world,—for
                example, in Abyssinia and elsewhere in Africa, and in Tibet and adjoining parts. See
                the testimony of Marco Polo (bk. ii. ch. 48) and Col. Yule’s note upon analogous
                customs elsewhere and on the use of salt as a medium of exchange in the Shan markets
                down to our own time, in his translation of Polo, ii. 48 <hi rend="italic">sq.
                </hi>In the same work interesting details are given as to the importance of salt in
                the financial system of the Mongol emperors (ii. 200 <hi rend="italic">sq.).</hi>
                (W. R. S.)</p>
            <p>SALTA, capital of a province of the same name in the Argentine Republic, with a
                population of about 20,000 (1881), is a well-built town occupying a somewhat
                insalubrious situation, 3780 feet above the sea, at the confluence of the Rio de la
                Sillata and Rio de Arias, head streams of the Rio Salado (there called Rio Pasaje or
                Juramanto), about 820 miles north-west of Buenos Ayres. The town, founded by Abreu
                in 1582, was originally known as San Clemente de Nueva Castilla, took the name of
                San Felipe de Lerma when Hernando de Lerma removed it to</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
