<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-05-23T18:46:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p> (3) With the Ripuarian Law the <hi rend="italic">Lex Francorum Chamavorum</hi> is
                intimately connected. The two MSS. in which it is preserved call it “ Notitia vel
                commemoratio de illa ewa (law) quæ se ad Amorem habet.” Amor is the district called
                Hamarlant, Hamalant, Hammelant, Hamuland, in the 9th century. This name was derived
                from the Chamavi, a German state mentioned by Tacitus <hi rend="italic">(Ann.,
                </hi>xiii. 55 ; <hi rend="italic">Gcrm.,c.</hi> 33, 34), which afterwards
                constituted a part of the Frankish empire. In the 9th century Hamalant was a part of
                the Pagus Ribuarioruin. The whole code consists of only forty- eight short
                paragraphs, which are apparently nothing but statements made in answer to the “
                missi dominici ” whom Charlemagne despatched to the various nations of his empire to
                inquire into their condition and to codify their respective laws. It may therefore
                be ascribed to the beginning of the 9th century (802 or 803). Professor Sohm has
                published it as an appendix to the Lex Ripuaria (<hi rend="italic">Mon</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">Germ. Hist.,</hi> Legg., vol. v. part 2, p. 269).</p>
            <p> (4) The <hi rend="italic">Lex Alamannorum</hi> was (according to the prologue
                mentioned above) first compiled by the East-Frankish king Thierry (511-534), and
                afterwards improved and renewed by Childebert I. (511-558), Chlotar I. (558), and
                Dagobert I. (622-638). Although not much reliance can be placed on this statement,
                the researches of Professor Merkel, who edited the code from forty-eight MSS. <hi
                    rend="italic">{Mon. Germ. Hist.,</hi> Legg., vol. iii.), show that some kind of
                code called Pactus (of which he published three fragments) was cornpiled for the
                Alamanni in the reign of Chlotar I. (537-561). Under Chlotar II. (613-622) a more
                complete code, consisting of seventy- five chapters, was compiled, which was revised
                under Dagobert (628) and augmented with chapters 76-97 ; it was again altered and
                augmented under the Alamannic duke Landfrid (d. 730), whose work Merkel calls <hi
                    rend="italic">Lex Alamannorum Lantfridana,</hi> and finally augmented in the
                Carolingian period (hence called <hi rend="italic">Lex Alamannorum Karolina sive
                    reformata),</hi> perhaps early in the 9th century. The code consists of 97 (in
                some MSS. 98, 99, 105, and 107) chapters.</p>
            <p> (5) The <hi rend="italic">Lex Bajuvariorum,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Pactus
                    Bawarorum,</hi> had the same origin as the Lex Alamannorum, if we accept the
                somewhat unreliable statement of the prologue spoken of above. It seems probable
                that some kind of code was compiled for the Bavarians during the reigns of Clovis’s
                sons. Those paragraphs which treat of ecclesiastical affairs and the position of the
                Bavarian dukes towards the Frankish kings (tit. ii. chap. xx. § 3) have clearly been
                inserted in Dagobert’s time, if not later. There is a great similarity between
                certain provisions of the Bavarian and the Alamannic codes, and also some paragraphs
                of the former have been derived from the earliest recension of the Lex Wisigothorum.
                Some additions were made by Duke Thassilo II. (763-775), some by Charlemagne (803),
                some by King Louis (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 906), and, finally, some by Duke Henry
                II. (end of 10th century). The emperor Henry III. is alleged to have granted the law
                of the Bavarians to the Hungarians in 1044. It consists of twenty-one chapters, each
                containing several paragraphs. Professor Merkel distinguishes three different
                recensions of the code and various additions, which he edited in 1863 from
                thirty-five MSS. for the <hi rend="italic">Mon. Germ. Hist.,</hi> Legg., iii. p. 183
                    <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p>
            <p> (6) For the <hi rend="italic">Lex Frisionum,</hi> see vol. ix. p. 789.</p>
            <p> (7) <hi rend="italic">The Lex Angliorum et Werinorum, hoc est, Thuringorum,</hi>
                consists of seventeen chapters. Early editions of this code contained some legal
                decisions identical with those of Judge Wlemarus in the appendix to the Lex
                Frisionum (L. Angl. Jud. Wlem., 1, 2, 6, 7<hi rend="italic">— L.</hi> Fris., 22, §§
                54, 55, 86 ; Addit., i. 18), from which circumstance it was inferred that the
                compilation, or at least the revision, of both codes took place at one and the same
                time (802-803). But Richthofen, who edited the work in <hi rend="italic">Mon. Germ.
                    Hist.</hi> (Legg., v. p. 103), and who rejects these legal decisions of Wlemarus
                as not belonging to this code at all, is of opinion (p. 115) that the code was not
                written even at the end of the 9th century. Opinions have differed also as to the
                region where the law originated. Some ascribe it to the Angli and Werini, who
                inhabited the Holstein and Schleswig regions ; others attribute it to Thuringia
                proper ; and in more recent times it has been ascribed to Thuringia on the left bank
                of the Rhine ( = South Holland, Brabant, &amp;c.). It was also argued that the code
                must have originated in a region where Frisian and Frankish elements had become
                mixed, both in language and in law, and where the Frankish preponderated. That the
                code originated in South Holland was inferred from its agreement in some respects
                with the Lex Chamavorum, which originated in the region of the lower Rhine and the
                Yssel. And the law may have come to be in force among the allied tribes on the Elbe
                in northern Thuringia, even though it originated in South Holland. If it originated
                in Thuringia, it must have been transplanted to the Holstein and Schleswig regions ;
                and it was used by the Danes, as is clear from Canute bringing it over to England
                when he conquered the country in 1013. @@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> But in
                England the code was simply called “ Lex Werinorum, h.e., Thuringorum,” but no
                longer “Anglorum,” as the Danes called the whole Anglo-Saxon population which they
                had conquered “ Angli,” and the law which they found in force “Lex Anglorum ” (Legg.
                Edw. Conf., c. 30). Hence it has been concluded that what was called in England Lex
                Danorum is nothing but the Lex Werinorum. When the Normans conquered England in 1066
                they soon recognized that this Lex Danorum and the Law of the Norwegians (Lex
                Noricorum or Norwegeusium), who had migrated to England in earlier times, were
                practically one and the same. Hence William I., declaring that the population which
                he had brought over with him from Normandy were also originally Norwegians, resolved
                to abrogate the Anglo-Saxon laws and to leave only that of the Danes in force (Legg.
                Edw. Conf., c. 30),—a plan which only the most persevering entreaties of the
                Anglo-Saxon barons could induce him to abandon. The latest edition of this code
                (1875) is by K. F. von Richthofen, who is decidedly against the South Holland origin
                of the law.</p>

            <p> (8) The <hi rend="italic">Lex Saxonum</hi> consists of nineteen chapters or
                sixty-six articles or paragraphs, and appears to be composed of three essential
                parts, the oldest of which (arts. 1-23) seems to have existed before the later
                additions known as the Capitulare Paderbornense (de partibus Saxoniæ) of 785 (or
                777) and the Capitulare Saxonicum of 797 (in which a “Lex Saxonum” and “Ewa Saxonum”
                are referred to; comp, chaps. 33 and 7, 8, 10); the second part (arts. 24-60) must
                have been compiled after that date; and the third (arts. 61-66) was probably added
                in 798, when Charlemagne had removed a part of the Saxon nobility as hostages from
                their own country ; while the whole was united into one code at the diet of
                Aix-la-Chapelle in 802-803 (Merkel, <hi rend="italic">Lex Saxonum,</hi> Berlin,
                1853). The enactments of this code are far more severe than those of any other of
                the barbarian laws, and it often inflicts capital punishment for crimes which the
                other laws punish with mere pecuniary fines, as, for instance, theft and
                incendiarism. This rigour Charlemagne softened by reserving to himself the right of
                asylum and pardon, but it was expressly retained and granted anew by Conrad II.
                (1024-1039). The code was edited in 1875 by Von Richthofen in <hi rend="italic">Mon.
                    Germ. Hist.,</hi> Legg., v. p. 1 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p>
            <p> (9) The <hi rend="italic">Leges Anglo-Saxonum</hi> are for a great part written in
                Anglo-Saxon, and as such may be reckoned among the most ancient monuments of the
                Teutonic language. They appeared mostly in the form of constitutions promulgated by
                the various kings (somewhat like the Frankish capitularies), with the co-operation
                of an assembly of leading men (“sapientes,” Beda, <hi rend="italic">H. E.,</hi> ii.
                5), and frequently also of the clergy (<hi rend="italic">concilium, synodus).</hi>
                They may be divided into two classes,—secular and ecclesiastical laws. Sometimes
                they are mere judicial sentences <hi rend="italic">(dôm)</hi> or treaties of peace
                    (<hi rend="italic">frio).</hi> The earliest laws we have are those of
                AEthelbert, king of Kent (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 561); then follow those of
                Hlodhaer (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 678) and Eâdrîc (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 685),
                Wihtraed (<hi rend="italic">c</hi>. 691), Ine (after 688), AElfred (after 871),
                Eadward (after 901), AEthelstan (after 924), Eadmund (after 941), Edgar (after 959),
                AEthelred II. (after 978), the Danish Canute (after 1017), William the Conqueror
                (after 1066). Then follow two collections of laws, the so-called “ Leges Edwardi
                Confessoris ” and “Leges Henrici I.,” which, drawing from the Anglo-Saxon Law,
                represent the modifications which had been made in the earliest laws during the
                Norman period, and the introduction of new elements derived from the Salic and
                Ripuarian Laws. Besides these there are a good many canons and other ecclesiastical
                ordinances enacted under the archbishops Theodore and Ecgbert and King Edgar,
                &amp;c. ; comp. <hi rend="smallcaps">England,</hi> vol. viii. pp. 285, 303. There is
                an edition of these laws by B. Thorpe (fol., London, 1840), another by Dr Reinh.
                Schmid (<hi rend="italic">Die Gcsetze der Angel- Sachsen,</hi> 2d ed., 8vo, Leipsic,
                1858).</p>
            <p> (10) The compilation of the <hi rend="italic">Lex Burgundionum</hi> is usually
                ascribed to Gundobald (d. 516), whence it is also called <hi rend="italic">Lex
                    Gundobada</hi> (corrupted <hi rend="italic">Gombata,</hi> Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Loi Gombette).</hi> It consists, according to its first prologue, of a
                collection of constitutions enacted partly by the earlier kings of Burgundy, partly
                by Gundobald, and revised by a general Burgundian diet. This agrees with the
                statements contained in its second prologue, which itself may be regarded as an
                independent constitution or edict to the counts and judges regarding the
                introduction of the law. In the rubric which it bears in the MSS. it is said that it
                was promulgated at Lyons on 29th March in the second year of Gundobald (some MSS.
                read Sigismund). As the year of Gundobald’s accession is supposed to be 465, the
                promulgation must have taken place in 467, or, if we assume that the year is meant
                in which Gundobald became sole king of Burgundy (478), the date of the law would be
                480, while it would be 517 if we adopt the reading “Sigismund” of some of the MSS.
                But as the law in its present state contains decrees both of Gundobald and of
                Sigismund we can only regard the whole as a compilation effected by the latter. In
                early editions the law was divided into eighty-nine chapters, with two additamenta,
                the first of which (consisting of twenty chapters) was ascribed to Sigismund, the
                second (of thirteen chapters) to his brother and successor, the last king of the
                Burgundians, Godomar. But Professor Bluhme (who published the law in 1863, in <hi
                    rend="italic">Mon. Germ. Hist.,</hi> Legg., iii. 497) places chap. i. (De causis
                itineribus et aliis servitutibus) and chap. xix. (De liberali causa) of the first
                additamentum as chaps.</p>

            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Comp. <hi rend="italic">Canuti Constit. de
                    Foresta,</hi> c. 33, “ Emendet secundum pretium hominis mediocris, quod secundum
                Legem Werinorum, <hi rend="italic">i.e</hi>., Thuringorum [= L. Angl. and Werin., i.
                2] est 200 solidorum.”</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
