<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-05-23T18:46:17Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>nervous system occurring for the most part in children, and characterized mainly by
                involuntary jerking movements of the muscles throughout almost the entire body. It
                is to be regarded as a functional nervous disorder of wide extent, the
                manifestations of which appear not merely in disturbance affecting the motor
                apparatus but in various associated morbid phenomena of cerebral origin. Among the
                predisposing causes age is important, chorea being essentially an ailment of
                childhood and more particularly of the period in which the second dentition is
                taking place. The greater number of the cases occur between the ages of nine and
                twelve. It is not often seen in very young children nor after puberty; but there are
                many exceptions to this rule. It is twice as frequent with girls as with boys.
                Hereditary predisposition to nervous troubles is apt to find expression in this
                malady in youth, more especially if the general health becomes lowered. Of exciting
                causes strong emotions, such as fright, ill-usage or hardship of any kind,
                insufficient feeding, overwork or anxiety, are among the most common; while, again,
                some distant source of irritation, such as teething or intestinal worms, appears
                capable of giving rise to an attack. It is an occasional but rare complication of
                pregnancy. The connexion of chorea with rheumatism is now universally recognized,
                and is shown not merely by its frequent occurrence before, after, or during the
                course of attacks of rheumatic fever in young persons, but even independently of
                this by the liability of the heart to suffer in a similar way in the two
                diseases.</p>
            <p>The symptoms of St Vitus’s dance are in some instances developed suddenly as the
                result of fright, but much more frequently they come on insidiously. They are
                usually preceded by changes in the temper and disposition, the child becoming sad,
                irritable, and emotional, while at the same time the general health is somewhat
                impaired. The first thing indicative of the disease is a certain awkwardness or
                fidgetiness of manner together with restlessness, the child being evidently unable
                to continue quiet, but frequently moving the limbs into different positions. In
                walking, too, slight dragging of one limb may be noticed. The convulsive muscular
                movements usually first show themselves in one part, such as an arm or a leg, and in
                some instances they may remain localized to that limited extent, while in all cases
                there is a tendency for the disorderly symptoms to be more marked on one side than
                on the other. When fully developed the phenomena of the disease are very
                characteristic. The child when standing or sitting is never still, but is constantly
                changing the position of the body or limbs in consequence of the sudden and
                incoordinate action of muscles or groups of them. The shoulder is jerked up, the
                head and trunk twisted about, the limbs crossed suddenly and changed again, the
                fingers keep moving restlessly, while the face is distorted with grimaces, frowning
                and smiling irregularly. These symptoms are aggravated when purposive movements are
                attempted or when the child is watched. Speech is affected both from the
                incoordinate movements of the tongue and from phonation sometimes taking place
                during an act of inspiration. The taking of food becomes a matter of difficulty,
                since much of it is lost in the attempts to convey it to the mouth, while swallowing
                is also interfered with owing to the irregular action of the pharyngeal muscles.
                When the tongue is protruded it comes out in a jerky manner and is immediately
                withdrawn, the jaws at the same time closing suddenly and sometimes with con</p>
            <p>siderable force. In locomotion the muscles of the limbs act incoordinately and there
                is a marked alteration of the gait, which is now halting and now leaping, and the
                child may be tripped by one limb being suddenly jerked in front of the other. In
                short, whether at rest or in motion the whole muscular system is seen to be deranged
                in its operations, and the term “ insanity of the muscles ” not inaptly expresses
                the condition, for they no longer act in harmony or with purpose, but seem, as
                Trousseau expresses it, each to have a will of its own and to be exercising this for
                different objects at one time. The muscles of organic life (involuntary muscles)
                appear scarcely, if at all, affected in this disease, as, for example, the heart,
                the rhythmic movements of which are not as a rule impaired. But the heart may suffer
                in other ways, especially from inflammatory conditions similar to those which attend
                upon rheumatism and which frequently lay the foundation of permanent heart disease.
                In severe cases of St Vitus’s dance the child comes to present a distressing
                appearance from the constant restlessness and disorderly movement, and the physical
                health declines. Usually, however, there is a remission of the symptoms during
                sleep. The mental condition of the patient is more or less affected, as shown in
                emotional tendencies, irritability, and a somewhat fatuous expression and bearing,
                but this change is in general of transient character and ceases with
                convalescence.</p>
            <p>This disease occasionally assumes a very acute and aggravated form, in which the
                disorderly movements are so violent as to render the patient liable to be injured
                and to necessitate forcible control of the limbs or the employment of anaesthetics
                to produce unconsciousness. Such cases are of very grave character, if, as is
                common, they are accompanied with sleeplessness, and they may prove rapidly fatal by
                exhaustion. In the great majority of cases of St Vitus’s dance, however, complete
                recovery is to be anticipated sooner or later, the symptoms usually continuing for
                from one to two months, or even sometimes much longer.</p>
            <p>The nature of this disease has given rise to much discussion and there still remains
                considerable difference of opinion as to its true pathology. The fact that the vast
                majority of cases recover would seem to show that there could have been no profound
                change in the structural integrity of the nerve-centres, while in those instances
                where a fatal result takes place <hi rend="italic">post-mortem</hi> examination
                reveals no constant morbid condition. A theory supported by high authority has
                referred the cause of the malady to the plugging up of minute blood-vessels in the
                motor centres of the brain (a condition not unlikely to occur in rheumatic
                inflammation affecting the lining membrane of the heart), and such a change has been
                seen in a few instances. In a still larger number, however, no appearances of this
                kind have been observed, but simply vascular changes of a congestive character
                widely diffused throughout the central nervous system, accompanied with evidences of
                slight inflammatory action. Dr Dickinson, whose views, founded upon carefully
                conducted investigations, are those most widely accepted, concludes as follows: “We
                see in chorea a widely distributed hyperaemia [<hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>
                congestion] of the nervous centres, not due to any mechanical mischance, but
                produced mainly by causes of two kinds,—one a morbid, probably a humoral influence,
                which may affect the nervous centres as it affects other organs and tissues; the
                other, irritation in some mode usually mental but sometimes what is called reflex,
                which especially belongs to and disturbs the nervous system, and affects persons
                differently, according to the inherent mobility of their nature.”</p>
            <p>For the treatment of St Vitus’s dance the remedies proposed have been innumerable,
                but it is doubtful whether any of them have much control over the disease, which</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
