<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-05-23T18:45:11Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>buildings. It contains an elaborate monument to Archbishop Sharp. Near the south-west of the town is the ruined northern transept of the chapel of the Dominican monastery founded by Bishop Wishart in 1274 ; but all traces of the Observantine monastery founded about 1450 by Bishop Kennedy have disappeared, except the well. The church of St Alary on the rock erected by the Culdees is supposed to have stood on the Lady’s Craig now covered by the sea ; and the foundations of another, also dedicated to the Virgin, to the west of the harbour were discovered in 1860, giving the full outline of the ground-plan of the building.</p><p>The university was possibly a development of the “schools” which were in existence as early as the beginning of the 12th century, and were endowed by certain “rents and kune” payable to them from lands in the neighbourhood. Its immediate origin was due to a society formed in 1410 by Lawrence of Lindores, abbot of Scone, Richard Cornwall, archdeacon of Lothian, William Stephen, afterwards archbishop of Dunblane, and a few others, for the instruction of all who chose to attend their lectures. A charter was granted in 1411 by Bishop Wardlaw, who attracted the most learned men in Scotland as professors, and bulls were obtained from the pope in 1413 confirming the charter and constituting it a <hi rend="italic">studium generate</hi> or university. The lectures were delivered in various parts of the town until 1430, when a building called the “pedagogy” to the Faculty of Arts was granted by the founder of the university. St Salvator’s College was founded and richly endowed by Bishop Kennedy in 1456; twelve years later it was granted the power to confer degrees in theology and philosophy, and by the end of the century was regarded as a constituent part of the university. In 1512 the university received a further addition by the foundation of St Leonard’s College by Prior John Hepburn and Archbishop Alexander Stuart on the site of buildings which at one time were used as a hospital for pilgrims. In the same year Archbishop Stuart nominally changed the original “ pedagogy ” into a college and annexed to it the parish church of St Michael of Tarvet; but its actual erection into a college did not take place until 1537. By a bull obtained from Paul III. it was dedicated to the Blessed Virgin Mary of the Assumption. The outline of the ancient structure is preserved, but the general character of the buildings has been much altered by various restorations. They form two sides of a quadrangle, the library and principal’s residence being on the north and the lecture-rooms and old dining-hall on the west. The university library, which now includes the older college libraries, was founded about the middle of the 17th century, rebuilt in 1764, and improved in 1829. The lower hall in the older part of the building has been used as a provincial meeting-place for the Scottish parliament. When the constitution of the colleges was remodelled in 1579 St Mary’s was set apart to theology ; and in 1747 the colleges of St Salvator and St Leonard were formed into the United College. The buildings of St Leonard’s are now occupied as a high class school for girls. The college chapel is in ruins. The United College occupies the site of St Salvator’s College, but the old buildings have been removed, with the exception of the college chapel, now used as the university chapel and the parish church of St Leonard’s, a fine Gothic structure containing an elaborate tomb of Bishop Kennedy ; the entrance gateway with the square clock tower rising to a height of 152 feet; and the janitor’s house, with some class-rooms above. The modern building, in the Elizabethan style, forming two sides of a quadrangle, was erected between the years 1827 and 1847. The Madras College was founded and endowed by Dr Andrew Bell. It is attended by about 700 pupils. There are also several large boarding and day schools.</p><p>St Andrews (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotland)</hi> is said to have been made a bishopric in the 9th century, and when in 908 the Pictish and Scottish Churches were united the primacy was transferred to it from Dunkeld, its bishops being henceforth known as bishops of Alban. Turgot, who was appointed in 1109, was the first bishop who really filled the see. It became an archbishopric during the primacy of Patrick Graham (1466-78). This ceased in 1688. It was created a royal burgh by David I. in 1124. The St Andrews district of burghs returns one member to the House of Commons.</p><p>Martine, <hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities of St Rule’s Chapel, St Andrews,</hi> 1787 ; Grierson, <hi rend="italic">Delineatlons of St Andrews,</hi> 1807, 3d ed. 1838 ; <hi rend="italic">Reliquiæ Divi Andreæ, 1797 </hi>; <hi rend="italic">Liber Cartarum Sancti Andreæ,</hi> Bannatyne Club, 1841; Skene, “ Ecclesiastical Settlements in Scotland,” in P<hi rend="italic">roc. Soc. Antiq. Scot.,</hi> 1862-63; <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi> of St Andrews by Lyon (1843) and Rogers (1849); Skene, <hi rend="italic">Celtic Scotland..</hi> (T. F. H.)</p><p>ST ASAPH, a city and parliamentary borough of North Wales, in the county of Flint, is situated on an eminence in the Vale of Clwyd, near the junction of the Clwyd and Elwy, about 6 miles south-south-east of Rhyl and 6 north-north-west of Denbigh. It is somewhat irregularly built and has an antique appearance. On the brow of the hill is an encampment, <hi rend="italic">Bron-y-Wylva,</hi> supposed to have been occupied by the Roman forces under Suetonius Paulinus. According to tradition the cathedral occupies the site of a church and monastery founded by St Kenti-</p><p>gern about 560, when he fled from Strathclyde. It was originally called Llan-Elwy, the church on the Elwy. It is uncertain whether the first bishop was Kentigern or Asaph, to whom Kentigern committed the charge of the church and monastery when he returned to Scotland. The ancient wooden structure was burnt down by the English in 1245; and again in 1278 the same fate befell the building. A third edifice was in great part destroyed during the wars of Owen Glendower in 1402. The greater part of the present building was constructed by Bishop Redman about 1480 ; the choir and chancel underwent restoration from the designs of Sir Gilbert Scott in 1867-68, and the nave in 1875, when a new roof was added. It is one of the smallest cathedrals in Britain, its total length being 182 feet, while the breadth across the transepts is 108 feet. It is a plain cruciform structure, chiefly Decorated, but with some Early English portions, with an embattled tower, 97 feet in height, rising from the intersection of the nave and the transept. In the south transept there is a library of nearly 2000 volumes, including some rare and valuable books. The bishop’s palace is a comparatively modern structure. The town has a grammar- school (1882), county court offices, the union workhouse, and almshouses. The population of the borough (area, 1155 acres) in 1881 was 1901 and of the parish 3177.</p><p>ST AUGUSTINE, a city of the United States, capital of St John’s county, Florida, has the distinction of being the oldest city in the States built by Europeans, and has recently become a popular winter watering-place. By rail it is 36 miles south-east from Jacksonville. It stands on a narrow sandy peninsula, not more than 12 feet above the sea, formed by the Matanzas and San Sebastian rivers, and is separated from the ocean by the northern end of Anastasia Island. The streets are very narrow, the principal thoroughfares being only 12 or 15 feet wide, and the balconies of the old houses often project so as almost to meet overhead. Along the sea-front for nearly a mile extends a granite- coped sea-wall (1837-43), which forms a fine promenade. At its northern end stands the old fort of San Marco (now Fort Marion), a well-preserved specimen of Spanish military architecture (finished 1756), with moat and outworks, walls 21 feet high, bastions at the corners, heavy casemates, dungeons, and subterranean passages. It is in the form of a trapezium, and covers about 4 acres. Like most of the Spanish buildings, it is constructed of coquina, a curious shelly conglomerate from Anastasia Island, which was easily quarried, but grew very hard on exposure to the atmosphere. The same material was used for paving the streets, which were thus kept extremely clean and firm. At the southern end of the sea-wall is the old Franciscan monastery, now used as United States barracks. Of the Spanish wall which ran across the peninsula and defended the city on the north side there only remains the so-called city gate. In the centre of St Augustine is the Plaza de la Constitucion, which takes its name from the monument in the middle, erected in 1812 in memory of the Liberal Spanish Constitution. On this square stand the' cathedral (1793), with a Moorish belfry, the old governor’s palace, now used as a post-office and public library, and an Episcopal church in modern Gothic. Other buildings of note in the town are the convent of St Mary and the convent of the sisters of St Joseph. Modern villas and hotels have recently been erected in various parts. Palmetto straw goods are largely manufactured in St Augustine, the palmetto being one of the characteristic features of the surrounding landscape, to which orange and lemon trees also contribute. The climate is remarkably equable, the mean temperature for winter being 58°, and for the other seasons 68°, 80°, and 71° respectively. Frosts seldom occur, though that of 1835 killed many of the orange-</p></body></text></TEI>