<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:16:08Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>(many of them natives of Wales) who did much to enrich and beautify the vast group of ecclesiastical buildings in the Close. But, with the partial destruction of the palace and the removal of the episcopal residence to Abergwili, it was not long before St Davids sank into a mere monument of its former splendour and importance. In 1539 Bishop Barlow even petitioned Thomas Cromwell for permission to remove the see itself to Carmarthen, a request which tradition declares Henry VIII. refused to grant solely out of respect for the memory of his grandfather Edmund Tudor, whose tomb had recently been taken from the suppressed priory of Grey Friars at Carmarthen and set up before the high altar of the cathedral. During the 17th and 18th centuries all the ancient buildings of the Close, except the cathedral (which served also as a parish church for the village of St Davids), were allowed to fall into hopeless ruin. Amongst the 119 bishops who have held the sec since its foundation by St David may be mentioned Asser, the friend of King Alfred (d. 906); Samson (loth century), honoured by the Welsh chroniclers with the proud title of “ Archbishop of the Isle of Britain ”; Rhyddmarch (d. 1096), the first biographer of St David; Henry de Gower (d. 1347), the munificent patron of art; Robert Ferrar, burned at Carmarthen in 1555 under Queen Mary; Richard Davies (d. 1581), patriot and translator of the Welsh Book of Common Prayer; Archbishop William Laud, bishop of the see between 1621 and 1627; George Bull, divine (d. 1710); and Connop Thirlwall, scholar and historian (d. 1875). The official title of the bishops of St Davids is <hi rend="italic">Episcopus Meneυensis.</hi> (H.M.V.) .</p><p>ST DENIS, an industrial town of northern France, capital of an arrondissement in the department of Seine, 5 m. N. of Paris. Pop. (1906) 62,323. St Denis, an important junction on the northern railway, stands in a plain on the right bank of the Seine, which is here joined by the canal of St Denis. It has numerous metallurgical works, where railway material, naval engines and the like are constructed, distilleries of spirits, glass- works, potteries and manufactories of drugs, chemical products, oils, nickel plate and pianos. The name and fame of the town are derived from the abbey founded by Dagobert I. on the spot where St Denis, the apostle of Paris, was interred. The abbey buildings, occupied by a school for daughters of members of the Legion of Honour, founded by Napoleon I., date from the 18th century.</p><p>The church exhibits the transition from the Romanesque to the Gothic style. The west front was built between 1137 and 1140. The right-hand tower is almost pure Romanesque; that on the left was Gothic, and its spire was carried to a height of 280 ft., but it was struck by lightning in 1837 and reconstructed in so clumsy a manner that it had to be reduced to the level of the roof of the nave. The rose window, now occupied by a clock face, dates from the 13th century. Under one of the three rows of arches above the main entrance runs an inscription recording; the erection of the church by Abbot Suger (<hi rend="italic">q.v.</hi>), minister of Louis VL, with abbatial funds and its consecration in 1140. The porch formed by the first three bays of the church contains some remains of the basilica of Pippin the Short and Charlemagne, by whom the church was rebuilt. The nave proper (235 ft. long and 57 wide) has seven bays, and dates, as well as most of the choir and transepts, from the reign of St Louis. The secondary apse (<hi rend="italic">rondpoint</hi>) and its semicircular chapels (consecrated in 1144) are considered as the first perfected attempt at Gothic. The transepts have fine façades, the north of the 12th, the south of the 13th century, each with two unfinished towers ; if the plan had been fully carried out there would have been six towers besides a central spire in lead. The church contains a series of tombs of the kings and princes of the royal houses of France. The most remarkable are those of Louis XII. and Anne of Brittany, executed from 1516 to 1532 ; of Henry IL and Catherine de’ Medici, a masterpiece by Germain Pilon (1564-1583); of Louis of Orleans and Valentine of Milan, from the old church of the Celestines at Paris (1502-1515) ; of Francis I. and Claude of France, one of the most splendid tombs of the Renaissance, executed under the direction of Philibert Delorme (1550-1560) ; and that of Dagobert, which, though considerably dilapidated, ranks as one of the most curious of medieval (13th-century) works of art. In the apse some stained glass of the time of Suger remains. The crypt dates partly from the 10th or 11th century. In the centre is the vault where the coffin of the king used to lie until, to make room for that of his successor, it was removed to its final resting-place. It is at present occupied by the coffin of Louis XVIII.,the last sovereign whose body was borne to St Denis. Besides fine statues, the crypt contains the Bourbon vault, in which among other coffins are deposited the remains of Louis XVI. and Marie Antoinette.</p><p>St Denis, the ancient <hi rend="italic">Catulliacum,</hi> was a town of no pretensions till the foundation of its abbey, which became one of the most powerful in France. The rebuilding of the church, begun in the 12th century by Suger, was completed in the 13th century. Among the many domains of the abbey was the French Vexin. It was held during the later middle ages by the French kings and vassals of the abbey, and to this fact is due their adoption of the oriflamme or red banner of St Denis as the royal standard. St Louis caused mausoleums to be erected with figures of the princes already buried in the abbey; and from his time to that of Henry II. every monarch in succession had his monument. Louis XIV. reduced the abbey to the rank of a priory; and at the Revolution it was suppressed, the tombs being violated and the church sacked (1793). Two years later all the remains that could be recovered were placed in the museum of the Petits Augustins at Paris; but the bronze tombs had been melted down, the stained-glass windows shattered, and large numbers of interesting objects stolen or lost. Louis XVIII. caused all the articles belonging to St Denis to be brought back to their original site, and added numerous other monuments from the suppressed abbeys. But it was not till after 1848 that, under the direction of Viollet le Duc, the basilica recovered its original appearance. St Denis, which was the key of Paris on the north, was more than once pillaged in the Hundred Years’ War, suffering especially in 1358 and 1406. A sanguinary battle, in which the Catholic leader Constable Anne de Montmorency found victory and death, was fought between Huguenots and Catholics in the neighbourhood on the 10th of November 1567.</p><p>See F. de Guilhermy, <hi rend="italic">Monographie de l'église royale de Si Denis </hi>(Paris, 1848).</p><p>ST DIÉ, a town of eastern France, capital of an arrondissement in the department of Vosges, 38 m. N.E. of Épinal by rail. Pop. (1906) town, 16,783; commune, 22,136. St Dié is situated on the Meurthe in a basin surrounded by well-wooded hills. The town, part of which was laid out in a uniform style after the fire of 1757, is built largely of red sandstone. Its cathedral has a Romanesque nave (12th century) and a Gothic choir; the portal of red stone dates from the 18th century. A fine cloister (13th century), containing a stone pulpit, communicates with the Petite-Église or Notre-Dame, a well-preserved specimen of Romanesque architecture (12th century). The hôtel-de-ville contains a theatre, a library with some valuable manuscripts, and a museum of antiquities. There is a monument by Mercié to Jules Ferry, born in the town in 1832. St Dié is the seat of a bishop and of a sub-prefect. The town benefited from the immigration of Alsatians after the Franco-German War of 1870-71, and its industries include the spinning and weaving of cotton, bleaching, wire-drawing, metal-founding, and the manufacture of hosiery, woodwork of various kinds, machinery, iron goods and wire-gauze.</p><p>St Dié (<hi rend="italic">Deodatum, Theodata, S. Deodati Fanum)</hi> grew up round a monastery founded in the 7th century by St Deodatus of Nevers, who gave up his episcopal functions to retire to this place. In the 1oth century the community became a chapter of canons; among those who subsequently held the rank of provost or dean were Giovanni de’ Medici, afterwards Pope Leo X., and several princes of the house of Lorraine. Among the extensive privileges enjoyed by them was that of coining money. Though they co-operated in building the town walls, the canons and the dukes of Lorraine soon became rivals for the authority over St Dié. Towards the end of the 15th century one of the earliest printing-presses of Lorraine was founded at St Dié. The institution of a town council in 1628, and the establishment in 1777 of a bishopric which appropriated part of their spiritual jurisdiction, contributed greatly to diminish the influence of the canons; and with the Revolution they were completely swept away. During the wars of the 15th, 16th and 17th centuries the town was repeatedly sacked. It was also partially destroyed by fire in 1065, 1155, 1554 and 1757. Funds for the rebuilding of the portion of the town destroyed by the last fire were supplied by Stanislas, last duke of Lorraine.</p><p>ST DÌZIER, a town of north-eastern France, in the department of Haute-Marne, 45 m. N.N.W. of Chaumont by rail, on the Marne and the Haute-Marne canal. Pop. (1906) town, 10,316; commune, 14,661. The town is a very important centre of the iron trade, with foundries, forges and engineering</p></body></text></TEI>