<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-03-26T21:14:46Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>that is to say, it was used by the Romans to form the names of the inhabitants of municipal towns, as for instance <hi rend="italic">Foro-iulienses, </hi>the inhabitants of Forum Julii. There remain, therefore, the three suffixes <hi rend="italic">-co-, -no-,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">-ti-,</hi> and it will be seen from the table that the relative frequency of these suffixes in different dialect-areas varies very greatly. The suffix <hi rend="smallcaps">-</hi><hi rend="italic">no</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">-,</hi> for example, has almost driven out any other in the district of the Hirpini, and it is greatly preponderant among the Campani, in the district of the Lucani, and among the Latini and Sabini themselves.</p><p>5.	On the other hand, the <hi rend="italic">-co-</hi> suffix, which is nowhere frequent, is practically confined to the central areas.</p><p>6.	The <hi rend="italic">-ti-</hi> suffix is comparatively frequent in the Volscian district and very frequent in the Umbrian ; it is also fairly well represented in Latium and Etruria.</p><p>7.	In the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Volsci</hi> it is shown that the addition of the-<hi rend="italic">no</hi>- suffix is often a mark of the conquest of an original <hi rend="italic">-co-</hi> folk by a Safine tribe. It is also fairly frequently added to names formed with the <hi rend="italic">-ti-</hi> suffix: <hi rend="italic">Ardea</hi> gave first <hi rend="italic">Ardeates</hi> and <hi rend="italic">then Ardeatini; </hi>the <hi rend="italic">Picentes</hi> became <hi rend="italic">Picentini,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Camertes Camertini</hi>; of such forms there are no fewer than 54.</p><p>8.	The addition of the <hi rend="italic">-ati-</hi> suffix to the <hi rend="italic">-no-</hi> ethnicοn, as in <hi rend="italic">Iguυinates,</hi> is comparatively rare, and no doubt denotes the opposite process, namely, the absorption of a <hi rend="italic">-no-</hi> tribe by a population to whom it was natural to use the suffix <hi rend="italic">-ti-.</hi> The two opposite processes confirm the inference that both are due to some change of race, not merely to a change of custom in the same population in a later age; for in that case the change would have been in one direction only.</p><p>The assumption of the Safine origin of the <hi rend="italic">-no-</hi> suffix is further confirmed by the practice of the Romans themselves. The folk of Latium after the Safine conquest were no longer <hi rend="italic">Latiares</hi> but <hi rend="italic">Latini,</hi> and over against the old name <hi rend="italic">Quiritis</hi> was the new <hi rend="italic">Populus Rοmanus.</hi> Just the same rough and ready nomen- clature was applied to communities conquered on foreign soil; the Σπαρτιάται became <hi rend="italic">Spartani,</hi> the ∑υpακoσιoι <hi rend="italic">Syracusani, </hi>and the ’Ασιατικοί <hi rend="italic">Asiani,</hi> and so on.</p><p>The assumption that Latin was properly the language of the Latian plain and of the Plebs at Rome, which the conquering patrician nobles learnt from their subjects, and substituted for their own kindred but different Safine idiom, renders easier to understand the borrowing of a number of words into Latin from some dialect (presumably Sabine) where the velars had been labialized; for example, the very common word <hi rend="italic">bos,</hi> which in pure Latin should have been <hi rend="italic">*υos.</hi> And in general it may be stated that the hypothesis of such an intermixture of forms from neigh- bouring dialects has been rendered in recent years far more credible by the striking evidence of such continual intermixture going on within quite modern periods of time afforded by the <hi rend="italic">Atlas linguistique de la Prance,</hi> even in the portion which has already been published.</p><p>The conclusion, therefore, to which the evidence appears to lead us is that in, say, the 7th century, <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> the Safines spoke a language not differing in any important particulars from that of the Samnites, generally known as Oscan; and that when this warlike tribe combined with the people of the Latian plain to found or fortify or enlarge the city of Rome, and at the end of the 6th century to drive out from it the Etruscans, who had in that century become its masters, they imposed upon the new community many of their own usages, especially within the sphere of politics, but in the end adopted the language of Latium henceforth known as <hi rend="italic">lingua Latina,</hi> just as the Normans adopted the language of the conquered English.</p><p>The glosses and place-names of the ancient Sabine district are collected by R. S. Conway, the <hi rend="italic">Italic Dialects</hi> (Cambridge, 1897), p. 351. For the history of the Sabine district see Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">C.I.L. </hi>ix. p. 396; and Beloch, “ Der italische Bund unter römischer Hegemonie ” (Leipzig, 1880) and “ La Conquista Romana della regione Sabina,” in the <hi rend="italic">Riυista di storia antica</hi> (1905), ix. p. 269.</p><p>(R. S. C.)</p><p>SABINIANUS, pope from 604 to 606, successor of St Gregory the Great. He incurred unpopularity by his unseasonable economies. The erudite Italian Augustinian Onofrio Panvinio (1529-1568) in his <hi rend="italic">Epitome pοntificum Romanorum</hi> (Venice, 1557) attributes to this pope the introduction of the custom of ringing bells at the canonical hours and for the celebration of the eucharist.</p><p>SABLE, the name of a small quadruped, closely akin to the martens, and known by the zoological name of <hi rend="italic">Mustela zibellina. </hi>It is a native of Siberia and famous for its fur. The name</p><p>appears to be Slavonic in origin, cf. Russian <hi rend="italic">sobol,</hi> whence it has been adapted into various languages, cf. Ger. <hi rend="italic">Zobel,</hi> Dutch <hi rend="italic">Sabel;</hi> the Mod. Fr. <hi rend="italic">zibelline</hi> and Med.Lat. <hi rend="italic">zibellina</hi> derive from the Ital. form. The Eng. and Med. Lat. <hi rend="italic">sabellum</hi> are from the O. Fr. <hi rend="italic">sable</hi> or <hi rend="italic">saible</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Marten</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Fur).</hi> “ Sable ” in English is a rhetorical or poetical synonym for “ black.” This comes from the usage in heraldry (first in French) for the colour equivalent to black, represented conventionally by a cross- hatching of vertical and horizontal lines. It has usually been assumed that this is an extension of the name of the fur, but sable fur is brown.</p><p>SABLÉ, MADELEINE DE SOUVRÉ, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marquise de (1599-</hi>1678) French writer, was bom in 1599, the daughter of Gilles de Souvré, marquis de Courtenvaux, tutor of Louis XIII., and marshal of France. In 1614 she married Philippe Emmanuel de Laval, marquis de Sablé, who died in 1640, leaving her in somewhat straitened circumstances. With her friend the comtesse de St Maur she took rooms in the Place Royale, Paris, and established a literary <hi rend="italic">salon.</hi> Here originated that class of literature of which the <hi rend="italic">Maximes</hi> of La Rochefoucauld are the best-known example. The <hi rend="italic">Maximes</hi> of the marquise de Sablé were in fact composed before those of La Rochefoucauld, though not published till after her death. In 1655 she retired, with the comtesse de St Maur, to the Convent of Port Royal des Champs, near Marly, removing in 1661, when that establishment was closed, to Auteuil. In 1669 she took up her residence in the Port Royal convent in Paris, where she died on the 16th of January 1678.</p><p>SABLÉ, a town of western France, in the department of Sarthe, on the river Sarthe, 30 m. W.S.W. of Le Mans by rail. Pop. (1906) 4952. Sablé has a château of the 18th century, a fortified gateway, relic of a medieval stronghold, and a modern church with fine stained glass of the early 15th century. Its importance, however, is chiefly due to the marble quarries of the vicinity, the products of which are worked in the town, where flour-milling, the manufacture of farm-implements and trade in cattle are also carried on. A communal college is among the public institutions. From the 11th century Sablé was the seat of a powerful barony, which in 1602 was made a duchy-peerage in favour of Urbain de Laval, marshal of France. The place afterwards came into the possession of Colbert de Torcy, nephew of the great Colbert who built the chateau. In 1488 a treaty which resulted in the union of France and Brittany was concluded at Sablé, between Charles VIII. and Duke Francis II.</p><p>SABLE ANTELOPE, the English name for a large and handsome South African antelope (<hi rend="italic">Hippotragus niger</hi>)<hi rend="italic">,</hi> exhibiting the rare feature of blackness or dark colour in both sexes. The sable and the roan antelope (<hi rend="italic">H. equinus)</hi> belong to a genus nearly related to the oryxes, with which they form a group or sub- family. In all these antelopes long cylindrical horns are present in both sexes; the muzzle is hairy; there is no gland below the eye; the tail is long and tufted; and in the breadth of their tall crowns the upper molar-teeth resemble those of the oxen. The sable and roan antelopes are distinguished from <hi rend="italic">Oryx</hi> by the stout and thickly ringed horns rising vertically from a ridge over the eyes at an obtuse angle to the plane of the lower part of the face, and then sweeping backwards in a bold curve. Sable antelope are among the handsomest of South African antelopes, and are endowed with great speed and staying power. They are commonly met with in herds including from ten to twenty individuals, but on rare occasions as many as fifty have been seen together. Forest-clad highlands are their favourite resorts. The roan antelope is a larger animal, with shorter horns, whose general colour in both sexes is strawberry-roan. It is typically a South African species, but is represented by a local race in the eastern Sudan <hi rend="italic">(H. equinus bakeri)</hi> distinguished by its redder colour and different face-makings.</p><p>SABLE ISLAND, an island of Nova Scotia, Canada, 110 m. S.E. of Cape Canso, in 43° 56' N. and 60° W. It is composed of shifting sand, and is about 20 m. in length by 1 m. in breadth, rising in places to a height of 85 ft. In the interior is a lake about 10 m. in length. At either end dangerous sandbars run out</p></body></text></TEI>