<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="eb11-23-s01-0988-04"
                facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_1051.jp2" type="entry">
                <p><label>SADDLERY and HARNESS</label>, two terms which embrace the whole equipment
                    for the horse when used for riding or driving. “ Harness ” (O. Fr. <hi
                        rend="italic">harneis,</hi> mod. <hi rend="italic">harnais,</hi> Ger. <hi
                        rend="italic">Harnisch,</hi> of unknown origin) was originally a general
                    term for equipment, <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> the body armour of a soldier. It
                    is now usually confined to the draught horse’s equipment, “ saddle and bridle ”
                    being used of that of the riding horse.</p>
                <p>Saddlery is principally a leather trade, and the craft has been established in
                    England as a separate trade since the 13th century, when the London Saddlers’
                    Company received its charter from Edward I. There is evidence also of its early
                    prosperity at Birmingham ; the principal seat of the cheaper saddlery trade is
                    now at Walsall. Saddler’s ironmongery embraces the making of buckles, chains,
                    stirrups, spurs, bits, hames, &amp;amp;c.</p>
                <p>The “ bridle ” (O.E. <hi rend="italic">bridet</hi> for <hi rend="italic"
                        >brigdel,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">bregdan,</hi> to pull) is the
                    combination of straps and buckles which fits on the horse's head, the headstall,
                    together with the bit and reins which it keeps in position. The headstall
                    consists of the headpiece passing behind the ears and joining the head-band over
                    the forehead ; the cheek-straps run down the head to the bit to which they are
                    fastened; in the driving bridle the “ blinkers,” rectangular or round leather
                    flaps which prevent the horse from seeing anything except what lies in front,
                    are attached to the cheek-straps; the nose-band passes round the head above the
                    nostrils and the throat-lash from the top of the cheek-straps underneath the
                    head. The “ martingale ” passes between the horse’s legs with one end fastened
                    to the girth and the other to the bridle or nose-band. It prevents the horse
                    throwing up his head. The bit is the metal contrivance inserted in the mouth to
                    which the reins are attached. There are innumerable patterns of bits, but they
                    may be divided into the “ snaffle ” (Du. <hi rend="italic">snaυel,</hi> horse’s
                    muzzle), the “ curb ” and combinations of the two. The “ snaffle ” for the
                    riding horse has a smooth jointed steel mouthpiece, with straight cheek-bars,
                    the rings for the reins and cheek-pieces of the headstall being fixed in the
                    bars at the junction with the mouthpiece. A severer snaffle has the mouthpiece
                    twisted and fluted. The bars prevent the horse pulling the bit through the
                    mouth. The snaffle without bars is generally termed a “ bridoon.” The commonest
                    form of bit used in driving is the double-ring snaffle, in which the rings work
                    one within the other, the headstall straps fastening to one and the reins to the
                    other, or, if the horse is driven on the double ring, the reins are buckled to
                    both rings. The curb-bit (Fr. <hi rend="italic">courbe,</hi> Lat. <hi
                        rend="italic">curυus,</hi> bent, crooked) is one to which a curb-chain or
                    strap is attached, fastened to hooks on the upper ends of the cheek-bars of the
                    bit and passing under the horse’s lower jaw in the chin groove. The reins are
                    attached to rings at the lower ends of the cheek-bars, the leverage thus
                    pressing the curb-chain against the jaw. The mouthpiece of the curb-bit is
                    unjointed and has in the centre a “ port,” <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> a raised
                    curve allowing liberty for the tongue and bringing the pressure on the base of
                    the horse’s jaw. The curb-bit and the bridoon can be used together with separate
                    headstalls and reins, but there are many combination bits, such as the Pelham.
                    In this the mouthpiece, without port, is that of the snaffle bit (it may be
                    unjointed), with the rings fixed at the junction of the mouthpiece and
                    cheek-bars; the lower ends have rein rings as in the plain curb-bit.</p>
                <p>The riding saddle is composed of the “ tree,” the framework or skeleton, the
                    parts of which are the pommel or head, the projection which fits over the
                    withers, and the side bars which curve round into the cantle or hind-bow. The
                    tree in the best saddles is made of beech wood split with the grain ; thin
                    canvas is glued over the wood to prevent splitting, and iron or steel plates
                    then riveted on the head and on the cantle. Linen webs are fastened lengthwise
                    and across, over which is nailed canvas and serge between which the padding is
                    stuffed. To the tree are fastened the stirrup-bars. The leather covering of the
                    tree should be of pig-skin ; cheap saddles are made of sheep-skin stamped to
                    imitate pig-skin. The various parts of the man’s saddle are the seat, the skirt,
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi> the fold or pad of leather on either side of the
                    head, and the hanging flaps ; knee-rolls are not used as much as they were,
                    except where roughly broken-in horses are ridden. The saddle is cut straight
                    over the withers with a square-ended cantle, as in the hunting saddle, or cut
                    back over the withers with a round-ended cantle, as in the polo saddle. The
                    saddles in use on the continent of Europe still retain the high pommel and
                    cantle and heavy knee-rolls discarded by riders trained in the British school
                    and the hunting-field. The saddles of the East and of the Arabs keep their
                    primitive shape, and they are really seats <hi rend="italic">in</hi> which
                    rather than <hi rend="italic">on</hi> which the rider sits. The Mexican saddle,
                    with its silver adornments and embossed leather, is a characteristic type. It
                    has a very high padded pommel and a round-headed projecting cantle.</p>
                <p>The lady’s side-saddle when first fully developed had two heads or pommels,
                    between which the right leg was supported, the support for the left being the
                    stirrup. The third pommel or “ leaping head,” against which the left leg rests,
                    was, it is said, invented as the result of a match between two gentlemen riders
                    to ride a steeplechase on side-saddles; the winner had provided himself this
                    support for his left leg. At first the “ leaping head ” was only used in the</p>
                <pb xml:id="eb11-23-s01-0989" facs="encyclopaediabri23chisrich_1052.jp2"/>
                <p>hunting-field and the double cow-horn was still retained; as its usefulness
                    became apparent the second pommel practically disappeared.</p>
                <p>Space forbids the discussion of the varieties of harness for the pair-horse
                    carriage, the four-horse coach, the farm wagon, &amp;amp;c., or the different
                    kinds of ornamentation that are or have been lavished upon it. The leather
                    collar, heavily padded, passes over the head and rests firmly on the shoulders;
                    the hames, linked pieces of metal, fit tightly round it and are fastened at the
                    top by the hame-strap ; they bear the traces, or straps which pass along the
                    horse’s sides and the shafts and are attached by loops slipped over hooks in the
                    body of the carriage. Where the collar is dispensed with, the traces are
                    attached to a breast-strap against which the horse works. This breast harness is
                    much used for the lightly harnessed American trotting horses, and for military
                    draught horses. The saddle pad is a narrow leather cushion girthed under the
                    belly and held in position by the crupper-dock and the crupper, a loop strap
                    passing under the tail. The saddle supports the shafts by the back-band and its
                    tugs and by the belly-band. The reins pasá from the bit through “ terrets ” or
                    rings on the hames and pad. The harness on the horse’s hindquarters consists of
                    the breeching, passing round behind the horse and helping in backing and
                    stopping the vehicle, the hip-strap fastened to the breeching and passing over
                    the hind-quarters, and the kicking-strap falling across the loins and fastened
                    to the shafts. The bearing rein, when used merely as a support to the head, or
                    as an aid to the improvement of the paces, consists of a separate bridoon-bit
                    with the reins passing through rings on the throat-band and thence slipped over
                    a hook on the pad. The severer form, which brings the rein over the head-stall,
                    keeps the horse’s head up. in a cramped attitude and the mouth continually
                    working on the bit. A recent modifica-tion of the severer form is not attached
                    to the bit. _</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Historical Sketch.</hi> —Questions as to the epoch in the
                    history of mankind when the horse was first trained for draught and riding are
                    for archaeologists and anthropologists to discuss (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Horse,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">§ History).</hi> With the domestication of the horse came the
                    development of the bit; first a halter of hide bound the muzzle, then a thong
                    slipped into the mouth, finally replaced by wood or bone. Stone age objects have
                    been found in lake-dwellings, such as that at Robenhausen, near Zürich which may
                    have been bits; one is slightly curved, with two knobs grooved at either end for
                    the reins. Bits from the bronze age and the iron age can be seen in most museums
                    showing that the forms have changed little. The Scandinavian museums are
                    particularly rich in early remains of harness and horse-trappings. An early
                    bronze age bit of bone with horn cheek-pieces and with holes on the upper ends
                    for the head-stall, and on the lower ends for the reins, was found at the
                    Corcelletes lake dwelling, and a twisted bronze bit jointed by interlocking
                    rings with straight cheek-pieces and rings and loops for headstall and reins is
                    in the National Museum at Zürich. In the late iron age burial of a Gaulish chief
                    with his chariot at Somme-Bionne were found two horse’s bits of the ordinary
                    jointed snaffle type (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Archaeology,</hi> plate VI). A
                    heavy snaffle unjointed bit with red and blue enamel ornamentation is
                    illustrated in the British Museum <hi rend="italic">Guide to the Late Iron
                        Age.</hi> Assyrian and Babylonian monuments show the harness of the chariot
                    horses and the bridling of the riding horse, cf. <hi rend="smallcaps">Babylonia
                        and Assyria,</hi> Plate 11, fig. 2.</p>
                <p>ln ancient Greece and Rome the bit and bridle were used during historic times,
                    and allusions to riding without them refer to cxhibi-tions of horsemanship. On
                    Trajan’s column the Numidians ride without bridles or bits, and various North
                    African tribes trained their horses to obey their voice alone (cf. Claudian, <hi
                        rend="italic">Epig.</hi> i. 10, of the Gaulish <hi rend="italic"
                        >essedarii,</hi> driving without bridle and reins). The <hi rend="italic"
                        >locus clαssicus</hi> for the bridling and saddling of the Greek horse is
                    Xenophon, II <hi rend="italic">ϵpί ίππίkἡs.</hi> The Greek name for the bridle
                    bit and reins collectively is <hi rend="italic">χa■■vόs (Lαt. frenum),</hi> the
                    bit proper is <hi rend="italic">ατόμων;</hi> in Lat. <hi rend="italic"
                        >frenum</hi> is also used of the bit itself. The headstall (κορυφαία) and
                    cheek-straps <hi rend="italic">(</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">πa</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">ρ</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">ἡi</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">a)</hi> were richly decorated. In Homer <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Il.</hi> iv. 142) the latter arc ornamented with ivory plates stained with
                    purple, and such have been found on the site of Troy (Schliemann, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ilios,</hi> 476, 631). The head-band also bore a crest <hi
                        rend="italic">(λοφόs, crista),</hi> and in front the ■ <hi rend="italic"
                        >μτryξ (frontale)</hi> might be extended down the face to serve as a
                    defence, as in the medieval <hi rend="italic">chaufrein.</hi> This frontal was a
                    special subject of decoration. Of the two principal types of ancient bits, the
                    unjointed and the jointed mouthpiece, the latter is the most common form. There
                    are also other forms of bits; those with sharp points were called <hi
                        rend="italic">lupata.</hi> (Virg. <hi rend="italic">Georg,</hi> iii. 208).
                    There is a Greek bit in the British Museum with revolving disks, a device which
                    occurs in medieval bits, to give the horse something to keep turning in his
                    mouth. The curb was also used: Xenophon distinguishes between the snaffle (λϵ■os
                    χαλ■vόs) and the curb. The curb-strap or chain was termed ύτοχαλιμίδία or <hi
                        rend="italic">■àλ■ov</hi>, which, however, may mean a muzzle. A bronze bit
                    found at Pompeii has a twisted and jointed metal mouthpiece and a plain curved
                    bar acting as a curb-strap. The cheek-bars of the bit take a variety of forms:
                    straight bars, circles with rays, square or oblong plaques, triangles and the
                    swan-necked or S-shaped type are all found. In medieval times compli-cated and
                    severe bits were used, and heavy bits with cruel mouth-pieccs and long
                    elaborately curved cheek-bars are still used by Arabs and the riders of Central
                    and South America. The bit of the armed war-horse in the middle ages was
                    sometimes provided with very long cheek-bars covered with sharp spikes to
                    prevent the foot-soldier catching hold of the bridle (see R. Tschille and R.
                    Forrer, <hi rend="italic">Die Pferdetrense in ihrer Formen-Entwicklung,</hi>
                    1903, for illustrations of bits from prehistoric times to the 16th century).</p>
                <p>The saddle was not used in Egypt; the Assyrian monuments (cf. the illustration
                    noticed above) chiefly show decorated saddle-cloths rather than any form of the
                    saddle proper. The harness of the chariots of Egypt and Assyria arc also
                    illustrated on the monuments (see especially Sir J. G. Wilkinson, <hi
                        rend="italic">Manners and Customs of the Ancient Egyptians).</hi> The
                    ancient Greeks rode bare-backed as in the Panathenaic frieze of the Parthenon or
                    used a saddle-cloth <hi rend="italic">(iφlτnrιοr,</hi> Lat. <hi rend="italic"
                        >ephippium; sella</hi> as applied to a saddle is quite late). Even the
                    saddle-cloth does not appear to have been in use till the 5th century. A
                    6th-century vase, found at Daphnae, Lower Egypt (Flinders-Petrie and Murray, <hi
                        rend="italic">Tanis,</hi> 1888, ii. ρl. xxix.), shows a woman riding astride
                    on a cloth, with fully developed headstall and powerful bit. A black-figured
                    sarcophagus, now in the British Museum, from Clazomenae, shows a long pointed
                        <hi rend="italic">ephippium</hi> with a chest-strap. These indicate Asiatic
                    influence, for Daphnae was an Ionian and Carian settlement of the 7th century
                    B.c. In Xenophon <hi rend="italic">(l.c.)</hi> we find that the saddle-cloth had
                    been adopted by the Athenian cavalry, and from his advice as to the scat to be
                    adopted pads or rolls seem to have been added. There were no stirrups (till the
                    time of the emperor Maurice, <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> 602), and the rider
                    mounted at a vault or by blocks; mounting by the spear used as a vaulting pole
                    was also practised as an athletic feat. On a funeral monument of the time of
                    Nero in the museum at Mainz is the figure of a horseman on a saddle-cloth with
                    something resembling the pommel and cantle of a saddle, but the first saddle
                    proper is found in the so-called column of Theodosius at Constantinople (usually
                    ascribed to the end of the 4th century A.D., though it may be more than 100
                    years earlier), where two figures are riding on high-peaked saddles resting on
                    embroidered saddle-cloths. In medieval times the saddle was much like that of
                    the Oriental saddle of to-day with high peaks before and behind. In the military
                    saddle of the 14th and 15th century the high front parts of the saddle were
                    armoured and extended to protect the legs of the rider. The jousting saddle (cf.
                    the example in the Tower of London) becomes almost a box into which the rider is
                    fixed; the high cantle fits round the rider’s loins and when charging he lifted
                    himself into practically a standing position in the stirrups. The saddle for use
                    on the road or hunting was much like the Arab saddle of to-day, and similar
                    forms are in use in Europe and elsewhere where the British saddle has not been
                    adopted. Women rode astride or on a pillion behind a male rider. The side-saddle
                    is said to date from the end of the 12th century. For the harness of the ancient
                    draught horse see <hi rend="smallcaps">Chariot.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bibliography.</hi> —J. C. Ginzrot, <hi rend="italic">Wagen
                        u. Fahrwerke</hi> d. <hi rend="italic">Griechen u. Romer, &amp;amp;c.</hi>
                    (1817); Daremberg and Saglio's <hi rend="italic">Dict. des antiquités grecques
                        et rom., s.υυ.</hi> "Ephippium,” “ Frenum,” &amp;amp;c.; Viollet-le-Duc's
                        <hi rend="italic">Dict. rais. du mobilier français,</hi> and the works
                    referred to in the text. See also <hi rend="smallcaps">Driving, Riding</hi> and
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Horse.</hi> (C. <hi rend="smallcaps">We.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
