<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>part of the fire-box and body of the boiler, by screws two inches apart. The wooden covering on the fire-box is finished to ⅞ -⅛ thick, and is made fast to the boiler by two hoops ; and round the fire door it is lined with thin sheet iron under the hoops ; the sheets being 6 feet long, and 2 feet 3 inches broad, with a hole cut out for the furnace, and secured at the ends by screw nails 2 inches apart, to prevent the fire from burning the wood casing on the boiler. The casing on the barrel of the boiler is secured by four hoops, with a strip of brass under the fore-end hoop, about 2½ inches in breadth, to cover the ends of the lining and the rivet heads at the junction of the barrel of the boiler, and the smoke-box. The boiler is wrapped in at least three thicknesses of flannel all over.</p><p>The lagging on the boiler is put together with iron feathers I by ⅛ ; the boiler is covered over the lagging with thin sheet lead, about 3½ feet broad along the top of the barrel. The smoke-box is No. 7 wire guage thick, and the chimney is No. 13 wire guage. The cover on the lockup safety valve is of brass, secured to the boiler ; there is a brass frame round the door of the smoke-box, and a brass handle to the small door in the middle of the large one.</p><p>All the pins of the joints are of steel, and hardened when practicable, but if not, they are steeled and hardened, and the working parts of the engine, which are of iron, are case-hardened. In making the boilers, the sharp edges of the rivet holes are taken off on both sides, and the rivets and rivet heads made to correspond. The engines are furnished with a wooden guard, and two leather buffers stuffed with cotton flock; and there are a draw-bar, draw-pin, and loop in the centre of the wooden guard, to connect them to the tender. They have three water guage cocks, and a glass water guage, with a lamp stand ; also a whistle, and a number plate on each side of the boiler ; and they are furnished with a complete set of screw-keys.</p><p>All the screws in all the engines correspond, for which purpose, either master taps, or sets of stocks and dies, at the option of other makers, are furnished them by Mr. Bury. They receive two coats of paint, and are finished with two coats of the best varnish. They are guaranteed for one month, or 1000 miles, during which trial, no other work is allowed but the tightening of cotters, and the very best workmanship and materials that can be produced, are in all cases rigidly insisted on.</p><p>The framing of the tenders is of well-seasoned oak, or ash timber, thoroughly secured with iron knees and bolts, having an iron box, No. 7 wire guage thick, underneath, to carry the coke, which box is secured to the wooden frame. The tank contains 700 gallons of water. The wheels are of cast-iron, turned to receive a tire of either Bowling or Lowmoor iron, bored out to secure a perfect fit, and finished to l¼ inches thick. The axles are 3¼ inches in thickness, of the best hammered scrap iron ; and the journals are 2¼ inches in diameter, case-hardencd, with brass bushes and oil box.</p><p>The Steadiment for the axles consists of two plates, one outside, and the other inside the framing ; both of them being bolted through the framing, and secured together below, by a piece of iron between the plates for steadying the axle bushes. These are made completely parallel, and the bushes fitted into these so as to move up and down, but in no other direction. The tenders have buffers, a spring to which the load is attached, and also four springs by which they are supported, one over each oil box.</p><p>The tank is No. 10 wire guage thick, having two brass cocks or valves, and rod handles with bushes for the top of the rods ; also two copper pipes, 1¾ inches in diameter, for carrying water from the tender to the engine. The tender frame and tank have two coats of paint inside and out, and two coats of varnish. They are fitted up with a brake, and furnished with a complete tool box ; a wire sieve in the main hole of the tank to prevent dirt or water from getting into the tank ; and two Macintosh hose pipes, one to each suction piece, with the necessary connexion to attach them to the engine.</p><p>When water requires to be pumped from the tender into the boiler of the engine, previous to the starting of the train, it is the usual practice to run the engine backwards and forwards for a short distance, in order to work the force pumps. This increases the wear and tear both of the engine and the road, besides inducing a liability in a crowded station of running foul of something, if great care be not taken. The following contrivance will obviate the necessity of this inconvenient method of filling the boiler. A square pit should be sunk in some convenient part of the line, selected with reference to its intended use. This pit should be large enough to admit a pair of three-feet wheels fixed on an axle similar to the carriage wheels. There should be no flanges, and a part of the circumference Of these wheels should come up through the rails, which must be cut so as to admit them, additional chairs being put in to support the ends of the rails. This part of the circumference of the wheels thus becomes a part of the railway, the wheels being made to lock at pleasure ; but when the engine requires to pump water into the boiler, it must be brought with its driving wheels directly on those in the pit, and these latter being then unlocked, the steam is let gradually on, and the pumps worked as long as is found necessary to fill the boiler, without the engine advancing from the exact spot in which it was first placed, the only effect produced by the driving wheels of the engine, being to turn round the wheels fixed in the pit. When the boiler is filled, the pit wheels are locked, and the engine proceeds to the performance of her assigned duty. How much more advantageous this mode of filling the boiler is, will be readily seen, particularly when it is remembered that if engine-men are not looked well after, they will oil the driving wheels and the rails when in the engine-house, and then letting on the steam, fill their boiler by means of the wheels slipping round on the rails. We have often seen this carried to such an extent, that streams of sparks have been struck out by the attrition. When no better plan can be obtained, the engine should have one end lifted by screw-jacks, till the driving wheels are off the rails, and the steam may then be let on without any damage being done.</p><p>The Caliban engine, made by Sharp, Roberts, and Company, of Manchester, drew 80 tons up an inclination of 1 in 180, on the Grand Junction Railway, for 3.<hi rend="sup">1</hi>∣ miles, at 13¼ miles per hour, at a steam pressure of 50 lbs. per square inch, and with a consumption of coke of 480 lbs. The average of 14 trips of three quarters of a mile each, up 1 in 90, from Euston Square to Camden Town, on the London and Birmingham railway, with the great engine made by Robert Stephenson and Company to work the trains up the inclination till the fixed engine was ready, amounted to 15 miles an hour, with 70 tons, viz. 14 carriages and 148 passengers, at a steam pressure of 50 lbs. per square inch. The average of 12 trips of 24¾ miles, up 1 in 440, on the Grand Junction Railway, with six engines, three made by Robert Stephenson and Company, and three by Sharp, Roberts, and Company, was 23¾ miles per hour, with a weight of 58 tons. The coke consumed was 864 lbs., and the steam power 48 lbs. per square inch ; this coke, however, was very bad. The average of 14 trips of 23 miles, up 1 in 440, on the London and Birmingham line, with No. 16 engine, built by Mr. Hawthorn of Newcastle, was 22 miles an hour, with a gross weight, including the tender, of 70 tons. The coke consumed was 486 lbs., and the steam pressure 48. The engine No. 7, on the London and Birmingham line, built by Mr. Bury of Liverpool, went 10 miles in ten minutes, 3d October 1838, with only one cylinder working, namely, from Hampton to Birmingham, being for 4½ miles, up 1 in 660, 3⅙ miles, up1 in 1370 ; the rest of the way was level, and the time included the getting up and slacking down the speed.</p></body></text></TEI>