<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by the explaining away of such points in the argument op- posed to us,—and by other artifices belonging to the numerous class of Rhetorical Fallacies. In its passionate parts the peroration has, both in ancient and in modern times, prompted some of the noblest flights of human eloquence.</p><p>If Eloquence depended solely on Style, those lofty pretensions of rhetoricians which were alluded to in the first paragraph of this paper would be not merely excusable or plausible, but to a considerable extent justified by their results. The highest qualities of style indeed are emanations from the mind ; but many of its excellences may be attained by industrious practice, conducted in obedience to systematic rules. The expression may be feeble, because words, phrases, and sentences cannot be strong, unless the thoughts which they represent be strong likewise ; it may be wanting in precision, because this is another quality flowing essentially from the nature of the author’s conceptions ; and if ornament be introduced, it may be destitute of originality and liveliness, because no rules can confer either the power of felicitous invention or that of extensive and acute observation. But even in these very particulars, art, although weak, is not altogether powerless ; accuracy, or even strength of thinking, and closeness of observation, may be increased by sound precepts and active exercise, which, by thus improving the faculties of the intellect, will necessarily facilitate the expression of its thoughts by language. And, again, if a man can only be taught to apprehend distinctly the limits of the province within which his mind may act with advantage, and to adapt the character of his style to that of his natural powers, the rules of composition may suffice to render his style, if not positively good, at least negatively faultless.</p><p>But Style, instead of solely constituting eloquence, might, if we chose to court contradiction by stating a truth in the shape of a paradox, be even said to be no essential part of it.  It is an unavoidable inference from the principles which we have laid down, that all eloquence is relative. The harangues which a chief in the centre of Africa delivers to his fellow-savages, or by which a demagogue in religion or politics excites an uneducated mob, such as unfortunately may still be found in our country as well as in others, may be truly and powerfully eloquent, because fitted beyond all other discourses for convincing and impelling to action the persons on whose understanding and will they are designed to operate ; and yet, not only may these orations contain constant violations of all rules of style, except those few which are directly referable to the thought, but they may owe to such violations no mean part of their persuasive efficacy. This view, however, is stated solely for the purpose of guarding against error in our notions as to the place which style really holds as an element of eloquence. In all the applications of preceptive systems of the art in civilized and cultivated society, or, in other words, in all cases in which such preceptive systems can arise, the rules of style must be obeyed more or less closely, and the acquisition of them is indispensable for every student of rhetoric.</p><p>But the details of the subject cannot here be taught. Our plan is that of a mere outline, and in tilling it up we confine ourselves to an attempt to illustrate some of those points which bear most strongly on the mental laws of rhetorical belief. Those useful rules which affect style chiefly or essentially as such, may be satisfactorily learned from many works of different kinds, both in our own language, and in others, both ancient and modern. The principles of style in the classical tongues are not truths foreign to our own, but only truths which, always analogically useful, do in many instances hold as to all languages, while in some they cannot be applied to the tongues of modern Europe, without cautions and modifications : we may learn much from Aristotle, Quinctilian, Dionysius of Halicarnassus, and even from the later rhetoricians and critics, Greek as well as Latin. On English style we have many good works : Campbell, Blair, Karnes, and Whately, abound with valuable illustrations of the subject in its relation to rhetorical principles ; and of those treatises which are designed chiefly as manuals of style, without aiming at a general exposition of the philosophical principles of eloquence, more than one might be safely recommended. Of those works which have attained reputation in this latter class, none will be found so useful as one of the latest, Irving’s unpretending and excellent Elements of English Composition.</p><p>We may here confine ourselves almost to a simple enumeration of those Qualities of Style which are strictly Rhetorical, and which, availing ourselves of Whately’s extension of the analysis proposed by Campbell, we may reduce to three : Perspicuity, Vivacity, and Beauty.</p><p>The first quality is of course an indispensable requisite in compositions of every kind ; and the principles of rhetoric remind us, that, while style, in order to be perspicuous at all, must obey certain general laws, the quality is also in a very important sense relative to the knowledge and intellect of those whom the language is intended to instruct, convince, or persuade. The same statement which is abundantly perspicuous to one audience, may be quite unintelligible to another less informed. In the adaptation of style in this respect to different classes of readers and hearers, the student cannot be so much aided by any rules as by his own judgment and observation ; but in order to avoid, on the one hand, the obscurity which may arise from conciseness, and, on the other, the wearisomeness which inevitably attends prolixity, it has been recommended to repeat the thought and argument in several different forms, “ each in itself brief, but all together affording such an expansion of the sense to be conveyed, and so detaining the mind upon it, as the case may require.” “ Cicero among the ancients, and Burke among the modern writers, afford perhaps the most abundant practical exemplifications of this rule.” But, as we shall speedily discover that an overflow of figurative language is inconsistent with perspicuity in all circumstances, we must not be thus tempted to believe that the style which is least figurative is the most perspicuous. Illiterate audiences, in particular, are not only-pleased with figurative language, but may often by means of it be made to comprehend a principle, which would have remained perfectly dark to them if conveyed in abstract and unimaginative terms.</p><p>Vivacity of style is the quality by which it makes its appeal to the imagination, or, through that faculty, to the passions and other active powers. Independently of those considerations as to the number and arrangement of words, upon which we cannot here enter, Vivacity is chiefly produced by the use of figurative language, which critical and rhetorical writers have divided into two kinds, Tropes and Figures. It has been said by some writers of authority, that the distinction implied in these terms is of little importance, because, it is added, “ nothing can be built upon it in practice, nor can it always be clearly observed.” The language of the imagination and passions, however, does naturally fall into two classes, the characteristics of which correspond substantially with those assigned by the rhetoricians to their two divisions ; and the student of the principles of eloquence may find it worth while to recollect the distinction. In the former class, which one may consider as properly Tropes, taking the metaphor as an example, a word is used in a sense different from its usual and appropriate one. In the other class, composing the Figures, a word or sentence, without being either employed in a different sense from its usual one, or put into any unusual form, derives its figurative or exciting power merely from the fact, that the form of expression is not that which an unimpassioned mind would have used in the place where it occurs, but that</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>