<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>philosophy ; both because they run into each other imperceptibly at every point of the progression, and because the same proof, perhaps, does not appear to any two minds as involving exactly the same strength of evidence. Nevertheless there are in popular language some distinguishing words, of which rhetoric may advantageously avail itself. The two most ordinary and useful of these are, Plausibility and Probability, both of them wide words, but each marked in common use by its own essential and distinctive character. Probability, indeed, in the philosophical and proper sense, embraces all the degrees of moral evidence ; but in the popular meaning here adverted to, it imports a degree of evidence higher than that of plausibility. Plausibility is a faint degree of likelihood, whose essence Campbell, quite accurately as it should seem, has analysed thus. The hearer considers an argument as plausible which does not contradict his own experience, or that system of general truths which, more or less extensive in different minds, has been collected by every mind from particular facts remembered. If the argument goes farther than this point, it loses the character of plausibility, and acquires a higher rank, passing, in ordinary language, into the class of probabilities ; if it falls short, by contradicting any of our habitual conclusions, it is less than plausible, and utterly worthless towards effecting conviction. The only objection to the term plausibility arises from this ; that, on account of ordinary associations, it suggests to most minds an unfavourable impression, which does not necessarily or properly belong to the species of evidence it is here used to designate ; for, although a plausible proof must never be taken for more than it is worth, it may often do infinite service in preparing the way for others more convincing. Campbell has proposed to substitute for it the word verisimilitude, but his advice has not been followed. It has been observed by the same writer, that this quality of a non-contradiction of experience, is the essential condition of what in poetical invention is called truth to nature. We pronounce the characters in a poem to be well sustained if the acts ascribed to them are similar to those which we have seen such men perform in such circumstances ; and as the poet undertakes to prove nothing, we rest in the intellectual pleasure which the invention affords us. If a similar picture of character in action is laid before us, as a step towards convincing us that a certain act has really been done, we try the representation by the former test ; but then, if the argument holds good to the extent to which it professes to go, we retain our conviction of this faint antecedent probability, as an element to aid us in judging of the sufficiency of other proofs, if such shall afterwards be adduced. Arguments <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>  which deserve the name of probable, go farther than this, and rise gradually till they operate complete conviction. “ As far as any cause, popularly speaking, has a tendency to produce a certain effect, so far its existence is an argument for that of the effect- If the cause be fully su<hi rend="italic">fficient,</hi>  and no <hi rend="italic">impediments</hi>  intervene, the effect in question follows certainly ; and the nearer we approach to this, the stronger the argument.”</p><p>The class of Signs forms a very large numerical proportion of our materials in argumentative composition. It is satisfactorily analysed by Whately, whom we here follow closely in all our observations on it, venturing only on one point a silent dissent. “ As far as any circumstance is what may be called a <hi rend="italic">condition</hi>  of the existence of a certain effect or phenomenon, so far it may be inferred from the existence of that effect ; if it be a condition absolutely essential, the argument is of course demonstrative ; and the probability is the stronger in proportion as we approach to that case. Of this kind are the following arguments. A man is suspected as the perpetrator of a murder, from the circumstance of his clothes being bloody ; the murder being considered as, in a certain degree, a probable <hi rend="italic">condition</hi>  of that appearance; that is, it is presumed that his clothes would not</p><p><hi rend="italic">otherwise</hi>  have been bloody. Again, from the appearance of ice, we infer decidedly the existence of a temperature below the freezing point ; that temperature being an essential <hi rend="italic">condition</hi>  of the crystallization of water.”</p><p>Arguments which infer effect from cause having been ranked as our first branch, and examples, the third branch, being, as we shall immediately discover, incapable by themselves of leading to absolute moral conviction,—the class of signs must include both those proofs which from an admitted phenomenon infer its cause, and those which from the same datum infer a condition which is not the cause. And, first, as to those arguments which prove the existence of causes by that of their effects, it must be specially observed, that the cause “ is never so proved <hi rend="italic">so far forth as</hi>  it is a <hi rend="italic">cause,</hi>  but so far forth as it is a <hi rend="italic">condition,</hi>  or necessary circumstance.” This is far from being so shadowy a distinction as might be supposed ; it enters radically into the mode in which the mind is affected by the different methods of using causes and effects to prove each other. The proposition as it is here maintained, without involving, or tempting us to institute, any inroad into the debateable land of the philosophy of causation, is simply this : that my conviction of the existence of a fact, from my knowledge of another fact which is its effect, is exactly the same kind of conviction as I should derive of the same truth from my knowledge of any fact which was not an effect, but a simple condition, or other concomitant ; any difference in the strength of evidence in particular cases depends solely on the circumstances, and, as these vary, the one kind of proof may now be the stronger, and now the other. From the fact that Moscow was burned in the month of September 1812, we infer the existence of the city in the preceding month, because that previous existence, although no cause of the conflagration, in any sense of the word, is a condition, but for which the catastrophe could not have taken place ; and as the previous existence is a necessary condition, the conviction which the inference gives amounts to complete moral certainty ; but, from the same fact, as it is now stated, we can draw, as to the causes of it, no inferences whatever that amount to more than the weakest of all plausibilities, being just an enumeration of causes, by any of which it is possible the event may have been produced, though, with regard to most of them, we cannot pronounce any one to be more probable than the rest. On the other hand, if, when we have perused the writings of an author, our feelings and our critical judgment agree in declaring them to possess high and genuine eloquence, we infer at once the genius of the writer (the cause, or one of the concurring causes, of the excellence), and our inference is one of positive certainty, because we know genius to be a necessary condition, without which the work could not have possessed the merit it does : while, in the same case, on this naked enunciation of it, our inferences as to many of those conditions of the excellence, which are not in any sense causes, must be founded on plausibilities as weak as those described under the last example.</p><p>Of Signs, then, many are not causes. It is needless to illustrate this species of signs further by individual examples ; but it is important to observe, that some general classes of, arguments fall under this second division of signs. Of this sort is the Argument from Testimony, to which, if we were to embrace in our view any besides moral truths, we should have to add the argument from Calculation of Chances, on which so much rests in the science of natural theology. Both of these arguments are signs from which we infer conditions that are not causes. The argument from testimony has been thus analysed. “ The premise is the existence of the testimony ; the conclusion, the truth of what is attested ; which is considered as a <hi rend="italic">condition</hi>  of the testimony having been given ; since it is evident, that so far only as this is allowed (i. e. so far only as it is allowed that the testimony would not have been given had it not been true)</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>