<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“ une accord superflue,” which we have translated a redundant chord, has by others been rendered a chord extremely sharp, as in the translation of Rameau’s Principles of . Composition. Their nature will be best understood by a few examples, and an account of the number of tones, semitones, or lesser intervals, contained in each.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">second redundant</hi>  is composed of a major tone and a minor semitone, as from <hi rend="italic">fa</hi>  to <hi rend="italic">sol</hi>  sharp. Its proportion is as 64 to 75. The <hi rend="italic">third redundant</hi>  consists of two tones and a semitone, as <hi rend="italic">fa Ut</hi>  sharp. Its proportion is as 96 to 125. The <hi rend="italic">fourth redundant</hi>  is the same with the tritone.</p><p>From these examples compared with the same intervals in their natural state, the reader may form a general idea of what is meant by <hi rend="italic">redundant.</hi></p><p>REDUPLICATION of sounds in musical harmony. See the article Music, under section <hi rend="italic">Harmony.</hi></p><p>REE, Reis, or <hi rend="italic">Res,</hi>  a small Portuguese coin. See Jfo-<hi rend="italic">KEY- Table.</hi></p><p>REEF, a term in navigation. When there is a heavy gale of wind, the seamen commonly roll up part of the sail below, that by this means it may become the narrower, and not draw so much wind ; and this contracting or taking up the sail they call a <hi rend="italic">reef,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">reefing the sail.</hi>  So also, when a <hi rend="italic">top-mast is sprung,</hi>  as they call it, that is, when it is cracked, or almost broken in the cap, they cut off the lower piece that was nearly broken off, and setting the other part, now much shorter, in the step again, they call it a <hi rend="italic">reefed top-mast.</hi></p><p>REEF Island, a small island in the Eastern Seas, about fifty miles from the west coast of Sumatra, and called also Disastrous Island, from the number of shipwrecks which have taken place near it. Long. 101. 3. E. Lat. 4. S. It is also the name of a small island near the northern coast of the island of Celebes. Long. 122. 48. E. Lat. O. 8. N.</p><p>REEL, in the manufactories, a machine employed for the purpose of reeling. There are various kinds of reels ; some very simple, others very complex.</p><p>REELING, in the manufactories, the winding of silk, cotton, or the like, into a skain, or upon a button, to prevent its entangling. It is also used for the charging or discharging of bobbins or quills, to be employed in the manufacture of different stuffs, as thread, silk, cotton, and the like. Reeling is performed in different ways, and on different engines.</p><p>REEPHAM, a market-town of the county of Norfolk, in the hundred of Eynesford, 113 miles from London, and thirteen from Norwich. It was once much larger than at present, and had three churches. It stands on the river Eyne, and has a market, which is held on Saturday. The population amounted in 1801 to 284, in 1811 to 299, in 1821 to 345, and in 1831 to 452.</p><p>REES, a town of the Prussian government of Cleves, the capital of a circle of the same name, which extends over 166 square miles, comprehending seven cities and towns, thirty-seven villages, and 32,950 inhabitants. The town is situated on the river Rhine, and contains two churches, 470 houses, and 2800 inhabitants. Long. 6. 17. 14. E. Lat. 51. 45. 55. N.</p><p>REEVE, Clara, the ingenious authoress of <hi rend="italic">Tlie Old English Baron,</hi>  was the daughter of the Reverend William Reeve, rector of Freston, and of Kerton, in Suffolk, and perpetual curate of St Nicholas. Her mother’s maiden name was Smitllies, daughter of Mr Smithies, goldsmith and jeweller to George I. The father of Miss Reeve was “ an old Whig,” and from him she learned all that she knew ; he was her oracle, and used to make her readl the parliamentary debates whilst he smoked his pipe after supper. Under the same paternal tuition, she also read Rapin’s History of England, Cato’s Letters, the Greek and Roman histories, and Plutarch’s Lives, at an age when few people of either sex can read their own names. Mr Reeve, himself one of a family of eight children, had the same number of offspring ; and hence it is probable that Clara’s strong natural turn for study, rather than any degree of exclusive care which his partiality could bestow, enabled her to acquire such a stock of early information.</p><p>After the death of Mr Reeve, his widow resided in Colchester with three of his daughters ; and it was here that Clara first became an authoress, by translating from the original Latin Barclay’s fine old romance of Argenis, which was published in 1762, under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Phœnix.</hi>  It was not, however, until 1767, five years afterwards, that she produced her first and most distinguished work, which was published by Mr Dilly of the Poultry, under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Champion of Virtue.</hi>  The sum given for the copyright was only ten pounds ; but in the following year the work came to a second edition, and was then first called <hi rend="italic">Tlie Old English Baron,</hi>  for what reason we do not pretend to conjecture. This production is inscribed to Mrs Brigden, the daughter of Richardson, who is stated to have lent some assistance in the revision and correction of the work.</p><p>The success of The Old English Baron encouraged Miss Reeve to devote more of her leisure hours to literary composition, and accordingly she published in succession, The Two Mentors, The Progress of Romance, The Exile, The School for Widows, Plans of Education, and Memoirs of Sir Roger de Clarendon, a natural son of the Black Prince, with Anecdotes of many other eminent persons of the fourteenth century. To these works there remains to be added another, the interest of which turned upon supernatural appearances. In a preface to a subsequent edition of The Old English Baron, Miss Reeve informs the public that, in compliance with the suggestion of a friend, she had composed <hi rend="italic">Castle Connor,</hi>  an Irish story, in which apparitions were introduced. But the manuscript being intrusted to some careless or unfaithful person, fell aside, and was never recovered. The various novels produced by this lady are all marked by excellent good sense, pure morality, and a considerable command of those qualities requisite to constitute a good romance. They were, generally speaking, favourably received at the time ; but none of them took the same strong possession of the public mind as The Old English Baron, upon which the fame of the author may be considered as now exclusively rested, and by which alone 6he will be known to posterity.</p><p>Miss Reeve led a retired life, affording no materials for biography, until the beginning of December 1803, when she died at Ipswich, her native city, at the advanced age of seventy-eight years, and was buried in the churchyard of St Stephens, according to her particular direction. Such are the only particulars that have been collected concerning this accomplished and excellent woman ; and, in their simplicity, the reader may remark that of her life and her character. The following critical observations, confined entirely to her most celebrated work, which first established her fame, and upon which alone it will in all probability rest, are extracted from the biographical notice of Miss Reeve by Sir Walter Scott, to which we have also been in-* debted for the foregoing particulars of her life.</p><p>“ The authoress has herself informed us that The Old English Baron is the * literary offspring of The Castle of Otranto ;’ and she has obliged us by pointing out the different and more limited view which she had adopted, of the supernatural machinery employed by Horace Walpole. She condemns the latter for the extravagance of several of his conceptions; for the gigantic size of his sword and helmet; and for the violent fictions of a walking picture, and a skeleton in a hermit’s cowl. A ghost, she contends, to be admitted as an ingredient in romance, must behave himself like ghosts of sober demeanour, and subject himself to the common rules still preserved in grange and hall, as circumscribing beings of his description.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>