<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>We have here supposed <hi rend="italic">a —1,</hi>  or the inclination of the</p><p>tire of the wheel to = y ; but it is evident this must be such,</p><p>that no rubbing of the flange will be produced on any curve on the line. We obtain this from the equation</p><p>βeD</p><p><hi rend="sup">μ</hi>~ 2(r—e)'</p><p>We first establish the play between the rails. Allow this to be two inches, or that the flanges of the wheels in their regular position are 1 inch from the rails ; then <hi rend="italic">μ</hi>  must never be quite equal to 1 inch, and if we give to <hi rend="italic">r</hi>  in the last equation above, its numerical value for the worst curve on the line, and to <hi rend="italic">μ</hi>  its limit, a small quantity less than half the play of the wheels, we obtain the value of <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>  which we must use on that line, as follows :</p><p>_2<hi rend="sub">M</hi>(r + e)<hi rend="italic"><hi rend="sup">α</hi>~ eO '</hi></p><p>For instance, with half thc play = 1 inch, or ∙0833 feet and μ=0∙9 inches, or, 075 feet, we haveα=    j <hi rend="sup">=</hi> l0<hi rend="sup">-</hi>669</p><p>or the inclination of the cone =    =, of a foot ; observ-</p><p>10∙67</p><p>ing that if we have only one or two bad curves, we must examine whether we may not admit a little rubbing on them for a corresponding gain on the good ones. This investigation will shew how necessary it is that the play of the axles on the carriages should be as small ns can possibly be, or the effect of the coned wheels will be completely deranged. This is a matter which is much too little attended to in practice.</p><p>There is nothing in a railway which demands such serious attention as the stations, both as to their numbers, position, and the mode of constructing them. The number and situation will of course be mainly determined by the nature and extentof the surrounding population ; and the first step should be to get a good map of all the places within the sphere of the railway, and to mark upon it thc population of each place from the last parliamentary census ; bearing in mind, that taking, for the present, railway-travelling to be twice as fast at half the cost of coach travelling, that a very wide portion of country will receive the benefit of a long line. We have explained this before ; but that it may be perfectly understood, we shall shortly advert to it in a different shape.</p><p>For instance, suppose a line 100 miles long, and a person 50 miles at right angles to one end of it, who wants to go to the other end. If he travelled in a stage-coach along the hypothenuse of the triangle, he would go about 112 miles, say at 4d. per mile, his total cost would be L.l, 17s. 4d., and his time expended about 11¼ hours. On the contrary, if he came first to the terminus of the railway nearest him, and then went along the railway to the other terminus, he would have first 50 miles in a stage-coach at 4d., or 16s. 8d., with an expenditure of time equal to 5 hours, and then 100 miles by the railway at 2d., or 16s. 8d. more in 5 hours, the total time being 10 hours, and the total expense L.l, 13s. 4d., consequently he would save 4s. in money, and l¼ hours in time, by taking the longest road.</p><p>There is no doubt but that the greater the number of stations, the more the travelling will increase ; for it has always been hitherto found that the quick and cheap transit by a railway has not only increased the already existing traffic, but has actually created it where no traces could be found of it before. The nature of the produce, and the state of trade should also be taken into account in determining both the number and the situation of the stations.</p><p>The minor stations along the line may be divided into two classes. The first might consist of merely one room, serving for office and waiting-room, where nothingbutpassengersand</p><p>small parcels are sent either upor down. Such stations would do for small villages or points where only a limited traffic is' expected. We do not, however, recommend these, although they are used on several railways. All passengers pay alike, and they are therefore entitled to the same accommodation. The other class should be a house containing an office, waiting-room in common, or which is better, one for each class of passengers, ladies’ waiting-room, and two rooms for the inspector of police to reside in, a small office for the police, and a porter’s room. To this would have to be added, if water was required to be pumped, a steam-engine, and the requisite room for the engineer, a locomotive engine-house when necessary, and a covered space for holding spare carriages, trucks, horse-boxes, &amp;c., together with the requisite sheds, and an office for the goods department.</p><p>The entrance to the station should be protected from the weather, so that when carriages drive up, the passengers can alight under shelter, and there should be a platform next the railway, about the same height as the carriage floors, so that the passengers can walk into the railway-carriages without having to climb up the steps. Arrangements should be made, for the passengers who are going into the carriages to go all in upon one side, and those going out should get out from the other side ; for which purpose the entrance should be on one side of the railway, and the exit on the other side. A light roof should be thrown over both lines of rails and their stages ; in fact, the passengers should be entirely under cover from the time of leaving the vehicles which bring them to the station, till the time the train takcs them away. This occasions very little expense, and is a great addition both to health and to comfort.</p><p>For such a station two clerks would be required, one for passengers, parcels, and private carriages, tile other for goods. The mode of conducting the business we shall advert to in its proper place. An inspector, and about four policemen, with porters, according to the extent of the traffic, would probably be sufficient ; the whole should be well lighted up with gas, if it can be conveniently got; and it would much conduce to the comfort of the passengers, particularly ladies, if a decent female attended in the waiting-room, and had for sale pastry, biscuits, or sandwiches, with lemonade and ginger beer.</p><p>Great care should be taken at each out-station, that the following things can all be simultaneously performed, viz. First, that the train can be setting down passengers on the one side who are going to remain ; secondly, taking up passengers on the other side who are going on, and this on both lines; thirdly, that the engine can be taking in coke and water, and also raking her fire, for which purpose, a small coke store should be built close to the water crane, and an ash pit properly excavated in the requisite position ; and, lastly, that horses and private carriages can be in a situation to enable them to be attached to and detached from the train, at the same time as the other things enumerated above are being done. It will also be requisite, that the same care be taken at the goods’ station, but goods’ waggons should also be able to be attached to and detached from passengers’ trains, as they will often be useful, when the traffic in passengers runs a good deal one way, in completing the load of the engine, and economising the outlay in locomotive power.</p><p>To explain how this is to be done, let us suppose a line of railway running north and south, and that the east line of rails is that by which the trains arrive when going from north to south, and the west line of rails is that by which they arrive when going from south to north. For the east line of rails, the water crane should be so far to the south of the station, that with an average number of carriages in the train, when the tender is under the crane, the middle of the train is opposite the station house. The position of</p></body></text></TEI>