<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Whilst such machines as these can be turned out of hand, we may rest satisfied, although considerable improvements will doubtless be yet made, great difference of opinion still existing respecting the proper size of the driving wheels, which may either be made larger to give an increased speed, or keeping the speed the same, the piston may move with less velocity, either of which is a desideratum. The crank axle may also be done away with, as Dr. Church has exemplified in his engine, or by other means, or it may be cut out of solid iron. At present, too, the steam whistle, which can be heard several miles in a still day, is only made use of to warn persons of the time when the engine is approaching them. How much better would it be to have two of these with totally distinct sounds, one to be used on the arrival line, and the other on the departure line ? Each would then not only perform its present office as an alarm, but would form the most complete fog and night signal that could be desired, and would at all times, in the densest fog or the darkest night, give perfect notice whenever two engines approached each other, on which line each was travelling, and thus prevent almost the possibility of a collision.</p><p>There has so seldom been an instance of a locomotive engine boiler bursting, that it is perhaps hardly necessary to advert to such an accident. We know only of two amongst the tubular boilers. One happened lately on the Liverpool and Manchester Railway, apparently from the boiler being used till the rivets got so worn, that they were weaker than the tubes. The fire-box end of the boiler was blown out, and the above is the only way of accounting for it, as tubes must always bear a steam of 50 lbs. on the square inch. Of course when new, they bear considerably more, and their form gives every advantage to their strength, the pressure on them being inwards, whilst on the boiler it is outwards. It is also known that the safety valve was held down. The second instance occurred on the Brussels railroad. In this case, the lock-up safety valve was found to be loaded to 105 lbs. upon the square inch ; and it had also been screwed down more on one side than on the other. These valves are held down by a series of elliptical springs, which move on a guide rod passing through their centres. When they are not screwed down equally on both sides, their position becomes diagonal, and they jamb on the guide road instead of working easily, as they do when rightly managed. Safety, in all the usual cases, is insured by having a fusible plug on the top of the fire-box, composed of four parts lead and one part tin. This will melt before any danger can arise, and the steam will rush into the furnace. The late American experiments on this head may be consulted with advantage ; but the mystery has not yet been unravelled. We have had an open vat burst in Meux’s brewery ; and in two instances boilers have been suffered to get quite cold. The man-hole has then been opened, and a person has gone inside, but soon afterwards, in each instance, upon their introducing a lighted candle, explosions took place, and they were in both cases killed. Gas generated by boilers getting red hot, and absorbing the oxygen, has been supposed to be a leading cause ; this, however, is exceedingly doubtful. If such be the case, it might be well to try protecting them by means of another metal. It would also be a good thing to rotate the safety valve, which is locked up from the engine-man, by machinery, to prevent any improper adhesion, and by using a mercurial steam guage, nearly all blowing-off at the safety valve might be avoided, which now often amounts to one-fourth of the generated steam. The boiler tubes, as now made, are capable of running 30,000 miles. The want of adhesion so much talked of, is found to be nonsense, and if there had been any, it would only be necessary, as the writer of this article suggested several years ago, to connect a galvanic magnet with one or more of the axles, to act on the rails, by which means, with the addition of only a few pounds, an adhesion equivalent to the weight of two tons could be produced at each axle, being capable also of acting or not at a moment’s notice. But there is always found to be sufficient adhesion, except sometimes in foggy weather, at first starting ; when once in motion, the train acts as a fly-wheel. We have no hesitation in saying, that electro-magnetism will at no distant day compete with steam as a motive power, and successfully.</p><p>We are yet, however, very ignorant not only of the powers but even of the nature of steam. No one can satisfactorily prove whether it is a mechanical division of water, or a chemical decomposition. The currents which take place in water whilst it is heating, and which are reversed when it cools, are not yet taken sufficient advantage of, and there are many other facts which require examination. It is well known, that if we put on our bare hand, an iron kettle of water boiling rapidly we feel no sensation of heat, but the moment the ebulition ceases, we feel a gradually increasing warmth, which is greatest at the edge of the bottom. When the bottom, well cleaned, is placed almost in contact with the bulb of a thermometer, it will only raise it 8° or 10° in thirty seconds, or about 40° in five or six minutes, although the water, at the expiration of that time, will be at 90° higher. With an earthenware pot, the difference is very great, the thermometer rising 100° in thirty seconds, instead of 8° or 10°. A drop of water placed in a metal vessel, at a white heat, is very slowly converted into steam, whilst at a lower temperature its conversion is so rapid, as almost to resemble an explosion. At the high temperature, it will spin round, and will take nearly a minute to evaporate, during which time, if it be turned into the hand, it will barely feel warm.</p><p>The experiments made by the committee of the Franklin Institute of Pennsylvannia, are well worth consulting on these subjects. It is there shown, that a drop of water on polished copper, at the temperature of 445°, took 210 seconds before it was converted into vapour. It was evaporated in the smallest time, at a temperature of 292°, at which it took three seconds. But when the copper, instead of being highly polished, was highly oxidated, the temperature of maximum evaporation was at 348°, and the time required to convert the drop into steam only one-fourth of a second, or as 12 to 1 ; whilst in iron the temperature suffered but little variation, whatever was the condition of the metal, except it was very highly oxidated, the iron having its highest evaporating points in this case about 35° above copper in the same condition. The time varied nearly in the ratio of the conducting power of the metals, or about 2½ to 1, the copper requiring the least.</p><p>At 20° to 40° above the point of maximum vaporisation there is a perfect repulsion between the drop of water and the heated metal, the former rotating in all directions, without wetting the metal. When larger quantities of water were used, the point of maximum vaporisation was much higher ; which renders it evident that locomotive engines have yet to be considerably altered, before they can work at the greatest advantage. The same experiments shew, that water injected, either hot or cold, into an engine boiler, heated to bright redness, produced no hydrogen, but that the resulting gas was nothing more than atmospherical air, deprived by the heated metal of more or less of its oxygen ; that is to say, nitrogen more or less pure, according to the quantity of oxygen which has been absorbed.</p><p>The nature of the most advantageous alloys for the fusible plugs of locomotive or other high-pressure boilers, has been carefully examined by the same committee, and the following table is deduced from their observations, tile stationary point being that of congelation.</p><p>The proportions are by weight throughout. The stationary points are not given for the ten latter alloys, but the decrease in temperature by which they became “hard solid,” on the surface we presume, was as follows, viz. 25°, 24°, 20½°,</p></body></text></TEI>