<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The sliding rail, which forms the communication from one line of rails to the other, and which is moved by an eccentric, turned by a lever handle, should have, on the other side of the line, an iron rod from the rail, going into a box at its end with a pinion on it. This pinioned end of the rod turns a rack when the sliding rail is moved, which rack is contained in the box, and is fixed to a vertical rod, moveable in an upright post, similar to a lamp post, through the top of which, about four feet in height, the upper end of the rod comes out for about six inches, and is in this part made square. On this square part there is put a lamp by night, to shew a white light when the points are right, and a red one when they are wrong ; so that whenever the sliding rail is moved, it of necessity turns the light round, and cannot fail to place the different colours in front of the line of rails to which the signal is meant to apply.</p><p>In the day time the lamp is removed from the square, which, however, is not necessary, and the same signal is made visible by two circular hoops covered with canvass, one being painted red and the other white, and one being fixed on the top of the other at right angles to it ; or the hoops may be one inside the other, at the same height and at right angles, nothing more being necessary than that the signal should be such that when combined in this way, the sliding rail can never move without the signal also moving, which should shew white when the points are right, and red when they are wrong. These things, however, will never be properly correct till the engine itself is made to turn the points, which has often been tried, and is considered as having tailed, but may certainly be done with ease and effect.</p><p>Self-acting alarms, with gong-shaped bells standing upright and fixed about twelve feet high to a wall, should be supplied to each station, and they should be wound up by men stationed at them, who may also act as policemen. These alarms are for the purpose of giving notice to the station-people of the arrival of a train. Two minutes are sufficient time in ordinary cases, and, with active men, one would suffice, and proper regulations must be established to ensure this space of time. On the train arriving at the proper spot, the man stationed at the alarm pulls a trigger, which allows a weight to descend. This turns a wheel, and this wheel works a pinion, to which is attached an eccentric, which gives motion to the clapper from side to side, and the alarm is struck by the hammer in the usual way, the man stationed at it being at liberty to attend to any other business the instant he has pulled the string. A large station-bell is also useful to summon all the persons to their posts at unusual times, in order to receive any unexpected trains, and for many other reasons. A bell should also run from the station office at the out-stations, to summon one or more porters inside the office.</p><p>A good means of preventing accidents would be, to have the engine-man in the front of the engine. If any thingcould ensure care, this would, the generality of engine-men being quite foolhardy ; a defect which will never be remedied till we have a distinct class of men educated and brought up for engine-men from their youth, to whom should be given such a salary as would bring in young men Ofrespectability.</p><p>In Plate CCCCXXV, fig. 3, we have given a plan of an invalid carriage, capable of containing four invalids and their four attendants, (α, <hi rend="italic">a)</hi>  are the seats for the passengers, one on each side of the firεt and second bodies of the carriage being for the invalid, and the opposite one, lengthways of the carriage, being for the attendants When the invalid wishes for the use of the closet, he comes out by the door (Z&gt;) into the middle part of the coach (&lt;∕), which is a gallery with a raised roof, as in fig. 2. There are three portable water-closets <hi rend="italic">(c)</hi>  in this carriage, or the middle one, if thought more desirable, may be merely an urinal ; the centre one, to whatever purpose it may be converted, is arrived at from the gallery by the door (c), and the right and left-hand clo-</p><p>VOL. XIX.</p><p>sets by the doors <hi rend="italic">(Jg) (fg)</hi>  respectively. The ventilation here would be very perfect, and no inconvenience whatever' could arise to any one of the passengers. An attendant belonging to the railway company could attend on all the passengers remaining in the gallery <hi rend="italic">(d)</hi>  till his assistance was required, for which purpose a bell might be hung with pulls in each compartment. By this arrangement double the number of invalids could in each case be accommodated with a passage.</p><p>The following are the engines in use on the London and j Birmingham railway, and which were made by Mr. Bury oft Liverpool. The description here given applies to both thef passenger and goods’ engines, except when otherwise stated.</p><p>The two cylinders are to have an l8-inch stroke, those of the passenger engines being 12 inches, and the goods’ engines 13 inches in diameter, with single slide valves, brass spring pistons, and cast iron packing ; the cover of each cylinder having one oil.cup., The boilers are made of the best YorkshireplatesjeitherBowlingorLowmoor. The fire-boxes are of the same material, and are welded so as not to have the rivets or lap exposed immediately to the action of the fire. They are 3-8ths of an inch thick, the back plates half an inch, the outside of the fire-box and the backplate 3-8ths of an inch, and the rest of the boiler <hi rend="sub">1</hi>⅞ths of an inch. Full-sized drawings are furnished to shew how the plates are to be worked ; the plate for the tubes at the smoke-box end is half an inch thick, and a lead plug, 5-8ths of an inch in diameter, is riveted in the crown of the fire-box.</p><p>The tubes are two inches indiameterinside,andare secured with steel hoops at the fire-box end, and iron hoops at the chimney end. These hoops are made to a given guage ; and the tubes are of the best rolled brass, No. 14 wire guage thick ; the arrangement as well as the exact size of the tubes being regulated by a template.</p><p>The engines have four wheels ; those for the passengers are 5½ and 4 feet in diameter, and those for the goods are each pair 5 feet in diameter. Each wheel has a cast iron centre ; and the spokes are of wrought iron, accurately fitted into the nave. Thetireconsists of two thicknesses, the inner being 3-4 ths of an inch when finished, of the best Staffordshire iron, well secured to the end of the spokes by riveting, the ends of the spokes having been previously turned in their exact position. The outside tire is made of the very best Bowling or Lowmoor iron Igths inches thick when finished. When the outside of the inner tire has been well riveted to the spokes it is turned ; and the inside of the outer tire having been accurately bored, so as to secure a perfect fit, it is then shrunk on, and the outside turned and finished. The naves are bored out, and the axles turned to fit ; they are secured on by two steel keys, one inch square, at right angles with each other. The goods’ engine wheels are connected on the outside by a rod, with a ball pin at one end, and a parallel pin at the other. These engines have also a damper to their blast pipe.</p><p>The crank axles are made from Backbarrow iron, cut out of solid blocks, and finished according to full-sized drawings. The straight axles are made of the very best scrap iron. The framing of the engine is of wrought iron accurately fitted. There is one pump attached to each cross-head, and made of good tough brass, the suction pieces being connected by Macintosh hose pipes, with screw coupling joints next the engine. The eccentrics are fixed on the crank axles in the mode shewn by drawings. The steam and exhausting pipes are of copper, No. 12 wire guage in thickness. When these engines are made by other persons, templates and full-sized working drawings are given out, from which no deviation whatever is allowed without Mr. Bury’s approbation, so as to secure all parts of the engines matching each other.</p><p>The top of the fire-box has a copper cover, No. 16 wire guage tllick, secured to the wooden covering on the lower</p></body></text></TEI>