<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>be canvassed for, and the men who would take the most pains to get it, would be just those least suitable for it.</p><p>It will be readily seen, also, that under such a triumvirate no really good officer could act. The perpetual meddling with matters they know little about, the jealousy of their authority, and the necessity to be busy in order to give a colour to the notion that they do work, which would inevitably belong to such a body, would disgust an officer who knew his duty and wished to do it, and they would be left to perform the business w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ith none but subordinates. So far, then, from attaining the advantage contended for, a triumvirate committee of management constituted on the above plan, would tend to greater evils than those sought to be remedied by it. The old Navy board, abolished by Sir James Graham, is a case in point : this board was an executive one, and yet subordinate to the admiralty, and the natural consequence followed ;; they were continually working against the orders they received from the superior board, in order to carry out their own plans, not openly, but covertly ; there was, in fact, a constant under current of opposition, from which the business of the country notoriously suffered.</p><p>If, indeed, the proprietors of any railway would agree to invest the whole power of management in three commissioners, chosen from the country at large, as the fittest men to be found, making them responsible to the proprietors assembled in general meeting, and assimilating this triumvirate as nearly as possible to a government board, more favourable results might be anticipated than from any other plan ; but how should any company get three paid commissioners, who are not proprietors, to look sufficiently closely to the economy, out of which a good dividend should arise ?</p><p>The conclusion, then, is, that the present system of direction is, on the whole, the most suitable for managing a concern, whose nature is commercial, and the end of which is the realising of a profit to the proprietors, upon a money investment. A very important principle, however, is too much lost sight of in the composition of boards of directors. The practice is, for the same persons to be selected year after year, till all sense of responsibility to the constituent body is lost, and the board becomes an oligarchy, of a spirit akin to the old self-elected municipal corporations, the members losing year by year their interest and sympathy in the views and feelings of their constituents, and yet prone to consider them as identical with their own.</p><p>For this the appropriate remedy is, periodically a new infusion into the direction from the body of the proprietors, and for w+ich parliament has in most cases provided, by requiring a certain portion of directors to retire every year. If the proprietors give common attention at their general meetings, and are careful to select for directors the fittest men, not allowing the re-election of retiring directors to take place, as a matter of course, they will find their interests as well secured under the system recommended, as they are likely to be under any other, namely, one general board and an efficient executive officer. We should always recommend one thing, which is, that the half-yearly reports should be printed and sent to the proprietors, at least a fortnight before the general meeting.</p><p>If we look back at the rapid progress which we have made <hi rend="sup">,</hi>in the science of locomotion during the last half-dozen years, and at the degree of comfort and accommodation ' which, in conjunction with rapidity of transport, have been afforded to the public, at in most cases so very moderate a cost, the strides by which we have attained our present advanced position, are certainly sufficiently gigantic ; but if we look forward, it requires but little of the gift of divination to perceive, that in a very few' years more, a still greater change will take place, more particularly in the essential article of comfort. In conducting a mode of transit so essentially new, and in which all our previous machines and appliances had to be completely reorganized, and numerous inventions of almost every kind were to be produced at a moment’s call, to meet the various difficulties and wants which were continually arising out of such a novel mode of conducting the business of travelling in what may be called the wholesale w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ay, it has been singularly fortunate, that in almost every instance, the various railway companies have kept on the safe side, that is to say, they have not done too much. They have erred on the best side they could commit an error on ; they have been too cautious. It seems as if it required a certain time merely to travel at twenty miles an hour, and let the mind sober down a little before much else could be attempted. This feeling may now be rapidly expected to give way, and we shall find that as confidence is acquired, all the requisite arrangements will become consolidated in much more perfect and improved forms.</p><p>There is nothing now which ought to be more attended to by railway companies, than keeping their fares down ; and this has in most instances been very much neglected. When parties Jlossesssuch a complete monojκ&gt;ly as a railway, they should be particularly careful not to shew it. The expenses in many instances are certainly very great, and the companies have much to suffer in their progress through Parliament, and the rough grinding they have generally received from the rapaciousness of landowners. Accidents, too, must happen, estimates will be exceeded, and these sources of expenditure must be met by a corresponding rate of price ; but when the railways are made, the feeling seems to be too general amongst some of these proprietors, that this is the moment for making reprisals ujιon the public for all losses, vexations, mishaps and mistakes.</p><p>In some cases railways have charged more for the carriage of passengers than the stages or mails did, trusting to beat them on the question of time only. In part the receipts are great ; a certain sum must be set aside for a good dividend, and the rest is to be spent somehow or other. The same thing is observable in the statistics of the road trusts, many of them largely in debt, yet Sjiending their money on fancied improvements, instead of getting out of debt, and then lowering the tolls.</p><p>The effect of this on travelling is fully shewn in the report of the Irish Railway Commission. For instance, the travellers from Brussels to Antwerji by railway in the year 1836 were 872,893, whereas those on the Liverjiool and Manchester Railway for the same year were only 522,991, being the largest number for any year since the opening. Now, the populationofBrussels, Antwerp, and Mechlin was 209,200, whilst that of Liverpool, Manchester, and Warrington was 486,812, considerably more than double, or the ratio of population was as 2∙327 to 1, whilst that of the travelling was only as ∙599 to 1. We must seek for the solution of this problem in the respective fares of the two companies. In the Liverpool and Manchester Railway, Mr. Pambour states, that there are 13 first-class trains to 16 second-class ; and as the last class hold most Jiassengers, suppose we omit the</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">.<hi rend="sub">1</hi>    .    13×5∙5s.+ 16 ×4s.</hi>    135-5    . -,<hi rend="sub">n4</hi>  ...</p><p>mails, and say---=—^-=4∙6724 shil</p><p>lings, the average fare. We have no means of ascertaining the numbers on the Brussels railway, but if we take the dearest and cheapest, and compare them in the same ratio</p><p>as we did the others, we shall have --</p><p>~y</p><p>= -θ^Jθ-=2 francs 23 cents per passenger on the average,</p><p>or about 1∙784 shillings, or 4s. 8d. in the one case, and Is. 9¼d. in the other, or, allowing for the value of money in the two countries, about double the price ; and this double</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>