<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>The Saurian order of reptiles was included by Linnæus under two genera, Dhaco and Lacerta. The latter has been greatly subdivided, in accordance with the number of the feet, the form of the tongue, tail, and scales ; and the formation of several separate families has resulted from the consideration of these important features. None of the saurian reptiles are venomous, although the bite of several of the larger kinds is to be avoided rather than otherwise. They all appear to be what may be called carnivorous ; that is, they feed on living prey. Many assume the torpid state during the colder seasons of the year ; but in their more active condition they affect, according to the species, a great diversity of situation ; some haunting obscure and humid places, others rejoicing in a dry and sandy soil, exposed to the influence of the most radiant sun. Several are ■  aquatic ; while many climb trees, or, avoiding “ leafy umbrage,” seek the surface of exposed and barren rocks. Their form and outward adornment are as varied as their habits. Some are remarkable for beauty of shape and brilliancy of colour, while others present a repulsive aspect and a lurid hue. Many are extremely small, entirely innocent, and naturally familiar and confiding in their mode of life ; others are of gigantic size, and distrustful and dangerous in their disposition. How great the"difference between the beautiful, bright-eyed lizard, which suns itself beside a cottage window, and the huge cayman of America, stretched like a blackened log along the desolate shore of some forsaken</p><p>river !</p><p>FAMILY I.—CR0C0DILIDÆ. CROCODILES IN GENERAL.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Crocodilidœ</hi>  take the first place in the Saurian order, a distinction to which they are well entitled from their great magnitude and strength, and a ferocity which has obtained for them the appellation of the tyrants of the fresh waters, both in the old and new world. They often attain the size of ten and twelve feet, frequently that of fifteen and twenty, and, more rarely, even that of twenty-five and thirty. Inhabiting the margins of the mighty streams of tropical climates, they are the terror of all who approach them ; they prey upon every animal which comes within their reach ; and man himself is not free from their attacks, for instances are by no means rare, both in ancient and modern times, of their suddenly seizing upon human beings, and carrying them off to their watery haunts. Hence these formidable animals are never witnessed, especially in temperate climates, but with the deepest interest. In the year 58 before the common era, the edile Scaurus exhibited at Rome five crocodiles from the Nile ; on another occasion, Strabo mentions that the inhabitants of Denderah brought many to the great capital of the world ; but the most astonishing spectacle of this sort ever witnessed was when the Emperor Augustus caused the Flavinian Circus to be filled with water, and there displayed thirty-six crocodiles, which were killed by an equal number of men accustomed to fight with these monsters. Popular curiosity continues unabated; and the intimate connection of the creatures in question with geological investigations has more recently conferred upon them a very different but not less important interest.</p><p>The Crocodilidœ form an exceedingly natural group, closely associated by many common characters, of which the following are the most striking. They all attain a great size.</p><p>Their tail is compressed laterally. The fore-feet have five toes ; the hind four, the three internal of which are furnished with nails, but all of them are more or less united by membranes. There is a single row of teeth in each jaw. The tongue is fleshy, flat, and attached by nearly the whole of its margin, a circumstance which led the ancients to believe that crocodiles were destitute of this member. The back and tail are covered with great scales or plates, which are often pointed in their centre ; the scales on the abdomen are not so thick and strong.</p><p>The nostrils of these amphibious creatures open at the end of their snout by two small apertures, which shut with valves. The lower jaw is prolonged behind the cranium, which gives the appearance of motion to the upper jaw when the mouth is opened, an idea entertained by the ancients. @@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Their external ears are shut at will by two fleshy lips ; their eye has three eyelids, two horizontal, like our own, and the third, a membrana nictitans, capable of being drawn from within outwards over the whole front of the globe. Beneath the lower jaw, on either side, is a gland, whose duct opens by a small slit a little within the lower edge of the jaw ; it secretes an unctuous matter of a strong musky smell, and is supposed by Mr Bell<hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans. </hi>1827) to be a bait for attracting fish towards the sides of the mouth. This gland, with others of a like nature situated elsewhere, confers a smell which pervades the whole animal. The vertebræ are to the number of sixty ; seven are cervical, and these are so connected with each other by bony processes that they impede lateral movements, so that it is difficult for the animal to change its direction; and hence, when a person is pursued, he may easily escape by turning. Of all the Saurians, they are the only ones which are destitute of clavicles. Besides the ordinary supply of ribs, they have some which protect the abdomen without ascending to the spine. Their lungs do not descend into the abdomen, as in other reptiles of their order ; and this, with their heart of three cavities, where the blood from the lungs does not mix with that from the body so freely as in the rest of the Reptilia, associates them somewhat nearer to warmblooded animals.</p><p>It would be interesting, did space permit, to enlarge upon these physiological details. It is not a little curious, that in the animals belonging to this group, two openings are found, leading from the surface to the internal cavity of the abdomen, a structure similar to that which prevails in a few animals further down the scale. M. Geoffroy St Hilaire supposes that the superior energy of the crocodile in water is due to this penetration of that fluid, and the consequent conversion of the peritoneum into an additional respiratory surface. Another singular circumstance is, that these animals, as in some higher up the scale, are in the habit of swallowing great stones. An officer in the Colombian navy, who mentions this, tells us, that being somewhat incredulous on the point, he was satisfied of the fact by Bolivar, who, in order to convince him, shot several alligators with his rifle, and in the stomachs of all of them were found stones varying in weight according to the size of the animal. The largest killed was about seventeen feet in length, and had within him a stone weighing from sixty to seventy pounds. Upon their dispositions and habits we cannot greatly dilate.</p><p>In relation to the geographical distribution of the Croco-dilidæ, we may here remark, that they are entirely foreign to Europe, and do not occur in New Holland, but are else-</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> The peculiar structure of the jaws, and the nature of their movement, among these reptiles, have formed the subject of frequent argument. The fact, or rather the knowledge of it, although controverted by Perrault and Duverney, is as old as the time of Herodotus ; and Aristotle asserts that they can move both jaws : x,,βa∕cι,w, «ΰτ» vw,<hi rend="italic">σ</hi><hi rend="italic">∣</hi><hi rend="italic">uγοvsη. </hi><hi rend="sup">"</hi>  Enfin, nous reviendrons encore sur la circonstance, tout-k-fait particulière, qui permet k la mâchoire supérieure, ou plutôt à toute la masse supérieure de la tête, de s’élever en bascule, et de se mouvoir ainsi sur la mâchoire inférieure quand celle-ci repose sur le terrain ou sur un plan fixé.”<hi rend="italic">(Erpitologit Giniralt,</hi>  iii. 2δ.) See also <hi rend="italic">Annales du Mus.</hi>  ii. 38.</p></body></text></TEI>