<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>nïus, a creature of the pope, and John Agricola, a native of Ayselben<hi rend="sub">1</hi> to draw up a formulary which might serve as a rule of faith and worship, till the council should be assembled. But as this was only a temporary expedient, and had not the force of a permanent or perpetual institution, it thence obtained the name of the Interim.</p><p>■  This project of Charles was formed partly with a design to vent his resentment against the pope, and partly to answer other political purposes. It contained all the essential doctrines of the Church of Rome, though considerably softened by the artful terms which were employed, and which were quite different from those employed before and after this period by the council of Trent. There was even an affected ambiguity in many of the expressions, which made them susceptible of different senses, and applicable to the sentiments of both communions. The consequence of all this was, that the imperial formulary was reprobated by both parties. However, it was promulgated with great solemnity by thc emperor at Augsburg. The Elector of Mentz, without even asking the opinion of the princes present, gave a sanction to this formulary, as if he had been commissioned to represent the whole diet. Many remained silent through fear, and that silence was interpreted as a tacit consent. Some who had the courage to oppose it, were reduced by force of arms ; and the most deplorable scenes of bloodshed and violence were enacted throughout the whole empire. Maurice, elector of Saxony, who had hitherto kept neutral, now assembled the whole of his nobility and clergy, in order to deliberate on this critical affair. At the head of the latter was Melancthon, whose , word was respected as a law amongst the Protestants. But this man had not the courage of Luther, and was therefore on all occasions ready to make concessions, and to propose schemes of accommodation. In the present case he gave it as his opinion, that the whole of the book called Interim could not by any means be adopted by the Protestants ; but at the same time he declared, that he saw no reason why this book might not be approved, adopted, and received, as an authoritative rule in things that did not relate to the essential parts of religion, and which he accounted indifferent. But this scheme, instead of cementing the differences, rendered them worse than ever ; and produced a division amongst the Protestants themselves, which might have overthrown the Reformation entirely, if the emperor</p><p>and the pope had seized the opportunity.</p><p>In the year 1549, Pope Paul III. died, and was suc</p><p>ceeded by Julius III. who, at the repeated solicitations of the emperor, consented to re-assemble the council of Trent. A diet was again held at Augsburg under the cannon of the imperial army, and Charles laid the matter before the princes of the empire. Most of those present gave their consent to it, and amongst the rest Maurice elector of Saxony, who consented on the following conditions, namely, that the points of doctrine which had already been decided there should be re-examined ; that this examination should be made in presence of the Protestant divines ; that the Saxon Protestants should have the liberty of voting as well as of deliberating in the council ; and that the pope should not pretend to preside in that assembly, either in person or by his legatees. This declaration of Maurice was read in the diet, and his deputies insisted upon its being entered into the registers, which the Archbishop of Mentz obstinately refused. This diet was concluded in the year 1551 ; and, at its breaking up, the emperor desired the assembled princes and states to prepare all things for the approaching council, and promised to use his utmost endeavours to procure moderation and harmony, impartiality and charity, in the transactions of that assembly.</p><p>On the breaking up of the diet, the Protestants took such steps as they thought most proper for their own safety. The Saxons employed Melancthon, and the Wurtembergers</p><p>Brcngius, to draw up confessions of faith to be laid before the new council. The Saxon divines, however, proceeded no farther than Nuremberg, having received secret orders from Maurice to stop there ; for the elector, perceiving that Charles had formed designs against the liberties of the German princes, resolved to take the most effectual measures for at once crushing his ambition. He therefore entered with the utmost secrecy and expedition into an alliance with the king of France and several of the German princes, for the security of the rights and liberties of the empire ; after which, having assembled a powerful army in 1552, he marched against the emperor, who lay with a handful of troops at Inspruck, expecting no attack from any quarter. By this sudden and unforeseen accident Charles was so much dispirited, that he was willing to make peace almost on any terms. The consequence was, that he concluded a treaty at Passau, which by the Protestants is considered as the basis of their religious liberty. By the first three articles of this treaty, it was agreed that Maurice and the confederates should lay down their arms, and lend their troops to Ferdinand to assist him against the Turks, and that the Landgrave of Hesse should be set at liberty. By the fourth it was agreed that the rule of faith called the Interim should be considered as null &lt;ind void ; that the contending parties should enjoy the free and undisturbed exercise of their religion, until a diet should be assembled to determine amicably the present disputes, which diet was to meet in the space of six months ; and that this religious liberty should continue always, in case it should be found impossible to come to an uniformity in doctrine and worship. It was also determined, that all those who had suffered banishment, or any other calamity, on account of their having been concerned in the league or war of Smalcald, should be reinstated in their privileges, possessions, and employments; that the imperial chamber at Spiresshouldbe open to the Protestants as well as to the Catholics ; and that there should always be a certain number of Lutherans in that high court. To this peace Albert, marquis of Brandenburg, refused to subscribe, and continued the war against the Roman Catholics, committing such ravages in the empire that a confederacy was at last formed against him. At the head of this conspiracy was Maurice, elector of Saxony, who died of a wound received in a battle fought in 1553.</p><p>The assembling of the diet promised by Charles was delayed by various incidents ; however, it met at Augsburg in 1555, where it was opened by Ferdinand in name of the emperor, and terminated those deplorable calamities which had so long desolated the empire. After various debates, the following acts were passed, on the 25th of September, viz. That the Protestants who followed the Confession of Augsburg should be for the future considered as entirely free from the jurisdiction of the Roman pontiff, and from the authority and superintendence of the bishops ; that they were left at perfect liberty to enact laws for themselves relating to their religious sentiments, discipline, and worship ; that all the inhabitants of the German empire should be allowed to judge for themselves in religious matters, and to join that church whose doctrine and worship they thought the purest and most consonant to the spirit of true Christianity ; and that all those who should injure or persecute any person under religious pretences, and on account of their opinions, should be declared and proceeded against as public enemies of the empire, invaders of its liberty, and disturbers of its peace.</p><p>Thus was the Reformation established in many parts of the German empire, where it continues to this day ; nor have the efforts of the Catholic powers at any time been able to suppress it, or even to prevent it from gaining ground. It was not, however, in Germany alone that a reformation of religion took place. About the same time almost all the kingdoms of Europe began to open their eyes to the truth.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>