<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Table IV. shews the effect of cheaper blocks on the total cost at each length of bearing ; it begins at 7s. per block, and increases 5¼d.or <hi rend="sub">5</hi>⅛th, for each 3 inch esof increase in the length of the rail. The price of rails will never materially differ in any part of England, the freight being the principal variable quantity, but the price of blocks will alter in a very great degree, and the effect of this may be shewn ; take, for example, 2s. 8d. as the price of one for a two-feet bearing, and we know they have been procured cheaper ; adding to this, as we have done before, 2s. for the other items connected with the block, we get 4s. 8d. as the price of a block complete, and the price of the rail being 3s. 4d., the total price is 8s. per rail, or l2s. per yard. In the same way we have l2s. 6d. per yard at 2¼-feet bearings ; 13s. ld. at 2½ feet; 13s. 7d. at 2¾ feet; l4s. 2d. at 3 feet; and 18s. lld. at 5 feet ; hence in a railway 31 miles long, we shall find the saving, by having the blocks at two feet apart, L.75,293, viz.</p><p>31 miles at 5 feet,..............L.206,237</p><p>„    „    2 feet,................130,944</p><p>L.75,293</p><p>And as an useful approximation to this calculation, we may take each farthing per yard increase of cost in the total price per yard of single rail, to give L.7∙3333 per mile of double line, or in the above instance, there being 332 farthings between 12s. and 18s. lld., we have 7∙3333 × 332 × 3l = L.75,474.</p><p>As we are obliged to place our supports close together, to get a minimum cost when the blocks are less in price than the cost we first assumed, so we shall find that when greater, we must increase their distance. For instance, if a block for a two-feet bearing costs 9s., the cost per yard of block and rail complete will be l8s. 6d. ; at 2¼ feet, 18s.4½d. and at 2½ feet, 18s. 4¾d., the minimum being between 2¼ and 2½ feet.</p><p>We have next to see what will be the effect when the rail and block are both either greater or less than in Table I. This divides itself into three branches ; first, when they decrease or increase in an equal ratio ; secondly, when the rail decreases or increases in a greater ratio than the block ; and, thirdly, when the block decreases and increases in a greater ratio than the rail.</p><p>In the first case, the ratio of the price per yard will remain evidently the same as in Table I. Thus, if both rail and block are reduced in price ⅙th, we shall have at 2 feet, the price per yard, l4s. l∙875d.; at 2¼ feet, 14s. l∙66d. per yard ; and at 2½ feet, 14s. 2∙4d. ; hence the minimum is as before at about 2 feet 2 inches, and the same will hold under any other increase or decrease, the ratio in rail and block being equal.</p><p>For the second case, when the rail decreases in price in a greater ratio than the block, Table V. shews the corresponding effect, and the minimum will be found again at about 2 feet 2 inches, for at that distance we have 44 lbs. for the weight of the rail per yard, or <hi rend="italic">32∙S67</hi>  lbs. for the weight per rail, which at l¼d. per lb. is 40∙334d. ; for the block, if <hi rend="sup">,</hi>25 of a foot, increases the price 5¼d., then ∙2 of a foot will increase it 4∙2d., which added to 84d., the price at 2 feet, gives 88∙2d. for 2∙2 feet. Hence the total price of rail and block is l0s. 8½d., or 14s. 7<hi rend="sup">-</hi>27d. per yard, which is rather less than at 2¼ feet.</p><p>It will be found, in like manner, that the effect of an increase of price in the same ratio will not affect the minimum ; for example, with an increase of ⅙th in the price of the rail, and ⅙th in the price of the block, we have at 2 feet the rail 3s. 10∙666d., the block 9s. ; total, 12s. 10∙666d., or 19s. 4d. per yard. With 2¼ feet, the rail will be 59'065d., the block ll4∙75d. ; total, l4s. 5'815d., or per yard, 19s∙ 3¾d. With 2½ feet the rail will be 72 9l5d., the block 121∙5d. ; total, l6s. 2½d., or per yard l9s. 5∙299d. ; and with 2∙2 feet, we have the rail 56∙466d., the block H3∙376d. ; total 14s. l∙842d., or per yard, 19s. 3∙6d., or rather less than at 2¼ feet.</p><p>For the case where the rail increases or decreases in a less ratio than the block, Table VI. shews the comparative effect on the minimum, which is here at about 2 feet, with a decrease in the prices; for trying 2∙2 feet, we get for the rail 40∙334d., the block 75∙6d. ; total, 115.934d., or per yard, 13s. 2∙09d. ; and at 2∙1 feet, we have for the rail 36<hi rend="sup">,</hi>75d., the block, 73∙8d. ; total, 1 l0∙55d., or per yard 13s. l∙93d.</p><p>When there is an increase of ⅙th in the price of the rail, and ¼th in the price of the block, we have for 2-feet bearings, the rail,46∙66d.,theblock, l20d.; total, l66∙66d.,or per yard, 20s. 10d.; for 2¼ feet, we have, rail, 59'0625d., block, l27.5d.; total, l86∙5625d., or per yard 20s. 8.75d. ; for 2½ feet, the rail is 72∙915d., the block, l35d. ; total, 207<hi rend="sup">,</hi>9l5d., or per yard, 20s. 9<hi rend="sup">,</hi>498d. Hence the minimum is at 2¼ feet, for at 2∙3 feet the rail is 61∙7165d., the block 129d. ; total, !90∙7l68d., and the price per yard, 20s. 8∙76d. ; and at 2.2 feet, the rail is 56∙4665d∙, the block, 126d.; total, 182∙4665d., and the price per yard, 20s. 8∙8ld.</p><p>We have now only left the cases where the price of the rail increases, while that of the block decreases ; the effect of this is shewn in Table VII. ; and when the price of the rail decreases, while that of the block increases, this is given in Table VIII. In Table VII. the minimum expense is at the distance of 2 feet, and in Table VIII. at 2¾ feet, this being the greatest distance yet obtained ; hence cheap rails and very dear blocks are the only conditions which will warrant a distance at all approaching to those now in use ; 2¾ feet appearing to be the limits under any ordinary prices, and in general only 2¼, while in some instances 2 feet only should be taken, in order to lay down a railroad at the minimum expense, as far as the cost of the permanent way is concerned.</p><p>In Table VIII. we do not know on which side of 2½ feet the minimum expense will be ; we shall therefore, in order to complete the inquiry, investigate this as we have done in the other cases. Taking, then, 2∙6 feet, we get 52 lbs. per yard for the weight, or 45∙065 lbs. per rail, costing at l¼d. per lb. 56∙332d. ; for the block we have as ∙25 feet : 7d. =∙1 foot : 2∙8d., or 10s. 8∙8d. ; total, 185∙132d., or per yard, 17s. 9"ld., being rather more than the price at 2∙5 feet. Trying now 2∙4 feet, we have 48 lbs. per yard, or 38∙4 lbs. per rail, costing 48d., and for the block 119d., the price at 2¼ feet plus 4'2d., the proportion for ∙15 feet, or l23∙2d. ; total, 171∙2d., or per yard, 17s. 10d. which is more again than at 2∙5 feet ; the minimum price will therefore be very near 2∙5 feet, but rather more if any thing.</p><p>It now remains for us to shew, why the particular rate of increase and decrease in the size of the rail and block, which we have given in the tables, has here been assumed. And, first, of the blocks. Every person, «’hen calculating this effect of prices for any particular railway, will of course take into consideration the cost of rails, blocks, and sleepers for the railway in question ; and as the rate of increase we have given, viz. one-fourth in the price of the block chair, and all appurtenances complete for each foot increase in the length of the rail, is more than whatis necessary rather than less, and as a decrease in the price of the blocks will lead to shortening the rails still more, it wall be seen that any error will be on the safe side. It will most probably be found in practice, that whatever the distance between the supports may be, the same absolute surface should be preserved in every case; for although it has been said that each block, be its distance what it may, has but to support a certain weight passing over it, yet this is not a correct mode of reasoning, because it has to support that weight for a longer time, when the distance between each</p></body></text></TEI>