<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ter, and there deposits them in safety, the tadpole soon issuing forth, and swimming immediately. The <hi rend="italic">prickly toad,</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">' B. spinosus</hi>  of Daudin, which derives its name from strong projections on its tubercles, seems also to possess a singular peculiarity. It is never met with on the surface of the soil, and is only procured by means of the plough. The country people are persuaded it never leaves its retreat voluntarily ; and Daudin suspects that it deposits its ova in the earth, in humid places, near the subterranean sources of water.</p><p>Most of the toads of tropical climates are remarkable for their great size. Of this we give an instance in the <hi rend="italic">marine toad, Rana marina,</hi>  Gmel., a native of South America, the length of whose body extends to nearly a foot. It is also remarkable for its <hi rend="italic">post-aural</hi>  projections, which are an inch long, and oval shaped. The feet are not webbed ; the toes are terminated with round knobs, and furnished with short claws resembling the human nails in miniature. There are many other recorded species of toads proper, on which, however, we cannot dwell ; and we now proceed to several genera which have recently been separated from the group.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Genus Bombinator. This genus differs from the other toads only in having the tympanum, or sort covering of the ear, hid under the skin. Rhinella of Fitzinger (Oxyr-hyncus of Spix) is distinguished by a prolonged muzzle. (See Plate CCCCXXXIII. fig. 4.) M. Gay has lately informed us </hi><hi rend="italic">(Ann. des Sc. Nat., Avril</hi>  1836, p. 224), that in Chili there is a genus allied to Rhinella, consisting of several agreeably coloured species, which are always viviparous. In the same locality he made a similar remark regarding several species of snakes. To these two genera succeed the Otilopha of Cuvier, which has also an acute snout, and on each side of the head a projecting crest extending to the gland called parotid. In the genus Breviceps of Merrem (part of Fitzinger’s genus Engystoma), neither the tympanum nor parotids are apparent ; the body is oval, the head and mouth are remarkably small, and the feet scarcely at all webbed. (See Plate CCCCXXXIII. fig. 5.) We shall here introduce a very few species belonging to these genera.</p><p>To the genus Bombinator belongs <hi rend="italic">B. bοmbiηus (Rαnα bοmbina,</hi>  Gmel.), which is the smallest and most aquatic of the European toads. It is gray or brown above, blackish blue with orange spots beneath. The hind feet are completely webbed, and nearly as long as those of frogs, so that it leaps nearly as well as they do. It affects morasses. Of the genus Rhinella, Spix has depicted and described five species, most of which, according to Cuvier, it is difficult to distinguish from the proper toads. The <hi rend="italic">mitred toad</hi>  of English writers, the <hi rend="italic">margaritifera</hi>  of Gmelin, is usually adduced as a type of the genus Otilopha. It is a native of Brazil, and about the size of the common toad ; it is rufous brown above and whitish beneath, beset with numerous small tubercles of a bluish or pearly cast, whence the French name <hi rend="italic">crapaud perlé ;</hi>  but its principal characteristic is the subtriangular form of its head, the sides of which, beyond each eye, project into an angular protuberance. From the nose likewise an elevated white line runs along each side of the head, over the shoulder, to the sides ; the fore feet are unwebbed, the hind are partly so. Genuine specimens of the genus Breviceps present animals not a little singular in their forms. Such are the <hi rend="italic">short-headed</hi>  and the <hi rend="italic">indistinct </hi><hi rend="italic">toad</hi>  of British authors, the <hi rend="italic">Rαna breνiceps</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">R. systoma </hi>of Schneider. They are oval-shaped like eggs, with scarcely any projecting head ; and one of them has actually been called the <hi rend="italic">headless toad. (Rana acephala,</hi>  Schn.). The <hi rend="italic">shortheaded toad</hi>  is a very small animal, about half the size of the common toad ; the head is completely blended and incorporated with the thorax, and the surface is rather wrinkled than tuberculous. It is a native of Africa, <hi rend="italic">li. systoma</hi>  comes from the East Indies, and has a thick rounded body, with a head so lost in the general outline that the mouth is scarcely apparent ; the legs, too, are peculiarly short, and appear almost as if imbedded in the wrinkled skin of the sides.</p><p>We now advance to tile genus Pipa, which is universally distinguished from the toads. Its generic characters are the following : The body is flattened horizontally ; the head is broad and triangular ; the tongue is so adherent that it appears to be wanting (it is often said to be so) ; the tympanum is hid beneath the skin ; the small eyes are placed toward the margin of the lower jaw ; the extremities of all the fingers are divided into four small points ; and finally, the male has an enormously sized larynx, like a triangular osseous box, which encloses two moveable ossiculi which occasionally close the branchiæ. Of this genus, that well-known and most singular animal commonly called the Surinam toad <hi rend="italic">(Pipa Surinamensis,</hi>  Laurenti,—<hi rend="italic">Ranapipa </hi>of Linnæus), may be taken as a type. It seems to have been introduced to the notice of naturalists at the close of the seventeenth century, and was first described by the celebrated Ruysch. It is one of the most uncouth and hideous of nature’s creatures, and is especially signalizcd for some of the most extraordinary phenomena regarding the growth of its young which are to be found throughout the range of the animal kingdom. The size of the Surinam toad considerably exceeds that of our common species. The mouth is very wide ; the hands are tetradactylous ; the fingers long and slender, and each divided at the tip into four distinct processes, all of which, when narrowly inspected with a glass, are found to be again subdivided in nearly a similar manner. The web of the hind feet reaches to the tips of the toes. The male is rather larger than the female, sometimes attaining the length of seven inches. The back is studded with granules, which are somewhat more numerous and larger on the female ; the skin round the neck, in both sexes, forms a kind of loose wrinkled collar. The general colour of both is a dark blackish brown. This reptile has been long celebrated for the manner in which its young are perpetuated ; and on this account it has become the object of much attention. It was for a time supposed that the ova issued from the deeper seated parts of the back, and were then enclosed in small cells on its surface till they were regularly hatched. Later observations in correcting this mistake have demonstrated a not less peculiar history. The precise truth was first made known by Dr Fermin, who had an opportunity, during his residence at Surinam, to investigate the creature’s structure in a more satisfactory manner than had previously been practicable. His account is, that the female Pipa spawns at the brink of some stagnant water, and that the male immediately collects and amasses the heap of ova, and after impregnation ■  deposits them with great care on the back of the female, where they are received into cellules which at this period are open for their reception, but speedily close upon them. They are there retained to the time of their second birth, which happens in somewhat less than three months. During this period the cells gradually enlarge, till the young emerge from the back of the parent in a completely formed state. During the time of their concealment, however, they undergo the usual change which is effected upon tlleir congeners, being first hatched from the ova in the form of a tadpole ; and then, after gradually acquiring their perfect shape, losing their tail, and so forth, they are extruded from the cellules. This strange process has since been examined and verified by Camper, Spallanzani, Blumenbach, and other naturalists, and is now established as a phenomenon equally true as extraordinary. Fermin found the brood he observed amount to seventy-five, and the period of their extrusion as young Pipas occupied five days. When they had made their escape, the female, having rubbed the epidermis from her back on some hard substance, returned to land. This</p></body></text></TEI>