<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Man. His Essay on Quantity, occasioned by reading a Treatise in which Simple and Compound Ratios are applied to Virtue and Merit, was composed previously to the year 1748, and published in the Philosophical Transactions of London for that year. This paper affords some light respecting the progress of his speculations about the period in question. The Inquiry into the Human Mind, of which we have already taken notice, appeared in 1764 ; and at this time he was complimented with the degree of Doctor in Divinity.</p><p>In the year 1796, the last of his life, he was prevailed upon to spend with his friends at Edinburgh a few weeks during the summer. From that visit he returned to Glasgow in his usual health and spirits, and for some time continued to devote a portion of his time to the exercise both of body and of mind. But about the end of September he was seized with a violent disorder, with which he maintained a severe struggle ; and this, together with repeated strokes of the palsy, put a period to his long and useful life on the 7th of October, and in the eighty-seventh year of his age.</p><p>As to his bodily constitution, few men have ever been more indebted to nature than Dr Reid. In this respect he was athletic and vigorous, and his muscular strength was uncommonly great ; advantages which were powerfully seconded by his temperance, exercise, and the unclouded serenity of his temper. Deep and collected thought was very conspicuous in his countenance, and all his looks were expressive of kindness and good will.</p><p>With respect to his character, his rectitude was inflexible and intrepid ; his attachment to truth was pure ; and he had an entire command over all his passions, which he acquired by the unwearied exertions of a long life. When, therefore, he found it necessary to dispute the conclusions of others in any of his writings, he nevcr employed any expressions to irritate those whom he was anxious to convince ; and the asperity of his opponents could not provoke him to repress his spirit of liberality and good humour ; for he considered the intemperance with which controversy is carried on, as an enemy to the progress of useful knowledge, and as having done more harm to the practice than service to the theory of morality. He uniformly maintained the dignity of philosophy in private life, and he united in his character the most amiable modesty and gentleness with the noblest spirit of independence. He never solicited any favours from the great ; and all his academical or other preferments were conferred upon him by those who were real judges of his merit, and thought he deserved them. To a sound, cautious, and discriminating judgment, a singular patience and perseverance of thought, and fixed attention to the operations of his own mind, he added the curiosity of a naturalist and the eyes of an observer ; and of course his information was accurate and extensive. His sensibility was of an active and lively nature ; and wherever he could command the means of relieving the distressed, he always employed them with the utmost possible secrecy. The life of Dr Reid, by his disciple and friend Mr Dugald Stewart, the great ornament of his master’s school, is known to all the world as one of the first specimens of philosophical biography that any language can furnish.</p><p>REIGATE, or Ryegate, a market and borough town of the county of Surrey, in the hundred of its own name, twenty-two miles from London. It is situated in a pleasant valley at the foot of the Chalk Hills, upon a branch of the river Mole. It has a weekly market on Tuesday, and a monthly one for cattle on Wednesday. It is an ancient borough, and, until 1832, returned two members to parliament, but it now returns only one. The population of the borough amounted in 1801 to 923, in 1811 to 1128, in 1821 to 1323, and in 1831 to 1419; but the Foreign, a part of the parish now added to the borough, contained, in 1831, 1978 inhabitants, making in all a population of 3397.</p><p>REISKE, John James, a profound scholar and eminent critic, was born in the year 1706, at a small town in the duchy of Anhalt, in Germany. His connections, it would appear, were in a humble situation of life ; and, in consequence of the narrow circumstances in which he was placed, he had many difficulties to struggle with during the early part of his education. These, however, he surmounted by unabating perseverance ; and in 1733 went to Leipsic, where he remained during five years in the ardent pursuit of his studies. Here he acquired an extensive knowledge of the Arabic, and engaged in the translation of a book from that language, which was afterwards published. With the view of prosecuting to greater advantage the study of Arabic, which had become with him a favourite object of pursuit, he travelled on foot to Leyden, where new difficulties attended him. Whilst he remained there he was employed in arranging the Arabic manuscripts belonging to the university ; and for this labour he received a very small compensation. During his residence at Leyden, part of his time was occupied in the translation of various essays from the German and French languages into Latin. These essays afterwards appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea Critica.</hi>  About the same time, also, our learned author translated into Latin the whole of the <hi rend="italic">Chariton</hi>  from the Greek, and the Geography of Abul-feda from the Arabic.</p><p>Having spent eight years at Leyden, Reiske was driven from this place by jealousy and calumny, which, it is said, were excited against him chiefly by the younger Burmann, in consequence of his critical strictures on the edition of Petronius published by that author ; but before his departure from this learned seminary, he had obtained the degree of doctor of physic, which was conferred in a manner highly to his honour. He afterwards visited different parts of Germany, and at last settled a second time at Leipsic, where he remained for twelve years. But although he had received the appointment of professor of Arabic, the emoluments of his office were so scanty, that he had still to struggle with all the difficulties attendant on poverty, and, merely to procure a subsistence, was obliged to engage in the humble employments of literary labour, and submit to the severe and ill-requited drudgery of editing works for booksellers, or contributing detached papers to periodical publications. About this time the <hi rend="italic">Acta Eruditorum</hi>  were greatly indebted to the labours of Reiske. But in the midst of all the difficulties and hardships now alluded to, he prepared and published a work of profound learning and great merit. This work, which extended to five volumes, appeared under the title of <hi rend="italic">Animadversiones in Auctores Grœ-cos,</hi>  and added much to our author’s reputation.</p><p>In the year 1758, in consequence of the death of HaI-tausius, he obtained a situation, which was not only honourable, but lucrative. This was the place of rector of the academy of Leipsic, in which he continued during the remainder of his life. He was now raised above want, and being free from the difficulties and embarrassmentswhich had hitherto constantly attended him, he was thus enabled, in the midst of learned ease, to prosecute his favourite studies.</p><p>In the year 1764 Reiske married E. C. Muller, a woman of great learning, and of whom it is said that her knowledge, especially in Greek literature, was little inferior to that of her husband. In all his literary labours she was an useful associate ; but the assistance which she contributed to his great work, the edition of the Greek Orators, was particularly valuable. Thus passed the latter period of the life of this learned man. He died in 1774, possessing a very distinguished reputation as a scholar and a critic. The number of the works which he superintended and published is very great. The most approved are the following, viz. Remarks upon Greek Authors ; an Edition of the Greek Ora-</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>