<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>by infusion, and not by decoction, as a high temperature impairs its purgative property. It is for this reason that the common extract of rhubarb of the shops is of no use as a  laxative. Rhubarb, from its astringency, has been supposed to contain tannine, but this has not been satisfactorily demonstrated by chemical experiment. The r∞ts contain a certain proportion of starch. This is most abundant in the English sort, which accounts for its generally having a somewhat mucilaginous taste.</p><p>The medicinal action of rhubarb varies according to the dose in which it is administered. In small quantities, as three or four grains, it is a gentle stomachic and astringent, and as such is employed in many cases of indigestion, and a relaxed state of the bowels. In cases of diarrhoea in children, which are generally attended with superabundant acidity of the <hi rend="italic">primœ viœ,</hi>  there is no safer or more effectual remedy than three or four grains of rhubarb, with twice that quantity of prepared chalk, which may be taken two or three times in the day.</p><p>In larger doses, as in quantities from fifteen to thirty grains, rhubarb is a mild and easy laxative, and, from its possessing no irritating qualities, is valuable in all cases where the bowels might be injured by more active substances. It is consequently well adapted to the more irritable constitutions of children and females. Where there is derangement of the stomach or bowels from indigestible matter, or from acidity, rhubarb is a very valuable laxative ; and in such cases its action is very much improved by its being combined with magnesia. The well-known <hi rend="italic">Gregorfs powder,</hi>  introduced by the late professor of physic at Edinburgh, consists of two parts of rhubarb, three of calcined magnesia, and one of ginger, and is one of the best remedies which can be employed in such cases. The usual dose of this for an adult is a tea-spoonful, which may be taken in water, combined with some aromatic tincture, or with a little of the tincture of rhubarb itself.</p><p>The colouring matter of rhubarb, and probably its purgative principle, are absorbed into the circulation during its action on the system. That the colouring matter is absorbed, is demonstrated by its presence in the urine, to which it communicates a reddish-brown colour ; a circumstance always to be borne in mind in forming an opinion of any case in which rhubarb may have previously been taken. The absorption of the purgative principle is inferred from the fact, that the milk of nurses who are using this medicine sometimes exerts a laxative influence on children at the breast.</p><p>In the year 1835, the quantity of rhubarb imported into Great Britain amounted to 81,100 lbs., and in 1836 to 122,142 lbs., of which in the former year 44,522 lbs., and in the latter 44,468 lbs., were retained for home consumption ; the duty being one shilling per lb., yielded a net revenue of L.2220 in the one year, and L.2236 in the other.    (b. m.)</p><p>RHUMB, in <hi rend="italic">Navigation,</hi>  a vertical circle of any given place, or intersection of such a circle with the horizon ; in which last sense it is the same with a point of the compass.</p><p><hi rend="italic">RHUMB-Linc</hi>  is also used for the line which a ship describes when sailing in the same collateral point of the compass, or oblique to the meridians.</p><p>RHYME, Rhimk, <hi rend="italic">Ryrne,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">Rime,</hi>  in <hi rend="italic">Poetry,</hi>  the similar sound or cadence and termination of two words which end two verses, &amp;c. Or rhyme is a similitude of sound between the last syllable or syllables of a verse, succeeding either immediately or at a distance of two or three lines.</p><p>RHYMER, Thomas the. See Thomas of Ekceldoun.</p><p>RHYTHM, Musical. See Music.</p><p>RHYTHMOMETER, from <hi rend="italic">ρuHμλς,</hi>  and /Λ&lt;rpov, an instrument contrived to measure equal portions of sounds in musical performance, and to mark the time, at longer or shorter intervals, according to adjustment of the mechanism. Mael-zel's <hi rend="italic">metronome</hi>  is the instrument of this kind most generally in use, although one more simple and less costly might easily be made. Diderot, in the fourth memoir of his mathematical works, suggested a musical chronometer, but added, “ Le seul bon chronomètre que l’on puisse avoir, c’est un habile musicien qui ait du goût, qui ait bien lui la musique qu’il doit faire exécuter, et qui sache en battre la mesure.” The chief utility of a rhythmometer consists in the power of fixing the duration of time which a composer wishes to give to the equalized portions of his composition, as indicated by the vibrations of a pendulum, and as marked by relative numerals affixed to characters of musical notation. Almost all pieces of music of classical importance are now printed with indications of the metronome measures of time ; and this is a great improvement, inasmuch as before the present century we had nothing but tradition, and often no tradition at all, to guide us in the comparative slowness or quickness with which the notes of a musical composition were to be performed.</p><p>RIAO, an island in the Eastern Seas, about twenty-five miles in circumference, near the west coast of Morty. Long. 128. 2. E. Lat. 2. 25. N.</p><p>RIASAN, a government of Russia, so called from the ancient city of that name. It extends in north latitude from 53. 1. to 55. 4L, and in east longitude from 38. 10. to 4L 14., and is 13,486 square miles. It contains twelve cities or towns, and 833 parishes or communes, with 1,250,000 inhabitants, a very great proportion of whom are in a state of vassalage. The district is an extensive plain watered by the rivers Don, Oka, Osetr, and Prona, and near to them it is highly fertile. In the other parts the soil is as productive as can well be expected in a climate so severe. The land is best in the southern division of the province, but the whole yields more com than is required for domestic consumption. A surplus for exportation is produced of grain, and brandy made from it, of salted meat, of leather, wax, honey, and hops. The forests afford a large supply of timber. The manufactures are confined to clothing, chiefly linen, and to iron implements. The exports proceed through the Oka to the river Wolga. The capital is the city of the same name on the river Trubusch, and is the seat of a bishop. It contains twenty churches, an ecclesiastical seminary, and one for the higher classes, with 760 dwellings, and 5000 inhabitants, chiefly employed in making linens. It is 617 miles from Petersburg. Long. 39.4.58. E. Lat. 54.58.6. N.</p><p>RIBAUVILLER, a city of the department of the Upper Rhine, and arrondissement of Colmar, in France. It is situated at the foot of the Vosges Mountains, on the river Stambach. In 1836, it contained 6558 inhabitants, who were employed in cultivating the vine, and in carrying on extensive cotton manufactures.</p><p>RIBERA, a town of the intendency of Girgenti, and the district of Mazzara, in the island of Sicily. It stands on an unhealthy plain on the sea-shore, near the river Ca-latabellota, sixty miles from Palermo, and contains 4800 industrious inhabitants.</p><p>RIBERAC, an arrondissement of the department of the Dordogne, in France, 557 square miles in extent. It comprises seven cantons, and eighty-three communes, and in 1836 contained 71,457 inhabitants. The capital is the city of the same name, in a fertile vale on the left bank of the rivcr Dronne. It is ill built, and in 1836 contained 3775 inhabitants, with but little commerce.</p><p>RICARDO, David, the most distinguished political economist since Dr Smith, was the third of a numerous family, and was born in the city of London on the 19th of April 1772. His father, a native of Holland, and of the Jewish persuasion, settled in this country early in life. He is said to have been a man of good talents and the strictest integrity ; and having become a member of the Stock Exchange, he acquired a respectable fortune, and possessed</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>