<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>ed filaments were most distinctly projected on a white plane held below the trough, so that they were accurately drawn with a pencil. A few important particulars may be here mentioned.</p><p>The still water ADC, fig. 10, lasted for a long while before it was renewed ; and it seemed to be gradually wasted by abrasion, by the adhesion of the surrounding water, which gradually licked away the outer parts from D to A and B ; and it seemed to renew itself in the direction CD, opposite to the motion of the stream. There was, however, a considerable intricacy and eddy in this motion. Some (seemingly superficial) water was continually, but slowly, flowing outward from the line DC, while other water was seen within and below it, coming inwards and going backwards.</p><p>The coloured lateral filaments were most constant in their form, while the body was the same, although the velocity was in some cases quadrupled. Any change which this produced seemed confined to the superficial filaments.</p><p>As the filaments were deflected, they were also constipated, that is, the curved parts of the filaments were nearer each other than the parallel straight filaments up the stream ; and this constipation was more considerable as the prow was more obtuse and the deflexion greater.</p><p>The inner filaments were ultimately more deflected than those without them ; that is, if a line be drawn touching the curve EFIH in the point H of contrary flexure, where the concavity begins to be on the side next the body, the angle HKC, contained between the axis and the tangent line, is so much the greater as the filament is nearer the axis.</p><p>When the body exposed to the stream was a box of upright sides, flat bottom, and angular prow, like a wedge, having its edge also upright, the filaments were not all deflected laterally, as theory would make us expect ; but the filaments near the bottom were also deflected downwards as well as laterally, and glided along at some distance under the bottom, forming lines of double curvature.</p><p>The breadth of the stream that was deflected was much greater than that of the body ; and the sensible deflection began at a considerable distance up the stream, especially in the outer filaments.</p><p>Lastly, the form of the curves was greatly influenced by the proportion between the width of the trough and that of the body. The curvature was always less when the trough was very wide in proportion to the body.</p><p>Great varieties were also observed in the motion or velocity of the filaments. In general, the filaments increased in velocity outwards from the body to a certain small distance, which was nearly the same in all cases, and then diminished all the way outward. This was observed by inequalities in the colour of the filaments, by which one could be observed to outstrip another. The retardation of those next the body seemed to proceed from friction ; and it was imagined that without this the velocity there would always have been greatest.</p><p>These observations give us considerable information respecting the mechanism of these motions, and the action of fluids upon solids. The pressure in the duplicate ratio of the velocities comes here again into view. We found, that although the velocities were very different, the curves were precisely the same. Now the observed pressures arise from the transverse forces by which each particle of a filament is retained in its curvilineal path ; and we know that the force by which a body is retained in any curve is directly as the square of the velocity, and inversely as the radius of curvature. The curvature, therefore, remaining the same, the transverse forces, and consequently the pressure on the body, must be as the square of the velocity ; and, on the other hand, we can see pretty clearly (indeed it is rigorously demonstrated by D’Alembert), that whatever be the velocities, the curves will be the same. For it is known</p><p>in hydraulics, that it requires a fourfold or ninefold pressure to produce a double or triple velocity. And as all pressures are propagated through a perfect fluid without diminution, this fourfold pressure, while it produces a double velocity, produces also fourfold transverse pressures, which will retain the particles, moving twice as fast, in the same curvilineal paths. And thus we see that the impulses, as thev are called, and resistances of fluids, have a certain relation to the weight of a column of fluid whose height is the height necessary for producing the velocity. How it happens that a plane surface, immersed in an extended fluid, sustains just half the pressure which it would have sustained had the motions been such as are represented in fig. 6, is a matter of more curious and difficult investigation. But we see evidently that the pressure must be less than what is there assigned ; for the stagnant water a-head of the body greatly diminishes the ultimate deflections of the filaments ; and it may be demonstrated, that when the part BE of the canal, fig. 9, is inclined to the part AB in an angle less than 90°, the pressures BG along the whole canal are as the versed sine of the ultimate angle of deflection, or the versed sine of the angle which the part BE makes with the part AB. Therefore, since the deflections resemble more the sketch given in fig. 10, the accumulated sum of all these forces BG of fig. 9 must be less than the similar sum corresponding to fig. 6, that is, less than the weight of the column of fluid having twice the productive height for its height. How it is just one half, shall be our next inquiry.</p><p>And here we must return to the labours of Sir Isaac Newton. After many beautiful observations on the nature and mechanism of continued fluids, he says, that the resistance which they occasion is but one half of that occasioned by the rare fluid which had been the subject of his former proposition. He then enters into another, as novel and as difficult an investigation, viz. the laws of hydraulics, and endeavours to ascertain the motion of fluids through orifices when urged by pressures of any kind. He endeavours to ascertain the velocity with w hich a fluid escapes through a , horizontal orifice in the bottom of a vessel, by the action of its weight, and the pressure which this vein of fluid will exert on a little circle which occupies part of the orifice.</p><p>To obtain this, he employs a kind of approximation and trial, of which it would be extremely difficult to give an extract ; and then, by increasing the diameter of the vessel and of the hole to infinity, he accommodates his reasoning to the case of a plane surface exposed to an indefinitely extended stream of fluid ; and, lastly, giving to the little circular surface the motion which he had before ascribed to the fluid, he says, that the resistance to a plane surface moving through an unelastic continuous fluid, is equal to the weight of a column of the fluid whose height is one half of that necessary for acquiring the velocity ; and he says, that the resistance of a globe is, in this case, the same with that of a cylinder of the same diameter. The resistance, therefore, of the cylinder or circle is four times less, and that of the globe is twice less, than their resistances on a rare elastic medium.</p><p>But this determination, though founded on principles or assumptions which are much nearer to the real state of things, is liable to great objections. It depends on his method for ascertaining the velocity of the issuing fluid; a method extremely ingenious, but defective. The cataract which he supposes, cannot exist as he supposes, descending by the full action of gravity, and surrounded by a funnel of stagnant fluid. For, in such circumstances, there is nothing to balance the hydrostatical pressure of this surrounding fluid ; because the whole pressure of the central cataract is employed in producing its own descent. In the next place, the pressure which he determines is beyond all doubt only half of what is observed on a plane surface in all our experiments. And, in the third place it is repugnant to all our</p></body></text></TEI>