<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>little affected by this. The rails are much too light and want <hi rend="sup">,</hi> depth, and their shape should be the subject of properly conducted experiments. The guage being retained, all the necessary information relative to its efficiency and economy, will, no doubt, in time be made known. The question of longitudinal or transverse bearings is of much less import than is generally imagined. The part of the line on piles between London and Maidenhead, twenty-three miles, if it be retained and kept in good order, will soon set at rest the question of expense in maintaining the way. Thus, then, so far as the public are concerned, all is well ; but the effect of this decision on the interests of the proprietors has received no light whatever ; there is nothing even to shew that in adopting a heavier rail, there is the slightest necessity also to adopt a greater scantling of timber ; and it is extraordinary that a point so easily submitted to experiment and calculation, should have been en</p><p>tirely passed by in the final report to the proprietors.</p><p>We have hitherto looked principally to the construction</p><p>of a railway ; there is, however, an equally important point to be considered, and that is, the working of it after it has been constructed. On this will mainly hinge the degree of profit which may be expected ; for, let all our previous instructions be duly considered and properly followed out, with such deviations only as may be rendered necessary by local circumstances ; or let a railway be constructed in the best and most advantageous manner, yet it will soon be discovered that, if it is not worked on a sound and effective system, it will turn out a vastly different speculation to what it would be under proper management-</p><p>For this purpose every thing should centre in one committee of directors ; these may with advantage subdivide themselves into smaller bodies, for particular purposes ; all business transacted by these subdivisions being merely preparatory, and nothing being finally concluded till brought before the general body. There should be no boards of direction at each end of a line, but that terminus which is best situated to effectually overlook the whole of the various business, should be made choice of for the seat of government. There should be ample inspection into every department, but it should be inspection only ; all orders should come from one committee, and through one general head. It may often happen, and always with advantage, that both ends of a railway may be opened before the middle is finished ; still every thing should centre at the governing end of the line, at one point ; and the mode by which this government should be carried on, must now be considered a little more at large.</p><p>The first question which arises is, by what system can a joint stock company be so managed as to obtain the same amount of alacrity, vigilance, and industry in its service, as characterises the conduct of individuals when acting for themselves, and to combine with these qualities an honest and economical administration. The system of management by boards of directors has stood the test of considerable experience, and, where the proper men are found for directors, this system is admiraoly adapted to answer the primary object of a board, viz. to deliberate and decide on principles. More information and greater variety of view is brought to bear upon a subject when it is discussed by several men, than almost any individual intellect could furnish ; and, as joint-stock companies consist of persons in almost all classes of society, a board composed, as it should be, of individuals holding a large amount of stock, and giving their services gratuitously, for that reason, as well as from a sense of public duty, by embodying various interests, claims and secures the confidence of all.</p><p>It is well known, however, that a body consisting of many individuals is utterly unfitted for executive functions. It is admitted as a principle, that executive administration is best and most efficiently exercised by one and one only, and,</p><p>accordingly, every board, whether of government commissioners, or of joint-stock companies, or of charitable institutions, has some one to whom is entrusted the executive superintendence, and control of that, whatever it be, on which the board exercises its legislative and judicial functions. Connected with this executive are other officers, many or few, exercising a separate jurisdiction over their several departments, and in all details independent, yet held together, for the purposes of combination, by the executive officer.</p><p>In the management of railways, such an officer is more especially required where the heads of departments are necessarily numerous, in consequence of the several branches of business into which the working of a railway is divided ; where each department employs a considerable number of men, two alone, those of the police and porters, amounting almost to a regiment, and where all are to be brought to act with the precision and regularity of a steam engine. It would be impossible to produce unity of action amidst such conflicting elements, without a close, active, and unremitting personal superintendence, such as may be accomplished by an individual, but can never be effected by a board.</p><p>Several attempts at a different system of management have been made by railway companies, but they have not been found to answer. A favourite project has been much talked of lately, viz. that a committee of three should be chosen from the body of the directors, in which triumvirate should reside all administrative and executive functions, and so much of the deliberative and judicial as relates to the ordinary affairs of the company, and that each triumvir should receive a salary sufficient to command his whole time for the company’s service, the chairman receiving a higher remuneration than his colleagues. The advocates of this plan contend, that it would first secure unity of action in the principles of management, with prompt execution in the details, a ready redress of grievances, and remedy, or rather prevention of abuses. Secondly, that it would give the personal responsibility of a few to the proprietors, in place of the collective responsibility of many ; and, thirdly, that it would keep in check the undue power and influence which, under a different system, the executive officers would be likely to acquire.</p><p>This view appears more plausible than sound, more specious than solid. In the first place, the triumvirate would monopolize the whole power of the company, and the board would go to sleep. The board of which the triumvirate form a part, would meet too seldom and know too little, to be a match for three men, who would act together every day and know every thing, and who, above all, would enter into debate with the larger body, and vote as directors upon questions affecting their own conduct. It has always proved a thoroughly vicious system to have an executive officer a member (as in many boards he is) of that body, whose orders he is to execute, and to whom he ought to be responsible ; and this applies to the triumvirate.</p><p>In the second place, the responsibility of each triumvir would merge in the collective responsibility of the whole board, and men would be exercising a power for which, practically, they could not be called to an account ; for, when the board had confirmed an act of the triumvirate, what chance would the proprietors have to make them accountable ? The results of irresponsible authority, it is well known, are jobbing and every sort of peculation.</p><p>In the third place, it is not likely that three men chosen out of a body of directors, would be the men best fitted for the situations contemplated. Not only is the number out of which they would be chosen too few to present sufficient of the peculiar ability required, but the selection of the individuals would be rather determined by personal predilections than by their fitness. It would be an appointment to</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>