<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>can this argument have any force.” The testimony of the inspired writers is before us, declaring the truth of the Bible history ; we believe in the truth thus testified, because,— assuming that we have examined the antecedent steps of the argument, and have reached the point at which the argument from testimony comes in unmixed,—we believe the witnesses, or, in other words, we are convinced that, but for the truth of their testimony (its condition), it would not have been given. On this head we must content ourselves with simply urging the study of one of the most deeply important inquiries connected with the argument, namely, the genuine test of concurrent testimonies. The subject is ably treated both by Campbell and Whately, and the former writer thus states the principle. “ In a number of concurrent testimonies (in cases wherein there could have been no previous concert), there is a probability <hi rend="italic">distinct</hi>  from that which may be termed the sum of the probabilities resulting from the testimonies of the witnesses,—a probability which would remain, even though the witnesses were of such a character as to merit no faith at all. This probability arises purely <hi rend="italic">from the concurrence itself.</hi>  That such a concurrence should spring from chance, is as one to infinitude ; that is, in othcr words, morally impossible. If, therefore, concert be excluded, there remains no other supposition but the reality of the fact.”</p><p>We now pass to the third and last kind of Arguments, those from Example, which Whately analyses thus. In all  the arguments designated by this name, “ we consider one or more <hi rend="italic">known</hi>  individual objects, or instances of a certain class, as fair <hi rend="italic">specimens,</hi>  in respect of some point or other, of that class; and consequently draw an inference from them respecting either the whole class, or other <hi rend="italic">less known </hi>individuads of it. In arguments of this kind, then, it will be found, that, universally, we assume as a major premise, that what is true (in regard to the point in question) of the individual or individuals which we bring forward and appeal to, is true of the whole class to which they belong : the minor premise next asserts something of that individual ; and the same is then inferred respecting the whole class ; whether we stop at that general conclusion, or descend from thence to another unknown individual ; in which last case, which is the most usually called the argument from example, we generally omit, for the sake of brevity, the intermediate step, and pass at once, in the expression of the arguments, from the known to the unknown individual.” These principles apply not only to the common argument from Example, but to those from Induction, Experience, Analogy, and the like.</p><p>The easiest way of discovering the real force of this class of arguments for direct conviction, is (for those at least who are not wilfully resolved on creating difficulties for themselves) to examine its relation to the principles of logic. Both the Argument from Antecedent Probability and the Argument from Signs are strictly logical ; or, in other words, they can be so stated that their form will of itself show whether the conclusion is legitimate or not ; for, in order to reduce arguments of these kinds to formal syllogisms, we have only to restore the premise suppressed in ordinary discourse, and to limit in such a way the expression of both premises, that the degree of probability may distinctly appear in each, and may thence pass regularly into the conclusion. If the premises are certain, the conclusion will be so likewise ; if that element is wanting, the conclusion will only reach one or another of the infinite degrees of probability. Now, on the other hand, the Argument from Example, in all its varied shapes, is always one which will not stand the test of transformation into a logical shape. We may comprehend this most readily in the case of a rhetorical Induction, which, assuming Whately’s analysis as our guide, is an argument stopping short at the general conclusion from the premises, without going on to the last step, which infers as to the unknown individual. The process thus performed corresponds with what most logicians call an Imperfect Induction, which is truly no logical induction at all, but merely something wearing the appearance of it-The logical induction (to borrow again from a high metaphysical authority already cited) is governed by the rule, “ That what belongs (or does not belong) to <hi rend="italic">all</hi>  the constituent parts, belongs (or does not belong) to the constituted whole.” The imperfect or rhetorical induction assumes, that what belongs (or does not belong) to <hi rend="italic">some</hi>  of the constituent parts, belongs (or does not belong) to the constituted whole. This conclusion may or may not be true in the particular case, but it is always illogical.</p><p>There is a pressing reason for urging the importance of this view of the subject. In matters of moral reasoning, the argument from example is oftener misused than any other, and is altogether a very dangerous one in unskilful hands, the mischief sometimes falling on him who uses it, and sometimes on those to whom it is addressed. We are apt to be widely misled by the analogies of physical science, which give the name of induction to arguments in which an inference is drawn respecting a whole class from experiments on a few individuals, or even from one solitary experiment. If this experiment has been cautiously and un-objectionably made, so as to insure the essential point, that the individual is truly an adequate specimen of the class, the inference is sound and the induction valid. The process of reasoning, in short, sets out from a number of silent assumptions, and it is worthless if any one of these has been unwarranted. The history of the material sciences abounds with instances of the most grievous errors which have arisen from such assumptions of false data ; and this notwithstanding the facilities generally existing there for decisive experiments, by which the philosopher may place the subjects of his inquiries almost in any circumstances he will. In moral science we can scarcely ever experiment at all ; we are confined to the task of watching the phenomena which the course of nature evolves, and of drawing our conclusions from facts as to which we are often exceedingly in doubt whether we may not have misapprehended their real nature and causes. “ The <hi rend="italic">experimentum crucis”</hi>  says Playfair, in his Preliminary Dissertation to this work, “ is of such weight in matters of induction, that in all those branches of science where it cannot easily be resorted to (the circumstances of an experiment being out of our power, and incapable of being varied at pleasure), there is often a great</p><p>want of conclusive evidence.......Men deceive themselves</p><p>continually, and think they are reasoning from fact and experience, when in reality they are only reasoning from a mixture of truth and falsehood.” I learn from a few experiments that certain acids act on certain other bodies as solvents ; and the inferences are correct, not because they are logically drawn, but because all the assumptions on which they proceed have been tested by observation, and discovered to be well founded. Afterwards, turning to subjects of moral reasoning, I infer that all political revolutions are accompanied by wars and bloodshed, because I know that such evils attended the French Revolution of the eighteenth century, and that which took place in England in the first half of the seventeenth. The conclusion, as every one will tell me, is false ; but it is also logically inconsequent ; for the reasoning has silently assumed as true an infinite number of principles, all of which are essential to its validity, and many of which are utterly destitute of truth and probability.</p><p>The principles to which it has been here attempted to invite the student’s notice, are convincingly illustrated by Campbell, in his analysis of arguments from experience. The evidence of Analogy, as the same writer observes, “ is but a more indirect experience, founded on some remote similitude ;” and its force is always small, requiring indeed</p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>