<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>are appointed by the guardians established under the poor-law amendment act, and 267 are registrars of temporary ' districts, appointed by the Poor-law Commissioners.</p><p>The number of registrars of marriages who had been appointed and held such office on the 3lst of December 1838 was 817, of whom 419 are also registrars of births and deaths. The foregoing, being in number 3209, act under the directions of the Registrar-General, and are removeable by him.</p><p>The number of other persons by whom registration of marriage is effected is as follows:—hi, 11,694 officiating ministers of the Established Church, to whom register-books have been furnished ; <hi rend="italic">2d,</hi>  ninety registering officers of Quakers ; 3rf, thirty-six secretaries of synagogues. All these are in communication with the Registrar-General with respect to the duties of registration.</p><p>One of the most important features of the new measures is the provision that certified copies shall be deposited quarterly in the General Register Office in London, there to be arranged and indexed for facility of reference ; a provision by means of which henceforth a copy of an entry of any registered birth, death, or marriage, in any part of England or Wales, may be obtained by application at a single office, at the trifling cost of 3s. 6d., which includes the fee for search.</p><p>The certified copies thus transmitted from the clergy, registrars, registering officers, and secretaries (amounting together to more than 15,000 persons), are all made on separate leaves of durable paper, of an uniform size and peculiar texture, having a distinguishing water-mark for the prevention of forgery, and furnished by the Registrar-General to every one of the foregoing persons, on whom the duty of registration devolves. They are sent by the superintendent registrars by the general post, each class of return (i. <hi rend="italic">e. </hi>birth, death, and marriage) being sent separate, and in a cover denoting by a mark the nature of the contents, and bearing the name of the district to which it belongs. Thus, on their reception at the General Register Office, the confusion which would Otherwuse ensue is avoided, by its being rendered possible to classify the certified copies to a considerable extent even before they are taken out of their covers.</p><p>They are then arranged and examined <hi rend="italic">seriatim,</hi>  and all defects are noted ; and letters on the subject of such defects as are of any importance are addressed to the persons from whom the defective copies come, and who arc required to furnish either other copies, or such explanations as may remove doubt. The copies are then paged, and inserted in books for reference.</p><p>Means of immediate reference to any one of the entries of births, deaths, and marriages deposited in the General Register Office, which will amount yearly to almost 1,000,000, are provided in the alphabetical indexes which are made there. This vast w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ork, far exceeding in magnitude anything of a similar kind ever before attempted in this country, is performed in the following manner. The few’ particulars requisite for the index are copied from each entry<hi rend="italic">seriatim,</hi>  on forms prepared for that purpose, containing space for as many entries as there are in one page of a certified copy. These, after having been checked, are cut into separate slips, each containing the reference to one entry ; and the slips are then sorted and arranged alphabetically on files, from w’hence they are then taken off one by one by the indexing clerks, and the contents of each copied into the index. In this manner nearly a million of names will be indexed alphabetically in the course of each year, the processes of transcribing, sorting, and indexing being per» formed by between thirty and forty persons. There is a separate index for each class of entries (births, deaths, and marriages), and for each quarter, or twelve separate indexes for the year. Any person, on payment of one shilling, may search these indexes, and, on finding the name sought, may obtain, for two shillings and sixpence, a copy of the entry of birth, death, or marriage referred to ; which copy, being stamped with the official seal, will be “ received as evidence of the birth, death, or marriage to which the same relates, without any further or other proof of such entry.” Thus not only are means afforded of obtaining for legal purposes, by application at one central office, certified copies of registers from every part of England and Wales, but the copies so obtained have the additional advantage of being sufficient evidence, without an affidavit, of their being correct, which is often required for the confirmation of extracts given from church registers.</p><p>It is stated in the preface to the Population Abstract for 1831, as the result of an inquiry respecting parochial registers in England, “ that eight hundred and twelve English parish registers commence in the year 1538, about forty of which contain entries (copied probably from family bibles and tomb-stones), anterior to the date of Cromwell’s injunction ; 1822 parish registers commence from a. d. 1538 to 1558, when Queen Elizabeth required a protestation from the clergy ; 2448 parish registers commence from a.d. 1558 to 1603, when the canons authorized by King James directed a copy of all extant parish registers to be made and preserved ; and nearly one half of them (5082) have been preserved accordingly, and are now extant. Parish registers to the number of 969 commence between that time to the year 1650 ; 2757 from a. d. 1650 to 1700 ; 1476 parish registers from a. d. 1700 to the year 1750; the rest (six or seven hundred) since that time.”</p><p>In addition to the registers heretofore and now kept under the sanction of ordinances and acts of parliament, there is a vast number of non-parochial registers and records of marriages, births and baptisms, deaths, or burials, which have been kept in some instances from a very remote period by various dissenting congregations, and in many cases w<hi rend="sup">,</hi>ith great care and correctness, but in no form produced by authority, and under no legal sanction ; and which were therefore not admitted in evidence as registers in courts of justice.</p><p>In September 1836, a commission was issued, which has been renewed in the present reign, directing certain commissioners to inquire into the state, custody, and authenticity of such registers or records ; “ and to inquire whether any or what measures could be beneficially adopted for collecting and arranging all or any of such registers or records, and for depositing the same, or copies thereof, in the office of the registrar-general of births, deaths, and marriages, or for otherwise preserving the same ; and also to consider and advise the proper measures to be adopted for giving full force and effect in evidence, in all courts of justice, to all such registers as might be found accurate and faithful, and for facilitating the production and reception of the same.” The commissioners have reported the result of their labours, from which report it appears, that about 7000 non-parochial registers have been transmitted to them for inspection from 3630 religious congregations, namely,</p><p>Foreign Protestant churches......................37</p><p>Presbyterians, Independents, and Baptists...2264</p><p>Wesleyan Methodists..............................618</p><p>Moravians.............................................10</p><p>Lady Huntingdon’s Connection..................44</p><p>Calvinistic Methodists.............................436</p><p>Swedenborgians.....................................21</p><p>Total..................3430</p><p>“ Each of these registers,” says the Report, “ was authenticated by a certificate under the signature of the minister, or of some officer of the church or denomination, from whom it was received ; and this certificate was generally accompanied by answers to the questions which had been circulated by the commissioners.” After being “ classed</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>