<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>where they formed a solemn alliance and confederacy, with the intention of defending vigorously their religion and liberties against the dangers and encroachments with which they were threatened by the edict of Augsburg, without attempting, however, any thing offensive against the votaries of Rome ; they invited the kings of England, France, and Denmark, to join this confederacy, leaving no means unemployed that might strengthen and cement so important an alliance.</p><p>This confederacy was at first opposed by Luther, from an apprehension of the calamities and troubles which it might produce ; but at last, perceiving the necessity of concert, he consented, though he uncharitably, as well as imprudently, refused to comprehend in it the followers of Zuing-lius amongst the Swiss, as well as the German states and cities which had adopted the sentiments and confession of Bucer. In the invitation addressed to Henry VIII. of England, whom the confederate princes were willing to declare the head and protector of their league, the following things, amongst others, were expressly stipulated : That the king should encourage, promote, and maintain, the true doctrine of Christ as it was contained in the Confession of Augsburg, and defend the same at the next general council ; that he should not agree to any council summoned by the bishop of Rome, but protest against it, and neither submit to its decrees, nor suffer them to be respected in his dominions ; that he should never allow the Roman pontiff to have any pre-eminence or jurisdiction in his dominions, and should advance 100,000 crowns for the use of the confederacy, engaging to double the sum if necessary : all which articles the confederate princes were equally obliged to observe upon their part. To these demands the king replied, that he would maintain and promote the true doctrine of Christ ; but, at the same time, as the true ground of that doctrine lay only in the Holy Scriptures, he would not accept at any one’s hand what should be his own faith, or that of his kingdom ; and therefore desired that they would send over two learned men to confer with him, in order to promote a religious union between him and the confederates. He, however, declared himself of their opinion with regard to the meeting of a free general council, and promised to join with them in all such councils for the defence of the true doctrine ; but he thought the regulation of the ceremonial part of religion, being comparatively a matter of indifference, should be left to the choice of each sovereign for his own dominions. Subsequently the king gave them a second and more satisfactory answer ; but after the execution of Anne Boleyn, this negotiation came to nothing. On the one hand, the king grew cold when he perceived that the confederates were no longer of use to him in supporting the validity of his marriage ; and, on the other, the German princes became sensible that they could never succeed with Henry, unless they allowed him an absolute dictatorship in matters of religion.</p><p>Whilst everything thus tended to an open war between the opposite parties, the Elector Palatine and the Elector of Mentz offered their mediation, and endeavoured to bring about a reconciliation. The emperor himself, for various reasons, was at this time inclined to peace. For, on the one hand, he stood in need of succours against the Turks, which the Protestant princes refused to grant as long as the edicts of Worms and Augsburg remained in force ; and, on the other, the election of his brother Ferdinand to the dignity of king of the Romans, which had been carried by a majority of votes at the Diet of Cologne in 1531, was by the same princes contested, as being contrary to the fundamental laws of the empire. In consequence of all this, after many negotiations and projects of reconciliation, a treaty of peace was concluded at Nuremberg in 1532, between the emperor and the Protestant princes, on the following conditions, viz. That the latter should furnish a subsidy for carrying on the war against the Turks, and acknowledge Ferdinand as lawful king of the Romans ; and that the emperor upon his part should abrogate and annul the edicts of Worms and Augsburg, and allow the Lutherans the free and undisturbed exercise of their religious doctrine and discipline, until a rule of faith should be fixed either in the free general council which was to be assembled in the space of six months, or in a diet of the empire.</p><p>Soon after the conclusion of the peace of Nuremberg, died JoIm elector of Saxony, who was succeeded by his son John Frederick, a prince of invincible fortitude and magnanimity, but whose reign was little better than one continued series of disappointments and calamities. The religious truce, however, gave new vigour to the Reformation. Those who had hitherto been only secret enemies of the Roman pontiff, now publicly threw off his yoke ; and various cities and provinces of Germany enlisted themselves under the religious banners of Luther. On the other hand, as the emperor had now no other hope of terminating the religious disputes except by the meeting of a general council, he repeated his request to the ι&gt;ontiff that such a council should be assembled. But Pope Clement VII., whom the history of past councils filled with the greatest uneasiness, endeavoured to retard what he could not with decency refuse. At last, in the year 1533, he made a proposal by his legate to assemble a council at Mantua, Piacenza, or Bologna ; but the Protestants refused their consent to the nomination of an Italian council, and insisted that a controversy which had its rise in the heart of Germany should be determined within the limits of the empire. The pope, by his usual artifices, eluded compliance with this demand, and, in 1534, he was cut off by death, before any determination could be come to. His successor Paul III. seemed to show less reluctance to the assembling of a general council, and in 1535 expressed his inclination to convoke one at Mantua ; and, the year following, he actually sent circular letters for that purpose throughout all the states and kingdoms under his jurisdiction. Tllis council was summoned by a bull issued on tile 2d of June 1536, to meet at Mantua in the Ibllowingyear. But several obstacles prevented its meeting ; one of the most material of which was, that Frederick duke of Mantua had no inclination to receive at once so many guests, some of them very turbulent, into the place of his residence. On the other hand, the Protestants were firmly persuaded that, as the council was to be assembled in Italy, and by the authority of the pope alone, the latter must have an undue influence in that assembly; and, consequently, that all things would be carried by the votaries of Rome. For this reason they assembled in the year 1537 at Smalcald, where they solemnly protested against this partial and corrupt council, and, at the same time, had a new summary of their doctrine drawn up by Luther, in order to present it to the assembled bishops if it should be required of them. This summary, which received the title of the Articles of Smalcald, is commonly conjoined with the creeds and confessions of the Lutheran church.</p><p>After the meeting of the general council in Mantua had thus been prevented, many schemes of accommodation were proposed both by the emperor and by the Protestants ; but, by the artifices of the Church of Rome, all of them came to nothing. In 1541, the emperor appointed a conference to be held at Worms on the subject of religion, between persons of piety and learning chosen from the contending parties. This conference, however, was, for certain reasons, removed to the diet which was to be held at Ratisbon that year, and in which the principal subject of deliberation was a memorial presented by a person unknown, containing a project of peace. But the conference produced no other effect than a mutual agreement of the contending parties to refer their matters to a general council, or, if the meeting of such a council should be prevented, to the next German Diet.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>