<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>the southern, Beira-Mar, or Sea-coast. These again are subdivided, the former into the districts of Paraiba Nova and Canto Gallo, the latter into Rio Janeiro, Bha Grande, Cape Frio, and Goytacazes. The Organ Mountains derive their extraordinary appellation from the appearance of their pyramidal heads of granite, which bristle up along the horizon, and bear a fanciful resemblance to organ-pipes in a vast cathedral. The whole province is well watered by a number of streams, the most considerable being the Paraiha. This river originates in a small lake in the southern part of the Serra da Bocania, a continuation of the Organ Mountains. It flows first into the province of San Paulo ; but after a long and winding course it re-enters the province in which it rose, and disembogues in its eastern part. The Rio de Janeiro is a misnomer, from De Sousa, the discoverer of this part of the country, having mistaken the salt bay or gulf, so called, for the mouth of a river. Many streams discharge themselves into this bay towards its upper end, several of them being navigable to some distance. Among these may be mentioned the Iraja, which issues from a small lake, and affords navigation with the tide to its port of the same name ; the Miriti, which traverses a marshy country, but whose banks have a very rich soil, and produce abundance of sugar, milho, and mandioc ; the Iguassu, which is navigable for four leagues, and has for a tributary the Iguare, a stream affording navigation for a mile to the port of the same name ; the Maraby, which flows from the Serra of Boavista, and is navigable to the port of Couto<hi rend="sub">1</hi> three leagues above its mouth ; the Inhumirim, a fine river, the banks of which, as well as those of its confluents, are well cultivated ; it is navigable for three leagues to the flourishing port of Estrella ; the Igu-apezu or Macacu, one of the largest streams which fall into the bay, being navigable for fifteen leagues, during which it receives several tributaries from the mountains ; the Suruhy, Mageassu, and Iguapimirim, which descend from the mountains. These and several other streams fall into the bay of Rio, and by their means different parts of the country to the northward of the capital may be visited with considerable facility. Near the right bank of the river Igua-pimirim is the parish of Ajuda, the soil of which is remarkably productive, and is planted with mandioc, rice, and coffee. Towns are in general situated on the banks of these streams, forming ports from which the products of the surrounding territory are embarked for the capital, the grand emporium of commerce. Lakes are very numerous in the province of Rio ; the most remarkable are the Ja-caré-Pagua, and the Roderigo de Freytas.</p><p>The principal bays by which the coast is indented are the bay of Rio de Janeiro, and Augra dos Reys or King’s Bay. The bay of Rio is stated to be no less than thirty-two miles in circumference, and on its shores are numerous smaller inlets, which may be termed sub-bays. All travellers agree in praising the surpassing grandeur and beauty of this majestic inlet of the sea. “ Nothing that I have ever seen,” says Mrs Graham, “ is comparable in beauty to this bay. Naples, the Frith of Forth, Bombay Harbour, and Trincomalee, each of which I thought perfect in its beauty, all must yield to this, which surpasses each in its different way.” This capacious basin is embosomed among elevated mountains, having conically shaped summits, and, being well wooded, are of romantic and picturesque beauty. Some of these advance a considerable distance into the bay, whilst others retire as far inland, leaving between them deep recesses and glens. The entrance of the bay is narrow, being only three quarters of a mile in breadth ; and its granite barriers are so bold, causing it to resemble a gap or chasm in the mountain ridge, that, doubtless, it was often passed by early navigators without their apprehending the existence of such an immense salt-water lake within. Being completely land-locked, and protected from gales on every side, it is perfectly secure, even for boats, at all seasons of the year ; from which circumstance, as well as from many other advantages which it possesses, it has been pronounced the finest harbour in the world. It is so well defended by strong forts that it seems completely closed against a hostile force. The bay is studded with about a hundred islands, on many of which are forts. That of Ilha dos Cobras, or Snake Island, is of great strength, and constitutes one of the most commanding points for the defence of the city. In short, the Brazilians and early subjugators of the country have carefully availed themselves of every advantage- presented by nature for rendering their capital unassailable by a maritime force. On either side the shores of the bay, lined at the water’s edge with cottages and hamlets of fishermen, sweep widely round ; while behind, hills in the richest state of cultivation, studded with farm-houses and villas, and crowned with churches and monasteries, all of purest white, rise abruptly on every side, till, a few miles inland, they terminate in the bold, beautiful, and picturesque ranges of the Organ Mountains.</p><p>With the exception of the capital, there are few places in the province of Rio which require particular notice. Canto Gallo is the capital of a district of amazing fertility, and carries on considerable trade with Rio in the productions of the soil. Porto d’Estrella and Mage are the names of other towns which also carry on a great deal of traffic with the capital. The productions of this province comprise almost every thing for which Brazil is celebrated ; diamonds and precious stones, sugar, coffee, cotton, and, in short, all fruits peculiar to the tropics, are here produced in the richest abundance, and of the most excellent quality.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">City of Rio. The city of St Sebastian, now universally called Rio de Janeiro, the capital of the Brazilian empire, is situated on the south-western side of the bay or harbour just described, about four miles from its entrance. It occupies the north-east part of a tongue of land of an irregularly quadrangular shape, and extending on an inclined plane, a short distance into the bay. The town itself, which also exhibits the form of a parallelogram, and rises between four fortified eminences, which flank it at each corner, presents a north-east aspect of the bay, whose waters wash three sides of the square promontory on which it stands. The site selected for their town by the early settlers is considered the best that could have been chosen, out of many excellent ones that everywhere present themselves. The most easterly point is the Punta do Calabouço ; the most northerly is the Armazem do Sal, opposite to which is the small island cf Ilha das Cobras. The most ancient and important part of the city is built between these two points along the shore, lying from north-west to south-east ; and a beautiful quay, constructed of solid blocks of chiselled granite, forms an elegant façade to it. The houses of Rio are neatly and substantially built, generally of granite, and two stories high, with little wooden balconies in front, the windows and doors being cased with hewn blocks of this stone, which the quarries at the end of every street supply in abundance, and of the finest quality. The lower stories are commonly occupied by shops and warehouses, and the upper ones by the family apartments. The whole town is disposed in squares, the streets crossing each other at right angles, and, although narrow, they are well paved, and lined at each side by flagged trottoirs. The style of architecture of the old town is in general mean, resembling that of the old part of Lisbon ; but the new town is in a much more handsome style. Although this town has always ranked as the most important in Brazil, or as second only to Bahia at the time when the latter was the seat of government ; yet it was only after the imperial residence and the court were fixed here that it assumed the character of a European city. Great improvements took place after that event. The new town has almost wholly sprung up</hi></p><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>