<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>transformed from HTML to TEI by eb-html2tei</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Principles of Political Economy. They contain a vindication of his own doctrines from the objections of Mr Malthus, and an exposition of the mistakes into which he conceives the latter had fallen.</p><p>Though not properly belonging to the Whig party, Mr Ricardo voted almost uniformly with them. He was fully impressed with a conviction of the many advantages that would result from giving the people a greater influence over the choice of their representatives in the House of Commons ; and was so far a friend to the system of the radical reformers, as to give his cordial support to the plan of voting by ballot, which he considered as the best if not the only means for securing the mass of the electors against improper solicitations, and enabling them to vote in favour of the candidates whom they really approved. He did not, however, agree with the radical reformers in their plan of universal suffrage : he thought the elective franchise should be given to all who possessed a certain amount of property ; but he was of opinion, that while it would be a very hazardous experiment, no practical good would result from giving the franchise indiscriminately to all.</p><p>When the circumstances under which the greater part of the life of Mr Ricardo was spent are brought under view, and when it is also recollected that he died at the early age of fifty· one, it may be truly said that very few men have ever achieved so much. His industry was quite unrivalled ; or if rivalled, it was only by his sagacity, his integrity, and his candour.</p><p>“ The history of Mr Ricardo,” to use the words of his friend Mr Mill, “ holds out a bright and inspiring example. Mr Ricardo had everything to do for himself, and he did everything. Let not the generous youth, whose aspirations are higher than his circumstances, despair of attaining either the highest intellectual excellence, or the highest influence on the welfare of his species, when he recollects in what circumstances Mr Ricardo opened, and in what he closed his memorable life. He had his fortune to make, his mind to form ; he had even his education to commence and conduct. In a field of the most intense competition he realized a large fortune, with the universal esteem and affection of those who could best judge of the honour and purity of his acts. Amid this scene of active exertion and practical detail, he cultivated and he acquired habits of intense and patient and comprehensive thinking, such as have been rarely equalled and never excelled.”</p><p>Mr Ricardo left a widow, three sons, and four daughters. One of his daughters died a few years before him, shortly after her marriage.    (c. c.)</p><p>RICAUT, or Rycaut, Sir Paul, an eminent English traveller, of the time of whose birth we find no account ; but in 1661 he was appointed secretary to the Earl of Win-chelsea, who was sent ambassador extraordinary to Turkey. During his continuance in that station he wrote “ The Present State of the Ottoman Empire, in three books, containing the maxims of the Turkish policy, their religion, and military discipline,” London, 1670; and he afterwards resided eleven years as consul at Smyrna, where, at the command of Charles II., he composed “ The Present State of the Greek and Arminian Churches, <hi rend="italic">anno Christi</hi>  1678.” On his return, Lord Clarendon being appointed lord lieutenant of Ireland, made him his principal secretary for Leinster and Connaught. King James II. knighted him, and made him one of the privy council in Ireland, and judge of the court of admiralty. These appointments he held till the Revolution. He was employed by King William as resident at the Hanse Towns, in Lower Saxony, where he continued for ten years ; but being worn out with age and infirmities, he obtained leave to return in 1700, and died the same year. Ricaut continued Knolles's History of the Turks, and Platina’s Lives of the Popes ; besides which there are some other productions which bear his name.</p><p>RICE. “ Rice <hi rend="italic">bras,"</hi>  says Mr Marsden, “ whilst in the husk, is in Indian called <hi rend="italic">paddee,</hi>  and assumes a different name in each of its other various states. We observe no distinction of this kind in Europe, where our grain retains through all its stages, till it becomes flour, its original name of barley, wheat, or oats. The following, besides many others, are names applied to rice in its different stages of growth and preparation : <hi rend="italic">paddee,</hi>  original name of the seed ; <hi rend="italic">oossαy,</hi>  grain of last season ; <hi rend="italic">bunnee,</hi>  the plants before removed to the sawoors ; <hi rend="italic">bras,</hi>  or <hi rend="italic">bray,</hi>  rice, the husk of the paddee being taken off ; <hi rend="italic">charroop,</hi>  rice cleaned for boiling ; <hi rend="italic">ηassee,</hi>  boiled rice ; <hi rend="italic">peerang,</hi>  yellow rice; <hi rend="italic">jambar,</hi>  a service of rice, &amp;c.</p><p>“ Among people whose general objects of contemplation are few, those which do of necessity engage their attention are often more nicely discriminated than the same objects among more enlightened people, whose ideas, ranging over the extensive field of art and science, disdain to fix long on obvious and common matters. <hi rend="italic">Paddee,</hi>  in Sumatra and the Malay Islands, is distinguished into two sorts ; <hi rend="italic">laddang</hi>  or upland paddee, and <hi rend="italic">sawoor</hi>  or lowland, which are always kept separate, and will not grow reciprocally. Of these, the former bears the higher price, being a whiter, heartier, and better-flavoured grain, and having the advantage in point of keeping. The latter is much more prolific from the seed, and liable to less risk in the culture, but is of a watery substance, produces less increase in boiling, and is subject to a swifter decay. It is, however, in more common use than the former. Besides this general distinction, the paddee of each sort, particularly the laddang, presents a variety of species, which, as far as my information extends, I shall enumerate and endeavour to describe. The common kind of dry ground paddee ; colour light brown ; the size rather large, and very little crooked at the extremity. Paddee <hi rend="italic">undal-long ;</hi>  dry ground; short round grain; grows in whorls or bunches round the stock. Paddee <hi rend="italic">Mass ;</hi>  dry ground ; large grain ; common. Paddee <hi rend="italic">gαlloo ;</hi>  dry ground ; light coloured ; scarce. Paddee <hi rend="italic">sennee ;</hi>  dry ground ; deep coloured ; small grain ; scarce. Paddee <hi rend="italic">ejoo ;</hi>  dry ground ; light coloured. Paddee <hi rend="italic">kooning ;</hi>  dry ground ; deep yellow ; fine rice ; crooked and pointed. Paddee <hi rend="italic">coocoor badium ;</hi>  dry ground ; much esteemed ; light coloured : small, and very much crooked, resembling a dove’s nail, from whence its name. <hi rend="italic">Paddee pesang ;</hi>  dry ground ; outer coat light brown ; inner red ; longer, smaller, and less crooked than the <hi rend="italic">coocoor bαllum,</hi>  Paddee <hi rend="italic">santong ;</hi>  the finest sort that is planted in wet ground; small, straight, and light coloured. In general it may be observed that the larger grained rice is the least esteemed, and the smaller and whiter the most prized. In the Lampoon country they make a distinction of paddee <hi rend="italic">crawrang</hi>  and paddee <hi rend="italic">jerroo ;</hi>  the former of which is a month earlier in growth than the latter.”</p><p>The following is the Chinese method of cultivating rice, as it is stated by Sir George Staunton : “ Much of the low grounds in the middle and southern provinces of the empire are appropriated to the culture of that grain. It constitutes, in fact, the principal part of the food of all those inhabitants who are not so indigent as to be forced to subsist on other and cheaper kinds of grain. A great proportion of the surface of the country is well adapted for the production of rice, which, from the time the seed is committed to the soil till the plant approaches to maturity, requires to be immersed in a sheet of water. Many and great rivers run through the principal provinces of China, the low grounds bordering on those rivers are annually inundated, by which means is brought upon their surface a rich mud or mucilage that fertilizes the soil, in the same manner as Egypt receives its fecundative quality from the overflowing of the Nile. The periodical rains which fall near the sources of the Yellow and the Kiang rivers, not very far distant from those of the Ganges and the Burumpooter, among</p></body></text></TEI>