<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0715.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0709-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPOTSWOOD</label>
(John), archbiſhop of St Andrew’s in Scotland, was deſcended from the lairds of Spotſwood in the Merſe, and was born in the year 1565. He was educated in the univerſity of Glaſgow, and ſucceeded his father in the parſonage of Calder when but 18 years of age. In 1601 he attended Lodowick duke of Lennox as his chaplain, in an embaſſy to the court of France for confirming the ancient amity between the two nations, and returned in the ambaſſador’s retinue through England. When he entered into the archbiſhopric of Glasgow, he found there was not 100 l. Sterling of yearly revenue left ; yet ſuch was his care for his ſucceſſors, that he greatly improved it, and much to the satisfaction of his dioceſe. After having filled this ſee 11 years, he was raised to that of St Andrew’s in 1615, and made primate and metropolitan of all Scotland. He presided in ſeveral aſſemblies for reſtoring the ancient diſcipline, and bringing the church of Scotland to ſome sort of uniformity with that of England. He continued in high esteem with king James I. nor was he leſs valued by king Charles I. who was crowmed by him in 1633, in the abbey-church of Holyroodhouſe. In 1635, upon the death of the earl of Kinnoul chancellor of Scotland, our primate was advanced to that poll ; but had ſcarcely held it four years, when the contuſions beginning in Scotland, he was obliged to retire into England ; and being broken with age, grief, and ſickness, died at London in<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0716.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0710"/>
1639, and was interred in Weſtminſter-abbey. He wrote A Hiſtory of the Church of Scotland from the year 203 to the reign oſ king James VI. in folio.</p></div></body></text></TEI>