<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0683.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0677-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPECTRE</label>,
an apparition, ſomething made preternaturally viſible to human ſight, whether the ghoſts of dead men or beings superior to man.</p><p>A belief that ſupernatural beings ſometimes make themſelves viſible, and that the dead ſometimes reviſit the living, has prevailed among moſt nations, eſpecially in the rudeſt stages of ſociety. It was common among the Jews, among the Greeks, and among the Romans, as we find from the Scriptures, and from the poems of Homer and Virgil. Celeſtial appearances were indeed ſo often exhibited to the Jews, that the origin of their belief is not difficult to be explained.— The Divine Being manifeſted himſelf to each of the Patriarchs by ſome ſenſible ſign, generally by a flame of fire, as he did to Moſes. Under this ſemblance alſo did he appear to the Iſraelites during their abode in the defert, and after they obtained a ſettlement in the land of Canaan. Nor did they believe that heavenly beings alone affirmed a ſenſible appearance : They believed that deceaſed men alſo ſometimes reviſited this world. When Saul went to conſult the witch at Endor, he asked her to bring up the perſon whom he ſhould name unto her ; a proof that he considered his demand as eaſy to be performed, and therefore that he probably acted under the influence of popular opinion. The ſame opinions had been generally entertained at a much earlier period ; for necromancy and witchcraft, the arts by which the dead were ſuppoſed to be raiſed, had been prohibited while the Iſraelites were in the wilderneſs, and yet untainted with the vices of the Canaanites. They muſt therefore have derived them from Egypt, the cradle of ſuperſtition, as well as of the arts and ſciences.</p><p>Among the Greeks and Romans the apparition of ſpectres was generally believed. On innumerable occa- ſions the gods are ſaid to have diſcovered themſelves to the eyes of mortals, to have held conferences, and to have interpoſed their aid. The ghoſts of the dead, too, are ſaid to have appeared. When Æneas, amidſt the diffraction and confusion of his mind in flying from the deſtruction of Troy, had loft his wife by the way, he returned in ſearch of her. Her ſhade appeared to him (for ſhe herſelf had been ſlain) with the ſame aſpect as before, but her figure was larger. She endeavoured to aſſuage the grief of her unhappy husband, by aſcribing her death to the appointment of the gods, and by foretelling the illuſtrious honours which yet awaited him. But when Æneas attempted to claſp her in his arms, the phantom immediately vaniſhed into air. From this ſtory we may obſerve, that the ancients believed that the um- bræ or ſhades, retained nearly the ſame appearance after death as before; that they had ſo far the resemblance of a body as to be viſible ; that they could think and ſpeak as formerly, but could not be touched. This deſcription applies equally well to thoſe ſhades which had paſſed the river Styx, and taken up their residence in the infernal regions. Such were the ſhades of Dido, of Deiphobus, and all thoſe which Æneas met with in his journey through the ſubterraneous world.</p><p>It appears from the writings of modern travellers who have viſited rude and ſavage nations, that the belief of ſpectres is no leſs common among them. Mr Bruce tells us, that the prieſt of the Nile affirmed, that he had more than once seen the ſpirit of the river in the form of an old man with a white beard. Among the Mahometans the doctrine of ſpectres ſeems to be reduced to a regular ſyſtem, by the accounts which they give of genii. Whoever has read the Arabian Nights Entertainments muſt have furniſhed his memory with a thou- ſand inſtances of this kind. Their opinions concerning genii ſeem to be a corrupted mixture of the doctrines of the Jews and ancient Perſians. In Chriſtian countries, too, notwithſtanding the additional light which their religion has ſpread, and the great improvement in the ſciences to which it has been ſubſervient, the belief of ghoſts and apparitions is very general, eſpecially among the lower ranks. They believe that evil ſpirits ſometimes make their appearance in order to terrify wicked men, eſpecially thoſe who have committed murder.— They ſuppoſe that the ſpirits of dead men aſſume a corporeal appearance, hover about church yards and the houſes of the deceaſed, or haunt the places where murders have been committed. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ghost.)</hi> In ſome places it is believed that beings have been ſeen bearing a perfect reſemblance to men alive. In the Highlands of Scotland, what is called the ſecond ſight is ſtill believed by many (ſee <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Second</hi> <hi rend="italic">Sight)</hi>; viz. that future events are foretold by certain individuals by means of spectral repreſentation.</p><p>So general has the belief of ſpectres been, that this circumſtance alone may be thought by ſome ſufficient to prove that it muſt have its foundation in human nature, or muſt rest upon rational evidence. When any doctrine has been univerſally received by all nations, by generations living ſeveral thouſand years from one another, and by people in all the different ſtages of ſociety, there is certainly the ſtrongeſt preſumption to conclude that ſuch a doctrine has its foundation in reaſon and in truth. In this way we argue in favour of the exiſtence of a. God, concerning moral diſtinction, and the doctrine of a future ſtate : and certainly ſo far we argue well. But if the ſame. argument be applied to idolatry, to ſacrifices, or to apparitions, we ſhall find that it is applied improperly. Idolatry was very general among ancient nations ; ſo was the offering of ſacrifices,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0684.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0678"/>
ſo was polytheiſm : but they were by no means univerſal. Should we allow, for the fake of ſhortening the argument, that all ancient nations were polytheiſts and idolaters, and presented oblations to their imaginary deities, all that could be concluded from this conceſſion is, that they fell into these miſtakes from their ignorance and from the rude ſtate of ſociety, from which their imperfect knowledge of theology and moral philoſophy was never able to reſcue them. Theſe erroneous notions fled before the brightneſs of the Chriſtian ſyſtem; while the doctrines of the exiſtence of God, of moral diſtinction, and of a future ſtate, have been more thoroughly confirmed and aſcertained. The ſame thing may be laid of the belief of ſpectres. However generally it has been adopted in the firſt ſtages of ſocſety, or by civilized nations who had made but little progreſs in the ſtudy of divine things, it has been rejected, we may ſay invariably, wherever theology and philoſophy have gone hand in hand.</p><p>As all popular and long eſtabliſhed opinions are objects of curioſity and reſearch for the philoſopher, we think the belief of ſpectres worthy of some attention even in this light. It will therefore, we hope, give ſome ſatisfaction to the philosophical reader to ſee a ſhort account of the ſources or principles from which this belief is derived. But as the belief of ſpectres is connected with other opinions which appear to us highly injurious to religion ; opinions which have been supported by many learned men, and which are ſtill believed by ſome men of literary education — it will alſo be proper, in the firſt place, to conſider the evidence on which this belief reſts, in which we muſt conſider both their probability and credibility.</p><p>In the preſent inveſtigation we mean to ſet aſide altogether the celeſtial appearances recorded in Scripture, as being founded on unqueſtionable evidence, and perfectly agreeable to thoſe rules by which the Deity acts in the uſual courſe of his Providence. The Iſraelites, during the exiſtence of their ſtate, were immediately under the authority of God, not only as the moral governor of the world, but as the king of Iſrael. In the infancy of the world, while men were rude and unenlightened, and entirely under the influence of idolatry, many revelations were neceſſary to preſerve in their minds pure ideas of the nature of God, and of the worship due to Him. They were neceſſary alſo to pave the way for that illuſtrious diſpenſation which the Lord Jeſus came from Heaven to diffuſe over the world. Every celeſtial appearance recorded in Scripture was exhibited for ſome wile and important purpoſe, which muſt be apparent to every perſon who conſiders theſe appearances with attention. But when the Scriptures were written and publiſhed, and the Chriſtian religion fully eſtabliſhed, revelation ceaſed, and miracles and heavenly meſsages were no longer requiſite. What credit then ought we to give to thoſe marvellous ſtories related in ancient authors concerning prodigies in the heavens, and the apparition of angels both good and bad ?</p><p>It is not pretended that any of thoſe prodigies and appearances were exhibited for purpoſes equally great and important with thoſe which are deſcribed in Scripture : And can we ſuppoſe that the all-wise Governor of the World would permit his angele to render themſelves viſible to the eye of man for no purpoſe at all, or for a purpoſe which might have been equally well accompliſhed without their interpoſition ? Would this be conſiſtent with perfect wiſdom, or would it be conſiſtent even with the excellence and ſuperiority of underſtanding which we are taught to aſcribe to theſe elevated beings ? The whole will of God is revealed to us in the Scriptures ; what further uſe for the visible interpoſition of angels ? It may be objected, Are they not all miniſtering ſpirits ſent forth to miniſter for them who ſhall be heirs of ſalvation<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>*Heb. 14.</p></note> * ? We anſwer, That angels may animate and ſupport good men by an inviſible interpoſition. But the Apoſtle is not ſpeaking of celeſtial ſpirits. The word ανγελος signifies “ a meſſenger ;” and in Scripture often refers to men. In the passage which we are now reviewing it certainly is applied with much more propriety to men than to angels : for the Apoſtle is ſtating a companion between <hi rend="italic">the Prophets,</hi> by whom God, at ſundry times and in divers manners, ſpake in time paſt to the fathers, and <hi rend="italic">the Son,</hi> by whom he hath ſpoken in theſe laſt days.</p><p>And if God has given no commiſſion to his angels to deliver to men since the publication of the Chriſtian religion, is there any probability that he would give any commiſſion or any licence to evil ſpirits ? It will be ſaid, that this doctrine is clearly taught in the New Testament, in theſe words, “ The devil goeth about as a roaring lion ſeeking whom he may devour,” We will not avail ourſelves of the interpretation of ſome, who ſay that the word <hi rend="italic">devil,</hi> which in the Greek language ſignifies an <hi rend="italic">adverſary,</hi> or s <hi rend="italic">landerer,</hi> refers here to ſome human being, who was a violent enemy of the Chriſtians. All that can be deduced from theſe words, upon the ſuppoſition that they reſer to a malignant ſpirit, is merely that he goeth about ſeducing men to vice. But it is not by aſſuming a hideous form, and preſenting himſelf to the midnight traveller, that ſuch a purpoſe is to be accompliſhed. A ſpirit may probably have direct acceſs to our minds without the intervention of any thing corporeal ; and by exciting our paſſions may plunge us into vice, which is the only object ſuch a being is ſuppoſed to have in view. None of the marvellous ſtories which we have heard concerning the apparition of evil ſpirits lead us to conclude that they appear to entice men to commit crimes. We never heard of any evil ſpirits that required men to ſteal, to perpetrate robbery or murder. They only appeared to terrify ſome crazy timorous individuals, who have whims and fancies enow of their own to agitate their minds, though no preternatural vision ſhould ever appear to them. It is not conſiſtent, therefore, with the character of God, and what he has revealed to us of his will, to believe that he would commiſſion good angels, or permit evil angels, to appear to men since the propagation of the goſpel, or indeed at any former period of the world, unleſs ſome great and mighty purpoſe was to be fulfilled. It is not conſiſtent with what we know of the nature of good or bad angels to ſuppoſe, that though permiſſion were granted them occasionally to ſhow themſelves to men, that they would appear in that way which ſtorytellers deſcribe.</p><p>It is equally improbable that the ſpirits of the dead who have removed from this world ſhould again be permitted to viſit it. At death men undergo as great, perhaps a greater change, than when they came firſt into the light of the ſun. Is it not therefore as improbable that a man ſhould return in a viſible corporeal<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0685.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0679"/>
<hi rend="italic">form</hi> after death, as that, after having arrived at manhood, he ſhould return to the ſtate in which he was before his birth ? Such changes as theſe are evidently made permanent by the invariable laws of nature. But ſuppoſe it were poſſible, for what purpoſe ſhould they return ? To deſcribe to us what is paſſing in the other world, to animate us to virtue, by informing us of the rewards which there await the good ; or to alarm us, by deſcribing the puniſhment of the wicked. Theſe ſeem important reaſons. But Divine Providence has wiſely thrown a veil over futurity. We know every thing of the other world from the ſcripture which it is proper for us at preſent to know. And as to incentives to virtue, we are already bleſſed with a number sufficiently great and powerful for moral beings, who are to act from rational motives, and not from compulſion. “ He that will not hear Moſes and the prophets, will not be perſuaded though one rose from the dead.”</p><p>There is one ſtrong objection againſt the probability of ſpectres, which is sufficient to prove that they are not intelligent creatures ; or at leaſt that they poſſeſs ſo ſmall a degree of intelligence, that they are unqualified to act with prudence, to propoſe any end to themſelves, or use the proper means to accompliſh that end. Ghoſts often appear in order to diſcover ſome crime that has been committed : but they never appear to a magiſtrate, or perſon in authority, but to ſome illiterate clown, who happens to live near the place where the crime was perpetrated ; to ſome perſon who has no connection with the affair at all, and who in general is the moſt improper in the world for making the diſcovery. For inſtance, in Glanville’s <hi rend="italic">Saduciſmus triumphatus</hi> (a book written in the laſt century by a chaplain of Charles II. in ſupport of the common opinions reſpecting witchcraft and apparitions), we have the following ſtory : James Haddock, a farmer, was married to Elenor Welſh, by whom he had a ſon. After the death of Haddock, his wife married one Davis; and both agreed to defraud the ſon by the former marriage of a leaſe bequeathed to him by his father. Upon this the ghoſt of Haddock appeared to one Francis Taverner the ſervant of lord Chicheſter, and desired him to <hi rend="italic">go to</hi> Elenor Welſh, and to inform her that it was the will of her former husband that their ſon ſhould enjoy the leaſe. Taverner did not at firſt execute this commiſſion ; but he was continually haunted by the apparition in the moſt hideous ſhapes, which even threatened to tear him in pieces, till at laſt he delivered the meſſage. Now, had this ſpectre had the leaſt common ſenſe, it would have appeared firſt to Elenor Welſh and her husband Davis, and frightened them into compliance at once, and not have kept poor Taverner in ſuch confiant diſquietude, who had no concern in the matter.</p><p>Another very odd circumſtance reflecting apparitions in general muſt not be omitted, which is, that they have no power to ſpeak till they are addreſſed. In the 27th of Glanville’s Relations we read of an old woman that appeared often to David Hunter, a neat-herd, at the house of the Bishop of Down and Conners. Whenever ſhe appeared, he found himſelf obliged to follow her ; and for three quarters of a year poor David spent the whole of almoſt every night in ſcampering up and down through the woods after this old woman. How long this extraordinary employment might have continued, it is impoſſible to guess, had not David’s violent fatigue made him one night exclaim, “ Lord bleſs me ! would I were dead!—ſhall I never be delivered from this miſery !” On which the phantom replied, “ Lord bleſs me too ! It was happy you ſpoke firſt, for till then I had no power to ſpeak, though I have followed you ſo long.” Then ſhe gave him a meſſage to her two ſons, though David told her he remembered nothing about her. David, it ſeems, neglected to deliver the message ; at which the old beldam was ſo much provoked, that ſhe returned and hit him a hearty blow on the ſhoulder, which made him cry out, and then ſpeak to her. Now if ſhe could not ſpeak till David addreſſed her, why might ſhe not have applied this oratorial medicine the firſt time ſhe appeared to him ? It would have ſaved both herſelf and him many a weary journey ; and certainly David would much rather have had even half a dozen of blows from her choppy fills than have wanted ſo many nights ſleep. To complete the ſtory, we muſt add, that when David s wife found it impoſſible to keep him from following the troubleſome visitor, ſhe trudged after him, but never was gratified with a fight of the enchantreſs. David’s little dog too was a dutiful attendant on his maſter during his pilgrim mage.</p><p>It is remarked by Glanville, that ghoſts are generally very eager to be gone; Indeed they are often ſo much ſo, that they do not ſtay to tell their errand. One would be induced from this, as well as the circumſtances already mentioned, to think that they are the stupidest and dullest of the dead that affirme the appearance of ghoſts ; unleſs we adopt the ingenious ſolution of Glanville, “ that it is a very hard and painſul thing for them to force their thin and tenuious bodies into a visible conſiſtence ; that their bodies muſt needs be exceedingly compreſſed ; and that therefore they muſt be in haste to be delivered from the unnatural preſſure.”</p><p>With reſpect to the <hi rend="italic">evidence</hi> in favour of ſpectres, if examined ever ſo ſlightly, it will be found very defective. They only appear to one perſon at a time ; they are ſeen only in the night ; they are viſible only to ignorant, illiterate, and credulous perſons, and never preſent themſelves before men of education and learning.</p><p>That ſpectres only appear to one perſon at a time, even though there are more in company, is an objection againſt the credibility of their appearance quite insurmountable. How is it poſſible that two men of eyesight equally good, directing their eyes to the same ſpot, ſhould not ſee ſo large an object as that of a man. or woman at a ſmall diſtance equally well ? Some will tell us that a mist is caſt over the eyes of the one, while the vicw of the other is free from obſtruction. But how is this to be proved ? and besides what purpoſe would it ſerve ? Ghoſts have ſeldom any ſecrets to diſcloſe ; they might be proclaimed to a multitude with as much propriety as confined to one perſon. Shall we be told, that the ſpectre has the power of becoming visible to ſome, and of remaining inviſible to others ? This cannot be allowed without adopting opinions deſtructive to revealed religion ; for it would be a miracle : and we cannot be persuaded, without evidence, that God would empower any inferior being to controul at pleaſure the wise laws which he has ordained for governing the world. To him who is of a different opinion, we<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0686.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0680"/>
would recommend Farmer on Miracles ; a book in which this queſtion is fully examined.</p><p>Spectres appear only in the night. But why ſhould they ſhun the light of the ſun ? Thoſe miſchievous ghoſts that Glanville mentions might indeed have ſome reason to chooſe midnight for the execution of their pranks, as they would be more eaſily detected in open day. Such was the roguiſh drummer that haunted Mr Mompeſſon’s houſe, who beat his drum all night, threw the old gentlewoman’s clothes about the room, hid her Bible in the aſhes, plucked the clothes off the bed, and amuſed himſelf with toſſing about Mr Mom. pesson’s ſhoes. But why ſhould a grave ſerious ghoſt appear at midnight ? Might it not deliver its message with as much eaſe and more ſucceſs in the day-time ? In the day-time it would not excite much fear ; it would be liſtened to therefore with more attention; and did it chooſe to exhibit itself before a number of witneſſes, its grievances would be more ſpeedily redreſſed, becauſe more perſons would intereſt themſelves in ſeeing juſtice done to the injured ghoſt.</p><p>Spectres not only chooſe the most improper time, but the moſt improper perſons. To render the teſtimony of any perſon credible, he muſt not only be a man of veracity, but he muſt have sufficient ability to judge of the ſubject to which he is to bear witneſs. It is not on the evidence of an ignorant illiterate perſon, who has more fancy and fear than judgment, that we are to rest our belief of what is ſupernatural. It is also worthy of remark, that we have never heard of a ghoſt appearing to any perſon who did not previouſly believe their exiſtence. A man muſt be prejudiced in favour of this opinion, or he will never ſee a ghoſt. But ſenſible men know, that he who has been accuſtomed to hear frightful ſtories of ghoſts and apparitions gliding thro’ a church-yard, or haunting ſome particular place, can ſcarcely paſs through a church-yard or haunted ſpot without conjuring up in his imagination the hideous phantoms which he has been accuſtomed to aſſociate with ſuch places. Is it ſtrange, then, that an ignorant man, with a mind uncultivated and uninformed, with all the prejudices of the nurſery about him, ſhould imagine he ſees ghoſts in thoſe places where he believes they hover, eſpecially in the dead hour of midnight, when, with the ſlighteſt aid of the imagination, a cow may be turned into a monſtrous phantom, and the reflection of the beams of the moon from a little water be converted into a ghoſt with a winding-ſheet ? But why ſhould apparitions ſhun men of underſtanding and learning ? Why ſhould learning be formidable to them<note anchored="true" n="2" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> The celebrated hiſtorian De Thou had a very singular adventure at Saumur, in the year 1598. One night, having retired to rest very much fatigued, while he was enjoying a found ſleep, he felt a very extraordinary weight upon his feet, which, having made him turn ſuddenly, fell down and awakened him. At firſt he imagined that it had been only a dream, but hearing soon after ſome noiſe in his chamber, he drew aſide the curtains, and ſaw, by help of the moon, which at that time ſhone very bright, a large white figure walking up and down, and at the ſame time obſerved upon a chair ſome rags, which he thought belonged to thieves who had come to rob him. The figure then approaching his bed, he had the courage to aſk it what it was. “ I am (ſaid it) the Queen of Heaven.” Had ſuch a figure appeared to any credulous ignorant man in the dead of night, and made ſuch a ſpeech, would he not have trembled with fear, and have frightened the whole neighbourhood with a marvellous deſcription of it ? But De Thou had too much underſtanding to be so impoſed upon. Upon hearing the words which dropped from the figure, he immediately concluded that it was ſome mad woman, got up, called his ſervants, and ordered them to turn her out of doors ; after which he returned to bed and fell aſleep. Next morning he found that he had not been deceived in his conjecture, and that having forgot to ſhut his door, this female figure had eſcaped from her keepers, and entered his apartment. The brave Schomberg, to whom De Thou related his adventure ſome days after, confessed that in ſuch a caſe he would not have shown ſo much courage. The king also who was informed of it by Schomberg, made the same acknowledgement.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a) ?</hi> it was not ſo with the celeſtial meſſengers mentioned in the Scriptures : they appeared to the patriarchs and prophets ; and the miracles there recorded were performed in the moſt public places, before the eyes of Rabbies, of Scribes, and Phariſees. Indeed this circumſtance is sufficient to deſtroy the evidence of ſpectres. They have never been ſeen by any but men of weak or diſtempered minds, or by men who have previouſly believed in them.</p><p>Having now conſidered the evidence on which the belief of ſpectres reſts, we will endeavour to give ſome account of the foundation of it. To trace an opinion that has prevailed ſo generally in the world to its ſource, is a labour not unworthy of the philoſopher, even tho’ the opinion be falſe. It is always gratifying to detect the cauſes of error : it is no leſs uſeful ; for in order to refute error, it is often sufficient to point out the ſources from which it has ſprung. To reach the origin of the belief of ſpectres is not more difficult than to account for idolatry or polytheiſm. In the infant ſtate of the intellectual powers every thing is conſidered as posseſſing life and intelligence. The child beats the ſtool over which he has fallen with the same passion that he would treat his companion : The young girl talks to her doll as if it underſtood her : The ſavages aſcribe every change which they obſerve on the face of nature to the action of ſome animated being. As knowledge advances, they single out thoſe beings which ſeem to produce the moſt ſtriking effects, arrange them into ſome kind of order, and divide the government of the world among them. Unable, at the ſame time, to conceive any nation of a pure ſpirit, they imagine thoſe divinities are corporeal beings. This is the foundation of idolatry. The belief of ſpectres is but another ſtep. That theſe animated corporeal beings, to whom they addreſs their prayers, and who preside ‘over the world, ſhould on particular occaſions display themſelves to the human eye, is what they muſt be previouſly diſpoſed to expect. Hence the numberleſs appearances of the heathen gods, of the Perſian and Mahometan genii. The<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0687.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0681"/>
belief of ghoſts may be eaſily deduced from the opinions entertained reſpecting a future ſtate. Theſe opinions are founded on that eſſential doctrine of natural religion, that there is another world in which men ſhall exiſt when death has removed them hence. This doctrine has been univerſally received both by ſavage and civilized nations ; but, as might be expected, men have formed very different ſentiments concerning the nature of a future ſtate, of the ſituation and employments of departed ſpirits, according to the degree of knowledge which they posseſſed. But the general opinion in ancient and rude nations was, that departed ſpirits retained the ſame external appearance, the ſame paſſions and principles as before. Nothing therefore was more natural than the opinion, that they might occaſionally reviſit this world, from an anxious deſire to alleviate the ſufferings of thoſe beloved friends and relations whom they had left behind them, or to communicate from the unſeen world what might be important to their welfare. Upon ſuch an errand did Creuſa appear to Æncas. The apparition of the ghoſts of murderers is eaſily explained upon the ſame general principles. The remorſe and horror of mind which the murderer feels are ſuppoſed to haunt him in the other world, and to render his ſituation there intolerable (eſpecially if the murder was never detected and puniſhed), till he return and give information againſt himſelf. In this way, then, we think it highly probable the belief of ſpectres has originated. But many other cauſes concur to confirm and propagate this belief. Theſe are, imperfect viſion united with fear, dreams, opium, diſeaſes, drunkenneſs, and artifice.</p><p>1. Tndiſtinct viſion is one ſource of apparitions, eſpecially when the mind is under the influence of fear. It is well known, that the ſenſe of seeing conveys no idea of diſtance till improved by experience and obſervation ; and how we come at length to diſtinguiſh objects at a diſtance from thoſe that are near, has been explained in another place (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> n⁰ 50).</p><p>In the day-time we ſeldom commit miſtakes, becauſe we know the object at which we look ; but at night, when we ſee objects obſcurely, and know not what they are, we have no diſtinct idea either of their diſtances or of their magnitude. We may miſtake a bush that is near us for a tree at a diſtance ; or if the imagination be under the influence of fear, it will eaſily convert it into a gigantic figure. “ It is generally aſſerted (ſays Buffon) that theſe figures exiſt only in the imagination ; yet they may have a real exiſtence in the eye ; for whenever we have no other mode of judging of an unknown object but by the angle it forms in the eye, its magnitude will uniformly increaſe in proportion to its propinquity. If it appears, when at the diſtance of 20 or 30 paces, to be only a few feet high, its height, when within two or three ſeet of the eye, will be many fathoms. An object of this kind muſt naturally excite terror and aſtoniſhment in the ſpectator, till he· approaches and recogniſes it by actual feeling ; for the moment a man knows an object, the gigantic appearance it aſſumed in the eye inſtantly diminiſhes, and its apparent magnitude is reduced to its real dimenſions. But if, inſtead of approaching ſuch an object, the ſpectator flies from it, he can have no other idea of it but from the image which it formed in his eye ; and, in this case, he may affirm with truth that he ſaw an object terrible in its aſpect, and enormous in its ſize. Thus the notions concerning ſpectres is founded in nature, and depend not, as ſome philoſophers affirm, upon the imagination alone.”</p><p>In addition to theſe obſervations of Buffon, we may take notice, that objects are always magnified in a fog ; ſo that when a fog happens in the night-time, objects may be magnified to an enormous ſize. But, at any rate, whether there be fog in the night or not, there is ſuch a great analogy between darkneſſs and a fog, that if the latter deceive us with reſpect to the ſize of objects, the former will alſo deceive us. The writer of this article was paſſing the Frith of Forth at Queenserry, near Edinburgh, one morning which was extremely foggy. Though the water be only two miles broad, the boat did not get within sight of the ſouthern ſhore till it approached very near it. He then ſaw to his great ſurpriſe a large perpendicular rock, where he knew the ſhore was low and almoſt flat. As the boat advanced a little nearer, the rock ſeemed to ſplit perpendicularly into portions, which ſeparated at a little diſtance from one another. He next ſaw theſe perpendicular divi- ſions move ; and upon approaching a little nearer, found it was a number of people ſtanding on the beach, waiting the arrival of the ferry-boat.</p><p>2. Dreams are another fertile ſource of apparitions. It is well known to every perſon, that while the mind is under the influence of a dream it conſiders it as much a reality as it does any particular action while awake. Now <hi rend="italic">if</hi> a person of a weak ſuperſtitious mind ſhould have a very lively dream, which intereſts his passions, particularly the paſſion of fear, it may make ſo deep an impression, that he may be firmly convinced that he has actually ſeen with his eyes what has only paſſed before his imagination (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Apparition)</hi><note anchored="true" n="3" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(b)</hi> When the thoughts are much troubled, and when a perſon ſleeps without the circumſtances of going to bed, or putting off his clothes, as when he nods in his chair, it is very difficult, as Hobbes remarks, to diſtinguiſh a dream from a reality. On the contrary, he that compoſes himſelf to ſleep, in caſe of any uncouth or absurd fancy, eaſily ſuſpects it to have been a dream.— <hi rend="italic">Leviathan,</hi> par. i. c. I.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(b).</hi> We ſhall here tell a ſtory, by way of illuſtration, which we have received on unqueſtionable authority, An East Indian captain had an honeſt faithful ſervant named <hi rend="italic">John,</hi> for whom he had a great regard. John died, if we recollect right, on a voyage from England to the Eaſt Indies during a French war. As the ship approached the place of its deſtination the captain had a dream, in which John appeared to him, and earneſtly beſought him not to ſail to the port for which he was bound, as it was in the hands of the French. The captain, though not addicted to ſuperſtition, thought it prudent to follow this admonition ; and after landing at a different port, he was informed that the place to which he had intended to ſteer was, according to the information of the dream, captured by the French. On the voyage home, the captain had a second dream, in which John again appeared to him, and gave him no-<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0688.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0682"/>
tice that he ſhould ſoon die and that the ſhip ſhould be taken in the mouth of the Channel by the French. Next morning the captain called his firſt mate, told him his dream, which he believed was prophetic, and delivered his papers, that he might take proper care of them aſter his deceaſe. Every thing happened exactly as the dream had foretold ; the captain died, and the veſſel was taken by a French man of war in the mouth of the Channel. This dream, wonderful as it appears, is eaſily explained. In the voyage out to India, nothing was more natural than that the captain ſhould ſometimes be thinking that amidſt the various chances of war, the port to which he was bound might be taken ; perhaps it was a place of conſequence, which the French might be eager to poſſeſs. The captain being accuſtomed to revolve theſe thoughts in the day-times they would naturally return at night ; the regret which he felt for the loſs of a faithful ſervant might mingle with his apprehenſions, and thus produce the dream. Perhaps the advice was ſuch as John would have given had he been alive. It is equally eaſy to explain the cauſe of the dream in the paſſage home. The captain, we are told, was very ill, and thought himſelf dying, at the very time he had the ſecond dream, and therefore did not expect to reach England. This part of the dream, then, was only his own thoughts, delivered by his ſervant. As to the other part, that his ſhip ſhould be taken in the mouth of the Channel, it may be thought unaccountable how the very place ſhould be foreſeen. But we muſt recollect, that the mouth of the Channel, being over againſt the coaſt of France, was by far the moſt dangerous place in the whole paſſage ; and that, therefore, the captain had more reaſon to be afraid of losing his ſhip there than in any other place. The uſe which we mean to make of this ſtory is this : Had the captain been a man of a Weak mind, he would certainly have considered the dream as a reality, and believed, that inſtead of having dreamed of the things on which his imagination had dwelled, he had actually ſeen his ſervant return from the dead, and heard him deliver the meſſage. But, on the other hand, the captain, though he believed the dream was prophetic, mentioned it without any ſigns of fear ; and no man of courage and reflection ever ſees an apparition. This fight is reſerved for the weak, the timid, and ſuperſtitious. Of this many inſtances might be mentioned.</p><p>3. Spectres are ſometimes alſo occasioned by opium. Gaſſendi the philoſopher found a number of people going to put a man to death for having intercourſe with the devil ; a crime which the poor wretch readily acknowledged. Gaſſendi begged of the people that they would permit him firſt to examine the wizard before putting him to death. They did ſo ; and Gaſſendi, upon examination, found that the man firmly believed himſelf guilty of this impoſſible crime. He even offered to Gaſſendi to introduce him to the devil. The philoſopher agreed ; and when midnight came, the man gave him a pill, which he ſaid it was neceſſary to ſwallow before ſetting off. Gaſſendi took the pill, but gave it to his dog. The man having ſwallowed his, fell into a profound ſleep ; during which he ſeemed much agitated by dreams. The dog was affected in a ſimilar manner. When the man awoke, he congratulated Gaſſendi on the favourable reception he had met with from his fable highneſs. It was with difficulty Gaſſendi convinced him that the whole was a dream, the effect of ſoporific medicines, and that he had never ſtirred from one ſpot during the whole night.</p><p>4. That diſeaſes, eſpecially the night mare, the hypochondria, hyſteric paſſion, and madneſs, are another source of ſpcteres, we have the ſtrongeſt reaſon to affirm, Perſons ſubject to the night-mare often imagine that they ſee ſpectres. This is ſtill more the cafe with hypochondriac and hyſteric perſons, and thoſe who are in any degree deranged in their intellects. A fact which fell within the obſervation of the writer of this article will both prove and illuſtrate this aſſertion. In a village in one of the midland counties of Scotland, lived a widow diſtinguiſhed among her neighbours for decency of manners, integrity, and reſpect for religion. She affirmed, that for ſeveral nights together ſhe had heard a ſupernatural voice exclaiming aloud, <hi rend="italic">Murder ! murder!</hi> This was immediately reported through the neighbourhood ; all were alarmed, and looked around them with ſolicitude for the detection of the murder which they ſuppoſed to have been committed ; and it was not long till a diſcovery ſeemed actually to be made. It was reported, that a gentleman, who had relations at no great diſtance, and had been residing in the West Indies, had lately arrived with a considerable fortune ; that he had lodged in an inn about three miles off ; and that he had afterwards been ſeen entering a houſe in the village where the widow lived, from which he had never returned. It was next affirmed, that a tradeſman paſſing the church-yard about twelve at midnight had ſeen four men carry a dead corpſe into that cemetery. Theſe three facts being joined together ſeemed perfectly to agree and to confirm one another, and all believed ſome horrible murder had been committed. The relations of the gentleman thought they were called upon to make inquiry into the truth of theſe allegations : they accordingly came firſt to the church-yard, where, in company with the ſexton, they examined all the graves with great care, in order to diſcover whether any of them had been lately dug, or had the appearance of containing more than one coffin. But this ſearch was to no purpoſe, for no alteration had been made upon the graves. It was next reported that the murdered man had been buried in a plantation about a mile distant from the village. As the alarm was now very general, a number of the inhabitants propoſed of their own accord to explore it. They accordingly ſpread themſelves over the wood, and ſearched it with care, but no grave nor new dug earth was found. The writer of this article, who was then a boy at ſchool, was along with them. The matter did not rest here : The perſon who was ſaid to have ſeen four men carry a dead corpſe into the church-yard at midnight was ſummoned to appear before a meeting of the juſtices of the peace. Upon examination he denied any knowledge of the affair, but referred the court to another perſon from whom he had received his information. This perſon was examined, and the reſult was the ſame as the former. In ſhort, one perſon had heard it from another, who had received it from a third, who had heard it from a fourth ; but it had received a little embellishment from every perſon who<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0689.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0683"/>
repeated it. It turned out to be the ſame with Smollet’s story of the three black crows, which ſome body was ſaid to have vomited.</p><p>Upon inquiry at the inn where the West Indian gentleman had lodged, no ſuch gentleman had been ſeen there. It was found afterwards he had never left the West Indies. Still, however, the veracity of the widow was not disputed ; and ſome dark and ſecret tranſaction was ſuſpected. But the whole affair was at length explained by diſcovering that ſhe was ſomewhat deranged by melancholy. And the cries which ſhe had at firſt imagined ſhe had heard were afterwards imitated by ſome roguiſh perſon, who was highly amuſed with ſpreading terror among the credulous.</p><p>5. Drunkenneſs alſo has the power of creating ſpectres. Its natural effect in most caſes is to derange the understanding, to throw it off its guard, and to give full ſcope to that paſſion which has a natural diſpoſition to gain an aſcendancy ; and ſometimes it excites paſſions which ſcarcely ſeem to exiſt at any other time. It makes ſome men licentious, ſome furious, ſome all benevolence and kindneſs, ſome from being cowards it renders undaunted heroes. It ſeldom, if ever, excites fear ; and therefore it may be thought ſtrange that men ſhould imagine they ſee ghoſts when intoxicated. But it must be remarked, that the ghoſts which the drunkard ſees, he ſees not with the ſame alarm and terror as men who are ſober. He is not afraid of them. He has the courage to converſe with them, and even to fight with them, if they give him provocation. A man returning home intoxicated, affirmed that he had met with the devil; and that after a ſevere encounter he had vanquiſhed him and brought him to the ground, to which he had nailed him faſt by driving his ſtaff through his body. Next morning the ſtaff was found ſtuck with great violence into a heap of turfs !</p><p>6. Many apparitions of ſpectres have no other origin than the artifices of the waggiſh or ſelf-intereſted. Dr Plot, in his Natural Hiſtory of Oxfordſhire, relates a marvellous ſtory, which will illuſtrate this affertion. Soon after the murder of King Charles I. a commiſſion was appointed to ſurvey the king’s houſe at Woodſtock, with the manor, park, woods, and other demeſnes to that manor belonging ; and one Collins, under a feigned name, hired himſelf as ſecretary to the commissioners, who, upon the 13th of October 1649, met, and took up their reſidence in the king’s own rooms. His majeſty’s bed-chamber they made their kitchen, the council hall their pantry, and the preſence-chamber was the place where they ſat for the diſpatch of buſineſs. His majeſty’s dining-room they made their wood-yard, and ſtored it with the wood of the famous royal-oak from the High Park, which, that nothing might be left with the name of king about it, they had dug up by the roots, and ſplit and bundled up into faggots for their firing. Things being thus prepared, they ſat on the 16th of the ſame month for the diſpatch of buſineſs; and in the midſt of their firſt debate there entered a large black dog (as they thought), which made a dreadful howling, overturned two or three of their chairs, and then crept under a bed and vaniſhed. This gave them the greater ſurpriſe, as the doors were kept conſtantly locked, ſo that no real dog could get in or out. The next day their ſurpriſe was increaſed, when sitting at dinner in a lower room, they heard plainly the noile of perſons walking over their heads, though they well knew the doors were all locked, and there could be no body there. Preſently after they heard alſo all the wood of the king’s oak brought by parcels from the diningroom, and thrown with great violence into the preſence chamber ; as alſo all the chairs, ſtools, tables, and other furniture, forcibly hurled about the room ; their papers, containing the minutes of their tranſactions, were torn, and the ink-glaſs broken. When all this noiſe had ceaſed, Giles Sharp, their ſecretary, propoſed to enter firſt into theſe rooms ; and in preſence of the commiſſioners, from whom he received the key, he opened the doors, and found the wood ſpread about the room, the chairs toſſed about and broken, the papers torn, the ink-glaſs broken (as has been ſaid), but not the leaſt tract of any human creature, nor the leaſt reaſon to ſuſpect one, as the doors were all faſt, and the keys in the cuſtody of the commiſſioners. It was therefore unanimouſly agreed, that the power who did this miſchief must have entered the room at the key-hole. The night following, Sharp the ſecretary, with two of the commiſſioners ſervants, as they were in bed in the ſame room, which room was contiguous to that where the commiſſioners lay, had their bed’s feet lifted up ſo much higher than their heads, that they expected to have their necks broken, and then they were let fall at once with ſo much violence as ſhook the whole houſe, and more than ever terrified the commiſſioners. On the night of the 19th, as all were in bed in the ſame room for greater ſafety, and lights burning by them, the candles in an inſtant went out with a ſulphureous ſmell, and that moment many trenchers of wood were hurled about the room, which next morning were found to be the ſame their honours had eaten on the day before, which were all removed from the pantry, though not a lock was found opened in the whole houſe. The next night they ſtill fared worſe ; the candles went out as before, the curtains of their honours beds were rattled to and fro with great violence ; their honours received many cruel blows and bruiſes, by eight great pewter-diſhes and a number of wooden trenchers being thrown on their beds, which being heaved off, were heard rolling about the room, though in the morning none of theſe were to be ſeen. This night likewiſe they were alarmed with the tumbling down of oaken billets about their beds, and other frightful noiſes; but all was clear in the morning, as if no ſuch thing happened. The next night the keeper of the king’s houſe and his dog lay in the commiſſioners room, and then they had no diſturbance. But on the night of the 22d, though the dog lay in the room as before, yet the candles went out, a number of brick-bats fell from the chimney into the room, the dog howled piteouſly, their bed clothes were all ſtripped off, and their tenor increaſed. On the 24th they thought all the wood of the king’s oak was violently thrown down by their bed-ſides ; they counted 64 billets that fell, and ſome hit and ſhook the beds in which they lay ; but in the morning none were found there, nor had the door been opened where the billet wood was kept. The next night the candles were put out, the curtains rattled, and a dreadful crack like thunder was heard ; and one of the ſervants running in halte, thinking his maſter was killed, found three dozen of trenchers laid ſmoothly under the quilt by him. But all this was nothing to what ſucceeded afterwards ; The<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0690.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0684"/>
29th, about midnight, the candles went out, ſomething walked majeſtically through the room, and opened and ſhut the windows ; great stones were thrown violently into the room, ſome of which fell on the beds, others on the floor ; and at about a quarter after one a noiſe was heard as of forty cannon discharged together, and again repeated at about eight minutes diſtance. This alarmed and raiſed all the neighbourhood, who coming into their honours room, gathered up the great ſtones, fourſcore in number, and laid them by in the corner of a field, where, in Dr Plot’s time, who reports this ſtory, they were to be ſeen. This noiſe, like the diſcharge of cannon, was heard through all the country for 16 miles round. During theſe noiſes, which were heard in both rooms together, the commiſſioners and their ſervants gave one another over for lost, and cried out for help ; and Giles Sharp, ſnatching up a ſword, had well nigh killed one of their honours, miſtaking him for the ſpirit, as he came in his ſhirt from his own room to theirs. While they were together, the noiſe was continued, and part of the tiling of the houſe was ſtript off, and all the windows of an upper room were taken away with it. On the 30th at midnight ſomething walked into the chamber treading like a bear ; it walked many times about, then threw the warming-pan violently on the floor ; at the ſame time a large quantity of broken glaſs, accompanied with great ſtones and horſes bones, came pouring into the room with uncommon force. Theſe were all found in the morning to the aſtoniſhment and terror of the commiſſioners, who were yet determined to go on with their buſineſs. But on the firſt of November the moſt dreadful ſcene of all enſued : Candles in every part of the room were lighted up, and a great fire made ; at midnight, the candles all yet burning, a noiſe like the burſting of a cannon was heard in the room, and the burning billets were tossed about by it even into their honours beds ; who called Giles and his companions to their relief, other- wiſe the houſe had been burnt to the ground ; about an hour after the candles went out as uſual, the crack as if many cannon was heard, and many pailfuls of green stinking water were thrown upon their honours beds ; great ſtones were alſo thrown in as before, the bed curtains and bedſteads torn and broken, the windows ſhattered, and the whole neighbourhood alarmed with the moſt dreadful noiſes ; nay, the very rabbit- ſtealers that were abroad that night in the warren were ſo terrified, that they fled for fear and left their ferrets behind them. One of their honours this night ſpoke, and, <hi rend="italic">in the name of God, aſked what it was, and why it disturbed them ſo ?</hi> No anſwer was given to this ; but the noiſe ceaſed for a while, when the ſpirit came again; and, as they all agreed, <hi rend="italic">brought with it ſeven devils worse than itſelf</hi> One of the ſervants now lighted a large candle, and ſet it in the door-way between the two chambers, to ſee what paſſed ; and as he watched it, he plainly ſaw a hoof ſtriking the candle and candle- ſtick into the middle of the room, and afterwards making three ſcrapes over the ſnuff, ſcraped it out. Upon this the ſame perſon was ſo bold as to draw a ſword ; but he had ſcarce got it out when he felt another inviſible hand holding it too, and pulling it from him ; and at length prevailing, ſtruck him ſo violently on the head with the pummel, that he fell down for dead with the blow. At this inſtant was heard another burst like the diſcharge of the broadſide of a ſhip of war, and at about a minute or two’s diſtance each no leſs than 19 more ſuch : theſe ſhook the houſe ſo violently, that they expected every moment it would fall upon their heads. The neighbours, on this, as has been ſaid, being all alarmed, flocked to the houſe in great numbers, and all joined in prayer and pſalm-ſinging during which the noiſe still continued in the other rooms, and the diſcharge of cannons was heard as from without, though no viſible agent was ſeen to diſcharge them. But what was the moſt alarming of all, and put an end to their proceedings effectually, happened the next day as they were all at dinner, when a paper, in which they had ſigned a mutual agreement to reserve a part of the premiſes out of the general ſurvey, and afterwards to ſhare it equally amongſt themſelves, (which paper they had hid for the preſent under the earth in a pot in one corner of the room, and in which an orange-tree grew), was conſumed in a wonderful manner, by the earth’s taking fire with which the pot was filled, and burning violently with a blue fume, and an intolerable ſtench ; ſo that they were all driven out of the houſe, to which they could never be again prevailed upon to return.</p><p>This wonderful contrivance was all the invention of the memorable Joſeph Collins of Oxford, otherwiſe called <hi rend="italic">Funny Joe,</hi> who having hired himſelf as ſecretary, under the name of <hi rend="italic">Giles Sharp,</hi> by knowing the private traps belonging to the houſe, and the help of <hi rend="italic">pulvis fulminans</hi> and other chemical preparations, and letting his fellow-ſervants into the fcheme, carried on the deceit without diſcovery to the very laſt; inſomuch that the late Dr Plot, in his Natural Hiſtory, relates the whole for fact, and concludes in this grave manner, “ That though tricks have been often played in affairs of this kind, many of the things above related are not reconcilcable with juggling ; ſuch as the loud noiſes, beyond the power of man to make without ſuch inſtruments as were not there ; the tearing and breaking the beds ; the throwing about the fire ; the hoof treading out the candle ; and the ſtriving for the ſword, and the blow the man received from the pummel of it.”</p></div></body></text></TEI>