<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0732.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0726-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STANNARIES</label>,
the mines and works where tin is dug and purified ; as in Cornwall, Devonſhire, &amp;c.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">STANNARY courts,</hi> in Devonſhire and Cornwall, for the adminiſtration of juſtice among the tinners therein. They are held before the lord-warden and his ſubſtitutes, in virtue of a privilege granted to the workers in the tin-mines there, to ſue and be ſued only in their own courts, that they may not be drawn from their busineſs, which is highly profitable to the public, by attending their law-suits in other courts. The privileges of the tinners are confirmed by a charter, 33 Edw. I. and fully expounded by a private ſtatute, 50 Edw. III. which has since been explained by a public act, <hi rend="italic">16</hi> Car. I. c. 15.<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Blackstone's Comment. vol. iii. p. 79 and 80.</p></note> What relates to our preſent purpoſe is only this : That all tinners and labourers in and about the ſtannaries ſhall, during the time of their working therein, <hi rend="italic">bona fide,</hi> be privileged from suits of other courts, and be only pleaded in the ſtannary court in all matters, excepting pleas of land, life, and member. No writ of error lies from hence to any court in Weſtminſter-hall ; as was agreed by all the judges, in 4 Jac. I. But an appeal lies from the ſteward of the court to the under-warden ; and from him to the lord-warden ; and thence to the privy-council of the prince of Wales, as duke of Cornwall, when he hath had livery or inveſtiture of the ſame. And from thence the appeal lies to the king himſelf, in the last resort.</p></div></body></text></TEI>