<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0704.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0698-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPIRITUOUS <hi rend="smallcaps">liquors</hi></label>
 have in all nations been conſidered as a proper ſubject of heavy taxation for the ſupport of the ſtate. This has naturally occaſioned a pice examination of their ſtrength. It having been at laſt found that this was intimately connected with the ſpeciſic gravity, this has been examined with the most ſcrupulous attention to every circumſtance which could affect it, ſo that the duties might be exactly proportioned to the quantity of ſpirit in any ſtrong liquor, independent on every other circumſtance of flavour or taſte, or other valued quality. The chemiſt at laſt found that the basis of all ſtrong liquors is the ſame, produced by the vinous fermentation of pure ſaccharine matter diſſolved in water. He alſo found, that whether this vegetable ſalt be taken as it is ſpontaneouſly formed in the juices of plants and fruits, or as it may be formed or extricated from farinaceous fruits and roots by a certain part of the proceſs of vegetation, ſt produces the ſame ardent ſpirit, which has always the ſame denſity in every mixture with water. The minute portions of aromatic oils, which are in ſome degree inſeparable from it, and give it a different flavour according to the ſubſtance from which it was obtained, are not found to have any ſenſible effect on its denſity or ſpecific gravity. This ſeems very completely eſtabliſhed in conſequence of the unwearied attempts of the manufacturers to leſſen the duties payable on their goods by mixtures of other ſubſtances, which would increaſe their denſity without making them leſs palatable. The vigilance of the revenue officers was no leſs employed to detect every ſuch contrivance. In ſhort, it is now an acknowledged point, that the ſpeciſic gravity is an accurate teſt of the ſtrength.</p><p>But though this is true in general, we cannot derive much benefit from it, unleſs we know the preciſe relation between the ſtrength and the denſity of a ſpirituous liquor. Do they increaſe <hi rend="italic">pari passu,</hi> or by what law are they connected ? It was natural to expect that equal additions of ardent ſpirits or alcohol to a given quantity of water would produce equal diminutions of denſity. Areometers were accordingly made on this principle above 200 years ago, as may be ſeen in the works of Gaſpar Schottus, Sturmius, Agricola, and other old authors. But when mathematical phyſics became more generally known, this was eaſily diſcovered to be erroneous ; and it was ſhown (we think firſt by Mr Boyle) that equal additions to the ſpecific gravity would be produced by ſucceſſively taking out of any veſſel a certain meaſure of alcohol and replacing it with an equal meaſure of water. This was the moſt convenient diſcovery for all parties, becauſe then the duties payable on a cask of ſpirits would be in the exact proportion of the diminution of its denſity. But it was ſoon found by thoſe who were appointed guardians of the revenue that this conclusion was erroneous, and that a mixture which appeared by this rule to contain 35 gallons of alcohol, did really contain 35½. This they found by actually making ſuch a mixture: 18 gallons of alcohol mixed with 18 of water produced only 35 gallons of ſpirits. The revenue officers, finding that this condenſation was moſt remarkable in mixtures of equal parts of water and the ſtrongeſt ſpirits which could then be procured, determined to levy the duties by this mixture ; becauſe, whether the ſpirituous liquor was ſtronger or weaker than this, it would appear, by its specific gravity, rather ſtronger than it really was. This ſagacious obſervation, and the ſimplicity of the composition, which could at all times be made for companion, ſeem to be the reaſons for our exciſe offices selecting this mode of eſtimating the ſtrength and levying the duties. A mixture of nearly equal meaſures of water and alcohol is called <hi rend="smallcaps">proof spirit,</hi> and pays a certain duty <hi rend="italic">per</hi> gallon; and the ſtrength of a ſpirituous liquor is eſtimated by the gallons, not of alcohol, but of proof ſpirit which the calk contains. But becauſe it might be difficult to procure at all times this proof ſpirit for compariſon, ſuch a mixture was made by order of the board of exciſe : and it was found, that when six gallons of it was mixed with one gallon of water, a wine gallon of the mixture weighed 7 pounds 13 ounces avoirdupois. The board therefore declared, that the ſpirituous liquor of which the gallon weighed 7 pounds 13 ounces ſhould be reckoned 1 to 6 or 1 in 7 under proof. This is but an awkward and complex formula ; it was in order to suit matters to a mode of examination which had by time obtained the sanction of the board. Mr Clarke, an ingenious artiſt of that time, had made a hydrometer incomparably more exact than any other, and conſtructed on mathematical principles, fit for computation. This had a ſet of weights correſponding to the additions of water or proof ſpirit, and the mixture 1 to 6 or 1 in 7 was the only one which weighed an exact number of ounces <hi rend="italic">per</hi> gallon without a fraction.</p><p>Thus ſtands the exciſe law; and Clarke’s hydrometer is ſtill the instrument of authority, although others have been since conſtructed by <hi rend="smallcaps">Dicas, Quin,</hi> and others, which are much more ingenious and convenient. The mathematician who examines Dicas’s hydrometer, with its sliding ſcale, by which it is adjuſted to the different temperatures, and points out the condensations, will perceive a beautiful and ſagacious combination of quantities, which he will find it difficult to bring under any analytical formula. Perhaps Quin’s may have ſome preference in reſpect of conveniency ; but <hi rend="italic">facile inventis addere.</hi> Mr Dicas’s was original.</p><p>As naturaliſts became more accuſtomed to exact observation in every topic of inquiry, the condensation which obtains in the mixture of different ſubstances became more familiarly known. This evidently affects the preſent queſtion; and both the exciſe and the distillers are interested in its accurate deciſion. This occaſioned an application to the Royal Society ; and a moſt ſcrupulous examination of the ſtrength of ſpirituous liquors was made by Sir Charles Blagden and Mr Gilpin, of which they have given a very particular account in the <hi rend="smallcaps">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for 1790 and 1792.</p><p>We have taken notice of this in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Specific</hi><pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0705.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0699"/>
<hi rend="smallcaps">gravity,</hi> mentioning ſuch circumſtances of the results as ſuited our purpoſes of phyſical diſcuſſion. At preſent we give the general reluit in the table oſ ſpecific gravity, as peculiarly belonging to ſpirituous liquors, affording the moſt exact: account of their denſity in every ſtate of dilution of alcohol with water. And as the relation between the proportion of ingredients and the denſity is peculiar to every ſubstance, ſo that ſcarcely any inference can be made from one to another, the reader will consider the tables here given as characteristic with reſpect to alcohol. In all ſolutions of salts we found that the condenſation increases continually with the dilution, whereas it is greatest when equal bulks of water and alcohol are mixed : yet we do not conſider this as an exception ; for it is certain, that in the ſtrongest brine the ſaline ingredient bears but a ſmall proportion to the water—and when we mix two ſolutions, the condenſation is greateſt when they are nearly equal in bulk. But we think ourſelves entitled to infer, that alcohol is not a dilution of a ſubftance in a quantity of water; but that water, in a certain proportion, not very distant from what we can produce by flow diſtillation, is an ingredient of alcohol, or is one of its component parts, and not merely a vehicle or menſtruum. We therefore imagine that proof ſpirit contains nearly equal bulks of water and ardent ſpirits.</p><p>The great difficulty in this examination aroſe from the very diſſimilar expansions of water and alcohol by heat. This determined Sir Charles Blagden to estimate the proportions of ingredients by weight, and made it abſolutely neceſſary to give a ſcale of ſpecific gravity and strength for every temperature. For it must be remarked, that the question (whether in commerce or philoſophy) always is, “ How many gallons of alcohol and of water, taken just now and mixed together, will produce a hundred gallons of the ſpirit we are examining ?” The proportion of theſe two will be different according to the temperature of both. As many mixtures therefore must have been made in each proportion as there were temperatures conſidered ; but by taking the ingredients by weight, and examining the denſity of the compound in one temperature, it is then heated and cooled, and its change of denſity obſerved. Calculation then can tell us the change in the proportion of the bulks or numbers of gallons in the mixture, by means of a previous table ſhowing the expansions of water and of alcohol.</p><p>The alcohol ſelected for this examination had the speciſic gravity 0,825. This is not the purest that can be procured ; ſome was produced oſ 0,816, of 0,814, and 0,81 3, both obtained from rum, from brandy, and from malt ſpirit. We are informed that Dr Black has obtained it of the ſpecific gravity 0,8 by digeſting alcohol with fixed ammoniac (muriatic acid united with lime) made very dry. It dephlegmates alcohol very powerfully without decompoſing it, which always happens when we uſe cauſtic alkali. Alcohol of 0,825 was choſen becauſe expreſſed by a number of eaſy management in computation.</p><p>The examination commenced by aſcertaining the expanſions of water and alcohol. The temperature 60⁰ of Fahrenheit’s ſcale was ſelected for the general temperature of compariſon, being eaſily attainable even in cold weather, and allowing the examinator to operate at eaſe. The firſt and laſt copartments of the tables contain the weights and ſpecific gravities of alcohol and water for every fifth degree of heat from 30⁰ to 100⁰. From theſe we have conſtructed the two following little tables of expanſion. The bulk of 1000 ounces, pounds, or other weight of water and of alcohol of the temperature 60⁰, occupies the bulks expreſſed in the tables for every other temperature. Water could not be eaſily or usefully examined when of the temperature 30⁰, becauſe it is with great difficulty kept fluid in that temperature. It is very remarkable, that when it can be ſo kept, it expands instead of contracting ; while cooling down from 35⁰ or thereabouts, and as it approaches to 32⁰, it expands rapidly. We obſerve the ſame thing in the cryſtallization of Glauber salt, martial vitriol, and ſome others, which contain much water in their crystals. We obſerve, on the other hand, a remarkable contraction in the zeolite just before its beginning to ſwell into bubbles by a red heat.</p><table> <row> <cell rows="2">Heat</cell> <cell cols="4">Bulk of 100,000 ounces.</cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="2">Of Water.</cell> <cell cols="2">Of Alcohol.</cell> </row> <row> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>Diff.</cell> <cell/> <cell>Diff.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>30⁰</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>119195</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>35</cell> <cell>99910</cell> <cell/> <cell>119514</cell> <cell>319</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>99906</cell> <cell><p>−4</p><p>+ 8</p><p>18</p></cell> <cell>119839</cell> <cell><p>325</p><p>332</p><p>342</p><p>348</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell>45</cell> <cell>99914</cell> <cell/> <cell>120172</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>99932</cell> <cell>30</cell> <cell>120514</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell><p>55</p><p>60</p></cell> <cell>100000</cell> <cell>38</cell> <cell>I2I2I2</cell> <cell>35⁰</cell> </row> <row> <cell><p>65</p><p>70</p></cell> <cell>100050</cell> <cell><p>50</p><p>56</p></cell> <cell>121565</cell> <cell><p>353</p><p>354</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>100170</cell> <cell>64</cell> <cell><p>121919</p><p>122279</p></cell> <cell>360</cell> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>100241</cell> <cell>71</cell> <cell>122645</cell> <cell>366</cell> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>100320</cell> <cell><p>79</p><p>84</p></cell> <cell>123017</cell> <cell><p>372</p><p>376</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>100404</cell> <cell>96</cell> <cell>123393</cell> <cell>380</cell> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>100500</cell> <cell/> <cell>123773</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>100</cell> <cell>I 00608</cell> <cell>108</cell> <cell>124157</cell> <cell>384</cell> </row> </table><p>This being premiſed, the examination was conducted in the following manner. It was determined to mix 100 parts by weight of pure alcohol with five, ten, fifteen, twenty, parts of distilled water, till they were compounded in equal quantities, and then to mix 100 parts of distilled water with 95, 90,85, 80, &amp;c. parts of alcohol, till they were mixed in the proportion of 100 to 5. Thus a ſeries of mixtures would be obtained, extending from pure alcohol to pure water. This ſeries would be ſuch, that the examinations would be moſt frequent in the cases moſt uſual in the commerce of ſtrong liquors. A ſet of phials, fitted with ground ſtoppers, were provided, of ſizes fit to hold the intended mixtures. Theſe mixtures were made by ſuſpending the phial to the arm of a very nice balance, in the oppoſite ſcale of which (besides the counterpoiſe of the phial) there was placed the weight 100 <hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi> Spirit was then poured into the phial till it exactly balanced the weight 100. The weight for the water to be added was then put into the oppoſite ſcale, and water was poured into the phial by means of a ſlender glaſs funnel, by ſmall quantities at a time, and the phial frequently agitated to promote the mixture. When the additional weight was exactly balanced, the phial was taken off, its ſtopper put in, and leather tied over it, and it was ſet by, for at leaſt a month, that the mixture and the whole<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0706.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0700"/>
proceſs of condenſation might be completed. The ſame method was followed in the mixtures where the water was predominant.</p><p>When the ingredients of theſe mixtures were judged to have completely incorporated, their ſpecific gravity was examined by weighing with the moſt ſcrupulous preciſion the contents of a veſſel which held 2925 troy grains of water, of the temperature 60⁰. The balance was ſo exceedingly ſenſible, that the 50th part of a grain greatly deranged its poſition when loaded with the ſcales and their contents. It was constructed by Mr Ramſden, and ſome account of its exquisite ſenſibility may be ſeen in the <hi rend="italic">Journal de Physique,</hi> vol. xxxiii. This quantity of materials was therefore thought abundantly sufficient for aſcertaining the denſity of the liquor. It is needleſs to detail the precautions which were taken for having the contents of the weighing bottle brought to the preciſe temperature proper for the experiment. They were ſuch as every perſon converſant with ſuch things is accuſtomed to take—The bottle had a ſlender neck, and being put on a lathe, a mark was made round it with a diamond. The bottle was filled till the bottom of the hollow ſurface of the fluid was in the plane of this mark ; and to judge of the accuracy attainable in filling the bottle, the operation was ſeveral times repeated and the contents weighed, without the difference of <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 50</hi> th of a grain in 2925. The only ſource of error which was to be guarded againſt was air-bubbles adhering to the inside of the bottle, or moiſture condensing (in the experiments with low temperatures) on the outside. Both of theſe were attended to as much as poſſible.</p><p>This method of determining the ſpecific gravity was preferred to the uſual method, obſerving the weight lost by a lump of glaſs when ſuſpended in water ; for Mr Gilpin had been enabled, by means of this nice balance, to diſcover, even in pure water and in alcohol, a want of perfect fluidity. Something like viſcidity rendered the motion of a lump of glaſs through the liquor ſensibly ſluggiſh, ſo that when the balance was brought to a level, there was not a perfect equilibrium of weights: (See what we have ſaid of this matter in <hi rend="smallcaps">Specific Gravity).</hi> Mr Gilpin alſo tried the ingenious instrument propoſed for ſuch experiments by Mr Ramſden, and deſcribed by him in a pamphlet on this very ſubject ; and he found the anomalies of experiment much greater than in this method by weighing.— Indeed the regular progreſſion of weights to be ſeen in the annexed tables is an unqueſtionable proof of the ſufficiency of the method ; and it has the evident advantage of all other methods in point of ſimplicity and practicability without any uncommon apparatus. Any perſon poſſeſſed of a good ordinary balance and a ſet of exact weights may examine all queſtions of this kind, by weighing pure water and the liquor which he may have occasion to examine in a common 6 or 8 ounce phial. For this reaſon, it is recommended (in preference to all hydrometers) to the board of exciſe to provide this simple apparatus in every principal office.</p><p>Every experiment was made at leaſt three times ; and the mean result which never differed one grain from the extreme) was taken.</p><p>From theſe experiments the annexed tables were constructed. The firſt is the simple abſtract of the experiments, containing the weights of the contents of the bottle of every mixture. The second contains the ſpecific gravities deduced from them.</p><p>We have ſaid that the experiments appear ſurprisingly accurate. This we ſay on the authority of the regular progreſſion of the ſpecific gravity in any of the horizontal rows. In the ſeries, for instance, for the temperature 60⁰, the greateſt anomaly is in the mixture of 50 parts of ſpirit with 100 of water. The ſpecific gravity is 95804, wanting 3 or 4 of the regular progreſſion. This does not amount to 1 in 18000.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0707.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0701"/>
<hi rend="italic">TABLE I.—</hi> Weights at the different Degrees 0f Temperature,</p><table cols="15"> <row> <cell>Heat.</cell> <cell>The pure ſpirit.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 1 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 10 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 15 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 20 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 25 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 30 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 35 grains of water</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 40 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 45 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 50 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 55 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 60 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 65 grains of water.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>deg.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>30</cell> <cell>2487,35</cell> <cell>2519,92</cell> <cell>2548,42</cell> <cell>2573,80</cell> <cell>2596,66</cell> <cell>2617,30</cell> <cell>2636,23</cell> <cell>2653,73</cell> <cell>2669,83</cell> <cell>2684,74</cell> <cell>2698,ςx</cell> <cell>27il,i4</cell> <cell>2722,89</cell> <cell>2733,87</cell> </row> <row> <cell>35</cell> <cell>248θ,87</cell> <cell>2513,43</cell> <cell>2541,84</cell> <cell>2567,26</cell> <cell>2590,16</cell> <cell>26l0,87</cell> <cell>2629,92</cell> <cell>2647,47</cell> <cell>2663,64</cell> <cell>2678,60</cell> <cell>2692,43</cell> <cell>2705,14</cell> <cell>2716,92</cell> <cell>2-27,87</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>2474,30</cell> <cell>2506,75</cell> <cell>2535,41</cell> <cell>2560,74</cell> <cell>2583,66</cell> <cell>2604,50</cell> <cell>2623,56</cell> <cell>2641,08</cell> <cell>2657,23</cell> <cell>2672,30</cell> <cell>2686,32</cell> <cell>2698,94</cell> <cell>27i0,8I</cell> <cell>2721,83</cell> </row> <row> <cell>45</cell> <cell>2467,62</cell> <cell>2500,I4</cell> <cell>2528,75</cell> <cell>2554,09</cell> <cell>2577,I0</cell> <cell>2597,98</cell> <cell>2617,03</cell> <cell>2634,64</cell> <cell>2650,87</cell> <cell>2666,04</cell> <cell>2679,99</cell> <cell>2692,77</cell> <cell>2704,57</cell> <cell>2715,62</cell> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>2460,75</cell> <cell>2493,33</cell> <cell>2521,96</cell> <cell>2547,47</cell> <cell>2570,42</cell> <cell>2591,38</cell> <cell>26l0,54</cell> <cell>2628,21</cell> <cell>2644,43</cell> <cell>2659,55</cell> <cell>2673,64</cell> <cell>2686,54</cell> <cell>2698,42</cell> <cell>2709,48</cell> </row> <row> <cell>55</cell> <cell>2453,80</cell> <cell>2486,37</cell> <cell>25i5,D3</cell> <cell>2540,6c</cell> <cell>2563,64</cell> <cell>2584,65</cell> <cell>2603,80</cell> <cell>2621,50</cell> <cell>2637,86</cell> <cell>2653,04</cell> <cell>2667,14</cell> <cell>2679,98</cell> <cell>2691,83</cell> <cell>2702,98</cell> </row> <row> <cell>60</cell> <cell>2447,00</cell> <cell>2479,56</cell> <cell>2508,27</cell> <cell>2533,83</cell> <cell>2556,90</cell> <cell>2577,95</cell> <cell>2597,22</cell> <cell>2615,03</cell> <cell>2631,37</cell> <cell>2646,53</cell> <cell>2660,62</cell> <cell>2673,55</cell> <cell>2685,52</cell> <cell>2696,73</cell> </row> <row> <cell>65</cell> <cell>2440,12</cell> <cell>2472,75</cell> <cell>250I,53</cell> <cell>2526,99</cell> <cell>2550,22</cell> <cell>257i,24</cell> <cell>2590,55</cell> <cell>2608,37</cell> <cell>2624,75</cell> <cell>2640,0l</cell> <cell>2654,04</cell> <cell>2667,07</cell> <cell>2679,15</cell> <cell>2690,32</cell> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>2433,23</cell> <cell>2465,88</cell> <cell>2494,56</cell> <cell>2520,03</cell> <cell>2543,32</cell> <cell>2564,47</cell> <cell>2583,88</cell> <cell>2601,67</cell> <cell>2617,96</cell> <cell>2633,32</cell> <cell>2647,52</cell> <cell>2660,63</cell> <cell>2672,74</cell> <cell>2684,02</cell> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>2426,23</cell> <cell>2458,78</cell> <cell>2487,62</cell> <cell>2513,08</cell> <cell>2536,39</cell> <cell>2557,61</cell> <cell>2576,93</cell> <cell>2594,8θ</cell> <cell>2611,19</cell> <cell>2626,55</cell> <cell>2640,81</cell> <cell>2653,99</cell> <cell>2666,06</cell> <cell>2677,34</cell> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>2419,02</cell> <cell>2451,67</cell> <cell>2480,45</cell> <cell>2506,08</cell> <cell>2529,24</cell> <cell>2550,50</cell> <cell>2569,86</cell> <cell>2587,93</cell> <cell>2604,29</cell> <cell>2619,72</cell> <cell>2633,99</cell> <cell>2647,12</cell> <cell>2659,36</cell> <cell>2670,69</cell> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>2411,92</cell> <cell>2444,63</cell> <cell>2473,33</cell> <cell>2499,01</cell> <cell>2522,29</cell> <cell>254304</cell> <cell>2563,0I</cell> <cell>2580,93</cell> <cell>2597,45</cell> <cell>2613,02</cell> <cell>2627,39</cell> <cell>2640,60</cell> <cell>2652,78</cell> <cell>2664,16</cell> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>2404,90</cell> <cell>2437,62</cell> <cell>2466,32</cell> <cell>2491,99</cell> <cell>2515,28</cell> <cell>2536,63</cell> <cell>2556,11</cell> <cell>2574,02</cell> <cell>259C,6θ</cell> <cell>2606,16</cell> <cell>2620,52</cell> <cell>2633,74</cell> <cell>2646,00</cell> <cell>2657,41</cell> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>2397,68</cell> <cell>2430,33</cell> <cell>2459,13</cell> <cell>2484,74</cell> <cell>2508,I0</cell> <cell>2529,46</cell> <cell>2549,13</cell> <cell>2567,03</cell> <cell>2583,65</cell> <cell>2599,24</cell> <cell>2613,57</cell> <cell>2626,94</cell> <cell>2639,25</cell> <cell>2650,63</cell> </row> <row> <cell>100</cell> <cell>2390,60</cell> <cell>2423,22</cell> <cell>2452,13</cell> <cell>2477,64</cell> <cell>25θθ,9i</cell> <cell>2522,30</cell> <cell>254i,92</cell> <cell>2559,96</cell> <cell>2576,56</cell> <cell>2592,14</cell> <cell>2606,5c</cell> <cell>2619,75</cell> <cell>2632,17</cell> <cell>2643,75</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Heat.</cell> <cell>The pure ſpirit.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 70 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 75 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 80 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 85 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 90 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 95 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water</cell> <cell>95 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>90 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>85 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>75 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>70 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>65 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>deg.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>30</cell> <cell>2744,20</cell> <cell>2753,75</cell> <cell>2762,72</cell> <cell>2771,08</cell> <cell>2778,99</cell> <cell>2786,36</cell> <cell>2793,22</cell> <cell>2799,85</cell> <cell>2806,61</cell> <cell>2813,85</cell> <cell>2821,3 ς</cell> <cell>2828,90</cell> <cell>2836,39</cell> <cell>2844,16</cell> </row> <row> <cell>35</cell> <cell>2738,13</cell> <cell>2747,74</cell> <cell>2756,91</cell> <cell>2765,32</cell> <cell>2773,22</cell> <cell>2780,59</cell> <cell>2787,54</cell> <cell>2794,19</cell> <cell>2801,i4</cell> <cell>2808,52</cell> <cell>2816,07</cell> <cell>2823,68</cell> <cell>2831,36</cell> <cell>2839,26</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>2732,24</cell> <cell>2741,86</cell> <cell>2750,96</cell> <cell>2759,50</cell> <cell>2767,48</cell> <cell>2774,90</cell> <cell>278l,84</cell> <cell>2788,69</cell> <cell>2795,70</cell> <cell>2803,17</cell> <cell>28l0,73</cell> <cell>2818,36</cell> <cell>2826,31</cell> <cell>2834,40</cell> </row> <row> <cell>45</cell> <cell>2726,09</cell> <cell>2735,77</cell> <cell>2744,82</cell> <cell>2753,36</cell> <cell>2761,42</cell> <cell>2768,85</cell> <cell>2775,94</cell> <cell>2782,99</cell> <cell>2789,99</cell> <cell>2797,45</cell> <cell>2805,08</cell> <cell>2812,93</cell> <cell>2821,00</cell> <cell>2829,28</cell> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>2719,93</cell> <cell>2729,64</cell> <cell>2738,74</cell> <cell>2747,27</cell> <cell>2755,37</cell> <cell>2762,95</cell> <cell>2770,14</cell> <cell>2777,19</cell> <cell>2784,30</cell> <cell>2791,72</cell> <cell>2799,58</cell> <cell>2807,56</cell> <cell>2815,71</cell> <cell>2824,12</cell> </row> <row> <cell>55</cell> <cell>2713,60</cell> <cell>2723,51</cell> <cell>2732,64</cell> <cell>2741,24</cell> <cell>2749,27</cell> <cell>2756,83</cell> <cell>2764,09</cell> <cell>2771,29</cell> <cell>2778,54</cell> <cell>2785,96</cell> <cell>l2793,82</cell> <cell>28θl,89</cell> <cell>2810,23</cell> <cell>2818,80</cell> </row> <row> <cell>60</cell> <cell>2707,40</cell> <cell>2717,30</cell> <cell>2726,52</cell> <cell>2735,17</cell> <cell>2743,28</cell> <cell>2750,93</cell> <cell>2758,I7</cell> <cell>2765,40</cell> <cell>2772,70</cell> <cell>2780,26</cell> <cell>2788,25</cell> <cell>2796,45</cell> <cell>2804,85</cell> <cell>2813,65</cell> </row> <row> <cell>65</cell> <cell>2701,05</cell> <cell>2710,96</cell> <cell>2720,25</cell> <cell>2728,98</cell> <cell>2737,09</cell> <cell>2744,86</cell> <cell>2752,2i</cell> <cell>2759,47</cell> <cell>2766,73</cell> <cell>2774,43</cell> <cell>2782,62</cell> <cell>2790,81</cell> <cell>2799,38</cell> <cell>2808,31</cell> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>2694,76</cell> <cell>2704,64</cell> <cell>2713,87</cell> <cell>2722,75</cell> <cell>2730,94</cell> <cell>2738,73</cell> <cell>∣2746,06</cell> <cell>2753,41</cell> <cell>2760,75</cell> <cell>2768,45</cell> <cell>2776,72</cell> <cell>278 ς,06</cell> <cell>2793,80</cell> <cell>2802,88</cell> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>2688,14</cell> <cell>2698,07</cell> <cell>2707,49</cell> <cell>2716,35</cell> <cell>2724,64</cell> <cell>2732,39</cell> <cell>∣2739,89</cell> <cell>2747,23</cell> <cell>2754,73</cell> <cell>2762,58</cell> <cell>2770,93</cell> <cell>2779,26</cell> <cell>2788,00</cell> <cell>2797,21</cell> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>2681,50</cell> <cell>2691,50</cell> <cell>2700,94</cell> <cell>2709,7i</cell> <cell>2718,12</cell> <cell>2726,06</cell> <cell>2733,53</cell> <cell>2740,93</cell> <cell>2748,42</cell> <cell>2756,43</cell> <cell>2764,87</cell> <cell>2773,33</cell> <cell>2782,14</cell> <cell>2791,52</cell> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>2674,95</cell> <cell>2684,98</cell> <cell>2694,53</cell> <cell>2703,33</cell> <cell>2711,86</cell> <cell>p7l9,74</cell> <cell>2727,25</cell> <cell>2734,80</cell> <cell>2742,31</cell> <cell>2750,22</cell> <cell>2758,80</cell> <cell>2767,44</cell> <cell>2776,33</cell> <cell>2785,8I</cell> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>2668,29</cell> <cell>2678,49</cell> <cell>2687,99</cell> <cell>2696,91</cell> <cell>2705,37</cell> <cell>∣27I3,32</cell> <cell>272i,0l</cell> <cell>2728,59</cell> <cell>2736,23</cell> <cell>2744,24</cell> <cell>2752,76</cell> <cell>2761,51</cell> <cell>2770,59</cell> <cell>2780,11</cell> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>2661,51</cell> <cell>2671,82</cell> <cell>2681,34</cell> <cell>2690,33</cell> <cell>2698,86</cell> <cell>2706,88</cell> <cell>2714,61</cell> <cell>2722,23</cell> <cell>2729,89</cell> <cell>2737,98</cell> <cell>2746,57</cell> <cell>2755,34</cell> <cell>2764,57</cell> <cell>2774,25</cell> </row> <row> <cell>100</cell> <cell>2654,76</cell> <cell>2664,99</cell> <cell>2674,62</cell> <cell>2683,63</cell> <cell>2692,25</cell> <cell>2700,33</cell> <cell>2708,04</cell> <cell>2715,73</cell> <cell>2723,35</cell> <cell>2731,55</cell> <cell>2740,43</cell> <cell>2749,28</cell> <cell>2758,48</cell> <cell>2768,43</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Heat</cell> <cell>60 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>55 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>50 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>45 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>30 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>35 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>30 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>25 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>20 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>15 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>10 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>5 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>Water.</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>deg.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell>Grains.</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>30</cell> <cell>2852,03</cell> <cell>2859,71</cell> <cell>2867,12</cell> <cell>2874,43</cell> <cell>2881,34</cell> <cell>2887,77</cell> <cell>2894,22</cell> <cell>2900,85</cell> <cell>2908,21</cell> <cell>2917,19</cell> <cell>2928,80</cell> <cell>2944,53</cell> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>35</cell> <cell>2847,45</cell> <cell>2855,32</cell> <cell>2863,16</cell> <cell>2870,87</cell> <cell>2878,21</cell> <cell>2885,06</cell> <cell>2892,07</cell> <cell>2899,31</cell> <cell>2907,45</cell> <cell>2916,95</cell> <cell>2928,99</cell> <cell>2945,02</cell> <cell>2967,14</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>2842,62</cell> <cell>2850,88</cell> <cell>2859,06</cell> <cell>2867,08</cell> <cell>2874,81</cell> <cell>2882,30</cell> <cell>2889,78</cell> <cell>2897,61</cell> <cell>2906,39</cell> <cell>2916,41</cell> <cell>2928,93</cell> <cell>2945,25</cell> <cell>2967,45</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>45</cell> <cell>2837,64</cell> <cell>2846,16</cell> <cell>2854,67</cell> <cell>2863,04</cell> <cell>2871,22</cell> <cell>2879,22</cell> <cell>2887,33</cell> <cell>2895,67</cell> <cell>2904,98</cell> <cell>2915,55</cell> <cell>2928,49</cell> <cell>2945,20</cell> <cell>2967,40</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>2832,76</cell> <cell>2841,52</cell> <cell>2850,29</cell> <cell>2858,96</cell> <cell>2867,52</cell> <cell>2875,98</cell> <cell>2884,57</cell> <cell>2893,58</cell> <cell>2903,39</cell> <cell>2914,42</cell> <cell>2927,81</cell> <cell>2944,73</cell> <cell>2967,05</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>55</cell> <cell>2827,68</cell> <cell>2836,69</cell> <cell>2845,72</cell> <cell>2854,75</cell> <cell>2863,75</cell> <cell>2872,67</cell> <cell>2881,69</cell> <cell>2891,11</cell> <cell>2901,42</cell> <cell>2913,02</cell> <cell>2926,73</cell> <cell>2943,98</cell> <cell>2966,34</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>60</cell> <cell>2822,65</cell> <cell>2831,90</cell> <cell>2841,10</cell> <cell>2850,50</cell> <cell>2859,87</cell> <cell>2869,15</cell> <cell>2878,72</cell> <cell>2888,62</cell> <cell>2899,35</cell> <cell>2911,32</cell> <cell>2925,50</cell> <cell>2942,98</cell> <cell>2965,39</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>65</cell> <cell>2817,49</cell> <cell>2826,90</cell> <cell>2836,30</cell> <cell>2845,97</cell> <cell>2855,65</cell> <cell>2865,45</cell> <cell>2875,49</cell> <cell>2885,85</cell> <cell>2897,09</cell> <cell>2909,43</cell> <cell>2923,90</cell> <cell>2941,69</cell> <cell>2964,11</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>2812,16</cell> <cell>2821,78</cell> <cell>2831,61</cell> <cell>2841,42</cell> <cell>2851,53</cell> <cell>2861,63</cell> <cell>2872,06</cell> <cell>2882,90</cell> <cell>2894,56</cell> <cell>2907,33</cell> <cell>2922,24</cell> <cell>2940,13</cell> <cell>2962,66</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>2806,75</cell> <cell>2816,63</cell> <cell>2826,56</cell> <cell>2836,80</cell> <cell>2847,14</cell> <cell>2857,70</cell> <cell>2868,49</cell> <cell>2879,67</cell> <cell>2891,79</cell> <cell>2905,04</cell> <cell>2920,17</cell> <cell>2938,33</cell> <cell>2960,97</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>2801,25</cell> <cell>2811,23</cell> <cell>2821,38</cell> <cell>2831,92</cell> <cell>2842,56</cell> <cell>2853,38</cell> <cell>2864,54</cell> <cell>2876,22</cell> <cell>2888,73</cell> <cell>2902,35</cell> <cell>2917,83</cell> <cell>2936,31</cell> <cell>2959,07</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>2795,69</cell> <cell>2805,85</cell> <cell>2816,32</cell> <cell>2827,12</cell> <cell>2838,07</cell> <cell>2849,28</cell> <cell>2860,86</cell> <cell>2872,88</cell> <cell>2885,56</cell> <cell>2899,55</cell> <cell>2915,46</cell> <cell>2934,14</cell> <cell>2956,94</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>2790,13</cell> <cell>2800,40</cell> <cell>2811,05</cell> <cell>2822,15</cell> <cell>2833,38</cell> <cell>2844,81</cell> <cell>2856,80</cell> <cell>2869,16</cell> <cell>2882,25</cell> <cell>2896,58</cell> <cell>2912,84</cell> <cell>2931,77</cell> <cell>2954,70</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>2704,36</cell> <cell>2794,91</cell> <cell>2805,79</cell> <cell>2817,08</cell> <cell>2828,46</cell> <cell>2840,26</cell> <cell>2852,47</cell> <cell>2865,15</cell> <cell>2878,71</cell> <cell>2898,44</cell> <cell>2910,02</cell> <cell>2929,15</cell> <cell>2952,08</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>100</cell> <cell>2778,64</cell> <cell>2789,32</cell> <cell>2800,25</cell> <cell>2811,80</cell> <cell>2823,55</cell> <cell>2835,3s</cell> <cell>2848,18</cell> <cell>2861,12</cell> <cell>2875,07</cell> <cell>2890,04</cell> <cell>2906,97</cell> <cell>2926,28</cell> <cell>2949,34</cell> <cell/> </row> </table>
<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0708.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0702"/>
<p><hi rend="italic">TABLE II.—</hi> Real specific Gravities at the different Temperatures.</p><table> <row> <cell>Heat.</cell> <cell>The pure ſpirit.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 5 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 10 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 15 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 20 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 25 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 30 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 35 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 40 grains of wacer.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 45 grains oſ water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 50 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 55 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 60 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 65 grains oſ water</cell> </row> <row> <cell>deg.</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>30</cell> <cell>,83896</cell> <cell>,84995</cell> <cell>,85957</cell> <cell>,86825</cell> <cell>,8758;</cell> <cell>,88282</cell> <cell>,8892i</cell> <cell>,895il</cell> <cell>,9OO54</cell> <cell>,90558</cell> <cell>,9iθ23</cell> <cell>,91449</cell> <cell>,91847</cell> <cell>,92217</cell> </row> <row> <cell>35</cell> <cell>,83672</cell> <cell>,84769</cell> <cell>,8.5729</cell> <cell>,86587</cell> <cell>,87357</cell> <cell>,88059</cell> <cell>,887OI</cell> <cell>,89294</cell> <cell>,89839</cell> <cell>,90345</cell> <cell>,90811</cell> <cell>,91241</cell> <cell>,91640</cell> <cell>,92009</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>,83445</cell> <cell>,84539</cell> <cell>,85507</cell> <cell>,8636l</cell> <cell>,87134</cell> <cell>,87838</cell> <cell>,88481</cell> <cell>,89e73</cell> <cell>,89617</cell> <cell>,90127</cell> <cell>,90596</cell> <cell>,91026</cell> <cell>,91428</cell> <cell>,91799</cell> </row> <row> <cell>45</cell> <cell>,83214</cell> <cell>,843iO</cell> <cell>,85277</cell> <cell>,86i3i</cell> <cell>,86907</cell> <cell>,87613</cell> <cell>,88255</cell> <cell>,88849</cell> <cell>,89396</cell> <cell>,89909</cell> <cell>,90380</cell> <cell>,90812</cell> <cell>,91211</cell> <cell>,91584</cell> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>,82977</cell> <cell>,84076</cell> <cell>,85042</cell> <cell>,85902</cell> <cell>,86676</cell> <cell>,87384</cell> <cell>,88030</cell> <cell>,88626</cell> <cell>,89174</cell> <cell>,89684</cell> <cell>,90160</cell> <cell>,90596</cell> <cell>,90997</cell> <cell>,91379</cell> </row> <row> <cell>55</cell> <cell>,82736</cell> <cell>,83834</cell> <cell>,84802</cell> <cell>,85664</cell> <cell>,8644i</cell> <cell>,87150</cell> <cell>,87796</cell> <cell>,88393</cell> <cell>,88945</cell> <cell>,89458</cell> <cell>,89933</cell> <cell>,90367</cell> <cell>,90768</cell> <cell>,91144</cell> </row> <row> <cell>60</cell> <cell>,82500</cell> <cell>,83599</cell> <cell>,84568</cell> <cell>,85430</cell> <cell>,86208</cell> <cell>,86918</cell> <cell>,87568</cell> <cell>,88169</cell> <cell>,88720</cell> <cell>,89232</cell> <cell>,89707</cell> <cell>,90144</cell> <cell>,90549</cell> <cell>,90927</cell> </row> <row> <cell>65</cell> <cell>,82262</cell> <cell>,83362</cell> <cell>,84334</cell> <cell>,85193</cell> <cell>,85976</cell> <cell>,86686</cell> <cell>,87337</cell> <cell>,87938</cell> <cell>,88490</cell> <cell>,89c06</cell> <cell>,89479</cell> <cell>,89920</cell> <cell>,90328</cell> <cell>,90707</cell> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>,82023</cell> <cell>,83124</cell> <cell>,84092</cell> <cell>,84951</cell> <cell>,85736</cell> <cell>,86451</cell> <cell>,87105</cell> <cell>,87705</cell> <cell>,88454</cell> <cell>,88773</cell> <cell>,89252</cell> <cell>,896⅛5</cell> <cell>,90104</cell> <cell>,90482</cell> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>,81780</cell> <cell>,82878</cell> <cell>,83851</cell> <cell>,84710</cell> <cell>,85493</cell> <cell>,86212</cell> <cell>,86864</cell> <cell>,87466</cell> <cell>,88018</cell> <cell>,88538</cell> <cell>,89018</cell> <cell>,89464</cell> <cell>,89872</cell> <cell>,90252</cell> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>,81530</cell> <cell>,82631</cell> <cell>,83603</cell> <cell>,84467</cell> <cell>,85248</cell> <cell>,85966</cell> <cell>,86623</cell> <cell>,87228</cell> <cell>,87776</cell> <cell>,88301</cell> <cell>,88781</cell> <cell>,8922</cell> <cell>,89639</cell> <cell>,90021</cell> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>,81283</cell> <cell>,82386</cell> <cell>,83355</cell> <cell>,84221</cell> <cell>,85006</cell> <cell>,85723</cell> <cell>,86380</cell> <cell>,86984</cell> <cell>,8754l</cell> <cell>,88067</cell> <cell>,88551</cell> <cell>,88998</cell> <cell>,89409</cell> <cell>,8979</cell> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>,81039</cell> <cell>,82142</cell> <cell>.83111</cell> <cell>,83977</cell> <cell>,84762</cell> <cell>,85483</cell> <cell>,86139</cell> <cell>,86743</cell> <cell>,87302</cell> <cell>,87827</cell> <cell>,88312</cell> <cell>,88758</cell> <cell>,89173</cell> <cell>,89556</cell> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>,80788</cell> <cell>,81888</cell> <cell>,82860</cell> <cell>,83724</cell> <cell>,84511</cell> <cell>,85232</cell> <cell>,85896</cell> <cell>,86499</cell> <cell>,87060</cell> <cell>,87586</cell> <cell>,88θ69</cell> <cell>,88521</cell> <cell>’88937</cell> <cell>’89321</cell> </row> <row> <cell>100</cell> <cell>,80543</cell> <cell>,81643</cell> <cell>,82618</cell> <cell>,83478</cell> <cell>,84262</cell> <cell>,84984</cell> <cell>,85646</cell> <cell>,86254</cell> <cell>,86813</cell> <cell>,87340</cell> <cell>,87824</cell> <cell>,88271</cell> <cell>,88691</cell> <cell>,89081</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Heat</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 70 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 75 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 80 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 85 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 90 grains of water</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 95 grains of water.</cell> <cell>100 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>95 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>90 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>85 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>80 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>75 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>70 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>65 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>deg.</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>30</cell> <cell>,92563</cell> <cell>,92889</cell> <cell>,93191</cell> <cell>,93474</cell> <cell>,93741</cell> <cell>,93991</cell> <cell>,94222</cell> <cell>,94447</cell> <cell>,94675</cell> <cell>,9492°</cell> <cell>,95173</cell> <cell>,95429</cell> <cell>,9568l</cell> <cell>,9594·</cell> </row> <row> <cell>35</cell> <cell>,92355</cell> <cell>,92680</cell> <cell>,92986</cell> <cell>,93274</cell> <cell>,9354l</cell> <cell>,9379o</cell> <cell>,94025</cell> <cell>,94249</cell> <cell>,94484</cell> <cell>,94734</cell> <cell>,94988</cell> <cell>,95246</cell> <cell>,955°2</cell> <cell>,0 ί 77</cell> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>,9215l</cell> <cell>,92476</cell> <cell>,92783</cell> <cell>,93072</cell> <cell>,9334i</cell> <cell>,93592</cell> <cell>,93827</cell> <cell>,94058</cell> <cell>,94295</cell> <cell>,94547</cell> <cell>,94802</cell> <cell>,95060</cell> <cell>,9532δ</cell> <cell>,956θ!</cell> </row> <row> <cell>45</cell> <cell>,9 ί 937</cell> <cell>,92264</cell> <cell>,92570</cell> <cell>,92859</cell> <cell>,93131</cell> <cell>,93382</cell> <cell>,93621</cell> <cell>,9386θ</cell> <cell>,94096</cell> <cell>,94348</cell> <cell>,94605</cell> <cell>,9487*</cell> <cell>,95*43</cell> <cell>,9542i</cell> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>,9l723</cell> <cell>,92050</cell> <cell>,92358</cell> <cell>,92647</cell> <cell>,92919</cell> <cell>,93i77</cell> <cell>,934*9</cell> <cell>,93658</cell> <cell>,93897</cell> <cell>,94M9</cell> <cell>,94414</cell> <cell>,94683</cell> <cell>’94958</cell> <cell>,95241</cell> </row> <row> <cell>55</cell> <cell>,915∙02</cell> <cell>,9*837</cell> <cell>,92145</cell> <cell>,9 2 43 6</cell> <cell>,92707</cell> <cell>,92963</cell> <cell>,93208</cell> <cell>,93452</cell> <cell>,93696</cell> <cell>,93948</cell> <cell>,942*3</cell> <cell>,94486</cell> <cell>’94767</cell> <cell>,oςoς,</cell> </row> <row> <cell>60</cell> <cell>,91287</cell> <cell>,91622</cell> <cell>,9i933</cell> <cell>,92225</cell> <cell>,92499</cell> <cell>,92758</cell> <cell>,93002</cell> <cell>,93247</cell> <cell>,93493</cell> <cell>,93749</cell> <cell>,94018</cell> <cell>,94296</cell> <cell>,94579</cell> <cell>,04.871</cell> </row> <row> <cell>65</cell> <cell>,91066</cell> <cell>,91400</cell> <cell>,91715</cell> <cell>,92010</cell> <cell>,92283</cell> <cell>,92546</cell> <cell>,92794</cell> <cell>,93040</cell> <cell>,93285</cell> <cell>’93546</cell> <cell>,93822</cell> <cell>,94°99</cell> <cell>,94388</cell> <cell>,qi68(</cell> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>,90847</cell> <cell>,91181</cell> <cell>,91493</cell> <cell>,9’793</cell> <cell>,92069</cell> <cell>,92333</cell> <cell>,92580</cell> <cell>,92828</cell> <cell>,93076</cell> <cell>,93337</cell> <cell>,936*6</cell> <cell>,93898</cell> <cell>,94*93</cell> <cell>,9450c</cell> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>,90617</cell> <cell>,90952</cell> <cell>,91270</cell> <cell>,91569</cell> <cell>,91849</cell> <cell>,9211 I</cell> <cell>,92364</cell> <cell>,92613</cell> <cell>,92865</cell> <cell>,93*32</cell> <cell>,934i3</cell> <cell>,93695</cell> <cell>,93989</cell> <cell>,94301</cell> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>,9o385</cell> <cell>,9°723</cell> <cell>,91042</cell> <cell>,9i34θ</cell> <cell>,91622</cell> <cell>,91891</cell> <cell>,92i42</cell> <cell>,92393</cell> <cell>,92646</cell> <cell>,929*7</cell> <cell>,932oι</cell> <cell>,93488</cell> <cell>,93785</cell> <cell>,94102</cell> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>,9oi57</cell> <cell>,90496</cell> <cell>,90818</cell> <cell>,91119</cell> <cell>,91403</cell> <cell>,91670</cell> <cell>,91923</cell> <cell>,92179</cell> <cell>,92432</cell> <cell>,92700</cell> <cell>,92989</cell> <cell>,93282</cell> <cell>’93582</cell> <cell>,9390i</cell> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>,89927</cell> <cell>,90270</cell> <cell>,90590</cell> <cell>,90891</cell> <cell>,91177</cell> <cell>,91446</cell> <cell>,9i705</cell> <cell>,91962</cell> <cell>,92220</cell> <cell>,92491</cell> <cell>,92779</cell> <cell>,93°75</cell> <cell>,9338ι</cell> <cell>,Q27O1</cell> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>,89688</cell> <cell>,90037</cell> <cell>,90358</cell> <cell>,9c662</cell> <cell>,90949</cell> <cell>,91221</cell> <cell>,9i48l</cell> <cell>,9174°</cell> <cell>,91998</cell> <cell>,92272</cell> <cell>,92562</cell> <cell>,928ς8</cell> <cell>,93*70</cell> <cell>,Q34-Q*7</cell> </row> <row> <cell>100</cell> <cell>’89453</cell> <cell>,89798</cell> <cell>,90123</cell> <cell>,90428</cell> <cell>,90718</cell> <cell>,90992</cell> <cell>,91252</cell> <cell>,915*3</cell> <cell>,91769</cell> <cell>,92047</cell> <cell>,92346</cell> <cell>,92646</cell> <cell>,92957</cell> <cell>,9329;</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Heat</cell> <cell>60 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>55 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell><p>50 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</p></cell> <cell>45 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>40 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>35 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>30 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>25 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>20 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water..</cell> <cell>15 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>10 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>5 grains of ſpirit to 100 grains of water.</cell> <cell>Water.</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>deg.</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>30</cell> <cell>,962Θ9</cell> <cell>,96470</cell> <cell>,96719</cell> <cell>,96967</cell> <cell>,97200</cell> <cell>,974*8</cell> <cell>,97635</cell> <cell>,97860</cell> <cell>,98lθ8</cell> <cell>,98412</cell> <cell>,98804</cell> <cell>,99334</cell> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>35</cell> <cell>,96048</cell> <cell>,963 Π</cell> <cell>,9^579</cell> <cell>,96840</cell> <cell>,97©86</cell> <cell>,973*9</cell> <cell>,97556</cell> <cell>,97801</cell> <cell>,98076</cell> <cell>,98397</cell> <cell>,98804</cell> <cell>,99344</cell> <cell>,00090</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>40</cell> <cell>,958/9</cell> <cell>,96159</cell> <cell>,96434</cell> <cell>,96706</cell> <cell>,96967</cell> <cell>,97220</cell> <cell>,97472</cell> <cell>,97737</cell> <cell>,98033</cell> <cell>,98373</cell> <cell>,98795</cell> <cell>,99345 1</cell> <cell>,00094</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>45</cell> <cell>,957°5</cell> <cell>»95993</cell> <cell>,96280</cell> <cell>,96563</cell> <cell>,96840</cell> <cell>,97110</cell> <cell>,97384</cell> <cell>,97666</cell> <cell>,97980</cell> <cell>,98338</cell> <cell>,98774</cell> <cell>,99338 I</cell> <cell>,00086</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>50</cell> <cell>,95534</cell> <cell>,95831</cell> <cell>,961 26</cell> <cell>,96420</cell> <cell>,96708</cell> <cell>,96995</cell> <cell>,97284</cell> <cell>,97589</cell> <cell>,97920</cell> <cell>,98293</cell> <cell>,98745</cell> <cell>,99316 I</cell> <cell>,00068</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>55</cell> <cell>,95357</cell> <cell>,95662</cell> <cell>,95966</cell> <cell>,96272</cell> <cell>,96575</cell> <cell>,96877</cell> <cell>,97i8l</cell> <cell>,975°c</cell> <cell>,97847</cell> <cell>,98239</cell> <cell>,98702</cell> <cell>99284 I</cell> <cell>,00038</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>60</cell> <cell>,95181</cell> <cell>,95493</cell> <cell>,95804</cell> <cell>,96122</cell> <cell>,96437</cell> <cell>,96752</cell> <cell>,97074</cell> <cell>,97409</cell> <cell>»97771</cell> <cell>,98176</cell> <cell>,98654</cell> <cell>99244 I</cell> <cell>,00000</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>65</cell> <cell>,95000</cell> <cell>,95318</cell> <cell>,95635</cell> <cell>,95962</cell> <cell>,96288</cell> <cell>,96620</cell> <cell>,96959</cell> <cell>,973o9</cell> <cell>,97688</cell> <cell>,98lθ6</cell> <cell>,98594</cell> <cell>99194</cell> <cell>,9995°</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>,94813</cell> <cell>,95*39</cell> <cell>,95469</cell> <cell>,95802</cell> <cell>,96143</cell> <cell>,96484</cell> <cell>,96836</cell> <cell>,97203</cell> <cell>,97596</cell> <cell>,98028</cell> <cell>98527</cell> <cell>99*34</cell> <cell>,99894</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>,94623</cell> <cell>,94957</cell> <cell>,95292</cell> <cell>,95638</cell> <cell>,95987</cell> <cell>,96344</cell> <cell>,96*708</cell> <cell>,97086</cell> <cell>,97495</cell> <cell>,97943</cell> <cell>,98454</cell> <cell>99066</cell> <cell>,99830</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>,94+31</cell> <cell>,94768</cell> <cell>,951 II</cell> <cell>,95467</cell> <cell>,95826</cell> <cell>,96192</cell> <cell>,96568</cell> <cell>,96963</cell> <cell>,973δ15</cell> <cell>,97845</cell> <cell>,98367</cell> <cell>98991</cell> <cell>,99759</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>,94236</cell> <cell>,94579</cell> <cell>,94'932</cell> <cell>,95297</cell> <cell>,95667</cell> <cell>,96046</cell> <cell>,96437</cell> <cell>,96843</cell> <cell>,97271</cell> <cell>,97744</cell> <cell>,98281</cell> <cell>98912</cell> <cell>,99681</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>,94042</cell> <cell>,94389</cell> <cell>,94748</cell> <cell>,95123</cell> <cell>,95502</cell> <cell>,95889</cell> <cell>,96293</cell> <cell>,96711</cell> <cell>,97*53</cell> <cell>,97637</cell> <cell>q8,8ς</cell> <cell>98824</cell> <cell>,99598</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>»93839</cell> <cell>,94196</cell> <cell>,94563]</cell> <cell>,94944</cell> <cell>,95328</cell> <cell>,95727</cell> <cell>,96l39</cell> <cell>,96568</cell> <cell>,97025</cell> <cell>,97523</cell> <cell>98082</cell> <cell>98729</cell> <cell>,99502</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>1OO</cell> <cell>,93638</cell> <cell>»93999</cell> <cell>,94368</cell> <cell>,94759</cell> <cell>,95152</cell> <cell>,95556</cell> <cell>,95983</cell> <cell>,96424</cell> <cell>,96895</cell> <cell>,974OI</cell> <cell>,97969</cell> <cell>,98625</cell> <cell>,99402</cell> <cell/> </row> </table>
<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0709.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0703"/>
<p>We formerly obſerved, that the ſeries of mixtures choſen by Sir Charles Blagden, for the advantages attending it in making the experiment, was not ſuited for ſolving the questions which commonly occur in the spirit buſineſs. He accordingly ſuggeſts the propriety of forming tables in a convenient series from the data furniſhed by theſe experiments, indicating the proportion of ingredients contained in ſome conſtant weight or bulk.</p><p>To facilitate the conſtruction of ſuch tables, it is neceſſary to conſider the ſubject in the moſt general manner. Therefore let <hi rend="italic">a</hi> repreſent the confiant number 100. Let w and <hi rend="italic">s</hi> repreſent the quantities of water and ſpirit by weight in any mixture ; that is, the pounds, ounces, or grains of each; Let <hi rend="italic">x</hi> repreſent the quantity <hi rend="italic">percent,</hi> of ſpirits alſo by weight ; that is, the number of pounds of ſpirits contained in 100 pounds of the mixture ; and let <hi rend="italic">y</hi> be its quantity <hi rend="italic">percent,</hi> in gallons, or the number of gallons contained in 100 gallons of the unmixed ingredients. Let <hi rend="italic">m</hi> be the bulk of a pound of ſpirit of any given temperature, the bulk of a pound of water <hi rend="italic">of the ſame temperature</hi> being accounted 1.</p><p>Then w+s is the weight of any mixture, and w+ <hi rend="italic">m s</hi> is its bulk.</p><p>We have the following proportions : I. w+ s: s = a : x, and x = as/w+s (Equation 1ſt); and hence s may be found when <hi rend="italic">x</hi> the percentage in weight is given, for s + wx/a-x (Equation 2.)</p><p>2. w + ms : ms = a : y, and y = a ms/w+ms (Equation 3d) ; and s may be found when y, the percentage in gallons, is given ; for s = my/a-y (Equation 4th.)</p><p>The uſual queſtions which can be ſolved from theſe experiments are,</p><p>I. To ascertain the quantity of ſpirits <hi rend="italic">per cent,</hi> in bulk from obſervation of the specific gravity, or to tell how many gallons of ſpirit are in 100 gallons of mixture.</p><p>Look for the specific gravity in the table, and at the head of the column will be found the w and <hi rend="italic">s</hi> correſponding. If the preciſe specific gravity obſerved is not in the tables, the s muſt be found by interpolation. And here it is proper to remark, that taking the ſimple proportional parts of specific gravity will not be sufficiently exact, eſpecially near the beginning or the end of the table, becauſe the denſities correſponding to the ſeries of mixtures do not change uniformly. We muſt have recourſe to the general rules of interpolation, by means of firſt and second differences, or be provided with a ſubsidiary table of differences. A good deal of practice in computations of this kind ſuggeſted the following method of making ſuch interpolations with great diſpatch and abundant accuracy. On a plate of wood, or metal, or ſtiff card-paper, draw a line EF (fig. 3.),. as a ſcale of equal parts, repreſenting the leading or equable arithmetical ſeries of any table. (In the preſent caſe EF is the ſcale on which <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is computed.)— Through every point of diviſion draw the perpendiculars BA, EC, F D, &amp;c. Make one of them AB more conſpicuous than the rest, and diſtinguiſh the others alſo in ſuch sort, that the eye ſhall readily catch their diſtance from the principal line A B. Let GPL be a thin flip of whalebone, of uniform breadth and thickneſs, alſo divided into equal parts properly diſtinguiſhable. Laſtly, let there be a pin P fixed near the middle of the principal line AB.</p><p>Now ſuppoſe that a value of s is to be interpolated by means of an obſerved specific gravity not in the table. Look for the neareſt to it, and note its diſtance from the preceding and the following. Let theſe be PH and PK on the flexible ſcale. Alſo take notice of the lines K 10 and H 10, whoſe diſtances from AB are equal to the conſtant difference between the ſucceſsive values of S, or to any eaſily eſtimated multiple of it (as in the preſent caſe we have taken 10 and 10, inſtead of 5 and 5, the running difference of Sir Charles Blagden’s table). Then, leaning the middle point P of the whalebone on the pin P in the board, bend it, and place it ſlantwiſe till the points K and H fall ſomewhere on the two parallels K 10 and H 10. No matter how oblique the poſition of the whalebone is. It will bend in ſuch a manner that its different points of division (repreſenting different specific gravities) will fall on the parallels which repreſent the correſponding values of <hi rend="italic">s.</hi> We can ſay that all this may be done in leſs than half a minute, and leſs time than is neceſſary for inſpecting a table of proportional parts, and not the tenth part of that neceſſary for interpolating by ſecond differences. Yet it is exact enough (if of the size of a duodecimo page ) for interpolating three decimal places, This is ten times more exact than the preſent caſe requires. To return from this digreſſion.</p><p>Having thus found <hi rend="italic">s</hi> in the table, we get <hi rend="italic">x</hi> or y by the equations as/w+s = x, and a ms/w+ms = y.</p><p>But here a material circumſtance occurs. The weight of alcohol <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> and its percentage <hi rend="italic">x,</hi> was rightly determined by the specific gravity, becauſe it was interpolated between two values, which were experimentally connected with this specific gravity. But in making the tranſition from <hi rend="italic">x</hi> to <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> we only give the per centage in gallons before mixture, but not the number of gallons of alcohol contained in an hundred gallons of mixed liquor. For when we have taken <hi rend="italic">a—y</hi> and y inſtead of w and <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> they will indeed make a ſimilar compound when mixed, becauſe the proportion of their ingredients is the ſame. But they will not make 100 gallons of this compound, becauſe there is a ſhrinking or condenſation by mixture, and the specific gravity by which we interpolated <hi rend="italic">s</hi> is the physical or real specific gravity correſponding to <hi rend="italic">w</hi> and <hi rend="italic">s</hi>; while w+s/w x ms, the specific gravity implied in the value of <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> is the mathematical denſity independent on this condenſation. Since therefore y, together with <hi rend="italic">a—y,</hi> make leſs than 100 gallons of the compound, there muſt in 100 gallons of it be more alcohol than is expreſſed by <hi rend="italic">y.</hi></p><p>Let G be the mathematical specific gravity (= w+s/w+ms), and <hi rend="italic">g</hi> the physical or real obſerved specific gravity (which we cannot expreſs algebraically) ; .and let <hi rend="italic">z</hi> be the gallons of alcohol really contained in 100 gallons of the compound. The bulk being inverſely as the denſity or specific gravity, it is evident that the.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0710.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0704"/>
bulk of the compound muſt be to 100 gallons as <hi rend="italic">g</hi> to G. And ſince we want to make it ſtill up to 100 gallons, we muſt increaſe it in the proportion of G to <hi rend="italic">g.</hi> And becauſe this augmentation muſt be of the same ſtrength with this contracted liquor, both ingredients muſt be increaſed in the proportion of G to <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> and we muſt have G <hi rend="italic">:g = y</hi>: z, and <hi rend="italic">z = g</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">× y/G.</hi> Now, instead of y, write a ms/w+ms, and inſtead of I/G write w+ms/w+s, which are reſpectively equal to them. This gives us z = <hi rend="italic">g a × w+ms/w+s × ms/w+s, = g a × ms/w+s.</hi> All this will be illuſtrated by an example.</p><p>Suppoſe that we have obſerved the ſpecific gravity of a ſpirituous liquor of the temperature 60⁰ to be 0,94128. Looking into Sir Charles Blagden’s table, we find the gravities 0,94018 and 0,94296, and the s correſponding to them is 80 and 75, the water in each mixture being 100. By interpolation we obtain the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> correſponding to 0,94128, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi> 78. At this temperature m = 1/0.825, = 1,21212, and ms= 94,54545, = 19,997, or very nearly 50.</p><p>We have ſeen even perſons not unacquainted with ſubjects of this kind puzzled by this fort of paradox, z is ſaid to be the percentage of ſpirit in the compound. The compound has the ſame proportion of ingredients when made up to 100 gallons as before, when <hi rend="italic">y</hi> was ſaid to be its percentage, and yet <hi rend="italic">y</hi> and <hi rend="italic">z</hi> are not the ſame. The fact is, that although z is the number of gallons of alcohol really contained in 100 gallons of the compound, and this alcohol is in the ſame proportion as before to the water, this proportion is not that of 50 to 50 : for if the ingredients were ſeparated again, there would be 50 gallons of alcohol and 52,876 of water.</p><p>The proportion of the ingredients in their ſeparate state is had by the 3d Equation <hi rend="italic">y = a ms/w+ms</hi>, which</p><p>is equivalent to G <hi rend="italic">a ms/w+s.</hi> For the preſent example <hi rend="italic">y</hi> will be found 48,599, and <hi rend="italic">a —y,</hi> or the water per cent. 51,401, making 100 gallons of unmixed ingredients. We ſee then that there has been added 1,398 gallons of alcohol ; and since both ingredients are augmented in the proportion of G to <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> there have alſo been added 1,478 of water, and the whole addition for making up the 100 gallons of compound is 2,876 gallons ; and if the ingredients of the compound were ſeparate, they would amount to 102,876 gallons. This might have been found at the first, by the proportion, G:y— G = 100: <hi rend="italic">(The addition.)</hi></p><p>The next queſtion which uſually occurs in busineſs is to find what density will reſult from any proposed mixture <hi rend="italic">per</hi> gallon. This queſtion is ſolved by means of the equation wy/m(a-y) = s <hi rend="italic">.</hi> In this examination it will be</p><p>moſt convenient to make w = <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> If the value of <hi rend="italic">s</hi> found in this manner falls on a value in the tables, we have the ſpecific gravity by inspection, If not, we must interpolate.</p><p><hi rend="italic">N. B.</hi> The value of m, which is employed in theſe reductions, varies with the temperature. It is always obtained by dividing the ſpecific gravity of alcohol of that temperature by the ſpecific gravity of water of the ſame temperature. The quotient is the real ſpecific gravity of alcohol for that temperature. Both of theſe are to be had in the first and laſt copartments of Sir Charles Blagden’s table.</p><p>Theſe operations for particular caſes give the anſwers to particular occasional questions. By applying them to all the numbers in the table, tables may be constructed for ſolving every queſtion by inspection.</p><p>There is another queſtion which occurs moſt frequently in the exciſe tranſactions, and alſo in all compositions of ſpirituous liquors, viz. What ſtrength will reſult from a mixture of two compounds of known ſtrength, or mixing any compound with water ? To ſolve queſtions of this kind by the table ſo often quoted, we muſt add into one film the water <hi rend="italic">per</hi> gallon of the different liquors. In like manner, take the ſum of the ſpirits, and ſay, as the ſum of the waters is to that of the alcohols, ſo is <hi rend="italic">a</hi> to <hi rend="italic">s ;</hi> and operate with <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and s as before.</p><p>Analogous to this is the queſtion of the duties. Theſe are levied on proof ſpirit ; that is, a certain duty is charged on a gallon of proof ſpirit ; and the gauger’s busineſs is to diſcover how many gallons of proof ſpirit there is in any compound. The ſpecification of proof ſpirit in our exciſe laws is exceedingly obſcure and complex. A gallon weighing 7 pounds 13 ounces (at 55⁰) is accounted 1 to 6 under proof. The gallon of water contains 58476 grains, and this ſpirit is 54688. Its denſity therefore is 0,93523 at 55⁰, or (as may be inferred from the table) 0,9335 at 60⁰. This denſity correſponds to a mixture of 100 grains of water with 93,457 of alcohol. If this be ſuppoſed to reſult from the mixture of 6 gallons of alcohol with 1 of water (as is ſuppoſed by the designation of 1 to 6 under proof), the gallon of proof ſpirits consists of 100 parts of ſpirits by weight, mixed with 75 parts of water. Such a ſpirit will have the denſity 0,9162 nearly.</p><p>This being premiſed, in order to find the gallons of proof ſpirits in any mixture, find the quantity of alcohol by weight, and then ſay, as 100 to 175, ſo is the alcohol in the compound to the proof ſpirit that may be made of it, and for which the duties muſt be paid.</p><p>We have considered this ſubject at ſome length, becauſe it is of great importance in the ſpirit-trade to have theſe circumſtances aſcertained with precision ; and becauſe the ſpecific gravity is the only ſure criterion that can be had of the ſtrength. Firing of gunpowder, or producing a certain bubble by ſhaking, are very vague teſts ; whereas, by the ſpecific gravity, we can very ſecurely aſcertain the ſtrength within one part in 500, as will preſently appear.</p><p>Sir Charles Blagden, or Mr Gilpin, have publiſhed @@* a moſt copious ſet of tables, calculated from theſe valuable experiments. In theſe, computations are made for every unit of the hundred, and for every degree of the thermometer. But theſe tables are ſtill not in the moſt commodious form for bufineſs. Mr John Wilſon, an ingenious gentleman reſiding at Dundee, has just pub- @@@[m]* Philosophy Trans. 179.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0711.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0705"/>
liſhed at Edinburgh tables ſomewhat ſimilar, founded on the ſame experiments. Both of theſe tables ſhow the quantities by meaſure correſponding to every unit by weight of Sir Charles Blagden’s experiments, and for every degree of temperature. They alſo ſhow the <hi rend="italic">percentage</hi> of alcohol, and the condenſation or the quantity lost by mixture. But as they both retain the original ſeries of parts by weight, which is very unuſual, the ſpirit traders will find conſiderable difficulty in making uſe of them. Retaining this ſeries alſo cauſes all the percentag <hi rend="italic">e</hi> numbers (which are the only intereſting ones to the trader) to be fractional, and no anſwer can be had without a double interpolation.</p><p>We have therefore calculated a table in the form in which it muſt be moſt uſeful and acceptable to thoſe who are engaged in the ſpirit trade, ſhowing at once the ſpecific gravity which reſults from any proportion of admixture in hundredth parts of the whole. This anſwers immediately the chief queſtions in the terms in which they are uſually conceived and propoſed. The two firſt or leading columns ſhow the proportion in gallons, pints, or other cubic meaſures, of the mixture, the whole quantity being always 100. The second column ſhows the correſponding ſpecific gravity : ſo that we can either find the proportion of the ingredients by the obſerved ſpecific gravity, or find the gravity reſulting from any proportion ot the ingredients. A third column ſhows how much the hundred meaſures of the two ingredients fall ſhort of making an hundred meaſures of the compound. A simple proportion, which can be done without the pen, will determine what part of this deficiency muſt be made up by ſpirit. The uſe of this table muſt now be ſo familiar to the reader’s mind, that we need not give further inſtructions about it.</p><p>This is followed by another ſimilar table, giving an immediate anſwer to the moſt usual queſtion, “ How many meaſures of alcohol are there really contained in 100 meaſures ? This is alſo accompanied by a column of condenſation. It would have been ſomewhat more elegant, had the ſpecific gravities in this table made the equable ſeries and leading column. But we did not advert to this till we had computed the table, and the labour was too great to be repeated for flight reaſons. The tables are only for the temperature 60⁰. To this the ſpirituous liquors can always be brought in theſe climates ; and in caſes where we cannot, a moment’s inspection of Sir Charles Blagden’s table will point out very nearly (or exactly, by a ſhort computation) the neceſſary corrections.</p><table> <row> <cell cols="2">Compound.</cell> <cell><p>Specific</p><p>Gravity.</p></cell> <cell>Cond. <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell cols="2">C∣&gt;nιp&lt;&gt;U! d.</cell> <cell><p>Specific</p><p>Gravity.</p></cell> <cell>Cond. /«· <hi rend="italic">cent.</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell cols="2">Compound.</cell> <cell><p>Specific</p><p>Gravity.</p></cell> <cell>Cond. <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>s.</cell> <cell>w.</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>S.</cell> <cell>w.</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>S.</cell> <cell>w.</cell> <cell/> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>IOO</cell> <cell>0</cell> <cell>O,825O</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>66</cell> <cell>34</cell> <cell>O,9o73</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi> <hi rend="italic">&gt;5</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell>33</cell> <cell>67</cell> <cell>C.964o</cell> <cell>2,3</cell> </row> <row> <cell>99</cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>O,8278</cell> <cell>O,i9</cell> <cell/> <cell>65</cell> <cell>35</cell> <cell>O,9o95</cell> <cell>2,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></cell> <cell>68</cell> <cell>O,965i</cell> <cell>2,3</cell> </row> <row> <cell>98</cell> <cell>2</cell> <cell>0,83c6</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;33</cell> <cell/> <cell>64</cell> <cell>36</cell> <cell>O,9il6</cell> <cell>2,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>31</cell> <cell>69</cell> <cell>O,9662</cell> <cell>2,2</cell> </row> <row> <cell>97</cell> <cell>3</cell> <cell>o»8333</cell> <cell>0 <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> 4</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> 3</cell> <cell>37</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 37</cell> <cell>2,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>3θ</cell> <cell>70</cell> <cell>O,9673</cell> <cell>2,I</cell> </row> <row> <cell>96</cell> <cell>4</cell> <cell>o,8?6o</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> √</cell> <cell/> <cell>62</cell> <cell>38</cell> <cell>o&gt;9i57</cell> <cell>2,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>29</cell> <cell>71</cell> <cell>O,9683</cell> <cell>2,</cell> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>5</cell> <cell>0,8387</cell> <cell>0,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>61</cell> <cell>39</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 77</cell> <cell>2&gt;7</cell> <cell/> <cell>28</cell> <cell>72</cell> <cell>O,9693</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> *9</cell> </row> <row> <cell>94</cell> <cell>6</cell> <cell>0,8413</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> c</hi> &gt;7</cell> <cell/> <cell>60</cell> <cell>40</cell> <cell>0,9198</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;7</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 7</cell> <cell>73</cell> <cell>0,9704</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">i,</hi> 9</cell> </row> <row> <cell>93</cell> <cell>7</cell> <cell>0,8439</cell> <cell>0,8</cell> <cell/> <cell>59</cell> <cell>41</cell> <cell>0,9218</cell> <cell>2,7</cell> <cell/> <cell>26</cell> <cell>74</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;97 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 3</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 158</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>92</cell> <cell>8</cell> <cell>0,8465</cell> <cell>0,9</cell> <cell/> <cell>58</cell> <cell>42</cell> <cell>0,9238</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;7</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 5</cell> <cell>75</cell> <cell>0,9724</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;7 !</cell> </row> <row> <cell>9 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></cell> <cell>9</cell> <cell>0,8491</cell> <cell>I,</cell> <cell/> <cell>57</cell> <cell>43</cell> <cell>0,9257</cell> <cell>2 7</cell> <cell/> <cell>24</cell> <cell>76</cell> <cell>°’9734</cell> <cell>i,6 1</cell> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>10</cell> <cell>0,8516</cell> <cell>I,I</cell> <cell/> <cell>56</cell> <cell>44</cell> <cell>0,9277</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 3</cell> <cell>77</cell> <cell>0,9744</cell> <cell>1,6 I</cell> </row> <row> <cell>89</cell> <cell>11</cell> <cell>c,8 c42</cell> <cell>1,2</cell> <cell/> <cell>55</cell> <cell>45</cell> <cell>c,9296</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell>22</cell> <cell>78</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9754</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1,5</hi> i</cell> </row> <row> <cell>88</cell> <cell>12</cell> <cell>0,8567</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;3</cell> <cell/> <cell>54</cell> <cell>46</cell> <cell>0,9316</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell>21</cell> <cell>79</cell> <cell>0,9763</cell> <cell>i,4 1</cell> </row> <row> <cell>1 <hi rend="superscript"> g</hi> 7</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 3</cell> <cell>0,8592</cell> <cell>M</cell> <cell/> <cell>53</cell> <cell>47</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> &gt;9335</cell> <cell>2.8</cell> <cell/> <cell>20</cell> <cell>80</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9773</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1,3</hi> 1</cell> </row> <row> <cell>j 86</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 4</cell> <cell>0,8617</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;5</cell> <cell/> <cell>52</cell> <cell>48</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9353</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 9</cell> <cell>81</cell> <cell>0,9783</cell> <cell>1,2 j</cell> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>I Ç</cell> <cell>0,8641</cell> <cell>bς</cell> <cell/> <cell>51</cell> <cell>49</cell> <cell>0,0371</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell>18</cell> <cell>82</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9793</cell> <cell>1&gt;2</cell> </row> <row> <cell>84</cell> <cell>16</cell> <cell>0,8666</cell> <cell>1,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>50</cell> <cell>5°</cell> <cell>c,9388</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 7</cell> <cell>83</cell> <cell>0,9802</cell> <cell>I&gt;I</cell> </row> <row> <cell>»3</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 7</cell> <cell>0,8690</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;7</cell> <cell/> <cell>49</cell> <cell>5 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></cell> <cell>c,94c6</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell>16</cell> <cell>84</cell> <cell>0,9812</cell> <cell>1,</cell> </row> <row> <cell>82</cell> <cell>18</cell> <cell>0&gt;S713</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> i</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">&gt;7</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell>4«</cell> <cell>5 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> &gt;94 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 3</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 5</cell> <cell>85</cell> <cell>0,9822</cell> <cell>0,9</cell> </row> <row> <cell>81</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 9</cell> <cell>0.8737</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;7</cell> <cell/> <cell>47</cell> <cell>53</cell> <cell>0,9440</cell> <cell>2,8</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> i</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">4</hi></cell> <cell>86</cell> <cell>0,9832</cell> <cell>0,9</cell> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>20</cell> <cell>0,876c</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>46</cell> <cell>54</cell> <cell>0,9456</cell> <cell>2,7</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> i</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">3</hi></cell> <cell>87</cell> <cell>0,9842</cell> <cell>0.8</cell> </row> <row> <cell>79</cell> <cell>21</cell> <cell>0,8764</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;9</cell> <cell/> <cell>45</cell> <cell>55</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9473</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;7</cell> <cell/> <cell>12</cell> <cell>88</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 9 <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> 53</cell> <cell>°&gt;7</cell> </row> <row> <cell>78</cell> <cell>22</cell> <cell>0,8807</cell> <cell>2,</cell> <cell/> <cell>44</cell> <cell>56</cell> <cell>0,9489</cell> <cell>2»7</cell> <cell/> <cell>I I</cell> <cell>89</cell> <cell>0,9863</cell> <cell>o,7</cell> </row> <row> <cell>77</cell> <cell>23</cell> <cell>0,8830</cell> <cell>2,</cell> <cell/> <cell>43</cell> <cell>57</cell> <cell>0,9505</cell> <cell>2,7</cell> <cell/> <cell>10</cell> <cell>90</cell> <cell>0,9874</cell> <cell>0,6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>76</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> 4</cell> <cell>0,8853</cell> <cell>2, I</cell> <cell/> <cell>42</cell> <cell>'5«</cell> <cell>0,9320</cell> <cell>2χ7</cell> <cell/> <cell>9</cell> <cell>9 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></cell> <cell>0,9886</cell> <cell>°»5</cell> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>25</cell> <cell>0,8876</cell> <cell>2,1</cell> <cell/> <cell>41</cell> <cell>59</cell> <cell>°’9535</cell> <cell>2,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>8</cell> <cell>92</cell> <cell>0,9897</cell> <cell>0,4</cell> </row> <row> <cell>74</cell> <cell>26</cell> <cell>0,8899</cell> <cell>2,2</cell> <cell/> <cell>40</cell> <cell>60</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9549</cell> <cell>2,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>7</cell> <cell>93</cell> <cell>0,9909</cell> <cell>°’3</cell> </row> <row> <cell>, 73</cell> <cell>27</cell> <cell>0,8921</cell> <cell>2,2</cell> <cell/> <cell>39</cell> <cell>61</cell> <cell>0,9563</cell> <cell>2,6</cell> <cell/> <cell>6</cell> <cell>94</cell> <cell>0,9921</cell> <cell>0,3</cell> </row> <row> <cell>7*</cell> <cell>28</cell> <cell>0,8944</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;3</cell> <cell/> <cell>3«</cell> <cell>62</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> &gt;9577</cell> <cell>2»5</cell> <cell/> <cell>5</cell> <cell>95</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9933</cell> <cell>0,2</cell> </row> <row> <cell>71</cell> <cell>29</cell> <cell>0,8966</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;3</cell> <cell/> <cell>37</cell> <cell>63</cell> <cell>0,9590</cell> <cell>2.5</cell> <cell/> <cell>.&lt; 4</cell> <cell>96</cell> <cell>0,9946</cell> <cell>0,1</cell> </row> <row> <cell>7 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi></cell> <cell>3 <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi></cell> <cell>0,8988</cell> <cell>2,4</cell> <cell/> <cell>3 <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> &gt;</cell> <cell>64</cell> <cell>c,6603</cell> <cell>2,4</cell> <cell/> <cell>3</cell> <cell>97</cell> <cell>0,9959</cell> <cell>0,07</cell> </row> <row> <cell>69</cell> <cell>31</cell> <cell>0,9010</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;5</cell> <cell/> <cell>35</cell> <cell>65</cell> <cell>0,9616</cell> <cell>2,4</cell> <cell/> <cell>2</cell> <cell>98</cell> <cell>0,9972</cell> <cell>0,03</cell> </row> <row> <cell>68</cell> <cell>3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></cell> <cell>0,9031</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> *5</cell> <cell/> <cell>34</cell> <cell>66</cell> <cell>c,9628</cell> <cell>2,3</cell> <cell/> <cell>I</cell> <cell>99</cell> <cell>0,9985</cell> <cell>0,01</cell> </row> <row> <cell>67</cell> <cell>33</cell> <cell>0,9053</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> »5</cell> <cell/> <cell>33</cell> <cell>67</cell> <cell>0,9640</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;3</cell> <cell/> <cell>0</cell> <cell>IOO</cell> <cell>1 I,OOCO</cell> <cell>0,00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>66</cell> <cell>34</cell> <cell>0,9073</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;5</cell> <cell/> <cell>1</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>1</cell> <cell/> </row> </table>
<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0712.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0706"/>
<table> <row> <cell>Spir. <hi rend="italic">per ■cent.</hi></cell> <cell>Specific Gravity.</cell> <cell>Contr.</cell> <cell/> <cell>Spir. <hi rend="italic">per cent.</hi></cell> <cell><p>Specific</p><p>Gravicy.</p></cell> <cell>Contr.</cell> <cell/> <cell>8pir. <hi rend="italic">.per cent.</hi></cell> <cell><p>Specific</p><p>Gravity.</p></cell> <cell>Contr.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>too</cell> <cell>θ,825θθ</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>66</cell> <cell>0,91095</cell> <cell>2,59</cell> <cell/> <cell>33</cell> <cell>O,9648l</cell> <cell>2,27</cell> </row> <row> <cell>99</cell> <cell>O,82629</cell> <cell>0,18</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> 5</cell> <cell>O,9i3θ6</cell> <cell>2,62</cell> <cell/> <cell>3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></cell> <cell>O,96587</cell> <cell>2,2 I</cell> </row> <row> <cell>98</cell> <cell>O,83142</cell> <cell>°’34</cell> <cell/> <cell>64</cell> <cell>O,9i5il</cell> <cell>2,64</cell> <cell/> <cell>31</cell> <cell>O,9669i</cell> <cell>2,1 5</cell> </row> <row> <cell>■97</cell> <cell>0,83449</cell> <cell>0,46</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi> 3</cell> <cell>O,91714</cell> <cell>2,66</cell> <cell/> <cell>30</cell> <cell>O,96793</cell> <cell>2,08</cell> </row> <row> <cell>96</cell> <cell>O,8375O</cell> <cell>0,57</cell> <cell/> <cell>62</cell> <cell>O,91914</cell> <cell>2,68</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 9</cell> <cell>0,96894.</cell> <cell>2,00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>95</cell> <cell>O,84O48</cell> <cell>0,68</cell> <cell/> <cell>61</cell> <cell>0,92i 12</cell> <cell>2,70</cell> <cell/> <cell>28</cell> <cell>O,96992</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;93</cell> </row> <row> <cell>r <hi rend="subscript"> 94</hi></cell> <cell>O&gt;84339</cell> <cell>0,8</cell> <cell/> <cell>60</cell> <cell>O,92qc8</cell> <cell>2,72</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 7</cell> <cell>0,97089</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">i,</hi> 86</cell> </row> <row> <cell>'93</cell> <cell>O,8462i</cell> <cell>0,9</cell> <cell/> <cell>59</cell> <cell>0,92 ÇOI</cell> <cell>2,74</cell> <cell/> <cell>26</cell> <cell>O.97i85</cell> <cell>ι&gt;79</cell> </row> <row> <cell>92</cell> <cell>O,849OO</cell> <cell>I 01</cell> <cell/> <cell>58</cell> <cell>O,92692</cell> <cell>2,76</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 5</cell> <cell>O,9728θ</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;7i</cell> </row> <row> <cell>91</cell> <cell>O,85i72</cell> <cell>I,XI</cell> <cell/> <cell>57</cell> <cell>O,92882</cell> <cell>2,77</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 4</cell> <cell>Q.97374</cell> <cell>1,63</cell> </row> <row> <cell>90</cell> <cell>0,85443</cell> <cell>1,21</cell> <cell/> <cell>5 <hi rend="superscript"> 6</hi></cell> <cell>0,93072</cell> <cell>2,78</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 3</cell> <cell>O,97468</cell> <cell>1,56</cell> </row> <row> <cell>89</cell> <cell>O,857o4</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>-3 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell>55</cell> <cell>O,93258</cell> <cell>2,80</cell> <cell/> <cell>22</cell> <cell>O,9756l</cell> <cell>1,48</cell> </row> <row> <cell>88</cell> <cell>O,8597i</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;39</cell> <cell/> <cell>54</cell> <cell>°’93 43^</cell> <cell>2,8 I</cell> <cell/> <cell>2 1</cell> <cell>0,97654</cell> <cell>¼</cell> </row> <row> <cell>87</cell> <cell>O,86228</cell> <cell>M7</cell> <cell/> <cell>53</cell> <cell>0,93612</cell> <cell>2,81</cell> <cell/> <cell>20</cell> <cell>0,97747</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">i,</hi> 3 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>86</cell> <cell>O,86483</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;54</cell> <cell/> <cell>5 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi></cell> <cell>0,93786</cell> <cell>2,82</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 9</cell> <cell>O,9784i</cell> <cell>1,24</cell> </row> <row> <cell>85</cell> <cell>O,86737</cell> <cell>1,61</cell> <cell/> <cell>51</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;9395 <hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi></cell> <cell>2,81</cell> <cell/> <cell>18</cell> <cell>0,97936</cell> <cell>M7</cell> </row> <row> <cell>84</cell> <cell>O,86987</cell> <cell>1,67</cell> <cell/> <cell>50</cell> <cell>0,94128</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,79</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 7</cell> <cell>0,98032</cell> <cell>i,08</cell> </row> <row> <cell>83</cell> <cell>O,87235</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>,74</cell> <cell/> <cell>49</cell> <cell>0,94293</cell> <cell>2,78</cell> <cell/> <cell>16</cell> <cell>O',98 I 29</cell> <cell>1,00</cell> </row> <row> <cell>82</cell> <cell>O,8748 i</cell> <cell>1.81</cell> <cell/> <cell>48</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> &gt;94455</cell> <cell>2,76</cell> <cell/> <cell>Π</cell> <cell>0,98228</cell> <cell>,93</cell> </row> <row> <cell>81</cell> <cell>O,87726</cell> <cell>i,88</cell> <cell/> <cell>47</cell> <cell>0,94610</cell> <cell>2,73</cell> <cell/> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 4</cell> <cell>0,98328</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>80</cell> <cell>O,87969</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> &gt;94</cell> <cell/> <cell>46</cell> <cell>0,94768</cell> <cell>2,71</cell> <cell/> <cell>*3</cell> <cell>0,98430</cell> <cell>&gt;78</cell> </row> <row> <cell>79</cell> <cell>0,88207</cell> <cell>2,</cell> <cell/> <cell>45</cell> <cell>o, <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi> 49 <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 3</cell> <cell>2,70</cell> <cell/> <cell>12</cell> <cell>0,98534</cell> <cell>,7i</cell> </row> <row> <cell>78</cell> <cell>O,88445</cell> <cell>2,05</cell> <cell/> <cell>44</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>-95θ74</cell> <cell>2,68</cell> <cell/> <cell>I I</cell> <cell>0,98640</cell> <cell>,66</cell> </row> <row> <cell>• 77</cell> <cell>O,88676</cell> <cell>2,1 I</cell> <cell/> <cell>43</cell> <cell>0,95219</cell> <cell>. 2,66</cell> <cell/> <cell>IO</cell> <cell>0,98748</cell> <cell>,61</cell> </row> <row> <cell>76</cell> <cell>0,88909</cell> <cell>2,17</cell> <cell/> <cell>42</cell> <cell>o,95364</cell> <cell>2,63</cell> <cell/> <cell>9</cell> <cell>0,98858</cell> <cell>&gt;5i</cell> </row> <row> <cell>75</cell> <cell>O,89i4θ</cell> <cell>2,22</cell> <cell/> <cell>41</cell> <cell>0,95502</cell> <cell>2,60</cell> <cell/> <cell>8</cell> <cell>0,98973</cell> <cell>&gt;43</cell> </row> <row> <cell>74</cell> <cell>O,893O7</cell> <cell>2,26</cell> <cell/> <cell>40</cell> <cell>0,95636</cell> <cell>2,58</cell> <cell/> <cell>7</cell> <cell>0,99091.</cell> <cell>&gt;34.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>73</cell> <cell>O,89593</cell> <cell>2, <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> I</cell> <cell/> <cell>39</cell> <cell>0,95766</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,54</cell> <cell/> <cell>6</cell> <cell>0,99211</cell> <cell>&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> 5</cell> </row> <row> <cell>72</cell> <cell>O,898i5</cell> <cell>2,36</cell> <cell/> <cell>38</cell> <cell>0,95894</cell> <cell>2,49</cell> <cell/> <cell>5</cell> <cell>0,99334</cell> <cell>,18</cell> </row> <row> <cell>7 <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi></cell> <cell>O,9OO35</cell> <cell>2,41</cell> <cell/> <cell>37</cell> <cell>0,96019</cell> <cell>2,46</cell> <cell/> <cell>4</cell> <cell>0,99461</cell> <cell>,12</cell> </row> <row> <cell>70</cell> <cell>O,9o24i</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;49</cell> <cell/> <cell>36</cell> <cell>0,96141</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,43</cell> <cell/> <cell>3</cell> <cell>0,9959 <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi></cell> <cell>»7</cell> </row> <row> <cell>69</cell> <cell>O,9O464</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,47</cell> <cell/> <cell>35</cell> <cell>0,96258</cell> <cell>2,38</cell> <cell/> <cell>2</cell> <cell>0,99725</cell> <cell>&gt;3</cell> </row> <row> <cell>68</cell> <cell>O,9θ675</cell> <cell>2,51</cell> <cell/> <cell>34</cell> <cell>0,96371</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;33</cell> <cell/> <cell>I</cell> <cell>0,99861</cell> <cell>,1</cell> </row> <row> <cell>67</cell> <cell>O,9θ885</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> &gt;55</cell> <cell/> <cell>33</cell> <cell>0,96481</cell> <cell>2,27</cell> <cell/> <cell>0</cell> <cell>I,00000</cell> <cell>,0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>66</cell> <cell>O,9IO95</cell> <cell><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>,59</cell> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> </row> </table>
<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0713.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0707"/>
<p>particles ; for the denſity of water is to that of ſpirits nearly as 6 to 5, and the changes of specific gravity are nearly as 6 to 3.</p><p>We alſo ſee that the changing cauſe, which produces the abſolute condenſation of each ingredient, ceaſes to operate when 75 parts of water have been mixed with 25 of alcohol: for the variation of specific gravity, from diminiſhing comes now to increaſe ; and therefore, in this particular ſtate of compoſition, is equable. Things are now in the ſame ſtate as if we were mixing two fluids which did not act on each other, but were mutually diſſeminated, and whoſe specific gravities are nearly as 9 to 10 ; for the variation 9 of specific gravity may be conſidered as the 100th part of the whole difference, in the ſame manner as 17,5 would have been had water and alcohol ſuſtained no contraction.</p><p>The imagination is greatly aſſiſted in the contemplation of geometrical quantity by exhibiting it in its own form. Specific gravity, being an expreſſion of denſity (a notion purely geometrical), admits of this illuſtration.</p><p>Therefore let AB (fig. 4.) repreſent the bulk of any mixture of water and alcohol. The specific gravity of water may be repreſented by a line of ſuch a length, that AB ſhall be the difference between the gravities of alcohol and water. Suppoſe it extended upwards, towards <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> till B <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is to A <hi rend="italic">a</hi> as 10,000 to 8250. It will suit our purpoſe better to repreſent it by a parallelogram <hi rend="italic">a</hi> BFe, of any breadth BF. In this caſe the difference of the specific gravities of alcohol and water will be expreſſed by the parallelogram ABFE. If there were no change produced in the denſity of one or both ingredients, the specific gravity of the compound would increaſe as this parallelogram does, and AGHE would be the augmentation correſponding to the mixture of the quantity AG of alcohol with the quantity GB of water, and ſo of other mixtures. But, to expreſs the augmentation of denſity as it really obtains, we must do it by ſome curvilineal area DABCHD, which varies at the rate determined by Sir Charles Blagden’s experiments. This area muſt be preciſely equal to the rectangle ABFE. It muſt therefore fall without it in ſome places, and be deficient in others. Let DMHKC be the curve which correſponds with theſe experiments. It is evident to the mathematical reader, that the ordinates LM, GH, IK, &amp;c. of this curve are in the ultimate ratio of the differences of the obſerved specific gravities. If A α, αβ, &amp;c. are each =5 <hi rend="italic">,</hi> the little ſpaces A α δ D, α <hi rend="italic">β b δ</hi> &amp;c. will be preciſely equal to the differences of the specific gravities 0,8250; 0,8387; 0,85 16; &amp;c. correſponding to the different mixtures of water and alcohol. The curve cuts the side of the parallelogram in K, where the ordinate GK expreſſes the mean variation of denſity 0,0017,5. IK is the ſmalleſt variation. The condenſation may be expreſſed by drawing a curve <hi rend="italic">dm G kſ</hi> parallel to DMGKF, making D <hi rend="italic">d —</hi> AE. The condenſation is now repreſented by the ſpaces comprehended between this laſt curve and the abſciſſa AGE, reckoning thoſe negative which lie on the other side of it. This shows us, not only that the condenſation is greateſt in the mixture AG X GB, but alſo that in mixing ſuch a compound with another AIxlB, there is a rarefaction. Another curve ANPOB may be drawn, of which the ordinates LN, GP, 10, &amp;c. are proportional to the areas AL <hi rend="italic">md,</hi> AGmD, AIZGmD (=AGmD—GIk), &amp;c. This curve ſhows the whole condenſation.</p><p>This manner of repreſenting the specific gravities of mixtures will ſuggeſt many curious inferences to ſuch as will conſider them in the manner of Boſcovich, with a view to aſcertain the nature of the forces of coheſion and chemical affinities: And this manner of viewing the ſubject becomes every day more promiſing, in conſequence of our improvements in chemical knowledge; for we now see, that mechaniſm, or motive forces, are the causes of chemical action. We ſee in almoſt every caſe, that chemical affinities are comparable with mechanical preſſures; becauſe the converſion of a liquid into a vapour or gas is prevented by atmoſpheric preſſure, and produced by the great chemical agent heat. The action of heat, therefore, or of the cauſe of heat, is a mechanical action, and the forces are common mechanical forces, with which we are familiarly acquainted.</p><p>“ It may be alſo remarked in the column of contractions, that in the beginning the contractions augment nearly in the proportion of the quantity of ſpirits (but more ſlowly) ; whereas, in the end, the contractions are nearly in the duplicate proportion of the quantity of water. This circumſtance deserves the conſideration of the philoſopher. We have repreſented it to the eye by the curve α <hi rend="italic">g h d.’’</hi></p><p>We ſhould here take ſome notice of the attempt made to elude ſome part of the duties, by adding ſome ingredient to the ſpirits. But our information on this ſubject is not very exact ; and beſides it would be doing no ſervice to the trader to put fraud more in his power. There are ſome salts which make a very great augmentation of denſity, but they render the liquor unpalatable. Sugar is frequently uſed with this view ; 16 grains of refined ſugar diſſolved in 1000 grains of proof ſpirits gave it no ſuſpicious taſte, and increaſed its specific gravity from 0,920 to 0,925, which is a very great change, equivalent to the addition of 9 grains of water to a mixture of 100 grains of alcohol and 80 of water.</p></div></body></text></TEI>