<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0699.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0693-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPINOZA</label>
(Benedict), was born at Amſterdam the 34th November 1632, His father was a Jew of Portugal, by profeſſion a merchant. After being taught Latin by a physician, he applied himſelf for many years to the ſtudy of theology, and afterwards devoted himſelf entirely to philoſophy. He began very early to be diſſatisfied with the Jewiſh religion ; and as his temper was open, he did not conceal his doubts From the ſynagogue. The Jews, it is ſaid, offered to tolerate his infidelity, and even promiſed him a pension of a thouſand dollars <hi rend="italic">per annum,</hi> if he would remain in their ſociety, and continue outwardly to practiſe their ceremonies. But if this offer was really made, he rejected it, perhaps from his aversion to hypocriſy, or rather becauſe he could not endure the reſtraint which it would have imposed. He alſo refuſed the legacy of a very conſiderable fortune, to the prejudice of the natural heirs ; and he learned the art of poliſhing glaſs for ſpectacles, that he might ſubſiſt independently of every one.</p><p>He would probably have continued in the ſynagogue for ſome time longer, if it had not been for an accident. As he was returning home one evening from the theatre, he was stabbed by a Jew : the wound was flight ; but the attempt naturally led Spinoza to conclude that the Jews had formed the deſign of aſſaſſinating him. After leaving the ſynagogue, he became a Chriſtian, and frequented the churches of the Lutherans and Calviniſts. He now devoted himſelf more than ever to his favourite philoſophical ſpeculations ; and finding himſelf frequently interrupted by the visits of his friends, he left Amſterdam, and settled at the Hague, where he often continued for three months together without ever ſtirring from his lodging. During his reſidence in that city, his hoſteſs, who was a Lutheran, asked him one day if ſhe could be ſaved while the continued in her religion ? “ Yes (replied Spinoza), “provided you join to your religion a peaceable and virtuous life ’’ From this anſwer it has been concluded that he was a Christan in appearance only, while in reality he regarded all religions as indifferent. But this concluſion would be too ſevere, even if the woman had been a Mahometan. H is <hi rend="italic">Tractatus Theolοgico-politicus</hi>, which was publiſhed about that time, is a better proof of his inſincerity than a thouſand ſuch conclusions ; tor this book contains all thoſe doctrines in embryo which were afterwards unfolded in his Op <hi rend="italic">era Posthuma,</hi> and which are generally conſidered as a ſyſtem of atheiſm.</p><p>His fame, which had now ſpread far and wide, obliged him ſometimes to interrupt his philoſophical reveries. Learned men viſited him from all quarters While the prince of Condé commanded the French army in Utrecht, he intreated Spinoza to viſit him; and though he was abſent when the philoſopher arrived, he returned immediately, and spent a conſiderable time with him in converſation. The elector Palatine offered to make Spinoza profeſſor of philoſophy at Heidelberg ; which, however, he declined.</p><p>He died of a conſumption at the Hague on the 21st February 1677, at the age or 45. His life was a perpetual contradiction to his opinions. He was temperate, liberal, and remarkably diſintereſted ; he was ſociable, affable, and friendly. His converſation was agreeable and inſtructive, and never deviated from the ſtricteſt propriety.</p><p>The only edition of the works of Spinosa that we have ſeen is in two volumes ſmall 4to; the former of<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0700.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0694"/>
which was printed at Hamburg in the year 1670, and the latter we know not where, in 1677, a few months after his death. In the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus Theologico-politicus,</hi> already mentioned, he treats of <hi rend="italic">prophecy</hi> and <hi rend="italic">prophets ;</hi> and of the <hi rend="italic">call of the Hebrews,</hi> whom he affirms to have been diſtinguiſhed from other nations only by the admirable form of their government, and the fitneſs of their laws for long preserving their political state. He is likewiſe of opinion, or at leaſt pretends to be ſo, that God may, in what we call a <hi rend="italic">ſupernatural way,</hi> have given political inſtitutes to other nations as well as to the Hebrews, who were, he ſays, at no time a peculiar people to the Supreme Lord of heaven and earth ; for, according to him, all hiſtory, ſacred and profane, teſtifies that every nation was bleſſed with the light of prophecy. That light indeed, if his notions of it be just, was of very little value. He labours to prove, that the prophets were diſtinguiſhed from other men only by their piety and virtue ; that their revelations depended wholly on their imaginations and the diſpositions of their minds ; that they were often groſsly ignorant and highly prejudiced ; that the ſpeculative opinions of one prophet are ſeldom in uniſon with thoſe of another ; and that their writings are valuable to us only for the excellent rules which he acknowledges they contain reſpecting the practice of piety and virtue. He then proceeds to treat of the divine law and of miracles ; and endeavours to prove that no miracle, in the proper ſenſe of the word, can have been at any time performed ; becauſe every thing happens by a neceſſity of nature, the reſult of the divine decrees, which are from all eternity neceſſary themſelves. He acknowledges, that in the Scriptures, which he professes to admit as true hiſtory, miracles are often mentioned ; but he ſays that they were only Angular events which the ſacred hiſtorrans <hi rend="italic">imagined</hi> to be miraculous: and he then gives ſome very extraordinary rules for interpreting the books of the Old and New Teſtaments where they treat of miracles, or appear to foretel future events. See our articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Miracle</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Prophecy.</hi></p><p>Having thus diveſted the Scriptures of every thing characteriſtic of a revelation from heaven, he next calls in queſtion their authenticity. He affirms, in contradiction to the cleareſt internal evidence, that the Pentateuch and all the other hiſtorical books muſt have been written by one man ; and that man, he thinks, could not have flourished at a period earlier than that of Ezra. The grounds of this opinion are unworthy of the talents of Spinoza; for that he had talents is incontrovertible. His principal objection to the authenticity of the Pentateuch is, that Moſes is made to ſpeak of himſelf in the third perſon, and to talk of the Canaanites being then in the land ; and becauſe he finds in his writings, as well as in the books of Joſhua, Judges, Ruth, Samuel, &amp;c. places deſigned by names which he suppoſes they had not in the early ages of which theſe books contain the hiſtory, he concludes that theſe writings muſt be one compilation from ancient records made at a very late period ; more eſpecially as the author often ſpeaks of things of great antiquity remaining to this day. The books of Eſther, Ezra, Nehemiah, and Chronicles, muſt have been compiled, he thinks, under the Maccabees ; and he ſeems to conſider as of equal value with them the ſtory of Tobit, and the other two apocryphal treatiſes intitled the Wiſdom of Solomon and Eccleſiaſticus.</p><p>Theſe ſenſeleſs cavils, worthy only of one of thoſe modern freethinkers whoſe learning, in the opinion of Biſhop Warburton, is not ſufficient to carry them even to the confines of rational doubt, we have ſufficiently obviated in another place (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Scripture,</hi> n⁰ 8—31 ) Spinoza urges them against the other books of the Old Teſtament. The prophecies of Iſaiah, Jeremiah, Ezekiel, Daniel, Hoſea, and Jonah, are, as we have them, only fragments, he ſays, of the writings of thoſe men compiled by the Phariſees under the second temple from ancient and voluminous records.</p><p>In the midſt of this dogmatical ſcepticiſm, if we may uſe ſuch a phraſe, he bears ſuch a teſtimony to the laſt chapters of the book of Daniel, as we ſhould not have looked for in the writings either of a Jew or of a Deiſt, After detailing the various hypotheſes which in his time were held reſpecting the author and the intention of the book of <hi rend="italic">Job ;</hi> in which, he ſays, <hi rend="smallcaps">Momus</hi> is called <hi rend="smallcaps">Satan,</hi> he proceeds in theſe words : “ Tranſeo ad Danielis librum ; his fine dubio ex cap. 8. ipſius Danſelis ſcripta continet. Undenam autem priora ſeptem capita deſcripta fuerint, neſcio<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>Tractatus, cap. <gap/> , p. 130.</p></note> *;” thus admitting the famous prophecy of the ſeventy weeks. The canon of the Old Teſtament, he ſays, was finally ſettled by rabbins of the Phariſaical ſect, who wiſhed to exclude from it the books of <hi rend="italic">Proverbs, Ecelesiastes,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Eseekiel,</hi> as they had actually excluded others of equal value ; but the three books in queſtion were inſerted by the influence of two of the rabbis of greater wiſdom and integrity than the rest.</p><p>That ſo paradoxical a writer, who had been originally a Jew, and was now almoſt a Deiſt, ſhould have treated the New Teſtament with as little ceremony as the Old, will not ſurpriſe the intelligent reader. He begins his remarks, however, with affirming, that no man can peruſe the Chriſtian Scriptures, and not acknowlcdge the apoſtles to have been prophets ; but he thinks that their mode of propheſying was altogether different from that which prevailed under the Moſaic dispenſation ; and that the gift, whatever it was, forſook them the inſtant that they left off <hi rend="italic">preaching,</hi> as their <hi rend="italic">writings</hi> have to him every appearance of human compoſitions. This diſtinction between Chriſtian and Jewiſh prophecy is the more wonderful, that he founds it principally on the diſſimilarity of sty <hi rend="italic">le</hi> viſible in the writings of the Old and New Teſtaments ; though, in his second chapter, which treats of the works of the Jewiſh prophets, he ſays expressly, “ Stylus deinde prophetiæ pro eloquentia cujuſque prophetæ variabat, prophetiae enim Ezekielis et Amosis non sunt, ut illæ Esaiæ, Nachumi eleganti, sed rudiore stylo scriptæ.” That the Hebrew ſcholar may be convinced of the truth of this remark, he recommends to him to ſtudy diligently the writings of theſe prophets, and to conſider the occaſions on which their prophecies were uttered : “ Quæ ſi omnia recte perpendentur (ſays he) facile oſtendant, Deum nullum habere ſtylum peculiarem dicendi, ſed tantum pro eruditione, et capacitate prephetæ eatenus effe elegantem, compendioſum, ſeverum, rudem, prolixum, et obſcurum.” Another objection brought by Spinoza againſt the prophecies of the New Teſtament ariſes from the authors of them having been<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0701.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0695"/>
at all times maſters of themſelves. This, ſays he, was peculiarly the caſe of St Paul, who often confirms his doctrine by <hi rend="italic">reaſoning,</hi> which the Jewish prophets never condeſcended to do, as it would have ſubmitted their dogmas to the examination of <hi rend="italic">private judgment.</hi> Yet, with singular inconſiſtency, he affirms, that the Jewiſh prophets could not know that the impreſſions made on their imaginations proceeded from God, but by a ſign given them, which by their own <hi rend="italic">reaſon</hi> or <hi rend="italic">judgment</hi> they knew would never be vouchſafed to an impious or a wicked man.</p><p>After theſe very free remarks on the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtaments, he naturally enough expreſſes a ſuſpicion, that by thoſe who conſider the Bible as the epiſtle of God ſent from heaven to men, he will be thought to have sinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt by vilifying his dictates. This leads him to inquire in what ſenſe the Scriptures are the word of God ; and he gravely determines them to be ſo only as they <hi rend="italic">actually</hi> contribute to make men more virtuous and holy. It is not enough that they are <hi rend="italic">calculated</hi> to improve virtue and holineſs : for ſhould the words of the languages in which they are written acquire in proceſs of time a ſignification different from what they had originally; ſhould mankind loſe all knowledge of theſe languages; or even ſhould they agree to neglect the books, whether from ignorance or from wilfulneſs— thoſe books would ceaſe to be the word of God, and become nothing better than waste paper and ink ; juſt as the two tables, which Moſes broke on obſerving the idolatry of his countrymen, were not the covenant between Jehovah and the Iſraelites, but merely two pieces of ſtone ! The Scriptures, however, are the word of God, becauſe they teach the true religion of which God is the author ; and they have taught it in ſuch a manner, he ſays, that it can never be loſt or corrupted whatever become of the books of the Old and New Teſtaments, or of the languages in which they are written. The whole of religion, as the Scriptures themſelves teſtify, conſiſts in the love of God above all things, and of our neighbours as ourſelves : whence it follows, that we muſt believe that God exiſts, and watcheth over all things by his providence ; that he is omnipotent, and has decreed the pious to be ultimately happy, and the impious miſerable ; and that our final ſalvation depends ſolely on His grace or favour. Theſe truths, with their necessary conſequences, are the word of God : they are clearly taught in the Scriptures, and can never be corrupted ; but every thing elſe in theſe volumes is vain, he ſays, and of no greater importance to us than facts related in any other ancient and authentic hiſtory.</p><p>Such are the opinions which were entertained of revelation by a man whom a critic, writing in a Chriſtian country, and profeſſing to be a zealous Chriſtian himſelf, has lately pronounced to have been a <hi rend="italic">chosen vessel.</hi> For what purpoſe he was <hi rend="italic">chosen</hi> it is not eaſy to conceive. His religion, as it appears in the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus,</hi> is the worſt kind of Deiſm ; and his politics are ſuch as our monthly critics are not wont to teach, and ſuch as we truſt ſhall never be ſeriouſly taught by any Britiſh subject. By the law of nature, he ſays, every man before the formation of civil government has an unqueſtionable right to whatever appears eligible either to his reaſon or to his appetites ; and may get posseſſion of it by <hi rend="italic">intreaty,</hi> by <hi rend="italic">violence, by fraud,</hi> or by <hi rend="italic">any other means</hi> attended with less trouble to himſelf <hi rend="italic">(sive vi, sive dolo, sive precibus, sive quocunque demum modo facilius poterit ) ;</hi> and may treat as an enemy every perſon who ſhall attempt to obſtruct his purpoſe. But when men agree to devolve this right upon others, and to conſtitute a political ſtate, which both reaſon and appetite muſt perſuade them to do, then are they in duty bound to obey every mandate of the government, however absurd it may be <hi rend="italic">(omnia mandata tametsi abſurdissima ),</hi> as long as that government can enforce its edicts, and no longer ; for, according to him, right and power are ſo inſeparably united, that when a government loses its power, it has no longer the ſmalleſt claim to obedience. This doctrine, he ſays, is moſt <hi rend="italic">obviously</hi> juſt when taught of democratical governments; but it is in fact equally true of monarchies and ariſtocracies : “ Nam quiſquis ſummam habet poteſtatem, five unus fit, five pauci, five denique omnes, certum eſt ei summum jus <hi rend="italic">quicquid velit imperandi,</hi> competere : et præterea quiſquis poteſtatem ſe defendendi, five ſponte, live vi <hi rend="italic">coactus,</hi> in alium tranſtulit, eum ſuo jure naturali plane ceſſisse, et conſequenter eidem ad omnia abſolute parere decreviſſe quod omnia præstare tenetur, quamdiu rex, five nobiles, five populus ſummam, quam acceperunt, poteſtatem, quæ juris transferendi fundamentum suit, conſervant; nec his plura addere opus eſt<note anchored="true" n="2" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Tract. cap. xvi. p. 181</p></note> *.” We heartily agree with him, that to this precious concluſion it is needleſs to add a single word.</p><p>Taking our leave therefore of his <hi rend="italic">Tractatus Theοlοgico-politicus,</hi> we ſhall now give our readers a ſhort account of his <hi rend="italic">Opera Posthuma.</hi> Theſe conſiſt of, 1. Ε <hi rend="smallcaps">τηκα,</hi> <hi rend="italic">more geometrico demonstrata ;</hi> 2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Politica;</hi> 3. <hi rend="smallcaps">De Emendatione Intellectus;</hi> 4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Epistolæ,</hi> <hi rend="italic">et ad eas</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Responsiones;</hi> 5. <hi rend="smallcaps">Compendium Grammatices Linguæ Hebrææ.</hi></p><p>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Ethica</hi> are divided into five parts, which treat in order, <hi rend="italic">de</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Deo ;</hi> <hi rend="italic">de natura et origine</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">mentis ;</hi> <hi rend="italic">de origine et natura</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">affectuum ;</hi> <hi rend="italic">de</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">servitute</hi> <hi rend="italic">humana, seu de</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">affectuum Viribus ;</hi> <hi rend="italic">de</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">potentia intellectus, s</hi> <hi rend="italic">eu de</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">libertate</hi> <hi rend="italic">humana.</hi> As the author professes to tread in the footſteps of the geometers, and to deduce all his conclusions by rigid demonſtration from a few ſelf-evident truths,he introduces his work, after the manner of Euclid, with a collection of <hi rend="italic">definitions</hi> and <hi rend="italic">axioms.</hi> Theſe are couched in terms generally ambiguous ; and therefore the reader will do well to conſider attentively in what ſenſe, if in any, they can be admitted ; for it will not be found easy to grant his premiſes, and at the ſame time refuſe his concluſions. His definition of ſubſtance, for inltance, is ſo expreſſed as to admit of two ſenſes ; in one of which it is juſt, whilſt in the other it is the parent of the moſt impious abſurdity. We ſhall give it in his own words ; “ Per ſubſtantiam intelligo id, quod in ſe eſt, et per ſe concipitur : hoc eſt id, cujus conceptus non indiget conceptu alterius rei, a quo formari debeat.” If by this be meant, that a ſubſtance is that which we can conceive by itſelf without <hi rend="italic">attending</hi> to any thing elſe, or <hi rend="italic">thinking</hi> of its formation, the definition, we believe, will be admitted by every reflecting mind as sufficiently diſtinguiſhing the thing defined from an attribute, which, he ſays, is that which we perceive <hi rend="italic">of</hi> a ſubſtance, and which we certainly cannot conceive as exiſting by itſelf. Thus the writer of this article can ſhut his eyes and contemplate in idea the ſmall 4to volume now be<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0702.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0696"/>
fore him, without attending to any thing elſe, or thinking of its paradoxical author, or even of the Great Being who created the matter both of him and of it ; but he cannot for an instant contemplate the yellow colour of its vellum boards without thinking of triple extenſion, or, in other words, of body. The book therefore is a <hi rend="italic">ſubstance,</hi> becauſe conceivable by itſelf ; the colour is an <hi rend="italic">attribute</hi> or <hi rend="italic">quality,</hi> becauſe it cannot be conceived by itſelf, but neceſſarily leads to the conception of ſomething elſe. But if Spinoza’s meaning be, that nothing is a ſubſtance but what is conceived as exiſting from eternity, independent of every thing as a cauſe, his definition cannot be admitted : for every man conceives that which in himſelf thinks, and wills, and is conscious, as a ſubſtance ; at the same time that he has the beſt evidence poſſible that he exiſted not as a conſcious, thinking, and active being, from eternity.</p><p>His fourth axiom is thus expreſſed : “ Effectus cognitio a cognitione causæ dependet, et eandem involvit;” and his fifth, "Quæ nihil commune cum se invicem habent, etiam per se invicem intelligi non poſſunt, live conceptus unius alterius conceptum non involvit.” The former of theſe propoſitions, ſo far from being ſelf-evident, is not even true ; and the latter is capable of two ſenſes very different from each other. That every effect proceeds from <hi rend="italic">a cauſe,</hi> is indeed an axiom ; but finely we may know the effect accurately, though we be ignorant of the <hi rend="italic">particular</hi> cauſe from which it proceeds (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Philosophy,</hi> n⁰ 36 ; and <hi rend="smallcaps">Physics,</hi> n⁰ 91, &amp;C.) ; nor does the knowledge of the one by any means involve the knowledge of the other. If different things have nothing in common, it is indeed true that the knowledge of one of them will not give us an <hi rend="italic">adequate conception</hi> of the other ; but it will in many cases compel us to believe, that the other <hi rend="italic">exists</hi> or has exiſted. A parcel of gunpowder lying at rest has nothing in common with the velocity of a cannon-ball ; yet when we know that a ball has been driven with velocity from a cannon, we infer with certainty that there has been a parcel of powder at rest in the chamber of that cannon.</p><p>It is upon ſuch ambiguous definitions and axioms as theſe that Spinoza has raiſed his pretended demonstrations, that one ſubſtance cannot produce another ; that every ſubſtance muſt neceſſarily be infinite ; that no ſubſtance exiſts or can be conceived beſides God ; and that extended ſubſtance or body is one of the infinite <hi rend="italic">attributes</hi> of God. We ſhall not waste our own time or the reader’s with a formal confutation of theſe impious abſurdities. We truſt they are sufficiently confuted in other articles of this work (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> Part III. <hi rend="smallcaps">Providence,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Theology,</hi> Part I.) ; and whoever wiſhes for a more particular examination of the author’s principles, may find it in Dr Clarke’s Demonſtration of the Being and Attributes of God. The truth, however, is, that no man will need the aſſiſtance of that eminent metaphyſician to diſcover the fallacy of the reasoning by which they are attempted to be proved, if he affix <hi rend="italic">any one preciſe meaning</hi> to the definitions and axioms, and adhere to that meaning ſteadily thro’ the whole procels of the pretended demonſtrations.</p><p>By way of apology for this jargon, it has been lately ſaid, that “ Spinoza takes the word substa <hi rend="italic">nce</hi> in its moſt ſimple and perfect ſenſe; which is necessary, as he writes mathematically, and propoſes a simple idea as the foundation oſ his theory.<note anchored="false" n="3" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Herder's Dialogues concerning God.</hi></p></note> What is the proper ſignification of a ſubſtance? Is it not that which ſtands alone, which has the cauſe of its exiſtence within itſelf ? I wiſh that this ſimple meaning of the word could be univerſally admitted in philoſophy. Strictly ſpeaking, no worldly thing is a ſubſtance ; ſince all mutually depend on each other, and finally on God, who, in this exalted ſenſe, is the only <hi rend="italic">ſubstance.</hi> The word <hi rend="italic">modification</hi> founds harſh and improper, and therefore it cannot be expected to gain a place in philoſophy ; but if the ſchool of Leibnitz may term matter the <hi rend="italic">appearance of ſubstances,</hi> why may not Spinoza be allowed a bolder term? Worldly subſtances are kept in union by divine power, as it was by divine power that they had exiſtence. They repreſent also, if you pleaſe, <hi rend="italic">modified</hi> appearances of divine power ; each according to the ſtation, the time, and the organs, in and with which it appears. The phraſe uſed by Spinoza is concise, and it gives an unity and simplicity to his whole ſyſtem, however ſtrange it may found in our ears.”</p><p>From this account of Spinoziſm, one who had never looked into the works of the author would be led to ſuppoſe that his ſyſtem is the same with that of Berkeley ; which, denying the exiſtence of material ſubſtance, attributes all our perceptions of what we call the qualities of body to the immediate agency oſ the Deity on our minds (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics,</hi> Part II. Chap. 3.) But Spinoza’s doctrine is very different. According to him, bodies are either attributes or affections of God; and as he ſays there is but one extended ſubſtance, he affirms that ſubſtance to be indivisible, and employs a long ſcholium<note anchored="true" n="4" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">* See his Prop. xv. &amp;c.</hi></p></note> * to prove that thoſe are miſtaken who ſuppoſe it finite and not <hi rend="italic">esſential to the Deity.</hi> That we do not miſrepreſent his ſentiments, the learned reader will be convinced by the two following definitions, with which he introduces that part of his ethics which treats of the nature and origin of mind. 1. “ Per corpus intelligo modum, qui Dei eſſentiam, quatenus, ut res extenſa conſideratur, certo et determinato modo exprimit.” 2. “ Ad essentiam alicujus rei id pertinere dico, quo dato res neceſſario ponitur, et quo sublato res neceſſario tollitur ; vel id, fine quo res, et vice verſa quod fine re nec eſſe nec concipi poteſt.” In conformity with theſe definitions, he attempts to prove that God<note anchored="true" n="5" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Prop. ii. vii. xi. Part 2.</hi></p></note> is an extended as well as a thinking ſubſtance ; that as a thinking ſubſtance he is the cause of the idea of a circle, and as an extended ſubſtance of the <hi rend="italic">circle</hi> itſelf ; and that the minds of men are not ſubſtances, but certain modifications of the divine attributes ; or, as he sometimes expreſses it, “ Quod humanae mentis actuale conſtituit, eſt idea rei ſingularis actu exiſtentis.” Hence, he ſays, it follows that the human mind is a part of the intellect of the infinite God ; so that when we ſpeak of the human mind perceiving this or that, we can only mean that God, not as he is infinite, but as he appears in the human mind or conſtitutes its eſſence, has this or that idea ; and when we ſpeak of God’s having this or that idea, we muſt conceive of Him not only as conſtituting the human mind, but as, together with it, having the idea of something elſe<note anchored="true" n="6" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> Hinc sequitur mentem humanam partem eſſe infiniti intellectus Dei ; ac proinde cum dicimus, mentem humanam hoc vel illud percipere, nihil aliud dicimus quam quod Deus, non quatenus infinitus est, sed quatenus per naturam humanæ mentis explicatur, five quatenus humanæ mentis essentiam conſtituſt, hanc vel illam habet ideam : et cum dicimus Deum hanc vel illam ideam habere, non tantum, quatenus naturam humanæ mentis constituit ; sed quatenus simul cum mente humana alterius rei etiam habet ideam. <hi rend="italic">Corol.</hi> prop. xi. part 2.</p></note> <hi rend="smallcaps">(a).</hi> In another place he tells us, that the human mind is nothing but the <hi rend="italic">idea</hi><pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0703.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0697"/>
which God has of the human body as actually exiſting; that this <hi rend="italic">idea</hi> of the body, and the <hi rend="italic">body</hi> itſelf, are one and the ſame thing ; and that thinking and extended ſubſtances are in reality but one and the ſame ſubſtance, which is ſometimes comprehended under one attribute of the Deity, and ſometimes under another<note anchored="true" n="7" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Prop. vii. <gap/> iii. xxi. Part 2.</p></note> *.</p><p>If this impious jargon be not Atheiſm, or as it has been ſometimes called Pantheiſm, we know not what it is (ſee <hi rend="smallcaps">Pantheism).</hi> According to Spinoza, there is but one ſubstance, which is extended, infinite, and indiviſible. That ſubstance indeed he calls God ; but he labours to prove that it is corporeal ; that there is no difference between mind and matter ; that both are attributes of the Deity variouſly considered ; that the human ſoul is a part of the intellect of God ; that the ſame ſoul is nothing but the idea of the human body ; that this idea of the body, and the body itſelf, are one and the ſame thing ; that God could not exiſt, or be conceived, were the visible univerſe annihilated ; and therefore that the viſible univerſe is either the one ſubstance, or at leaſt an eſſential attribute or modification of that ſubſtance. He ſometimes indeed ſpeaks of the <hi rend="italic">power</hi> of this ſubſtance; but when he comes to explain himſelf, we find that by power he means nothing but blind neceſſity<note anchored="true" n="8" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* Prop. xxxiii. Part <gap/></p></note> * ; and though he frequently talks of the <hi rend="italic">wiſdom</hi> of God, he ſeems to make uſe of the word without meaning. This we think evident from the long appendix to his 36th proposition ; in which he labours to prove that the notion of final cauſes is an idle figment of the imagination, since, according to him, nothing but the prejudices of education could have led men to fancy that there is any real diſtinction between <hi rend="italic">good</hi> and <hi rend="italic">evil, merit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">demerit, praiſe</hi> and <hi rend="italic">reproach, order</hi> and <hi rend="italic">confusion ;</hi> that <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> were given them that they might be enabled to <hi rend="italic">ſee ; teeth for</hi> the purpoſe of chewing their <hi rend="italic">food ; herbs</hi> and <hi rend="italic">animals</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">matter</hi> of that <hi rend="italic">food ;</hi> that the <hi rend="italic">ſun</hi> was formed to give <hi rend="italic">light,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">ocean</hi> to nouriſh fish <hi rend="italic">es.</hi> If this be true, it is impoſſible to diſcover wiſdom in the operations of his <hi rend="italic">one ſubſtance;</hi> since, in common apprehension, it is the very characteriſtic of folly to act without any end in view.</p><p>Such are the reveries of that writer, whoſe works a German philoſopher of ſome name has lately recommended to the public, as calculated to convey to the mind more just and ſublime conceptions of God than are to be found in moſt other ſyſtems. The recommendation has had its effect. A literary journaliſt of our own, reviewing the volume in which it is given, feels a peculiar ſatisfaction from the diſcovery that Spinoza, inſtead of a formidable enemy to the cauſe of virtue and religion, was indeed their warmeſt friend ; and piouſly hopes that we ſhall become more cautious not to ſuffer ourſelves to be deceived by empty names, which thoſe who <hi rend="italic">cannot</hi> reaſon ( Sir Iſaac Newton and Dr Clarke perhaps) give to thoſe who can (Hobbes, we ſuppoſe, and Spinoza). But though we have the honour to think on this queſtion with our illuſtrious countrymen, we have no desire to depict Spinoza as a <hi rend="italic">reprobate,</hi> which the critic ſays has often been done by ignorance and enthuſiaſm. We admit that his conduct in active life was irreproachable ; and for his ſpeculative opinions, he muſt ſtand or fall to his own Master. His <hi rend="italic">Ethics</hi> appear to us indeed a ſyſtem ſhockingly impious ; and in the tract intitled <hi rend="smallcaps">Politica,</hi> <hi rend="italic">power</hi> and <hi rend="italic">right</hi> are confounded as in the former volume ; but in the treatiſe <hi rend="smallcaps">De Intellectus Emendatione,</hi> are ſcattered many precepts of practical wiſdom, as well as ſome judicious rules for conducting philoſophical inveſtigation ; and we only regret, that the reader muſt wade to them through pages of fataliſm, ſcepticiſm, and palpable contradictions. His <hi rend="italic">Compendium Grammatices Linguae Hebraeae,</hi> though left imperfect, appears to have ſo much merit, that it is to be wiſhed he had fulfilled his intention of writing a philoſophical grammar of that language, inſtead of waſting his time on abſtruſe ſpeculations, which, though they ſeem not to have been injurious to his own virtue, are certainly not calculated to promote the virtue of others, or to increaſe the ſum of human happineſs.</p></div></body></text></TEI>