<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0703.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0697-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPIRÆA</label>,
in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the claſs of <hi rend="italic">icoſandria,</hi> and to the order of <hi rend="italic">pentagynia ;</hi> and in the natural ſyſtem arranged under the 26th order, <hi rend="italic">Pomacea.</hi> The calyx is quinquesid ; there are five petals; and the capſule is polyſpermous. There are 18 ſpecies ; of which two only are Britiſh, the fili- pendula and ulmaria. 1. The fi <hi rend="italic">lipendula,</hi> dropwort, has pinnated leaves ; the leaflets are ſerrated ; the ſtalk is herbaceous, about a foot and a half high, terminated with a looſe umbel of white flowers, often tinged with red. The petals are generally six, and the ſegments of the calyx are reflexed : the ſtamina are 30 or more ; the germina 12 or upwards. It grows in mountainous paſtures. 2. The <hi rend="italic">ulmaria,</hi> meadow-ſweet. The leaves have only two or three pair of pinnæ, with a few ſmaller ones intermixed ; the extreme one being larger than the rest, and divided into three lobes. The calyx is reddiſh ; the petals white, and the number of capſules from six to ten twiſted <hi rend="italic">in a</hi> ſpiral. The tuberous pea, like roots of the filipendula dried and reduced to powder, have been uſed inſtead of bread in times of ſcarcity. Hogs are very fond of theſe roots. Cows, goats, ſheep, and ſwine, eat the plant ; but horſes refuſe it. The flowers of the ulmaria have a fragrant ſcent, which riſes in diſtillation. The whole plant indeed is extremely fragrant, ſo that the common people of Sweden ſtrew their floors with it on holidays. It has alſo an aſtringent quality, and has been found uſeful in dyſenteries, ruptures, and in tanning of leather.</p></div></body></text></TEI>