<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0723.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0717-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SQUARE</label>,
in geometry, a quadrilateral figure both equilateral and equiangular. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Geometry.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SQUA</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> re-</hi> <hi rend="italic">Root.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Algebra,</hi> Part I. Chap. iv. and <hi rend="smallcaps">Arithmetic,</hi> n⁰ 33. and 34.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Hollow SQUARE,</hi> in the military art, a body of foot drawn up with an empty ſpace in the middle, for the colours, drums, and baggage, faced and covered by the pikes every way, to keep off the horſe.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Square,</hi> among mechanics, an inſtrument conſiſting of two rules or branches, faſtened perpendicularly at one end of their extremities, so as to form a right angle. It is of great use in the description and menſuration of right angles, and laying down perpendiculars.</p><p><hi rend="italic">SQUA</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> re-</hi> <hi rend="italic">Rigged,</hi> an epithet applied to a ſhip whoſe yards are very long. It is alſo uſed in contradiſtinction to all veſſels whoſe sails are extended by ſtays or lateen-yards, or by booms and gaffs ; the usual situation of which is nearly in the plane of the keel ; and hence,</p><p><hi rend="italic">SQUARE-Sail,</hi> is a ſail extended to a yard which hangs parallel to the horizon, as diſtinguished from the other sails which are extended by booms and ſtays placed obliquely. This ſail is only uſed in fair winds, or to ſcud under in a tempeſt. In the former caſe, it is furniſhed with a large additional part called the <hi rend="italic">bonnet,</hi> which is then attached to its bottom, and removed when it is neceſſary to <hi rend="smallcaps">scud.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Scudding.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>