<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0698.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0692-14" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPINET</label>,
or <hi rend="smallcaps">Spinnet,</hi> a musical inſtrument ranked in the second or third place among harmonious inſtruments. It consists of a cheſt or belly made of the moſt porous and reſinous wood to be found, and a table of fir glued on flips of wood <hi rend="italic">called ſummers,</hi> which bear on the sides. On the table is raised two little prominences or bridges, wherein are placed ſo many pins as there are chords or ſtrings to the inſtrument. It is played on by two ranges of continued keys, the former range being the order of the diatonic ſcale, and that behind the order of the artificial notes or ſemitones. The keys are ſo many flat pieces of wood, which, touched and presſed down at the end, make the other raiſe a jack which ſtrike and ſound the ſtrings by means of the end of a crow’s quill, wherewith it is armed. The 30 firſt strings are of braſs, the other more delicate ones of ſteel or iron-wire ; they are all ſtretched over the two bridges already mentioned. The figure of the ſpinet is a long square or parallelogram ; ſome call it an <hi rend="italic">burp couched,</hi> and the harp an <hi rend="italic">inverted spinet.</hi> See the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Harp.</hi></p><p>This inſtrument is generally tuned by the ear, which method of the practical musicians is founded on a ſupposition that the ear is a perfect judge of an octave and a fifth. The general rule is to begin at a certain note, as C, taken towards the middle of the inſtrument, and tuning all the octaves up and down, and alſo the fifths, reckoning ſeven ſemitones to each fifth, by which means the whole is tuned. Sometimes to the common or fundamental play of the ſpinet is added another ſimilar one in uniſon, and a third in octave to the firſt, to make the harmony the fuller ; they are either played ſeparately or together by means of a ſtop : theſe are called <hi rend="italic">double</hi> or <hi rend="italic">triple spinets ;</hi> ſometimes a play of violins is added, by means of a bow, or a few wheels parallel to the keys, which press the ſtrings and make the found laſt as long as the muſician pleaſes, and heighten and ſoften them more or leſs, as they are more or leſs pressed. The harpsichord is a kind of spinet, only with another diſposition of the keys (see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Harpsichord).</hi> The inſtrument takes its name from the ſmall quill ends which touch the ſtrings, resembling spinae or thorns.</p></div></body></text></TEI>