<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0825.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0819-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STOW</label>
(John), the induſtrious historian, ſon of Thomas Stow merchant-taylor of St Michael’s, Cornhill, in London, was born about the year 1525. Of the early part of his life we know very little, except that he was bred to his father’s buſineſs, which in the year 1560 he relinquiſhed, devoting himſelf entirely to the study of our ancient historians, chronicles, annals, charters, registers, and records. Of theſe he made a conſiderable collection, travelling for that purpoſe to different parts of the kingdom, and tranſcribing ſuch manuſcrips as he could not purchaſe. But this profeſſion of an antiquary being attended with no preſent emolument, he was obliged for ſubſistence to return to his trade.— It happened, however, that his talents and neceſſities were made known to Dr Parker archbishop of Canterbury ; who being himſelf an antiquary, encouraged and enabled Mr Stow to proſecute his darling ſtudy. In thoſe times of perſecution, though Elizabeth was then upon the throne, honest John Stow did not eſcape danger. His collection of Popiſh records was deemed cauſe of ſuſpicion. His younger brother Thomas preferred no leſs than 140 articles againſt him before the ecclesiaſtical commiſſion ; but the proof being inſufficient, he was acquitted. In 1565 he firſt. publiſhed his Summary oſ the Chronicles of England. About the year 1584 he began his Survey of London. In 1585 he was one of the two collectors for a great muſter of Limeſtreet ward : in the ſame year he petitioned the corporation of London to beſtow on him the benefit of two freemen, to enable him to publiſh his survey ; and in 1589 he petitioned again for a penſion. Whether he ſucceeded, is not known. He was principally concerned in the ſecond edition of Holinſhed’s chronicle, publiſhed in 1587. He alſo corrected, and twice augmented, Chaucer’s works, publiſhed in 1561 and in 1597. His ſurvey of London was firſt publiſhed in 1598. To theſe laborious works he would have added his large Chronicle, or History of England ; but he lived only to publiſh an abſtract of it, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Flores Historiarum.</hi> The folio volume, which was printed after his death, with the title of <hi rend="italic">Stow's Chronicle,</hi> was taken from his papers by Edmund Howes. Having thus ſpent his life and fortune in theſe laborious purſuits, he was at laſt obliged to ſolicit the charitable and well diſpoſed for relief. For this purpoſe, king James I. granted him, in 1603, a brief, which was renewed in 1604, authorising him to collect in churches the benefactions of his fellow-citizens. He died in April 1605, aged 80 ; and was buried in his pariſh-church of St Andrew's, Underſhaft, where his widow erected a decent monument to his memory. John Stow was a moſt indefatigable antiquarian, a faithful historian, and an honeſt man.</p></div></body></text></TEI>