<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0690.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0684-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPECULUM</label>
for reflecting teleſcopes, is made of a kind of white copper conſiſting of 32 parts fine<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0691.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0685"/>
red copper, I of braſs, 15 of grain-tin, and 3 of white arſenic. The proceſs given by the late J. Edwards, who was rewarded by the Board oſ Longitude for diſcloſing it to the public, was publiſhed in the Nautical Almanack for 1787, and is as follows ; Melt the copper in a large crucible, employing ſome black flux, compoſed of two parts of tartar and one of nitre ; when melted, add to it the braſs and the ſilver. Let the pure tin be melted in another crucible, alſo with ſome black flux. Take them both from the fire, and pour the melted tin into the fuſed maſs in the large crucible. Stir the whole well with a dry ſpatula of birch, and pour off the fuſed metal immediately into a large quantity of cold water. The ſudden chill of the water will cauſe the fluid metal to divide into an infinite number of ſmall particles, which will cool inſtantly.</p><p>2. If the copper be completely ſaturated, the fracture of one piece of this mixed metal will appear bright, and of a gloſſy look, reſembling the face of pure quick- filver. But if it is of a brown reddiſh colour, it wants a little more tin. To aſcertain the required proportion, melt a ſmall quantity, known by weight, of the mixed metal, with a known very ſmall part of tin ; and, if neceſſary, repeat the trial with different dozes, till the fracture of the new mixture looks as already deſcribed. Having now aſcertained the neceſſary addition of tin that is required, proceed to the laſt melting of the whole metal, together with the additional proportional doſe of tin ; fuſe the whole, obſerving the ſame cautions as before ; and you will find that the mixture will melt with a much less heat than that for the first fuſion. Have ready as many ounces of white arſenic in coarſe powder as there are pounds in the weight of the metal ; wrap up the arſenic in a ſmall paper, and put it, with a pair of tongs, into the crucible ; ſtir it well with the ſpatula, retaining the breath to avoid the arſenical fumes or vapours (which however are not found to be hurtful to the lungs) till they diſappear ; take the crucible off the fire, clear away the droſs from the top of the metal, pour in about one ounce of powdered rosin, with as much nitre, in order to give the metal a clean ſurface, and pour out the metal into the moulded flaſks.</p><p>3. The ſpeculum ſhould be moulded with the concave ſurſace downwards, and many ſmall holes ſhould be made through the fand upwards, to diſcharge the air. The moulding fand from Highgate near London, uſed by the founders, is as good as any for casting theſe metallic mirrors. The cast metal ſhould be taken out from the sand of the flaſks whilſt it is hot, or else it may happen to crack if left to cool within. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Telescope.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Speculum,</hi> a looking glaſs or mirror, capable of reflecting the rays of the fun.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Speculum,</hi> in ſurgery, an infiniment for dilating a wound, or the like, in order to examine it attentively. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Surgery.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>