<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0738.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0732-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STATUE</label>,
is defined to be a piece of ſculpture in full relievo, repreſenting a human figure. Daviler more ſcientifcally defines ſtatue a repreſentation, in high relievo and insulate, of ſome perion diſtinguiſhed by his birth, merit, or great actions, placed as an ornament in a fine building, or expoſed in a public place, to preſerve the memory of his worth. In Greece one of the highest honours to which a citizen could aſpire was to obtain a ſtatue.</p><p>Statues are formed with the chiſel, of ſeveral matters, as ſtone, marble, plaſter, &amp;c. They are alſo cast of various kinds of metal, particularly gold, silver, brass, and lead. For the method of calling ſtatues, ſee the article <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> FounderY</hi> <hi rend="italic">of Statues.</hi></p><p>Statues are uſually diſtinguiſhed into four general kinds. The firſt are thoſe leſs than the life ; of which kind we have ſeveral ſtatues of great men, of kings, and of gods themſelves. The second arc thoſe equal to the life ; in which manner it was that the ancients, at the public expence, uſed to make ſtatues of perſons eminent for virtue, learning, or the ſervices they had done. The third are thoſe that exceed the life ; among which thoſe that ſurpaſſed the life once and a half were for kings and emperors ; and thoſe double the life, ſor heroes. The fourth kind were thoſe that exceeded the life twice, thrice, and even more, and were called <hi rend="italic">colossuses.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Colossus.</hi></p><p>Every ſtatue reſembling the perſon whom it is intended to repreſent, is called <hi rend="italic">ſtatua iconica.</hi> Statues acquire various other denominations. 1. Thus, allegorical ſtatue is that which, under a human figure, or other ſymbol,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0739.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0733"/>
repreſents ſomething of another kind ; as a part of the earth, a ſeaſon, age, element, temperament, hour, &amp;c. 2. Curule ſtatues, are thoſe which are repreſented in chariots drawn by bigæ or quadrigæ, that is, by two or four horſes ; of which kind there were ſeveral in the circules, hippodromes, &amp;c. or in cars, as we see ſome, with triumphal arches on antique medals. 3. Equeſtrian ſtatue, that which repreſents ſome illustrious perſon on horſeback, as that famous one of Marcus Aurelius at Rome ; that of king Charles I. at Charing-croſs ; King George II in Leicester-Square, &amp;c. 4. Greek statue, denotes a figure that is naked and antique ; it being in this manner the Greeks repreſented their deities, athletæ of the Olympic games, and heroes ; the statues of heroes were particularly called <hi rend="italic">Achillean statues,</hi> by reaſon of the great number of figures of Achilles in moſt of the cities of Greece. 5. Hydraulic statue, is any figure placed as an ornament of a fountain or grotto, or that does the office of a <hi rend="italic">jet d’eau,</hi> a cock, ſpout, or the like, by any of its parts, or by any attribute it holds : the like is to be underſtood of any animal ſerving for the ſame uſe. 6. Pedeſtrian ſtatue, a ſtatue standing on foot; as that of king Charles IL in the Royal Exchange, and of king James II. in the Privy- Gardens. 7. Roman ſtatue, is an appellation given to such as are clothed, and which receive various names from their various dreſſes. Thoſe of emperors, with long gowns over their armour, were called st <hi rend="italic">atuae paludata :</hi> thoſe of captains and cavaliers, with coats of arms, <hi rend="italic">thoracata ;</hi> thoſe of ſoldiers with cuirasses, <hi rend="italic">loricata ;</hi> thoſe of ſenators and augurs, <hi rend="italic">trabeata;</hi> thoſe of magiſtrates with long robes, <hi rend="italic">togata ;</hi> thoſe of the people with a plain tunica, <hi rend="italic">tumcatae ;</hi> and, laſtly, thoſe of women with long trains, st <hi rend="italic">olutae.</hi></p><p>In repairing a ſtatue caſt in a mould, they touch it up with a chiſel, graver, or other infiniment, to finiſh the places which have not come well off : they alſo clear off the barb, and what is redundant in the joints and projectures.</p></div></body></text></TEI>