<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0809.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0803-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STIRRUP</label>,
in the manege, a reſt or ſupport for the horſeman’s foot, for enabling him to mount and for keeping him firm in his ſeat.</p><p>Stirrups were unknown to the ancients. The want of them in getting upon horſeback was ſupplied by agility or art. Some horſes were taught to ſtoop to take their riders up; but the riders often leapt up by the help of their spears, or were aſſiſted by their ſlaves, or made uſe of ladders for the purpoſe. Gracchus filled the highways with ſtones, which were intended to anſwer the ſame end. The ſame was alſo required of the ſurveyors of the roads in Greece as part of their duty.</p><p>Menage obſerves, that St Jerome is the firſt author who mentions them. But the passage alluded to is not to be found in his epiſtles ; and if it were there, it would prove nothing, becauſe St Jerome lived at a time when ſtirrups are ſuppoſed to have been invented, and after the uſe of ſaddles. Montfaucon denies the authenticity of this passage ; and, in order to account for the ignorance of the ancients with regard to an inſtrument ſo uſeful and ſo eaſy of invention,<note anchored="true" n="1" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> So called from the wailings and lamentations (in Scotch <hi rend="italic">gowlings)</hi> that were made for Duke Murdoch.</p></note> he obſerves, that while cloths and houſings only were laid upon the horſes backs, on which the riders were to sit, ſtirrups could not have been uſed, becauſe they could not have been faſtened with the ſame ſecurity as upon a ſaddle. But it is more probable, that in this inſtance, as in many others, the progreſs of human genius and invention is uncertain and flow, depending frequently upon accidental cauſes.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Stirrup</hi> <hi rend="italic">of a Ship,</hi> a piece of timber put upon a ſhip’s keel, when ſome of her keel happens to be beaten off, and they cannot come conveniently to put or fit in a new piece ; then they patch in a piece of timber, and bind it on with an iron, which goes under the ſhip’s keel, and comes up on each side of the ſhip, where it is nailed ſtrongly with ſpikes ; and this they call a ſtirrup.</p></div></body></text></TEI>