<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0716.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0710-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPRING</label>,
in natural hiſtory, a fountain or ſource of water riſing out of the ground.</p><p>Many have been the conjectures of philoſophers concerning the origin of fountains, and great pains have been taken both by the members of the Royal Society and thoſe of the Academy of Sciences at Paris, in order to aſcertain the true cauſe of it. It was Ariſtotle’s opinion, and held by moſt of the ancient philoſophers after him, that the air contained in the caverns of the earth, being condenſed by cold near its ſurface, was thereby changed into water ; and that it made its way through, where it could find a paſſage. But we have no experience of any ſuch tranſmutation of air into water.</p><p>Thoſe who imagine that fountains owe their origin to waters brought from the ſea by ſubterraneous ducts, give a tolerable account how they loſe their ſaltneſs by percolation as they paſs through the earth : but they find great difficulty in explaining by what power the water riles above the level of the ſea to near the tops of mountains, where ſprings generally abound ; it being contrary to the laws of hydroſtatics, that a fluid ſhould riſe in a tube above the level of its ſource. However, they have found two ways whereby they endeavour to extricate themſelves from this difficulty. The one is that of Des Cartes, who imagines, that after the water is become freſh by percolation, it is raiſed out of the caverns of the earth in vapour towards its ſurface ; where meeting with rocks near the tops of mountains in the form of arches or vaults, it ſticks to them, and runs down their sides, (like water in an alembic), till it meets with proper receptacles, from which it ſupplies the fountains. Now this is a mere hypothesis, without foundation or probability : for, in the first place, we know of no internal heat of the earth to cauſe ſuch evaporation ; or if that were allowed, yet it is quite incredible that there ſhould be any caverns ſo ſmooth and void of protuberances as to anſwer the ends of an alembic, in collecting and condenſing the vapours together in every place where fountains ariſe. There are others (as Varenius, &amp;c. ) who ſuppoſe that the water may riſe through the pores of the earth, as through capillary tubes by attraction. But hereby they ſhow, that they are quite unacquainted with what relates to the motion of a fluid through ſuch tubes ; for when a capillary tube opens into a cavity at its upper end, or grows iarger and larger, ſo as to ceaſe to be capillary at that end, the water will not ascend through that tube into the cavity, or beyond where the tube is capillary ; becauſe that part of the periphery of the cavity, which is partly above the ſurface of the water and partly below it, is not of the capillary kind. Nay, if the cavity is continually ſupplied with water, it will be attracted into the capillary tube, and run down it as through a funnel, if the lower end is immerged in the ſame fluid,· as in this cafe it is ſuppoſed to be.</p><p>It has been a generally received opinion, and much eſpouſed by Mariotte (a diligent obſerver of nature), that the riſe of ſprings is owing to the rains and melted ſnow. According to him, the rain-water which falls upon the hills and mountains, penetrating the ſurface, meets with clay or rocks contiguous to each other ; along which it runs, without being able to penetrate them, till, being got to the bottom of the mountain, or to a conſiderable diſtance from the top, it breaks out of the ground, and forms ſprings.</p><p>In order to examine this opinion, Mr Perrault, De la Hire, and D. Sideleau, endeavoured to make an<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0717.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0711"/>
eſtimate of the quantity of rain and ſnow that falls in the space of a year, to ſee whether it would be ſufficient to afford a quantity of water equal to that which is annually diſcharged into the ſea by the rivers. The result of their inquiries was, that the quantity of rain and ſnow which fell in a year into a cylindrical veſſel would fill it (if ſecured from evaporating) to the height of about nineteen inches. Which quantity D. Sideleau showed, was not sufficient to ſupply the rivers ; for that those of England, Ireland, and Spain, diſcharge a greater quantity of water annually, than the rain, according to that experiment, is able to ſupply. Beſides which, another obſervation was made by them at the same time, viz. that the quantity of water raiſed in vapour, one year with another, amounted to about thirty- two inches, which is thirteen more than falls in rain : a plain indication that the water of fountains is not ſupplied by rain and melted ſnow.</p><p>Thus the true cauſe of the origin of fountains remained undiſcovered, till Dr Halley, in making his celeſtial obſervations upon the tops of the mountains at St Helena, about 800 yards above the level of the ſea, found, that the quantity of vapour which fell there (even when the sky was clear) was ſo great, that it very much impeded his obſervations, by covering his glaſſes with water every half quarter of an hour ; and upon that he attempted to determine by experiment the quantity of vapour exhaled from the ſurface of the ſea, as far as it riſes from heat, in order to try whether that might be a sufficient ſupply for the water continually diſcharged by fountains. The proceſs of his experiment was as follows : He took a vessel of water ſalted to the ſame degree with that of ſea water, in which he placed a thermometer ; and by means of a pan of coals brought the water to the ſame degree of heat, which is obſerved to be that of the air in our hottest ſummer ; this done, he fixed the veſſel of water with the thermometer in it to one end of a pair of ſcales, and exactly counterpoiſed it with weights on the other : then, at the end of two hours, he found, by the alteration made in the weight of the veſſel, that about a ſixtieth part of an inch of the depth of the water was gone off in vapour ; and therefore, in twelve hours, one-tenth of an inch would have gone off. Now this accurate obſerver allows the Mediterranean Sea to be forty degrees long, and four broad, (the broader parts compenſating for the narrower, ſo that its whole ſurface is 160 ſquare degrees) ; which, according to the experiment, muſt yield at leaſt 5,280,000,000 tons of water : In which account no regard is had to the wind and the agitation of the ſurface of the ſea, both which undoubtedly promote the evaporation.</p><p>It remained now to compare this quantity of water with that which is daily conveyed into the ſame ſea by the rivers. The only way to do which was to compare them with ſome known river ; and accordingly he takes his computation from the river Thames ; and, to avoid all objections, makes allowances, probably greater than what were abſolutcly neceſſary.</p><p>The Mediterranean receives the following conſiderable rivers, viz. the Iberus, the Rhone, the Tyber, the Po, the Danube, the Nieſter, the Borysthenes, the Tanais, and the Nile. Each of theſe he ſuppoſes to bring down ten times as much water as the Thames, whereby he allows for ſmaller rivers which fall into the same ſea. The Thames, then, he finds by menſuration to diſcharge about 20,300,000 tons of water a-day. If therefore the above-said nine rivers yield ten times as much water as the Thames doth, it will follow, that all of them together yield but 1827 millions of tons in a day, which is but little more than one-third of what is proved to be raiſed in vapour out of the Mediterranean in the ſame time. We have therefore from hence a ſource abundantly sufficient for the ſupply of fountains.</p><p>Now having found that the vapour exhaled from the ſea is a sufficient ſupply for the fountains, he proceeds in the next place to conſider the manner in which they are raiſed ; and how they are condenſed into water again, and conveyed to the ſources of ſprings.</p><p>In order to this he considers, that if an atom of water was expanded into a ſhell or bubble, ſo as, to be ten times as big in diameter as when it was water, that atom would become specifically lighter than air ; and therefore would riſe ſo long as the warmth which firſt ſeparated it from the ſurface of the water ſhould continue to diſtend it to the ſame degree ; and conſequently, that vapours may be raiſed from the ſurface of the ſea in that manner, till they arrive at a certain height in the atmoſphere, at which they find air of equal specific gravity with themſelves. Here they will float till, being condenſed by cold, they become specifically heavier than the air, and fall down in dew ; or being driven by the winds againſt the ſides of mountains (many of which far ſurpaſs the uſual height to which the vapours would of themſelves aſcend), are compelled by the ſtream of the air to mount up with it to the tops of them; where being condenſed into water, they preſently precipitate, and gleeting down by the crannies of the ſtones, part of them enters into the caverns of the hills ; which being once filled, all the overplus of water that comes thither runs over by the loweſt place, and breaking out by the ſides of the hills forms single ſprings. Many of theſe running down by the valleys between the ridges of the hills, and coming to unite, form little rivulets or brooks : many of theſe again meeting in one common valley, and gaining the plain ground, being grown leſs rapid, become a river ; and many of theſe being united in one common channel, make ſuch ſtreams as the Rhine and the Danube ; which latter, he obſerves, one would hardly think to be a collection of water condenſed out of vapour, unless we conſider how vaſt a tract of ground that river drains, and that it is the sum of all thoſe ſprings which break out on the ſouth side of the Carpathian mountains, and on the north side of the immenſe ridge of the Alps, which is one continued chain of mountains from Switzerland to the Black Sea.</p><p>Thus one part of the vapours which are blown on the land is returned by the rivers into the ſea from whence it came. Another part falls into the ſea before it reaches the land ; and this is the reaſon why the rivers do not return ſo much water into the Mediterranean as is raiſed in vapour. A third part falls on the low lands, where it affords nouriſhment to plants ; yet it does not rest there, but is again exhaled in vapour by the action of the ſun, and is either carried by the winds to the ſea to fall in rain or dew there, or else to the mountains to become the ſources of ſprings.</p><p>However, it is not to be ſuppoſed that all fountains are owing to one and the ſame cauſe ; but that ſome proceed from rain and melted ſnow, which, ſubſiding<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0718.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0712"/>
through the ſurface of the earth, makes its way into certain cavities, and thence issues out in the form of ſprings ; becauſe the waters of ſeveral are found to increaſe and diminiſh in proportion to the rain which falls : that others again, eſpecially ſuch as are ſalt, and ſpring near the ſea-ſhore, owe their origin to sea-water percolated through the earth ; and ſome to both theſe cauſes: though without doubt most of them, and especially ſuch as ſpring near the tops of high mountains, receive their waters from vapours, as before explained.</p><p>This reaſoning of Dr Halley’s is confirmed by more recent obſervations and diſcoveries. It is now found, that though water is a tolerable conductor of the electric fluid, dry earth is an electric <hi rend="italic">per ſe,</hi> conſequently the dry land muſt always be in an electrified ſtate compared with the ocean, unleſs in ſuch particuler caſes as are mentioned under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Earthquake,</hi> n⁰ 82. It is also well known, that ſuch bodies as are in an electrified ſtate, whether plus or <hi rend="italic">minus,</hi> will attract vapour, or other light ſubſtances that came near them. Hence the vapours that are raised from the ocean muſt neceſſarily have a tendency to approach the land in great quantity, even without the aſſiſtance of the wind, though this laſt muſt undoubtedly contribute greatly towards the ſame purpoſe, as Dr Halley juſtly obſerves. In like manner, the higher grounds are always in a more electrified ſtate than the lower ones : and hence the vapours having once left the ocean and approached the ſhore,are attracted by the high mountains , of which Mr Pennant gives an inſtance in Snowdon. Hence we may ſee the reaſon why ſprings are ſo common in the neighbourhood of mountains, they being ſo advantageouſly formed in every reſpect for collecting and condensing the vapours into water.</p><p>The heat of ſprings is generally the ſame with the mean temperature of the atmoſphere. The mean temperature of the ſouth of England is 48⁰ ; in Scotland, near Edinburgh, it is 45⁰ ; in the north of Ireland it is 48⁰, and on the ſouth coaſt about 51⁰. At Upſal, in Sweden, it is 43⁰, and in Paris 53⁰. According to accurate experiments made by eminent philoſophers, the heat of the ſprings in theſe different countries correſponds with the medium temperature. We have not heard that ſimilar experiments have been made in other countries, or we ſhould have been careful to collect them. We do not, however, doubt but they have been made in moſt countries of Europe ; yet we ſuſpect little attention has been paid to this ſubject within the tropical regions.</p><p>Though this coincidence of the heat of ſprings with the mean temperature of the climate where they flow, ſeems to be a general fact, yet it admits of many exceptions. In many parts of the world there are ſprings which not only exceed the mean temperature, but even the ſtrongeſt meridian heat ever known in the torrid regions. The following table will give a diſtinct notion of the degrees of heat which different ſprings have been found to poſſeſs, according to the experiments of philoſophers. It is necessary to remark, that experiments made upon the ſame ſprings, made by different perſons, vary a little from one another, which may be owing to many accidents eaſily accounted for. Where this is the caſe, we ſhall mention both the loweſt and higheſt degree of heat which has been aſcribed to the ſame ſpring, according to Fahrenheit's thermometer.</p><table> <row> <cell>Places.</cell> <cell>Springs.</cell> <cell>Higheſt degree of heat.</cell> <cell>Loweſt degree of heat.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Briſtol,</cell> <cell>St Vincent’s or the hot well,</cell> <cell>84</cell> <cell>76</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Buxton,</cell> <cell>Gentleman’s bath,</cell> <cell>82</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>Matlock,</cell> <cell/> <cell>69</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>Bath,</cell> <cell>King’s bath,</cell> <cell>119</cell> <cell>113</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Aix-la-Chapelle,</cell> <cell/> <cell>I 46</cell> <cell>136</cell> </row> <row> <cell>Barege,</cell> <cell/> <cell>I 22</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>Piſa,</cell> <cell/> <cell>104</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>Caroline baths in Bohemia,</cell> <cell>Prudel or furious,</cell> <cell>165</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell>Iceland,</cell> <cell>Geyzer,</cell> <cell>212</cell> <cell/> </row> </table><p>In cold countries, where congelation takes place, the heat of the earth is conſiderably above the freezing point, and continues ſo through the whole year. From experiments that have been made in mines and deep pits, it appears that this heat is uniform and ſtationary at a certain depth. But as the heat of theſe ſprings far exceeds the common heat of the internal parts of the earth, it muſt be occasioned by cauſes peculiar to certain places ; but what theſe cauſes are it is no eaſy matter to determine. We are certain, indeed, that hot ſprings receive their heat from ſome ſubterranean cauſe; but it is a matter of difficulty to inveſtigate how this heat is produced and preſerved. Theories, however, have been formed on this subject. the ſubterranean heat has been aſcribed to the electrical fluid, and to a great body of fire in the centre of the earth : But we ſuſpect that the nature of the electrical fluid and its effects are not ſufficiently understood. As to the ſuppoſition that the heat of ſprings is owing to a central fire, it is too hypothetical to require any refutation. From what then does this heat originate, and whence is the fuel which has produced it for so many ages ? To enable us to anſwer theſe queſtions with precision, more information is necessary than we have hitherto obtained reſpecting the ſtructure of the internal parts of the earth. It is peculiarly requiſite that we ſhould be made acquainted with the foſſils which are moſt common in those places where hot ſprings abound. We ſhould then perhaps diſcover that hot ſprings always paſs thro' bodies of a combuſtible nature. It is well known to chemiſts, that when water is mixed with the vitriolic acid, a degree of heat is produced ſuperior to that of boiling water. It is also an eſtabliſhed fact, that when water meets with pyrites, that is, a mixture of ſulphur and iron, a violent inflammation takes place. If, therefore, we could prove that theſe materials exiſt in the ſtrata from which hot ſprings are derived, we ſhould be enabled to give a satisfactory account of this curious phenomenon. As ſome apology for this ſuppoſition, we may add, that moſt of the hot ſprings mentioned above have been found by analyſis to be impregnated with ſulphur, and ſome of them with iron. It muſt, however, be acknowledged, that the hot ſprings of Iceland, which are 112⁰, the heat of boiling water, according to an accurate analyſis of their contents by the ingenious Dr Black, were neither found to contain iron nor ſulphur. It will therefore, perhaps, be necessary that we ſhould wait with patience, and continue to collect facts, till the ſciences of chemiſtry and mineralogy ſhall be ſo far advanced as to enable us to form a permanent theory on this ſubject.</p><p>Springs are of different kinds. Seme are perennial,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0719.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0713"/>
or continue to flow during the whole year ; others flow only during the rainy ſeaſon ; ſome ebb and flow. At Torbay there is one of this kind, which ebbs and flows five or six inches every hour. There is another near Coriſo in Italy, which ebbed and flowed three times a- day in the time of Pliny, and continues to do ſtill. A ſpring near Henly ſometimes flows for two years together, and then dries up for an equal period. The cauſe of this is explained under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Hydrostatics,</hi> n⁰ 26. For the ingredients found in ſprings, see <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Mineral</hi> <hi rend="italic">Waters, and</hi> W <hi rend="smallcaps">ater.</hi></p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Spring,</hi> in mechanics, denotes a thin piece of tempered ſteel, or other elaſtic ſubſtance, which being wound up ſerves to put machines in motion by its elasticity, or endeavours to unbend itſelf ; ſuch is the ſpring of a watch, clock, or the like.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Spring, Ver,</hi> in coſmography, denotes one of the seaſons of the year ; commencing, in the northern parts of the world, on the day the ſun enters the firſt degree of Aries, which is about the 10th day of March, and ending when the ſun leaves Gemini ; or, more ſtrictly and generally, the ſpring begins on the day when the diſtance of the ſun’s meridian altitude from the zenith, being on the increaſe,is at a medium between the greateſt and leaſt. The end of the ſpring coincides with the beginning of ſummer. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Summer.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">SPRING-Tide.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy-Index,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Tide.</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Burning</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Springs.</hi> See <hi rend="italic">BURNING-Springs.</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Springer,</hi> or SPRI <hi rend="italic">NG-Bok,</hi> in zoology. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Capra.</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>