<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0735.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0729-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STATICE <hi rend="smallcaps">Thrift,</hi></label>
 in botany : A genus of plants belonging to the class of <hi rend="italic">pentandria,</hi> and order of p <hi rend="italic">entagynia;</hi> and in the natural ſystem ranging under the 48th order, <hi rend="italic">aggregates.</hi> The calyx is monophyllons, entire, folded, and ſcarioſe. There are five petals, with one ſuperior ſeed. There are 22 ſpecies, the armeria, pſeudarmeria, limonium, incana, cordata, reticulata, echioides, ſpecioſa, tatarica, echinus, flexuoſa, purpurata, minuta, ſuffruticoſa, monopetala, aurea, ferulacea, linifolia, pruinoſa, sinuata, mucronata, and lobata. Three of theſe are Britiſh plants.</p><p>I. The <hi rend="italic">armeria,</hi> thrift, or sea gilly-flower, has a simple<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0736.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0730"/>
naked stem about six inches high. The radical leaves are like graſs. The flowers are terminal, pale red, with a round head, and not very large. This plant flowers in July or Auguſt, and grows in meadows near the ſea.</p><p>2. <hi rend="italic">Limonium,</hi> ſea lavender. The ſtem is naked, branched, and about a foot high. The radical leaves are long, pointed, and grow on footſtalks. The flowers are blue, and grow on long ſpikes on the tops of the branches. It grows on the ſea-coast in South Britain.</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">Reticulata,</hi> matted ſea-lavender. The ſtem is prostrate, and terminated by a panicle of flowers. The branches are naked, barren, and bent back. The leaves are wedge ſhaped. This ſpecies is alſo found on the ſea-coaſt of South Britain.</p></div></body></text></TEI>