<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0830.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0824-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STRATA</label>,
in natural hiſtory, the ſeveral beds or layers of different matters whereof the earth is complied. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Quarry.</hi></p><p>The ſtrata whereof the earth is compoſed are ſo very different in different countries, that it is impoſſible to ſay any thing concerning them that may be generally applicable : and indeed the depths to which we can penetrate are ſo ſmall, that only a very few can be known</p><p>of his life, which we have laid beſore our readers, upon the expreſs condition that we ſhould not alter a <hi rend="italic">ſingle word oſ it ;</hi> as the compoſition, we were told, would do <hi rend="italic">honour to our work.</hi> We have obſerved the condition, and therefore cannot claim this honour to any of the uſual writers in the Encyclopædia Britannica. If Sir Robert’s more intimate friends ſhall be pleaſed with the article, their gratitude will be due not to us, but to ſome of his neareſt relations ; and what may appear its defects to others (for the taſtes of mankind are very different), we truſt will be ſupplied by the following authentic catalogue of his works ; Plate 1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Two</hi> Heads of the author—one an etching, the other a finiſhed proof, from a drawing by John Baptiſte Greuſe ; 2. The Return from Market, by Wouvermans ; 3. Cupid, by Vanloo ; 4. Mary Magdalen, by Guido ; 5. Cleopatra, by the ſame ; 6. The Madonna, by the ſame ; 7. The Angel Gabriel, by the ſame ; 8. The Virgin, holding in her hand a book, and attended by angels, by Carlo Maratt ; 9. The Virgin with the Child aſleep, by the ſame ; 10. Liberality and Modeſty, by Guido ; 1 1. Apollo rewarding Merit and puniſhing Arrogance, by Andrea Sacchi ; 12. The Finding of Romulus and Remus, by Pietro da Cortona; 13. Cseſar repudiating Pompeia, by the ſame; 14. Three Children of King Charles I. by Vandyke ; l5. Beliſarius, by Salvator Roſa ; 16. St Agnes, by Dominichino ; 17. The Judgment of Hercules, by Nicolas Pouſſin ; 18. Venus attired by the Graces, by Guido ; 19 and 20. Justice and Meekneſs, by Raphael ; 21. The Offspring of Love, by Guido ; 22. Cupid ſleeping, by the ſame ; 23. Abraham giving up the Handmaid Hagar, by Guercino ; 24. Eſther a Suppliant before Ahaſuerus, by the ſame ; 25. Joſeph and Potiphar’s Wife, by Guido ; 26. Venus Blinding Cupid, by Titian ; 27. Venus, by the ſame ; 28. Danae, by the ſame ; 29. Portrait of King Charles I. by Vandyke ; 30. The Madonna, by Correggio ; 31. St Caecilia, by Raphael ; 32. Mary Magdalen, by Guido ; 33. Our Saviour appearing to his Mother after his Reſurrection, by Guercino ; 34. A Mother and Child, by Parmegiano; 35. Cupid Meditating, by Schidoni ; 36. Laomedon King of Troy detected by Neptune and Apollo, by Salvator Roſa ; 37. The Death of Dido, by Guercino ; 38. Venus and Adonis, by Titian ; 30. Fortune, by Guido; 40. Cleopatra, by the ſame 541. Two Children at School, by Schidoni ; 42. Mary Magdalen, by Correggio ; 43. Portrait of King Charles I. attended by the Marquis of Hamilton, by Vandyke ; 44. Queen Henrietta, attended by the Prince of Wales, and holding in her Arms the Duke of York, by the ſame ; 45. Apotheosis of the Royal Children, by West ; 46. The Annunciation, by Guido ; 47. Portrait of Raphael Sancio D’Urbino, by himſelf ; 48. Sappho, by Carlo Dolci ; 49. Our Saviour aſleep, by Vandyke ; 50. St John in the Desert, by Murillo.<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0831.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0825"/>
to 113 at any rate ; thoſe that lie near the centre, or even a great way from it, being for ever hid. one reaſon why we cannot penetrate to any great depth is, that as we go down the air becomes foul, loaded with pernicious vapours, inflammable air, fixed air, &amp;c <hi rend="italic">.</hi> which destroy the miners, and there is no poſſibility of going on. In many places, however, theſe vapours become pernicious much ſooner than in others, particularly where sulphureous minerals abound, as in mines of metal, coal, &amp;c.</p><p>But however great differences there may be among the under ſtrata, the upper one is in ſome reſpects the ſame all over the globe, at leaſt in this reſpect, that it is fit for the ſupport of vegetables, which the others are not, without long exposure to the air. Properly ſpeakmg, indeed, the upper ſtratum of the earth all round, is compoſed of the pure vegetable mold, though in many places it is mixed with large quantities of ether ſtrata, as clay, sand, gravel, &amp;c. ; and hence proceed the differences of soils ſo well known to thoſe who practiſe agriculture.</p><p>It has been ſuppoſed, by ſome naturaliſts, that the different ſtrata of which the earth is compoſed were originally formed at the creation, and have continued in a manner immutable ever since : but this cannot poſſibly have been the caſe, since we find that many of the ſtrata are ſtrangely intermixed with each other ; the bones of animals both marine and terreſtrial are frequently found at great depths in the earth ; beds of oyſter-ſhells are found of immenſe extent in ſeveral countries ; and concerning theſe and other ſhell-fiſh, it is remarkable, that they are generally found much farther from the ſurface than the bones or teeth either oſ marine or terreſtrial animals. Neither are the ſhells or other remains of ſiſh found in thoſe countries adjoining to the ſeas where they grow naturally, but in the moſt diſtant regions. Mr Whitehurſt, in his Inquiry into the Original State and Formation of the Earth, has given the following account of many different kinds of animals, whoſe ſhells and other remains or <hi rend="italic">exuvia</hi> are found in England ; though at preſent the living animals are not to be found except in the Eaſt and West Indies.</p><table> <row> <cell cols="2"><hi rend="italic">A</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Catalogue</hi> <hi rend="italic">of</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Extraneous Fossils,</hi> <hi rend="italic">showing where they were dug up ; alſo their native Climates, Mostly ſelected from the curious Cabinet of Mr</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Neilson,</hi> <hi rend="italic">in</hi> King-ſtreet, Red-Lion Square.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><p>Their names and Places where found.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Chambered Nautilus.</hi> Sheppy Islands ; Richmond in Surrey ;</p><p>Sherbone in Dorſetſhire, - _</p></cell> <cell><p>Native Climates.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Chineſe Ocean, and other Parts of that</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">great sea.</hi></p></cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Teeth of Sharks.</hi> Sheppy Ifland, Oxfordshire, Middleſex, Surrey, Northamptonſhire,</cell> <cell><p><hi rend="italic">East and West In-</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">dies.</hi></p></cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Sea-Tortoise,</hi> ſeveral kinds; the <hi rend="italic">Hawskbill, Loggerhead, and Green</hi> ſpecies. Sheppy Island,</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">West Indies.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Mangrove Tree Oysters.</hi> Sheppy Island,</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">Weβ Indies.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Coxcomb Tree Oysters.</hi> Oxfordſhire, Glouceſterſhire, Dorſetſhire, and Hanover,</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">Cοast of Guinea.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>VERTEBRÆ and PALATES of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Orbes.</hi> Sheppy Iſlands, and many other parts of England,</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">East and West Indies.</hi></cell> </row> </table> <table> <row> <cell>Their names, and Places where found.</cell> <cell>Native Climate«.</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Crocodile.</hi> Germany, Derbyſhire, Nottinghamſhire, Oxfordſhire, and Yorkſhire,</cell> <cell/> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Alligator’s Teeth.</hi> Oxfordshire, Sheppy Island, - J</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">East and West Indies.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Banded Buccinu μ.</hi> Oxfordſhire, and the Alps,</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">West Indies.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>The <hi rend="smallcaps">Dipping-Snail,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Star-Fish.</hi> Sheppy Iſland.</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">West Indies.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Tail Buccinum.</hi> Sheppy Iſland,</p><p>Hordel Cliff, Hampſhire, - j</p></cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">East Indies.</hi></cell> </row> </table><p>Nothing has more perplexed thoſe who undertake to form theories of the earth than theſe appearances. Some have at once boldly asserted, from theſe and other phenomena, that the world is eternal. Others have had recourſe to the univerſal deluge. Some, among whom is the Count de Buffon, endeavour to prove that the ocean and dry land are perpetually changing places ; that for many ages the higheſt mountains have been covered with water, in conſequence of which the marine animals juſt mentioned were generated in ſuch vaſt quantities, that the waters will again cover theſe mountains, the habitable part of the earth become ſea, and the ſea become dry land as before, &amp;c. Others have imagined that they might be occaſioned by volcanoes, earthquakes, &amp;c. which confound the different ſtrata, and often intermix the productions of the ſea with thoſe of the dry land.</p><p>Theſe ſubjects have been discuſſed under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Earth,</hi> to which therefore we refer the reader; and ſhall conclude with ſome account of the ſtrata in thoſe places where they have been moſt particularly obſerved.</p><p>Under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Natural History,</hi> Sect. I. it is obſerved, that the upper ſtrata oſ the earth and mountains generally conſiſt of rag-ſtone, the next of slate, the third of marble filled with petrifactions, the fourth again of slate, and the next of free-ſtone. But we are far from considering this as a rule which holds universally. The ſtrata differ exceedingly in a great number of places ; ſome inſtances of which we ſhall give from Mr Whitehurſt.—At Alfreton Common in Derbyſhire, the ſtrata are,</p><table> <row> <cell cols="3"><hi rend="italic">A</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Table</hi> <hi rend="italic">of the</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Strata</hi> <hi rend="italic">at</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Alereton Common.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell>Numb.</cell> <cell>Feet.</cell> <cell>Inch.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>I <hi rend="smallcaps">Clay</hi></cell> <cell>7</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>2 <hi rend="smallcaps">Ratchell,</hi> <hi rend="italic">fragments of stone</hi></cell> <cell>9</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>3 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi> <hi rend="italic">indurated clay</hi></cell> <cell>03</cell> <cell>4</cell> </row> <row> <cell>4 <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone,</hi> <hi rend="italic">argillaceous concreted clay</hi></cell> <cell>6</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>5 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind .</hi></cell> <cell>8</cell> <cell>8</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="italic">6</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>25</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>7 <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone,</hi> <hi rend="italic">a black colour</hi></cell> <cell>5</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>8 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>2</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>9 <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell> <cell>2</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">io Bind</hi></cell> <cell>5</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>11 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">5</hi></cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>12 <hi rend="smallcaps">Coal</hi></cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>13 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>14 <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell> <cell>23</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>15 <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell> <cell>14</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>16 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>7</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>17 <hi rend="smallcaps">SmutT,</hi> <hi rend="italic">a black substance, resembling a</hi> ſtratum <hi rend="italic">of coal-dust</hi></cell> <cell cols="2">30</cell> </row> <row> <cell/> <cell cols="2"/> </row> <row> <cell>5 M Carried over</cell> <cell>138</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> </table>
<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0832.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0826"/>
<table> <row> <cell>Numb.</cell> <cell>Brought over</cell> <cell><p>Feet.</p><p>138</p></cell> <cell><p>Inch.</p><p>0</p></cell> </row> <row> <cell>18 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>» - -</cell> <cell>3</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>19 <hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>20</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>20 <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell>16</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>21 <hi rend="smallcaps">Coal</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell>7</cell> <cell>4</cell> </row> <row> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>184</cell> <cell>4</cell> </row> </table> <table> <row> <cell cols="5"><hi rend="italic">A</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> TaBle</hi> <hi rend="italic">of the</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Strata</hi> <hi rend="italic">at</hi> <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> West HalIam.</hi></cell> </row> <row> <cell cols="2">Numb.</cell> <cell/> <cell>Feet.</cell> <cell>Inch.</cell> </row> <row> <cell>I</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clay</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>7</cell> <cell>6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>2</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>48</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>3</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Smutt</hi></cell> <cell>- ■</cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>4</cell> <cell>C <hi rend="smallcaps">lunCh,</hi> <hi rend="italic">or indurated clay</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>4</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>5</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>3</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>6</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>2</cell> <cell>3</cell> </row> <row> <cell>7</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>1</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>8</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>9</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>3</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>10</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Stone</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>11</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>16</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>12</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Shale</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>2</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>13</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>12</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">14</hi></cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Shale</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>3</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">15</hi></cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clunch, stone</hi> <hi rend="italic">and ſometimes cank</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>54</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>16</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Soft Coal</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell>4</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>17</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clay</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>0</cell> <cell>6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>18</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Soft Coal</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>4</cell> <cell>6</cell> </row> <row> <cell>19</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Clunch</hi> <hi rend="italic">and</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell/> <cell>21</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>20</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Coal</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>21</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>I</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>22</cell> <cell><hi rend="italic">Strong, broad</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Bind</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>25</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell>23</cell> <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">Coal</hi></cell> <cell>-</cell> <cell>6</cell> <cell>0</cell> </row> <row> <cell/> <cell/> <cell/> <cell>222</cell> <cell>3</cell> </row> </table><p>Mr Forſter has given an account of ſome of the ſtrata of the South-Sea iſtands, the ſubſtance oſ which may be seen in the following table.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">South Georgia.</hi></p><p>1. No soil, except in a few crevices of the rocks.</p><p>2. Ponderous ſtate, with ſome irony particles, in horizontal ſtrata, perpendicularly intersected with veins of quartz.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Southern Isle of</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">New Zealand.</hi></p><p>1. Fine light black mould, in ſome places nine inches deep, but generally not ſo much.</p><p>2. An argillaceous ſubſtance, nearly related to the claſs oſ <hi rend="smallcaps">Talcons,</hi> turned into earth by the action of the air.</p><p>3. The ſame ſubſtance farther indurated, in oblique ſtrata, generally dipping to the south.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Easter Island.</hi></p><p>1. Reddiſh-brown duſty mould, looking as if it had been burnt.</p><p>2. Burnt rocks, reſembling flags or droſs and other volcanic matters.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Marquesas.</hi></p><p>1. Clay mixed with mould.</p><p>2. An earthy argillaceous ſubſtance mixed with tarras</p><p>and puzzolana.</p><p><hi rend="italic">OTAHEITE.</hi></p><p>The ſhores are coral rock, extending from the reef encircling theſe iſles to the very high water-mark. There begins the sand, formed in ſome places from ſmall ſhells and rubbed pieces of coral ; but in others the ſhores are covered with blackiſh sand, conſiſting of the former sort mixed with black, ſometimes glittering, particles of mica, and here and there ſome particles of the refractory iron ores called in England <hi rend="smallcaps">Skim,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">ferrum micaceum</hi> of Linnaeus, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Kall</hi> the <hi rend="italic">molybdaenum spuma lupi</hi> of the ſame author. The plains from the ſhores to the foot of the hills are covered with a very fine thick ſtratum of black mould, mixed with the above-mentioned sand, which the natives manure with ſhells. The firſt and lower range of hills are formed of a red octιreous earth, ſometimes ſo intenſely red, that the natives uſe it to paint their canoes and cloth. The higher hills consiſt of a hard, compact, and ſtiff clayey ſubſtance, hardening into ſtone when out of the reach of the sun and air. At the top of the valleys, along the banks of the rivers, are large maſſes of coarſe granite ſtones of various mixtures ; in one place are pillars oſ a grey, ſolid baſaltes ; and, in ſeveral others, fragments of black baſaltes.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Friendly Islands</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">New Hebrides.</hi> The ſame with the above.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mallicollo.</hi></p><p>Yellowiſh clay mixed with common sand.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Tanna,</hi> <hi rend="italic">a Polcanic Island.</hi></p><p>The chief ſtrata here are clay mixed with aluminous earth, interſperſed with lumps of pure chalk. The ſtrata of the clay are about six inches, deviating very- little from the horizontal line.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">New Caledonia</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">adjacent Isles.</hi></p><p>The ſhores conflit of ſhell-ſand, and particles of quartz; the soil in the plains a black mould mixed with this sand. The ſides of the hills compoſed of a yellow ochreous clay, richly ſpangled with ſmall particles of cat-ſilver, or a whitiſh kind of daze, the <hi rend="italic">mica argenteae</hi> of Linnæus. The higher parts of the hills conſist of a ſtone called by the German miners <hi rend="italic">gestelstein,</hi> compoſed of quartz and great lumps of the above cat- ſilver. The latter is ſometimes of an intenſely red or orange colour, by means of an iron ochre.</p><p>“ From the above account, “ ſays Mr Forſter,” it appears, I think, evidently, that all the high tropical isles of the South Sea have been ſubject to the action of volcanoes. Pyritical and ſulphureous ſubſtances, together with a few iron-ſtones, and ſome veſtiges of copper, are no doubt found in ſeveral of them : but the mountains of New Caledonia are the moſt likely to contain the richeſt metallic veins ; and the ſame opinion, I ſuſpect, may be formed of the mountains in New Zealand.”</p><p>In the city of Modena in Italy, and for ſome miles round that place, there is the moſt ſingular arrangement of ſtrata perhaps in the whole world. From the ſurface of the ground to the depth of 14 ſeet, they meet with nothing but the ruins of an ancient city. Being come to that depth, they find paved ſtreets, artificers ſhops, floors of houſes, and ſeveral pieces of inlaid work. After theſe ruins they find a very solid earth, which one would think had never been removed ; but a little lower they find it black and marſhy, and full of briars. Signior Ramazzini in one place found a heap of wheat entire at the depth of 24 feet ; in another, he found<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0833.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0827"/>
filbert-trees with their nuts. At the depth of about 28 feet, they find a bed of chalk, about 11 feet deep, which cuts very eaſily ; after this a bed of marſhy earth of about two feet, mixed with ruſhes, leaves, and branches. After this bed comes another of chalk, nearly of the ſame thickneſs ; and which ends at the depth oſ 42 feet. This is followed by another bed of marſhy earth like the former; after which comes a new chalk-bed, but thinner, which alſo has a marſhy bed underneath it. This ends at the depth of 63 feet ; after which they find sand mingled with ſmall gravel, and ſeveral marine ſhells. This stratum is uſually about five feet deep, and underneath it is a vaſt reſervoir of water. It is on account of this water that the soil is ſo frequently dug, and the ſtrata ſo well known in this part oſ the world. After coming to the ſandy bottom above-mentioned, the workmen pierce the ground with a terebra or auger, when the water immediately ſprings up with great force, and fills the west to the brim. The flow is perpetual, and neither increaſes by rain, nor decreaſes by drought. Sometimes the auger meets with great trees, which give the workmen much trouble ; they also ſometimes ſee at the bottom of theſe wells great bones, coals, flints, and pieces of iron.</p><p>It has been aſſerted by ſome, that the ſpecific gravity of the ſtrata conſtantly increaſed with the depth from the surface. But Dr Leigh, in his Natural Hiſtory of Lancaſhire, ſpeaking of the coal-pits, denies the ſtrata to lie according to the laws of gravitation ; obſerving, that the ſtrata there are firſt a bed of marle, then free-ſtone, next iron-ſtone, then coal, or channel mire, then ſome other ſtrata, then coal again, &amp;c. This determined Mr Derham to make a nicer inquiry into the matter : accordingly, in 1712, he cauſed divers places to be bored, laying the ſeveral ſtrata by themſelves ; and afterwards determined very carefully their ſpecific gravity. The reſult was, that in his yard the ſtrata were gradually ſpecifically heavier and heavier the lower and lower they went ; but in another place in his fields, he could not perceive any difference in the ſpecific gravities.</p><p>Acquainting the Royal Society therewith, their operator Mr Haukſbee was ordered to try the ſtrata of a coal pit, which he did to the depth of 30 ſtrata : the thickneſs and ſpecific gravity of each whereof he gives us in a table in the Philoſophical Transactions<note anchored="false" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Vol. xxvii. p 541</hi></p></note>; and from the whole makes this inference, that it evidently appears the gravities of the ſeveral ſtrata are in no manner of order, but purely caſual, as if mixed by chance.</p></div></body></text></TEI>