<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0810.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0804-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STOCKING</label>,
that part of the clothing of the leg and foot which immediately covers and ſcreens them from the rigour of the cold. Anciently, the only flockings in uſe were made of cloth, or of milled fluffs ſewed together ; but ſince the invention of knitting and weaving flockings of silk, wool, cotton, thread, &amp;c. the uſe of cloth flockings is quite diſcontinued. Dr Howel, in his Hiſtory or the World (vol. ii. p. 222.) relates, that queen Elizabeth, in 1501, was preſented with a pair of black knit ſilk flockings by her ſilk-woman, and thenceforth ſhe never wore cloth ones any more. The ſame author adds, that king Henry VIII. ordinarily wore cloth hoſe, except there came from Spain, by great chance, a pair of ſilk stockings. His ſon, king Edward VI. was preſented with a pair of long Spanish ſilk stockings by Sir Thomas Greſham,<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0811.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0805"/>
and the preſent was then much taken notice of. Hence it ſhould ſeem, that the invention of knit ſilk flockings originally came from Spain. Others relate, that one William Rider, an apprentice on London bridge, seeing at the houſe of an Italian merchant a pair of knit worsted stockings from Mantua, took the hint, and made a pair exactly like them, which he preſented to William earl of Pembroke, and that they were the first of that kind worn in England, anno 1564.</p><p>The modern flockings, whether woven or knit, are formed of an infinite number of little knots, calledy stitches, <hi rend="italic">loops,</hi> or meshes, intermingled in one another.</p><p>Knit flockings are wrought with needles made of poliſhed iron, or brats wire, which interweave the threads and form the meſhes the flocking conſiſts of. At what time the art of knitting was invented it is perhaps impoſſible to determine, though it has been uſually attributed to the Scots, as it is ſaid that the first works of this kind came from Scotland. It is added, that it was on this account that the company of stocking-knitters, eſtabliſhed at Paris 1527, took for their patron St Fiacre, who is ſaid to have been the ſon of a king of Scotland. But it is moſt probable that the method of knitting flockings by wires or needles was first brought from Spain.</p><p>Woven stockings are generally very fine ; they are manufactured on a frame or machine made of poliſhed iron, the ſtructure of which it is needleſs to deſcribe, as it may be ſeen in almost every conſiderable town in Great Britain. The invention of this machine is, by Mr Anderſon, attributed to William Lee, Μ. A. of St John’s College, Cambridge, at a period ſo early as 1589. Others have given the credit of this invention to a ſtudent of Oxford at a much later period, who, it is laid by Aaron Hill<note anchored="true" n="1" place="margin" type="authorial"><p>* See An Account of the Rise and Progress of the Beech Oil Invention, &amp;c. 8vo. 1715.</p></note> *, was driven to it by dire neceſſity. This young man, falling in love with an inn-keeper’s daughter, married her though ſhe had not a penny, and he by his marriage lost a fellowſhip. They ſoon fell into extreme poverty ; and their marriage producing the conſequences naturally to be expected from it, the amorous pair became miſerable, not ſo much on account oſ their ſufferings, as from the melancholy dread of what would become of their yet unborn infant. Their only means of ſupport were the knitting of stockings, at which the woman was very expert : “ But sitting conſtantly together from morning to night, and the ſcholar often fixing his eyes, with ſtedfaſt observation, on the motion of his wife’s finger’s in the dexterous management of her needles, he took it into his imagination, that it was not impoſſible to contrive a little loom which might do the work with much more expedition. This thought he communicated to his wife, and joining his head to her hands, the endeavour ſucceeded to their wiſh. Thus the ingenious stockingloom, which is ſo common now, was first invented ; by which he did not only make himſelf and his family happy, but has left his nation indebted to him for a benefit which enables us to export ſilk flockings in great quantities, and to a vaſt advantage, to thoſe very countries from whence before we uſed to bring them at conſiderable loſs in the balance of our traffic.”</p></div></body></text></TEI>