<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0830.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0824-06" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STRASBURG</label>,
an ancient, large, handſome, populous, and ſtrong city of France in Alſace. It contains about 200 ſtreets, part of which are very narrow, and moſt of the houſes are built after the ancient taſte. However, there are a great number of handsome buildings, ſuch as the hotel of the marſhal of France, who is commander of the city ; the hotel of the cardinal of Rouen, the biſhops palace, the Jeſuits college, the royal hoſpital, the hotel of Heſſe-Darmſtadt, the arſenal, the town-houſe, and the cathedral. It has a wooden bridge over the Rhine, which is thought to be one of the fineſt in Europe ; as is likewiſe the cathedral church, whoſe tower is the handsomeſt in Germany, and the clock is greatly admired by all travellers. Some look upon it as one of the wonders of the world, and the ſteeple is allowed to be the higheſt in Europe. The clock not only ſhows the hours of the day, but the motion of the sun, moon, and ſtars. Among other things there is an angel, which turns an hour-glaſs every hour ; and the twelve apoſtles proclaim noon, by each of them ſtriking a blow with a hammer on a bell. There is likewiſe a cock, which is a piece of clock-work, that crows every hour. There are 700 ſteps up to the tower or ſteeple, it being 500 feet high. It was a free and imperial city; but the king of France became maſter of it in 1681, and greatly augmented the fortifications, though beſore it had as many cannon as there are days in the year. The inhabitants were formerly Proteſtants, and carried on a great trade ; but moſt of them have been obliged to embrace the Romiſh ſuperſtition, though there is ſtill a sort of toleration. Such was Straſburg before the French revolution ; what it is now we have not leiſure to inquire. It is ſeated on the river Ill, 55 miles north of Baſil, 112 ſouth-weſt of Mentz, and 255 eaſt of Paris. E. Long. 7. 51. N. Lat. 48. 35.</p></div></body></text></TEI>