<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0789.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0783-03" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STEERING</label>,
in navigation, the art of directing the ſhip’s way by the movements of the helm ; or of applying its efforts to regulate her courſe when ſhe advances.</p><p>The perfection of ſteering conſiſts in a vigilant attention to the motion of the ſhip’s head, ſo as to check every deviation from the line of her courſe in the firſt inſtant of its motion ; and in applying as little of the power of the helm as poſſible. By this ſhe will run more uniformly in a ſtraight path, as declining leſs to the right and left ; whereas, if a greater effort of the helm is employed, it will produce a greater declination from the courſe, and not only increaſe the difficulty of ſteering, but alſo make a crooked and irregular tract through the water. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Helm.</hi> The helmſman ſhould diligently watch the movements of the head by the land, clouds, moon, or ſtars ; becauſe, although the courſe is in general regulated by the compass, yet the vibrations of the needle are rot ſo quickly perceived as the ſallies of the ſhip’s head to the right or left, which, if not immediately reſtrained, will acquire additional velocity in every inſtant of their motion, and demand a more powerful impulſe of the helm to reduce them ; the application of which will operate to turn her head as far on the contrary side of her courſe, —The phraſes uſed in ſteering a ſhip vary according to the relation of the wind to her courſe. Thus, if the wind is fair or large, the phraſes uſed by the pilot or officer who ſuperintends the ſteerage are, <hi rend="italic">port, star-board,</hi> and st <hi rend="italic">eddy.</hi> The firſt is intended to direct the ſhip’s courſe farther to the right ; the second is to guide her farther to the left ; and the laſt is deſigned to keep her exactly in the line whereon ſhe advances, according to the courſe preſcribed. The excels of the firſt and ſecond movement is called <hi rend="italic">hard-a-port,</hi> and. <hi rend="italic">hard-a-starboard;</hi> the former of which gives her the greateſt poſſible inclination to the right, and the latter an equal tendency to the left.—If, on the contrary, the wind is foul or ſcant, the phraſes are <hi rend="italic">luff, thus,</hi> and no <hi rend="italic">nearer :</hi> the firſt of which is the order to keep her cloſe to the wind ; the ſecond, to retain her in her preſent ſituation ; and the third, to keep her sails full.</p><p>In a ſhip of war, the exerciſe of ſteering the ſhip it, uſually divided amongst a number of the moſt expert ſailors, who attend tire helm in their turns ; and are accordingly called <hi rend="italic">timoneers,</hi> from the French term <hi rend="italic">timonier,</hi> which signifies “helmſman.” The ſteerage is conſtantly ſuperviſed by the quarter-matters, who alſo attend the helm by rotation. In merchant-ſhips every ſeaman takes his turn in this ſervice, being directed therein by the mate of the watch, or ſome other officer. —As the ſafety of a ſhip, and all contained therein, depends in a great meaſure on the ſteerage or effects of the helm, the apparatus by which it is managed ſhould often be diligently examined by the proper officers. In<pb facs="gri_33125011196363_0790.tif" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0784"/>
deed, a negligence in this important duty appears almoſt unpardonable, when the fatal effects which may reſult from it are duly conſidered.</p></div></body></text></TEI>