<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0695.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0689-07" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SPHEX, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ichneumon Wasp,</hi></label>
 or <hi rend="italic">Savage ;</hi> a genus of insects belonging to the order of <hi rend="italic">hymenopterae.</hi> The mouth is armed with entire jaws, but contains no tongue ; the mandibles are horny, crooked, dentated ; the lip horny, the apex membranaceous. The palpi or feelers are four. The antennæ have from 10 to 16 joints. The wings of both ſexes are extended without folds, and laid horizontally on the back. The ſting is ſharp, arid concealed within the abdomen. There are 97 ſpecies, of which two only are natives of Britain and Ireland, the viatica and cribraria. 1. The <hi rend="italic">viatica</hi> is black : the antennæ are ſhort and thick : the three firſt ſegrnents of the abdomen red-brown : the pedicle is ſhort: the, length half an inch. 2. The <hi rend="italic">cribraria</hi> is black, with yellow ringlets on the abdomen : the antennæ are ſhort, and turned backwards : the fore-legs are broad, with an appendix like a shield.</p><p>The manner of living is different in the various ſpecies, and ſo is the general form of the body and their haunts ; but though the method of life be utterly different, yet the ſame manners appear innate and inherent in all. They agree in being the fierceſt of all flies : they will attack infects much larger than themſelves, and this whether they be defenceleſs or armed as they are provided with a ſting. The ſtrength in all this savage kind is great ; their jaws are hard and ſharp, and in their ſting lies a poiſon ſuddenly fatal to the creatures with whom they engage. The ſavage ſeizes hardily on the animal he attacks, and gives a ſtroke of amazing force ; after which he falls down as if himſelf were killed, but it is to rest from his fatigue, and enjoy his victory. He keeps a ſteady eye on the creature he has ſtruck till it dies, which happens in à few minutes, and then drags it to the neſt to feed the young. The number of other insects they deſtroy is ſcarce to be conceived ; the mouth of their cave is like that of a giant in the days of yore, ſtrewed with the remains of prey. The eyes, the filament that serves as a brain, and a ſmall part of the contents of the body, are all the ſavage eats, and will kill 50 for a meal.</p></div></body></text></TEI>