<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="gri_33125011196363_0828.tif" type="entry" xml:id="eb03-17-s05-0822-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STRAIT</label>,
a narrow channel or arm of the ſea, ſhut up between lands on either side, and affording a passage out of one great ſea into another.</p><p>There are three kinds of ſtraits; I. Such as join one ocean to another. Of this kind are the ſtraits of Magellan and Le Maire. 2. Thoſe which join the ocean to a gulf : the ſtraits of Gibraltar and Babelmandel are of this kind, the Mediterranean and Red Sea being only large gulfs. 3. Thoſe which join one gulf to another ; as the ſtraits of Caffa, which join the Palus Mæotis to the Euxine or Black Sea. The passage of ſtraits is commonly dangerous, on account of the rapidity and oppoſite motion of currents. The moſt celebrated ſtrait in the world is that of Gibraltar, which is about from 24 to 36 miles long, and from 15 to 24 broad, joining the Mediterranean ſea with the Atlantic ocean. The ſtraits of Magellan, discovered in 1520 by F. Magellan, were uſed ſome time as a passage out of the North into the South Sea ; but since the year 1616, that the ſtrait of Le Maire has been diſcovered, the former has been disuſed ; both becauſe of its length, which is full three hundred miles, and becauſe the navigation thereof is very dangerous, from the waves of the North and South Seas meeting in it and claſhing. The ſtrait at the entrance of the Baltic is called the <hi rend="italic">Sound.</hi> That between England and France, <hi rend="italic">Le pas de Calais,</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">Channel.</hi> There are alſo the ſtraits of Weigats, of Jesso, of Anian, of Davis, and Hudſon, &amp;c.</p></div></body></text></TEI>