<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>plebeian organization was materially advanced by the Publilian law of 471 b.c.,<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">@@ which appears to have formally recognized as lawful the
                    plebeian</hi><hi rend="italic">concilia,</hi> and established also the tribune’s
                right <hi rend="italic">cum plebe agere, i.e.</hi> to propose and carry resolutions
                in them. These assemblies were <hi rend="italic">tributa,</hi> or, in other words,
                the voting in them took place not by curies or centuries but by tribes. In them,
                lastly, after the Publilian law, if not before, the tribunes were annually
                elected.@@ By this law the foundations were laid both of the powerful<hi
                    rend="italic">concilia plebis</hi> of</p>
            <p>/ater days and also of the legislative and judicial prerogatives of the tribunes. The
                patricians maintained indeed that resolutions <hi rend="italic">(plébiscita)</hi>
                carried by tribunes in the <hi rend="italic">concilia plebis</hi> were not binding
                on their order, but the moral weight of such resolutions, whether they affirmed a
                general principle or pronounced sentence of condemnation on some single patrician,
                was no doubt considerable.</p>
            <p>The next stage in the struggle is marked by the attempt to substitute a public
                written law for unwritten usage.</p>
            <p>The proposal of C. Terentilius Arsa (462 b.c.) to appoint a plebeian commission to
                draw up laws restricting the powers of the consuls@@ was resolutely opposed by the
                patricians» but after ten years of bitter party strife a compromise was effected. A
                commission of ten patricians was appointed, who should frame and publish a code of
                law binding equally on both the orders. These decemviri were to be the sole and
                supreme magistrates for the year, and the law of appeal w<hi rend="sup">T</hi>as
                suspended in their favour.@@ The code which they promulgated, the famous XII.
                Tables, owed little of its importance to any novelties or improvements contained in
                its provisions. For the most part it seems merely to have reaffirmed existing usages
                andlaws (see Roman Law). But it imposed, as it was intended to do, a check on the
                arbitrary administration of justice by the magistrates. With the publication of the
                code the proper work of the decemvirs was finished; nevertheless, for the next year
                a fresh decemvirate was elected, and it is conceivable that the intention was
                permanently to substitute government by an irresponsible patrician “ council of ten
                ” for the old constitution.@@ However this may have been, the tyranny of
                the decemvirs themselves was fatal to the continuance of their power. We are told of
                a second secession of the<hi rend="italic">plebs,</hi> this time to the Janiculum,
                and of negotiations with the senate, the result ofr which was the enforced
                abdication of the decemvirs. The <hi rend="italic">plebs</hi> joyfully chose for
                themselves tribunes, and in the <hi rend="italic">camitia centuriata</hi> two
                consuls were created. But this restoration of the old regime was accompanied by
                legislation which made it an important crisis in the history of the struggle between
                the orders. With the fall of the decemvirate this struggle enters upon a new
                phase.</p>
            <p>The tribunes appear as at once more powerful and more strictly constitutional
                magistrates; the plebeian <hi rend="italic">concilia</hi> take their place by the
                side of the older assemblies; and finally this improved machinery is used not simply
                in self-defence against patrician oppression but to obtain complete political
                equality. This change was no doubt due in part to circumstances outside legislation,
                above all to the expansion of the Roman state, which swelled the numbers and added
                to the social importance of the <hi rend="italic">plebs</hi> as compared with the
                dwindling forces of the close corporation of patrician <hi rend="italic"
                    >gentes.</hi> Still the legislation of 449 clearly involved more than a
                restoration of the old form of government. The Valerio-Horatian laws, besides
                reaffirming the right of appeal and the inviolability of the tribunes, improved the
                position of the plebeian assemblies by enacting that <hi rend="italic"
                    >plébiscita</hi> passed in them, and, as seems probable, approved by the <hi
                    rend="italic">patres,</hi> should be binding on patricians as well as
                plebeians.@@</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>By this law the tribunes obtained a recognized initiative in legislation. Henceforth
                the desired reforms were introduced and carried by tribunes in what were now styled
                    <hi rend="italic">comitia tributa,</hi> and, if sanctioned by the <hi
                    rend="italic">patres,</hi> became laws of the state. From this period, too, must
                be dated the legalization at any rate of the tribune’s right to impeach any citizen
                before the assembly of the tribes.@@ Henceforward there is no question of the
                tribune’s right to propose to the<hi rend="italic">plebs</hi> to impose a fine, or
                of the validity of the sentence when passed. The efficiency of these new weapons of
                attack was amply proved by the subsequent course of the struggle. Only a few years
                after the Valerio-Horatian legislation came the <hi rend="italic">lex Camdeia,</hi>
                itself a <hi rend="italic">plebiscitum </hi>(445 B.c.), by which mixed marriages
                between patricians and plebeians were declared lawful, and the social exclusiveness
                of the patriciate broken down. In the same year with this measure, and like it in
                the interests primarily of the wealthier plebeians, a vigorous attack commenced on
                the patrician monopoly of the consulate, and round this stronghold of patrician
                ascendancy the conflict raged until the passing of the Licinian laws in 367.
                The original proposal of the tribune Gaius Canulcius, in 445, that the people should
                be allowed to elect a plebeian consul was evaded by a compromise. The senate
                resolved that for the next year, in the stead of consuls, six military tribunes with
                consular powers should be elected,@@ and that the new office should be open to
                patricians and plebeians alike. The consulship was thus for the time saved from
                pollution, as the patricians phrased it, but the growing strength of the<hi
                    rend="italic">plebs</hi> is shown by the fact that in fifty years out of the
                seventy-eight between 444 and 366 they succeeded in obtaining the election of
                consular tribunes rather than of consuls.</p>
            <p>Despite, however, these discouragements, the patricians fought on. Each year they
                strove to secure the creation of consuls rather than consular tribunes, and failing
                this strained every nerve to secure for their own order at least a majority among
                the latter. Even the institution of the censorship (435)? though rendered desirable
                by the increasing importance and complexity of the census, was, it is probable, due
                in part to their desire to discount beforehand the threatened loss of the consulship
                hy diminishing its powers.@@ Other causes, too, helped to protract the struggle.
                Between the wealthier plebeians, who were ambitious of high office, and the poorer,
                whose minds were set rather on allotments of land, there was a division of
                interest of which the patricians were not slow to take advantage, and to this must
                be added the pressure of war. The death struggle with Veii and the sack of Rome by
                the Gauls absorbed for the time all the energies of the community. In 377, however,
                two of the tribunes, C. Licinius Stolo (see Licinius Stolo, Gaius) and L.
                Sextius,came forward with proposals which united all sections of the<hi
                    rend="italic">plebs</hi> in their support. Their proposals were as follows:@@
                (1) that consuls and not consular tribunes be elected; (2) that one consul at least
                should be a plebeian; (3) that the priestly college, which had the charge of
                the Sibylline books, should consist of ten members instead of two, and that of these
                half should be plebeians; (4) that no single citizen should hold in occupation more
                than 500 acres of the common lands, or pasture upon them more than 100 head of
                cattle and 500 sheep; (5) that all landowners should employ a certain amount of free
                as well as slave labour on their estates; (6) that interest already paid on debts
                should be deducted from the principal, and the remainder paid off in three
                years. The three last proposals were obviously intended to meet the patres
                plebiscitis legem comitiis centuriatis tulere, ut quod tributim plebs jussisset
                populum tencret, qua lege tribuniciis rogationibus telum acerrimum datum est.” What
                were the precise conditions under which a<hi rend="italic">plebiscitum</hi> became
                law can, only be, conjectured. The control of the <hi rend="italic">patres</hi> over
                legislation certainly remained effective until 287 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                (See below.)</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@Livy ii. 56, 60; Dionys, ix. 41; Schwegler ii. 541; Soltau 493-</p>
            <p>@@@For theories as to the original mode of appointing tribunes see Mommsen,<hi
                    rend="italic">Forsch,</hi> i. 185, <hi rend="italic">Staatsr.</hi> ii. 274
                sqq.</p>
            <p>@@@Livy iii. 9.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Ibid. iii. 32.</p>
            <p>@@@On the disputed question of the date of the XII. Table’s see Pais,</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Storia di Roma,</hi> vol. i. chap, iv., and Greenidge, <hi
                    rend="italic">Eng. Hist. Review </hi>(1905). PP- i sqq.</p>
            <p>@@@Livy iii. 55, “ quum veluti in controverso jure esset, tenerenturne</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@After the decemvirate, the tribunes no longer pronounce capital sentences. They
                propose fines, which are confirmed by the<hi rend="italic">comitia tributa.</hi></p>
            <p>@@@Livy iv. 6; cf. Mommsen,<hi rend="italic">Staatsrecht,</hi> ii. 181.</p>
            <p>@@@Mommsen,<hi rend="italic">Staatsrecht,</hi> ii. 331.’</p>
            <p>@@@Livy vi. 35, 42 ; Appian,<hi rend="italic">B.C.</hi> i. 8.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
