<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Period II.: The Dominate, a.d. 284-476.—(a) </hi><hi rend="italic">From the Accession of Diocletian to the Death of Theodosius </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(a.d. 284-395).</hi></p><p>The work of fortifying the empire alike against internal sedition and foreign invasion, begun by Aurelian and Probus, was completed by Diocletian and Constantine the Great, whose system of government, novel as it appears at first sight, was in reality the natural and inevitable outcome of the history of the previous century.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Its object was twofold, to give increased stability to the imperial authority itself, and to organize an efficient administrative machinery throughout the empire. In the second year of his reign Diocletian associated Maximian with himself as colleague, and six years later (293) the hands of the two <hi rend="sup">u</hi> Augusti ” were further strengthened by the proclamation of Constantins and Galerius as “Caesares.” Precedents for such an arrangement were to be found in the earlier history of the Principate@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi>; and it divided the burdens and responsibilities of government, without sacrificing the unity of the empire; for, although to each of the Augusti and Caesars a separate sphere was assigned, the Caesars were subordinate to the higher authority of the Augusti, and over all his three colleagues Diocletian claimed to exercise a paramount control. It also reduced the risk of a disputed succession by establishing in the two Caesars the natural successors to the Augusti, and it satisfied the jealous pride of the rival armies by giving them<hi rend="italic">imperatives</hi>  of their own. The distribution of power between Diocletian and his colleagues followed those lines of division which the feuds of the previous century had marked out. The armies of the Rhine, the Danube and of Syria fell to the lot respectively of Constantius, Galerius and Diocletian, the central districts of Italy and Africa to</p><p>Maximian.@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi></p><p>In the new system the imperial authority was finally emancipated from all constitutional limitation and control and the last traces of it's republican origin disappeared. The emperors from Diocletian onwards were autocrats in theory as well as in practice. This avowed despotism Diocletian, following in the steps of Aurelian, hedged round with all the pomp and majesty of</p><p>Oriental monarchy. The final adoption of the title <hi rend="italic">dominus, </hi>the diadem on the head, the robes of silk and gold, the replacement of the republican salutation of a fellow-citizen by the adoring prostration even of the highest in rank before their lord and master, were all significant marks of the new regime.@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi>  In the hands of this absolute ruler was placed the entire control of an elaborate administrative machinery. Most of the old local and national distinctions, privileges and liberties which had once flourished within the empire had already disappeared under the levelling influence of imperial rule, and the process was now completed.</p><p>Roman citizenship had, since the edict of Caracalla, ceased to be the privilege of a minority. Diocletian finally reduced Italy and Rome to the level of the provinces: the provincial land-tax and provincial government were introduced into Italy@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> while Rome ceased to be even in name the seat of imperial authority@@<hi rend="sup">6</hi> Throughout the whole area of the empire a uniform system of administration was established, the control of which was centred in the imperial palace.@@<hi rend="sup">7</hi> Between the civil and military departments the separation was complete. At the head of the former were the praetorian prefects@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi> next below them the<hi rend="italic">vicarii,</hi>  who had charge of the <hi rend="italic">dioceses',</hi>  below these again Jhe governors of the separate provinces <hi rend="italic">(praesides, correctores,
                consulares),</hi>@@<hi rend="italic">9</hi>  under each cf whom was a host of minor officials. Parallel with this civil hierarchy was the scries of military officers, from the <hi rend="italic">magislri mililum,</hi>  the <hi rend="italic">duces</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">comiles</hi>  downwards.@@<hi rend="sup">10</hi>  In both there is the utmost possible subordination and division of authority. The subdivision of provinces, begun by the emperors of the 2nd century, was systematically carried out by Diocletian, and each official, civil or military, was placed directly under the orders of a superior; thus a continuous chain of authority connected the emperor with the meanest official in his service. Finally, the various grades in these two imperial services were carefully marked by the appropriation to each of distinctive titles, the highest being that of<hi rend="italic">illustris,</hi>  which was confined to the prefects and to the military <hi rend="italic">magislri</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">comites,</hi>  and to the chief ministers.@@<hi rend="sup">11</hi></p><p>@@@ See Gibbon (ed. Bury), ii. chap. xvii. 158 ff.; Marquardt,<hi rend="italic">Staatsvene.</hi>  i. pp. 81, 336, 337, ii. 217 seq,; Madvig, <hi rend="italic">Verf. d. Röm. Reichs,</hi>  i. 585; Böcking, <hi rend="italic">Notitia dignitatnm</hi>  (Bonn, 1853); Hodgkin, <hi rend="italic">Italy and her Invaders</hi>  (ed. 2), bk. i. chap, xii.; Preuss, <hi rend="italic">Diocletian </hi>(Leipzig, 1869); Seeck, <hi rend="italic">Untergang der antiken Welt,</hi>  vols. i., ii. (1897-1902).</p><p>@@@    Mommsen,<hi rend="italic">Staatsrecht,</hi>  ii. 1168 seq. Verus was associated with Marcus Aurelius as Augustus; Severus gave the title to his two sons. The bestowal of the title “ Caesar " on the destined successor dates from Hadrian. Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>  1139.</p><p>@@@ The division was as follows:—(1) Diocletian—Thrace, Egypt, Syria, Asia Minor; (2) Maximian—Italy and Africa; (3) Galenufr— Illyricum and the Danube; (4) Constantius—Britain, Gaul, Spain. See Gibbon, i. 354; Aurelius Victor, c. 39.</p><p>@@@    Aurel. Victor, 39; Eutroj?. ix. 26.</p><p>@@@ Marquardt,<hi rend="italic">Staatsvene.</hi>  i. 233 ff. Italy, together with Sicily, Sardinia and Corsica, was divided into 17 provinciae. Each had its own governor; the governors were subject to the two <hi rend="italic">vicarii (vie. urbis, vie. Italiae),</hi>  and they in turn to the prefect of Italy, whose prefecture, however, included as well Africa and Western Illyricum.</p><lb/><p>There can be little doubt that on the whole these reforms prolonged the existence of the empire, by creating a machinery which enabled the stronger emperors to utilize effectively all its available resources, and which even to some extent made good the deficiencies of weaker rulers.</p><p>But in many points they failed to attain their object. Diocletian’s division of the imperial authority among colleagues, subject to the general control of the senior Augustus, was effectually discredited by the twenty years of almost constant conflict which followed his own abdication (305-23). Constantine’s partition of the empire among his three sons was not more successful in ensuring tranquillity, and in the final division of the East and West between Valens and Valentinian (364) the essential principle of Diocletian’s scheme, the maintenance of a single central authority, was abandoned. The “ tyrants,” the curse of the 3rd century, were far from unknown in the 4th. The system, moreover, while it failed altogether to remove some of the existing evils, aggravated others. The already overburdened financial resources of the empire were strained still further by the increased expenditure necessitated by the substitution of four imperial courts for one, and by the multiplication in every direction of paid officials. The gigantic bureaucracy of the 4th century proved, in spite of its undoubted services, an intolerable weight upon the energies of the empire.</p><p>Diocletian and Maximian formally abdicated their high office in 305. Nineteen years later Constantine I., the Great, the sole survivor of six rival emperors, united the whole empire under his own rule. His reign of fourteen years was marked by two events of first-rate importance,—the recognition of Christianity as the religion oi the</p><p>@@@ The seats of government for Diocletian and his three colleagues were Mediolanum, Augusta Treyirorum, Sirmium, Nicomedia.</p><p>@@@    For these last, see Gibbon, ii. chap. xvii. p. 188; cf. also<hi rend="italic">Notitia Dignitatum</hi>  and Booking's notes.</p><p>@@@    At first the number of these varied and there was no fixed division of provinces between them; but by the close of the 4th century’ there were four prefectures, viz. Oriens, Illyricum, Italia, Gallia, to which must be added the prefectures of Rome and Constantinople. See Mommsen in<hi rend="italic">Hermes,</hi>  xxxvi. 204 ff. .</p><p>@@@<hi rend="sup">9 </hi>There were 12 dioceses and 101 provinces; cf., in addition to the authorities mentioned above, Bethmann-Hollweg,<hi rend="italic">Civil-Prozess,</hi>  iii.; Kuhn, <hi rend="italic">Die städtische und bürgerliche Verfassung des römischen Reichs</hi>  (1877).</p><p>@@@    The army was completely remodelled, and the old frontier garrisons (now called<hi rend="italic">Limitanet)</hi>  were supplemented by a field force attached to the persons of the Augusti and Caesares, ana hence called <hi rend="italic">Comitatenses.</hi>  The change was accompanied by the subdivision of the old legions into units of about 2000 men. For these reforms see Seeck, <hi rend="italic">Untergang der antiken Welt,</hi>  bk. iii. chap, v.; Mommsen in <hi rend="italic">Hermes,</hi>  xxiv. 225 ff.</p><p>@@@    The grades were as follows:<hi rend="italic">illustres, spectabiles, clarissimi, perfectissimi, egregii.</hi>  For the other insignia, see Madvig, ii. 590, and the <hi rend="italic">Notitia Dignitatum.</hi></p><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>