<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>of Syracuse, led to the outbreak of war between Rome and Carthage in 264 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b. c.</hi> The military history of the struggle which followed
                is treated in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Punjc</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Wars;</hi> it will suffice to note here that the war lasted
                until 241 B.c., when the Carthaginians were compelled to cede Sicily and the Lipari
                islands to Rome, and to pay an indemnity of 3200 talents (about £800,000).</p>
            <p>The struggle was one in which both Rome and Carthage were serving an apprenticeship
                in a warfare the conditions of which were unfamiliar to both. The Roman legions were
                foes very unlike any against which the Carthaginian leaders had ever led their
                motley array of mercenaries, while Rome was called upon for the first time to fight
                a war across the sea, and to fight with ships against the greatest naval power of
                the age. The novelty of these conditions accounts for much of the vacillating and
                uncertain action observable on both sides. It is possible that Hamilcar had already
                made up his mind that Rome must be attacked and crushed in Italy, but his government
                attempted nothing more than raids upon the coast. There are indications also that
                some in the Roman senate saw no end to the struggle but in the destruction of
                Carthage; yet an invasion of Africa was only once seriously attempted, and then only
                a half-hearted support was given to the expedition. But these peculiarities in the
                war served to bring out in the clearest relief the strength and the weakness of the
                two contending states. The chief dangers for Carthage lay obviously in the jealousy
                exhibited at home of her officers abroad, in the difficulty of controlling
                her mercenary troops, and in the ever-present possibility of disaffection among her
                subjects in Libya—dangers which even the genius of Hannibal failed finally to
                surmount. Rome, on the other hand, was strong in the public spirit of her
                citizens, the fidelity of her allies, the valour and discipline of her legions. What
                she needed was a system which should make a better use of her splendid materials
                than one under which her plans were shaped from day to day by a divided senate, and
                executed by officers who were changed every year, and by soldiers most of whom
                returned home at the close of each summer’s campaign.</p>
            <p>The interval between the First and Second Punic Wars was employed by both Rome and
                Carthage in strengthening their respective positions. The eastern end of Sicily was
                still left under the rule of Hiero as the ally of Rome, but the larger western
                portion of the island became directly subject to Rome, and a temporary arrangement
                seems to have been made for its government, either by one of the two praetors, or
                possibly by a quaestor.@@<hi rend="sup">1</hi> Sardinia and Corsica had not been
                surrendered to Rome by the treaty of 241, but three years later (239), on the
                invitation of the Carthaginian mercenaries stationed in the islands, a Roman force
                occupied them; Carthage protested, but, on the Romans threatening war, she gave way,
                and Sardinia and Corsica were formally ceded to Rome, though it was some seven or
                eight years before all resistance on the part of the natives themselves was
                crushed. In 227, however, the senate considered matters ripe for the establishment
                of a separate administration in her oversea possessions. In that year two additional
                praetors were elected; to one was assigned the charge of western Sicily, to the
                other that of Sardinia and Corsica,@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and thus the first stones
                of the Roman provincial system were laid. Of at least equal importance for the
                security of the peninsula was the subjugation of the Celtic tribes in the valley of
                the Po. These, headed by the Boii and Insubres and assisted by levies from the Celts
                to the westward, had in 225 alarmed the whole of Italy by invading Etruria and
                penetrating to Clusium, only three days’ journey from Rome. Here, however, their
                courage seems to have failed them. They retreated northward along the Etruscan
                coast, until at Telamon their way was barred by the Roman legions, returning from
                Sardinia to the defence of Rome, while a second consular army hung upon their rear.
                Thus hemmed in, the Celts fought desperately,</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>but were completely defeated and the flower of their tribesmen slain. The Romans
                followed up their success by invading the Celtic territory. The Boii were easily
                reduced to submission. The Insubres, north of the Po, resisted more obstinately, but
                by 222 the war was over, and all the tribes in the rich Po valley acknowledged the
                supremacy of Rome. The conquered Celts were not enrolled among the Italian allies of
                Rome, but were treated as subjects beyond the frontier. Three colonies were founded
                to hold them in check—Placentia (218) and Cremona in the territory of the Insubres,
                Mutina (183)* in that of the Boii; and the great northern road (Via Flaminia) was
                completed as far as the Celtic border at Ariminum.</p>
            <p>On the Adriatic coast the immediate interests of Rome were limited to rendering the
                sea safe for Italian trade. It was with this object that, in 229, the first Roman
                expedition crossed the Adriatic, and inflicted severe chastisement on the Illyrian
                pirates of the opposite coast.@@<hi rend="sup">3 </hi>This expedition was the means
                of establishing for the first time direct political relations between Rome and the
                states of Greece proper, to many of which the suppression of piracy in the Adriatic
                was of as much importance as to Rome herself. Alliances were concluded with Corcyra,
                Epidamnus, and ApoIIonia; and embassies explaining the reasons which had brought
                Roman troops into Greece were sent to the Aetolians, the Achaeans, and even to
                Athens and Corinth. Everywhere they were well received, and the admission of the
                Romans to the Isthmian games@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> (228) formally acknowledged them
                as the natural allies of the free Greek states against both barbarian tribes and
                foreign despots. Meanwhile Carthage had acquired a possession which promised to
                compensate her for the loss of Sicily, Sardinia and Corsica. The genius of her
                greatest citizen and soldier, Hamilcar Barca, had appreciated the enormous value of
                the Spanish peninsula, and conceived the scheme of founding there a Carthaginian
                dominion which should not only add to the wealth of Carthage, but supply her with a
                base of operations for a war of revenge with Rome. The conquest of southern and
                eastern Spain, begun by Hamilcar (236-28) and carried on by his kinsman Hasdrubal
                (228-21), was completed by his son Hannibal, who, with all his father’s genius,
                inherited also his father’s hatred of Rome, and by 219 the authority of Carthage had
                been extended as far as the Ebro (see<hi rend="smallcaps">Spain, </hi><hi
                    rend="italic">History).</hi> Rome had not watched this rapid advance without
                anxiety, but, probably owing to her troubles with the Celts, she had contented
                herself with stipulating (226) that Carthage should not carry her arms beyond the
                Ebro, so as to threaten Rome’s ancient ally, the Greek Massilia (mod. Marseilles),
                and with securing the independence of the two nominally Greek communities, Emporiae
                . and Saguntum,@@<hi rend="sup">5</hi> on the east coast.</p>
            <p>But these precautions were of no avail against the resolute determination of
                Hannibal, with whom the conquest of Spain was only preliminary to an attack upon
                Italy, and who could not afford to leave behind him in Spain a state allied to
                Rome. In 219, therefore, disregarding the protests of a Roman embassy, he attacked
                and took Saguntum, an act which, as he had foreseen, rendered a rupture with Rome
                inevitable, while it set his own hands free for a further advance.</p>
            <p>For the details of the war which followed, the reader may be referred to the articles
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Punjc Wars, Hannibal,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Scipio. </hi>From the outbreak of hostilities until the crowning victory of
                Cannae in 216 Hannibal’s career of success was unchecked; and the annihilation of
                the Roman army in that battle was followed by the defection of almost the whole of
                southern Italy, with the exception of the Latin colonies and the Greek coast towns.
                In 215, moreover, Philip V. of Macedon formed an alliance with Hannibal and
                threatened to invade Italy; in 214 Syracuse revolted, and in 212 the Greek cities in
                S. Italy went over to Hannibal. But the indomitable spirit</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@    Marquardt,<hi rend="italic">Staatsvenu.</hi> i. 243; Mommsen, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hist, of Rome,</hi> ii. 209; Appian, <hi rend="italic">Sic.</hi>
                2.</p>
            <p>@@@    Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.</hi> xx.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">3</hi> Polyb. ii. 8 seq.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> Ibid. ii. 12.</p>
            <p>@@@ Livy xxi. 2, 5; Polyb. iii. 15, 31.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
