<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>in 1824 became professor of oriental languages at Pisa University. He is best known as the associate of J. F. Champollion <hi rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi>  whose studies he shared and whom he accompanied in his Egyptian explorations (1828). On the death of Champollion the publication of the results of their expedition fell to Rosel-lini <hi rend="italic">(Monumenti deir Egitto e della Nubia,</hi>  Florence, 1832-40, 10 vols. fob).</p><p>ROSEMARY, botanically <hi rend="italic">Rosmarinus,</hi>  a Labiate plant, the only representative of the genus and a native of the Mediterranean region. It is a low shrub with linear leaves, dark green above, white beneath, and with margins rolled back on to the under face. The flowers are in small axillary clusters. Each has a two-lipped calyx, from which projects a bluish two-lipped corolla enclosing two stamens, the other two, which are generally present in the family, being deficient. The fruit consists of four smooth nutlets. Botanically the genus is near to <hi rend="italic">Salvia,</hi>  but it differs in the shorter connective to the anther. Rosemary was highly esteemed by the ancients for its aromatic fragrance and medicinal uses. In modern times it is valued mainly as a perfume, for which purpose the oil is obtained by distillation. It doubtless has slight stimulant properties, such as are common to all volatile oils, which may account for the general belief ' in the efficacy of the plant in promoting the growth of the hair. Rosemary plays no unimportant part in literature and folk-lore, being esteemed as an emblem of remembrance. “ There’s rosemary, that’s for remembrance,” says Ophelia. Its use in connexion with funeral ceremonies is not extinct in country places to this day, and it was formerly much valued at wedding festivities. The name “ ros marinus ” or <hi rend="sup">il</hi>  ros maris,” literally “ sea-dew,” was probably given in allusion to its native</p><p>habitat in the neighbourhood of the sea.</p><p>ROSENHEIM, a town and watering-place of Germany, in the kingdom of Bavaria, situated at the confluence of the Mangfall and the Inn, 40 mi by rail S.E. of Munich. Pop. (1905) 15,403-It is an interesting town, with many medieval houses. Among its seven churches the Roman Catholic parish church, with a curious cupola and containing numerous old tombs and effigies, and that of the Holy Ghost (15th century), are remarkable. There are a monastery, two convents, several schools and a hospital. Rosenheim is frequented for its saline and sulphur baths, and there are important saltworks, the brine being conveyed from Reichenhall in pipes; it has also machine factories, metalworks and breweries. Cordage is manufactured, and there is a trade in cattle and grain. Although founded in the 12th century Rosenheim did not become a town until 1864.</p><p>See Ditterich, <hi rend="italic">Rosenheim in Oberbayern</hi>  (Munich, 1870), and Eid, A <hi rend="italic">Altrosenheim</hi>  (Rosenheim, 1906).</p><p>ROSENKRANZ, JOHANN KARL FRIEDRICH (1805-1879), German philosopher, was born at Magdeburg on the 23rd of April 1805. He read philosophy at Berlin, Halle and Heidelberg, devoting himself mainly to the doctrines of Hegel and Schleiermacher. After holding the chair of philosophy at Halle for two years, he became, in 1833, professor at the university of Königsberg, where he remained till his death on the 14th of July 1879. In his last years he was quite blind. Throughout his long professorial career, and in all his numerous publications he remained, in spite of occasional deviations on particular points, loyal to the Hegelian tradition as a whole. In the great division of the Hegelian school, he, in company with Michelet and others, formed the “ centre,” midway between Erdmann and Gabler on the one hand, and the “ extreme left ” represented by Strauss, Feuerbach and Bruno Bauer.</p><p>Of his numerous writings, the following may be mentioned:— I. Philosophical: <hi rend="italic">Kritik der Schleiermacher sehen Glaubenslehre </hi>(1836); <hi rend="italic">Psychologie oder Wissenschaft vom subjektiven Geist</hi>  (1837; 3rd cd., 1863); <hi rend="italic">Kritische Erläuterungen des Hegelschen Systems </hi>(1840); <hi rend="italic">Vorlesungen über Schelling</hi>  (1842); <hi rend="italic">System der Wissenschaft </hi>(1850); <hi rend="italic">Meine Reform der Hegelschen Philosophie</hi>  (1852); TFisißn-<hi rend="italic">schaft der logischen Idee</hi>  (1858-59), with a supplement <hi rend="italic">(Epilegomena, </hi>1862); <hi rend="italic">Hegels Naturphilosophie und die Bearbeitung derselben durch Vera</hi>  (1868); <hi rend="italic">Erläuterungen zu Hegels Enzyklopädie der philosophischen Wissenschaften</hi>  (1871). Two other of his works on Hegel are important, the <hi rend="italic">Leben Hegels</hi>  (1844) and the <hi rend="italic">Hegel als deutscher</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Nationalphilosoph</hi>  (1870). Between 1838 and 1840 in conjunction with F. W. Schubert, he published an edition of the works of Kant, to which he appended a history of the Kantian doctrine. 2. Literary and General: <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der deutschen Poesie im Mittelalter </hi>(1830); <hi rend="italic">Handbuch einer allgemeinen Geschichte der Poesie</hi>  (1832-33); <hi rend="italic">Die Pädogogik als System</hi>  (1848); <hi rend="italic">Aesthetik des Hässlichen</hi>  (1853); <hi rend="italic">Die Poesie und ihre Geschichte</hi>  (1885); <hi rend="italic">Studien</hi>  (1839-47) and <hi rend="italic">Neue Studien</hi>  (1875-78). He published also an autobiography entitled <hi rend="italic">Von Magdeburg nach Königsberg</hi>  (1873), which deals with his life up to the time of his settlement at Königsberg.</p><p>See Quäbicker, <hi rend="italic">Karl Rosenkranz</hi>  (1899), and J. Hutchison Stirling, <hi rend="italic">The Secret of Hegel,</hi>  part 6.</p><p>ROSENTHAL, TOBY EDWARD (1848-    ), American</p><p>artist, was born at New Haven, Connecticut, on the 15th of March 1848. Removing to San Francisco with his parents in 1855, he there studied painting under Fortunato Arriola. In 1865 he went to Munich, where he was a pupil of the Royal Academy under Strachuber, Raupp and Piloty. Among his more important works are: “ Morning Prayers ” (Leipzig Museum), “ Elaine,” “ Trial of Constance de Beverley,”</p><p>“ Dancing Lesson During the Empire ” and “ Departure from the Family.”</p><p>ROSES, WARS OF THE, a name given to a series of civil wars in England during the reigns of Henry VI., Edward IV. and Richard III. Their importance in the general history of England is dealt with elsewhere, and their significance in the history of the art and practice of war is small. They were marked by a ferocity and brutality which are practically unknown in the history of English wars before and since. The honest yeoman of Edward III.’s time had evolved into a professional soldier of fortune, and had been demoralized by the prolonged and dismal Hundred Years’ War, at the close of which many thousands of ruffians, whose occupation had gone, had been let loose in England. At the same time the<hi rend="underline">power of </hi>feudalism had becomprnnrpntmfed <hi rend="underline">in, </hi><hi rend="underline">the hands of a few great lords^vho were wealthy enough and</hi>  powerful .ennngh<hi rend="underline">'ln hrenm^</hi></p><p>The disbanded mercenaries enlisted indifferently on cither side, corrupting the ordinary feudal tenantry with the evil habits of the French wars, and pillaged the countryside, with accompaniments of murder and violence, wherever they went. It is true that the sympathies of the people at large were to some extent enlisted: London and, generally, the trading towns being Yorkist, the country people Lancastrian—a division of factions which roughly corresponded to that of the early part of the Great Rebellion, two centuries later, and similarly in a measure indicative of the opposition of hereditary loyalty and desire for sound and. effective government. <hi rend="underline">But</hi>  there was this difference, that in the 15th century the feeling of loyalty was to a great extent focused upon the great lords. Each lord could depend on his own tenantry, and he could, further, pay large bands of retainers. <hi rend="sup">r</hi><hi rend="underline">Hence, </hi>much as the citizen desired a settlement, the issue <hi rend="bold">w5s Ta </hi>the hands of the magnates; and as accessions to and defections from one party and the* other „constantly shifted the balance of power, the war dragged on, becoming more and more brutal with every campaign.</p><p>It is from the Wars of the Roses that there originated the deep.-rooted dislike of the professional soldier which was for nearly four centuries a conspicuous feature of the English social and governmental system, and it is therefore in their results rather than their incidents that they have affected the evolution of war. They withdrew the English army system from European battlefields precisely at the moment of transition when the regimental and technical organization of armies was becoming a science and seeking models, and the all-powerful English longbow at the moment when the early, scarcely effective firearms were, so to speak, struggling for recognition as army weapons. On the other hand, they destroyed the British military organization. The national army, aloof from the main streams of military progress, remained for 150 years an aggregation of county levies armed with bills and bows. In so far as the king was permitted or able to raise armies, they were small mercenary forces formed, on a basis of unemployed professionals, from pressed men and criminals, and they were</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>