<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>marble, cover a great part of the top of the hill. These and other parts of the Palatine were supplied with water by an aqueduct built by Nero in continuation of the Claudian agueduct, some arches of which still exist on the slope of the Palatine (“Aqua Claudia** on Plan) (see Spart. <hi rend="italic">Sept. Sev.</hi>  24). One of the main roads up to the Palatine passes under the arched substructures of Severus, and near this, at the foot of the hill, at the south angle, Septimius Severus built an outlying part of his palace, a building of great splendour called the Septizodium,@@  or House of the Seven Planets. Part of the Septizodium existed as late ¿is the reign of Sixtus V. (1585-90), who destroyed it in order to use its marble decorations and columns in the new basilica of St Peter; drawingsof it are given by Du P6rac, <hi rend="italic">Vestigj di Roma</hi>  (1575), pi. 13, and in other works of that century.@@</p><p>The name Palatium seems to have originally denoted the southern height of the Palatine hill, while the summit overlooking the Vela-brum was called Cermalus, and the saddle connecting the Palatine and the Esquiline on which the temple of Venus and Rome and the arch of Titus now stand bore the name Velia.@@ It is evident that this was once higher than it is now; a great part of it was cut away when the level platform for the temple of Venus and Rome was formed. The foundations of part of Nero’s palace along the road between this temple and the Esquiline are exposed for about 20 to 30 ft. in height, showing a corresponding lowering of. the level here, and the bare tufa rock, cut to a flat surface, is visible on the site of Hadrian’s great temple; that the Velia was once much loftier is also indicated by the story</p><p>of the removal of Valerius Publicola’s dwelling.@@</p><p>The arch of Titus, erected in memory of that emperor’s subjugation of the Jews, but not completed until after his death, stands at the pcint where the Sacra Via crosses the Velia; it is possible that it once stood farther to the east and was removed to its present position when the temple of</p><p>Venus and Rome was built. The well-known reliefs of the archway depict the Jewish triumph and the spoils of the Temple. In the middle ages the arch was converted into a fortress by the Frangipani; their additions were removed and the arch restored in its present shape in 1821.</p><p>On the Velia and the adjoining Summa Sacra Via were the temples of the Lares and Penates which Augustus rebuilt.@@ The “ Aedes Larum ’’ is probably distinct from the “ Sacellum Larum ” mentioned by Tacitus G4ww. xii. 24) as one of the points in the line of the original pomerium. The temple of</p><p>Jupiter Stator, traditionally vowed by Romulus during his repulse by the Sabines (Liv. i. 12), stood near the Porta Mugonia, and therefore near the road leading up to the Palatine Sacra Via.@@ To the south-east of the arch of Titus (see Plan) are the remains of a concrete podium which may have belonged to this temple in its latest form; and Comm. Boni discovered (in 1907) some early tufa walling close to the above-named arch in which he recognized the foundations of the earlv temple. Augustus rebuilt the. temple of Victory, which gave its name to the Clivus Victoriae; this temple stood on the site of a prehistoric altar (Dionys. i. 32), and was more than once rebuilt,—e.g. by L. Postumius, 294 B.c. (Liv. x. 33).</p><p>In 193 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>  an aedicula to Victory was built near it by M. Porcius Cato (Liv. xxxv. 9). Remains of the temple and a dedicatory inscription were found in 1728@@not far from the church of S. Teodoro; the. temple was of Parian marble, with Corinthian columns of Numidian giallo antico. The Sacra Via started at the Sacellum Streniae, an unknown point on the Esquiline, probably in the valley of the Colosseum (Varro,<hi rend="italic">L.L. v.</hi>  47), in the quarter called Cerolia. Thence it probably (in later times) passed round part of the Colosseum to the slope leading up to the arch of Titus on the Velia; this piece of its course is lined on one side by remains of private houses, and farther back, against the cliff of the Palatine, are the substructures of the Area Apollinis. From the arch of Titus or Summa Sacra Via the original line of the road has been altered, probably when the temple of Venus and Rome was built by Hadrian. Its later course passed at a sharp angle from the arch</p><lb/><p>of Titus to the front of Constantine’s basilica, and on past the temple of Faustina. It is uncertain, whether the continuation of this road to the arch of Severus was in later times called the Sacra Via or whether it rejoined its old line along the Basilica Julia by the cross-road in front of the Aedes Julii. Its original line past the temple of Vesta was completely built over in the 3rd and 4th centuries, and clumsily fitted pavements of marble and travertine occupy the place of the old basalt blocks.@@ The course of the Nova Via@@9(see Plan) along the north-east slope of the Palatine@@was exposed in 1882-84. According to Varro (L.L. vi. 50) it was a very old road. It led up from tne Velabrum, probably winding along the slope of the Palatine, round the north angle above the church of S. Maria Antiqua. The rest of its course, gently ascending towards the arch of Titus, is now exposed, as arc also the stairs which connected it with the Clivus Victoriae at the northern angle of the Palatine; a continuation of these stairs led down to the Forum.@@</p><p>The extent of the once marshy Velabrum (Gr. féXos) is not known, though part of its site is indicated by the church of S. Giorgio in Velabro; Varro (L.L. vi. 24) says, “ extra urbem antiquam fuit, non longe a porta Romanula.” It was a district full of shops (Plaut. <hi rend="italic">Capt.</hi>  489; Hor. <hi rend="italic">Sat.</hi>  ii. 3, 30). The Vicus Tuscus on its course from the Forum to the Circus skirted the Velabrum (Dionys. v. 26), from which the goldsmiths’ arch was an entrance into the Forum Boarium.</p><p>From the S.W. end of the Velabrum the Clivus Victoriae rose in a gradual ascent along the slope of the Palatine and ultimately wound round the northern angle.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Capiioline Hill</hi>@@<hi rend="italic"/></p><p>The Capitoline hill, once called Mons Satumius (Varro, L.L. v. 42), consists of two peaks, the Capitolium and the Arx,@@ with an intermediate valley (Asylum). The older name of the Capitolium was Mons Tarpeius (Varro, L.L. v. 41). Livy (i. 10) mentions the founding of a shrine to Jupiter Feretrius on the Capitolium by Romulus;@@ this summit was afterwards occupied by the great triple temple dedicated to Jupiter, Juno and Minerva, a triad of deities worshipped under the names of Tinia, Thalna and Menerva in every Etruscan city. This great temple was (Liv. i. 38, 53) founded by Tarquín I., built by his son Tarquín II., and dedicated by M. Horatius Pulvillus, consul suffectus in 509 b.c.<hi rend="smallcaps">@@</hi>  It was built in the Etruscan style, of peperino stuccoed and painted (Vitr. iff. 3), with' wooden architraves, wide intercolumniations and painted terra-cotta statues.@@  It was rebuilt many times; the original temple lasted till it was burnt in 83 b.c.; it was then refounded in marble by Sulla, with Corinthian columns stolen from the temple of Olympian Zeus in Athens (Plin. xxxvi. 4, 5), and was completed and dedicated by Q. Lutatius Catulus, whose name appeared on the front. Augustus, although he restored it at great expense<hi rend="italic">{Mon. Anc.</hi>  4, 9), did not introduce his name by the side of that of Catulus. It was again burnt by the Vitellian rioters in a.d. 70, and rebuilt by Vespasian in 71.@@  Lastly, it was burnt in the three days* fire of Titus’s reign @@  and rebuilt with columns of Pentelic marble by Domitian; the gilding alone of this last rebuilding is said to have cost 2| millions sterh’ng (Plut.<hi rend="italic">Publ.</hi>  15). Extensive substructures of tufa have been exposed on the eastern peak; in 1875 a fragment of a fluted column was found, of such great size that it could only have belonged to the temple of Jupiter; and a few other architectural fragments have been discovered at different times. The western limit of the temple was determined in 1865, its eastern limit in 1875, and the S.E. angle in 1896.</p><lb/><p>@@@See form Septizonium is also found.</p><p>@@@See Huelsen,<hi rend="italic">Das Septizonium des Septimius Severus</hi>  (Berlin, 1886); Maass, <hi rend="italic">Die Tagesgötter in Rom und den Provinzen</hi>  (Berlin, 1902).</p><p>@@@ Huic (Palatio) Germalum et Velias conjunxerunt . . .</p><p>‘ Germalum ’ a gerrnanis Romulo et Remo, quod ad ficum Rumin-alem ibi rnventi ” (Varro, L.L. v. 54).</p><p>@@@Liv. ii. 7; Cic.<hi rend="italic">Rep.</hi>  ii. 31; see also Ascon. <hi rend="italic">Ad Cic. in Pis.</hi>  52.</p><p>@@@EDEM.LARVM.IN.SVMMA.SACRA. VIA. AEDEM.DEVM. PENATIVM.IN.VELIA... FECI (Afow.<hi rend="italic">Anc.).</hi></p><p>@@@Dionys. ii. 50; see also Plut.<hi rend="italic">Cic.</hi>  16; Ov. <hi rend="italic">Fast.</hi>  vi. 793, and <hi rend="italic">Trist,</hi>  iff. i, 131. Near this temple, and also near the Porta Mugonia, was the house of Tarquinius Pnscus (Liv. i. 41; §olin. i. 24). Owing to the strength of its position this temple was more than once selected during troubled times as a safe meeting-place for the Senate; it was here, as being a “ locus munitissimus,” that Cicero delivered his <hi rend="italic">First Catiline Oration</hi>  (see Cic. <hi rend="italic">In Cat.</hi>  i. 1).</p><p>@@@See Bianchini,<hi rend="italic">Pal. dei Cesari</hi>  (1738), p. 236, pi. viii.</p><lb/><p>@@@See Jordan,<hi rend="italic">Topographic der Stadt Rom.</hi>  i. 2. 274-91.</p><p>@@@ See Solinus (i. 24) and Varro (ap. Gell. xvi. 17), who mention</p><p>its two ends, <hi rend="italic">summa</hi>  and <hi rend="italic">infima</hi>  (cf. Liv. v. 32).</p><p>@@@See<hi rend="italic">Not. d. Scavi</hi>  (1882), p. 234. Original level laid bare, 1904.</p><p>@@@  See marble plan on Plate VI1. and cf. Ov.<hi rend="italic">Fast.</hi>  vi. 395.</p><p>@@@See Rodocanachi,<hi rend="italic">Le Capitole romain</hi>  (1903; Eng. trans., 1906).</p><p>@@@The first-named was tne southern, the second the northern summit.</p><p>@@@This is the earliesCtemple mentioned in Roman history. It was rebuilt by Augustus<hi rend="italic">{Mon. Anc.</hi>  4, 5).</p><p>@@@See Plut.<hi rend="italic">Publ.</hi>  14; <hi rend="italic">C.I.L.</hi>  i. p. 487; Liv. ii. 8. Dionys. v. 35 wrongly gives 507 B.c.</p><p>@@@Plin. xxxv. 157; see Tae.<hi rend="italic">Hist.</hi>  iff. 72; Val. Max. v. 10.</p><p>@@@Suet.<hi rend="italic">Vit.</hi>  15, and <hi rend="italic">Vesp.</hi>  8; cf. Tae. <hi rend="italic">Hist.</hi>  iv. 53, and Dio</p><p>Cass. lxvi. 10.</p><p>@@@Suet.<hi rend="italic">Dom.</hi>  5; Dio Cass. lxvi. 24.</p><lb/></body></text></TEI>