<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>later times, when no <hi rend="sup">a</hi> patrician magistrates ” were forthcoming
                to hold the elections for their successors, a procedure was adopted which was
                believed to represent the manner in which the early kings had been appointed.@@In
                this procedure the ancient privileges of the old<hi rend="italic">gentes</hi> and
                their elders, the importance of maintaining unbroken the continuity of the <hi
                    rend="italic">sacra,</hi> on the transmission and observance of which the
                welfare of the community depended, and thirdly the rights of the freemen, are all
                recognized. On the death of a king, the <hi rend="italic">auspicia,</hi> and with
                them the supreme authority, revert to the council of elders, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >patres,</hi> as representing the <hi rend="italic">gentes. </hi>By the <hi
                    rend="italic">patres</hi> an <hi rend="italic">interrex</hi> is appointed, who
                in turn nominates a second; by him, or even by a third or fourth <hi rend="italic"
                    >interrex,</hi> a new king is selected in consultation with the <hi
                    rend="italic">patres. </hi>The king-designate is then proposed to the freemen
                assembled by their curiae for their acceptance, and finally their formal acceptance
                is ratified by the <hi rend="italic">patres,</hi> as a security that the <hi
                    rend="italic">sacra</hi> of which they are the guardians have been
                    respected.@@<hi rend="sup"> </hi>Thus the king is in the first instance selected
                by the representatives of the old<hi rend="italic">gentes,</hi> and they ratify his
                appointment. In form he is nominated directly by a predecessor from whose hands he
                receives the <hi rend="italic">auspicia.</hi> But it is necessary also that the
                choice of the <hi rend="italic">patres</hi> and the nomination of the <hi
                    rend="italic">interrex </hi>should be confirmed by a solemn vote of the
                community.</p>
            <p>It is useless to attempt a precise definition of the prerogatives of the king when
                once installed in office. Tradition ascribes to him a position and powers closely
                resembling those of the heroic kings of Greece. He rules for life, and he is the
                sole ruler, unfettered by written statutes. He is the supreme judge, settling all
                disputes and punishing wrongdoers even with death. All other officials are appointed
                by him. He imposes taxes, distributes lands and erects buildings. Senate and
                assembly meet only when he convenes them, and meet for little else than to receive
                communications from him. In war he is absolute leader,@@and finally he is also the
                religious head of the community. It is his business to consult the gods on its
                behalf, to offer the solemn sacrifices and to announce the days of the public
                festivals. Hard by his house was the common hearth of the state, where the vestal
                virgins cherished the sacred fire.</p>
            <p>By the side of the king stood the senate, or council of elders. In the descriptions
                left us of the primitive senate, as in those of the <hi rend="italic">rex,</hi> we
                can discover traces of a transition from an earlier state of things when Rome was
                only an assemblage of clans or village communities, allied indeed, but each still
                ruled by its own chiefs and headmen, to one in which these groups have been fused
                into a single state under a common ruler. On the one hand the senate appears as
                a representative council of chiefs, with inalienable prerogatives of its own, and
                claiming to be the ultimate depositary of the supreme authority and of the <hi
                    rend="italic">sacra</hi> connected with it. The senators are the <hi
                    rend="italic">patres',</hi> they are taken from the leading <hi rend="italic"
                    >gentes*,</hi> they hold their seats for life; to them the <hi rend="italic"
                    >auspicia </hi>revert on the death of a king; they appoint the <hi rend="italic"
                    >interrex</hi> from their own body, are consulted in the choice of the new
                king@@ and their sanction is necessary to ratify the vote of the assembled freemen.
                On the other hand, they are no longer supreme.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>They cannot appoint a king but with the consent of the community, and their relation
                to the king when appointed is one of subordination. Vacancies in their ranks are
                filled up by him, and they can but give him advice and counsel when he chooses to
                consult them.</p>
            <p>The popular assembly of united Rome in its earliest days was that in which the
                freemen met and voted by their curiae <hi rend="italic">(comitia curiata</hi>@@<hi
                    rend="italic">.</hi> The place of assembly was in the Comitium at the north-east
                end of the Forum@@/ at the summons and under the presidency of the king or, failing
                him, of the<hi rend="italic">interrex.</hi> By the <hi rend="italic">rex</hi> or the
                    <hi rend="italic">intcrrex </hi>the question was put, and the voting took place
                    <hi rend="italic">curiatim,</hi> the curiae being called up in turn. The vote of
                each curia was decided by the majority of individual votes, and a majority of the
                votes of the curiae determined the final result. But the occasions on which the
                assembly could exercise its power must have been few. Their right to elect
                magistrates was apparently limited to the acceptance or rejection of the king
                proposed by the <hi rend="italic">interrex.</hi> Of the passing of laws, in the
                later sense of the term, there is no trace in the kingly period. Dionysius’s
                statement@@ that they voted on questions of war and peace is improbable in itself
                and unsupported by tradition. They are indeed represented, in one instance, as
                deciding a capital case, but it is by the express permission of the king and not of
                right.@@Assemblies of the people were also, and probably more frequently, convened
                for other purposes. Not only did they meet to hear from the king the announcement of
                the high days and holidays for each month, and to witness such solemn .religious
                rites as the inauguration of a priest, but their presence (and sometimes their vote)
                was further required to authorize and attest certain acts, which in a later age
                assumed a more private character. The disposal of property by will@@ and the solemn
                renunciation of family or gentile<hi rend="italic">sacra</hi>@@<hi rend="italic"
                />could only take place in the presence of the assembled freemen, while for
                    adoption@@11<hi rend="italic">(adrogatio)</hi> not only their presence but their
                formal consent was necessary.</p>
            <p>A history of this early Roman state is out of the question. The names, dates and
                achievements of the first four kings are all too unsubstantial to form the basis of
                a sober narrative;@@ a few points only can be considered as fairly well established.
                If we except the long eventless reign ascribed to King Numa, tradition represents
                the first kings as incessantly at war with their immediate neighbours. The details
                of these wars are no doubt mythical; but the implied condition of continual
                struggle, and the narrow range within which the struggle is confined, may be
                accepted as true. The picture drawn is that of a small community, with a few square
                miles of territory, at deadly feud with its nearest neighbours, within a radius of
                some 12 m. round Rome. Nor, in spite of the repeated victories with which tradition
                credits ’ Romulus, Ancus and Tullus, does there seem to have been any real extension
                of Roman territory except towards the sea. Fidenae remains Etruscan; the Sabines
                continue masters up to the Anio; Praeneste, Gabii and Tusculum are still
                untouched; and on this side it is doubtful if Roman territory, in spite of
                the possible destruction of Alba, extended to a greater distance than the sixth
                milestone from Rome.@@ But along the course</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>failed to bring out the nature of the compromise on which the kingship rests.</p>
            <p>@@@Cic.<hi rend="italic">De Legg.</hi> iii. 3; Livy iv. 7.</p>
            <p>@@@ Patres. auctores facti,” Livy i. 22; <hi rend="sup">41</hi> patres fuere
                auctores,” ibid. i. 32. In 336<hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> (Livy viii. 12) the
                Publilian law directed that this sanction should be given beforehand,<hi rend="sup"
                    >44</hi> ante initum suffragium,” and thus reduced it to a meaningless form
                (Livy i. n). It is wrongly identified by Schwegler with the <hi rend="sup">44</hi>
                lex curiata de imperio,” which in Cicero’s day followed and did not precede
                election. According to Cicero<hi rend="italic">(De Rep.</hi> ii. 13, 21), the
                proceedings included, in addition to the <hi rend="sup">44</hi> creation ” by the<hi
                    rend="italic">comitia curiata</hi> and the sanction of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >patres,</hi> the introduction by the king himself of a <hi rend="italic">lex
                    curiata</hi> conferring the <hi rend="italic">imperium</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">auspicia*,</hi> hut this theory, though generally accepted, is
                probably an inference from the practice of a later time, when the <hi rend="italic"
                    >crealio</hi> had been transferred to the <hi rend="italic">comitia
                    centuriata.</hi></p>
            <p>@@@For the references, see Schwegler i. 646 seq.</p>
            <p>@@@If the analogy of the<hi rend="italic">rex sacrorum</hi> is to be trusted, the
                “king” could only be chosen from the ranks of the <hi rend="italic"
                >patricii. </hi>Cic. <hi rend="italic">Pro Domo,</hi> 14; Gaius i. 122.</p>
            <p>@@@Cic.<hi rend="italic">De Rep.</hi> ii. 13; Dionys. ii. 14, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>@@@Varro,<hi rend="italic">L.L.</hi> v. 155. For the position of the Comitium, see
                Smith, <hi rend="italic">Diet. Geog., s.v.</hi><hi rend="sup">44</hi> Roma,” and
                    Jordan,<hi rend="italic">Topog. d.Stadt Rom. </hi>(Petersen).</p>
            <p>@@@Dionys.<hi rend="italic">l.c.</hi></p>
            <p>@@@Livy i. 26; Dionys. iii. 22.</p>
            <p>@@@Gaius ii. 101.</p>
            <p>@@@ Gell. xv. 27.</p>
            <p>@@@Gell. v. 19, “ Comitia praebentur, quae curiata appellantur." Cf. Cic.<hi
                    rend="italic">Pro Domo,</hi> 13, 14; and see.<hi rend="smallcaps">Roman
                    Law.</hi></p>
            <p>@@@By far the most complete criticism of the traditional accounts of the first four
                kings will be found in Schwegler’s<hi rend="italic">Rom. Geschichte, </hi>vol. i.;
                compare also Ihne’s <hi rend="italic">Early Rome</hi> and Sir G. C. Lewis’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Credibility of Early Roman History.</hi> More recently, E. Pais
                    <hi rend="italic">(Storia d'Italia}</hi> ha6 subjected the early legends to
                learned and often suggestive criticism, but without attaining very solid
                results.</p>
            <p>@@@The<hi rend="italic">fossa Cluilia,</hi> 5 m. from Rome (Livy ii. 39), is regarded
                by Schwegler (i. 585) and by Mommsen (i. 45) as marking the Roman frontier towards
                Latium. Cf. Ovid. <hi rend="italic">Fast.</hi> ii. 681; Strabo 230,"<hi
                    rend="italic">ueratv yovv rov Trefnrrov Kai tov Iktov\KIov . . . t6tos 4M}crTOt
                    . . . bpuw rife rbrt 'Pupalw yip.</hi>”</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
