<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>of the Tiber below the city there was a decided advance. The fortification of the
                Janiculum, the building of the <hi rend="italic">pons sublicius,</hi> the
                foundation of Ostia and the acquisition of the saltworks near the sea may all be
                safely ascribed to this early period. Closely connected, too, with the control of
                the Tiber from Rome to the sea was the subjugation of the petty Latin communities
                lying south of the river; and the tradition of the conquest and destruction of
                Politorium, Tellenae and Ficana is confirmed by the absence in historical times of
                any Latin communities in this district.</p>
            <p>With the reign of the fifth king Tarquinius Priscus a marked change takes place. The
                traditional accounts of the last three kings not only wear a more historical air
                than those of the first four, but they describe something like a transformation of
                the Roman city and state. Under the rule of these latter kings the separate
                settlements are for the first time enclosed with a rampart of colossal size and
                extent.@@ The low grounds are drained, and a forum and circus elaborately laid out;
                on the Capitoline Mount a temple is erected, the massive foundations of which were
                an object of wonder even to Pliny.@@ To the same period are assigned the redi vision
                of the city area into four new districts and the introduction of a new military
                system. The kings increase in power and surround themselves with new splendour.
                Abroad, too, Rome suddenly appears as a powerful state ruling far and wide over
                southern Etruria and Latium. These startling changes are, moreover, ascribed to
                kings of alien descent, who one and all ascend the throne in the teeth of
                established constitutional forms. Finally, with the expulsion of the last of
                them—the younger Tarquin—comes a sudden shrinkage of power. At the commencement of
                the Republic Rome is once more a comparatively small state, with hostile and
                independent neighbours at her very doors. It is impossible to. doubt the conviction
                that the true explanation of this phenomenon is to be found in the supposition that
                Rome during this period passed under the rule of powerful Etruscan lords.@@ In the
                7th and 6th centuries b.c., and probably earlier still, the Etruscans appear as
                ruling widely outside the Emits of Etruria proper. They were supreme in the valley
                of the Po until their power there was broken by the irruption of Celtic tribes
                from beyond the Alps, and while still masters of the plains of Lombardy they
                estabEshed themselves in the rich lowlands of Campania, where they held their ground
                until the capture of Capua by the Samnite highlanders in 423 b.c. It is on the face
                of it improbable that? a power which had extended its sway from the Alps to the
                Tiber, and from the Liris to Surrentum, should have left untouched the intervening
                stretch of country between the Tiber and the Liris. And there is abundant evidence
                of Etruscan rule in Latium.@@ According to Dionysius there was a time when the Latins
                were known to the Greeks as Tyrrhenians, and Rome as a Tyrrhenian city.@@ When
                Aeneas landed</p>
            <p>in Italy the Latins were at feud with Turnus (Turrhenos? Dionys. i.64) of Ardea,
                whose close ally was the ruthless Mezentius, prince of Caere, to whom the Latins had
                been forced to pay a tribute of wine.@@ Cato declared the Volsci to have been
                once subject to Etruscan rule@@ and Etruscan remains found at Velitrae,@@ as well as
                the second name of the Volscian Anxur, Tarracina (the city of Tarchon), confirm his
                statement. Nearer still to Rome is Tusculum, with its significant name, at
                Praeneste we have a great number of Etruscan inscriptions and bronzes, and at Alba
                we hear of a prince Tapxcrtos,@@ lawless and cruel like Mezentius, who consults the
                    <hi rend="sup">u</hi> oracle of Tethys in Tyrrhenia.” Thus we find the Etruscan
                power encircling Rome on aU sides, and in Rome itself a tradition of the rule of
                princes of Etruscan origin. The Tarquinii come from south Etruria; their name can
                hardly be anything else than the Latin equivalent of the Etruscan Tarchon, and is
                therefore possibly a title ( = “ lord ” or “ prince ”) rather than a proper name.@@
                Even Servius Tullius was identified by Tuscan chroniclers with an Etruscan “
                Mastarna.”@@ Again, what we are told of Etruscan conquests does not represent them
                as moving, like the Sabellian tribes, in large bodies and settEng down<hi
                    rend="italic">en masse</hi> in the conquered districts. We hear rather of
                military raids led by ambitious chiefs who carve out principalities for themselves
                with their own good swords, and with their foUowers rule oppressively over alien and
                subject peoples.@@ And so at Rome the story of the Tarquins implies not a wave of
                Etruscan immigration so much as a rule of Etruscan princes over conquered
                Latins.</p>
            <p>The achievements ascribed to the Tarquins are not less characteristic. Their despotic
                rule and splendour contrast with the primitive simplicity of the native kings. Only
                Etruscan builders, under the direction of wealthy and powerful Etruscan lords, could
                have built the great cloaca, the Servian wall, or the Capitoline temple,—monuments
                which challenged comparison with those of the emperors themselves. Nor do the traces
                of Greek influence upon Rome during this period@@ conflict with the theory of an
                Etruscan supremacy; on the contrary, it is at least possible that it was thanks to
                the extended rule and wide connexions of her Etruscan rulers that Rome was first
                brought into direct contact with the Greeks, who had long traded with the Etruscan
                ports and influenced Etruscan culture.@@</p>
            <p>The Etruscan princes are represented, not only as having raised Rome for the time to
                acommandingpositioninLatium and lavished upon the city itself the resources of
                Etruscan civiEzation, but also as the authors of important internal changes.</p>
            <p>They are represented asfavouringnewmenattheexpense of the old patrician families, and
                as reorganizing the Roman army on a new footing, a policy natural enough in military
                princes of alien birth, and rendered possible by the additions which conquest had
                made to the original community. From among the leading famiEes of the conquered
                Latin states a hundred new members were admitted to the senate, and these <hi
                    rend="italic">gentes </hi>thenceforth ranked as patrician, and became known as
                    <hi rend="italic">gentes minores.</hi>@@ The changes in the
                army begun, it is said, by the elder Tarquin and completed by Servius TulEus were
                more important. The basis of the primitive military system had been three tribes,
                each of which furnished 1000 men to the legion and 100 to the cavalry.@@ Tarquinius
                Triscus, we are told, contemplated the creation of three fresh tribes and three
                additional centuries of horsemen with new names,@@ though in face of the opposition
                offered by the old famiEes he contented himself with simply doubEng the strength
                without altering the names of the old divisions.@@ But the change attributed to
                Servius TuUius went far beyond this. His famous distribution of all freeholders<hi
                    rend="italic">(assidui)</hi> into tribes, classes and centuries,@@
                though subsequently adopted with modifications as the basis of the</p>
            <p>@@@ Livy i. 36.</p>
            <p>@@@ Ibid. 1.38, 55; Plin.<hi rend="italic">N.H.</hi> xxxvi. 15.</p>
            <p>@@@ This was the view of O. Müller, and more recently of Deecke, Gardthausen and
                Zoller.</p>
            <p>@@@ W. Schulze,<hi rend="italic">Gesch.</hi> d. <hi rend="italic">Lat.
                    Eigennamen,</hi> passim (esp. pp. 579 ff.); Zoller, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Latium</hi> w. <hi rend="italic">Rom,</hi> 166, 189; Gardthausen, <hi
                    rend="italic">Mastarna</hi> (Leipzig, 1882).</p>
            <p>@@@ Dionys. i. 29.</p>
            <p>@@@ Livy i. 2; Dionys. 1. 64, 65; Plut.<hi rend="italic">Q.R.</hi> 18.</p>
            <p>@@@ Cato ap. Serv.<hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi> xi. 567. </p>
            <p>@@@ Helbig,<hi rend="italic">Ann. d. Inst.</hi> (1865).</p>
            <p>@@@ Plut.<hi rend="italic">Rom.</hi> 2. <hi rend="italic">TrapavopL&amp;raTos Kai</hi>
                ¿i/x6raror; cf. Rutulian Tarquitius, Virg. <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi> x. 5so.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@ Müller-Deecke, i. 69, 70; Zoller,<hi rend="italic">Latium u. Rom,</hi> 168; cf.
                Strabo, p. 219; Serv. on <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi> x. 179, 198. The existence of
                an independent “ gens Tarquinia ” of Roman extraction (Schwegkr, i. 678) is unproven
                and unlikely. See now Schulze, <hi rend="italic">Lat. Eigennamen, </hi>PP* 95 <hi
                    rend="sup">an</hi>d 402 n. 6.</p>
            <p>@@@ See speech of Claudius,<hi rend="italic">Tab. Lugd.</hi> App. to Nipperdey’s edit
                ion of the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> Tacitus, “ Tusce Mastarna ei nomen erat.”
                For the painting in the François tomb at Vulci, see Gardthausen, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mastarna,</hi> 29 secj.j <hi rend="italic">Annali dell. Instil.</hi> (Rome,
                1859).</p>
            <p>@@@ Cf. the traditions of Mezentius, of Caeles Vibenna, Porsena, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>@@@ Schwegler,<hi rend="italic">R.G.</hi> i. 679 seq.</p>
            <p>@@@ <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> i. 791, 792. He accepts as genuine, and as
                representing the extent of Roman rule and connexions under the Tarquins, the first
                treaty between Rome and Carthage mentioned by Polybius (iii.„22); see, for a
                discussion of the question, Vollmer, <hi rend="italic">Rhein. Mus. </hi>xxxii. 614
                seq.; Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">Rom. Chronologie,</hi> 20; Dyer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Journ. of Philol.</hi> ix. 238.</p>
            <p>@@@ Livy i. 35 ; Dionys. iii. 67 ; Cic.<hi rend="italic">De Rep.</hi> ii. 20.</p>
            <p>@@@ Varro, L.L. v. 8ç.</p>
            <p>@@@ Livy 1.36; Dionys. iii. 71.</p>
            <p>@@@ The six centuries of horsemen were thenceforward known as “ primi secundique
                Ramnes ” (Fest. 344; cf. Schwegler, i.685 seq.). It is possible that the reforms of
                Tarquinius Priscus were limited to the cavalrv.</p>
            <p>@@@ Cic.<hi rend="italic">De Rep.</hi> ii. 22; Livy i. 42; Dionys. iv. 16.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
