<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ROMAN EMPIRE CONTD large in the criminal law, of which a prominent feature is the substitution of
                mutilation of. various kinds for the capital penalty» Death is retained for some
                crimes, such as murder and high treason; other offences were punished by amputation
                (of hand, nose, &amp;c.). This system (justified by the passage in the New
                Testament, “ If thine eye offend thee,” &amp;c.), though to modern notions
                barbaric, seemed a step in the direction of leniency; and it may be observed that
                the tendency to avoid capital punishment increased, and we are told that in
                the.reign of John Comnenus it was never inflicted. (The same spirit, it may be
                noted, is apparent in the usual, though by no means invariable, practice of
                Byzantine emperors to render dethroned rivals or members of a deposed dynasty
                innocuous by depriving them of eyesight or forcing them to take monastic orders,
                instead of putting them to death.) The Church, which had its own system of
                penalties, exercised a great influence on the actual operation of criminal law,
                especially through the privilege of asylum (recognized by Justinian, but with
                many reserves and.restrictions), which was granted to Christian churches and is
                admitted without exceptions in the <hi rend="italic">Ecloga.</hi></p>
            <p>(3) The last period of legislative activity under Basil I. and Leo VI. represents a
                reaction, in a certain measure, against the <hi rend="italic">Ecloga</hi> and a
                return to Justinian. The <hi rend="italic">Ecloga</hi> had met practical needs, but
                the Isaurian and Phrygian emperors had done nothing to revive legal study. To do so
                was the aim of Basil, and the revival could only be based on Justinianean law books
                or their Greek representatives. These books were now treated somewhat as Justinian
                and his lawyers had treated their own predecessors. A handbook of extracts from the
                Institutes, Digest and Code was issued in 879    <hi rend="italic">(6    </hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">p6/xos, **</hi> the law as it is ”), to</p>
            <p>fulfil somewhat the same function as the Institutes. Then a collection of all the
                laws of the Empire was prepared by means of two commissions, and completed under Leo
                VI. It was entitled the <hi rend="italic">Basilika.</hi> In many points (in civil,
                but not in criminal, law) the principles of the <hi rend="italic">Ecloga</hi> are
                set aside in favour of the older jurisprudence. Thus the Justinianean ordinances on
                the subject of divorce were revived, and there remained henceforward a contradiction
                between the civil and the canon law.</p>
            <p>After this there was no legislation on a grand scale; but there was a great revival
                of legal study under Constantine IX., who founded a new law-school, and there were
                many learned specialists who wrote important commentaries, such as John Xiphilin
                filth century), Theodore Balsamon (12th century), Harmenopulos (14th century). The
                civil code of Moldavia (published 1816—17) is a codification of Byzantine law; and
                modern Greece, although in framing its code it took the Napoleonic for its model,
                professes theoretically to base its civil law on the edicts of the emperors
                as contained in the <hi rend="italic">Hexabiblos</hi> of Harmenopulos.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Administration.—</hi>Three principles underlay the administrative
                reform of Diocletian: the separation of civil from military functions; the formation
                of small provincial units; and the scalar structure which deepened on the
                interposition of the vicar of a diocese and the praetorian prefect between the
                provincial governor and the emperor. This system lasted unchanged for three and a
                half centuries. The few unimportant alterations that were made were in harmony
                with its spirit, until the reign of Justinian, who introduced certain reforms that
                pointed in a new direction. We find him combining some of the small provinces into
                large units, undermining the scalar system by doing away with some of the dioceses
                and vicars, and placing in some eases military and civil authority in the same
                hands. The chief aim of Diocletian in his general reform had been to secure central
                control over the provincial governments; the object of Justinian in these particular
                reforms was to remedy corruption and oppression. These changes, some of which were
                soon cancelled, would hardly in themselves have led to a radical change; but
                they prepared the way for an administrative revolution, brought about by stress of
                external necessities. In the 7th century all the energies of the Empire, girt about
                by active enemies, were centred on war and defence; everything had to give way to
                military exigencies; and a new system was gradually introduced which Jed ultimately
                to the abolition of the old. The change began in Italy and Africa, at the end of the
                6th century, where operations against the Lombards and the Berbers were impeded by
                the friction between the two co-ordinate military and civil authorities (masters of
                soldiers, and praetorian prefects). The military governors were made supreme with
                the title of <hi rend="italic">exarchs,</hi> “ viceroys”; the civil authority was
                subordinated to them in ease of collision, otherwise remaining unaltered. The change
                is an index of the dangerous crisis through which these provinces were passing. In
                the East similar circumstances led to similar results. The Saracen danger hanging
                imminent over Asia Minor imposed a policy of the same kind. And so before the end of
                the 7th century we find the Empire divided into six great military provinces, three
                in Europe and three in Asia: (1) Exarchate of <hi rend="italic">Africa,</hi> (2)
                Exarchate of <hi rend="italic">Italy, </hi>(3) Strategia of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thrace,</hi> (4) County of <hi rend="italic">Opsikion ( —
                obsequium), </hi>including Bithynia, Honorias, Paphlagonia, parts of Helles-pontus
                and Phrygia, (5) Strategia of the <hi rend="italic">Anatolikoi,</hi> most of west
                and central Asia Minor, (6) Strategia of the <hi rend="italic">Armenia
                koi, </hi>eastern Asia Minor. In addition to these there was a
                naval circumscription, (7) the Strategia of the <hi rend="italic">Karabisianoi</hi>
                (from xapa/Jo?,a vessel), including the southern coastland of Asia Minor, and the
                Aegean (see below under <hi rend="italic">Navy),</hi></p>
            <p>The lands of the old prefecture of Illyricum were not included in the system, because
                this part of the Empire was then regarded as a lost position. On the contrary, here
                military powers were committed to the Prefect of Illyricum, whose actual sphere
                extended little beyond Thessalonica, which was surrounded by Slavonic tribes.</p>
            <p>The Eastern changes, perhaps initiated by Heraclius, but probably due mainly to
                Constans II., did not interfere with the civil administration, except in so far as
                its heads were subordinated to the military commanders. But Leo III., who as a gieat
                administrative reformer ranks with Augustus and Diocletian, did away w'ith the old
                system altogether. ft) Reversing Diocletian’s principle, he combined military and
                civil powers in the same hands. The strategos or military commander became also a
                civil governor; his higher officers (tur-marchs) were likewise dvil functionaries.
                *(2) The scalar principle disappeared, including both the vicars and the praetorian
                prefect of the East (some of whose functions were merged in those of the prefect of
                the dty); no authority interposed between the strategoi and the emperor. (3) The
                new provinces, which were called <hi rend="italic">themes</hi> (the name marks
                their military origin: <hi rend="italic">thima —</hi> corps), resembled in size the
                provinces of Augustus, each including several of the Diocletian divisions. This
                third and last provindal reform has, like its predecessors, its own history. The
                list of themes in the nth century is very different from that of the 8th. The
                changes were in one direction—the reduction of large provinces by cutting off
                parts to form smaller themes, a repetition of the process which reduced the
                provinces of Augustus. Hence the themes came to vary greatly in size and importance.
                Leo himself began the process by breaking up the Anatolic command into two
                themes (Anatolic and Thraeesian). The principle of splitting up was carried out
                systematically by Leo VI. (who was also responsible for a new ecclesiastical
                division of the Empire).</p>
            <p>The development will be exhibited by a list of the themes in the middle of the 10th
                century. A. Asia: j(1) Opsikion, (2) Optimaton,</p>
            <p>(з)    Paphlagonia, (4) Bukellarian) = old Opsikion; J(5) Anatolic, (6) Thraeesian,
                (7) Samos (naval), (8) Cappadocia, (o) Scleucia) = old Anatolic; }(io) Armeniac,
                (11) Colonea, (12) Scbastca, (13) Charsianon, (14) Chaldia, (15) Mesopotamia) =old
                Armeniac; (16) Cibyrrhaeot, (17) Aegean (= Dodekanesos). B. Europe: (1) Thrace, (2)
                Macedonia, (3) Strymon, <hi rend="smallcaps">(a)</hi> Thessalonica, (5) Hellas, (6)
                Peloponnesus, (7) Nicopolis, (8) Dyrrnachium, (9) Longibardia, (10) Cephallenia,
                (11) Cherson.</p>
            <p>It is interesting to note that up to Leo VI. the district between Constantinople and
                the wall of Anastasius formed a separate theme or government, entitled the Wall
                (r&lt;5 Tet^io*) or the Ditch (1$ <hi rend="italic">T&amp;Qpcn)'; </hi>Leo VI.
                united it with the theme of Thrace.</p>
            <p>In the central administration, the general principles seem to have remained
                unchanged; the heads of the great administrative bureaux in Constantinople retain
                the <hi rend="italic">palatine</hi> character which belonged to most of them from
                the beginning. But there were many changes in these offices, in their nomenclature
                and the delimitation of their functions. There are great differences between the
                administrative corps in the $th, in the 10th and in the 15th centuries. We can
                hardly be wrong in conjecturing that, along with his provincial reform, Leo III.
                made a rearrangement of the central bureaux; the abolition of the Praetorian
                Prefecture of the East entailed, in itself, modifications. But minor changes were
                continually being made, and we may note the following tendencies: (1) Increase in
                the number of ministers directly responsible to the emperor,</p>
            <p>(и)    subordinate offices in the bureaux being raised to the rank</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
