<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>translated from HTML to TEI</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>and the forum was heaped high with the bodies of the slain.@@<hi rend="sup">1
                </hi>Cinna fled, but fled, like Sulla, to the legions. When the senate declared him
                deposed from his consulship, he replied by invoking the aid of the soldiers in
                Campania in behalf of the violated rights of the people and the injured dignity of
                the consulship, and, like Sulla, found them ready to follow where he led.
                The neighbouring Italian communities, who had lost many citizens in the recent
                massacre, sent their new champion men and money;@@<hi rend="sup">2</hi> while from
                Africa, whither he had escaped after Sulla’s entry into Rome, came Marius with 1000
                Numidian horsemen. The senate had prepared for a desperate defence, but fortune was
                adverse, and after a brief resistance they gave way. Cinna was acknowledged as
                consul, the sentence of outlawry passed on Marius was revoked and Cinna and
                Marius entered Rome with their troops. Marius’s thirst for revenge was gratified by
                a frightful massacre, and he lived long enough to be nominated consul for the
                seventh time. But he held his consulship only a few weeks. Early in 86 lie died,
                and for the next three years Cinna ruled Rome. Constitutional government was
                virtually suspended. For 8 5 and</p>
            <p>84 Cinna nominated himself and a trusted colleague as consuls.@@<hi rend="sup">3
                </hi>The state was, as Cicero@@<hi rend="sup">4</hi> says, without lawful
                    authority.@@<hi rend="sup">5 </hi>One important matter was carried through—the
                registration in all the tribes of the newly enfranchised Italians,@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >6</hi> but beyond this little was done. The attention of Cinna and his friends
                was in truth engrossed by the ever-present dread of Sulla’s return from Asia. The
                consul of 86, L. Valerius Flaccus (who had been consul with Marius in 100<hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> sent out to supersede him, was murdered by his own
                soldiers at Nicomedia@@.<hi rend="sup">7</hi></p>
            <p>In 85 Sulla, though disowned by his government, concluded a peace with
                    Mithradates.@@<hi rend="sup">8</hi> In 84, after settling affairs in Asia and
                crushing Flaccus’s successor, C. Flavius Fimbria, he crossed into Greece, and in the
                spring of 83 landed at Brundusium with 40,000 soldiers and a large following of
                ¿migré nobles. Cinna was dead,@@<hi rend="sup">9 </hi>murdered like Flaccus by his
                mutinous soldiers; his most trusted colleague, Cn. Papirius Carbo, was commanding as
                proconsul in Cisalpine Gaul; and the resistance offered to</p>
            <p>Sulla’s advance was slight. At Capua, Sulla routed the forces of one consul, Gaius
                Norbanus; at Teanum the troops of the other went over in a body to the side of the
                outlawed proconsul. After a winter spent in Campania he pressed forward to
                Rome, defeated the younger Marius (consul,82) near Praeneste, and entered the city
                without further opposition. In north Italy the success of his Ueutenants,Q.Caecilius
                Metellus Pius</p>
            <p>(son of Metellus Numidicus), Cn. Pompeius and Marcus Crassus, had been fully as
                decisive. Cisalpine Gaul, Umbria and Etruria had all been won for Sulla, and the two
                principal leaders on the other side, Carbo and Norbanus, ,had each fled, one to
                Rhodes, the other to Africa. Only one foe remained to be conquered. The Samnites and
                Lucanians whom Cinna had conciliated, and who saw in Sulla their bitterest foe, were
                for the last time in arms, and had already joined forces with the remains of the
                Marian army close to Rome. The decisive battle was fought under the walls of the
                city, and ended in the complete defeat of the Marians and Italians (battle of the
                Colline Gate).@@<hi rend="sup">10</hi></p>
            <p>For a period of nearly ten years Rome and Italy had been distracted by civil war.
                Sulla was now called upon to heal</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>the divisions which rent the state asunder, to set in working again the machinery of
                civil government and above all so to modify it as to meet the altered
                conditions, and to fortify it against the dangers which visibly threatened it in the
                future. The real charge against Sulla@@<hi rend="sup">11</hi> is not that he failed
                to accomplish all this, for to do so was beyond the powers even of a man so able,
                resolute and self-confident as Sulla, armed though he was with absolute authority
                and backed by overwhelming military strength and the prestige of unbroken success.
                He stands convicted rather of deliberately aggravating some and culpably ignoring
                others of the evils he should have tried to cure, and of contenting himself with a
                party triumph when he should have aimed at the regeneration and confirmation of the
                whole state. His victory was instantly followed, not by any measures of
                conciliation, but by a series of massacres, proscriptions and confiscations, of
                which almost the least serious consequence was the immediate loss of life which they
                    entailed.@@<hi rend="sup">12</hi> From this time forward the fear of
                proscription and confiscation recurred as a possible consequence of every
                political crisis, and it was with difficulty that Caesar himself dissipated the
                belief that his victory would be followed by a Sullan reign of terror. The legacy of
                hatred and discontent which Sulla left behind him was a constant source of disquiet
                and danger. In the children of the proscribed, whom he excluded from holding office,
                and the dispossessed owners of the confiscated lands, every agitator found ready
                and willing allies.@@<hi rend="sup">13</hi> The moneyed men of the equestrian
                order were more than ever hostile to the senatorial government, which they now
                identified with the man who cherished towards them a peculiar hatred,@@<hi
                    rend="sup">14</hi> and whose creatures had hunted them down like dogs. The
                attachment which the new Italian citizens might in time have learnt to feel for the
                old republican constitution was nipped in the bud by the massacres at Praeneste and
                Norba, by the harsh treatment of the ancient towns of Etruria, and by the ruthless
                desolation of Samnium and Lucania.@@<hi rend="sup">15</hi> Quite as fatal were the
                results to the economic prosperity of the peninsula. Sulla’s confiscations,
                following on the civil and social wars, opened the doors wide for a long train of
                evils. The veterans whom he planted on the lands he had seized@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >16</hi> did nothing for agriculture, and swelled the growing numbers of the
                turbulent and discontented.@@<hi rend="sup">17</hi> The “ Sullan men ” became as
                great an object of fear and dislike as the “Sullan reign?’@@<hi rend="sup">18</hi>
                    The<hi rend="italic">latijundia</hi> increased with startling rapidity—whole
                territories passing into the hands of greedy partisans.@@<hi rend="sup">19</hi> Wide
                tracts of land, confiscated but never allotted, ran to waste.@@<hi rend="sup"
                    >20</hi> In all but a few districts of Italy the fiee population finally and
                completely disappeared from the open country; and life and property were rendered
                insecure by the brigandage which now developed unchecked, and in which the
                herdsmen slaves played a prominent part. The outbreaks of Spartacus in 73, and of
                Catiline ten years later, were significant commentaries on this part of Sulla’s
                    work.@@<hi rend="sup">21</hi> His constitutional legislation, while it included
                many useful administrative reforms, is marked by as violent a spirit of
                partisanship, and as apparently wilful a blindness to the future.
                There-establishment on a legal basis of the ascendancy which custom had so long
                accorded to the</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@    Cic.<hi rend="italic">Pro Sestio,</hi> 36, 77; <hi rend="italic">Catil.</hi>
                iii. 10, 24.</p>
            <p>@@@    Tibur and Praeneste especially.</p>
            <p>@@@ The consuls of 86, 85, 84 were all nominated without election. Livy,<hi
                    rend="italic">Epit.</hi> lxxx. lxxxiii.; App. i. 75.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="italic">    Brut.</hi> 227.</p>
            <p>@@@    The nobles had fled to Sulla in large numbers; Veil. ii. 23.</p>
            <p>@@@ This work was accomplished apparently by the censors of 86; but cf. Lange iii.
                133; Mommsen,<hi rend="italic">Hist, of Rome,</hi> iv. 70; Livy, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epit.</hi> lxxxiv.</p>
            <p>@@@    Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.</hi> lxxxii; Appian, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mithr.</hi> 52; Plut. <hi rend="italic">Sulla,</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>@@@    Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.</hi> lxxxiii.; Veil. ii. 23; Plut. <hi
                    rend="italic">Sulla,</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>@@@    In 84; App.<hi rend="italic">B.C.</hi> i. 78; Livy, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epit.</hi> lxxxiii.</p>
            <p>@@@    Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.</hi> lxxxviii., “ cum Samnitibus ante portam
                Collinam debellavit ”; Plut. <hi rend="italic">Sulla,</hi> 29, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Crassus,</hi> 6. According to App. i. 9J, and Livy, <hi rend="italic">loc
                    cit.,</hi> 8000 captives were massacred. Florus, iii. 21, gives 4000. Praeneste
                surrendered, was razed to the ground, and its population put to the sword.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>@@@    Compare especially Mommsen’s brilliant chapter, which is, however, too
                favourable (bk. iv. cap. x.),and also Lange (iii. 146 seq.). Further references will
                be found in the article<hi rend="smallcaps">Sulla </hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(q.v.).</hi></p>
            <p>@@@    App. i. 95 seq.; Dio Cassius, fr. 109; Plut.<hi rend="italic">Sulla,</hi> 31.
                The number of the proscribed is given as 4700 (Val. Max.), including, according to
                Appian, 2600 members of the equestrian order.</p>
            <p>@@@    E.g. Catiline, in 63. Sail.<hi rend="italic">Cat.</hi> 21, 37. For the <hi
                    rend="italic">liberi pro-</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">scriptorum,</hi> see Veil. ii. 28.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">14</hi> Cic.<hi rend="italic">Pro. Cluent.</hi> 55, 151.</p>
            <p>@@@    Cic.<hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi> v. 16, 43, “ tot municipiorum maximae
                calamitates.” Cic. <hi rend="italic">Pro Domo,</hi> 30, 79; Cic. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ad AtL</hi> i. 19; Florus iii. 21; Strabo, 223, 254.</p>
            <p>@@@    Livy,<hi rend="italic">Epit.</hi> lxxxix.; App. <hi rend="italic">B.C.</hi> i.
                100; Cicero, <hi rend="italic">Catil.</hi> ii. 79. 20.</p>
            <p>@@@    Sail.<hi rend="italic">Cat. 28.</hi></p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">18</hi> Cic.<hi rend="italic">Agr.</hi> ii. 269.</p>
            <p>@@@ Cic.<hi rend="italic">Agr.</hi> ii. 26, 69 seq.; 28, 78; iii. 2, 8—the
                territories of Praeneste and of the Hirpini.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="sup">20</hi> Ibid. iii. 4, 14.</p>
            <p>@@@ See especially Cicero’s oration<hi rend="italic">Pro Tullio.</hi> For the <hi
                    rend="italic">pastores</hi> of Apulia, Sail. <hi rend="italic">Cat.</hi> 28.</p>
            <lb/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
