<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>translated from HTML to TEI</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>succulent torus, which in the other genera is dry. In <hi rend="italic">Geum</hi>  (avens) and <hi rend="italic">Dryas</hi>  (an arctic and alpine genus) the style is persistent in the</p><p>fruit, forming a feathery appendage <hi rend="italic">(Dryas)</hi>  or a barbed awn (avens), either of which is of service in distributing the fruit. The Poten-tilleae are chiefly north temperate, arctic and alpine plants.</p><p><hi rend="italic">I</hi></p><p>The Roseae comprise the large genus <hi rend="italic">Rosa,</hi>  characterized by <hi rend="bold">a </hi>more or less urn-shaped torus (fig. 4) enclosing the numerous carpels which form dry one-seeded fruits enveloped in the bright-coloured fleshy torus. The numerous stamens surround the mouth of the torus. The plants are shrubs bearing prickles on the stems and leaves; many species have a scrambling habit resembling the brambles. The species of <hi rend="italic">Rosa,</hi>  like those of <hi rend="italic">Rubus,</hi>  are extremely variable, and a great number of subspecies, varieties and forms have been described. The Sanguisorbeae are a reduced form of Rosoideae. The dry one-seeded fruit is enclosed in the urn-shaped</p><p>torus, which, however, is dry and inconspicuous, and the number of carpels is much reduced, sometimes to one (fies. 2. 5. 6). Petals are often wanting, as in <hi rend="italic">Alchemilla</hi>  (lady’s</p><p>mantle) and <hi rend="italic">Poterium,</hi>  and the flowers</p><p>are often unisexual and frequently wind-</p><p>pollinated, as in salad burnet <hi rend="italic">(Poterium</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Sanguisorba),</hi>  where the small flowers</p><p>are crowded in heads, the upper pistil</p><p>late, with protruding feathery stigmas,</p><p>and the lower staminate (or bisexual),</p><p>with exserted stamens. <hi rend="italic">Agrimonia</hi></p><p>(agrimony) has a long spike of small</p><p>honeyless flowers with yellow petals; in</p><p>the fruit the torus becomes nard and</p><p>crowned by hooked bristles which ensure</p><p>the distribution of the enclosed achenes.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Suborder IV. Neuradoideae</hi>  contains only two genera of desert-inhabiting herbs with yellow flowers; and the five to ten carpels are united together and with the base of the cup-shaped torus, which enlarges to form a dry covering round the one-seeded fruits.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Suborder V. Prunoideae</hi>  (fig. 7) is characterized by a free solitary carpel with a terminal style and two pendulous ovules, and the fruit a one-seeded drupe.</p><p>The torus, forms a cup from the edge of which spring the five sepals, five alternating petals and the ten to indefinite stamens. The plants are deciduous or evergreen trees <hi rend="bold">or </hi>shrubs with simple leaves, often</p><p>with small caducous stipules, and racemes or umbels of generally showy, white or pink flowers. There are five genera, the chief of which is <hi rend="italic">Prunus,</hi>  to which belong the plum <hi rend="italic">(Prunus communis),</hi>  with several well-marked subspecies—<hi rend="italic">P. sbinosa</hi>  (sloe or blackthorn), <hi rend="italic">P. insititia</hi>  (bullace), <hi rend="italic">P. domestica</hi>  (wild plum), the almond (P. <hi rend="italic">Amygdalus),</hi>  with the nearly allied peach (P. <hi rend="italic">pérsica),</hi>  cherry (P. <hi rend="italic">Cerasus),</hi>  birdcherry (P. <hi rend="italic">Padus)</hi>  and cherry</p><p>laurel (P. <hi rend="italic">Laurocerasus).</hi>  . The tribe is distributed through the north temperate zone, passing into the tropics.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Suborder VI. Chrysobalanoideae</hi>  resembles the last in having a single free carpel and the fruit a drupe, but differs in having the style basal, not terminal, and the ovules ascending, not pendulous; the flowers are also frequently zygomurphic. The 12 genera are tropical evergreen trees or shrubs, the great majority being. South American. The zygomorphic flowers indicate an affinity with the closely allied order Leguminosae.</p><lb/><lb/><lb/><lb/></body></text></TEI>