<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0555.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0488-04" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>SOUTHERNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>,
 an eminent dramatic writer, was born at Dublin in 1660, and received his education in Trinity College. He came young to London to study law ; but instead of that, devoted himself to poetry and the writing of plays. His Persian Prince, or Loyal Brother, was introduced in 1682, when the Tory interest was triumphant in England ; and the character of the Loyal Brother being intended to compliment James duke of York, he rewarded the author when he came to the throne with a commission in the army. On the Revolution taking place, he retired to his studies, and wrote several plays, from which he is supposed to have derived a very handsome subsistence, being the first who raised the advantage of playwriting to a second and third night. The most finished of all his plays are the Fatal Marriage, or the Innocent Adultery ; and Oroonoko, or the Royal Slave, which is built on a true story related in one of Mrs Behn’s novels.<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0556.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0489"/>
Mr Southerne died in 1746, in the eightysixth year of his age; the latter part of which he spent in a peaceful serenity, having, by his commission as a soldier, and the profits of his dramatic works, acquired a handsome fortune, and being an exact economist, he improved what fortune he gained to the best advantage. He enjoyed the longest life of all our poets, and died the richest of them, a very few excepted. His plays are printed in three volumes 12mo. See the Biographia Dramatics, vol. i. p. 680.</p></div></body></text></TEI>