<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0685.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0604-02" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STEAM, TO PRACTICAL AND ECONOMICAL PURPOSES</label>
.</p><p>1. Warming apartments and buildings by steam. 2.</p><p>Heating greenhouses &amp;e., by steam. 3. Evaporating solutions, drying fabrics, paper, gunpowder, grain, &amp;e., by steam. 4. Warming baths, boiling liquids, and distilling by steam. 5. Preparation and economy of wholesome food by steam. 6. The steam-engine.</p><p>1. <hi rend="italic">Warming Apartments by Steam.</hi></p><p>66. One of the most important applications of steam in the economy of fuel, is its employment as a vehicle for Transferring to a distance, and distributing uniformly, the heat of a fire for the purpose of warming an apartment or building. Its great efficiency for this purpose arises from the largeness of its capacity for caloric, because, as it holds a quantity of caloric equal to 1000 degrees, it will communicate as much heat as a mass of red hot iron ; and it will have this advantage over the iron, that it can carry this heat to a distance without a similar loss ; because, the heat being latent, will not be given out until it arrive at its destination and become condensed, when the whole of its 1000° will be usefully applied.</p><p>The manner in which warming by steam is to be effected, is this. At a convenient part of the building, and as low as possible, there is to be placed a close steam boiler of the ordinary construction. From this boiler a small steam pipe is to be carried to the part of the building which is to be warmed. This small pipe should be pretty thick, and carefully rolled round with a fillet of flannel to a quarter of an inch thick, and the boiler should be wholly covered with bricks and plastered over to keep it warm. This smaller steam pipe should have an area of one square inch for every six gallons of water that the boiler can boil off in an hour. Pipes of a larger size are to be laid round the room above the floor, or under the floor if apertures be left to allow a free circulation of warmed air to enter the room ; but the best method we have seen is, to make the surbase, which passes round the room of thin iron plate or copper having the external figure of the surbase, and sufficiently strong to withstand the pressure of the steam, which strong tin plate or copper of 1½ lb. to the foot will sufficiently effect, if the surbase be not more than about 4 inches square. Into these larger pipes the steam is to be conducted, and in them the steam will be condensed into water, and will give 1000° of heat to the colder air of the room which is in contact with the outside of these pipes. In doing so the steam being condensed into water, small pipes of lead or tin must be provided, for the purpose of bringing back this condensed water into the boiler ; and, in order that they may act well, care is to be taken that a gentle slope, of about an inch in 20 feet, be given to all the pipes. The condensed water being thus conducted back to the bottom of the boiler, it will there be replenished with heat, and in the form of steam will again carry up its supply of 1000° to the apartment, again to be given off as formerly to the room, and then returning once more to the boiler, a continual circulation of the same particles of water, giving out in each circuit a quantity of heat equal to red hot iron, is uniformly and gently imparted to and diffused equally over the apartment. The pipe which brings the steam from the boiler may be called the feeding pipe, the pipes which give off the heat the radiating pipes, and the pipes which lead back the water to the boiler the return pipes. We have already given dimensions for the feed</p><p>pipe. The return pipes need not be more than <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 12</hi> of the diameter of the feed pipe, but an increase of size could do little harm, and may have the effect of preventing accidental obstruction : the boiler will require to have a pint of water added now and then to supply accidental waste ; and a safety-valve on the boiler is indispensable. A self-regulating feeder, such as that mentioned in the article S <hi rend="smallcaps">τεαμ-Ενgινε,</hi> among the apparatus of boilers, is also to be recomended where it can be readily attained, It is necessary, however, to give directions at greater length for the dimensions of the warming or radiating pipes, as it is upon their proper construction and arrangement that the efficiency of the apparatus entirely depends ; and the apparatus has frequently failed from the want of proper precaution. The radiating pipes in the room are generally too small. It is their extent of surface, and the free circulation of air round them, which determines how much of the heat will be given out, and how rapidly. From very accurate experiments I am induced to conclude, that a room containing 500 cubic feet of air, and exposing 400 feet of surface, may be maintained at a temperature of 20° above that of the air without—that is to say, at 60° in the inside of the room when the atmosphere is at 40 without—for a space of twelve hours, by the evaporation of 2 gallons of water, and at the expense of about three pounds of coal of the value of one farthing. But this supposes that there is no ventilation, and that the air of the room is never changed ; whereas, the presence of one individual would render it necessary to introduce nearly 400 cubic feet of external air every hour. Now, the heat of 20° given to 400 cubic feet of air would require the evaporation of 3 gallons of water ; and, therefore, the evaporation of 3 gallons of water would be required for such a room, and 3 gallons for every person in it, if properly ventilated, and for every 2 gallons there should be at least one square foot of radiating surface ; so that such a room, occupied by one person, would require a surface of warming pipe equal to 2½ square feet, and so on for every such room and occupant, for a space of 12 hours in the day.</p><p>Thus, the evaporation of 1 gallon per day for every 400 feet of surface, with a difference of temperature of 20 from the external air, and 1½ gallons per day for each person, and 1 square foot of radiating surface, is a standard from which we easily calculate.</p><p>A room 30 feet long, 20 feet wide, and 10 feet high, has a surface of 2200 feet, which would require 5½ gallons ; six people would require 9 gallons; therefore, 14½ gallons of water and 7¼ feet of radiating surface will heat the well-ventilated room 12 hours for 6 persons at an expense of 25 lbs. of coal, or about threepence per day; or a whole house, occupied by 6 persons, may be warmed, if 30 feet high, 30 feet wide, and 30 feet deep, at tenpence aday, the price of coals being twenty shillings aton.</p><p>It is scarcely necessary to add, that the radiating pipes may be best constructed of thin copper, and ought to be roughened and blackened on the outside.</p><p>In the same way the calculation may be made for any other room, building, and number of occupants.</p><p>For more extensive and minute information on the subject of Warming, the reader is requested to consult the article “ <hi rend="smallcaps">Warming and Ventilation</hi>,” in the Encyclopedia.</p><p>The form in which the radiating surface may be distributed admits of variety.</p><p>Provision must be made for the expansion and con traction of the pipes.</p><p>The arrangement of steam in the apartment to be heated is of some consequence. It is, we have already stated, sufficiently out of the way in the surbase, but, in that case, much heat passes out into the walls and wood. It may stand on the hearth like a stove, and consist<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0686.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0605"/>
of concentric cylindric</p><p>chests within each other</p><p>(fig. 24), filled with</p><p>steam, and allowing air</p><p>to ascend by the sides</p><p>and through the inter</p><p>vening spaces, so as to</p><p>be made warm, and</p><p>the outer surface radia</p><p>ting directly on the sur</p><p>face exposed. It may be</p><p>tubular, and coiled in</p><p>a large quantity in a</p><p>small box fitted up exter</p><p>nally in the appearance</p><p>of a cabinet or pedestal</p><p>in the apartment, thus :</p><p>(Figs. 25 and 26) ; the</p><p>feed pipe commencing</p><p>at the top of the coils,</p><p>and the return pipe passing off from the bottom. As the conducting power of tin is nearly equal to that of iron, a quantity of tin pipe will suffice, and be more economical than iron or copper. This coil may be placed in a eabi net or pedestal of the form of Fig. 26, and the warm air will have free egress through the wire work of the panel.</p><p>The next diagram (Fig. 27,) shows an arrangement of copper steam-vessels, by which an extensive surface is very efficiently exposed to the air, the condensed water being drawn off at the bottom.</p><p>There is one case in which warming by steam may be employed with especial advantage, and where it is frequently neglected—where the power of steam is already employed to drive machinery. Let the engine employed be what is called high-pressure, or non-condensing, in which the steam escapes from the engine and is passed off into the air ; and, instead of the common plan, let the steam from the engine be conveyed in pipes through the apartments to be warmed, and let the diameter of the pipe</p><p>gradually increase towards the end of its circuit, and finally terminate in a hot-water pipe, which may also circulate in the building and there will be given out the whole original heat of the steam after having done its work in the steam engine, and that as effectually as if there had been no steam-engine at all, and the whole power of the engine will thus be clear saving. This will be the case to a still greater extent if the steam-engine work expansively, and may further be increased if the pipes be so formed as to constitute an aerial condenser. For further information on this subject see article <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam-Engine</hi>.</p><p>2, <hi rend="italic">Warming Hothouses, Greenhouses, &amp;c. by Steam.</hi></p><p>67∙ The principles which regulate this application of</p><p>steam are similar to those mentioned already in Art. 66, and steam possesses the same advantages in the distribution of heat for this purpose, which it does in the cases already mentioned. The warmth thus distributed is freed from those risks of injury to the vitality of the plants, which accompany the old method of warming by hot air flues, in which a contaminated and unwholesomely dry air and unequable temperature were inevitably produced, and an occasional annoyance from smoke. The warmth given out by the steam is of uniform intensity throughout the whole length of the glass ; it occupies very small space —one furnace and chimney is all that is required for any extent of range of glasshouses, as the steam may be conveyed to any usual distance in well swathed pipes without sensible loss. The saving thus effected by the concentration of the fire, and by its equable distribution, has been found to produce an economy of more than one-third of the fuel commonly used. At Sion House, the seat of the Duke of Northumberland, there are nearly a thousand feet in length of glasshouses heated by one such apparatus. The boiler and chimney may also be placed at a convenient distance from the houses—a circumstance which contributes much to the beauty of this arrangement.</p><p>Those who wish to study the details of this subject are referred to Mr Loudon’s Horticultural Works, and to the article “ <hi rend="smallcaps">Horticulture</hi>,” in this Encyclopedia. The fol lowing are the mechanical principles and arrangements that belong exclusively to this article.</p><p>Our first subject of enquiry, is into the amount of heat requisite to sustain the glass at a given temperature higher than that of the external air ; if we take the temperature of the atmosphere at 35°, and that of the hot house at 65°, giving 30° of difference, we shall have a case approaching near to that of a glasshouse in winter. In order to determine this question, which can only be as certained by experiment, the author has examined a case upon a large scale, which may furnish a standard of comparison.<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0687.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0606"/>
The large palm house of the Botanic Garden of Edin burgh is an octagonal structure, 60 feet in diameter, and 45 feet high. Excepting stone pillars at the angles, and between the windows, of about three feet wide, the whole building is glass, presenting a surface of almost exactly 5000 square feet of glass. The quantity of fuel required in a cold atmosphere, having a mean of 35°, is 1344 pounds for 24 hours ; being at the rate of 269 lbs. of coal for every 1000 feet of glass in a day, or 11.2 pounds an hour for 1000 feet, or .0112 of a pound per hour for each foot.</p><p>To confirm this observation, it was thought proper to examine another house of different dimensions. The eastern wing of the great range of houses is warmed by a fire, which consumes half that quantity of coals, of about half the value, being dross of a bad quality ; so that its consumption is about ¼ of the other in real value, being about 672 lbs. of dross, equivalent to 336 lbs. of good coal in 24 hours. Now, the exposed glass of this wing amounts to about 1376 square feet, being at the rate of 243 lbs. to 1000 feet—a result which is sufficiently near to the other, to allow us to assume 250 or 260 lbs. of fuel in 24 hours for each thousand feet, as a standard of tolerable accuracy in such cases. It may be useful to add, that these houses are in tolerably sheltered situations, and that the glass faces in every direction, so as to be acted on with tolerably uniformity.</p><p>Hence we have the following results :</p><p>Temperature of the air 35°—temperature of the hot house 65°.</p><p>Heat sustained 24 hours, by 250 lbs. of good coal, for 1000 square feet of glass.</p><p>Heat sustained 1 hour, by 10.4 lbs. of good coal for 1000 feet of glass.</p><p>Heat sustained 1 hour, by 0.0104 lbs. of good coal, for one foot of glass.</p><p>To find what amount of steam will be required to warm such a house, we have only to apply the calculations of Art. 66 ; 10.4 lbs. of good coal will convert seven gallons of water into steam ; therefore, a boiler of one horse’s power is necessary to evaporate a sufficient quantity of water for the supply of steam for each 1000 feet of glass ; that is to say, for the palm-house alone, a boiler of five horses’ power would be required to furnish steam ; and this supposes the hot water of the condensed steam to be returned into the boiler immediately ; and if this were not the case, six horses’ power would be the size of boiler ordered for this purpose : hence—</p><p>To warm a hothouse by steam, there is required the boiler of a steam-engine, reckoned at one horse’s power for every thousand feet of glass.</p><p>The method of distributing the heat through the rooms of the hothouse, is not a matter of so nice calculation as in a common apartment. There is much greater convenience for this purpose in a greenhouse than a common room, on account of the necessary vacuities under the ranges and beds. In general, a single circuit of steam-pipe four inches in diameter, round the apartment, with a re turn pipe of equal dimensions laid parallel to it, is sufficient.</p><p>It is, however, of great importance to provide a remedy for one of the practical inconveniences of steam. When the fire is not very carefully tended, ns during the night, the steam in the boiler falls below the proper point, and the supply instantly ceases. This is remedied by the following method. Cast iron boxes, a foot square and five or six feet deep, are filled with stones, and ranged round the forcing rooms—a pipe passing into each of them communicates a supply of steam to them, and the stones they contain. The caloric entering first of all with rapidity into the stones, is afterwards given out gradually by them to the house ; and the advantage of this arrangement is, that even if neglect or accident were to occasion a tem</p><p>porary cessation of the supply, this heat would still continue to be given out from the matter of the boxes for several hours until the defect might be remedied. These boxes of stones perform the same function for caloric that a flywheel does for mechanical power—absorbing it when in excess, and giving ft out again when deficient.</p><p>It is a valuable hint to economy, which Mr Macnab has put in execution in his houses at the Botanical Gar den, that the boiler flues should be extended to the green house after they have left the boiler ; the remaining heat is thus given out to the hothouse, and the last degree of saving accomplished. With this arrangement a smaller boiler will suffice, but it will not always be convenient ; neither can a greater length than about 30 feet of flue be advantageously used in this way.</p><p>3. <hi rend="italic">On Evaporating and Drying Solutions, Cloths, Paper, Grain, Gunpowder, &amp;c., by Steam.</hi></p><p>68. We have already observed how well the peculiarities of steam enables us to make use of it as a vehicle for the collection, transference, and distribution of heat. In addition to the facility with which it may be carried to a distance, and the uniformity of temperature resulting from it, we have this further adaptation to the purposes now under consideration, that the temperature can at no time become so great ns to produce injury, or deteriorate the substances to which it is applied. Hence it follows that thickened liquids, strong solutions, and any porous solid matter impregnated with fluid may be evaporated, and wholly separated from the fluid, without incurring the danger and suffering the deterioration resulting from direct application of the fire. And, further, by the proper application of steam, as a conductor of heat, liquids may be warmed, evaporated, and even boiled in vessels of wood, which is in some cases, as in brewing and delicate distributions, a matter of much importance.</p><p>When any mixture or solution of a solid in water is to be evaporated by steam, it may be done in some of the following ways.</p><p>(1.) The vessel containing the solution may have two bottoms, the interval between them being filled with water and steam, and the solution resting on the upper one, the fire is applied to the under one ; thus the steam and water intervening between the solution and the fire, the latter is protected, as well as the vessel itself, from being burnt when the process has nearly attained the necessary degree of dryness ; and the process of communicating the heat from the fire to the water takes place in the following manner ; the fire generates in the water bubbles of steam, which ascend from the lower to the higher bottom of the vessel, which is in contact with the solution and acquires its temperature, and, giving off their heat to the upper bottom, are condensed, and fall down again to the lower bottom to acquire the accession necessary to rise, once more, in steam to the top. This plan has been successfully used in making salt ; and it is necessary to have a safety and an atmospheric valve attached to the space between the lower and upper bottoms. The quantity of heat required for the purpose of evaporating the water of the mixture is neither increased sensibly, nor diminished by the intervention of the steam between the bottoms ; the number of gallons of water to be evaporated from the solution will determine the quantity of heat by Art. 66.</p><p>(2.) A second method of producing evaporation is to introduce among the mixture a steam pipe, so as to wind amongst it either in the form of a helix, like a corkscrew or worm of a still, or to perform such a circuit as shall expose a large quantity of surface, with tolerable uniformity, to the fluid for the absorption of heat from the steam. Copper is the best material for the tubes, and wooden tanks lined with lead or tin will contain the mixture. The fuel<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0688.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0607"/>
required for evaporation will be 5 lbs. for every 31 gallons of water to be evaporated, and the steam boiler must have one horse’s power for every 6 gallons to be evaporated in an hour.</p><p>(3.) A third method is the invention of Mr Goodlet of Leith. The substance to be evaporated is forced by means of a pump into a long copper pipe, which enters a close steam boiler, and after winding through it so frequently as to expose a sufficient surface for a sufficient length of time to acquire the necessary supply of heat from the boiler, again passes out from the boiler and discharges its heated contents into an appropriate reservoir, again, if necessary, to be passed once more through the same process by the force pump. In this case the substance is brought to the steam boiler for evaporation instead of having the steam brought to it, and thus any loss of heat during the transit of the steam is prevented.</p><p>A steam kiln for drying grain has been used with great success by the same person. The grain is spread out on the iron floor of a large room—this floor is perfo rated with a mιdtitude of small openings, or formed of a very fine grating ; immediately under the floor steam pipes of 6 inches diameter lie parallel to each other at small intervals apart, and radiate heat directly to the floor and the grain, and also to the surrounding air, which in this hot state ascends through the grain ; numerous large ventilators being provided for the escape of the vapour thus impregnated with moisture, after it has ascended through the grain. This method has been found effectual, and 13 attended with less risk of injury than the ordinary one.</p><p>In the processes of drying and printing cloths and fabrics of various kinds, rapid and complete drying is of much importance. This is effected principally in what is called a drying frame : this consists of a dozen of tin cylinders, a foot in diameter and 6 or 8 feet long ; these cylinders are closed completely by two hemispherical ends, and are placed upon an axis in a frame, so as to revolve in contact with each other. Steam is conducted into all these cylinders by a pipe passing through the axis, which is hollow, and the joint is made steam-tight by a stuffing box similar to that of the cover of a steam-engine cylinder. A piece of cloth dripping from the dye-vat is passed through the frame once and is then perfectly dry. Of course, the quantity of steam required for this process is proportional to the number of pounds of water to be evaporated from each piece, that is, to the difference between the weight <hi rend="italic">of a</hi> piece when wet and when dry. The number of lbs. being ascertained, the fuel and power of the boiler are found from article 66.</p><p>In the manufacture of paper the process of drying by steam is beautifully exhibited. The wet pulp, laid out on the web of wire cloth, is gradually strained as it approaches the large hollow cylinders, around which it winds for half a minute and then comes off perfectly dry finished paper, ready for use. This process is minutely described in the article “ <hi rend="smallcaps">Paper</hi> ” of this Encyclopedia.</p><p>4. <hi rend="italic">Warming Baths, Boiling Liquids, Distilling by Steam.</hi></p><p>69∙ To heat water rapidly, and in considerable quantity, by means of a fire placed at some distance, is a problem frequently proposed ; and steam for such a case is an excellent vehicle for the heat. Let there be placed in a steam boiler 10 gallons of water, and heated into steam ; these 10 gallons conveyed to a reservoir or bath of water at a distance, by a small lead pipe, will heat nearly 55 gallons of water from 32° to the boiling point, or 165 gallons from 40° to 100°, the usual temperature of a warm bath. A bath of the ordinary construction will require about 160 gallons, and the said 10 gallons will require 18 lbs.</p><p>of coal, value sixpence. Besides this, the sides of the bath, if made hollow, may be warmed by the introduction of steam between the lining and the outside, at the same time that the water is warmed ; and the apartment may further be heated with steam pipes from the same apparatus.</p><p>The most effectual method of communicating the heat of steam to water is to pass the open end of the steam pipe from the boiler directly into the water to be heated, so as at once to mix with it. The mouth of the pipe, properly regulated by a stopcock, should enter at the bottom, and be directed from one end of the bath along one side towards the other, and thus the impetus of the steam on entering will communicate to the water a circulation highly conductive toan equable distribution of heat.</p><p>A very simple apparatus of this kind may be placed in the same apartment with the bath itself. A boiler 4 feet long and 2 feet deep, with a fire covering a square of 18 inches, will heat such a bath in three quarters of an hour. A copper boiler will be most effective, and the steam pipe should first be matted with bandages of flannel, and then stitched with canvass painted, from the boiler to where it enters the bath.</p><p>In establishments where there are many baths, a reser voir at the top of the building may be kept constantly filled with water ready to descend into the baths, the reservoir being supplied with heat from the steam pipe of a boiler placed in the outer buildings, or some other suitable place. It is to be recollected that the boiler used must be what is called a one, two, or three horse power boiler, according as one hundred, two hundred, or three hundred gallons per hour are wanted ; and so on for every additional hundred gallons of water at 100° of temperature—one horse power of boiler for one hundred gallons.</p><p>The same process may be used for heating and even for boiling a liquid or solution, in which no injury will result from adding the steam of this condensed water to the liquid. In a dye-work, or other work where much boiling and many solutions are used, steam boiling in this manner is a process of great convenience and value. The vessels containing dyes of various kinds, including leys and solutions of various substances, in which cloths, yarns, wools, and various materials are to be boiled, are ranged around a spacious apartment. Around this apartment, attached to the wall, circulates a steam pipe of two inches diameter, from which smaller branch pipes go off to each of the boilers from the nearest point, and pass down to the bottom of their respective vessels. The exit of the steam is governed by a stopcock under the hand of the operator; and by this means he can easily, by allowing a smaller or greater supply of steam to enter the liquid, produce a uniform and gentle simmer or excite an instantaneous and tumultuous ebullition. Two great advantages give this method much superiority over the common mode of boiling by the direct action of the fire. The condensed steam supplies to the solution exactly as much water as is lost by evaporation, so that it remains of the same strength through a protracted process, and there is no injury sustained by. allowing the substances immersed to settle down and rest at the bottom.</p><p>Where it is not aIlowable for the caloriferous steam to be condensed in contact with the liquid to be warmed or boiled, we must resort to the method of heating by sur face ; that is to say, the steam must be conveyed through the mass of liquid by a pipe, or other conductor best fitted to give out the heat or retain the water. A very thin pipe of the purest soft copper is best for this purpose ; 2 inches in diameter and <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 20</hi> to <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> / <hi rend="subscript"> 40</hi> of an inch in thickness will be found good dimensions, and a square foot of surface for every 10 gallons of water to be boiled per hour will be required. For some purposes, it will be enough to wind the pipe in a spiral<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0689.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0608"/>
round the inside of the vessel to be heated ; but if the vessel be large, numerous pipes must pass through the liquid. For boiling 1000 gallons per hour, 200 feet of copper pipe 2 inches in diameter are required.</p><p>In distillation by steam, the same method of communicating heat to the liquid to be distilled is employed as al ready described in boiling. But the vapours of other liquids, having less specific caloric than water, a smaller quantity of steam from the boiler will be required to evaporate than to evaporate an equal quantity of water; thus the heat of one gallon of water will evaporate and cause to be distilled 2 gallons of alcohol, 3 of sulphuric ether, and 4 of turpentine. It is a curious phenomenon, of which distillers should avail themselves in carrying off the vapour in distillation, that although alcohol floats on water, and ether on alcohol, nevertheless the vapour of water floats above vapour of alcohol, and vapour of alcohol above vapour of ether.</p><p>The densities of water, alcohol, and ether being 10. 8. 7∙</p><p>and the densities</p><p>of their vapours 6. 16. 25.</p><p>in round numbers.</p><p>5. <hi rend="italic">Preparation of Food by Steam.</hi></p><p>70. The last of the applications of steam which we shall here examine is that which was historically the first, its application to cooking and other domestic uses. This invention makes its appearance in the following record of the Royal Society of London.</p><p>At a meeting of the Council of the Royal Society,</p><p>December 8, 1680.</p><p>Ordered, that a book intituled A New Digestor, or Engine for softening Bones, &amp;c., written by Denys Papin, Doctor of Physick, and Fellow of this Society, be printed and published. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chr. When.</hi></p><p>This work on the New Digester was accordingly published in 1681 ; “ Containing the description of its make and use in these particulars, viz., Cookery, Voyages at Sea, Confectionary, Making of Drinks, Chymistry and Dyeing, with an Account of the Price a good big Engine will cost, and of the profit it will afford.”</p><p>The following list will show the extent to which the learned doctor had proceeded in applying steam to the improvement of the dietetic art. It is copied from the Index to the work. “ (1.) How to know the quantity of pressure in the Digestor. (2.) How to know the degree of heat. (3.) How meat may be kept upon the fire three times as long as is necessary to make it ready, and yet it will not be spoiled. (4.) The same experiment made upon bones. (5.) How to boil mutton. (6.) How to boil beef. (7.) How to boil lamb. (8.) How to boil rabbits. (9∙) How to boil pigeons. (10.) How to boil fish. (11.) How to boil pulse. (12.) How to make jelly, very cheap. (13.) Glue for glasses. (14.) Hartshorn turned like Parmesan cheese. (15.) A macquerel kept without salt. (16.) Salt water as good for nourishment as fresh water. (17∙) To make sweetmeats at a cheap rate, and of a new taste. (18.) To make two sorts of drink with the same fruit. (19.) To make a new sort of wine. (20.) Tinctures drawn in the hundredth part of the time usually required for them. (21.) New ways for distilling. (22.) How to hatch chickens (23.) How to save the labour of grinding cochenille. (24.) To dye with thick juices. (25.) To make horn and tortoiseshell soft for a great while.”</p><p>This catalogue of uses of steam we shall shortly run over, as the modern uses of steam for cookery are principally applications of Dr Papin’s methods, and as valuable economization in the preparation of food on a large scale has resulted from them, especially in the extraction of</p><p>highly nutritious food from bones. A digester on the principle of Dr Papin is used in every modern kitchen.</p><p>“ Description of the Digester and how to use it safely.”</p><p>“ A A is a brass (or copper) cylinder, hollow within, shut at the bottom and open at the top. B is another cylinder inverted upon it. C C are two appendices or ears cast to the cylinder A A, as the trunnions of a piece of ordnance. D D are two pieces of iron put upon the appendices at one end, and the iron bar E E at the other. F F are two screws, which serve to press both the cylinders A A, B B, against one another. G is another hollow cylinder, made of glass, pewter, or some other materials, fitted to receive those things that are to be included in the cylinders A A, and B B, with water all round it.</p><p>“To use this engine with convenience and ease, it ought to be fitted in a furnace built on purpose for it, and should go on ns far as the appendices C C ; so the fire being underneath, and the screws well fastened, and a piece of moistened paper laid between the cylinders at the joint <hi rend="italic">i i</hi> to make it steam tight, you may boil your meat as long as you please without danger of wasting it by the ex halation of the volatile parts.</p><p>“ To know the quantity of the inward pressure, you must have a little pipe open at both ends as H H : this being soldered to a hole in the cover B B, is to be stopped at the top with a little valve P, exactly ground to it. This must be kept down with an iron rod I M, one end of which must be put. into an iron staple M, fastened to the bar E E, and the other end kept down by a weight N to be hung upon it nearer or further from the valve according as you would keep it less or more strong, after the manner of an ordinary Roman balance, or steelyard.</p><p>“ To know the degree of heat, I hang a weight to a thread about 3 feet long, and I let fall a drop of water into a little cavity made for that purpose at the top of it, and I tell how many times the hanging weight will move to and fro before the drop of water is quite evaporated.</p><p><hi rend="italic">“ Experiment.</hi> Having filled my pot with a piece of a breast of mutton, and weighed five ounces of coals, I lighted my fire, and by blowing gave such a heat that a drop of water would evaporate in 4 seconds, the inward pressure being about 10 times stronger than the atmosphere : I let the fire go out of itself, and then the mutton was very well done, <hi rend="italic">the bones soft</hi> and the juice a strong jelly. So that, having had occasion to boil mutton several times since, I have always observed the same rule, and never have missed to have it in the same condition, which I take to be best of all.’’</p><p>Beef required 7 ounces of coal and the same heat, and the beef was very well boiled, although there were more parts of the bones not quite softened. Lamb, rabbits, and pigeons, mackerel, pike, and eel, were subjected to the same process; whence the doctor infers that the bones of young beasts require almost as much fire as those of old ones to be boiled, that rabbit bones are harder than those of mutton, that tough old rabbits may be made as good as tender young ones by this means, that pigeons may be best boiled with a heat that ovapo rates a drop of water in 5 seconds, that mackerel was<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0690.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0609"/>
cooked with gooseberries in a digester, the fish being good and firm, and the bones so soft as not to be felt in eating ; and he particularly recommends, as an excellent dish cooked in this manner, cod fish and green peas.</p><p>The most important of Papin’s experiments are those on the extraction of gelatine from bones, as now done on a large scale in France and in this country, as also the manufacture of essence of meat, soups, &amp;., especially suitable for long sea voyages.</p><p>“ I took,” says he, “ beef bones that had never been boiled, but kept dry a long time, and of the hardest part of the leg; these being put into a little glass pot with water, I included in the engine, together with another little glass pot full with bones and water too, but in this the bones were ribs and had been boiled already. Havingprest the fire till the drop of water would dry away in three seconds, and ten pressures, I took off the fire ; and the vessels being cooled, I found very good jelly in both my pots ; but that which had been made out of ribs had a kind of a reddish colour, which I believe might proceed from the medullary part, the other jelly was without colour like hartshorn jelly ; and I may say, that having seasoned it with sugar and juice of lemon, I did eat it with as much pleasure, and found it as stomachical, as if it had been jelly of hartshorn. Mutton bones are better than beef bones ; and he infers (1.) that one pound of beef bones afford about two lbs. of jelly ; (2.) that it is the cement (gelatine) that unites the parts of the bones, which is dis solved in the water to make it a jelly, since after that, the bones remain brittler ; (3.) that few glutinous parts are</p><p>sufficient to congeal much water, for I found that when the jelly was dried, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> had very little glue[-ten?] remaining; (4.) I used it to glue a broken glass, which did since that time hold very well, and can be washed as well as if it had never been broken ; (5.) it is heavier than water, and sinks to the bottom ; (6.) hartshorn produces five times its weight of jelly.</p><p>“ From all these experiments, I think it very likely, that if people would be persuaded to lay by bones, gristles, tendons, feet, and other parts of animals that are solid enough to be kept without salt, whereof people throw away more than would be necessary to supply all the ships that England hath at sea, the ships might always be furnished with better and cheaper victuals than they used to have. And I may say, that such victuals would take up less room too, because they have a great deal more nourishment in them in proportion to their weight. They would also be more wholesome than salt meat. Vege tahles, such as dried peas, may also be cooked by the steam of salt water without becoming salt.”</p><p>We have entered thus fully upon the work of Doctor Denys Papin, and the properties of his digester for cooking, and extracting jellies by high-pressure steam, because it contains nearly all that is at present practised in the preparation of food by steam.</p><p>If to what has been already stated, we add, that if the steam of salt water be collected in a vessel kept cold on the outside, the condensed water will not be impregnated with salt, and may be used as food, the importance of steam in the economical and menial capacity of cook, will be sufficiently apparent. The supply of water to the crew of a steam vessel may be obtained in this manner, and an apparatus for thus procuring fresh water from the condensation of steam from salt water, has been used with advantage in ordinary ships.</p><p>Fig. 29 contains the steam-cooking apparatus used in modern kitchens ; <hi rend="italic">a a</hi> is a portion of the kitchen fireplace In one of the divisions of it, <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> is placed a steam boiler, furnished with the usual apparatus of feeding pipes, gauge cocks, &amp;c. From this boiler a steam pipe, <hi rend="italic">c c,</hi> is led along the back of the cooking table <hi rend="italic">d d,</hi> and at certain</p><p>intervals, branch pipes, furnished each with a stopcock, project across the table at right angles to the main pipe.</p><p>The extremities of these branch pipes are conical, and made accurately to fit into conical sockets inserted into the cooking pans, one of which, <hi rend="italic">e</hi>, is seen in its place on the table. These pans have each a double bottom, the lower one close, the upper one perforated ; between the bottoms the socket before mentioned, through which the steam enters, is inserted. The manner of using this apparatus is simple. The article to be cooked is laid in its place on the perforated bottom of the pan, the lid is applied, and the pan is joined to one or other of the branch pipes, by its socket receiving the conical end of the pipe ; the stopcock is now turned, and the matter in the pan is subjected to the action of the steam. Each pan has a crane in front, to allow of the condensed steam being drawn off.</p><p>The remaining part of the apparatus is the hot closet, <hi rend="italic">ff.</hi> This consists of a steam-tight iron box, containing shelves, inserted in another iron box of dimensions so much greater as to allow of a considerable vacuity being between them ; into this vacuity the steam from the boiler is permitted to flow, and give out its heat to the articles placed in the closet to receive it.</p><p>Fig. 30 contains a steam-apparatus for cooking the<pb facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0691.jpf" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0610"/>
food of cattle and horses, designed by Mr Newlands of Edinburgh, <hi rend="italic">a a</hi> is a steam boiler, furnished with man hole, safety-valve, gauge-cocks, supply pipe, and regulating float ; <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> water cistern, placed not less than six feet above the boiler ; <hi rend="italic">c c,</hi> the steam pipe proceeding from the boiler, and extending along the front of the gauntree for supporting the casks or other vessels in which the food is held. These vessels are hung on pivots, between the uprights, (of which one is seen in the drawing,) in such a manner as to throw the centre of gravity a little below the points of support; and each vessel has a false bottom pierced with many holes, and fixed a few inches above the true bottom. When the contents of a vessel arc to be discharged, the superintendent lays hold of the handle, seen in the front, and, by a little force, turns the vessel round its axis, until its front lip rest on the front bar of the gauntree, which is placed so low as again to throw the centre of gravity of the vessel below the points of support ; the contents may then be emptied into a close barrow, or other suitable vessel, or into a trough extending along the front of the gauntree.</p><p>The manner of connecting the vessels with the steam</p><p>pipe remains to be noticed. From the main pipe <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> branches are carried through the front bar of the framing opposite to the centre of every vessel, of which there may be many, although two only are represented. Fig. A exhibits a section of the main pipe, the branch pipe, and a part of the bottom of the vessel. The branch pipe <hi rend="italic">d</hi> terminates in a conical socket, and into this the plug fixed on the vessel <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is fitted. When the vessel is in a vertical position, the connexion between it and the boiler is complete, but when, in being emptied, the vessel is overturned, the plug is withdrawn from the socket, and the communition cut off. When the vessel is again restored to its vertical position, the parts again fit each other without trouble or care on the part of the attendant. The branch pipe is moreover furnished with a stopcock, the handle of which is wrought by a rod from either an eccentric or a crank fixed to one of the pivots of the vessel. When the vessel is overturned and the plug withdrawn, the eccentric shuts the stopcock, and prevents the steam from escaping, and reopens it when the vessel regains its vertical position.</p></div></body></text></TEI>