<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p/></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="chi.28490924-1526168109_Page_0651.jpf" type="entry" xml:id="eb07-20-s04-0570-01" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><label>STEAM</label>
.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Τηε</hi> articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam-engine</hi> in the third edition of the present work were originally written by <hi rend="smallcaps">Dr Robison,</hi> and were long the standards of reference upon these subjects. The rapid progress of science and <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the mechanical arts during the present century, has now rendered it necessary to substitute for these articles those maturer results of recent research, to the attainment of which the original papers were themselves the means of very materially conducing. The value of these original researches was further enhanced by passing through the hands of the man of all others the most capable of appreciating their value, and the best qualified to increase it by his contributions. It was the early friend and companion of Professor Robison, Mr <hi rend="smallcaps">Watt</hi> himself, who, towards the close of his life, and notwithstanding the laborious nature of the undertaking, agreed to revise those articles for republication, so as to present them to the public with somewhat of that greater completeness which it is to be presumed their author would himself have conferred upon them, had he lived to see the investigations which he had begun, carried forward and completed. Mr Watt was, however, prevented by the weakness of increasing years from doing more than adding notes to these articles, and they were accordingly printed in that form; but they contain a most interesting chapter of the history of inventive genius, for they give us, in Watt’s own words, the history of the progress and consummation of his own noble inventions, and display the efforts of genius working its way through the obscurities of imperfect knowledge to the discovery of pure truth and the achievement of the most exquisite combinations.</p><p>While, therefore, it was impossible to retain the articles themselves, it was highly desirable that all that had rendered them valuable should be retained, and more especially such portions as serve to record the state of the mechanics and physics of steam at that time, and the pro gress of the invention ; and these, together with the notes of Mr Watt, it has been thought better to give in the precise words of the original, than to transpose them into language which could neither be more clear nor more appropriate than that with which their authors had invested them. Such portions of the articIes on steam and the steam-engine, as have been in this manner retained, are distinguished by an appropriate mark. Paragraphs from the pen of Dr Robison have a star * placed at their commencement ; those of Mr Watt, in like manner, have a cross. To all that was interesting and valuable in the original articles, an attempt has been made to superadd whatever subsequent labour and research may have brought to light. These remarks apply to the articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam-engine</hi>. <hi rend="smallcaps">Steam Navigation</hi> is entirely new.</p></div></body></text></TEI>