<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:23:12Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SEVENTH, in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> an interval called by the Greeks heptachordon.</p><p>SEVERN, a river of England, which rises near Plinlimmon Hill, in Montgomeryshire, and before it enters Shropshire receives about thirty streams, and passes down to Laudring, where it receives the Morda, that flows from Oswestrey. When it arrives at Monford, it receives the river Mon, passing on to Shrewsbury, which it almost surrounds, and then to Bridgeworth ; afterwards it runs through the skirts of Staffordshire, enters Worcestershire, and passes by Worcester ; then it runs to Tewkesbury, where it joins the Avon, and from thence to Gloucester, keeping a northwesterly course, till it falls into the Bristol Channel. It begins to be navigable for boats at Welchpool, in Montgomeryshire, and takes in several other rivers in its course, besides those already mentioned, and is the second in England. By means of inland navigation, it has communication with the rivers Mersey, Dee, Kibble, Ouse, Trent, Derwent, Humber, Thames, and Avon ; which navigation, including its windings, extends above five hundred miles in the counties of Lincoln, Nottingham, York, Lancaster, Westmoreland, Chester, Stafford, Warwick, Leicester, Oxford, and Worcester. A canal from Stroudwater, a branch of the Severn, to join the Thames, was projected and executed for the purpose of conveying a tunnel sixteen feet high and sixteen feet wide, under Sapperton Hill and Hayley Wood, for two miles and a quarter in length, through a very hard rock, which was lined and arched with brick. This stupendous undertaking was completed, and boats passed through it the 21 st of May 1789. By this opening a communication is made between the river Severn at Framiload and the Thames near Lechlade, and is continued over the Thames near Inglesham, into deep water in the Thames below St John Bridge, and so to Oxford and London, for conveyance of coals and goods.</p><p>SEVERNDROOG, a small rocky island of Hindustan, on the coast of the Concan, joined to the continent by a reef of rocks, which forms a safe bay for vessels on the south side. This place was taken by the Mahrattas from the king of Bejapore ; but his admiral revolting from their authority, it became the head-quarters of a gang of pirates. It was taken by the British in 1756. Long. 73. 13. E. Lat. 17. 47. N.</p><p>SEVERUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Cornelius,</hi> an ancient Latin poet of the Augustan age, whose <hi rend="italic">Ætna,</hi> together with a fragment <hi rend="italic">De Morte Ciceronis,</hi> were published, with notes and a prose interpretation, by Le Clerc, Amsterdam, 1703, in 12mo. They were before inserted among the <hi rend="italic">Caralecta l'irgilii, </hi>published by Scaliger, whose notes, with others, Le Clerc has received among his own.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Severus’s </hi><hi rend="italic">Wall,</hi> in British topography, the fourth and last barrier erected by the Romans against the incursions of the North Britons.</p><p>We learn from several hints in the Roman historians, that the country between the walls of Hadrian and Antoninus continued to be a scene of perpetual war and contention between the Romans and Britons, from the beginning of the reign of Commodus to the arrival of the Emperor Septimius Severus in Britain, in the year 206. This last emperor having subdued the Mæntæ, and repulsed the Caledonians, determined to erect a stronger and more impenetrable barrier than any of the former, against their future incursions.</p><p>Though neither Dio nor Herodian make any mention of a wall built by Severus in Britain for the protection of the Roman province, yet we have abundant evidence from other writers of equal authority that he really built such a wall. “ He fortified Britain,” says Spartian, “ with a wall drawn cross the island from sea to sea, which is the greatest glory of his reign. After the wall was finished, he retired to the next station (York), not only a conqueror, but the founder</p><p>of an eternal peace.” To the same purpose Aurclius Victor and Orosius, to say nothing of Eutropius and Cassiodorus : “ Having repelled the enemy in Britain, he-fortified the country, which was suited to that purpose, with a wall drawn cross the island from sea to sea.” “ Severus drew a great ditch, and built a strong wall, fortified with several turrets, from sea to sea, to protect that part of the island which he had recovered from the yet unconquered nations.” As the residence of the Emperor Severus in Britain was not quite four years, it is probable that the two last of them were employed in building this wall ; according to which account, it was begun in the year 209, and finished in the year 211.</p><p>This wall of Severus was built nearly on the same track with Hadrian’s rampart, at the distance only of a few paces north. The length of this wall, from Cousin’s House, near the mouth of the river Tyne on the east, to Boulness on the Solway Frith on the west, has been found, from two actual mensurations, to be a little more than sixty-eight English miles, and a little less than seventy-four Roman miles. To the north of the wall was a broad and deep ditch, the original dimensions of which cannot now be ascertained, only it seems to have been larger than that of Hadrian. The wall itself, which stood on the south brink of the ditch, was built of freestone ; and where the foundation was not good, it is built on piles of oak. The interstices between the two faces of this wall arc filled with broad thin stones, placed not perpendicularly, but obliquely on their edges ; and the running mortar or cement was then poured upon them, which, by its great strength and tenacity, bound the whole together, and made it firm as a rock. But though these materials are sufficiently known, it is not easy to guess where they were procured, for many parts of the wall are at a great distance from any quarry of freestone ; and though stone of another kind was within reach, yet it does not appear to have been anywhere used. The height of this wall was twelve feet besides the parapet, and its breadth eight feet, according to Bede, who lived only at a small distance from the east end of it, and in whose time it was in many places almost quite entire. Such was the wall erected by the command and under the direction of the Emperor Se verus in the north of England ; and, considering the length, breadth, height, and solidity, it was certainly a work of great magnificence and prodigious labour. But the wall itself was but a part, and not the most extraordinary part, of this work. The great number and different kinds of fortresses which were built along the line of it for its defence, and the military ways with which it was attended, are still more worthy of our admiration, and come now to be described.</p><p>The fortresses which were erected along the line of Severus’s wall for its defence were of three different kinds, and three different degrees of strength ; and were called by three different Latin words, which may be translated <hi rend="italic">stations, castles,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">turrets.</hi> Of each of these in their order.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">stationes,</hi> stations, were so called from their stability, and the stated residence of garrisons. They were also called <hi rend="italic">castra,</hi> which has been converted into <hi rend="italic">chestres,</hi> a name which many of them still bear. These were by far the largest, strongest, and most magnificent of the fortresses which were built upon the wall, and were designed for the head-quarters of the cohorts of troops which were placed there in garrison, and whence detachments were sent into the adjoining castles and turrets. These stations, as appears from the vestiges of them which arc still visible, were not all exactly of the same figure nor of the same dimensions ; some of them being exactly squares, and others oblong, and some, again, a little larger than others. These variations were no doubt occasioned by the difference of situation, and other circumstances. The stations were for- tificd with deep ditches and strong walls, the wall itself coin-</p></body></text></TEI>