<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:00Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>others, one having its termä produced by the substitution of</p><p>2,	3, &amp;c. for <hi rend="italic">v</hi> in the function —, and the other by e(υ + 1)	<hi rend="superscript">j</hi></p><p>	3</p><p>a like substitution in the function —,—. .. .—<hi rend="subscript">r</hi>-Now, c(t' + l)(u+ 2)</p><p>by our theorem, the sum of the first of these is -, and that of 	3	1	1</p><p>the second is —5- ' —5 = — -, therefore the sum of the <hi rend="italic">A	A ' .s</hi>	4</p><p>. . . 1	1 _ 1</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">proposed scries is 5 — - = -.</hi></p><p>From these examples it is sufficiently evident how the theorem is to be applied in other cases ; and it appears also, that by means of it we can sum any series whatever whose general term is of the form</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">∣ 	5.	 , </hi><hi rend="underline smallcaps">C</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"> ,</hi></p><p>t∙(l + e)^<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>^r(l+ u)(p+ l)^<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>^r(e + ∣)(e + 2)(υ +3) <hi rend="superscript">+, </hi>&amp;c.</p><p>or admits of being reduced to that form.</p><p>(16.) It deserves to be remarked, that the series</p><p>1	1 I 1	1</p><p>Î + 2+3 + 4 +5+’<hi rend="superscript">&amp;C</hi>· which is of a very simple form, and in appearance of the same nature as those we have summed, does not, however, admit of being treated in the same manner; and indeed if it be continued <hi rend="italic">cd infinitum,</hi> its sum is infinite, that is, it exceeds any number which can be assigned. The truth of this assertion will be evident if we can show that a certain definite number of its terms, beginning with any proposed term, can always be found, the sum of which shall exceed an unit, of 1 ; for this being the case, as we can go on continually in assigning such sets of terms, we can conceive as mnny to be taken as there are units in any proposed numbcr, however great ; and therefore their sum, and much more the sum of all the terms of the series, from its beginning to the end of the last sets of terms, will exceed that number. Now, that this can always be done may be proved as follows :</p><p>Let the term of the series from which we are to reckon bc^, then, if the thing he possible, and if <hi rend="italic">n</hi> be the requisite number of terms, we must have</p><p>1 <hi rend="underline">I</hi>	I		1_		l</p><p>w+α-∣-l+α-f-2 a -f- 3	+ π -∣- n— <hi rend="italic">1 '</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">Now,</hi> because</p><p><hi rend="subscript">0</hi>(<hi rend="subscript">1 +</hi> l)≈=<hi rend="subscript">0+2</hi>÷∙ √.<hi rend="subscript">+</hi>i)'=.+.<hi rend="subscript">+</hi>i<hi rend="subscript">+</hi>⅛</p><p>and in general,</p><p>α(l+l)<hi rend="superscript">i</hi>'=σ + <hi rend="subscript">p</hi> + ^=21+,ftc. therefore, <hi rend="italic">p</hi> being any whole number,</p><p><hi rend="italic">a</hi> ( 1 + -) <hi rend="superscript">,</hi> <hi rend="italic">a + ρ,</hi> and consequently</p><p><hi rend="superscript">β</hi>⅛7¾<hi rend="superscript">ι</hi></p><p>hence it follows, that the series</p><p><hi rend="superscript">,</hi> <hi rend="subscript">1</hi> <hi rend="superscript">1</hi> , <hi rend="superscript">1</hi> 1 <hi rend="italic">a + a</hi> + I + <hi rend="italic">a</hi> -(- 2 ■" + α -j- n — I</p><p>w ill be greater than the other series</p><p><hi rend="superscript">μ</hi>≠Γ≠Γ≠Γ</p><p>1</p><p>+ ∕. ∣∖<hi rend="superscript">i</hi>~<hi rend="superscript">l α</hi> (<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> + 0)</p><p>Now, this last being evidently a geometrical series, of which the common ratio is ——r its sum is</p><p>■ +-ι<hi rend="superscript">,</hi></p><p>1 4- <hi rend="superscript">1</hi> _	-!-_</p><p>' FT</p><p>therefore the sum of the series</p><p><hi rend="superscript">l</hi> I <hi rend="superscript">1	1	1	1</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">a</hi> α-f-l+α4-2 + α-}-3<hi rend="superscript">-</hi> +a-f-n — I</p><p>will always be greater than this expression ; but if we suppose <hi rend="italic">η</hi> so great that the quantity (l -(- -) is equal to or</p><p>exceeds <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> which is evidently always possible, then the above expression for the sum of the geometrical series will be equal to 1, or will exceed 1 ; therefore the same number of terms</p><p>of the series-^ + -——, -1	-—7: + —7—4-, &amp;c. will al-</p><p>α<hi rend="superscript">l</hi>α-∣-l <hi rend="superscript">1</hi> <hi rend="italic">a</hi> -{- 2 <hi rend="superscript">,</hi> <hi rend="italic">a</hi> 4- 3</p><p>ways exceed 1 ; now this is the property of the series we proposed to demonstrate.</p><p>Whcn <hi rend="italic">a =</hi> (l 4- ^)	, then <hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> = a</hi> (l -f-	; but</p><p>this quantity is greater than <hi rend="italic">a -j- n—</hi> 1, the denominator of the last term of the series</p><p>i <hi rend="subscript">+</hi> ^<hi rend="subscript">+</hi>LL<hi rend="subscript">a+</hi>-J-... <hi rend="subscript">+</hi>	I—,</p><p><hi rend="italic">a' a-j-L'a-j-2 a -j- 3 a</hi> -j- <hi rend="italic">η —</hi> 1 the sum of which, we have proved, will upon that hypothesis exceed unity ; much more then will the sum exceed unity if we suppose the series continued until the denominator of its last term be equal to or greater than a*. Hence, beginning with the term ∣, it appears that</p><p>i + ⅜ + 4_	<hi rend="superscript">,</hi>&gt;</p><p>, 1</p><p>i + i∙∙∙ +⅛τpΙ,</p><p>, 1</p><p><hi rend="subscript">9</hi>⅛+ 2V∙∙∙ + <hi rend="subscript">676</hi> = 26*^<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>-</p><p>K⅛ + 5⅛ ” ∙+ <hi rend="subscript">45832</hi>9 _ <hi rend="subscript">677</hi>.	1,</p><p>&lt;S∙∙c.</p><p>Although the sum of the series we have been considering is infinite, yet it evidently increases very slowly ; indeed it is a limit to all such as have a finite sum ; for every infinite series the terms of which decrease faster than the reciprocals of an arithmetical progression is always finite.</p><p>(17.) We have already explained what is meant by a <hi rend="italic">recurring series</hi> (2.). We shall now treat briefly, first, of their origin ; next, of the way in which they may be summed ; and, lastly, of the manner of determining the <hi rend="italic">general term</hi> of any particular series.</p><p>The series which is produced by the development of a rational algebraic fraction has always the property which constitutes the characteristic of the class called <hi rend="italic">recurring </hi>(2.) ; and, on the other hand, any series having that property being proposed, an algebraic fraction may be found, by the expansion of which the series shall be produced.</p><p>1 _L. 2 <hi rend="italic">X</hi></p><p>The fraction ——	-, for example, by dividing the</p><p>numerator by the denominator, is convertcd into the infinite series</p><p>1 ψ3χ-j-4χSψ7x<hi rend="superscript">3</hi>-p 11 <hi rend="italic">X*</hi> -f∙ 18 <hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">i</hi> -∣-, &amp;c.</p></body></text></TEI>