<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:19:55Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>arrangement of the nature of a lease ; and the result, as might be expected, has been very favourable to the interests of the public. The lights, which were formerly maintained by lessees, whose interests, in some cases, led them to adopt every saving, without regard to the efficiency of the light, are now maintained in a manner worthy of the country to which they belong. This condemnation of the manner in which the lessees of some of the lights discharged their obligations, by no means applies indiscriminately to all of them ; for there were several honourable exceptions. In 1834, the court of the corporation of Trinity House consisted of one master, four wardens, eight assistants, and eighteen elder brothers. Of these, eleven are in the honorary line of the brotherhood, and twenty-one are chosen from the merchant service. There are also younger brothers, whose number is unlimited, and who are elected by the elder brothers. The elder brothers are self-elected from the list of younger brothers. The business is managed by seven committees, who separately superintend the treasury and accounts, the examination of and granting certificates to masters in the navy and pilots, the supervision of ballastage in the Thames, the lighthouses, the collection of the dues, the pensioners and the management of the house affairs. In each of these committees a majority constitutes a quorum.</p><p>The rate of dues chargeable by the Trinity House before the passing of the last act in 1836, varied from l-6th of a penny to one penny per ton on each light passed ; and it appears from the Parliamentary Report of 1834, that in 1832, the nett amount of revenue was L.77,371, and the expense of maintaining the lights was L.36,904, leaving a surplus of L.40,467. This surplus is partly expended in the extensive charities which are distributed by the Corporation, to the annual amount of L.35,000, and partly in the erection of new lighthouses, and the maintenance of the general establishment</p><p>The public lights in England, including Heligoland, are 71 in number, and may be arranged in the following classes :—</p><p>1stt, Those belonging to, and under the management of, the corporation of the Trinity House of Deptford Strond, in number	 55 lights.</p><p>2d. Those in the charge of individuals, under lease from the Trinity House, and having different periods to run, viz. the Longships, Smalls, and Mumbles, in number	 3	„</p><p>3d, Those let by the crown to individuals for a period of years, on leases renewed since 1822, viz. Harwich, 2; Dungeness, 1; Wintertonness and Oxfordness, 3 ; and Hunstanton Cliff, 1 ; in number	 7 ,,</p><p>4th, Lights held originally under patents, subsequently sanctioned by acts of Parliament and now in the hands of proprietors, viz. the Spurn,</p><p>Tynemouth Castle and Skerries, in number		4 „</p><p>5th, One light at Heligoland	 1 „</p><p>6th, One floating light at Benbridge Lodge... 1 „</p><p>Total number of public general lights in 1 England,		71 ,,	</p><p>The lights in Scotland may be divided into public and local or harbour lights. the public lights are under the management of a board denominated “Commissioners of Northern Lights.” The Board was incorporated in 1786, by the 38th Geo. III. c. 58, and the Commissioners hold their office at the board by virtue of the public situations they fill. The Act of the 26th Geo. III. c. 101, gives authority to erect lighthouses and to collect duties.</p><p>The commissioners, twenty-five in number, are the Lord Advocate and the Solicitor-General for Scotland ; the provosts of Edinburgh, Glasgow, Aberdeen, Inverness, and</p><p>Campbeltown ; the first bailies of Edinburgh and Glasgow ; the sheriffs of the counties of Edinburgh, Lanark, Renfrew, Bute, Argyll, Inverness, Ross, Orkney, Caithness, Aberdeen, Ayr, Fife, Forfar, Wigton, Sutherland, and Kincardine, which are maritime counties or shires. The services of the commissioners are entirely gratuitous ; there are two or three general meetings annually, and the general business is conducted by committees, whose meetings take place as occasion requires. A committee of the board was appointed at the time the Bell-Rock lighthouse was erected, which has been continued ever since, and to which all general business is referred ; special committees have also been appointed for particular objects, as for accounts, stores, experiments on lenses, light-duties, visitation of lighthouses, special repairs and new works ; and there is besides a sub-committee on each lighthouse. No public lights on the Scotch coast are in the hands of private individuals ; and all the light-dues collected from the general shipping in Scotland, are received by the Commissioners of Northern Lighthouses, for public use. In the year 1641, a patent for the erection of a private light in the island of May, was ratified in the Scottish Parliament ; and this is supposed to have been the earliest sea-light on the shores of Scotland. In 1814, the Commissioners purchased the Island from the Duke of Portland tor L.60,000, and erected a new lighthouse there. There are now 25 land-lights under the charge of the Commissioners, for which light-dues are levied from the shipping generally ; and there are 28 local or harbour lights under the management of trustees and corporations, maintained by dues levied on the trade of the respective ports where the lights are situated, and on vessels resorting to them. Some of these lights are established by act of Parliament as those of Cumbrae, Clough, and Toward, under the 29th of Geo. III. c. 20. Others, as those of Leith and Dundee, are secured, by ancient charters, to the fraternities of the ports ; and others, as those of Montrose and Arbroath, were erected and are maintained, by tne ship-owners and merchants of the ports.</p><p>Before the passing of the Act 6th and 7th of William IV. there was no separate charge for each of the lights under the management of the Commissioners of the Northern Lights ; but each vessel paid a fixed sum according to the bruits within which she came. The rates were as follows :—For every British ship or decked vessel sailing within the limits of the light of the island of May, viz. between the Castle of Dunnottar on the north, and St Abb’s Head on the south, 2½d. per ton ; and for foreign vessels sailing within these limits, 5d. per ton. For every British ship or decked vessel liable to dues without these limits, 2d. per ton ; and for foreign vessels, 4d. per ton. Vessels sailing to or from any place between Holyhead and Howth Head, both inclusive, on the north, paid ¼d. per ton for each of the three lights in the Isle and Calf of Man ; and foreign ships ½d per ton ; but if they had paid the other northern duties, they were exempted from the charge for these lights. The rates were levied on the registered tonnage of all vessels passing any of the lighthouses, whether loaded or in ballast outwards or homewards bound, on a foreign voyage, or sailing coastways ; and it appears from the Parliamentary Report of 1834, that the revenue of the Commissioners was L.36,283. Since the passing of the act 6th and 7th of William IV. cap. 79, in 1836, however, the rates of the duties, and the mode of levying them, have been completely altered, and in some degree assimilated to the system pursued by the Trinity House, so that a certain duty is now paid for every light that is passed.</p><p>The lights of Ireland have had frequent changes in regard to superintendance, and they were finally placed under “ The Corporation for Preserving and Improving the Port of Dublin,” by the act 50th Geo. III. c. 35. The powers of the corporation, which is generally named the Ballast Board, have received various alterations by subse-</p></body></text></TEI>