<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:24:35Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>taken to resist the enemy, who had attacked the English at sea with their barges, galleys, and other vessels. In 1405 Henry IV. directed his council to apply to the king of Portugal to lend him his galleys to assist the English navy against the French.”</p><p>In Sir Grenville Temple’s Travels in Greece and Turkey, we find the following description of a Maltese galley, or, more correctly, galleas, made from an old model preserved there. “ These galleys measured a hundred and sixty-nine feet one inch in length, and thirty-nine feet six inches in breadth. They had three masts with latine sails, and were propelled by forty-nine oars, each forty-four feet five inches long. Their armament consisted of one thirty- six pounder, two of twenty-four, and four of six, all on the forecastle, which in those days had in reality some appearance of a castle. On each side of the vessel, aft of the forecastle, were four six-pounders.” The total crew, including galley-slaves, consisted of 549 persons.</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Galleas</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Galleon</hi> appear to have been successive improvements on the original galley, rendered necessary by the introduction of cannon into naval warfare. The artillery introduced on board the early galleys was placed either before or abaft the rowers, and to fire in the direction of the length. (Plate CCCCXLVII.) In the galleas, a description of vessel first used at the battle of Lepanto, guns were also placed between the rowers, to fire from the broadside. Evelyn describes the galleasses he saw at Venice (1645) as being “ vessels to rowe of almost 150 foote long and thirty wide, not counting prow or poop, and contain twenty-eight banks of oares, each seven men, and to carry 1300 men, with three masts.” In the galleon the oars ceased to be the principal means of propulsion, and if used at all, were only so as occasional aids. The galley and galleas had overhanging topsides for the accommodation of the oars. In the galleon, on the contrary, the topsides “ tumbled home” to so extraordinary an extent, that the breadth at the water was twice that at the topside, a fashion which has continued, but in a much less degree, to the present time. Plate CCCCXLVIII.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Spynes</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Spynaces, “</hi> now called pinnaces, seem to have been large boats, capable of holding twenty-five men, and were probably used for swiftness. To these must be added crayers, hulks, gabarres or gabbars, a kind of flat- bottomed boat used in shallow' rivers.” The French still continue to apply the term “ gabarre” to store-ships.</p><p>“ Playtes, cogships, whence perhaps cogs and coggles are derived ; farecrofts, passagers, which were perhaps boats used between England and France ; and cock-boats, a small boat which attended upon all kinds of ships. The whole of these vessels were employed in conveying goods or passengers, and most of them on rivers or in the coasting trade. The ships, carracks, barges, balingers, and galleys, were employed equally for commerce or for war. When sent against the enemy, soldiers were put on board of them ; and it is most likely they were at all times partly manned by soldiers. In foreign voyages they usually sailed in convoys ; and it was a very ancient custom for the masters and sailors to elect their own admiral.”</p><p>In Burchett’s account of the unfortunate action in the Bay of Conquet in 1513, in which the Lord High Admiral, Sir Edward Howard, lost his life, four <hi rend="italic">Joists</hi> are mentioned as forming a part of the French force. They were probably vessels of a similar character with the galley, but smaller in size. About the beginning of the seventeenth century, “ carracks,” “ galleons,” and “ tail shippes” appear to have become synonymous terms. Plate CCCCXLVIH.</p><p>The term hulk originally was applied in a different sense from that which is stated in the part of the foregoing remarks which we have quoted from the preface to the proceedings of the privy council. Frequent allusion is made to hulks in documents of the fifteenth and sixteenth</p><p>centuries. In a letter from Sir Thomas Seymour to the privy council, dated the 13th of November 1544, when in command of the “ shipes whyche was a poyntede to kepe the Narrow Sees,” vindicating himself for putting back on account of a storm, there is the following passage, from which we might almost infer that hulk was a general name synonymous with ships. “ Thre holkes that come after me colde nott gett syght thereof (the ‘ Eylle of Wyght),’ tyll they warre in a hay on the est syde of the Eylle, of the whyche Mr Strowd, Bramston, and Battersebe of the garde, God rest their sowles, was in on of them, whyche holke brake all her ankeres and cabelles, and she brake all to peses on the shorr, and but 41 of 300 saved a lyve. The other two rode out the storme, whyche lasted all that nyght and the next day. My brother (Sir Hy Seymour) and John Roberds of the garde, tryde the sees all the fiιrst nyght, and the next day cam into Dartemouth haven, wharre my brothers holke strake on a roke and brest all to peses ; but God be praysede, all the men warre savede, savying thre ; and a nother new holke that tryde the sees that nyght brake thre of her bernes, and with moche ado came into the Wyght.”</p><p>Again, in a letter from Lord Viscount Lisle, Baron Malpas, the Lord High Admiral of England, to Henry VIII., we have an announcement, that “ their is cum into the Downes 30 sayle of hulkses, whereof sum be tall shipes.” And again, in a letter from the same to the Lord Chamber- lain, Lord St John, he speaks of having detained “ 3 grate hulkes bound, as they say, for Lusshbome, the leste of y<hi rend="superscript">m </hi>500 tunnes.” And again, from the same to the same, he speaks of his former letter and the “ goodly hulkes,” and says, “ sithens that tyme I have stayed other too, which in beautye and well appoynting are beyond the others. That 1 have last stayed ys a shipe of 600 at the least, and hath 5 toppes, and she ys of the town of Dansick, and ladon in Flanders for Lusshbourne.”</p><p>The importance of the mercantile shipping of England during the fifteenth century must have been considerable. About the middle of it flourished the celebrated William Canynge, a merchant of Bristol, who built the church of St Mary’s, Redcliff, in that city, in which church he was buried in 1474. This man appears to have been much in advance of the rude times in which he lived. His mercantile transactions were on so extensive a scale, and carried on in vessels of such large size, that they must have had an important influence in improving the navies of the period. It is therefore not only as a fact of much historical interest, but as one which is intimately connected with and most probably materially affecting our subject, that we shall dwell on the information which has descended to us respecting him. He was a great patron of the arts, a friend and protector of genius, and eminent for bis virtue and piety. From an inscription upon his tomb, a tradition has become current, that Edward IV. took 2470 tons of shipping from him, he having “ forfeited the king’s peace ;” and for the obtaining of which again, it is stated that Edward accepted these ships instead of a fine of 3000 marks. The Itinerary of William of Worcester, preserved in the library of Bennett College, Cambridge, gives the names of Canynge’s vessels, among which are the Mary and John of 900 tons, Mary Redcliff of 500 tons, and Mary Canynge of 400 tons. The same authority gives the names and tonnage of other large ships belonging to Bristol merchants, among which are the John, of 511 tons, and the Mary Grace, of 300 tons. If there be any truth in the tradition of the confiscation of the shipping, it is probable that the inscription on the tomb may refer to some act of Canynge’s in favour of the house of Lancaster, as he appears to have enjoyed the favourable opinion of Henry VI. Another account, which, it is said, is authenticated by the original instrument in the Exchequer, states that this Canynge assisted Edward IV. with a loan, and received in return a license to have 2470 tons of shipping free</p></body></text></TEI>