<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:40Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>extremely gentle in its manners, and docs not attempt to bite even when seized in its native haunts. It is very common in the fields near Tivoli, but is usually found on hillsides. There is a passage in Pliny@@* which relates that the Boas of Italy sometimes attain to so great a size that the entire body of an infant was found in the interior of one slain during the reign of the Emperor Claudius. The species just noticed is certainly the largest of all the Roman serpents, but its natural attributes in no way favour the reception of this preposterous story.@@* The largest species of the genus is <hi rend="italic">coluber corais</hi> of Surinam. There are twenty- seven different kinds described by M. Schlegel.</p><p>Genus <hi rend="smallcaps">Hebpktodryas.</hi> This genus was established by the late M. Boié for the reception of certain species of Coluber (<hi rend="italic">Col. carinatus,</hi> &amp;c.), which combine the aspect and physiognomy of the preceding genus (to which they are closely allied) with the lengthened form and much of the habits of the arboreal serpents. Their colours are usually of a uniform greenish hue, sometimes passing into brown, or occasionally longitudinally rayed. The tail is generally long and slender, a character which, combined with the narrow and very angular abdomen, announces their arboreal disposition. Their manners are wild and distrustful, and they inhabit the warmer regions of both the Old and New World, with the exceptions, so far as yet known, of Africa and New Holland. We shall here name only <hi rend="italic">Herp. carinatus,</hi> a Brazilian species, also common in Surinam. It is remarkable for having two central rows of dorsal scales, so that the total number of rows forms an <hi rend="italic">equal</hi> number, a character unique in the Ophidian order. It varios greatly in its external markings.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi></p><p>Genus <hi rend="smallcaps">PsammopHIS.</hi> This little group may also be regarded as a dismemberment from Coluber, and brings us into still closer contact with the genuine tree-serpents. They offer an anomaly in their dentition, in as far as their posterior teeth, and those of the centre, are usually longer than the others, and furrowed. The head is elongated, the vertical plate very narrow. Some have the body thin and long drawn out, while others are more compact like Coluber. The species occur in India, Africa, and America ; and <hi rend="italic">Psam. lacertina</hi> is an European example well known in Dalmatia.@@<hi rend="superscript">4 </hi>They all prefer sandy soils, and prey chiefly upon Saurian reptiles. Green and brown are the prevailing colours, although several arc longitudinally rayed, or have the head adorned by linear figures.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Family IV.—Arboreal or Tree-Serpents.</hi></p><p>The members of this family are characteristic of the great forests of the tropical countries of Asia and America. They are rare in Africa, still more so in New Holland, and Europe produces only a few anomalous species. Their form is in general extremely elongated, they pass the greater portion of their time in trees and bushes, and prey both on birds and lizards.</p><p>Genus <hi rend="smallcaps">Dendrophis.</hi> Body compressed ; abdomen (and sometimes the tail) angular, and furnished with very broad plates ; scales narrow and elongated. Tail very slender. Head lengthened. Eye large, the pupil orbicular. See Plate CCCCXLIII. fig. 5.</p><p>These reptiles inhabit both the western and eastern world, but are rare in New Holland, and unknown in Europe. They climb trees with great facility, and are extremely quick in their general movements. They are frequently adorned by lively colours. Nearly a dozen species are known to naturalists.</p><p>Genus <hi rend="smallcaps">Dryophis.</hi> Muzzle slender and projecting. General form greatly elongated, the body compressed, the abdomen convex. Eye of moderate size.</p><p>The species of this genus are among the most remarkable of the innocuous serpents, their shape being so extraordinarily lengthened out, that many measure nearly five feet in length, and are yet no thicker than the little finger. Hence their Anglo-American name of coach-whip snakes, of one of which, first described by Catesby, it was absurdly believed by the Indians, “ that it will by a jerk of its tail separate a man in two parts.”@@<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> The tail, of extreme slenderness, always measures half the length of the whole body ; and the muzzle is often drawn out in the form of a pointed proboscis. These reptiles inhabit the torrid zone, or the countries near the tropics, in Asia and the two Americas. Although unknown in the continent of Africa, a species (<hi rend="italic">D</hi>. <hi rend="italic">langaha)</hi> occurs in Madagascar. The genus admits of a geographical division,—those of the ancient continent being characterized by grooved maxillary teeth, and the pupil of the eye elongated horizontally, while such as inhabit America have the teeth less developed, and the pupil orbicular. We may briefly notice <hi rend="italic">Dryophis nasuta</hi> (the <hi rend="italic">Passeriki</hi> of Russel),@@<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> a remarkable species, of a beautiful grass-green colour above, the lower surface paler, and marbled with red. A white or yellow ray extends from behind the eye to the commissure of the lips, and another very distinct one passes along each side of the abdomen and tail. The muzzle is very sharp, and is terminated by a moveable fleshy appendage (See Plate CCCCXLIII. figs. 7 and 9.) This kind occurs over a great extent of India and the great eastern islands, and is frequent in the environs of Vizagapatam. It lives in trees, and its manners are described as being even ferocious. Its bite, however, is attended by no other bad consequences than the pain of the wound ; but the common people deem it dangerous, as directing its attacks chiefly at the eyes of the passers by. There is an Indian whip-snake (probably not of this genus) common in the Concan, where it is described as concealing itself among the foliage of trees, from which it darts at cattle grazing below, generally also aiming at the eye. A bull which was thus wounded at Dazagon tore up the ground with extreme fury, and died in half an hour, foaming at the mouth. This habit of the reptile is truly singular,—for it seems to proceed neither from resentment nor from fear, nor yet from the impulse of appetite, but seems, “ more than any other known fact in natural history, to partake of that frightful and mysterious principle of evil, which tempts our own species so often to tyrannize for mere wantonness of power.”@@?</p><p>The species already named as a native of Madagascar, <hi rend="italic">Dryophis langaha,</hi> Schlegel, partakes of those anomalous attributes which characterize so many animal products of that extraordinary island. It measures between two and three feet in length, and is of a beautiful reddish-brown colour above, the under surface being of a deep though lively yellow, spotted with brown, especially beneath the tail; but its most peculiar character is seen in the muzzle, which is prolonged into a fleshy appendage of half an inch in length, covered with small scales, and of variable form, being in some cases sharp-pointed, in others compressed and enlarged, or leaf-shaped. This curious reptile seems to have been first (we believe inaccurately) described by M. Bruguières,@@<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> and has since been banded about through various genera.@@® It is classed by M. Schlegel (we presume after due examination),@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> among the innocuous, that is, the non-venomous kinds,—although the natives of Madagascar</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Lib. viii. c. 14.		</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@,</hi> <hi rend="italic">Quadrupèdes Oripares,</hi> ii. 163, pl. 7, fig. 1.		</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> Wagler, <hi rend="italic">Seep. Bros.</hi> pl. 7 and 12.	</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@4</hi> Fleischman, Aor. Gen. ph 2.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@5</hi><hi rend="italic"> Carolina,</hi> ii. plate 54.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@β</hi><hi rend="italic"> Indian Serpents,</hi> plate 12 and 13.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@7</hi><hi rend="italic"> Quarterly Beriete,</hi> xii. 183.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@s</hi><hi rend="italic"> Journal de Physique,</hi> xxiv. 132, plate 2.</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@’ Langaha Madagascariensis,</hi> Lacép. <hi rend="italic">Quad. Ovip.</hi> ii. 499:—<hi rend="italic">Langaya nasuta,</hi> Shaw, <hi rend="italic">Gen. Zool.</hi> iii. 571, plate 127 :—<hi rend="italic">Amphisbæna langaha. </hi>Schneid. <hi rend="italic">Hist. Amphib.</hi> ii. 151.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@10</hi> <hi rend="italic">Physiognomie des Serpents,</hi> ii. 148.</p></body></text></TEI>