<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:36Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>beautiful <hi rend="italic">coluber melanurus</hi> inhabits Java, Sumatra, and the Celebes ; but the individuals from the last-named locality have the nape of the neck constantly adorned by an angular black mark. <hi rend="italic">Herpetodrgas oxyeephalus</hi> is of a beautiful grass-green colour in Java; but this pure tint becomes embrowned in Borneo, and in Celebes appears almost black upon the dorsal region. <hi rend="italic">Dendrophis picta</hi> inhabits almost all the intertropical countries of the Old World, from Senegal to New Guinea, but varies considerably at distant points of such a vast and surprising distribution. <hi rend="italic">Dryophis nasuta</hi> of Bengal and the Mariannas has in Java the abdomen rayed with yellow. <hi rend="italic">Dryophis prasina,</hi> common in the isles of Sunda, exhibits a local variety in the Celebes; and <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus quincunciαtus,</hi> a species widely spread through India, has in Java the spots confluent, so that the dorsal portion seems rayed with black. <hi rend="italic">Trop. chrysargos</hi> of Sumatra bears a different aspect from that species in the Celebes, while both vary from the individuals found in Java. <hi rend="italic">Homalopsis Schneiden,</hi> which is spread from India to New Guinea, exhibits several varieties in different regions. The great <hi rend="italic">Python bivittatus</hi> occurs in China, the isles of Sunda, both the Indian peninsulas, and Ceylon, and is, moreover, distributed across Africa as far as Senegambia. In this vast extent of territory it exhibits some considerable variations, which, when the extreme differences merely are regarded, and the intermediate links kept out of view, have caused it to be described, in its different aspects, as distinct species, all however referable, in Mr Schlegel’s opinion, to one and the same. <hi rend="italic">Elaps fureatus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bivirgatus</hi> exhibit a different distribution of colours in Sumatra from what they do in Java ; but it may be stated as a general fact, that almost all the known serpents of the former island have been found also in the latter. Indeed a considerable number of these insular Ophidians occur likewise both in Hindustan and Bengal.</p><p>It is a singular circumstance, that the two most remarkable species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Trigonocephalus (Trig, puniceus </hi>and <hi rend="italic">rhodostoma)</hi> have hitherto been observed only in Java ; while <hi rend="italic">Trig, viridis,</hi> so common in India, Bengal, Sumatra, and Timor, does not occur in the first-named island. The genus <hi rend="italic">Bungarus,</hi> on the other hand, which inhabits Ceylon, Hindustan, and Bengal, does not occur in any other of the great eastern islands, except Java. In the Celebes we find many peculiar forms of animal life, combined with others well known elsewhere. Among the serpents we find there a beautiful species of <hi rend="italic">Herpetodryas (Herp. dipsas),</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dipsas irregularis,</hi> which also occurs in Amboyna. Several species are absolutely the same as those of Java and Sumatra, although a few form permanent local varieties, which exhibit some slight disparities of colour. Such are <hi rend="italic">Tortrix rufa, coluber melanurus, Herpetodryas oxycephalus, Dryophis prasina, Dipsas dendrophilus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus chry- sargus.</hi> Of the Moluccas our knowledge is extremely slight, being confined chiefly to the island of Amboyna. We there find three or four serpents, likewise known as Javanese species ; but it does not appear that the isles of Sunda produce <hi rend="italic">Lycodon modestus, Boa carinata, Dendrophis rhodopleuron,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Python amethystinus.</hi> Timor is in some measure intermediate in its productions between Java and the Moluccas. Its <hi rend="italic">Python</hi> is perhaps different from that of Amboyna, and it produces a singular <hi rend="italic">Homalopsis (H. leu- cobalia). Lycodon hebe</hi> is there of a deeper tint than in Java ; and <hi rend="italic">coluber radiatus</hi> is represented in Timor by <hi rend="italic">col. subradiatus,</hi>—a species analogous, but not the same. New Guinea and the adjacent islands produce several new species. We know little of the reptiles of the Philippines, though a few have been collected in the environs of Manilla, in the island of Luçon ; and these clearly establish the curious fact, that the species of that island bear a strong analogy to those of Ceylon,—not a few being identical. The <hi rend="italic">Noja</hi> of the Philippines belongs to the ordinary variety</p><p>of <hi rend="italic">N. tripudians,</hi> as it occurs in India, and which always differs in some measure from the same species from the isles of Sunda.</p><p>The vast insular continent of New Holland is as yet but slightly known, most of its ascertained productions having been sent only from a few limited localities; but the anomalous and extraordinary character of its productions may even now be fairly inferred. The snakes seem peculiar, and almost all belong to the venomous division. No water species have as yet been seen there. It has already been observed, that the innumerable islands of the great Pacific Ocean are believed to be unproductive of serpents. The Mariannas, however, form an exception to this general rule, and Dampier mentions green serpents as inhabitants of the Gallipagos.</p><p>A few brief notices of the serpents of the New World may terminate the geographical department of our subject. On comparing the species of the two great continents of America with each other, we observe some interesting parallels. The rattle-snake, <hi rend="italic">Crolalus horridus,</hi> so common over a large extent of South America, is represented in the northern territories by <hi rend="italic">Crot. durissus,</hi> as is <hi rend="italic">Coronella venustissima</hi> by <hi rend="italic">cor. coccinea.</hi> This kind of comparison, however, applies but to a few species, for the majority of kinds produced by one of the continents differ from those of the other. Thus, the genera <hi rend="italic">Tortrix, Dipsas, Dendrophis, Boa,</hi> have as yet been found only in South America, or as far north as the Antilles, while <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus,</hi> on the contrary, is not found in the southern continent, though frequent in the northern, from which it likewise extends to parts of the West Indies. A small number, however, of southern species are found also in North America, such as <hi rend="italic">Calamaria melanocephala, Lycodon clelia, Coronella cobella, Herpetodryas cursor, IIry- ophis Catesbyi, Elaps corallinus, Homalopsis carinicauda ; </hi>while in like manner <hi rend="italic">Heterodon platyrhinus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Herpetodryas œstivus,</hi> which may be regarded rather as northern species, have been ascertained to inhabit Brazil. The following species of North American reptiles also inhabit the Antilles ; <hi rend="italic">calamaria striatula, Coronella coccinea, Hetero- dan platyrhinus, coluber constrictor, Herpetodryas œstivus </hi>and <hi rend="italic">cursor, Tropidonotus bipunciatus, fasciatus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">saurita.</hi> Those next named also occur in the Antilles, although their proper country is South America ; <hi rend="italic">calamaria me- lanocephala, Coronella reginæ, Lycodon clelia, Dendrophys liocercus, Dryophis Catesbyi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">aurata, Dipsas annulata, Homalopsis angulata, Boa constrictor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cenchria,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Elaps corallinus.</hi> The species peculiar to these West Indian islands are very few in number, the most characteristic being <hi rend="italic">Psammophis Antillensis, Trigonocephalus lanceo- latus, Dendrophis catesbyi,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Boa melanura.</hi> On comparing the snakes of Guiana with those of Brazil, we find many species common to both countries, several, however, forming local varieties more or less distinct, as in the cases of <hi rend="italic">Herpetodryas linearus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Olfersii, coluber poëcilοstοma, &amp;c.</hi> Certain species are peculiar to one or other of the countries above named,—for example, <hi rend="italic">Calamaria badia, Xenodon typhlus, coluber corais, Herpetodryas Boddaertii, Dendrophis aurata, Dryophis catesbyi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">argentea, Homalopsis plicatilis, Elaps lemniscatus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Surinamensis,</hi> &amp;c. have never been seen except in Guiana ; while <hi rend="italic">calamaria Blumii, Coronella Merτemii, Xenodon Scholrii</hi> and <hi rend="italic">rhinos- torna, Lycodon formosus, Herpetodryas serra, Homalopsis carinicauda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mardi,</hi> are found only in Brazil. Other species, again, appear as it were to represent each other in these parts of South America, so that we may place in parallel, <hi rend="italic">Coronella venustissima, Dipsas Mikani, Wegeli, leucοcephala,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Nattereri,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Trigonocephalus Jararaca, </hi>of Brazil, with <hi rend="italic">Coronella venusta, Dipsas nebulata, catesbyi, macrorhina, ρunctatissima,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Trigonocephalus atrox</hi> of Guiana. The other parts of South America are too little known to admit of any detailed comparison ; but it</p></body></text></TEI>