<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:14Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>ther as belonging to his separate class <hi rend="smallcaps">Αμρηιβιλ,</hi> which,
                after the example of Blainville and Latreille, he constitutes by means of the entire
                Batrachian order.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> Thus also <hi rend="italic">Lacerta
                    apoda</hi> of Pallas, though furnished on each side with a small bone analogous
                to the femur, and pertaining to an actual pelvis concealed beneath the skin, is yet
                classed by the great French anatomist with the Ophidians, being, so to say, the “
                very head and front of their offending ;”@@<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> while
                several systematic writers range our <hi rend="italic">Anguis fragilis,</hi> and
                other snakes commonly so called, among the lizards. An American reptile, <hi
                    rend="italic">Anguis ventralis</hi> of Linn., now forms Daudin’s genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Ophisaurus,</hi> the name of which (derived from ὄφις<hi
                    rend="italic">, serpent,</hi> and σαυϑoς, <hi rend="italic">lizard)</hi> implies
                the peculiar combination now referred to. The Saurian genus <hi rend="italic">Seps,
                </hi>described at the conclusion of our former treatise, is characterized by Cuvier
                as having an elongated body, “ tout- à-fait semblable à celui d’un orvet’’ (<hi
                    rend="italic">Anguis)</hi> ; and, on the other hand, the same author enters upon
                his Ophidian order by means of the <hi rend="italic">Anguidæ,</hi> or slow-worms,
                which he simply describes as “ des seps sans pieds.” These, and other examples which
                it would be easy to adduce, demonstrate the close connection which subsists between
                the Saurian and Ophidian orders.</p>
            <p>It has indeed been customary to class among serpents whatever reptiles combined the
                absence of limbs with an extremely lengthened form of body ; but a more rigorous
                observation will demonstrate that several species which, in accordance with that
                principle, will take their place as serpents, are yet in their prevailing organic
                structure removed from them in most essential points, the chief resemblance being
                that of the external and extremely lengthened form. Now this attenuated aspect, and
                absence of all the ordinary locomotive members, are likewise exhibited by several
                Saurian reptiles, and of course in an increased degree as they actually approach the
                serpent or Ophidian tribes ; but the two characters just mentioned do not convert
                them from one order to another, being still held, as it were, in subordination to
                the general structure.@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi></p>
            <p>We bring forward these observations at present, chiefly that the reader may
                understand why we commence our treatise on serpents by <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                brief sketch of several species which in truth we can scarcely regard as serpents at
                all, however raised “ to that bad eminence” by many noted writers. We might have
                placed them at the termination of the Saurian order of our former article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Reptilia</hi> ; but the fact being that we did not do so, we
                feel it incumbent on us, before proceeding to the serpents properly so called, to
                present a short notice of their names and nature. In doing this we shall follow for
                a space the arrangement of Baron Cuvier, presuming that the reader will now
                understand our views regarding the doubtful nature of all those genera which precede
                the true serpents, of the advent of which due notice will be given.</p>
            <p>The French anatomist defines serpents as,—reptiles without feet, which advance by
                means of sinuous movements of</p>
            <p>the body. He divides them into three great groups,—the Anguidæ or slow-worms,—the
                true serpents (subdivided into, 1st, double movers, <hi rend="italic">i</hi>. <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi>. the genera <hi rend="italic">Amphisbæna</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Typhlοps ;</hi> 2dly, serpents properly so called, containing all
                the actually Ophidian species),—and the naked serpents, composed of the single genus
                    <hi rend="italic">Cacilia.</hi></p>
            <p>We commence, then, with the</p>
            <p>ANGUIDÆ, OR SLOW-WORMS.</p>
            <p>These still exhibit the bony head, the teeth, the tongue of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Seps,</hi> and the eye is furnished with three eyelids. They correspond to the
                ancient unrestricted genus <hi rend="smallcaps">Anguis</hi> of Linnæus, and are
                characterized externally by imbricated scales covering the whole body. The species
                now form four minor genera, of which the first three still exhibit beneath the skin
                certain small bones corresponding to those of the shoulder and pelvis.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Genus Pseudopus,</hi> Merrem. Tympanum visible externally. A
                prominence on each side of the anus, containing a small bone analogous to the femur,
                and appertaining to a true pelvis hid beneath the skin. Rudiments of the anterior
                extremities barely manifested by an inconspicuous fold, containing no interior
                humerus. One of the lungs is a quarter less than the other. The scales are thick and
                imbricated, and between those of the back and belly are some smaller scales, which
                produce a longitudinal furrow on either side.</p>
            <p>Of the species, the earliest known is <hi rend="italic">P. Pallasii,</hi> Cuv,, <hi
                    rend="italic">Laceτta apοda,</hi> Pallas,—discovered in the south of Russia by
                the naturalist last named.@@* It measures from one to two feet in length, and the
                colours are ferruginous above, pale yellow beneath. The scales of the back are
                smooth, those of the tail carinated. This species occurs also in Hungary and
                Dalmatia, and the specimen figured by Dr Shaw@@<hi rend="superscript">s</hi> was
                procured in Greece by Dr John Sibthorpe, the professor of botany in the university
                of Oxford. M. Dur- ville discovered another species (which bears his name) in the
                    Archipelago.@@<hi rend="superscript">8</hi> See Plate CCCCXLIII. fig. 1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Genus Ophisaurus,</hi> Daudin. No external appearance even of
                the hinder extremities, but the tympanum is still apparent, and the scales exhibit a
                plication or folding upon each side of the trunk. The smaller lung only equals a
                third of the greater.@@<hi rend="superscript">7</hi></p>
            <p>The best known species is <hi rend="italic">Oph. ventralis,—Anguis ventralis,</hi>
                Linn.,—an American reptile, common in the southern states of the union. It is of a
                greenish yellow, spotted above with black. Its tail is longer than its body, and the
                creature itself is so brittle and easily broken, even in the living state, as to be
                known by the name of glass serpent. According to Catesby, “ a small blow of a stick
                causes the body to separate, not only at the place struck, but at two or three other
                places, the muscles being articulated quite through the vertebrae.”@@·</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@1</hi><hi rend="italic"> Encyclopedia of Anatomy and
                    Physiology,</hi> part i. p. 91. These amphibian orders are as follows : 1st, <hi
                    rend="italic">Anιpl∣ipneurta,</hi> containing the Sirens and Proteans; 2d, <hi
                    rend="italic">Anoura,</hi> the frogs and toads ; 3d, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Urodela,</hi> tbe salamanders; 4th, <hi rend="italic">Abranchia,</hi> the
                genera Menopoma and Ampbiuma; and, 5th, <hi rend="italic">Apoda,</hi> the genus
                Crecilia. “ It is easy,” adds Mr Swainson, “ to perceive that this last passes into
                the first by means of the dipod Sirens, and thus the whole form a circular group
                more or less perfect in its connecting links.” (<hi rend="italic">Cabinet
                    Cydopœdia,</hi> vol. cxvi. p. 86.)</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@s</hi> See <hi rend="italic">Règne Animat,</hi> ii. 69.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@s</hi> “ Lin examen comparatif,” observes M. Schlegel, “
                des objets m’a démontré que ces Sauriens anomaux, c’est-à-dire, à formes alongées et
                à extrémités rudimentaires, appartiennent toujours par l’ensemble de leur
                organisation à quelque espèce de l’une ou l’autre des familles de cet ordre, parmi
                lesquelles ils doivent être distribués. On ne peut nier, par exemple, qu’il y a un
                passage graduel des Scinques à l’Anguis et aux Acontias, par l'intermède des
                Scinques brachypus, decreensis, serpens, seps, du Pygodactyle et du Bipes,—êtres
                moins différons entre eux par leur organisation que par leurs formes, et qui ne
                composent qu’une seule famille, celle des Scincoïdes, de laquelle on ne saurait
                exclure ui les Ablephares ni les Gymnophthalmes. Le mime passage graduel existe dans
                la famille des Lézards, des genres Lacerta et Tachydromus au Monodactyle ; on y peut
                ajouter comme espèce anomale le Pygopus. On pourrait rapprocher dans la méthode le
                Tetradactyle, le Chalcis, le Pseudopus, et l’Ophisaurus. Viennent enfin la famille
                des Amphisbènes,—Chirotes, Leposternon, Amphisbaena, et celle des
                Typhlops,—Typhlops, Rhinophis, Uropeltis.” <hi rend="italic">{Physiognomie des
                    Serpens,</hi> i. p. 2.)</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@• Non. Com. Petrop.</hi> zïx. plate 9, fig. 1. </p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@* General Zoology,</hi> iii. plate 86. </p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> Griffith’s <hi rend="italic">Animat Kingdom,</hi>
                ix. 307.</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@j</hi> Of the cranium of this genus, Cuvier has remarked, “
                C’est une vraie tête de Saurien.” <hi rend="italic">Règne Animal,</hi> iii. 430.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@• Curotina,</hi> ii. plate 59.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
