<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:20:51Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Old Testament, the gospel history, the Acts of the Apostles, and one or more of the doctrinal epistles ; and who also gives a view of the divine dispensations, as these are detailed in the Holy Scriptures. The course of the present professor embraces a critical exposition of the principal prophecies of the Messiah, the doctrines of Jesus Christ, and the Epistles to the Romans, Galatians, and Hebrews. 3. The professor of systematic theology. 4. The professor of pastoral theology and ecclesiastical history, whose duty it is to explain the qualifications of the ministerial character, and the duties of the pastoral office ; and to give instruction in all the services which, as teachers or rulers in the church, ministers are called upon to perform, such as conducting the public devotions of the church, the composition and delivery of pulpit discourses, ministerial visitation of families, public catechising, visitation of the sick, the government and discipline of the church, giving also an abstract of ecclesiastical history. The term of study is five years, and the duration of the annual session two months ; and it is rendered imperative on students to attend the whole time. They are usually from five to six hours a day in the classroom. For the first and second sessions of their attendance at the hall, they are committed to the care of the professor of biblical literature and exegetical theology, and the professors of systematic and pastoral theology during the last three years of their course. During the vacation the students are under the superintendence of their respective presbyteries, who meet and converse with them as to their progress in their studies, and hear and criticise their trial discourses. The examinations and exercises prescribed on trials for license and ordination are much the same as in the Established Church.</p><p>The Secession has produced a respectable proportion of authors distinguished in various departments of literary pursuit. To say nothing of living authors, the works of Dr Jamieson, the profound and ingenious author of the Scottish Dictionary, and of several learned defences of some of the fundamental principles of religion, entitle him to a place among the distinguished men of his age and country ; and the writings of the founders of the Secession, and of Law- son, Dick, Belfrage, Pollock, and others, are well known and highly esteemed in religious and literary circles.</p><p>The United Associate Synod now comprehends twenty- two presbyteries, composed of 361 congregations, exclusive of missionary stations both at home and abroad. The following statement will show the regular and steady progress which it has made during the period of one hundred and six years which has elapsed since its origin.</p><p>“ When the Associate Presbytery was first constituted by the fathers of the Secession, on the 6th of December 1733, the number of the brethren who took this important step amounted only to <hi rend="italic">four.</hi></p><p>“ When the General Assembly pronounced sentence of deposition on the members of the Associate Presbytery on the l5th of May 1740, their number had increased to <hi rend="italic">eight.</hi></p><p>“ Five years after this, when the Associate Presbytery constituted itself into a synod, on the first Tuesday of March 1745, the number of ministers amounted to <hi rend="italic">twenty-six.</hi></p><p>“ When the division occasioned by the burgess oath controversy took place, on the 9th of April 1747, the number had increased to <hi rend="italic">thirty-two.</hi></p><p>“ When the re-union was accomplished, on the 5th of September 1820, the number of ministers belonging to the two synods that were united on that occasion amounted to <hi rend="italic">two hundred and sixty-two.</hi></p><p>“ Since that event took place a period of nineteen years has elapsed, and the number of ordained ministers who are members of the United Associate Synod amounts at the</p><p>present period to <hi rend="italic">three hundred and fifty-seven,</hi> being an in crease, since the re-union, of nearly <hi rend="italic">one hundred</hi> ministers.”</p><p>From accurate returns made by the different congregations, it has been ascertained that the population connected with the Secession Church, including young and old, amounts to 261,345 ; the number of communicants is 126,070; the sabbath-schools and classes, 716; the number of scholars, 37,612. The average number of persons connected with each congregation is 730, the average number of communicants is 349. The stipends of the ministers vary from L.70 to L.450. The average paid to each minister, exclusive of sacramental expenses, is L.131. In the country, in addition to the stipend, the minister is generally furnished with a dwelling-house. None of the ministers have or ever had a legal bond securing their incomes.</p><p>Annual amount of stipends in Secession Church..L.47, 315</p><p>Annual allowance for the poor..,	 4,011</p><p>Collected for missions by congregational associations 11,042</p><p>Annual allowance for sacramental expenses	 3,610</p><p>Annual collection for synod fund	 760</p><p>Total amount collected annually by the Secession</p><p>Church	66,728@@'</p><p>A considerable number of missionaries and catechists are maintained in Canada, Jamaica, and other places, either by the synod or by individual congregations in connection with the Secession Church ; and many congregations, particularly in the larger towns, support one or more local missionaries at their own expense.</p><p>The Presbyterian Synod of Ireland in connection with the United Associate Synod comprehends nine presbyteries and 134 congregations. Proposals are at present making for a union between this body and the Synod of Ulster. The Synod of Nova Scotia contains five presbyteries and twenty-four congregations.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Associate Synod of Original Seceders.</hi> This body separated from the Antiburgher Synod in 1806, and formed themselves into a distinct presbytery, called at first <hi rend="italic">The constitutional Associate Presbytery ;</hi> but after their junction with the few ministers who refused to accede to the union of the Burghers and Antiburghers in 1820, they assumed the name of <hi rend="italic">The Associate Synod of Original Seceders. </hi>This body now extends to four presbyteries, comprehending thirty-six congregations. They have a professor of divinity of their own, and, with the exception of their opinion respecting the interference of the magistrate in religious matters, they are identical in their leading principles with the United Associate Synod. The late Dr M'Crie, the able and learned biographer of Knox and Melville, was a minister of this body.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Original Burgher Associate Synod.</hi> In our history of the Secession Church we gave a brief statement of the controversy which led to the separation of this body from her communion. They extended latterly to four presbyteries, including forty-two congregations. A short time ago, however, they made a formal application to be received into the communion of the Established Church. The proposal met with a favourable reception from the General Assembly, and at the meeting of the Burgher Synod in 1839 a majority of the members agreed to accept of the terms offered by the Assembly, and have accordingly returned into the bosom of the national church. The minority seem as yet not to have determined as to the course which they will pursue.</p><p>(Mackerrow’s History of the Secession Church ; Brown’s History of the Secession Church ; Testimony of the United Associate Synod ; Fraser’s Lives of Ebenezer and Ralph Erskine; Ferrier's Memoirs of the Rev. W. Wilson ; Mon- crieff’s Life of Dr Erskine.)	<hi rend="smallcaps">(b. q.)</hi></p><p>@@@• These, and a variety of other interesting details, will be found in Mackerrow’s valuable History of the Secession Church.</p></body></text></TEI>