<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:06Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Taking now the fluxions, and substituting instead of <hi rend="italic">dp</hi> the expression it was put to represent, we get</p><p><hi rend="italic">x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">n</hi><hi rend="italic"> ~ </hi><hi rend="italic superscript">,</hi><hi rend="italic">ds</hi> + (» — 1 ) <hi rend="italic">sx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">m</hi><hi rend="italic"> ~ </hi><hi rend="italic superscript">t</hi><hi rend="italic">dx </hi>= (n-l)*-¾te + <hi rend="subscript">Ί</hi>-—-<hi rend="subscript">+(Τ=</hi>-</p><p>and this, after reduction, becomes</p><p><hi rend="italic subscript">d</hi><hi rend="italic">s+--sdx =	—- +</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">T</hi><hi rend="italic">__</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">+</hi><hi rend="italic">__.</hi></p><p>This fluxional equation being of the first degree and first order, its primitive equation may be found (from the general formula given in <hi rend="smallcaps">Fluxions,</hi> § 171) to be</p><p><hi rend="superscript">1</hi> V <hi rend="italic">cf</hi> z ι∖ „ sj <hi rend="italic">,mx"~'dx x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">n</hi><hi rend="italic">dx</hi> 1</p><p><hi rend="superscript">i</hi>= F=<hi rend="superscript">7</hi>∙×√i<hi rend="superscript">(</hi>"“<hi rend="superscript">υ</hi>~ <hi rend="superscript">dx+</hi>-∣⊂7~ + J<hi rend="superscript">5</hi></p><p>and this again, by remarking that <hi rend="italic">p(n — i)x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">π</hi><hi rend="italic">~ </hi><hi rend="italic superscript">t</hi><hi rend="italic">dx = x^ ~ *, </hi>and that</p><p>∕&gt;m.r" ^^ <hi rend="italic superscript">l</hi><hi rend="italic">dx	 mx</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">n</hi><hi rend="italic">	∕∙ mx^dx</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">J ∖-x</hi> <hi rend="superscript">-</hi>n(l —a·)<hi rend="superscript">-</hi>.∕∏(l-.r)∙<hi rend="superscript">,</hi></p><p>may be reduced to</p><p>— ι <hi rend="smallcaps">_l </hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps">mx</hi> <hi rend="italic">∣</hi> <hi rend="italic superscript">w</hi><hi rend="italic"> — </hi><hi rend="italic superscript">m</hi><hi rend="italic"> Γ </hi><hi rend="italic superscript">χn</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">χ</hi></p><p>« (I — <hi rend="italic">x) m</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">n</hi><hi rend="italic"> ~</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">l</hi><hi rend="italic">J</hi> (1 — je)<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>'</p><p><hi rend="italic">/» .}'</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">il</hi><hi rend="italic">(lfC</hi></p><p>The remaining fluent ∕ —	-<hi rend="subscript">3</hi> may be found by § 101,</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Flux∣0N3,</hi> and it must be so taken, that after being multiplied by -	it shall vanish when <hi rend="italic">x = Ö ;</hi> for then this</p><p>hypothesis will make the whole function which expresses the value of <hi rend="italic">s</hi> vanish, except its first term 1, as it ought to do.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi> Let us suppose <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 2, then</p><p><hi rend="italic">j» x dx	</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">t</hi><hi rend="italic"> x </hi><hi rend="smallcaps">,a,	..	,</hi></p><p>∕(TΞΞ7y = * + Γ=ι <hi rend="superscript">+ 21</hi>°<hi rend="superscript">β</hi>∙&lt;<hi rend="superscript">1</hi>-<hi rend="superscript">a</hi>* and</p><p>2 — <hi rend="italic">m ∕∙ x</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">i</hi><hi rend="italic">dx 	</hi>(2—<hi rend="italic">m)x</hi></p><p><hi rend="italic">2x J</hi> (T∑∑^ij<hi rend="superscript">5 -</hi> 8(1—»)</p><p>+ <hi rend="superscript">10g</hi>∙ (<hi rend="superscript">1 -</hi> *)<hi rend="superscript">,</hi></p><p>the fluent being here taken as directed. In this case, after collecting the terms, we get or</p><p><hi rend="italic">m</hi>	m+l m+2</p><p>1 + —— » + —,*<hi rend="superscript">s</hi>+ —ÿ- ·»’ +, &amp;c.</p><p>log. (!-»).</p><p>(24.) There is a branch of the doctrine of series which is of considerable importance in pure mathematics, as well as in many physical inquiries, and in the science of astronomy ; it is called the <hi rend="italic">Interpolation</hi> of series.</p><p>To interpolate a series is to interpose among its terms others which shall be subject to the same law, or which shall be formed in the same manner as the original terms of the series ; or, in other words, it is to find the value of one or more terms by means of others which are given, and which may be either at equal or unequal intervals from one another, the places of the given terms as well as of those sought being supposed known.</p><p>It is easy to see that this problem may be applied to the construction of logarithmic tables ; for we may regard the logarithms of the natural numbers 1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c. <hi rend="italic">ad infini- tutn,</hi> as the terms of a particular series of which the numbers themselves are the indices ; thus having given the logarithms of some numbers, we may by interpolating deduce from them the logarithms of others.</p><p>Again, in astronomy we may consider the numbers which express the successive observed ∣κ&gt;sitions of a celestial body</p><p>as the term3 of a series, their indices being the intervals of time between the observations and some assumed epoch, and the problem we are considering will enable us to determine the position at any instant different from the times of actual observation, provided the intervals between the observations be small, and the instant for which the position is sought not very remote from those at which the observations were made.</p><p>(25.) To illustrate the nature of the problem to be resolved, let us consider some particular case, as, for example, the arithmetical series</p><p><hi rend="italic">a, a + d, a + 2d, a + 3d, a -⅛- id,</hi> &amp;c.</p><p>Let <hi rend="italic">t</hi> and <hi rend="italic">t</hi> be two givcn terms of the series which are at any distance from one another, and let <hi rend="italic">n</hi> and <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">,</hi> be their indices, or numbers which denote their places in the series. Also let <hi rend="italic">y</hi> be any term whatever, and <hi rend="italic">x</hi> its index. Then, by the nature of an arithmetical series,</p><p><hi rend="italic">r = a + (n—</hi> l)rf, &lt;<hi rend="superscript">z</hi> = α + (n'— l)rf, y= a + (at— l)d.</p><p>Now, as there are here three equations, each involving the quantities <hi rend="italic">a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> we may eliminate both these quantities by the common rules <hi rend="smallcaps">(Algebra,</hi> sect, vii.) ; and this being done, we get</p><p><hi rend="italic">(x—ri)</hi> (ι'—<hi rend="italic">t)</hi> = (»' -&gt;- n) (y — &lt;<hi rend="superscript">,</hi>) ; and hence we find this expression,</p><p><hi rend="italic">y=τ∑∑*</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">l</hi><hi rend="italic">+*≡n</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">t</hi><hi rend="italic">'</hi></p><p>which is a general formula for interpolating any arithmetical series ; and it is observable, that it is entirely independent both of the first term and common difference.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Example.</hi> The 7th term of an arithmetical series Ls 15, and the 12th term is 25 : it is required to find the 10th term.</p><p>Here <hi rend="italic">n</hi> = 7, <hi rend="italic">n'</hi> = 12, <hi rend="italic">x</hi> = 10 ;</p><p><hi rend="italic">t =</hi> 15, &lt;' = 25, y is sought.</p><p>Therefore, by the formula,</p><p>2	3</p><p>w = -χl5 + -×25=2l, the answer.</p><p>5	o</p><p>(26.) The mode of investigation by which we have found a formula for the interpolation of an arithmetical series will apply also to others, if the law according to which the terms arc formed be known ; in general, however, the law of a series to be interpolated is either not known, or it is not taken into account, and we only consider the absolute magnitudes of certain terms, and the numbers expressing their places in the series. To resolve the problem generally with these <hi rend="italic">data,</hi> it is usual to proceed as follows: Let a straight line AB, and a point A in it, be assumed as given in position, and let there be taken the segments AD, AD', AD”, AD’", Ac., proportional to the numbers denoting the places of the terms of a series reckoned from any term assumed as a fixed origin ; and at the points D, D', D<hi rend="superscript">,</hi>, let there be erected perpendiculars proportional to the terms themselves. Let us now suppose a curve to pass through C, C', C”, C'", &amp;c. ; then, if it be so chosen that its curvature may vary gradually in its progress from point to point, without any abrupt changes of inflection, and, moreover, if the terms (which we may suppose to be either at equal or unequal distances) are pretty near to one another, it is easy to conceive, that if AP be taken equal to the number expressing</p></body></text></TEI>