<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:19:59Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea</hi><hi rend="italic">-Plants</hi> are those vegetables that grow in salt-water, within the shores of the sea. The old botanists divided these into three classes. The first class, according to their arrangement, contained the <hi rend="italic">algæ,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">fuci,</hi> the s<hi rend="italic">ea-mosses </hi>or <hi rend="italic">confervas,</hi> and the different species of sponges. The second contained substances of a hard texture, like stone or horn, which seem to have been of the same nature with what we call <hi rend="italic">zoophyta,</hi> with this difference, that we refer sponges to this class, and not to the first. The third class is the same with our <hi rend="italic">lithophyta,</hi> comprehending corals, madrepores, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi> It is now well known that the genera belonging to the second and third of these classes, and even some referred to the first, are not vegetables, but animals, or the productions of animals. Sea-plants, then, properly speaking, belong to the class of cryptogamia, and the order of algæ ; and, according to Bomare, are all comprehended under the genus fucus. We may also add several species of the ulva and conferva, and the sargazo. The fuci and marine ulvæ are immersed in the sea, are sessile, and without root. The marine confervæ are either sessile or floating. The sargazo grows beyond soundings.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea</hi><hi rend="italic">-Serpent,</hi> a monstrous creature, said to inhabit the northern seas, about Greenland and the coasts of Norway. “ In 1756,” says Guthrie, “one of them was shot by a master of a ship. Its head resembled that of a horse ; the mouth was large and black, as were the eyes, a white mane hanging from its neck. It floated on the surface of the water, and held its head at least two feet out of the sea. Between the head and neck were seven or eight folds, which were very thick ; and the length of this snake was more than a hundred yards, some say fathoms. They have a remarkable aversion to the smell of castor ; for which reason, ship, boat, and bark masters provide themselves with quantities of that drug, to prevent being overset, the serpent’s olfactory nerves being remarkably exquisite. The particularities related of this animal would be incredible, were they not attested upon oath. Egede, a very reputable author, says, that on the 6th of July 1734, a large and frightful sea monster raised itself so high out of the water, that its head reached above the main-top-mast of the ship ; that it had a long sharp snout, broad paws, and spouted water like a whale ; that the body seemed to be covered with scales ; the skin was uneven and wrinkled, and the lower part was formed like a snake. The body of this monster is said to be as thick as a hogshead ; his skin is variegated like a tortoise-shell; and his excrement, which floats upon the surface of the water, is corrosive.” No man of sound judgment, however, would think these recitals sufficient to establish the existence of such monsters.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sea</hi><hi rend="italic">-Sickness,</hi> a disorder incident to most persons on their first going to sea, and occasioned by the agitation of the vessel. This disorder has not been much treated of, although it is very irksome and distressing to the patient during its continuance. It appears to be a spasmodic affection of the stomach, occasioned by the alternate pressure and recession of its contents against its lower internal surface, according as the rise and fall of the ship oppose the action of gravity.</p><p>Many methods of preventing, or at least mitigating, this disorder, have been recommended, of which the most efficacious appear to be the following : Not to go on board immediately after eating, and not to eat, when on board, any large quantity at a time ; to lie down the moment the symptoms are felt, and to remain in the horizontal position till they arc removed ; to keep much upon deck, even when the weather is stormy, as the sea-breeze is not so apt to affect the stomach as the impure air of the cabin, rendered so for want of proper circulation ; and not to watch the motion of the waves, particularly when strongly agitated with tempest.</p><p><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Se.i-</hi><hi rend="italic"> Weed,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Alga marina,</hi> is commonly used as a manure on the sea-coast, where it can be procured in abun</p><p>dance. The best sort grows on rocks, and is that from which kelp is made. The next to this is called the <hi rend="italic">peasy seaweed ;</hi> and the worst is that with a long stalk.</p><p>SEADOWLY, a port of Northern Hindustan, in the territories of the Nepaul rajah district of Mocwanpoor. To this port the British forces penetrated in 1767, and took it ; but were obliged to retreat, from the pestilential effects of the climate.</p><p>SEAFORD, a town on the sea-shore, in the hundred of Flexborough and rape of Pewensey, in the county of Sussex, sixty-three miles from London. It was in former times much more extensive than it is at present. It is now a mere fishing and bathing place. It is a corporate town, with a bailiff and twelve jurats, and returned two members to the House of Commons till the year 1832. The population amounted in 1821 to 1047, and in 1831 to 1098.</p><p>SEAL, a stone, piece of metal, or other matter, usually either round or oval, on which are engraven the arms or device of some prince, state, community, magistrate, or private person, often with a legend or inscription.</p><p>The use of seals, as a mark of authenticity to letters and other instruments in writing, is extremely ancient. We read of it among the Jews and Persians in the earliest and most sacred records of history ; and in the book of Jeremiah there is a very remarkable instance, not only of attestation by seal, but also of the other usual formalities attending a Jewish purchase. In the civil law, also, seals were the evidences of truth, and were required, on the part of the witnesses at least, at the attestation of every testament. But in the times of our Saxon ancestors they were not much in use in England ; for though Sir Edward Coke relies on an instance of King Edwyn’s making use of a seal about a hundred years before the Conquest, yet it does not follow that this was the usage among the whole nation ; and perhaps the charter he mentions may be of doubtful authority, from this very circumstance of its being sealed, since we are assured by all our ancient historians that sealing was not then in common use. The method of the Saxons was, for such as could write to subscribe their names, and, whether they could write or not, to affix the sign of the cross ; which custom our illiterate vulgar for the most part observe, by signing a cross for their mark when unable to write their names. And indeed this inability to write, and therefore making a cross in its stead, is honestly avowed by Caedwaila, a Saxon king, at the end of one of his charters. In like manner, and for the same insurmountable reason, the Normans, a brave but illiterate nation, at their first settlement in France used the practice of sealing only, without writing their names; and this custom continued when learning made its way among them, though the reason for doing it had ceased ; and hence the charter of Edward the Confessor, to Westminster Abbey, himself being brought up in Normandy, was witnessed only by his seal, and is generally thought to be the oldest sealed charter of any authenticity in England. At the Conquest the Norman lords brought over into this kingdom their own fashions, and introduced waxen seals only, instead of the English method of writing their names, and signing with the sign of the cross. The impressions of these seals were sometimes a knight on horseback, sometimes other devices ; but coats of arms were not introduced into seals, nor indeed used at all, till about the reign of Richard I. who, it is said by some, brought them from the crusade in the Holy Land, where they were first invented and painted on the shields of the knights, to distinguish the variety of persons of every Christian nation who resorted thither.</p><p>This neglect of signing, and resting only upon the authenticity of seals, remained in Scotland till the year 1540, when a statute was enacted ordering subscription for the purpose of authenticating deeds and writs.</p></body></text></TEI>