<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:24:03Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>tures of Sheffield were placed on an entirely new footing ; the liberty of engaging in any of the heretofore incorporated trades, either as masters or journeymen, being extended indifferently to all persons, whether freemen or strangers. The act which thus abolished the old corporation influence and jurisdiction still perpetuated its formal continuance, with power to grant marks, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.,</hi> the “ master-cutler” being also the returning officer in the election of the two members of parliament for the borough of Sheffield, under the reform act. The corporation have a very handsome hall in Church Street.</p><p>Although the throwing open the old corporate trades to unrestrained competition had a considerable effect in multiplying manufacturers, yet the peculiar nature of the handicrafts generally limited in some degree the changes which, under other circumstances, might have resulted from the sudden rush of capital into a new channel. In the first place, a workmanlike expertness in any branch of cutlery cannot be acquired without a considerable period of probation. In the second place, the application of machinery could only be applied, except in the department of grinding, to a very limited extent ; and, with this exception, manual labour can hardly be said to be superseded, but rather assisted, by water or steam power. There are other circumstances which have operated in the same direction, especially the division of labour in the production of a single article, which has given the artisans in one branch a control over the others. This has led the workmen generally to act in concert in all questions touching their respective departments of labour, as wages, apprentices, engagements with masters, &amp;c. To maintain what they have considered their rights, or at least their interests, recourse has been had to various compacts formed under the designation of “ Trades’ Unions,” frequently exhibiting all the melancholy results of illegal combinations. Nor has the mischief of these confederations been confined to portentous “ strikes,” contests between the masters and the journeymen ; but nonjuring or suspected individuals among the latter have sometimes become victims to the vigilance and the vengeance of their banded fellows. What has been the entire effect of this system upon the trade of the town generally, and upon the present condition of the parties, it is not very easy to say. It may have kept up wages, but it has more certainly broken down that good understanding which formerly existed between masters and workmen, and driven numerous customers to foreign markets. The number of persons employed in the cutlery workshops is about 10,000.</p><p>About 700 tons of Swedish iron are annually landed at the canal wharf, which are converted in the town into the steel which is used in the manufacture of knives, scissors, razors, files, saws, axes, and various other cutting instruments. Of this really “ precious metal,” however, the greater part is exported to the United States in the form of tilted <hi rend="italic">cast steel ;</hi> that is, steel which, after carbonization in the original bars, is broken up and melted in a crucible, afterwards cast into a mould, and then reduced at the forges into rods of such sizes as the trade requires. Besides, three or four thousand tons of British iron are annually brought into the town, and some portion of it converted into steel for inferior purposes. There are several large establishments for the manufacture of the finer kinds of stoves, grates, and fenders. These articles are often executed in the most superb style, modellers and other artists being constantly employed in devising new patterns.</p><p>About a century ago, the art of plating upon copper with silver was discovered in Sheffield ; and thus originated a trade of immense importance to the town. For many years past the quantity of wares executed in this beautiful and comparatively cheap material has been very great, including particularly urns, salvers, dishes, epergnes, candelabras, and indeed almost every article which had formerly been</p><p>made of silver. The silver-plating establishments are among the most respectable in the town ; their interests have also been the least fluctuating. These circumstances are due mainly to the fact, that in works of this kind a large capital must be sunk in stamps, dies, and other tools ; added to which is the expense of creating new designs, and involving the consideration of taste as well as cost. Sheffield plate, for richness of design, the strength of its more precious material, and for excellence of workmanship, is everywhere in high estimation.</p><p>Manufactures in Britannia metal, which are likewise indigenous to the town, are carried on to a great extent, and to a singular degree of perfection. Nearly every one of the articles made in silver-plate are elegantly imitated in this cheap material ; with the addition of vast quantities of spoons, which are first cast in metal moulds, and afterwards polished by brushing.</p><p>Latterly both the foregoing lucrative branches of trade have encountered some competition from the use of what has been terme&lt;l German silver, a kind of brass, which combines the colour, lustre, and durability of silver, at a cost not greatly above that of manufactured copper.</p><p>Here are two or three large establishments for the manufacture of optical instruments, including especially curious works for the grinding of spectacle-glasses, the greater part of the trade throughout the country being supplied from Sheffield. Several of the manufacturers have show-rooms on their premises for the display of their brilliant wares, which are celebrated for the variety and beauty of the cutlery-goods which they contain ; and visiters may here witness the various operations carried on in the workshops.</p><p>The town of Sheffield, in every branch of its productive industry, not only carries on a considerable home trade, but its leading wares find a market in every quarter of the globe. It is, however, to the United States of America that the largest and most constant consignments are made ; and hence Sheffield participates very largely in every fluctuation which affects Transatlantic mercantile interests.</p><p>The inhabitants of Sheffield are largely provided with places for the promotion of religion, education, philanthropy, and intelligence. There are in the parish twelve churches, seven in the town and five in the rural townships, containing in all 15,160 sittings. Holy Trinity, or the parish church, is a noble Gothic structure, enclosing a parallelogram 240 feet in length by 130 feet in width. From near the centre rises a tower, containing ten very well- tuned bells, and surmounted by a lofty spire of handsome proportions. That part of the church now used for divine service was, in 1800, rebuilt from the foundation, and the interior fitted up in a solid, handsome, and commodious manner, so that the chancel alone presents any traces of antiquity.</p><p>The living is a vicarage, two parties presenting in turn, as representatives of the original grantees of the advowson in 1544. Independently of the vicarial patronage, three assistant ministers are appointed and maintained by the church burgesses.</p><p>In addition to the churches and chapels of the establishment, the Methodists, Independents, Baptists, Quakers, and Roman Catholics, have respectively large, handsome, and commodious places of worship, in the whole not fewer than twenty. Of these, six belong to the Wesleyans, and include some of the largest and most ornamental chapels in the connection.</p><p>Here is an old endowed grammar-school ; a collegiate school, recently built by shareholders, at an expense of L.3000 ; and two charity schools, one for sixty boys, and the other for sixty girls, all conducted in conformity with the principles of the Church of England. The Wesleyan Methodists have just erected, outside the town, and at a cost of about L. 15,000, a splendid proprietary school, ca-</p></body></text></TEI>