<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:52Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>nearly befallen an artist employed by Professor Reinwardt to paint the portrait of a
                living Naja. It had in some way disengaged its bands, and seemed to have prepared
                itself to attack the unsuspecting painter the moment he entered his apartment. He
                there found it supported on its tail, its body raised, its neck dilated, its head
                advanced,—and then giving utterance to some hissing sounds, it threw a quantity of
                saliva upon the very man who was about to hand it down to posterity, but who
                fortunately effected an instantaneous retreat before it came to closer quarters. We
                doubt not the painter loved the picturesque, although that was not the time to gaze
                with admiration on the fierce intruder :—</p>
            <p>Not with intended wave,</p>
            <p>Prone on the ground (as since), but on his rear,</p>
            <p>Circular base of rising folds, that tower’d Fold above fold, a surging maze ! his
                head Crested aloft, and carbuncle his eyes.</p>
            <p>Dr Russel informs us that he never knew the bite of a hooded snake prove mortal to a
                dog in much less than half an hour, although it kills chickens in less than half a
                minute. Now the rattle-snake has been known to kill a dog in less than two minutes.
                Yet the use of the lunar caustic, which in the hands of the Abbé Fontana proved so
                efficacious when applied as remedial to the bite of the viper, was found of little
                or no avail in India as a counteraction to the venom of the <hi rend="italic">cobra
                    de capello.@@'</hi> We shall conclude our notices of this species by observing,
                that the Ceylonese jugglers, according to Dr Davy, use it without extracting the
                fangs, the only means which they employ to avoid its vengeance being courage and
                agility. It is in fact held in veneration by the natives of that island, who
                carefully avoid it, offer it no injury, and put it out of doors unhurt when it
                happens to enter their dwellings.@@* The root of <hi rend="italic">Ophiorhyza
                    mungos</hi> is believed in India to be a specific against the bite of the <hi
                    rend="italic">cobra de capello.</hi></p>
            <p>Another noted species is the <hi rend="italic">Naja haje (coluber haje, </hi>Linn.),
                which plays the same part in the history and superstitions of the African tribes as
                the preceding does in those of the Asiatic nations. The ancient Egyptians named it
                    <hi rend="italic">Ouro,</hi> a term which signifies king, and which the Greeks
                adopted into their language in the word <hi rend="italic">Ouraios.</hi> It is
                frequently represented in various Egyptian antiquities, whether as drawn in colours,
                sculptured on the covers of sarcophagi, or cast in bronze. One of the great creative
                spirits of the world, called Cneph, Cnouphis, or Ammon, in the cosmogony of Egypt,
                was represented in their symbolical writings under the form of a serpent winding
                itself around a globe, or placed in the centre of a disk.</p>
            <p>The jugglers of modern Egypt, especially of Cairo, use this Naja in their pretended
                sorceries. These people affect to be descendants of the ancient Psylli, and boast of
                inheriting from their ancestors the power of subduing and commanding the most
                poisonous reptiles. The principal feat which they execute consists in making the
                naja counterfeit death, or they change it into a rod. This they seem to effect by
                pressing the neck of the creature between their fingers, so as to produce a kind of
                catalepsy, which renders it stiff and motionless. This is rather a singular fact
                when considered in connection with the scriptural narrative, where the rods of the
                magicians, when thrown down, are converted into serpents.@@<hi rend="superscript"
                    >3</hi> According to M. Geoffroy, the species is still sufficiently common in
                Egypt, occurring both in fields and ditches. “ Les cultivateurs sont donc exposés à
                le rencontrer fréquemment ; mais quoiqu’ils n’ignorent pas le danger de sa morsure,
                sa présence ne les empêche nulle</p>
            <p>ment de vaquer à leur travaux ordinaires ; connaissant bien les habitudes du
                redoubtable reptile, ils savent qu’ils n’auraient à craindre d’être attaqués par
                lui, que s’ils venaient à commetre l’imprudence de s’en approcher. En effet, tant
                qu’ils se tiennent à quelque distance, l’haje se contente de les suivre du regard,
                en élevant sa tête et en prenant l’attitude dans laquelle les fig. 4 et 5 le
                    represent.”@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi> The African Naja attains to about the
                same size as the Asiatic, and greatly resembles it in general aspect ; but its neck
                is less capable of inflation, and its muzzle more conical. It is usually of a
                yellowish-brown colour above, varied with numerous black and white spots ; the under
                surface whitish, although some individuals exhibit broad black spots or bands on the
                abdomen. The Cape Naja is regarded by M. Schlegel merely as a climatic variety of
                that now mentioned.</p>
            <p>The Australian species <hi rend="italic">(Naja pοrphyrica)</hi> was first described
                by Dr Shaw.@@<hi rend="superscript">,</hi> It belongs to the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Oplocepluιlus</hi> of Baron Cuvier, and we place it here on the authority of M.
                Schlegel. According to M. Lesson, it is greatly dreaded at Port Jackson, and several
                convicts are said to have died of its bite in a quarter of an hour. It is common in
                the sandy brushw∞d of the shores of Botany Bay. Its movements are full of force and
                vigour, its agility remarkable, and it defends itself when attacked with great
                    hardihood.@@<hi rend="superscript">6</hi> Another New Holland species is <hi
                    rend="italic">Naja curta,</hi> described by MM. Quoy anil Gaimard, and said to
                bear resemblance to a viper. It is probably the only Colu- briform venomous reptile
                which exhibits a somewhat vertically elongated pupil.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Family II.—Sea-Serpents.</hi></p>
            <p>Our present family is placed here, on the supposition that all the species which it
                contains are poisonous. Several naturalists, proceeding on certain data given by Dr
                Russel, have maintained the contrary opinion ; but long- continued researches on the
                part of M. Schlegel have led to the conclusion that there is really no exception to
                the rule. Great confusion prevails in the synonymy of the species, chiefly owing to
                the absence of good figures and accurate comparative descriptions,—even Dr Russel’s
                plates, which are the most numerous, being insufficient to lead to a rigorous
                determination of the species. The specimens themselves are obtained with great
                difficulty, and are consequently rare in our collections.</p>
            <p>We have pot sufficiently precise information on which to settle the geographical
                boundaries of the marine family of serpents. That species occur in the Persian and
                Arabian Gulfs is by no means improbable ; but the fact is inferred rather from some
                passages in ancient writers than from modern observation ; and we know that the
                authors of antiquity, at least in some instances, mistook certain eel-formed fishes
                for actual snakes. Schneider indeed@@<hi rend="superscript">7</hi> (whose competence
                as a <hi rend="italic">scholar</hi> no naturalist would dare to doubt) has quoted
                several classical writers to demonstrate a remote knowledge of sea-serpents ; but
                that knowledge seems too superficially and vaguely expressed to be altogether
                trusted, or even understood. Elian comes closer to the point when he says, that “
                the seas of India produce hydras with flattened tails.”@@<hi rend="superscript"
                    >8</hi></p>
            <p>Modern naturalists are believed to be in error who assert their occurrence in the
                Atlantic Ocean, no proper proof having been yet adduced of any of these species
                inhabiting the “ American Ferry,” as we see that world of waters now named, since
                the steaming days of the British Queen and</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@,</hi><hi rend="italic"> Edinburgh Cabinet
                    Library,</hi> vol. viii. </p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">@@@» Ceylon,</hi> p. 83, <hi rend="italic">et seq.</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@3</hi> "Then Pharaoh also called the wise men and the
                sorcerers: now the magicians of Egypt, they also did in like manner with their
                enchantments; for they cast down every man his rod, and they became serpents ; but
                Aaron’s rod swallowed up their rods.” <hi rend="italic">(Exodus,</hi> vii.
                11,12.)</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@4</hi><hi rend="italic"> Descrip. de l'Egypte.,</hi>
                Atlas, Reptiles, pi. 7. </p>
            <p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@5</hi><hi rend="italic"> Zoology of New Holland</hi>
                pl. 10. </p>
            <p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@6</hi><hi rend="italic">Voyage de lu Coquille,</hi>
                Zoologie, ii. p. 55.</p>
            <p>@@@7 <hi rend="italic">Hist. Amphib</hi>. i. p. 255.</p>
            <p>@@@ ÆI. 1. 16, chap. 8.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
