<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:23:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>separated, and the straw is broken into small fragments.</p><p>Γhey then wait till the wind rises, when the breeze performs the operation of separating the grain from the chaff and broken straw. The former is sent to the granary in a kind of rush paniers on the backs of asses, and the latter is made into a clumsy stack in the field, and kept there for food in the dry season. The barley sown in the spring is most rapid in its growth : sometimes in less than twelve weeks from the period of its being sown, it is cut, thrashed, and fit for the market. But grain is not the most important branch of rural economy in this province. Oil, the substitute for butter in warm climates, is the chief dependence of the Andalusian farmer, and the cultivation of it is more congenial to the indolent habits of the natives. The trees only require planting, and will then yield their produce for ages, with but little attention on the part of the proprietors. The oil, though an important article, and the chief source of the wealth of the province, is not made with much attention either to its cleanliness or its sweetness. The oils of Spain are inferior to those of France and Italy, though the olives from which they are made are decidedly superior. Wines are made to a considerable extent in this province, but not sufficient for its consumption.</p><p>Few articles of husbandry are of more universal attention than garlic, which grows in prodigious quantities, and forms in all the markets of Andalusia the most prominent object. The capsicum, or pimento, is also much in demand, and is used in almost every culinary preparation. Instead of hedges formed by thorn bushes, the enclosures are secured by die aloe plant, which makes excellent fences, and, by their sharp points, are a security against all cattle. Instead of orchards of apples and pears, nothing is seen but oranges, lemons, pomegranates, and other fruits of a southern climate.</p><p>One production, not alimentary, is of vast importance, and is sedulously cultivated, the Spanish broom or esparto, which is made into a variety of articles for domestic uses.</p><p>The breed of horses in Andalusia has at all times been very highly esteemed ; they have in them a considerable mixture of the Arabian breed. As cows are not kept for the purposes of the dairy, they are rather neglected, and the breed is by no means good. The sheep are numerous ; those of the merino kind are migratory, and belong rather to the whole kingdom of Spain than to this particular province. There are, however, large flocks on the mountains ; but as their propagation is left in a great measure to nature, neither their flesh nor their wool is very good.</p><p>Some of the largest estates in the province belong to convents, cathedrals, or municipal corporations: they are frequently let to tenants, who pay rent in a portion of the produce. The richer inhabitants in all parts of the peninsula prefer mules to horses for drawing their carriages ; and they are used by the corps of artillery in the military service, where they can be procured, in preference to horscs.</p><p>Besides its agricultural riches, this province is stored with mineral wealth to a great degree. It is well known that the Romans drew from this district, then called Betica, a great portion of their silver; and it continued equally productive during the power of the Arabian race ; but the discovery of America, an event contemporaneous with the final extinction of the Moorish government, rendered the industry applied to mining less productive, and in consequence it has greatly diminished. There are, however, mines of silver, copper, mercury, lead, and iron, still worked. The commerce and manufactures of this province are almost wholly confined to the cities of Cadiz and Seville. The inhabitants are estimated at 746,221. It possesses the laws and privileges of Castille. The captain-general resides at Puerto Maria, but there is a royal audienza at Seville.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Seville</hi>, a city of Spain, the capital of the province of the same name, and formerly the capital of the ancient kingdom of Aragon. Its origin is unknown ; but, un</p><p>der the Roman government, it was a place of considerable note under the narae Hispalis. It enjoys a most delightful climate, and is surτounded by a fruitful country. It contains about 100,000 inhabitants, exclusive of the suburb Triana, divided from it by the river. The population of the latter is about 15,000.</p><p>Seville abounds with ancient buildings, both Roman and Moorish, and with numerous modem structures of great extent and magnificence. The golden tower, on the banks of the river, is said to have been the work of Julius Csesar. It is in perfect repair, and, before Cadiz rose to its present importance, the gold and silver transmitted from America was landed here, and deposited in this tower, on account of its strength and security. The aqueduct which supplies the city with spring-water is the work of the same people. It is still in perfect repair, and now, after the lapse of ages, serves the purpose for which it was originally constructed. In the vicinity of the city, at the ancient town of Italica, the birthplace of the Emperor Trajan, are the remains of an ancient amphitheatre, which, though partly in ruins, is sufficiently perfect to show its plan and extent ; and from the rows of benches for spectators, which remain, it may be calculated that it would seat about ten thousand persons. Its dilapidated condition is the result of an earthquake, and has not been occasioned by the regular decay of time.</p><p>The chief building of the Moorish period that remains is the alcazar or palace : the date of its origin is not ascertained. A considerable part was added by Peter the Cruel, between the years 1353 and 1364. In the addition, the Arabian style of building is so closely imitated, that it is impossible to determine which part was built first. Though the exterior is mean, like all the Arabian buildings, yet the inside is beautifully filled up with noble staircases, marble halls, and courts with fountains of pure and cool water. Before the French entered Andalusia, the central junta occupied the palace after their dispersion. Joseph Bonaparte held his court in it.</p><p>Some of the houses of this city, belonging to individuals, have the most entire specimens of the exquisite stucco workmanship with which the rich Moors adorned the interior of their houses. In some of the most obscure streets of the city are found houses with the exterior appearance of a prison, with no windows towards the town, and only an entrance through massy doors studded or plated with iron ; but the visiter, on entering, is surprised with the view of arcades surrounded with marble courts and sparkling fountains, and the whole adorned with that durable kind of stucco, in the composition of which the Moors so greatly excelled.</p><p>The buildings erected in Seville since the extirpation of the Moors are materially different in their style of archi- tecture. One of these is the cathedral, with its tower, the Giraldo, 360 feet in height. The length of this church is 398, and the breadth 290 ; but its choir and principal altar being in the centre, they take off very considerably from the effect of its dimensions. The different specimens of architecture which in successive periods have prevailed in Spain, may all be seen in this extraordinary church. The tower, and a part called the orange court. <hi rend="italic">Patio de las Narangas,</hi> was built about the year 1000, by the Moors, and in their peculiar style ; another part, built 200 years later, is in the Gothic taste, which was then introduced into Spain ; whilst the part which completed it, and which was finished about the year 1520, is in a style denominated by Spanish artists <hi rend="italic">plarareca,</hi> or the imitation of the silver ornaments of a Catholic church. Though this last fashion is a most gross perversion of taste, yet the contrast with the Gothic is not unpleasing ; and, viewed as a whole, the cathedral is perhaps one of the grandest of all the modern edifices in the Peninsula.</p><p>La Lonja, or the Exchange, for it was designed, though</p></body></text></TEI>