<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:21:16Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>nia ; and returned by way of the East Indies to England, where they arrived on the 1st of October 1711 ; Selkirk having been absent, on the day of his arrival in London, eight years one month and three days, more than half of which time he had spent alone on the island. The public curiosity being excited respecting him, he was induced to put his papers into the hands of Defoe, to arrange and form them into a regular narrative. These papers must have been drawn up after he left Juan Fernandez, as he had no means of recording his transactions there. Captain Cooke remarks, as an extraordinary circumstance, that he had contrived to keep an account of the days of the week and the month ; but this might be done, as Defoe makes Robinson Crusoe do, by cutting notches in a post, or many other methods. From this account of Selkirk, Defoe adopted the notion of writing a more extensive work, the romance of Robinson Crusoe, and very dishonestly defrauded the original proprietor of his share of the profits. After his return to England he waited in London till he got his effects realized, and then proceeded, in the spring of 1712, to his native village Largo. For a few days he enjoyed the society of his relatives and friends ; but, from long habit, he soon felt averse to society, and was most happy in being alone. In the upper part of the garden attached to his father’s house, he formed a kind of cave or grotto, which commanded an extensive and delightful view of the bay of Largo, and the shores of the Forth. In musing here, or wandering through a secluded and solitary valley called Keil’s Den, and fishing in the bay, he spent the greater part of his time. How long he remained here cannot be ascertained, but he eloped some time afterwards with a girl of the neighbourhood, named Sophia Bruce, and proceeded with her to London. He never returned to Largo, and but little is known of him during the latter part of his life. Sophia Bruce appears to have died between 1717 and 1720 ; for in the latter year he again married Frances Candis, who survived him. Selkirk died lieutenant on board his majesty’s ship Weymouth, some time in the year 1723; and it is believed that he had no children by either of his wives.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi></p><p>S<hi rend="smallcaps">elkirk,</hi> an ancient royal burgh, and chief town of the county of Selkirk, in Scotland. It is situated on an elevation overlooking the valley of the river Ettrick, and commands an extensive view. It consists chiefly of one street, which expands at the market-place into an open space ; and in it is the ancient tolbooth. In addition to this main street, there are a few small streets that diverge from it. The town has not increased in size or in importance for centuries ; but it has been much improved of late years, and now contains many good houses, with a town-hall, having an elegant spire 110 feet in height, and in which there are apartments for the burgh and sheriff courts. There are two places of worship, one belonging to the established church, and the other to the United Associate Synod. A new prison has been erected at the north side of the town ; and it also possesses several excellent schools, in which the classics, French, Italian, and the more usual branches, are taught.</p><p>Selkirk was formerly famed for the manufacture of shoes, in which it had an extensive trade ; but it has now no manufactures of any consequence, the restrictions on trade, and the jealousy of the burghers or freemen, preventing young men of small capital from pushing business, and forcing them to repair to places more open to enterprise. The property of the burgh extends to 1784 acres, and its yearly income amounts to nearly L.1100. In 1833, its debts amounted to L. 16,088. It is governed by a provost, two bailies, a treasurer, and twenty-nine councillors ; and it votes with the county in returning a member to parliament. The population of the burgh and parish in 1821 amounted to 2728,</p><p>and in 1831 to 2833. The population of the burgh alone in the latter year was 1880.</p><p>During the wars between England and Scotland the citizens of Selkirk were famed for their courage. A party of them, amounting to between eighty and a hundred, under the command of the town-clerk, William Brydone, proceeded to the battle of Flodden, and fought with such gallantry that only a few returned. Brydone was afterwards knighted for his conduct ; and the town received from James V. a grant of a thousand acres, as a recompense for the courage of the burghers, and for the town being totally burned by the English, in revenge for the bravery displayed by them at that battle. Brydone’s sword is still in the possession of his lineal descendants ; and a pennon, taken, it is believed, from the Percys, by a person of the name of Fletcher, is still kept by the successive deacons of the weavers, and displayed on all civic occasions by that corporation. A mile north from the town is Philiphaugh, where the celebrated Marquis of Montrose was defeated by the covenanters under General Leslie.</p><p>SELKIRKSHIRE, a county of Scotland, situated between 55° 21 and 55° 42' north latitude, and between 2° 48' and 3° 20' west longitude from Greenwich. It has Mid-Lothian, or the county of Edinburgh, on the north ; Roxburghshire on the east and south-east ; Dumfriesshire on the south ; and Peeblesshire, or Tweeddale, on the west ; the line which separates it from these counties being on all sides, but especially the south, exceedingly irregular. Its area has been computed very differently ; but, according to the latest authorities, it appears that its extreme length is thirty miles, its extreme breadth twenty, and it is calculated to contain 264½ square miles, nearly equal to 169,280 English acres. It includes only two entire parishes, Yarrow and Ettrick ; the parishes of Selkirk and Galashiels being partly in Roxburghshire. These may be said to form the county, although small parts of the parishes of Ashkirk, Inverleithen, Peebles, Roberten, and Stow, are also included in it.</p><p>This is almost entirely a pastoral district, and in many respects bears a resemblance to the higher parts of the contiguous county of Roxburgh. Like the latter county, the general declivity of the mountain range is from west- south-west to east-north-east, and all its streams discharge themselves into the Tweed. The rocks are of the transition series, and are chiefly greywacke, graywacke-slate, and clay-slate. On the borders of Peeblesshire extensive layers of porphyry, alternating with thin strata of slate and granite, are to be found. The hills are generally ridge-shaped, and rounded on the tops, with acclivities of from 10° to 30°. The secondary valleys are small, being caused by the Ettrick and Yarrow running nearly parallel, and at no very great distance from each other ; but where the Y arrow and Tweed diverge, the valleys increase in magnitude, as they are then drained by larger streams. Several of the hills are above 2300 feet in height, such as Windlestraw Law, at the northern extremity of the county, on the confines of Mid-Lothian ; Blackhouse Heights (2370); Minchmoor (2280), on the borders of Peeblesshire ; and Ettrick-pen (2200), on the south-west boundary. The lower hills are for the most part gτeen, and afford good pasturage for sheep ; but heath prevails on many of the higher grounds, especially towards the south-west. The lowest land is 280 feet, and the sites of many of the houses are from 600 to 1000 feet and upwards, above the level of the sea.</p><p>The rivers are, the Tweed, which crosses the north side of the county in its course from Peeblesshire on the west to Roxburghshire on the east ; the Gala, which for some distance forms the boundary with Roxburghshire on the north-east, and falls into the Tweed, from the north, a little</p><p>@@@* Life and Adventures of Alexander Selkirk, by John Howell, Edinburgh.</p></body></text></TEI>