<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:23:19Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>SEWER, in the household, an officer who arranged on the table the dishes of a king or nobleman.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sewer</hi> is also a passage or gutter made to carry water into the sea or a river, and thereby to preserve the land from inundations and other annoyances.</p><p><hi rend="italic">common </hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sewers,</hi> in Rome, were executed at a great expense. It was proposed that they should be of sufficient dimensions to admit a waggon loaded with hay. When these common sewers came to be obstructed, or out of repair, under the republic, the censors contracted to pay a thousand talents, or about L. 193,000, for clearing and repairing them. They were again in disrepair at the accession of Augustus Cæsar, and the reinstating of them is mentioned among the great works of Agrippa. He is said to have turned the course of seven rivers into these subterraneous passages, to have made them navigable, and to have actually passed in barges under the streets and buildings of Rome. These works are still supposed to remain ; but as they exceed the power and resources of the present city to keep them in repair, they are quite concealed, except at one or two places. They were, in the midst of the Roman greatness, and still are, reckoned among the wonders of the world ; and yet they are said to have been works of the elder Tarquin, a prince whose territory did not extend in any direction above sixteen miles ; and, on this supposition, they must have been made to accommodate a city that was calculated chiefly for the reception of cattle, herdsmen, and banditti. Rude nations sometimes execute works of great magnificence, as fortresses and temples, for the purposes of war and superstition ; but seldom palaces, and still more seldom works of mere convenience and cleanliness, in which, for the most part, they are long defective. It is not unreasonable, therefore, to question the authority of tradition in respect to this singular monument of antiquity, which so greatly exceeds what the best accommodated city of modern Europe could undertake for its own convenience. And as those works are still entire, and may continue so for thousands of years, it may be suspected that they were even prior to the settlement of Romulus, and may have been the remains of a more ancient city, on the ruins of which the followers of Romulus settled, as the Arabs now encamp on the ruins of Palmyra and Baalbeck. Livy owns, that the common sewers were not accommodated to the plan of Rome as it was laid out in his time ; they were carried in directions across the streets, and passed under buildings of the greatest antiquity. This derangement, indeed, he imputes to the hasty rebuilding of the city after its destruction by the Gauls; but haste, it is probable, would have determined the people to build on their old foundations, or at least not to change them so much as to cross the direction of former streets.</p><p>SEWISTAN. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Seistan.</hi></p><p>SEWURI, an oriental kind of guitar.</p><p>SEX, the property by which any animal is male or female.</p><p>“ The primary matter of which women are constituted appears to be more flexible, irritable, and elastic, than that of man. They are formed to maternal mildness and affection ; all their organs are tender, yielding, easily wounded, sensible, and receptible.”</p><p>“ The female thinks not profoundly ; profound thought is the power of the man. Women feel more. Sensibility is the power of woman. They often rule more effectually, more sovereignly, than man. They rule with tender looks, tears, and sighs, but not with passion and threats.”</p><p>“ Men embrace the whole, women remark individually, and take more delight in selecting the minutiæ which form the whole. Man hears the bursting thunder, views the destructive bolt, with serene aspect, and stands erect amidst the fearful majesty of the streaming clouds. Woman trembles at the lightning, and the voice of distant thunder, and shrinks into herself, or sinks into the arms of</p><p>man. Man receives a ray of light single ; woman delights to view it through a prism in all its dazzling colours.”</p><p>In determining the comparative merit of the two sexes, it is no derogation from female excellency that it differs in kind from that which distinguishes the male part of our species ; and if, in general, it shall be found that women fill up their appointed circle of action with greater regularity than men, the claim of preference cannot justly be decided in our favour. In the prudential and economical parts of life, it is undeniable that they rise far above us ; and if true fortitude of mind is best discovered by a cheerful resignation to the measures of Providence, we shall find little reason to claim that exalted virtue as our peculiar privilege. But whatever real difference there may be between the moral or intellectual powers of the male and female mind, nature does not seem to have marked the distinction so strongly as our vanity is willing to imagine; and after all, perhaps, education will be found to occasion the chief distinction.</p><p>SEXAGENARY, something relating to the number sixty. Thus sexagenary or sexagesimal arithmetic is a method of computation proceeding by sixties, such as that used in the division of a degree into sixty minutes, of the minute into sixty seconds, and of the second into sixty thirds. Sexagenary tables are also tables of proportional parts, showing the product of two sexagenaries that are to be multiplied, or the quotient of the two that are to be divided.</p><p>SEXAGESIMA, the second Sunday before Lent, or the next to Shrove Sunday ; so called as being about the sixtieth day before Easter.</p><p>SEXAGESIMALS, or <hi rend="italic smallcaps">Sessgesimal</hi><hi rend="italic"> Fractions,</hi> fractions whose denominators proceed in a sexagecuple ratio ; that is, a prime, or the first minute = <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">60</hi>; a second = <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">3600</hi> ; a third = <hi rend="superscript">1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">216000</hi>. Anciently there were no other than sexagesimals used in astronomy ; and they are still retained in many cases, though decimal arithmetic has come into use now in astronomical calculations. In these fractions, which some call <hi rend="italic">astronomical fractions,</hi> the denominator, being always CO, or a multiple of that number, is usually omitted, and the numerator only written down. Thus 4°, 59<hi rend="superscript">,</hi>, 32”, 50”, 16'", is to be read, 4 degrees, 59 minutes, 32 seconds, 50 thirds, and 16 fourths.</p><p>SEXTANS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sextant,</hi> a sixth part of certain things. The Romans having divided their <hi rend="italic">as</hi> into twelve ounces or uncia, the sixth part of that, or two ounces, was the sextans.</p><p>Sextans was also a measure which contained two ounces of liquor, or two cyathi.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Sextans,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Astronomy,</hi> a constellation of the southern hemisphere, made by Hevelius out of unformed stars. In Hevelius’s catalogue it contains eleven, but in the British forty-one stars.</p><p>SEXTANT, in <hi rend="italic">Mathematics,</hi> denotes the sixth part of a circle, or an arch comprehending sixty degrees.</p><p>The word sextant is more particularly used for an astronomical instrument made like a quadrant, excepting that its limb only comprehends sixty degrees. The use and application of the sextant is the same with that of the quadrant.</p><p>SEXTILE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sextilis,</hi> the position or aspect of two planets when at sixty degrees distance, or at the distance of two signs from one another. It is marked thus (*).</p><p>SEXTIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Quintus</hi>, a Pythagorean philosopher, who flourished in the time of Augustus. He seemed formed to rise in the republic ; but he shrunk from civil honours, and declined accepting the rank of senator when it was offered him by Julius Cæsar, that he might have time to apply to philosophy. It appears that he wished to establish a school at Rome, and that his tenets, though chiefly drawn from the doctrines of Pythagoras, in some particulars resembled those of the Stoics.</p><p>He soon found himself involved in many difficulties. His laws were tinctured with great severity, and in an early period of this establishment he found his mind so harassed,</p></body></text></TEI>