<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:31Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>at 263,@@<hi rend="superscript">l</hi> we do not find above fifty-seven of these
                endowed with injurious attributes,—that is, the proportion is not much more than one
                to five. This proportion, however, is not maintained throughout the various
                countries of the globe,— the venomous kinds seeming to be comparatively more
                numerous in open sterile countries. Of this, Africa and New Holland furnish
                examples,—the venomous species of the former continent being to the innocuous kinds
                as one to two or three, while of the ten species (or thereabouts) of ascertained New
                Holland species, not fewer than seven are venomous. In general, the number of
                individuals of each species is much more limited among the venomous kinds, as these
                live in an isolated manner, and rarely multiply so as to become abundant. Local
                circumstances sometimes favour an exception to this rule, as in the case of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Trigo- noeephalus lanceοlarus</hi> of Martinique and St Lucia, and
                that of the Dalmatian <hi rend="italic">Viperus ammodytes.</hi> The sea-snakes, all
                of which are poisonous, are likewise of a gregarious nature.</p>
            <p>Excepting the anomalous group called <hi rend="italic">Tortrix,</hi> there does not
                seem to exist any genus of serpents which is spread over all countries capable of
                maintaining reptile life ; and this restriction seems to illustrate the intimate
                relation which subsists between the organization of these beings, and the countries
                they inhabit. For example, the Colubers properly so called, which are destined to
                dwell in countries which are either well wooded, or marshy with abundant vegetation,
                have not yet been observed in New Holland, and are so rare in South Africa that only
                a single species has been found there, and that of a somewhat anomalous nature, in
                so far as its characters exhibit an approach to those of species which dwell by
                preference in sandy deserts.</p>
            <p>A similar observation applies nearly to the genus <hi rend="italic">Corοnella,
                </hi>composed of species which inhabit marshy plains, or such as are covered by
                brushwood. None of these occur in New Holland (which is noted for its frequent want
                of water), while the South African kinds differ from the typical species of the
                genus. The <hi rend="italic">tree-serpents</hi> are characteristic of equatorial
                countries, inhabiting of course only those portions which fulfil the conditions of
                their existence, that is, are well wooded. The three genera which compose the family
                are found both in the Old and New World ; but it is noticeable that the species of
                the genus <hi rend="italic">Dipsas</hi> of America do not attain to so great a size
                as the majority of those of India ; while the genus <hi rend="italic">Dryophis</hi>
                in America forms a true geographical division of the group, in so far as the dental
                system and muzzle are less developed, and the pupil of the eye is orbicular. The
                fresh-water snakes, comprised in the genera <hi rend="italic">Tropidonotus</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Homalopsis,</hi> occur abundantly in countries rich in
                permanent lakes, and watered by continuous rivers. They are thus well known in Asia,
                America, and even Europe, but are extremely rare in Africa, and unknown in New
                Holland. The genus <hi rend="italic">Homalopsis,</hi> indeed, which contains the
                essentially aquatic species, does not occur in Africa, but predominates in the New
                World, so rich and unrivalled in its mighty reservoirs of water.</p>
            <p>The geographical distribution of the <hi rend="italic">Boas</hi> exhibits some facts
                worthy of record. The whole are peculiar to warm countries. The genuine species are
                confined to South America ; their analogues in the ancient world being the <hi
                    rend="italic">Pythons</hi> of India, although in the latter country we also find
                several serpents very similar to Boas, but of very small size, and of which none
                exists in the western world, except a single representative in the island of Cuba.
                The genus <hi rend="italic">Acrοchordus</hi> forms a limited group, entirely
                confined to the East Indies. Of the venomous serpents, it is chiefly the vipers, and
                perhaps a few rattle-snakes, which make their way into temperate or colder
                countries, the majority of the genera occurring in intertropical regions. Of the
                colubriform venomous serpents, the genus <hi rend="italic">Elaps</hi> is the only
                one which occurs in both worlds; and it is not improbable that the American species
                will be found to constitute a geographical group, distinguished by their peculiar
                coloration, and certain small distinctions even in form. The Indian species of the
                genus last named are longitudinally striped, instead of being ringed with red and
                black, while those of New Holland present some anomalous features. The genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Bungarus</hi> is proper to the East Indies, where also are found
                certain <hi rend="italic">Najas,</hi> although the majority of these prefer a drier
                and more sandy soil,—a circumstance which explains their greater predominance in
                Africa and New Holland. The fact does not seem to admit of easy explanation, that
                    <hi rend="italic">salt-water serpents</hi> should be found almost exclusively in
                the Indian seas, from Malabar to the great Pacific Ocean. In regard to the venomous
                kinds properly so called, of the three genera of which that division is composed, it
                may be observed, that one, <hi rend="italic">Viperus,</hi> is proper to the ancient
                world ; that another, <hi rend="italic">Crotalus,</hi> is confined to the new ;
                while a third, <hi rend="italic">Trigonocephalus,</hi> occurs in both. These
                last-named reptiles dwell in great forests, or in well-w∞ded countries, and for that
                reason are not observed either in Africa or New Holland, where they are replaced by
                vipers ; but it may be mentioned, that the viper of New Holland is an anomalous
                species, while such as inhabit Europe equally depart from the typical form, and tend
                towards that of <hi rend="italic">Trigonοcephalus. </hi>In the genus just named two
                divisions may be established, one composed of species with the head clothed with
                scales, and which inhabit more particularly tropical countries; another formed of
                species with the head covered by scaly plates, and which extend into temperate
                regions.</p>
            <p>The preceding are a few of the most general facts in the distribution of Ophidian
                reptiles. We shall now notice some of those peculiarities which distinguish
                particular continents,—and, first, of Europe. We here find no species of the genera
                    <hi rend="italic">calamaria, Heterodon,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lycodοn,</hi>
                no genuine tree-serpents, no species of <hi rend="italic">Homalopsis</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Boa.</hi> We never meet in Europe with any salt-water serpents,
                nor with any of the colubriform venomous kinds ; and the poisonous tribes in general
                are represented merely by a few vipers. That the entire order of Ophidian reptiles
                has its great centre of dominion in sultry regions, is made manifest by the
                fact,</p>
            <p><hi rend="superscript">@@@,</hi> We here follow the computation of M. Schlegel, who
                probably proceeds upon the idea that the actual species have been nominally
                multiplied by the misapplication (and duplication) of various names. The amount must
                have been considerably greater in M. Humboldt's opinion, as that illustrious writer
                incidentally states that equatorial America produces 115 serpents out of the 320
                which form the Ophidian order. Daudin, even in his time, described about 313
                supposed species, of which eighty were regarded as venomous and 233 as innocuous,
                which gives a greater proportion to the former than they are at present entitled to.
                Nearly 400 different kinds of serpents are believed to exist in the Paris Museum,
                although we know not with what degree of critical accuracy that enumeration has been
                made.</p>
            <p>We do not ourselves possess the means of ascertaining the total number of reptiles
                now known to naturalists; but the following table exhibits the amount (as in 1834)
                in the National Museum of Paris, compared with the number described in the works of
                three principal writers on the class in question :—</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>Lacépède, 1790.</cell>
                    <cell>Daudin, 1805.</cell>
                    <cell>Merτem, 1820.</cell>
                    <cell>French Museum, 1834.</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Chelonians </cell>
                    <cell> 24</cell>
                    <cell>62</cell>
                    <cell>62</cell>
                    <cell>97</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Saurians </cell>
                    <cell> 56</cell>
                    <cell>86</cell>
                    <cell>S3</cell>
                    <cell>168</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Ophidians </cell>
                    <cell> 172</cell>
                    <cell>315</cell>
                    <cell>348</cell>
                    <cell>391</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Batrachians </cell>
                    <cell> 40</cell>
                    <cell>91</cell>
                    <cell>87</cell>
                    <cell>190</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell/>
                    <cell>292</cell>
                    <cell>556</cell>
                    <cell>580</cell>
                    <cell>846</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>We may conclude this note by observing, that the unfortunate Wagler, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Naturliches System der Amphibien,</hi> four vols. Munich, 1830,
                with folio Atlas of plates, has described no fewer than 248 <hi rend="italic"
                    >genera</hi> of the reptile race.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
