<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:23:15Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>Now, if this prodigious wall, with all its appendages of ditches, stations, castles, turrets, and military ways, was executed in the space of two years by two legions only, which, when most complete, required no less than 12,000 men, how greatly must we admire the skill, the industry, and excellent discipline of the Roman soldiers, who were not only the valiant guardians of the empire in times of war, but its most active and useful members in times of peace ?</p><p>This wall of Severus, and its fortresses, proved an impenetrable barrier to the Roman territories for nearly two hundred years. But about the beginning of the fifth century, the Roman empire being assaulted on all sides, and the bulk of their forces withdrawn from Britain, the Mæatæ and Caledonians, now called Scots and Picts, became more daring ; and some of them breaking through the wall, and others sailing round the ends of it, they carried their ravages into the very heart of provincial Britain. These invaders were indeed several times repulsed after this, by the Roman legions sent to the relief of the Britons. The last of these legions, under the command of Gallio of Ravenna, having, with the assistance of the Britons, thoroughly repaired the breaches of Severus’s wall and its fortresses, and exhorted the Britons to make a brave defence, took their final farewell of Britain. It soon appeared that the strongest walls and ramparts are no security to an undisciplined and dastardly rabble, as the unhappy Britons then were. The Scots and Picts met with little resistance in breaking through the wall, while the towns and castles were tamely abandoned to their destructive rage. In many places they levelled it with the ground, that it might prove no obstruction to their future inroads. From this time no attempts were ever made to repair this noble work. Its beauty and grandeur procured it no respect in the dark and tasteless ages which succeeded. It became the common quarry, for more than a thousand years, out of which all the towns and villages around were built; and is now so entirely ruined, that the penetrating eyes of the most poring and patient antiquary can hardly trace its vanishing foundations.</p><p>SEVIGNE', <hi rend="smallcaps">Marik de Rabutin,Marquise de,</hi> a French lady, was born in 1626. When only a year old she lost her father, who was killed in the descent of the English on the isle of Rhé, where he commanded a company of volunteers. In 1644 she married the Marquis of Sevigné, who was slain in a duel by the Chevalier d’Albret, in 1651. She had by him a son and a daughter, to the education of whom she afterwards religiously devoted herself. Her daughter was married in 1669 to the Count de Grignan, who conducted her to Provence. Madame de Sevigné consoled herself by writing frequent letters to her daughter, but she fell at lost the victim to her maternal tenderness. In one of her visits to Grignan, she fatigued herself so much during the sickness of her daughter, that she was seized with a fever, which carried her off on the l4th of January 1696. We have two portraits of Madame de Sevigné ; the one by the Comte de Bussi, and the other by Madame de la Fayette. The first exhibits her defects, the second her excellencies. Bussi describes her as a lively gay coquette, a lover of flattery, fond of titles, honour, and distinction ; M. de la Fayette, as a woman of wit and good sense, as possessed of a noble soul, formed for dispensing benefits, incapable of debasing herself by avarice, and blessed with a generous, obliging, and faithful heart. Both these portraits are in some measure just. That she was vain-glorious, appears evident from her own letters, which, on the other hand, exhibit undoubted proofs of her virtue and goodness of heart.</p><p>This illustrious lady was acquainted with all the wits of her age. It is said that she decided the famous dispute between Perrault and Boileau concerning the preference of the ancients to the moderns. She left behind her a most valuable collection of letters, the best edition of which is</p><p>that of 1775, in eight volumes 12mo.	“ These letters,”</p><p>says Voltaire, “ are filled with anecdotes, written with freedom, and in a natural and animated style ; are an excellent criticism on studied letters of wit, and still more on those fictitious letters which aim at the epistolary style, by a recital of false sentiments and feigned adventures to an imaginary correspondent." It were to be wished that a proper selection had been made of these letters. It is difficult to read eight volumes of letters, which, though inimitably written, present frequent repetitions, and are often filled with trifles. What makes them in general perhaps so interesting is, that they are in part historical. They may be looked on as a relation of the manners, the tone, the genius, the fashions, the etiquette, which reigned in the court of Louis XIV. They also contain many curious anecdotes nowhere else to be found. But these excellencies would be still more striking, were they sometimes stripped of that multitude of domestic affairs and minute incidents which ought naturally to have died with the mother and the daughter. A volume entitled <hi rend="italic">Sevigniana</hi> was published at Paris in 1756, which is nothing more than a collection of the fine sentiments, literary and historical anecdotes, and moral apophthegms scattered throughout these letters.</p><p>SEVILLE, the largest, the richest, and most populous of the four kingdoms or provinces of Andalusia, in Spain. Its extent is 752 square miles, and its population amounts to 970,087 souls. It is bounded on the east by Granada and Cordova, on the north by Estremadura, on the west by Portugal, and on the south by the Mediterranean Sea.</p><p>The principal river of this province is the Guadalquivir, which, rising in the southern part of New Castille, passes through the whole of the province. This river is navigable for small ships up to the centre of the capital, and much higher for boats and small craft. Below Seville the Guadalquivir is divided into three branches, forming large islands between them, after passing which it unites and enters the ocean at St Lucar.</p><p>A great portion of this province is very mountainous. Next to the mountains of Ronda, the loftiest and most picturesque are the Trocha, to the westward of Algesiras, and those on which the city of Medina is situated, and a part of the Sierra Morena. Although these mountains are for the most part uninhabited and uncultivated, yet they afford excellent pasture for sheep during the winter season, when all is bare in the north of Spain. In the valleys is found the most extensive plains of the richest alluvial land, which, though frequently so burnt up by the heat of the summer sun as to display no traces of vegetation, yet, after two or three days of autumnal rain, produce the very richest pasture. As no hay is made in any part of Andalusia, the greatest distress is experienced by the farmers in keeping their cattle through the summer months, and at that period they feed mostly on broken straw, and become very lean ; but after the autumnal rains the verdure is abundant, and the cattle become fat. Though the province of Seville does not grow com sufficient for its own consumption, yet considerable quantities of wheat and barley are produced. The former grain is generally sown after a fallow, which may be made by about three ploughings in the summer months. Where they have manure, as is the case near the large towns, the increase is very great ; and where they have not, the fallow alone will produce a very fair crop. The rotation of crops is little attended to. Clover and turnips are not cultivated. The harvest generally takes place in the latter end of June or beginning of July, when the weather is invariably fine. As soon as the wheat is cut, it is thrashed in the field where it is grown. This is done by piling the sheaves on a floor of round pebbles in the open air ; and a number of unbroken mares, with a long rein held by a driver, are galloped in a circle over the sheaves. By this operation, from the dry state of the com, it is easily</p></body></text></TEI>