<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:22:57Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>have also multiplied prodigiously in St Lucia and Martinique, where from sixty to eighty may be killed during the cutting of a single field of sugar-cane. According to M. Moreau de Jonnès, they people the marshes, the cultivated grounds, the forests, the banks of rivers, and even the summits of the mountains. The observer just named encountered one on the very edge of the crater of that naked mountain which overhangs the town of St Pierre, in Martinique, at an elevation of more than 5000 feet ; and he feared it the more from the excessive lassitude under which he himself at that time laboured. His alarm was not without cause, for only a few days before, a fisherman at the foot of the mountain had been attacked by a similar reptile, which issued from its concealment among the basalts of the shore, and no efforts could save his life. These dreaded serpents arc sometimes found in holes made by rats or land- crabs. They also enter hen-r∞sts and poultry-yards, and sometimes creep into dwelling-houses, chiefly, however, the huts of the negroes. But the sugar-plantations are their favourite places of resort. “Je n’ai jamais trouvé,” says our author, “ de serpent stationnaire, qu’il ne fût dans une <hi rend="italic">position offensive.</hi> L’action par laquelle le reptile prend cette position, s’exprimer aux Antilles par le verbe <hi rend="italic">lover. </hi>Elle consiste à contourner en spirale toute la longueur de son corps, qui forme quatre cercles egaux en diamètre, superposés les uns au dessus des autres, et sous le dernier duquels la queue est placée comme point central d’appui, de resort et de pivot. La tête, qui termine le cercle superior, est retirée en arrière. Quand l’animal s’élance sur une proie, il fait effort sur la queue, et déroule subitement les quatre cercles qui semblent se débander.” This species preys on birds as well as quadrupeds, and the former manifest their hatred by vain and clamorous cries whenever they behold their “ arch destroyer.” It avoids the brilliant equatorial light, and usually dwells in shaded places, seeking what it may devour chiefly towards sunset, or during cloudy weather.@@<hi rend="superscript">1</hi> The distribution of this species is rather remarkable. It does not extend throughout the whole of the Antilles, nor is it found even in the majority of those islands. “ By a chance equally singular, fortunate, and inexplicable, it is confined to the islands of Martinique, St Lucia, and Be- conia alone ; and there is no proof, as has been pretended, that it is common in the American continent. Nevertheless, a tradition exists among the Indigenes, that it was introduced into Martinique by the Arronages, a horde which inhabited near the mouth of the Orinoco, and which, impelled by sentiments of hatred and vengeance against the Carribs of that island, made them this fatal present, and let loose in their forests this serpent, which was brought over in calabashes. But according to another popular opinion in the</p><p>same country, the Trigonocephalus is aboriginal of Martinique, and cannot live elsewhere, not even in Guadaloupe.</p><p>Some, however, think differently, and explain the phenomenon by the existence of the dog-headed serpent, which is believed to be a Boa, and which, common in Dominica and St Vincent, has delivered these islands from the Trigonocephalus.”@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></p><p>Of the second section of this genus, comprising such ns have the head covered by plates instead of scales, we may here name <hi rend="italic">Trig, rhodοstoma,</hi> which is of a thicker and more vigorous form than the other species. The body tapers towards either end, the tail is short and acuminated, the abdomen broad, and the back prolonged into a well- marked keel. The colour is reddish brown, paler on the back, the sides adorned by broad, deep, triangular spots, the abdomen white. The summit of the head is black, surrounded by a broad streak of pale red, which descends the sides of the neck to combine with the beautiful rose- colour which tinges the lateral parts of the head, and from which it is separated by a black band proceeding from behind the eye. The iris is of a golden yellow. “ L’expression sauvage de sa physiognomie,” says M. Schlegel, “ est, pour ainsi dire, adoucie par la nature et la conformation des plaques écailleuses qui semblables à celles de la plupart des couleuvres, ont la surface unie et luisante.”@@<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> This species inhabits the western parts of Java, where it conceals itself in tangled vegetation, and makes its way at times into fields and gardens. It preys chiefly on frogs, and is itself attacked by a species of civet cat which occurs in Java. It is greatly dreaded by the natives on account of its deadly poison ; and during M. Khul’s residence at Buitenzorg, two labourers bitten by it died in five minutes. Although a viviparous reptile, the foetus is enclosed in a coriaceous envelope, as large as a pigeon’s egg. The species is figured by Russel.@@<hi rend="superscript">4</hi></p><p>The only other example of the genus we need here notice is <hi rend="italic">Trig, cenchris,</hi> which inhabits the southern provinces of the United States. Its occipital plates are of small dimensions, and are sometimes even wanting. The ground colour is grayish brown, marked by broad transverse bands of a more coppery hue. The abdomen is yellowish, marked by dark irregular spots. The point of the tail is usually black, and all the parts are minutely speckled by that colour. It is a sluggish, slow-moving reptile, very poisonous, but not given to bite, except in self-defence, when it maintains its position courageously. It has been described by different authors under a great variety of names, and by some under more than one at a time.@@<hi rend="superscript">5</hi> It is the <hi rend="italic">Mokassin </hi>snake of the Anglo-Americans, thus called on account of the resemblance of its colour to the piece of dress so named by the native tribes. It is figured by M. Daudin.@@<hi rend="superscript">6</hi></p><p>Genus <hi rend="smallcaps">Crotalus.</hi> This dreaded genus contains the rattle-snakes, and is distinguished from the preceding by a more robust form, a thicker head, and a tail either armed</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@1</hi><hi rend="italic"> Μonοgraphie,</hi> p. 37.	</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@1</hi> Griffith’s <hi rend="italic">Animal Kingdom,</hi> is. 350.</p><p><hi rend="italic superscript">@@@,</hi><hi rend="italic"> Phys, des Serpens,</hi> ii. 547.</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@* Indian Serpents,</hi> ii. pl. 21.</p><p><hi rend="superscript">@@@s</hi> It is both the brown and the <hi rend="italic">black viper</hi> of Catesby’s <hi rend="italic">Carolina,</hi> pl. 44 and 45 ; it is once figured, and at least twice described, by</p><p>Dr Shaw, as <hi rend="italic">Col. Cacodoemon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tisiphone, Gen. Zoo/.</hi> iii. pp. 377 and 406 ; it is the <hi rend="italic">Pelias Niger</hi> of Merrem, <hi rend="italic">Tentamen,</hi> p. 149 ; and had been previously described by Linnæus as a Boa (B. <hi rend="italic">Contortrix,</hi> xii. ed. p. 373). M. Schlegel, indeed, supposes that it is also the <hi rend="italic">Coluber Constrictor</hi> of the great Swedish naturalist. The Boa just named is believed to be identical with the <hi rend="italic">hog-nosed snake</hi> of Catesby <hi rend="italic">(Car.</hi> ii. pl. 66), and may be identical with the preceding nominal species, none of which seem to exceed the size of our common viper ; but <hi rend="italic">Col. Constrictor</hi> of America is usually described as of different habits and much larger dimensions. It is the black <hi rend="italic">snake </hi>of Catesby (Car. ii. pl. 48).	“ This,” observes that author, “ is a large and very long snake, some being six feet in length. They</p><p>are all over of a shining black, never changing their colour, and are very nimble amd beneficial in killing rats, which they pursue with wonderful agility to the roofs and all parts of houses and barns, where rats are able to run, for which service they are preserved by most of the inhabitants. They are bold and furious, leaping at and biting those that attack them, though no harm ensues, <hi rend="italic">their bile not being venomous.</hi> It is said in Carolina that they will attack and swallow rattle-snakes. It is certain most or all snakes will devour one another, not only of their own, but of other kinds, which I have often seen; one, after a long struggle, swallowing another but little leas than itself. They are the most numerous of all snakes." “ Many ridiculous frights,” says Mr Pennant, “ have happened from this <hi rend="italic">innocent</hi> reptile. As every one in America is full of the dread of the rattle-snake, they are apt to fly at the sight of any of the serpent kind. This pursues, soon overtakes, and twisting round the legs of the fugitive, soon brings him to the ground ; but he happily receives no hurt, but what may result from the fright. All the mischief this species does is to the housewives, for it will skim their milk-pans of the cream, and rob their hen-roosts of all the eggs.” <hi rend="italic">( Arctic Zoology,</hi> Appendix, p. 92.)</p><p><hi rend="italic">@@@* Reptiles,</hi> V. 338, pl. 70, figs. 3 and 4, and 60, fig. 25.</p></body></text></TEI>