<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:23:21Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>and the harshness of the doctrines which he wished to establish <hi rend="smallcaps">bo</hi> repulsive, that he had nearly resolved to put a period to his existence.</p><p>Of the school of Sextius were Fabianus, Sotion, Flavianus, Crassitius, and Celsus. Of his works only a few fragments remain ; and whether any of them formed a part of the work which Seneca admired so much, cannot now be determined. Some of his maxims are valuable. He recommended an examination of the actions of the day to his scholars when they retired to rest ; and he taught, that the road to heaven was by frugality, temperance, and fortitude. He used to recommend holding a looking-glass before persons disordered with passion. He enjoined his scholars to abstain from animal food.</p><p>SEXTON, a church-officer, thus called by corruption of the Latin, <hi rend="italic">sacrista,</hi> or Saxon, <hi rend="italic">segerstone,</hi> which denotes the same thing. His office is to take care of the vessels, vestments, and other things belonging to the church ; and to attend the minister, church-warden, and others at church. He is usually chosen by the parson only. Sextons, as well as parish-clerks, are regarded by the common law as persons who have a freehold in their offices ; and, therefore, though they may be punished, yet they cannot be deprived by ecclesiastical censures.</p><p>The office of sexton in the pope’s chapel is appropriated to the order of the hermits of St Augustin. He is generally a bishop, though sometimes the pope only gives a bishopric <hi rend="italic">in partibus</hi> to him on whom he confers the post. He takes the title of <hi rend="italic">Prefect of the Pope's Sacristy,</hi> and has the keeping of the vessels of gold and silver, the relics, and so forth. When the pope says mass, the sexton always tastes the bread and wine first. If it be in private he says mass, his holiness, of two wafers, gives him one to cat; and if in public, the cardinal, who assists the pope in quality of deacon, of three wafers, gives him one to eat. When the pope is desperately sick, he administers to him the sacrament of extreme unction, and enters the conclave in quality of first conclavist.</p><p>The office of sexton in Sweden is sometimes singular. During M. Outhier’s stay at Stockholm in 1736, he visited the church of St Clara, and during divine service he observed a sexton going about with a long rod, waking those persons who had fallen asleep.</p><p>SEXTUPLE, in <hi rend="italic">Music,</hi> denotes a mixed sort of triple, which is beaten in double time.</p><p>SEXTUS <hi rend="smallcaps">Empirus,</hi> a famous Pyrrhonian philosopher, who lived in the second century, under the reign of Antoninus. He was a physician of the sect of the Empirics, and is said to have been one of the preceptors of Antoninus the Philosopher. There are still extant his Pyrrhonian Institutions, and a large work against the mathematicians. The best edition of Sextus Empiricus is that of Fabricius in Greek and Latin, printed at Leipsic in 1718, folio.</p><p>SEXUALISTÆ, among botanical writers, those who have established the classes of plants upon the differences of the sexes and parts of fructification in plants, according to the modern method.</p><p>SEYNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lλ,</hi> a city of France, in the department of the Var, and the arrondissement of Toulon. It is a port on a small bay or roadstead, about three miles from Toulon. It is well built, has good quays, and an establishment for building vessels. It contains 5230 inhabitants, many of whom are occupied in fishing for sardinias and tunnies.</p><p>SEYSUMAH, a town of the Mahratta territories, in Hindustan, province of Malwah, situated on the east side of the Chumbul. It is twenty miles south-west from Kotah. Long. 75. 37. E. Lat. 24. 55. N.</p><p>SEZAWUL, a Hindu word, used in Bengal to express an officer employed at a monthly salary to collect the revenue.</p><p>SHACK, in ancient customs, a liberty of winter-pasturage. In the counties of Norfolk and Suffolk, the lord of</p><p>the manor has shack, that is, a liberty of feeding his sheep at pleasure in his tenants’ lands during the six winter months. In Norfolk, shack also extends to the common for hogs, in all men's grounds, from the end of harvest till seed-time. Hence to go <hi rend="italic">a∙shack</hi> is to feed at large.</p><p>SHACKLES, aboard a ship, are those oblong iron rings, bigger at one end than at the other, with which the ports are shut fast, by thrusting the wooden bar of the port through them. There is also a sort of shackles to lift up the hatches with, of a like figure, but smaller. They are fastened at the corners of the hatches.</p><p>SHADOW, in <hi rend="italic">Optics,</hi> a privation or diminution of light, by the interposition of an opaque body ; or a plane where the light is either altogether obstructed, or greatly weakened, by the interposition of some opaque body between it and the luminary.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Shadow</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">Perspective.</hi> The appearance of an opaque body, and a luminous one whose rays diverge, being given ; to find the just appearance of the shadow, according to the laws of perspective. The method is this. From the luminous body, which is here considered as a point, let fall a perpendicular to the perspective plane or table, that is, find the appearance of a point upon which a perpendicular, drawn from the middle of the luminary', falls on the perspective plane ; and from the several angles, or raised points of the body, let fall perpendiculars to the plane. These points, on which the perpendiculars fall, connect by right lines with the point upon which the perpendicular let fall from the luminary falls, and continue the lines to the side opposite to the luminary. Lastly, through the raised points draw lines through the centre of the luminary, intersecting the former ; the points of intersection are the terms or bounds of the shadow.</p><p>SHADOWRAH, a town of Hindustan, in the Mahratta territories, province of Malwah, forty miles north by west from Seronge. Long. 77. 47. E. Lat. 24. 20. N.</p><p>SHADWEL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi>, descended of an ancient family in Staffordshire, was born in 1640, and educated at Caius College, Cambridge. He was then placed in the Middle Temple to study the laws ; and having spent some time there, he travelled abroad. Upon his return home, he became acquainted with the most celebrated persons of wit in that age. He applied himself chiefly to dramatic writing, in which he had great success, and upon the Revolution was made poet laureat and historiographer to King William and Queen Mary, in the room of Mr Dryden. These employments he enjoyed till his death, which happened in 1692. Besides his dramatic writings, he composed several other pieces of poetry, the chief of which are his congratulatory poem on the Prince of Orange’s coming to England, another on Queen Mary, and his translation of Juvenal's tenth satire. Mr Dryden treats him with great contempt, in his satire called <hi rend="italic">Macflecno.</hi> The best judges of that age, however, gave their testimony in favour of his comedies, which have in them fine strokes of humour ; the characters are often original, strongly marked, and well sustained. An edition of his works, with some account of his life and writings prefixed, was published in 1720, in four vols. 8vo.</p><p>SHADWELL, a large village of the county of Middlesex, in the hundred of Ossulston, touching on the city of London, but lower down on the same bank of the Thames, two miles and a half from St Paul’s church. It is within the bills of mortality, and is a parish of itself. The population consists chiefly of sea-faring people, and of such as are connected with the building and equipment of shipping. The parish church is a large and handsome building, dedicated to St Paul. The inhabitants amounted in 1821 to 9557, and in 1831 to 9544. Many of the smaller houses, more than two hundred, have been taken down to make space for the docks that have been built, which accounts for the decrease in the population.</p></body></text></TEI>