<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>unknown title</title>
                <author>unknown author</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition><date>unknown date</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>unknown</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
                    <label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change><date>2019-02-19T20:19:43Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>volving red and white lights revolving in equal periods. The utility of all these
                distinctions is chiefly to be imputed to their at once striking the eye of an
                observer and being instantaneously obvious to strangers.</p>
            <p>@@Before entering upon the subject of the dioptric lights, the writer of this article
                embraces with pleasure the opportunity afforded to him, of acknowledging the
                liberality of M. Léonor Fresnel, the present Secretary of the Lighthouse Commission
                of France. It was entirely owing to the readi ness with which M. Fresnel afforded
                him access to every avenue of information on the subject of lighthouses, that he was
                enabled to effect the object of a mission to France, on which he was sent in the
                year 1834, by the Commissioners of Northern Lights.</p>
            <p>The first proposal of applying lenses to lighthouses, is recorded by Smeaton in his
                account of the Eddystone Lighthouse, where he mentions that, in 1759, an optician in
                London proposed grinding the glass of the lantern to a radius of seven feet six
                inches ; but the description is too vague to admitof even a conjecture regarding the
                proposed arrangement of the apparatus. Above forty years ago, however, lenses were
                actually tried in several lighthouses in the south of England ; but their imperfect
                figure, and the quantity of light absorbed by the glass, which was of inferior
                quality and of considcrable thickness, rendered their effect so much inferior to
                that of the parabolic reflectors then in use, that, after trying some strange
                combinations of lenses and reflectors, the former were finally abandoned.</p>
            <p>The object to be attained by the use of lenses in a lighthouse, is, of course,
                identical with that which is answered by employing reflectors ; and both instruments
                effect the same end by different means, collecting the rays which diverge from a
                point called the <hi rend="italic">focus,</hi> and projecting them forward in a
                beam, whose axis coincides with the produced axis of the instrument. The actions by
                which these similar results are effected, have been termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >reflection</hi> and <hi rend="italic">refraction.</hi> In the one case, the
                light, as has been already said, merely impinges on the reflecting surface, and is
                thrown back ; whilst in the other, the rays pass through the refracting medium, and
                are bent or refracted from their natural course.</p>
            <p>The celebrated Buffon, to prevent the great absorption of light by the thickness of
                the material, which would necessarily result from giving to a lens of great
                dimensions a figure continuously spherical, proposed to grind out of a solid piece
                of glass, a lens in steps or concentric zones. This suggestion of Buffon regarding
                the construction of large burning glasses, was first executed, with tolerable
                success, about the year 1780, by the Abbé Rochon; but such are the difficulties
                attending the process of working a solid piece of glass into the necessary form,
                that it is believed the only other instrument ever constructed in this manner, is
                that which was made by Messrs. Cookson of Newcastle-upon- Tyne, for the
                Commissioners of Northern Lighthouses.</p>
            <p>The merit of having first suggested the building of these lenses in separate pieces,
                seems to be due to Condorcet, who in his <hi rend="italic">Eloge de Buffon,</hi>
                published so far back as 1773, enumerates the advantages to be derived from this
                    method.@@<hi rend="superscript">2 </hi>Sir David Brewster also described this
                mode of building lenses in 1811, in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh
                    Encyclopædia;</hi> and in 1822, the late eminent Fresnel, alike unacquainted
                with the suggestions of Condorcet, or the description by Sir David Brewster,
                explained with many ingenious and interesting details, the same mode of constructing
                these instruments.</p>
            <p>To Fresnel belongs the additional merit of having first followed up his invention, by
                the construction of a lens, and in conjunction with MM. Arago and Mathieu of placing
                a powerful lamp in its focus, and indeed of finally applying it to the practical
                purposes <hi rend="italic">of a</hi> lighthouse. The fertile genius of the French
                Academician has produced many ingenious combi nations of dioptric instruments for
                lighthouses, which we shall have occasion to notice in the sequel.</p>
            <p>The great advantages which attend the mode of construction proposed by Condorcet,
                are, the ease of execution, by which a more perfect figure may be given to each
                zone, and spherical aberration almost entirely corrected, and the power of forming a
                lens of larger dimensions than could easily be made from a solid piece. Both Buffon
                and Condorcet, however, chiefly speak of reducing the thickness of the material, and
                do not seem to have thought of determining the radius and centre of the curvature of
                the generating arcs of each zone, having contented themselves with simply depressing
                the spherical surface in separate portions. Fresnel, on the other hand, determined
                these centres, which constantly recede from the axis of the lens in proportion as
                the zones to which they refer are removed from its centre ; and the surfaces of the
                zones of the annular lens, consequently, are not parts of concentric spheres, as in
                Buffon’s lens. It deserves notice, that the first lenses constructed for Fresnel by
                M. Soleil had their zones polygonal, so that the surfaces were not annular, a form
                which Fresnel considered less accommodated to the ordinary resources of the
                optician. He also, with his habitual penetration, preferred the plano-convex to the
                double-convex form, as more easily executed. After mature consideration, he finally
                adopted crown glass, which, notwithstanding its greenish colour, he considered more
                suitable than flint glass, as being less liable to <hi rend="italic">strife.</hi>
                All his calculations were made in reference to an index of refraction of l∙5l, which
                he had verified by repeated experiments, conducted with that patience and accuracy
                for which, amidst his higher qualities, he was so remarkably distinguished. These
                instruments have received the name <hi rend="italic">of annular</hi> lenses, from
                the figure of the surface of the zones.</p>
            <p>Fig. 6, Plate II, exhibits a plan and section of an annular lens of the largest size,
                whose focal distance is 92 centimètres, or about 36∙22 inches, and which subtends a
                luminous pyramid of 46° of inclination, having its apex in the flame.</p>
            <p>Having once contemplated the possibility of illuminating lighthouses by dioptric
                means, Fresnel quickly perceived the advantage of employing for fixed lights a lamp
                placed in the centre of a polygonal hoop, consisting of a series of cylindric
                refractors, <hi rend="italic">infinitely small</hi> in their length, and having
                their axes in planes parallel to the horizon.</p>
            <p>Such a continuation of vertical cylindric sections of various curvatures, by
                refracting the rays proceeding from the focus only in a direction perpendicular to
                the vertical sections of the cylindric parts, must distribute a zone of light <hi
                    rend="italic">equally brilliant</hi> in every point of the horizon. This effect
                will be easily understood, by considering the middle vertical section of one of the
                great annular lenses or burning glasses, already described, abstractly from its
                relation to the rest of the instrument. It will readily be perceived that this
                section possesses the property of simply refracting the rays at right angles to the
                line of the section, or in a direction parallel to the horizon, and cannot collect
                the rays from either side of the vertical line ; and if this section, by its
                revolution about a vertical axis, becomes the generating line</p>
            <p>@@@[mu] <note anchored="true" place="margin" type="authorial">In all probability
                        directly derived from the Greek <hi rend="italic">διόπτρα,</hi> an optical
                        instrument with holes for looking through, which is a compound of διὰ, <hi
                            rend="italic">through,</hi> and ὄ<hi rend="italic">πτoμαι, l
                        see.</hi></note>Dioptic system of Fresnel.</p>
            <p>@@@<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> On pourrait même composer de plusieurs pièces ces
                loups à échelons ; on y gagnerait plus de facilité dans la construction, une grande
                diminution de dépense, l'avantage de pouvoir leur donner plus d'étendue, et celui
                d'employer suivant le besoin un nombre des cercles plus ou moins grand, et d'obtenir
                ainsi du même instrument differens dégrès de force· <hi rend="italic">Eloge de
                    Βuffon,</hi> p. 35. <hi rend="italic">Œuvres de Condorcet,</hi> tom. iv. Pana,
                1804</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
