<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>unknown title</title><author>unknown author</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>unknown date</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document with eb-docx2tei.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>Knowledge Project: DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2019-02-19T20:24:34Z</date><name>unknown author</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>belonged to the “ commons,” in the quaint rhymes of an anonymous author of the year 1433, which have been pre- served by Hackluyt, termed “ The Prologue of the processe of the Libel of English policie, exhorting all England to keepe the sea, and namely, the narrowe sea, shewing what profite commeth thereof, and also what worship and saluation to England, and to all Englishmen.”</p><p>And if I should conclude all by the king Henrie the Fift, what was his purposing,</p><p>Whan at Hampton be made the great dromons.</p><p>Which passed other great ships of all the commons ;</p><p>The Trinitie, the Grace de Dieu, the Holy Ghost,</p><p>And other moe, which as nowe bee lost.</p><p>What hope ye was the king’s great intent Of thoo shippet, and what in minde hee meant :</p><p>It was not ellis ; but that hee cast to be Lorde round about environ of the sea.</p><p>The term dromond is the corruption of a Levantine terra, dromones, imported probably by the crusaders. The dromones were long row-galleys, but the adopted term dromond was applied generally to all large ships.</p><p>There is a list of Henry’s vessels in the fourth year of his reign, preserved in the proceedings of the privy council. His navy then consisted of three “ large ships” or “ grands niefs,” three “ carracks,” eight barges, and ten balingers. In 1417 it was augmented to three “ large ships,” eight “ car- racks,” six other ships, one barge, and nine balingers.</p><p>Again, in a letter preserved among the Cottonian manuscripts, and printed in Ellis’s collection, we find that the Spaniards offered Henry V. two carracks for sale, one of which is described as of a tonnage equal to 1400, and the other to 1000 butts. So energetical was Henry V. in all things relating to his navy, and the consequent increase in the number of the royal ships during his reign was so great, as to have led to the error that before his time the sovereigns of England were not possessed of vessels, but relied wholly upon the aid to be gathered from the different ports of England, or to be hired from foreigners. This is evidently incorrect.</p><p>On the death of Henry V. a different line of policy appears to have been adopted; for in May 1423 the king’s ships were all sold at Southampton, under a restriction that no foreigner could be a purchaser of them. But it appears that a long period did not elapse before the depressed state of the naval resources of the kingdom, consequent on this injudicious measure, attracted the attention of parliament. The following interesting quotation from the preface of the fifth volume of the Proceedings of the Privy Council, printed by the Record Commission, refers to this event. “ In 1443 the attention of parliament was directed to this important part of the national defence (the naval force), and a highly curious ordinance was made for t he safeguard of the sea. From February to November eight ships with forestages, or, as they were sometimes called then, as now, forecastles, armed with 150 men each, were to be constantly at sea. Every large ship was to be attended by a barge of eighty men, and a balinger of forty men. There were also to be 'awaiting and attendant upon them’ four  spynes’ or ‘ spi- naces,' with twenty-five men each. The whole number of men in these twenty-four ships was 2240.”</p><p>There is also in the same preface an account of the various kinds of ships which formed the navies of this period, a part of which we shall quote, and by the addition of some further information of the same nature, derived from Froissart, Monstrelet, and other sources, the reader will be enabled to form a tolerably correct opinion as to the state of naval architecture in England previous to and during the fifteenth century. Plate CCCCXLVI.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Ships.</hi> “ The burthen of the largest ships at that period probably did not exceed 600 tons, though some of them were certainly very large” as, for instance, the vessel built at Bayonne for Henry V., already mentioned. “ One</p><p>which belonged to Hull was released from arrest" (she having been pressed into the king’s service), “ because she drew so much water that she could not approach within two miles of the coast of Guienne, where the Duke of Somerset’s army intended to disembark ;” and several notices occur of ships of 300 and 400 tons and upwards. Some had three and others only two masts, with short topmasts, and a “ forestage” or “ forecastle,” consisting of a raised platform or stage, which obtained the name of castle from its containing soldiers, and probably from its having bulwarks. In this part of the ship it appears business was transacted ; and in the reign of Edward III., if not afterwards, ships had sometimes one of these stages at each end, as ships “ <hi rend="italic">oue chastiel devant et derere"</hi> are then spoken of. (Plate CCCCXLVI. figs. 2, 3, 4, 5.) Lydgate, describing the fleet with which King Henry V. went to France after the battle of Agincourt, says,</p><p>Fifteen hundred ships ready there be found,</p><p>With rich sails and high topcastle.</p><p>This is a confusion of terms. The “ topcastles” were not the forecastles, but were castellated enclosures at the mast- hcads, in which the pages to the officers were stationed during an engagement, in order to annoy the enemy with darts and other missiles ; as is frequently mentioned in Froissart, and is represented in the illuminations to his work. Plate CCCCXLV. fig. 3.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Carracks</hi> “ were vessels of considerable burthen, and were next in size to great ships, in which class they indeed were sometimes included. Their tonnage may be estimated by their being in some instances capable of carrying 1400 butts ; and the sail of one afforded Chaucer a strange simile expressive of magnitude,</p><p>And now hath Sathanas, saith he, a tayl Broder than of a carrike is the sayl.</p><p>Though occasionally armed and employed against the enemy, they were more generally used in foreign trade.”</p><p>Charnock says that the first carrack which was built in England was built for a merchant, John Tavenier, of Hull, who was consequently honoured by Henry VI. with distinguished favour ; and she was licensed in 1449 with particular privileges to trade through the Straits of Morocco. The king also ordered her to be called the Grace Dieu Carrack. The license states her to have been built “ by the help of God and some of the king's subjects.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Barges</hi> “ were a smaller kind of vessel and of a different construction from ships, though, like them, they sometimes had forecastles. Those appointed to protect the seas in 1415 were of 100 tons burthen, and contained forty mariners, ten men-at-arms, and ten archers ; whilst the ships employed on the same occasion were of 120 tons, and had forty-eight mariners, twenty-six men at arms, and twenty- six archers each. Four large barges and two balingcrs were capable of holding 120 men-at-arms and 480 archers and sailors.”</p><p><hi rend="italic">Balingers “</hi> were still smaller than barges, had no forecastle, and sometimes contained about forty sailors, ten men- at-arms, and ten archers.” Froissart makes frequent mention of “ balniers,” “ balleniers,” which he describes “ as drawing little water, and being sent in advance to seek adventures, in the same manner as knights and squires, mounted on the fleetest horses, are ordered to scour in front of an enemy, to see if there be any ambuscades.” Monstrelet speaks of one vessel that was employed by Louis XI. to abduct the Count de Charolais, by the two names ballenier and balayer. It is not improbable that the name is derived from the French word <hi rend="italic">baleine,</hi> and that its origin was similar to that of our English name whaler. The whale- fishery in Biscay was of a very early date.</p><p><hi rend="italic">Galleys</hi> (Plate CCCCXLVI. fig. 1) “ are frequently mentioned at a very early period ; and in the 5th Rich. II. 1381, the Commons complained that no measures had been</p></body></text></TEI>